<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370741">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001492448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Mindfulness app for brain tumors </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of a novel application of a mindfulness phone app for those with brain tumors: a feasibility study </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1182-8783</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>RO# 16079</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Brain tumors (including benign and malignant tumors, primary or secondary)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Brain</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this study is to determine the feasibility of a mindfulness treatment delivered by a commercial App-based mindfulness training or AMT (Headspace 'Registered Trademark') in patients with primary or secondary brain tumours. This project aims to deliver an 8-week mindfulness treatment  to ten participants diagnosed with brain tumours in Christchurch Hospital, Canterbury District Health Board. 
Participants will be recruited in the neurosurgical ward and/or clinic. If considered eligible by their treating clinician, they will be told about the study. If interested, they will be approached and given information about the study (including the study brochure) before surgery. Prior to (or subsequent to) discharge after an uncomplicated surgery, patients who are interested in participating will meet with either J Jordan or C De Tommasi to go through the information sheet and provide informed consent. They will complete a self-report questionnaire booklet assessing demographic, anxiety and mood symptoms, quality of life and mindfulness questionnaires. The measures include the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS),  Five Facet Mindfulness Questionnaire, general quality of life (QoL, SF-12)  and disease specific quality of life (FACT-BR).
Clinical information regarding tumour management will also be collected: tumour histology, surgical treatment, adjuvant therapy, medications etc. Participant confidentiality will be preserved by allocation of a unique research identifier. 
Participants will then receive a preliminary 10 minute guided mindfulness practice session via the AMT Headspace 'Registered Trademark', and will receive an email with a unique activation code for a free full subscription for 1 year to Headspace 'Registered Trademark'. This is an easily accessible self-guided meditation application that allows patients to customize their experience. We will not impose specific criteria with regard to app use and utilization but will recommend a minimum of 10 minutes daily practice for at least 8 weeks.
Participants will be informed on the information sheet that we will be obtaining data about frequency and duration of practice from the app provider about their use of the app during the project. 
We will re-assess patients at end treatment (week 8) and at 1-month follow-up (12 weeks), repeating key measures (HADS, FFMQ and QoL measures). A treatment satisfaction and feedback questionnaire will also be completed at end treatment.
To assist with retention the following strategies will be employed: 1) fortnightly check-in text or email to keep participants engaged and address questions and 2) the study incentive (i.e., free one year subscription to Headspace 'Registered Trademark' app).
Enrolment will be continuous until a proposed sample of 10 participants is obtained. 
There will be no cost to participants to take part in this study.
The researchers include registered health professionals (CDT and JJ) and have processes for dealing with any clinical matters arising during the treatment.
This research is investigator-devised and led. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>This is an open label feasibility study with no comparator treatment</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This research will establish the feasibility of recruiting 10 patients, delivering to this group, and provide valuable information about the practicalities of recruitment, patients compliance, and whether any adaptations are necessary</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be recruited over 1 year period ( from 1/12/2016 to 31/12/2017)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' adherence to the number of recommended practice sessions per week will be monitored; We will not impose specific criteria with regard to app use and utilization but will recommend a minimum of 10 minutes daily practice for at least 8 weeks.
Participants will be informed on the information sheet that we will be obtaining data about frequency and duration of practice from the app provider about their use of the app during the project. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0,8 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital anxiety and depression scale; % of change across all time points</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0, 8 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Short Form 12 (Quality of life) - % change across all time points</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 8 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy- Brain (Quality of life) - % change across all time points</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 8 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Five Facet Mindfulness Questionnaire - % change across all time points</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 8 and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient-rated treatment credibility. The 4 item treatment credibility scale (based on Borkevic and Nau 1972) asks participants to rate the treatment on a 7 point Likert scale (from 1 Not at all -  7 Very) for how logical, how useful, confidence that it will be successful and how confidently they would recommend it to a friend. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction scale.The Patient Satisfaction Scale has 5 items rated on a 7 item Likert scale from (1 Not at all  to 7 Very much): How valuable was the content of the app, how valuable was the relationship with the researchers, extent of improvement in anxiety/depression, extent of improvement in general functioning, extent to which the treatment contributed to the improvement.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progress rating scale- change from baseline, across time points. The 5 item participant Progress Rating Scale was designed specifically for this study. The 5 point likert scale from 1Not at all to 5 Very much is used to rate how appropriate the content was, extent of improvement in depression/ anxiety symptoms, improvement in general functioning, extent of practice and rating of the sufficiency of that practice for them.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 2,4,6,8</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Males and females with a diagnosis of a brain tumour, able to read or understand the information sheet and consent form to provide informed consent, adequate e-Literacy at baseline and access to a computer or smart-phone.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Karnofsky performance scale (KPS) below 70 after surgery (i.e.inability to care for self and to work) multiple brain lesions, other body metastases,  unwilling to complete the questionnaires or use the mindfulness intervention. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed. This is an open label feasibility study. Partecipants will not be referred, and all eligible for the trial will be invited to participate after providing informed consent.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Claudio De Tommasi</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Neurosurgery Department, Christchurch Hospital, 2 Riccarton avenue, 4710,Christchurch </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Headspace'Registered Trademark'</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit B-C, Papermill Building, City Garden Row, London, N18DW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Jennifer Jordan</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Psychological Medicine, University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345, 4 Oxford Terrace, Christchurch 8140
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Assoc Prof Marco Reale</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Mathematics and Statistics, College of Engineering
University of Canterbury, 8041, Ilam, Christchurch
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to determine the feasibility of a mindfulness treatment delivered by a commercial App-based Mindfulness Training or AMT (Headspace 'Registered Trademark') (https://www.headspace.com), provided free of charge for the pilot study by Headspace) in patients with primary or secondary brain tumours. This project aims to deliver an 8-week mindfulness treatment through Headspace 'Registered Trademark' to ten participants diagnosed with brain tumours, recruited through the Neurosurgery Department of Christchurch Hospital, Canterbury District Health Board. This research will establish the feasibility of delivering to this group, and provide valuable information about the practicalities of recruitment, patients compliance, and whether any adaptations are necessary. Secondary outcomes are to assess changes in self-reported psychological distress, quality of life and mindfulness capacity. This feasibility study will provide valuable information to inform planning for future research trials</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern B Health and Disability Ethics Commettees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/NTB/183</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Claudio De Tommasi</name>
      <address>Neurosurgery department, Christchurch Hospital, 2 Riccarton avenue, 4710, Christchurch</address>
      <phone>+64 03 3641217</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>claudio.detommasi@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Claudio De Tommasi</name>
      <address>Neurosurgery department, Christchurch Hospital, 2 Riccarton avenue, 4710, Christchurch</address>
      <phone>+64 03 3641217</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>claudio.detommasi@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Claudio De Tommasi</name>
      <address>Neurosurgery department, Christchurch Hospital, 2 Riccarton avenue, 4710, Christchurch</address>
      <phone>+64 03 3641217</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>claudio.detommasi@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Claudio De Tommasi</name>
      <address>Neurosurgery department, Christchurch Hospital, 2 Riccarton avenue, 4710, Christchurch</address>
      <phone>+64 03 3641217</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>claudio.detommasi@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>