<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369323">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001106527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Chemotherapy-induced alopecia (CIA) in breast cancer patients: effectiveness of two temperature levels of scalp cooling on reducing rates of CIA.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Incidence of chemotherapy-induced alopecia (CIA) in breast cancer patients": effectiveness of two temperature levels of scalp cooling on reducing incidence of CIA</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CIA-study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>BCRC113</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>chemotherapy-induced alopecia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>scalp-cooling treatment:patient wears a cap which is connected to a refrigerated cooling system which pumps liquid coolant through the cap to keep the scalp cool and blood vessels constricted to minimise chemotherapy delivery to hair follicles. The TGA-approved cap will be fitted to patients on day 1 of each chemotherapy cycle at one of two temperature settings (3 degrees vs 5 degrees Celsius) 30 min prior, during and 90min after their chemotherapy treatment for the duration of their planned chemotherapy. Scalp cooling start/stop time, chemotherapy start/stop time as well as duration of scalp cooling interruption, if applicable, will be recorded.</interventions>
    <comparator>Historical data (viz published adjuvant chemotherapy trials evaluating contemporary chemotherapy regimens from early 2000 to current)</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>incidence of patient reported minimal CIA (Dean's score 1/2 OR WHO grade 1/2) after completion of planned chemotherapy in this clinical setting compared to the population overall</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of chemotherapy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>comparison of rate of minimal CIA ( patient-reported on Dean's scale for Hair loss and WHO Scale for Hair Loss) at the 2 temperature settings as per protocol</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of chemotherapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of compliance with scalp cooling as determined in the protocol: patient's adherence to scalp cooling duration at each cycle, and patient's adherence to scalp cooling temperature setting. Temperature settings and scalp cooling times as well as chemotherapy treatment times will be collected.</outcome>
      <timepoint>per cycle and overall for planned number of chemotherapy cycles</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite outcome: frequency and severity of scalp-cooling adverse events. Known reported side-effects are feeling of cold, headache and light-headedness. At each treatment, the patient will be asked for any AEs/SAEs by study site staff who will document and report those AEs in the CRF and grade them according to CTCAE. </outcome>
      <timepoint>throughout study, at the start of each scalp cooling treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>incidence of scalp metastasis as reported by patients (phone contact) or from review of medical records (routine standard of care visit)</outcome>
      <timepoint>yearly for 10 years since start of chemotherapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- histologically confirmed invasive breast cancer 
- suitable to receive one of the approved chemotherapy regiments, defined in the protocol, in the neo/adjuvant or metastatic setting 
- minimum understanding of English language to complete quality of life questionnaire
- willingness to be followed for 10 years</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- history of malignant primary brain tumour
- history of scalp or brain metastasis
- recommended chemotherapy given on weekly schedule
- patient suffering from cold sensitivity, cold agglutinin disease, cryoglobulinemia, cryofibrogenemia or cold traumatic dystrophy
- prior chemotherapy for any reason
- allergy to silicon
- concurrent treatment affecting hair growth</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Within each treatment cohort, eligible patients will be randomised to one of two scalp cooling treatment arms on a 1:1 ratio.
Randomisation will be allocated by selected staff who do not have direct patient contact during the study. Allocation is concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)
Patients will be stratified according to treatment regimen recommended. There will be 3 treatment cohorts and within each cohort eligible patients will be randomised to one of two scalp cooling treatment arms on a 1:1 ratio.
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To detect a difference with 80% of power at a one-sided significant level of 0.025 (ower from 0.05 as Bonferroni correction applied to enable multiple groups comparisons), stratifying for treatment cohorts, a sample of 20 per cohort is required (assuming 20% dropout rate)</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/12/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>8/02/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>63</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>13/11/2025</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Breast Cancer Research Centre - Western Australia - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>6000 - Perth</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Breast Cancer Research Centre of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hollywood Private Hospital
Entrance 3, Lower ground level
101 Monash Avenue
Nedlands WA 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Breast Cancer Research Centre - WA</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hollywood Private Hospital
Entrance 3, Lower ground level
101 Monash Avenue
Nedlands WA 6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to gather more scientific data on the efficacy of scalp cooling to prevent chemotherapy-induced hair loss and to assess the effect of specific temperature used on the efficacy of scalp cooling. Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are 18 or over and have histologically confirmed invasive breast cancer, and a planned course of one of the approved chemotherapy regimens. Study details All participants enrolled in this trial will be randomly allocated (by chance) to receive scalp-cooling at 3 degrees Celsius or 5 degrees Celsius. Scalp-cooling involves wearing a cap connected to a cooling device that will lower the temperature of your scalp. The cap is to be worn at each chemotherapy treatment 30 minutes before, during and 90 minutes after the chemotherapy treatment. Patient outcomes will then be assessed through patient-reported level of hair loss at the end of planned chemotherapy and monitoring of short-term and long-term side effects of scalp-cooling for 10 years after the end of planned chemotherapy. It is hoped that the findings of this trial will enhance our knowledge of the efficacy and long-term safety of using scalp-cooling to prevent chemotherapy-induced alopecia in breast cancer patients. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Arlene Chan</name>
      <address>Breast Cancer Research Centre-WA
Hollywood Private Hospital
Entrance 3, Lower Ground Floor
101 Monash Avenue
Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 9481 4522</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>admin.profachan@me.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Jeannette Devoto</name>
      <address>Breast Cancer Research Centre-WA
Hollywood Private Hospital
Entrance 3, Lower Ground Floor
101 Monash Avenue
Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6500 5556</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>BCTU@bcrc-wa.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Jeannette Devoto</name>
      <address>Breast Cancer Research Centre-WA
Hollywood Private Hospital
Entrance 3, Lower Ground Floor
101 Monash Avenue
Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6500 5556</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>BCTU@bcrc-wa.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Jeannette Devoto</name>
      <address>Breast Cancer Research Centre-WA
Hollywood Private Hospital
Entrance 3, Lower Ground Floor
101 Monash Avenue
Nedlands WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6500 5556</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>