<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363701">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000185763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Facilitating Effective Communication and Coping among Women tested for BRCA1/2 Mutations and their Male Partners</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised trial among women undergoing genetic testing for breast/ovarian cancer and their male support partners to evaluate the impact of the 'Supporting Men, Supporting Women' web-based intervention, compared with participants assigned to the wait-list control group, and its impact on distress, perceived relational support, satisfaction with genetic-related information and knowledge about genetic testing.   </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Psychological distress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Unmet information needs</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Unmet emotional and relational needs </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Inability to provide relational support</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The 'Supporting Men, Supporting Women' web-based intervention aims  to increase mens understanding of the genetic testing process and to facilitate their personal coping, as well as their ability to communicate and provide support to woman at risk for developing breast and/or ovarian cancer. 

'Supporting Men, Supporting Women' is organised in a menu-driven modular format, with each module addressing an identified area of concern and need for male support partners. As well as providing a thorough explanation of the genetic testing process, it offers information about womens typical and preferred coping responses, and the implications of different testing results, including surveillance and preventive options. The intervention is unique in that it also provides information from the male perspective including: common responses of male partners to being a support person; ways for men to cope with these responses; guidance for how male partners can support the woman through testing process (including videos providing simple strategies for recognising and reducing stress); and, how couples can effectively communicate with each other and with other family members about genetic testing and its implications. 

In addition to usual care received throughout the genetic testing process (genetic testing of a blood sample as well as genetic counseling prior to, and following, test result disclosure), both male and female participants in the intervention group will receive full and immediate access to the Supporting Men, Supporting Women web-based intervention for the duration of the study (4 months).  Please note that there is no minimum or maximum amount of time participants are required to use this website.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive usual care from the recruiting Hereditary Cancer Clinics and will be wait-listed to receive access to the intervention after the 4-month study period.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Testing-specific distress, as measured by the Impact of Event Scale-Revised (IES-R)</outcome>
      <timepoint>All timepoints (baseline, and 1- and 4- months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generalized distress, as measured by the Depression, Anxiety, Stress Scales (DASS-21)</outcome>
      <timepoint>All timepoints (baseline, and 1- and 4- months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with the ability to provide support (for men) or satisfaction with support received (for women), each assessed with our previously published support scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>All timepoints (baseline, and 1- and 4- months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Unmet needs related to emotional and relational issues surrounding genetic testing, assessed with the Cancer Survivors Unmet Needs Measure (CaSUN; for women) and the Cancer Survivors Partners Unmet Needs Measure (CaSPUN; for men), each modified for use in the genetic testing context </outcome>
      <timepoint>All timepoints (baseline, and 1- and 4- months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>BRCA1/2-related genetics knowledge, as measured by an 8-item genetics knowledge measure used in our prior research  </outcome>
      <timepoint>All timepoints (baseline, and 1- and 4- months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with genetics-related information, as measured by a modified version of the Satisfaction with Information Scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>All timepoints (baseline, and 1- and 4- months post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligibility criteria for inclusion of women in the study will be (a) over 18 years of age; (b) a candidate for BRCA1/2 testing for breast/ovarian cancer susceptibility, (c) access to a computer connected to the internet; (d) ability to read and understand English; (e) informed consent and (f) nominated male support partner. 

Eligibility criteria for inclusion of men in the study will be (a) over 18 years of age; (b) supporting a woman through BRCA1/2 testing for breast cancer susceptibility (may be the womans husband or partner, brother, father, uncle or friend), (c) access to a computer connected to the internet; (d) ability to read and understand English and (e) informed consent. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women who do not have a male support partner or who are not undergoing genetic testing for breast/ovarian cancer risk. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/05/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>3/05/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>780</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>2</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Macquarie University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Balaclava Road, North Ryde, New South Wales, 2109</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Macquarie University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Balaclava Road, North Ryde, New South Wales, 2109</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will assess the efficacy of the 'Supporting Men, Supporting Women' website in providing information for men supporting women through genetic testing for breast/ovarian cancer. It aims to help men understand and cope with genetic testing, and communicate and support women throughout this process. We expect that individuals accessing this website will have low levels of distress, feel satisfied with the extent of support offered and received in their relationship, have high knowledge of genetic testing and feel satisfied with genetic information.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room G71 East Wing
Edmund Blacket Building 
Prince of Wales Hospital 
Randwick NSW 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/POWH/94</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kerry Sherman </name>
      <address>Centre for Emotional Health
Department of Psychology, C3A 705
Macquarie University NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 6874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kerry.sherman@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kerry Sherman </name>
      <address>Centre for Emotional Health
Department of Psychology, C3A 705
Macquarie University NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 6874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kerry.sherman@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kerry Sherman </name>
      <address>Centre for Emotional Health
Department of Psychology, C3A 705
Macquarie University NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 6874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kerry.sherman@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kerry Sherman </name>
      <address>Centre for Emotional Health
Department of Psychology, C3A 705
Macquarie University NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 6874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kerry.sherman@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>