<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368076">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000323527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase III Prospective Double Blind Placebo Controlled Randomized Study of Adjuvant MEDI4736 In Completely Resected Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase III Prospective Double Blind Placebo Controlled Randomized Study on the effect of Adjuvant MEDI4736 on Disease Free Survival In patients with Completely Resected Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>BR.31</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NCIC CTG Identifier: BR.31
</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT02273375</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Lung cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Non small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>MEDI4736 by intravenous infusion. MEDI4736 is supplied as a vialed liquid solution containing 500mg (nominal) MEDI4736. The solution contains 50mg/mL MEDI4736, 26mM histidine/histidine-HCl, 275mM trehalose dehydrate, 0.02% (w/v) polysorbate 80, at pH 6.0.
Treatment from Day 1 for a maximum of 12 months or study drug withdrawal if this occurs earlier.
Dosages are as follows:  20mg/kg every 4 weeks for 12 months. </interventions>
    <comparator>Matched Saline PLACEBO by intravenous infusion. Treatment from Day 1 for a maximum of 12 months or study drug withdrawal if this occurs earlier.
Infusions occur every 4 weeks for 12 months.
</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare Disease free survival (DFS) for patients with NSCLC that is PD-L1 positive using the RECIST criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time Frame: 5.5 years </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare Disease Free Survival in all randomized patients using the RECIST criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time Frame: 7 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare overall survival (OS) for patients with NSCLC that is PD-L1 positive using a p-value and a Lan-DeMets error spending function with O'Brian-Fleming type boundaries.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time Frame: 5.5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare overall survival for all randomized patients using a p-value</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time Frame: 7 years </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare Lung cancer specific survival for patients with NSCLC that is PD-L1 positive and all randomized patients using a p-value</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time Frame: 7 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the nature, severity and frequency of adverse effects and tolerability of MEDI4736 using NCI CTC AE Version 4.0</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time Frame: every 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the Quality of life between the two treatment arms
The quality of life (QoL) of patients will be assessed using EORTC QLQ-C30 and the lung cancer module (QLQ-LC13) questionnaires</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time Frame: 5.5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine survival benefits participants judge necessary to make adjuvant immunotherapy worthwhile using the Preferences for Adjuvant Immunotherapy Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time Frame: 5.5 years </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the incremental cost effectiveness and cost utility ratios for MEDI4736 by analysis of the EQ-5D questionnaire and determine through the US Valuation of the EuroQoL EQ-5D Health States. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Time Frame: 5.5 years </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the predictive/prognostic significance of PD-L1 expression by tissue sampling</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time Frame: 5.5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluation of changes in plasma/serum cytokines and other blood and tissue based biomarkers after treatment with MEDI4736 and at disease event </outcome>
      <timepoint>Time Frame: 5.5 years </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Explore polymorphisms that may be associated with outcomes by analysis of blood samples. Polymorphisms known or suspected to be associated with the outcomes of completely resected NSCLC, platinum based ACT as well as immune pathways and response to immunotherapies will be analysed in the lab using these blood samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time Frame: Baseline only </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Histologically confirmed diagnosis of primary non-small cell carcinoma of the lung

*Patients must be classified post-operatively as Stage IB (greater than or equal to 4cm in the longest diameter), II or IIIA on the basis of pathologic criteria
 -Complete surgical resection of the primary NSCLC is also mandatory. All gross disease must have been removed at the end of surgery. All surgical margins of resection must be negative for tumour. Resection may be accomplished by open or VATS techniques


Prior Systemic Therapy:
*Pre-operative (neo-adjuvant) platinum based or other chemotherapy is not permissible.

*Patients may have received prior post-operative platinum based chemotherapy as per standard of care.

*No prior anticancer therapy for treatment of NSCLC other than standard post-operative adjuvant chemotherapy is permissible.

Radiation:

*Pre-operative or post-operative or planned radiation therapy is not permissible.

*The patient must have an ECOG performance status of 0, 1.

*Hematology: . Absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1.5 x 109/L or greater than or equal to 1,500/microlitres Platelets greater than or equal to 100 x 109/L or greater than or equal to 100,000/microlitres

*Biochemistry:

Total bilirubin* within normal institutional limits 
Alkaline phosphatase less than or equal to 2.5 x institutional upper limit of normal 
AST(SGOT) and ALT(SGPT) less than or equal to 2.5 x institutional upper limit of normal 
Creatinine Clearance greater than or equal to 50 ml/min

* excluding Gilbert's syndrome

Creatinine clearance to be measured directly by 24 hour urine sampling or as calculated by Cockcroft Formula:

Females: GFR = 1.04 x (140-age) x weight in kg serum creatinine in micromol/L Males: GFR = 1.23 x (140-age) x weight in kg serum creatinine in micromol/L

*Patient able and willing to complete the QoL, economics and other questionnaires. The baseline assessment must already have been completed within required timelines prior to randomization. Inability (illiteracy, loss of sight, or other equivalent reason) to complete the questionnaires will not make the patient ineligible for the study. However, ability but unwillingness to complete the questionnaires will make the patient ineligible

*Patient consent must be appropriately obtained in accordance with applicable local and regulatory requirements. Each patient must sign a consent form prior to enrolment in the trial to document their willingness to participate

*Patients must be accessible for treatment and follow-up. Investigators must assure themselves the patients randomized on this trial will be available for complete documentation of the treatment, adverse events, and follow-up

*Protocol treatment is to begin within 2 working days of patient randomization
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Patients with a history of other malignancies, except: adequately treated non-melanoma skin cancer, curatively treated in-situ cancer, or other solid tumours curatively treated with no evidence of disease for great than or equal to 5 years following the end of treatment and which, in the opinion of the treating physician, do not have a substantial risk of recurrence of the prior malignancy.

*A combination of small cell and non-small cell lung cancer or pulmonary carcinoid tumour.

*History of autoimmune disease, including but not limited to myasthenia gravis, myositis, autoimmune hepatitis, systemic lupus erythematosus, rheumatoid arthritis, inflammatory bowel disease, vascular thrombosis associated with antiphospholipid syndrome, Wegener's granulomatosis, Sjögren's syndrome, Guillain-Barré syndrome, multiple sclerosis, vasculitis, or glomerulonephritis.

*History of primary immunodeficiency, history of organ transplant that requires therapeutic immunosuppression and the use of immunosuppressive agents within 28 days of randomization* or a prior history of severe (grade 3 or 4) immune mediated toxicity from other immune therapy.

*Live attenuated vaccination administered within 30 days prior to randomization.

*History of hypersensitivity to MEDI4736 or any excipient.

*Mean QTc correction &gt; 470msec in screening ECG measured using standard institutional method or history of familial long QT syndrome.

*Patients who have experienced untreated and/or uncontrolled cardiovascular conditions and/or have symptomatic cardiac dysfunction (unstable angina, congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction within the previous year or cardiac ventricular arrhythmias requiring medication, history of 2nd or 3rd degree atrioventricular conduction defects). Patients with a significant cardiac history, even if controlled, should have a LVEF &gt; 50%.

*Concurrent treatment with other investigational drugs or anti-cancer therapy.

*Patients with active or uncontrolled infections or with serious illnesses or medical conditions which would not permit the patient to be managed according to the protocol. This includes but is not limited to:
- known prior history of tuberculosis;
- known acute hepatitis B or C by serological evaluation;
- known Human immunodeficiency virus infection.

*Pregnant or lactating women. Women of childbearing potential must have a urine pregnancy test proven negative within 14 days prior to randomization. Men and women of child-bearing potential must agree to use adequate contraception.
 </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <hospital>Coffs Harbour Base Hospital - Coffs Harbour</hospital>
    <hospital>Nambour General Hospital - Nambour</hospital>
    <hospital>Epworth Richmond - Richmond</hospital>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <hospital>Campbelltown Hospital - Campbelltown</hospital>
    <hospital>The Chris O’Brien Lifehouse - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Peninsula Oncology Centre - Frankston</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincents &amp; Mercy Private Hospital - Mercy campus - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Gosford Hospital - Gosford</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Moorabbin campus - East Bentleigh</hospital>
    <hospital>Northern Cancer Institute - Frenchs Forest - Frenchs Forest</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Adult Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Border Medical Oncology - Wodonga</hospital>
    <postcode>3690 - Wodonga</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic Of</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
119-143 Missenden Road, Camperdown, NSW 2050
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Canadian Cancer Trials Group</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Cancer Clinical Trials Division
Cancer Research Institute
Queen's University
10 Stuart St
Kingston ON Canada K7L 3N6

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Canada</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Canadian Cancer Trials Group</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Cancer Clinical Trials Division
Cancer Research Institute
Queen's University
10 Stuart St
Kingston ON Canada K7L 3N6</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Canada</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Australasian Lung Cancer Trials Group</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Australasian Lung Cancer Trials Group 
Lung Foundation Australia
Level 2, 11 Finchley Street
Milton, QLD 4064


</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>BR.31 a clinical research study that is testing MEDI4736, a new type of drug for the treatment of non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) that was completely removed with surgery. It is being led by the Australasian Lung Cancer Trials Group (ALTG) and coordinated by the National Health and Medical Research Council Clinical Trials Centre (NHMRC CTC). The purpose of this study is to find out whether it is better to receive the new drug, MEDI4736, or no further treatment after surgery (and possibly chemotherapy) for lung cancer.
The study involves randomly allocating participants to receive treatment with either MEDI4736 or placebo, a substance that has no active medicine in it. Two-thirds (2/3) of the participants in this study will receive MEDI4736 and the other third (1/3) will receive placebo.
Participants will be required to receive intravenous infusions of MEDI4736 or placebo at 20mg/kg every 4 weeks for 12 months. Participants will then be followed up for a maximum of 10 years to assess overall survival and disease free survival. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Prince Alfred Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Camperdown NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/RPAH/442</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/10/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Sue-Anne McLachlan</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Melbourne
41 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>BR.31@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>BR.31 Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre, University of Sydney
119-143 Missenden Road, Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>BR.31@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>BR.31 Clinical Lead</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre, University of Sydney
119-143 Missenden Road, Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>BR.31@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>BR.31 Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre, University of Sydney
119-143 Missenden Road, Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>BR.31@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>