<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308313">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000665235</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised Phase II Trial of Pre-operative cisplatin, 5 fluorouracil and docetaxel ± Radiotherapy based on poor early response to standard chemotherapy for resectable adenocarcinoma of the oesophagus and/or OG Junction.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Phase II Trial of Pre-operative cisplatin, 5 fluorouracil and docetaxel +/- Radiotherapy based on poor early response to standard chemotherapy for resectable adenocarcinoma of the oesophagus and/or Oesphago-gastric  Junction.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DOCTOR</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Adenocarcinoma of the Oesophagus and/or OG Junction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Oesophageal (gullet)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Randomised study of patients that have not shown early response to standard chemotherapy. All participants receive the standard treatment of a 21 day cycle of Cisplatin 80mg/m2 (intravenously infused over 2 hours) Day 1 and 5-Fluorouracil 1000 mg/m2 (continuous infusion) Days 1-4. All participants are restaged at day 15 with Positron Emission Tomography (PET). If significant response then standard treatment is repeated over another 21 day cycle. However if no significant response, subjects will be randomised to receive either 2 x 21 day cycles of Cisplatin 60mg/m2 (intravenously infused over 2 hours) on day 22 &amp; day 50, Docetaxel 35mg/m2 (intravenously infused over 1 hour) on Day 22, 29, 36, 50 ,57 &amp; 64 &amp; 5-Fluorouracil 150mg/m2 continuous intravenous infusion for 6 weeks starting Day 22 OR Cisplatin 60mg/m2 (intravenously infused over 2 hours) on day 22 &amp; day 50, Docetaxel 35mg/m2 (intravenously infused over 1 hour) on Day 22, 29, 36, 50 ,57 &amp; 64 &amp; 5-Fluorouracil 150mg/m2 continuous intravenous infusion for 6 weeks starting Day 22 plus radiation 45Gy/25Fr starting Day 22. Radiation will be administered once daily, Monday to Friday on 25 occasions. All participants will have surgery in an attempt for complete resection, 4 - 8 weeks after completion of neoadjuvant therapy. The operation should aim to remove the tumour in total, with an adequate margin in each direction. This may be done as a subtotal esophagectomy with proximal gastric resection and a right intrathoracic oesophago-gastrostomy (IvorLewis procedure), a subtotal oesophagectomy with proximal gastric resection and a cervical oesophago-gastrostomy (McKeon procedure). This is a complicated surgery often taking more than 6 hours.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment of Cisplatin 80mg/m2 Day 1(intravenously infused over 2 hours) &amp; 5-Fluorouracil 1000 mg/m2 Days 1-4 continous intravenous infusion for first 21 day cycle then if significant response on PET restaging at day 15.  Cisplatin &amp; 5-Fluorouracil repeated.

All participants will have surgery in an attempt for complete resection, 4 - 8 weeks after completion of neoadjuvant therapy.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the histological response to the neoadjuvant therapy regime</outcome>
      <timepoint>Tumour samples will be taken at baseline and at surgery (after neoadjuvant therapy).  After 23 patients have completed neoadujvant treatment and no histological responses have been observed then consideration will be given to stopping that particular arm.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the early PET response to the induction neoadjuvant therapy regimen</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pet scans will be done at baseline and then day 15.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the toxicity of Docetaxel in combination therapy for oesophageal cancer.  This will be done be review of clinical data such as physical exams and blood analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Toxicity will be assessed weekly whilst participants are receiving docetaxel.  Toxicity will be assessed pre-surgery, 6 weeks post surgery, 12 weeks post surgery, every 3 months for 2 years, then every 6 months out to 5 yrs</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the overall survival in the three treatment arms</outcome>
      <timepoint>After follow up completed for enrolled patients.  Patients will followed up until 5 years post surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the disease-free survival in the three treatment arms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After follow up completed for enrolled patients.  Patients will followed up until 5 years post surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the tumour down-staging in the three treatment arms.

Participants will be restaged post completion of neoadjuvant therapy with endoscopy, computed tomography scan and comparison of pre and post neoadjuvant tumour samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>Studies to be done on tissue samples banked at baseline and pre-surgery.  Surgery will be done 4-8 weeeks after completion of neoadjuvant therapy.  To ensure participants have recovered.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the effect of the treatment regimen on quality of life in each of the treatment arms. To be assessed by quality of life forms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quality of life forms done at baseline, pre-surgery and at various timepoints though-out the 5 year follow up period. Surgery will be done 4-8 weeeks after completion of neoadjuvant therapy. To ensure participants have recovered.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Histologically proven invasive adenocarcinoma of the oesophagus or gastroesophageal junction.

2.	Tumour thought to be T2 or greater or T1 tumours that are poorly differentiated or thought to be node-positive.

3.	Technically resectable disease, as assessed in consultation with the intended surgeon. 

4.	Tumour is sufficiently F-18 fluorodeoxyglucose (FGD) avid on the initial staging PET scan to provide sufficient contrast between tumour and the surrounding normal tissues so that a response to the neoadjuvant therapy may be assessed.

5.	Written informed consent of the patient according to local ethics committee guidelines.

6.	Medically fit for surgical resection, defined as having adequate cardiopulmonary function and Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Evidence of extrathoracic or extragastric spread apart from perigastric or mediastinal nodes, which are resectable. (Supraclavicular nodes renders the patient ineligible) 2. Tumour is located in the cervical oesophagus requiring pharyngolaryngectomy. 3. Tumour is predominantly within the stomach ie. most of the tumour is not involving the oesophagus or gastroesophageal junction. 4. Evidence of tracheo- or broncho oesophageal fistula. 5. Adequate haematological function. 6. Adequate renal function 7. Adequate liver function 8. Previous radiation therapy to the chest, previous chemotherapy within the last 5 years. 9. Previous malignancy for the previous 5 years apart from non metastatic Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the skin, Basal Cell Carcinoma or carcinoma in situ of the cervix. 10. Pregnant, lactating or inadequate contraception.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study population will consist of patients with localised, resectable adenocarcinoma of the oesophagus or gastroesophageal junction. Patients that show less than a 35% reduction from the baseline PET scan standard uptake value (SUV) on a PET scan performed 15 days after the commencement of the first cycle of cisplatin/5-FU chemotherapy will be randomised between chemotherapy (cisplatin/5-FU with the addition of docetaxel) followed by surgery or chemotherapy (cisplatin/5-FU with the addition of docetaxel) and radiation followed by surgery. Patients are allocated treatment via telephone randomisation with the NHMRC clinical trials centre.</concealment>
    <sequence>Treatment will be allocated using the minimization method, patients will be stratified using the following factors: Site of disease: OG Junction or Oesophogus and insitution.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>23/12/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>126</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,NSW,VIC,SA,WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AGITG</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre, THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
The Lifehouse Building, Level 6, 119-143 Missenden Road Camperdown,  NSW, 2050

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study compares the effectiveness of pre-operative treatment with cisplatin, 5 fluorouracil and docetaxel with or without radiotherapy in treating people who have shown a poor early response to standard chemotherapy for adenocarcinoma of the oesophagus and/or gastroesophageal junction. 

Who is it for? 
You can join this study if you have localised adenocarcinoma of the oesophagus or gastroesophageal junction which is due to be treated by surgery.

Trial details: 
After the first cycle of standard cisplatin/5-FU chemotherapy all patients will have a PET scan. Patients who have a poor response on the PET scan, will be randomly divided into two groups. One group will receive chemotherapy (cisplatin/5-FU with the addition of docetaxel) followed by surgery, and the other will receive chemotherapy (cisplatin/5-FU with the addition of docetaxel) and radiation followed by surgery. In both groups, the chemotherapy is given intravenously. In the group receiving radiation treatment, this will overlap with the chemotherapy treatment. The study aims to evaluate the response to the different therapy regimens, by comparing pathology samples, looking at the response on PET scans, toxicity, survival rates and quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Barbour A. et al. (2016) An AGITG trial  A randomised phase II study of pre-operative cisplatin, fluorouracil and DOCetaxel +/-radioTherapy based on poOR early response to cisplatin and fluorouracil for resectable esophageal adenocarcinoma. Ann Oncol 27(6): 2016 ESMO Congress. Abstract 610O. Presented October 8, 2016.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba, Qld 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/12/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008/148</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Greenslopes Private Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Newdegate Street
Greenslopes Qld 4120</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/06/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09/23</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cancer Institute NSW</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 9, 8 Central Avenue, Australian Technology Park, Eveleigh, NSW 2015</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011C/06/162</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SLHD Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X13-0175 and HREC/13/RPAH/261</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/07/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Barbour c/- DOCTOR Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre, University of Sydney, Locked bag 77, Camperdown, NSW, 1450</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>doctor@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>DOCTOR Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre, University of Sydney, Locked bag 77, Camperdown, NSW, 1450</address>
      <phone>02 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>doctor@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Barbour c/- DOCTOR Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre, University of Sydney, Locked bag 77, Camperdown, NSW, 1450</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>doctor@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>