<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372060">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000037303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study of EnGeneIC Dream Vectors (EDV's) packaged with the chemotherapy PNU-159682, given simultaneously as non-targeted EDVs carrying  an immune enhancer called EDVs40-mer, in participants with advanced cancer who have no curative treatment options. . 

</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1 Study of Anti-Human EGFR (Vectibix Sequence) Targeted EDVs Carrying the Cytotoxic Drug PNU-159682 (EGFR-VEDVsPNU) with Concurrent Non-Targeted EDVs Carrying an Immunomodulatory Adjuvant (EDVs40-mer) in Subjects with Advanced Solid Tumours who have No Curative Treatment Options </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Designer EDV / ENG8</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Advanced Solid Tumours</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is an open-label feasibility study of Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor (EGFR)-VEDVs containing PNU-159682 administered via intravenous (IV) infusion in combination with EDVs containing an immunomodulatory adjuvant (EDVs40-mer), in subjects with advanced solid tumours who have no curative treatment options. 

EGFR-VEDVsPNU and EDVs40-mer will be mixed together and administered IV in cycles consisting of 1 infusion per week for 8 weeks (8 doses in total), followed by a treatment free week in which tumours are assessed radiologically (week 9). 

The starting dose of EGFR-VEDVsPNU will be 2.5 x 10^9. The dose of PNU-159682. within the EGFR-VEDVsPNU equates to 1.5 micrograms. The starting dose of EDVs40-mer will be 5 x 10^8, 

A further two dose levels will be explored according to standard 3+3 dose escalation guidelines to evaluate 3 dose levels of EGFR-VEDVsPNU and EDVs40-mer, The second dose level will be 5 x 10^9 of EGFR-VEDVsPNU. The dose of PNU-159682. within the EGFR-VEDVsPNU equates to 3 micrograms, the concurrent dose of EDVs40-mer will be 1 x 10^9,

The third and final dose level will also be 5 x 10^9 of EGFR-VEDVsPNU, but the concurrent dose of EDVs40-mer will be increased to 2 x 10^9,

EDV treatment may continue for a maximum of 12 months duration, unless the subject becomes intolerant to the study medication, the subject withdraws consent, or at the discretion of the Investigator if it is felt to be in the best interests of the participant.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the safety and tolerability of EGFR-VEDVsPNU (with adjuvant EDVs40-mer) in subjects with advanced solid tumours.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety assessment will involve recording the incidence of Adverse Events (AEs) and clinically significant changes in vital signs and clinical laboratory tests. AE's and vital signs will be assessed pre-dose infusion and then at 1, 2 and 3 hours post each dose infusion and at 14 day withdrawal visit and 30-35 days post final dose. 

A designated Safety Review Committee will assess if any reported adverse event including Serious Adverse Events (SAE's) and Suspected Unexpected Serious Adverse Reactions (SUSAR's)  are attributable to the study treatment and fulfill the protocol defined criteria of a Dose Limiting Toxicity (DLT). 

Participants will be assessed for DLTs within the first 28 days of treatment. and will include up to the first 6 subjects enrolled at each dose level. In the case of missed doses, the DLT evaluable period will be extended by 7 days for each missed dose so that a DLT evaluable subject is defined as having received 4 doses and been evaluated for 7 days following each dose. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess anti-tumour response in subjects with advanced solid tumours who have exhausted all curative treatment options when administered EGFR-VEDVsPNU (with adjuvant EDVs40-mer).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Evidence of anti-tumour activity will be assessed radiologically, and response graded according to iRECIST or iRANO criteria. The overall response for each subject will be recorded at Week 9 of every cycle of treatment for the duration of treatment.. 

Results for best overall response (Complete Response, Partial Response, Stable Disease, or Progressive Disease) will be presented for individual subjects, and for the whole cohort or relevant subsets if applicable using frequency counts and percentages.

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival (OS) in subjects with advanced solid tumours who have exhausted all curative treatment options when administered EGFR-VEDVsPNU (with adjuvant EDVs40-mer).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Survival will be presented as months following administration of Dose 1 for individual subjects, and overall or for relevant subsets if applicable (particularly the cohort treated at the RP2D). Survival will continue to be monitored for the duration of the long term follow-up (every 3 months from the safety follow-up visit, for a period of 12 months, and then for the extent of subject survival). Kaplan Meier curves will be utilised to determine percentage and median survival. There is no control arm for this study. Survival will be compared to historic survival data for individual tumour types. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess immune response in subjects administered EGFR-VEDVsPNU (with adjuvant EDVs40-mer).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples will be collected from all subjects for culture of Peripheral Blood Mononuclear Cells (PBMCs) to assess immune response in vitro at screening and then at pre-Dose 8 (last dose) for each cycle. 

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess cytokine responses in subjects administered EGFR-VEDVsPNU (with adjuvant EDVs40-mer).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Cycle 1, collection of blood samples (pre-dose and 3 hours post-dose) will be taken for cytokine response analyses at each dose ,For all subsequent cycles the blood samples will be performed at dose 1 (pre and post dose) only. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance score of 0-2.
2.	Life expectancy greater than 3 months 
3.	Histologically or cytologically confirmed advanced solid tumour that is metastatic or unresectable and for which standard curative or palliative measures are not available or are no longer effective.
4.	Measurable disease per irRECIST or iRANO criteria. 
5.	Able to undergo CT or MRI (+/- PET) evaluation as applicable to tumour type. 
6..	Adequate cardiac function with LVEF greater or equal to 50% at baseline.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Significant pericardial effusions, pleural effusions or ascites.
2.	Concurrent unstable diabetes mellitus or other contraindications for the use of dexamethasone.
3.	Uncontrolled concurrent cardiac disease including, but not limited to symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia.
4.	Known to be human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B surface antigen or hepatitis C positive; or with a history of chronic active hepatitis or cirrhosis.
5.	History of uncontrolled arterial or venous thrombosis. Subjects with a history of arterial or venous thrombosis are eligible if the subject is controlled on low dose molecular weight heparins or low dose aspirin.
6.	Uncontrolled brain metastases. Subjects with a history of brain metastases are eligible if the subject is stable and off corticosteroids for at least 2 weeks prior to treatment in the study
7.	Received therapies or procedures within 28 days prior to receiving their first dose (or has not recovered from the toxic effects of such therapy) including:
-	Therapy with an EGFR inhibitor e.g. cetuximab or erlotinib.
-	Anti-angiogenic therapy e.g. Bevacizumab (Avastin).
-	Immunotherapeutic agents, vaccines, or monoclonal antibody therapy.
-	Alkylating agents.
-	Chemotherapy.
-	Other investigational therapy.
-	Any major surgery.
8.	Prior exposure to PNU.

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Due to the small number of subjects to be enrolled, and the range of tumour types for possible evaluation, findings will be presented in a descriptive manner with no formal statistical comparisons performed. 

Data will be presented for individual subjects. Where feasible (e.g. for subjects with the same tumour type, or for variables relevant to general EDV administration), continuous data will be summarised by the following descriptive statistics: n (number of observations), mean, standard deviation, median, minimum, maximum. Categorical data will be summarised by frequencies and percentages.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>19/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>4/02/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>29/06/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>3</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis>No data analysis planned</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Other reasons/comments</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother>Pre-clinical data and results from both the Designer EDV (ENG8) and in a small number of compassionate use patients, have demonstrated ways of eliminating or minimising any potential patient reaction post EDV dose, whilst potentially improving efficacy. It has been determined to develop a new protocol encompassing this new data rather than submit a major amendment. </withdrawnreasonother>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>EnGeneIC Pty Limited </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Building 2/25 Sirius Rd.
 Lane Cove West 
NSW 2066</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>EnGeneIC Pty Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Building 2/25 Sirius Rd.
Lane Cove West
NSW 2066</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this trial is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of a combination treatment of EnGeneIC Dream Vectors (EDV's) packaged with the chemotherapy PNU-159682, given with EDVs40-mer.

Who is it for? 
You may be eligible to enroll in this trial if you are aged 18 to 75 years old and have an advanced solid tumour that is metastatic or unresectable which cannot be treated with standard care or for which standard care treatment is no longer effective.

Study details
All participants enrolled in this trial will receive combination treatment with the following:
1. The EnGeneIC Dream Vector(TM) (EDV(TM)). The EDVs are very small particles known as nanocells, which are made from Salmonella bacteria. The type of Salmonella is one that does not cause disease. The EDV is the delivery vehicle used to transport the study drug directly to the site of the cancer. 
2. The Cancer Treatment. The study drug is called PNU-159682 (EGFR-VEDVsPNU). PNU-159682 is a type of chemotherapy. The study drug is packaged inside the EDVs and is delivered directly to the site of the tumour, rather than the bodys healthy cells and tissues. The EDVs will also be packaged with another substance that is designed to boost the immune system, called EDVs40-mer. 
3. Bispecific antibody. The EDV delivery system works in 2 ways, as well as carrying the study drug, the EDV surface is also coated with a bispecific antibody. A bispecific antibody is two antibodies linked together, such that one can attach to the EDV and the other to cancer cells. Once attached, the EDVs are taken up inside the cancer cells, and the study drug is delivered directly inside the cell itself, causing the cancer cell to fail and/or to die. 

Treatment will be administered in 9-week cycles. The treatment is combined in a syringe and administered in to a vein (intravenous), over a period of 20 minutes using a special pump.  One injection of the treatment mixture is given per week for the first 8 weeks of the cycle, followed by one week for CT or MRI scanning to evaluate the tumour response to treatment. Treatment will continue for up to 12 months or until the patient or investigator deems it suitable to stop treatment, for example if serious side effects occur. Each participant will receive one of three possible dose levels, depending on when they are enrolled and on the drug effects in previous participants.

It is hoped that the findings from this trial will provide information on whether EGFR-VEDVsPNU and EDVs40-mer treatment may be safe and effective for the treatment of otherwise incurable advanced solid tumours.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>246 Clayton Road
Clayton 
VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/03/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/MonH/407</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Vinod Ganju</name>
      <address>Peninsula and Southeast Oncology
Level 3, 24-28 Frankston-Flinders Road
Frankston  VIC  3199


</address>
      <phone>+61-3-9781-5244</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vinod.ganju@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Cheryl-Ann Hawkins RN MHA</name>
      <address>Oncology Research Department 
Monash Translation Research Precinct 
Level 3
246 Clayton Rd
Clayton, 3168
Victoria, Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61-3-8572-2429 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Cherylann.hawkins@monashhealth.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jennifer MacDiarmid</name>
      <address>EnGeneIC Pty Limited
Building 2/25 Sirius Rd.
Lane Cove West, 
NSW 2066
</address>
      <phone>+61-2-9420-5833</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jmacdiarmid@engeneic.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Helen Foster</name>
      <address>Building 2/25 Sirius Rd.
Lane Cove West, 
NSW 2066
</address>
      <phone>+61-2-8203-5033</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hfoster@engeneic.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>