<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369407">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001203549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study to evaluate safety and tolerability of a Traditional Chinese Herbal medicine combination AL (Astragalus membranaceus and Ligustrum lucidum) in people with advanced cancer.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot study to evaluate the safety and tolerability of a Traditional Chinese Medicine herbal combination AL (Astragalus membranaceus and Ligustrum lucidum) in people with advanced cancer.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1174-9933</utrn>
    <trialacronym>AL study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil known
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cancer
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The herbal combination AL is composed of 2 herbs (Astragalus membranaceus and Ligustrum lucidum) in a granule form but will be administered in the form of capsules.
For this study, the source of combination ALwill be a commercially available product called Zhenqi Fuzheng Capsule (ZFC). ZFC is extracted by a herbal pharmaceutical company in China (Gansu Fuzheng Pharmaceutical Technology Co. Ltd). This product has been registered by China State Drug Administration as a prescribed medicine (Z62020987). 



This is a pilot multicentre open-labelled study. Consenting patients will receive 12 capsules of AL each day for 12 weeks. Each capsule contains 400mg of AL. Participants will complete fatigue and quality of life questionnaires, and donate blood for tests at the beginning of the study, during AL treatment and after 12 weeks of AL treatment.  The ability of participants to tolerate AL will be determined by their treating physician. 

Known and possible side effect(s) for each arm of the trial (if applicable): Possible side effects (though uncommon as evidence relates to the
intravenous use of this herbal combination given with cancer
chemotherapy):
- Skin eruption and itching
- Hypertension
- Headache, dizziness and chest distress
- Insomnia

Even less common side effects
- Pain in limbs
- Abdominal bloating, poor appetite and vomiting
-Fever
- Gum bleeding
-Jaundice

Adherence will be monitored by self-report at each assessment and returned pill count at the end of the study. 

Specifically full blood counts (FBC) including a differential will be obtained prior to AL treatment, during (2 weeks, and 6 weeks after starting) and after AL treatment (12 weeks) at the follow up visit in line with usual care. In addition immunological and inflammatory markers will be measured at these time points.

A brief patient diary will be completed daily whilst on AL treatment to obtain information on toxicity 

The following questionnaires have all been well validated and are included to determine whether the measured symptoms are improved by the active treatment.
-General Health Questionnaire (GHQ) 12
-Functional Assessment of Cancer Treatment Fatigue (FACT-F)

In short, the study aims to determine the safety and tolerability of AL after 12 weeks of supplementation in patients with advanced cancer.

</interventions>
    <comparator>This is an open labelled pilot study. There is no comparator for this study</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The first primary endpoint will be the proportion of participants to experience serious adverse effects (safety)..Safety will be assessed based on patient diaries, hematological and non-hematological toxicities, performance status; tolerability will be assessed by the treating physician and pill count</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of the study after 12 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The second primary endpoint will be the proportion of participants to complete the study (tolerability) by review of patient diary and pill count</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of the study after 12 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite secondary outcome includes changes in inflammatory markers (NLR, CRP, albumin) measured using serum assays</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life (assessed by FACT-G)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety and depression assessed by GHQ</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue measured by FACT-F</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite secondary outcomes include hematological parameters such as haemoglobin, platelet and neutrophil count measured via blood counts</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 weeks, 6 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite secondary outcomes include biochemical parameters such as creatinine, urea and electrolytes measures by urinalysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 weeks, 6 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Random glucose by blood test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 weeks, 6 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite secondary outcomes include changes in T-regulatory cell populations and immunological markers.using flow cytometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in weight</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease status (compared with baseline, using RECIST and physician assessment)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of drug-related toxicity (haematological and non-haematological) as measured by the CTCAE.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease progression, assessed by ECOG status</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks and 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Diagnosis of recurrent or metastatic cancer
-	Aged greater than or equal to 18 years
-	Ability to understand  spoken and written English (to understand the study, provide informed consent and enable completion of self-report QOL questionnaires) or access to an appropriate translator
-	Give written informed consent
-	Patients must be accessible for treatment and follow-up. Investigators must assure themselves the patients entering this trial will be available for complete documentation of the treatment, adverse events, and follow up
-	Able to swallow capsules WHOLE
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-	Currently undergoing chemotherapy including palliative chemotherapy
-	ECOG Performance Status of greater than or equal to 3
-	Life expectancy is less than or equal to 12 weeks
-	Inadequate haematopoetic function (WBC &lt; 3.0 x 10^9/L; ANC &lt; 1.5 x 10^9/L, platelets &lt; 100 x 10^9/dL), or renal function (eGFR &lt; 50 mL/min/1.73m2) 
-	Inadequate hepatic function (either AST/ALT &gt; 2.5 x ULN, or &gt; 5   x ULN in case of liver metastases, or bilirubin &gt; 1.5 x ULN)
-	Any major pre-existing psychiatric history or dementia that (in the view of the investigator) would interfere with the ability to provide informed consent and/or compliance with study procedures
-	Pregnant or lactating women
-	Cerebral or leptomeningeal metastases that are unstable in spite of cranial radiotherapy &amp;/or stereotactic radiosurgery
-	Serious intercurrent medical illness including (but not restricted to) HIV, active infection, unstable angina, severe heart failure, or ongoing surgical complications
-	Major surgery within 2 weeks prior to study commencement
-	Concurrent Radiotherapy
-	Clinical evidence of current or impending bowel obstruction
-	Reluctance or inability to cease other Traditional Chinese or other herbal, homeopathic or naturopathic medicines at least a week prior to trial commencement
-	Documented allergy to study compounds
-	Patients must not be participating in (or planning to participate in) trials of other pharmacological agents during their time on this study
-	Concurrent use of immune-modulators
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>N/A</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analysis of the secondary endpoints, if continuous, will be based on t-tests or the non-parametric equivalent test if the data is non-normal. Descriptive statistics, such as the mean and standard deviation, will be used to summarise the patients. If the secondary endpoint is categorical contingency tables, proportions and frequencies will be used to summarise the results. On-sample proportion, chi-square, McNemar and Fishers exact tests will be used where appropriate. Exact p-values and 95% confidence intervals will be reported for all notable results, and plots and tabled data will be used to further describe the variables of interest. 

Investigation of potential association between the primary endpoint and the baseline factors of age, gender and tumour type will be undertaken using regression techniques. Linear transformations of skewed data will be performed as appropriate. 

For all statistical tests, a p-value of 0.05 will be considered statistically significant. However, since many secondary analyses will be conducted some tests may appear statistically significant due to chance, even if no association exists. These analyses will therefore be considered exploratory and are not powered to draw definitive conclusions.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord Repatriation Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - Royal North Shore Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Missenden Road</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Concord Repatriation General Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hospital Road, Concord NSW 2139</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Concord Repatriation General Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hospital Road, Concord NSW 2139</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Sydney, Faculty of Pharmacy</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Pharmacy and Bank Building (A15)
Camperdown Campus 
University of Sydney Sydney NSW 2006.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Australian Sikh Association (ASA)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress> 4-18 Meurants Lane
Glenwood  NSW 2768 </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aims:
This pilot trial aims to evaluate the safety and tolerability of a Traditional Chinese Medicine herbal combination AL (Astragalus membranaceus and Ligustrum lucidum) in people with advanced cancer. It will also investigate whether AL can improve the immune function

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or older and have been diagnosed with recurrent or metastatic cancer or have declined or are ineligible for further treatment.

Study details
All participants in this study will receive AL herbal treatment and take 12 capsules of AL each day for 12 weeks. The study treatment is a combination of two herbal medicines known as AL (Astragalus membranaceous and Ligustrum lucidum). AL consists of herbal medicines, which have been used together for many years in China especially in people undergoing cancer treatment. AL is commonly available as a registered product in China called Zhenqi Fuzheng Capsule. This product is registered by the China State Drug Administrations as a prescribed medicine (Z62020414). At least 17 clinical studies have investigated this combination AL using this same product Zhenqi Fuzheng Capsule in people with cancer who have undergone standard chemotherapy or radiotherapy treatments. We know from studies in other people with cancer that AL is usually well tolerated. It is possible that AL may help lessen some of the side-effects of cancer treatment  but this is the focus of future studies. The results from this study will be used to design future studies looking at combining these herbal medicines with current treatments.

Participant will complete fatigue and quality of life questionnaires, and donate blood for tests at baseline, during AL treatment and after.treatment The ability of participants to tolerate AL will be determined by their treating physician.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital Road, Concord NSW 2139</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/09/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/CRGH/139</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Philip Beale</name>
      <address>Concord Cancer Centre
Gloucester House, Level 6
Life House (Royal Prince Alfred Hospital)
Camperdown
NSW
2050
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9515 7404</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9767 5764</fax>
      <email>philip.beale@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Bhagwant Sekhon</name>
      <address>Building 4
Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital Road, Concord NSW 2139</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9767 6586</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bhagwant.sekhon@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew McLachlan </name>
      <address>Building 76
Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital Road, Concord NSW 2139</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9767 7373</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.mclachlan@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Bhagwant Sekhon</name>
      <address>Building 4
Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital Road, Concord NSW 2139</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9767 6586</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bhagwant.sekhon@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>