<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363696">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000264785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Immunogenicity and Safety of a 13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine in paediatric oncology patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Immunogenicity and Safety of a 13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine in paediatric oncology patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1139-5120 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>PCVPON1</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none here</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>paediatric malignancy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Brain</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Leukaemia &amp; Lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Other</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients will receive a pre-vaccination blood sample and a nasal swab. All patients will then be administered single dose of 13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine, 0.5 mL intramuscular injection. All patients will then have a post-vaccination blood sample and a nasal swab 1 month later.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator treatment being studied is the immunogenicity of the pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (13-valent) being given to  oncology children on immunosuppressive treatment. All patients will be administered single dose of 13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine, 0.5 mL intramuscular injection. 

There is a active control group of oncology children who had completed treatment within 12 months. This is not a "true" control group, since the current standard practice are to administer vaccinations when 6 months after treatment completion.

Therefore, both comparator groups will be compared to historical control groups, who are healthy infants with previous PCV7 given single dose of PCV13 (reference: Silfverdal SA et al Vaccine. 2013 Feb 18;31(9):1284-92.). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the percentage of participants who achieve protective vaccine type serotype specific serum IgG antibody levels (&gt;0.35 microgram/mL)  following single dose administration of PCV13. (5 mL of venous blood will be taken). Method: microsphere based flow-cytometric assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month post vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the percentage of participants who achieve protective vaccine type serotype specific opsonophagocytic assay titre &gt;1:8 following single dose administration of PCV13. 5 mL of venous blood will be taken for serum, from which the multiplex opsonophagocytic assay is performed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month post vaccination</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine change in serotype-specific nasopharyngeal colonisation rate of Streptococcus pneumoniae following single dose of PCV 13. A nasopharyngeal swab will be taken and bacterial cultures performed. Bacterial identification, serotyping and antibiotic sensitivity will be tested.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month post vaccination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine persistence of antibody levels and OPA titres in patients receiving PCV13 booster vaccination during cancer treatment, by measuring serum levels of IgG antibody and opsonophagocytic assay. A 5 mL venous blood sample will be taken.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post end of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>patients with haematological and solid organ malignancies at Princess Margaret Hospital for Children and currently receiving chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy, or those who have completed chemotherapy or radiotherapy within the last 12 months and have not yet received a PCV 13 booster. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>previous anaphylaxis to Prevenar 13 or any vaccine component, received intravenous immunoglobulin in the 3 months prior to administration of vaccination, and patient with asplenia or conditions known to be associated with hyposplenia.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Te-Yu Hung</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Roberts Rd
Subiaco WA 6008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Princess Margaret Hospital Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 68 Hay street, Subiaco Western Australia 6008</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>PMH Telethon Fellowship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Roberts Rd, Subiaco 6008 WA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Peter Richmond</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Roberts Rd Subiaco WA 6008</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will look at the effectiveness of the 13-valent pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (Prevenar 13 registered trademark) in children currently or recently receiving cancer treatment. Prevenar13 (registered trademark) has been part of the regular immunisation schedule for all children at 2, 4, and 6 months in Australia since 2011. Pneumococcal conjugate vaccines are known to be very effective in healthy children under 2 years in preventing severe bacterial infections caused by Streptococcus pneumoniae, such as meningitis, bloodstream infections, chest and ear infections.

Currently the vaccine is only licensed in Australia for children under 5 years and adults over 50 years of age. It is expected that it will be licensed for older children soon. It is recommended by experts that older children up to the age of 18 years with a medical condition that lowers the bodys immune system be given a dose of the Prevenar 13 (registered trademark) vaccine.

Who is it for? 
All children aged between 1 and 18 years with a diagnosis of cancer who are either receiving chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy, or have recently completed chemotherapy or radiotherapy within the last 12 months. Patients who have completed treatment and already given a booster dose of Prevenar 13 (registered trademark) are not eligible.

Trial details 
You will be asked to sign a consent form permitting your child to take part in the study. You will be asked  questions regarding your childs diagnosis, treatment (current or past), previous immunisations received and any side effects experienced. We will ask for your permission to access the Australian Childhood Immunisation Registry (ACIR) database for details of the immunisations. 

We ask you to remain for at least 15 minutes after the vaccination for observation of your child to monitor for any side effects. This is routine practice for all immunisations. You will be given a 7 day symptom diary to record any side effects, including measuring the body temperature at least once in the evening, and any other time that the child feels warm or unwell. You will be asked to bring the diary back at the next appointment.

We will take a blood sample (5 mL or 1 teaspoon) to measure the immune level against the bacteria and a nasal swab to see if the bacteria is carried in the nose. The blood sample may be taken at the same time when other treatment bloods are being taken (e.g. from the port or Broviac). 

We will give the Prevenar 13 (registered trademark) vaccine by an injection in the leg or the upper arm. When you return for your appointment one month later, we will take another blood sample (5 mL) and a nasal swab to compare. 

If your child is enrolling and being vaccinated whilst still on cancer treatment,  another blood sample (5 mL) and a nasal swab will be taken 6 months after your child has completed treatment.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Roberts Road Subiaco WA 6008
GPO Box D184 Perth WA 6840</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2072/EP</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/12/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Te-Yu Hung</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Roberts Rd
Subiaco WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 8222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Te-Yu.Hung@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Te-Yu Hung</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Roberts Rd
Subiaco WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 8222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Te-Yu.Hung@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Te-Yu Hung</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Roberts Rd
Subiaco WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 8222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Te-Yu.Hung@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>