<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335226">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/03/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/04/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000271000</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Lenalidomide and 5azacitidine treatment versus 5azacitidine alone in patients with the blood cancers myelodysplastic syndrome or acute myeloid leukaemia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Phase II study comparing the efficacy of 5azacitidine alone versus combination therapy with lenalidomide and 5azacitidine in patients with higher risk myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS) and low marrow blast count acute myeloid leukaemia (AML).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Low marrow blast count acute myeloid leukaemia (AML)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Acute leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>combination 5azacitidine (subcutaneous administration) and oral lenalidomide. All patients begin 5azacitidine 75mg/m2/day x 7 days (75mg/m2/day on days 1-5 and days 8-9) of a 28 day cycle. At Cycle 3, patients are randomised to commence lenalidomide (at 10mg/day x 21 days of a 28 day cycle) in combination with 5 azacitidine (75mg/m2/day x 5 days (days 1-5) of a 28 day cycle)  until primary endpoint at 12 months after commencing treatment. Following this, all patients may continue 5azacitidine alone until progression or toxicity.</interventions>
    <comparator>5azacitidine alone (subcutaneous administration; 75mg/m2/day on days 1-5 and days 8-9 of each 28 day cycle) for 12 months until primary endpoint, then all patients may continue 5azacitidine alone until progression or toxicity.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To demonstrate improved efficacy with the combination of lenalidomide and 5azacitidine compared to 5azacitidine alone in patients with MDS and low marrow blast count AML, with acceptable toxicity of the combination. Outcome will be assessed by measures of disease response as defined by International Working Group (IWG) criteria (2006) and determined by peripheral blood counts, transfusions, bone marrow morphology and cytogenetics.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months from start of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To describe responses, duration of response and overall survival with 5azacitidine or lenalidomide + 5azacitidine in patients with MDS and low marrow blast count AML. Outcome will be assessed by measures of disease response as defined by International Working Group (IWG) criteria (2006) and determined by peripheral blood counts, transfusions, bone marrow morphology and cytogenetics.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years after last accrued patient completes study treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To describe tolerability of the combination of lenalidomide and 5azacitidine in patients with MDS and low marrow blast count AML. Outcome will be assessed by rate of non-haematological adverse events and  a protocol-specific definition of haematologic toxicity. These events will be documented by clinicians during clinic visits.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years after last accrued patient completes study treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To explore biomarkers of response and mechanism of action of 5azacitidine and lenalidomide in patients with MDS and low marrow blast count AML using a variety of correlative studies at baseline and on treatment correlated to individual clinical responses</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years after last accrued patient completes study treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Disease diagnosis of either MDS (by World Health Organisation criteria, those with refractory anaemia and Refractory Anaemia with Ringed Sideroblasts to also have at least one clinically significant cytopenia), nonproliferative Chronic Myelomonocytic Leukaemia (CMML) or low marrow blast count AML; Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) 2 or less with life expectancy at least 3 months, adequate contraception and adequate renal and hepatic function, written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prior chemotherapy for MDS or AML except low dose cytarabine or hydroxyurea, any prior demethylating agent or immunomodulatory drug (including thalidomide or lenalidomide), prior diagnosis of cancer except with low risk of recurrence, significant renal, hepatic, cardiac or respiratory disease or severe active infection.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be registered and randomised at a central administration site. The clinician at the study site who assesses study eligibility as per protocol criteria is unaware prior to the randomisation procedure, which study arm the subject will be allocated.</concealment>
    <sequence>a dynamic computer-based minimisation algorithm will be used to determine approximately equal (1:1 ratio) numbers of patients to each arm (AZA+/- LEN), with stratification by International Prognostic Scoring System (low-int1 or int2-high)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/03/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>12/03/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>160</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/08/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC,ACT,QLD,SA,WA,NT,TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 2/10 St Andrews Place
East Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, 3002</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Celgene Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Celgene Australia Melbourne
Level 7, 607 St Kilda Road
Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Lenalidomide and Azacitidine each have clear evidence of efficacy in MDS, and have shown activity in AML. However, not all patients respond so better regimens, including combinations, are required. MDS and AML are heterogeneous diseases, and lenalidomide and azacitidine may target different cellular populations and induce differing clinical responses. Combinations of immunomodulatory drugs and azacitidine have been explored and shown to be feasible. This is an open label, multi-centre, randomised Phase II study exploring the toxicity and efficacy of the combination of lenalidomide and 5azacitidine compared to 5azacitidine alone. After an initial 2 cycles with 5azacitidine (75mg/m2/day x7days over 9days of a 28 day cycle; 5-2-2 regimen), patients will be randomised 1:1 to either combination 5azacitidine and lenalidomide (5azacitidine 75mg/m2/day x5days of a 28 day cycle + lenalidomide commencing cycle 3 10mg/dayx21days of a 28 day cycle) or 5azacitidine alone (75mg/m2/day x7days over 9days of a 28 day cycle; 5-2-2 regimen) for 12 months to primary endpoint, then all patients may continue 5azacitidine alone until progression or toxicity. Response will be determined by peripheral blood counts, transfusions, bone marrow morphology and cytogenetics, according to IWG criteria. The study also incorporates a correlative laboratory component designed to determine the mechanism of action of 5azacitidine +/- lenalidomide and to determine a baseline profile which may predict those most responsive. These studies will incorporate gene methylation and expression, and enumeration of lymphocyte subsets, natural killer cell function and cytokine profiles.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/08/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>AUSTIN HEALTH HUMAN RESEARCH ETHICS COMMITTEE</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg VIC 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/Austin/49</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/11/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Melita Kenealy</name>
      <address>c/o Department of Haematology and Medical Oncology
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
Locked Bag 1
ABeckett Street
Melbourne VIC 8006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9509 6505</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>melitak@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Melita Kenealy</name>
      <address>c/o Department of Haematology and Medical Oncology
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
Locked Bag 1
ABeckett Street
Melbourne VIC 8006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9509 6505</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>melitak@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Melita Kenealy</name>
      <address>Update c/o Department of Haematology and Medical Oncology Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre Locked Bag 1 ABeckett Street Melbourne VIC 8006</address>
      <phone>61 3 9509 6505</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>melitak@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>