<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372989">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000847314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effects of High Intensity Exercise on Cardiovascular Function in Men with Metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer (MCRPC): a sub study of GAP4-QLD INTense Exercise foR surVivAL among men with MCRPC (INTERVAL - MCRPC)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Effects of High Intensity Exercise on Cardiovascular Function in Men with Metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer (MCRPC): a sub study of GAP4-QLD INTense Exercise foR surVivAL among men with MCRPC (INTERVAL - MCRPC)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer (MCRPC)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Men with Metastatic Castrate-resistant Prostate Cancer (MCRPC) who are receiving a tapered high-intensity exercise intervention plus psychosocial support will be observed for 24 months within the larger 'INTense Exercise foR surVivAL Among Men With Metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer (INTERVAL)' (Trial ID: NCT02730338) clinical trial.  Changes in cardiovascular function will be observed and periodically tested within this 24-month period. 

Participants randomised to the intervention arm within the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (Trial ID: NCT02730338) will undertake 24 months of high intensity interval training.  Participants will be required to complete three one-hour exercise sessions per week in either a university strength and conditioning gym or in the participants community/home.  Each session will include a combination of high intensity aerobic and resistance exercises.  

The exercise intervention will taper from fully supervised (month 1), to partially supervised (months 2-12) to fully self-managed (months 13-24).  Supervised sessions will either be individual or group-based and will be supervised by an Accredited Exercise Physiologist (AEP).   Participants will be provided with tailored exercise programs, designed by an AEP, for the duration of the intervention.  These tailored exercise programs will be reviewed after each exercise session and will take into account each participants disease-status, exercise performance and exercise preferences.  Programs will be delivered via a computer/phone application and thus can be accessed both at the gym and during self-managed sessions.  Participants will be instructed on how to use the application during their first supervised training session. 

Intervention participants will also receive psychosocial support, in the form of monthly newsletters, which will address prostate cancer-specific lifestyle factors/topics e.g. sexual health, dietary guidance.     </interventions>
    <comparator>Men with Metastatic Castrate-resistant Prostate Cancer (MCRPC) who are receiving psychosocial support alone will be observed for 24 months within the larger 'INTense Exercise foR surVivAL Among Men With Metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer (INTERVAL)' (Trial ID: NCT02730338) clinical trial.  Changes in cardiovascular function will be observed and periodically tested within this 24-month period.  

Men randomised to the control arm within the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (Trial ID: NCT02730338) will receive 24 months of psychosocial support only.  Psychosocial support will be provided in the form of monthly newsletters, which will address prostate cancer-specific lifestyle factors/topics e.g. sexual health, dietary guidance.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Brachial Artery Flow-mediated Dilation (FMD) as assessed via doppler ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 24 months after randomisation within the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (Trial ID: NCT02730338). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Heart Rate Variability (HRV) as assessed via resting 3-lead ECG</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 24 months after randomisation within the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (Trial ID: NCT02730338). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Pulse Wave Analysis (PWA) as assessed via SphygmoCor® XCEL PWA and PWV system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 24 months after randomisation within the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (Trial ID: NCT02730338). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in Pulse Wave Velocity (PWV) as assessed via SphygmoCor® XCEL PWA and PWV system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 24 months after randomisation within the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (Trial ID: NCT02730338). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in oxidative stress as assessed via plasma nitrate and nitrite levels.  Collected via a 10mL vacutainer. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 24 months after randomisation within the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (Trial ID: NCT02730338). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>As participants for the sub-study will be recruited through the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (Trial ID: NCT02730338), the key inclusion criteria have been listed previously in INTense Exercise foR surVivAL Among Men With Metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer (INTERVAL) (Trial ID: NCT02730338).

No additional key inclusion criteria are required to be met for involvement in this sub-study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>As participants for the sub-study will be recruited through the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (Trial ID: NCT02730338), the key exclusion criteria have been listed previously in INTense Exercise foR surVivAL Among Men With Metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer (INTERVAL) (Trial ID: NCT02730338).

No additional key exclusion criteria are required to be met for involvement in this sub-study. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>All participants in the sub-study will be recruited through the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (Trail ID: Trial ID: NCT02730338).  Approximately 60 participants randomised at a 1:1 ratio with Metastatic Castrate-Resistance Prostate Cancer will be recruited and allocated to the School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences, University of Queensland, St Lucia site.

Therefore, the sample size for this sub-study has been defined as a convenience sample as the sub-study will be provided with a pre-determined number of possible participants.  Similar sample sizes are also commonly used in studies which investigate differences in the primary outcome for this sub-study.

All raw data will be analysed via relevant software packages.  Statistical analyses of raw data will be conducted on IBM SPPS Statistics for iOS.  Analysis of normal distribution, within and between group differences over the five time points will be conducted. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/08/2022</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences, University of Queensland, St Lucia, QLD, 4072.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences, University of Queensland, St Lucia, QLD, 4072.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this sub-study is to assess the effects of high intensity aerobic and resistance training plus psychosocial support on cardiovascular function in men with metastatic castrate-resistant prostate cancer (MCRPC).

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to participate in this sub-study if you are already enrolled in the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (ClinicalTrials.gov ID: NCT02730338) in Queensland.

Study details
In addition to the requirements of the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial, all participants in this sub-study will be asked to attend assessment sessions at the University of Queensland at baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months and 24 months after randomisation into the GAP4 INTERVAL trial. At each of these visits, various measures will be taken in order to assess cardiovascular function, including ultrasound and blood tests.

The findings of this sub-study will help in developing safe and effective lifestyle interventions which have the potential to lead to improved clinical practice for men with MCRPC.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>This sub-study is to be conducted alongside the larger 'INTense Exercise foR surVivAL Among Men With Metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer (INTERVAL)' (Trial ID: NCT02730338) clinical trial.  For the purpose of this application, the clinical trail will be referred to as the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (Trial ID: NCT02730338). 

This sub-study is to be conducted at only one investigation site, the School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences, University of Queensland, St Lucia, Queensland, Australia, 4072.  Participants will not be randomised within the sub-study itself, but will be eligible for enrolment once they have passed screening and randomisation within the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (Trial ID: NCT02730338). 

This sub-study is to include additional and seperate outcome measures (listed as primary and secondary outcomes within this application) to those being assessed within the GAP4 INTERVAL clinical trial (Trial ID: NCT02730338).  These additional outcome measures will be assessed during 5 additional testing sessions within the GAP4 intervention/control period (12 months in total, with a follow-up at 24 months). </publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland Human Research Ethics Committee A</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Queensland, St Lucia, QLD, 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2017000497</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/04/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Natalie Vear</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences, Level 5, Human Movement Studies Building (26B), Blair Drive, University of Queensland, St Lucia, QLD, 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 4 3490 4208</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.vear@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jeff Coombes</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences, Level 5, Human Movement Studies Building (26B), Blair Drive, University of Queensland, St Lucia, QLD, 4072
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 6767</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jcoombes@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jeff Coombes</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences, Level 5, Human Movement Studies Building (26B), Blair Drive, University of Queensland, St Lucia, QLD, 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 6767</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jcoombes@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Natalie Vear</name>
      <address>School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences, Level 5, Human Movement Studies Building (26B), Blair Drive, University of Queensland, St Lucia, QLD, 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 4 3490 4208</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.vear@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>