<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82507">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/01/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/01/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000011381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial to evaluate the effectiveness of a bowel cancer screening decision aid for adults with low literacy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of a bowel cancer decision aid to support informed decision making among adults with low literacy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Low literacy FOBT DA</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bowel cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A paper-based decision aid (with and without a question prompt list), audio visual DVD which had been specifically designed for adults with low education and literacy, who are making decisions about bowel cancer screening (using the Faecal Occult Blood test). The decision aid (a 33-page booklet) covers information provided by the Australian Commonwealth screening booklet, but is presented in a different format using simplified text and visual cues. The decision aid includes additional probabilistic information on cumulative FOBT outcomes over 10 years and a personal worksheet for people to complete to help them decide whether to do the screening test. about doing the screening test. We decided to produce an audio-visual DVD to accompany the text-based booklet and improve the accessibility of the information for adults with very basic literacy skills. The DVD lasted for about 20 minutes. 

Participants will receive the intervention (decision aid and DVD) after they have completed a baseline telephone survey. The intervention package will be sent directly to people at home which means they have the choice of reading the booklet or watching the DVD, or both. They will be telephoned 2-3 weeks later to complete a follow-up survey.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard Australian Commonwealth Bowel Cancer Screening written information booklet which is currently posted to adults who are invited to take part in the National Bowel Cancer Screening program</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Informed decision making (attitudes towards bowel cancer screening, knowledge about screening and screening behaviour). This will be measured using a telephone survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Attitudes and understanding of bowel cancer screening will be measured 2-3 weeks after intervention commencement
Screening behaviour will be cross checked with the laboratory, 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Involvement preferences in screening decisions. This will be measured using a telephone survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-3 weeks post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety. This will be measured using a telephone survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-3 weeks after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bowel cancer worry. This will be measured using a telephone survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-3 weeks after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bowel cancer screening interest. This will be measured using a telephone survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-3 weeks after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bowel cancer screening intentions. This will be measured using a telephone survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-3 weeks after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decisional conflict. This will be measured using a telephone survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-3 weeks after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decision satisfaction. This will be measured using a telephone survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-3 weeks after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluation of materials (written information &amp; DVD). This will be measured using telephone survey questions devised by the research team.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-3 weeks after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Use of different components (DVD, Question Prompt List). This will be measured using telephone survey questions devised by the research team.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-3 weeks after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Influence of doctor on participant's bowel cancer screening decision. This will be measured using telephone survey questions devised by the research team.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-3 weeks after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Men and Women aged 55-64 years
Low levels of education (no formal educational qualifications, intermediate certificate (or equivalent), trade/apprenticeship (e.g. hairdresser, carpenter)
English as main language spoken at home
Average risk of bowel cancer (no family history or weak family history of bowel cancer)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>55</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>64</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Respondents who attained higher school or leaving certificate (or equivalent), TAFE certificate, diploma, University degree or higher will not be able to take part in the trial
Respondents who have invited to and or already taking part in the National Bowel Cancer Screening program 
Respondents who have bowel cancer or had a bowel condition in the last 12 months which is currently under treatment
Respondents who have had a bowel cancer screening test in the last 2 years (this includes: faecal occult blood test, colonoscopy, flexible sigmoidoscopy)
Respondents with a strong family history of bowel cancer</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Please replace "Participants will be randomized to group A or B study arms using random permuted blocks within gender strata" with "Participants were randomised to one of three trial arms using random permuted blocks within gender strata.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised to one of three study arms using random permuted blocks within gender strata.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2774</postcode>
    <postcode>2564</postcode>
    <postcode>2148</postcode>
    <postcode>2460</postcode>
    <postcode>2870</postcode>
    <postcode>2310</postcode>
    <postcode>2348</postcode>
    <postcode>2421</postcode>
    <postcode>2678</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Kirsten McCaffery</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Screening and Test Evaluation Program
School of Public Health 
Edward Ford Building (A27)
Room 301F
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421 
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Screening and Test Evaluation Program</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Screening and Test Evaluation Program
School of Public Health 
Edward Ford Building (A27)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Lyndal Trevena</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Public Health 
Edward Ford Building (A27)
Room 321B
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Professor Alexandra Barratt</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Public Health 
Edward Ford Building (A27)
Room 323A
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Don Nutbeam</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>A14- Quadrangle
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Judy Simpson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Public Health 
Edward Ford Building (A27)
Room 301A
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Sian Smith</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Public Health, Edward Ford Bldg (A27), Room 126A,  University of Sydney, NSW 2006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a study to evaluate the effectiveness of a new decision aid for bowel cancer screening, for adults with low literacy levels.

 Participants are eligible to participate if they:
- are aged 5564 years
- have lower levels of education
- are at average  or slightly above average risk of bowel cancer.

Trial details

Eligible participants will invited via telephone to take part in the trial. Those who consent will then be randomly divided into three groups. One group will receive a written decision aid (plus DVD and Question Prompt list) specifically designed for adults with low education and literacy, who are making decisions about bowel cancer screening. The second group will receive the written decision aid (+ DVD) without question prompt list, and the third group will receive the standard government consumer information. Both groups will receive a bowel cancer screening Faecal Occult Blood test (FOBT) kit and instructions. Participants will be telephoned 23 weeks later to complete a follow-up survey. At 3 months, we will record whether participant completed the screening test by checking against the laboratory records. 



This study aims to evaluate the extent to which a written decision aid tailored for adults with low levels of literacy can increase understanding of bowel cancer screening and promote informed decision making.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Smith SK, Trevena LJ, Barratt A, Simpson J, Nutbeam D, McCaffery KJ. Design and preliminary evaluation of a bowel cancer screening decision aid for adults with low literacy. Patient Education and Counselling, accepted February 2009. Health literacy special issue.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee
Main Quad (A14)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/10/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10403</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kirsten McCaffery</name>
      <address>Screening and Test Evaluation Program
School of Public Health 
Edward Ford Bldg (A27)
Room 301F
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93517220</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93515049</fax>
      <email>kirstenm@health.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sian Smith</name>
      <address>Screening and Test Evaluation Program
School of Public Health 
Edward Ford Bldg (A27)
Room 126A
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93517186</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93515049</fax>
      <email>sians@health.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sian Smith</name>
      <address>Screening and Test Evaluation Program
School of Public Health 
Edward Ford Bldg (A27)
Room 126A
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93517186</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93515049</fax>
      <email>sians@health.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>