<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365601">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000074695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Get Healthy after Breast Cancer - examining the feasibility and acceptability of referring breast cancer survivors to the NSW Get Healthy Service  a telephone-delivered program targeting physical activity, healthy diet and weight loss</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Examining the feasibility and acceptability of referring breast cancer survivors to the NSW 'Get Healthy Service' - a telephone-delivered program targeting physical activity, healthy diet and weight loss</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>GHaBC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This research study seeks to look at the best ways of supporting women who have completed breast cancer treatment within the last 12 months to make lifestyle changes (increasing physical activity, improving eating habits, and achieving and maintaining a healthy weight) to promote longer-term health and well-being. Participants will receive 6 months of telephone counselling from the 'NSW Get Healthy Information and Coaching Service' (GHS). The GHS is a free telephone counselling program designed to help participants increase their physical activity, improve their diet and achieve and maintain a healthy weight. Participants receive up to 10 coaching calls, with an average duration of 13 minutes, over a period of 6 months (up to 6 calls during the first 12 weeks and up to 4 calls in the remaining 14 weeks). GHS health coaches are all university qualified health professionals, such as psychologists, nurses, dieticians, exercise physiologists, sports scientists, social workers, and physiotherapists. They receive further training to ensure they meet the requirements of the GHS. The aim of the study is to evaluate the feasibility and acceptability of the GHS for women within 12 months of end-of-treatment for stage I-III breast cancer. </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group - all participants receive the intervention</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome of feasibility and acceptability will be measured via the following indicators: GHS uptake and number of calls (from GHS records), and womens satisfaction with the GHS, including likes/dislikes and suggestions for improvement (as reported during qualitative telephone interviews conducted after the completion of the intervention).</outcome>
      <timepoint>End-of-intervention - 6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight - objectively assessed during nurse visits</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (6 months after baseline assessment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary intake as measured by the Fat &amp; Fibre Behaviour Questionnaire (22 items including fruit and vegetable intake, fat and fibre intake, and breakfast consumption) during telephone interviews</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (6 months after baseline assessment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity as measured by the Active Australia Survey (8 items + 2 additional items on strength exercise) during telephone interviews</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (6 months after baseline assessment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life as measured by the PROMIS global health scale in the self-report questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (6 months after baseline assessment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue as measured by the FACT-IT scale in the self-report questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (6 months after baseline assessment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression as measured by the PROMIS SF-Depression 1.0 scale in the self-report questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (6 months after baseline assessment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body image as measured by the PAL Relationships and Body Image scale in the self-report questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (6 months after baseline assessment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Menopausal symptoms as measured by the Greene Climacteric scale in the self-report questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post-intervention (6 months after baseline assessment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Female
2. First diagnosis of stage I-III breast cancer (unilateral or bilateral)
3. Aged 18-75 years
4. Completed primary treatment with curative intent (i.e., initial surgery, chemotherapy, radiation therapy) within the past 12 months (endocrine or targeted therapies may be ongoing)
5. Scheduled to return to the breast cancer clinic where they were recruited into the study for a follow-up appointment within approximately 6 months of starting the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Diagnosed with ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS; stage 0) or distant metastases (stage IV)
2. Pregnant
3. Contraindications to participating in an unsupervised program (active heart disease, impaired mobility)
4. Taking warfarin
5. Insufficient English to complete assessments and participate in a telephone-delivered program
6. Reporting depression/anxiety as a current significant problem that would interfere with study participation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A maximum of 50 women will be recruited into the study, which should allow an adequate test of the primary outcomes of feasibility and acceptability. The proposed sample size will also allow for estimation of effect sizes for quality of life, physical activity, dietary intake and changes in weight. Primary outcomes will be reported using descriptive statistics (i.e., means and standard deviations or their non-parametric equivalents, as appropriate to data distributions). Secondary outcomes will be assessed by examining pre-test to post-test changes using paired t-tests (or non-parametric tests, as appropriate). Statistical significance will be set at p &lt; 0.05 (two-tailed). Follow-up qualitative interviews will be audio-recorded, transcribed, coded and then thematically analysed.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Population Health, Cancer Prevention Research Centre, Level 4 Public Health Building, Herston road, HERSTON, QLD, 4006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Queensland, St Lucia, Brisbane, QLD, 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Westmead Breast Cancer Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Westmead Breast Cancer Institute, Level 1, Westmead Hospital, corner Hawkesbury &amp; Darcy roads, WESTMEAD, NSW, 2145</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research study seeks to look at the best ways of supporting women who have completed breast cancer treatment within the last 12 months to make lifestyle changes (increasing physical activity, improving eating habits, and achieving and maintaining a healthy weight) to promote longer-term health and well-being. 

Who is it for? 
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a female aged between 18-75 years who has completed primary treatment with curative intent for stage I-III breast cancer (unilateral or bilateral) within the past 12 months. 

Study details 
All participants in this study will receive 6 months of telephone counselling from the NSW Get Healthy Service (GHS), which is a telephone counselling program for physical activity, healthy eating and weight loss. We are interested in whether this program is acceptable and beneficial for breast cancer survivors. In order to determine this, participants will be asked to complete a number of assessments and questionnaires on completion of the program to evaluate feasibility and acceptability of the project, changes in body weight, dietary intake, physical activity levels, quality of life, fatigue, depression, body image and menopausal symptoms.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.uq.edu.au/cprc/index.html?page=197476</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office, Room 1072, Level 1, Education Block, Westmead Hospital, Hawkesbury &amp; Darcy roads, WESTMEAD, NSW, 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC2012/12/4.10(3628) AU RED HREC/12/WMEAD/428</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Queensland, UQ Research &amp; Innovation,
Cumbrae-Stewart Building, Research Road, BRISBANE, QLD, 4072, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/12/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013000426</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sheleigh Lawler</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland, School of Population Health, Cancer Prevention Research Centre, Level 4 Public Health Building, Herston road, HERSTON, QLD, 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5544</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 5540</fax>
      <email>s.lawler@sph.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Erin Robson</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland, School of Population Health, Cancer Prevention Research Centre, Level 4 Public Health Building, Herston road, HERSTON, QLD, 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 4669</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 5540</fax>
      <email>e.robson@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sheleigh Lawler</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland, School of Population Health, Cancer Prevention Research Centre, Level 4 Public Health Building, Herston road, HERSTON, QLD, 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5544</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 5540</fax>
      <email>s.lawler@sph.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>