<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365406">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/12/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001365752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A blood test for improving participation in bowel cancer screening</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Will people at average risk for developing colorectal cancer, who are offered a screening program for colorectal cancer (CRC) that includes a blood test in addition to faecal occult blood tests (FOBT) participate at a significantly greater rate relative to people offered a screening program consisting of  FOBT only. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1150-9448 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>WolRes</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Colorectal cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is a screening program for CRC that includes the availability of a blood test for CRC.

The intervention group are initially mailed an offer of screening for bowel cancer by FOBT. 

At 12 weeks from date of the FOBT-screening offer, subjects who have not participated in FOBT-screening are mailed a second invitation to screen for CRC using a blood test for CRC. 

Intervention group subjects contact the study Help-Line to request a referral to a pathology service for a blood to be taken for the blood test.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The Control group are initially mailed an offer of screening for bowel cancer by FOBT. 

At 12 weeks from date of the initial FOBT-screening offer, subjects who have not participated in FOBT screening are mailed a second invitation to screen for CRC using FOBT.

Control group subjects contact the study Help-Line to request a FOBT to be posted to them

 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Completion of a screening test for bowel cancer within a bowel cancer screening program.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks from written offer of a second screening test.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Completion of a screening test for CRC after having recently declined a faecal occult blood test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks from written offer of second screening test for CRC.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>General Practice patients
average risk for bowel cancer</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>74</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable to provide informed consent.
Unsuitable for CRC screening as judged by the person's GP.
Medical record documented recent CRC screening within previous 2 years (FOBT/FIT; colonoscopy within 5 years) or participating in appropriate high risk CRC surveillance. 
Patients who are likely to be sent a test from the NBCSP within the expected study duration.
Otherwise deemed unsuitable for screening offer by the GP (eg poor English language comprehension or inability to follow protocol). 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients receive a letter from their general practice inviting them to participate in a research study concerned with screening for bowel cancer.

The practice is unaware to which group their patient will be allocated.

Eligible patients who provide their signed consent are enrolled in the study </concealment>
    <sequence>Patients are listed on a MS Access database in order of firstly date of providing consent, and secondly alphabetical order of surname. The list is exported to Microsoft Excel.

Patients are assigned a random number using the RANDOM function of Microsoft Excel, the list is ordered in an ascending way and the list divided equally in two.
Patients in the half associated with the lower numbers are allocated to intervention group. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>For the main objective, participation in the intervention group should be at least 10% greater than control across the program.

Expected participation rate for control Standard FOBT offer (Phase 1) plus additional participation from second offer (Phase 2) = 55%. This is based on NBCSP participation (average risk screening program) of &lt;40%, influence of GP on participation = 10% above standard offer (Cole et al J Med Screen 2002;9:147-52), additional increment due to motivated population. 

Expected participation for intervention = 50% from Phase 1 (same as Phase 1 control) plus 50% of Phase 2 = 75%. Second offer participation rate is based on preference for screening test specimen type data (Osborne et al Open J Prev Med 2012;2:326-331) and GP personal communication. 

For the main objective A two group chi-square test (not Yates corrected) with a 0.050 two-sided significance level will have 80% power to detect a 10% difference between Group 1 proportion (control) of 0.550 and a Group 2 proportion (intervention) of 0.650 (odds ratio of 1.519) when the sample size in each group is 376. 

For the secondary objective, a worthwhile improvement is seen as a 20% difference between the arms (this is equivalent to a 10% difference across the program if the phase 1 participation is 50%. Based on the prediction that Phase 2 participation in the control group will be 10%, intervention group participation would need to be at least 30%. A two group chi-square test (not Yates corrected) with a 0.050 two-sided significance level will have 80% power to detect the difference between a Group 1 proportion of 0.10 and a Group 2 proportion of 0.30 (odds ratio of 3.857) when the sample size in each group is 62.

To allow for lower participation in the intervention group, and/or improved power, we use group sizes of 600.

Statistical tests: Descriptive, Bivariate chi2, multivariate (GLM) to control for differences in population age, gender, SES, general practice affiliation
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>10/12/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>10/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Clinical Genomics</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Riverside Life Sciences Building,
11 Julius Ave,
North Ryde,
NSW, 2113</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Clinical Genomics
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Riverside Life Sciences Building,
11 Julius Ave,
North Ryde,
NSW, 2113
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Flinders University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Sturt Road
Bedford Park 5042
South Australia </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study aim is to determine whether the availability of a simple blood test for colorectal cancer will improve participation in screening for colorectal cancer (CRC). Our hypothesis is that a blood test will improve participation in screening for CRC.
Patients attending General Practices in Adelaide that are involved in the study, who are aged 50-74 years old and are at average risk for bowel cancer may be invited to participate in this study. Study details: Many people do not participate in stool (faecal) sample-based screening programs for early detection of colorectal cancer because of their dislike for the test. The purpose of this research is to determine if a blood test for colorectal cancer, if offered to people who have just declined a standard faecal occult blood (FOB)-based screening test, will be completed and result in a significant improvement in the overall program participation rate, relative to a program where only faecal occult blood test (FOBT) is offered. Participants in this study will be randomly (by chance) allocated to one of two programs  one where they are offered the blood test if they declined the FOBT provided through the study, and one where FOBT is offered twice. We will assess how many of these invitees completed a screening test and compere participation rates between groups. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Flats G5  Rooms 3 and 4
Flinders Drive
Flinders Medical Centre
Bedford Park
SA 5042



</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>422.13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Stephen Cole</name>
      <address>Bowel Health Service,
Repatriation General Hospital
216 Daws Road
Daw Park
SA 5041
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751838</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>steve.cole@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Stephen Cole</name>
      <address>Bowel Health Service,
Repatriation General Hospital
216 Daws Road
Daw Park
SA 5041
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751838</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>steve.cole@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Stephen Cole</name>
      <address>Bowel Health Service,
Repatriation General Hospital
216 Daws Road
Daw Park
SA 5041
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751838</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>steve.cole@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>steve.cole@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>