<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364086">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000470796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Testing an online intervention to improve the sun protective behaviour of Australian adults.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Testing an online intervention which utilises the theory of planned behaviour to improve the sun protective behaviour of Australian adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sun preventative-behaviours</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Non melanoma skin cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The interactive intervention will be delivered during one online session lasting between 20 and 25 minutes. The intervention will address 3 different constructs, (1) designed to encourage supportive sun protection related attitudes and beliefs, (2) fostering perceptions of friendship group normative support for sun protection and (3) increase perceptions of control/self-efficacy over using sun protection. A series of questions/ quizzes will be used to encourage supportive sun protection related attitudes and beliefs. Animated scenarios depicting situations in which one character is faced with opposition from an important referent to performing sun protective behaviour will be used to foster perceptions of friendship group normative support for sun protection.  A series of questions will be used to prompt participants to consider how they would respond and how they may prevent the situation from occurring.  An increase in perception of control/self-efficacy over using sun protection will be the aim of a set of animated scenarios and questions which ask participants to consider scenario specific barriers to sun protective behaviour and to suggest solutions to the barriers. Increasing intention to sun protect will be addressed through setting sun safe goals and through the creation of a contract outlining intention.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will be randomly allocated to the intervention group (n = 200), the information only group (n = 200) or the control group (n=20). The information only group will be asked to view an 8 minute online DVD and three fact sheets relating to sun-protective behaviour which are currently available from Cancer Council Queenslands website. 

The control group will not be asked to do anything beyond completing the 3 questionnaires.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: Participants sun protective-behaviour as measured by self-report through the use of an online questionnaire developed by the researchers, using standard theory of planned behaviour items.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, immediately following intervention and at 1 and 4 weeks post intervention
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2: Participants intentions to sun-protect as measured by self-report through the use of an online questionnaire developed by the researchers, using standard theory of planned behaviour items.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, immediately following intervention and at 1 and 4 weeks post intervention
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: Participants attitude toward sun-protection as measured by self-report through the use of an online questionnaire developed by the researchers, using standard theory of planned behaviour items.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, immediately following intervention and at 1 and 4 weeks post intervention 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2: Participants perception of normative support for sun-protection as measured by self-report through the use of an online questionnaire developed by the researchers, using standard theory of planned behaviour items.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, immediately following intervention and at 1 and 4 weeks post intervention
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3: Participants perception of control/self-efficacy toward sun-protection as measured by self-report through the use of an online questionnaire developed by the researchers, using standard theory of planned behaviour items.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, immediately following intervention and at 1 and 4 weeks post intervention
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligibility criteria include male and female adults, living in metropolitan, regional, and coastal areas of Queensland, Australia.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants from a previous research study relating to sun protection who have already provided their consent to be contacted for participation in further research studies, will receive an email invitation to participate in the main  research study. 

Additionally, Australian adults (approximately equal numbers of males and females) living in metropolitan, regional and coastal areas will be approached via QUT media releases, through use of recruitment notices in newsletters and newspapers, radio stations, and community billboards, through QUT classifieds and websites and email lists and through snow balling techniques.
Participants will be provided with information via email on a participant recruitment flyer. They will be provided with an online link to the participant information sheet and will provide their consent to participate by ticking a box indicating they agree to participate. Participants will be randomly allocated to their treatment group via a computer generated number sequence after completion of the first questionnaire.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Consenting participants who have completed the first questionnaire will be randomised in a 200:200:20 ratio to the intervention or information only or control group using a computer-generated random number sequence.</sequence>
    <masking />
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/03/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>420</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kelvin Grove Campus
Cnr Musk and Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 2702 
Canberra ACT 2601 
Australia 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Council Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>553 Gregory Terrace, Fortitude Valley QLD 4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to evaluate the effect of an online intervention in improving the sun protective behaviour of Australian adults. Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above and live in metropolitan, regional or coastal areas of Queensland, Australia. Trial details: Participants in this trial will be randomly (by chance) allocated to one of three groups: the intervention group, the information only group, or the control group. Participants in the intervention group will receive the online intervention which focuses on encouraging supportive sun protective attitudes and beliefs, fostering perceptions of normative support for sun protection behaviour and increasing perceptions of control/self-efficacy over using sun protection. It will be delivered during one online session lasting between 20 and 25 minutes. Participants in the information only group will be asked to view a short online DVD and three fact sheets relating to sun-protective behaviour which are currently available from Cancer Council Queenslands website. Data on intentions to sun protect and sun protection behaviour will be collected via questionnaire immediately prior to the intervention (Time 1), immediately following the intervention (Time 2) and at one week (Time 3) and four weeks (Time 4) post-intervention. The control group will not be asked to do anything beyond completing the 3 questionnaires. The study will provide valuable information about the effectiveness of the intervention in improving the sun protective behaviour of Australian adults  a population which has the highest incident rates of skin cancer in the world (Queensland).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://sunsafestudy.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Katherine M. White, Ross McD. Young, Anna L. Hawkes, Catherine Cleary, Stuart Leske, Louise Starfelt, Kylie Wihardjo  (2013, April). A randomised controlled trial of an online theory-based intervention to improve adult Australians' sun-protective behaviours. Paper presented at the APS Health Psychology Conference Cairns</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University Human Research Ethics Committee, Queensland University of Technology</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Queensland University of Technology,  88 Musk Avenue Kelvin Grove Campus, GPO Box 2434, BRISBANE   QLD   4001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1200000658</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Katherine White</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Counselling,  Queensland University of Technology,  Victoria Park Road, Kelvin Grove. Brisbane, Queensland 4059, AUSTRALIA </address>
      <phone>+61 07 3138 4689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>km.white@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Katherine White</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Counselling,  Queensland University of Technology,  Victoria Park Road, Kelvin Grove. Brisbane, Queensland 4059, AUSTRALIA </address>
      <phone>+61 07 3138 4689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>km.white@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Katherine White</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Counselling,  Queensland University of Technology,  Victoria Park Road, Kelvin Grove. Brisbane, Queensland 4059, AUSTRALIA </address>
      <phone>+61 07 3138 4689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>km.white@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>