<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366235">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000478617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase II Study of Stereotactic Ablative Body Radiotherapy (SABR) for Stage I Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessing the feasibility of Stereotactic Ablative Body Radiotherapy (SABR) for stage I Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC): A single arm prospective phase II non-randomized multicentre study </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1156-1927</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SABR Lung</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non-small cell lung cancer, stage T1-T2, N0M0 (AJCC staging, 6th ed.)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Non small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Stereotactic ablative body radiotherapy
Patients will be assigned to 1 of 3 treatment arms, dependent on site of the lesion.
1. Peripheral lesions:
- Tumour GTV less than 1.5 cm from ribs: 48 Gy in 4 fractions (12Gy/#)
- Tumour GTV greater than or equal to1.5 cm from ribs: 54 Gy in 3 fractions (18Gy/#)
2. Central lesions:
- 50 Gy in 5 fractions (10Gy/#)

Two to three treatments are to be delivered per week. There must be a minimum break of 1 day and a maximum break of 4 days between fractions. The following applied to the treatment delivery times:
3 fraction regimens to be delivered within 11 days
4 fraction regimens to be delivered within 14 days
5 fraction regimens to be delivered within 14 days</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Local control 
The primary lung tumour (target lesion) is measured by CT scans and evaluated using the Revised Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours (RECIST) Guideline version1.1. Local control consists of Complete Response or Partial Response or Stable Disease and will be correspond to the absence of Local Failure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 4 weeks post-treatment, then 3 montly until 24 months </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Achievement of dosimetric constraints
Dosimetry assessment is based on the dose information reported according to the requirements of International Commission on Radiation Units and Measurements (ICRU83). Doses to central organs at risk and all the conformity indices parameters are also recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>collected from the treatment planning data</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival measured from the date of enrolment to death from any cause. Assessed via clinical assessment and ongoing follow-up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks post treatment, then 3 monthly until 24 months and then 6 monthly until 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression free survival-defined as the absence of local failure and/or regional failure and/or distant failure and/or death from any cause. Assessed via clinical asssessment and ongoing follow-up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks post treatment, then 3 monthly until 24 months and then 6 monthly until 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Loco-regional control
Assessment of loco-regional control is made by evaluation of non-target lesions, which is recorded at the point of their appearance and throughout follow-up. Assessed via CT scans.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 monthly until 24 months and then 6 monthly until 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Distant metastases
Metastatic progression is made in comparison to the required pretreatment staging studies or any other pretreatment imaging evaluations available. Assessed via CT scans.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 monthly until 24 months and then 6 monthly until 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung function
Lung function is assessed by lung function test which is performed once every 6 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 monthly until 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life outcomes
Measured using European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire-Cancer 30 (EORTC QLQ-C30) and Lung Cancer (LC-13)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks post treatment, then 3 monthly until 24 months and then 6 monthly until 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ability to deliver treatment with the development of no Grade 3 or greater CTCAE version 4.0 toxicity. Assessment made by clinical assessment and ongoing follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks post treatment, then 3 monthly until 24 months and then 6 monthly until 60 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of non-small cell lung cancer
-Pathological diagnosis is desirable where this can be achieved.
-Diagnosis based on imaging: requires evidence that lesion(s) are increasing in size on 2 consecutive CT scans and /or increased uptake on PET.

Stage T1-T2, N0M0 (AJCC Staging, 6th ed.) with tumour size less than or equal to 5 cm, based upon:
-History and physical examination 4 weeks prior to registration.
-CT chest, abdomen and pelvis and/or
-FDG PET-CT scan

ECOG performance status of less than or equal to 2

Patients must be able to lie flat and comply with the requirements of simulation and treatment.

Patients with previous thoracic radiotherapy are permitted, provided V20 less than 15% on previous treatment an no overlap with intended current radiotherapy field

Patients with previous history of malignancy may be included provided the previous malignancy is in remission and after a MDT discussion the current lung lesion is thought to be more likely of lung primary rather than metastatic disease</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant women

Inability to lie flat and tolerate immobilization for duration of planning and treatment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary end point, local control at 24 months from start of treatment, is used for sample size calculation. Prior data indicate that the probability of local recurrence amongst cases receiving the historical standard treatment (3D-Conformal radiotherapy from 60 to 70 Gy) is 0.65. This estimate of local control from historical techniques is conservatively high, and other studies have shown local control rates under 50%. A sample size of 85 will allow the detection of a 15% difference in local control rates to 65% from those of historical data (50%), with a significance level of 5% and power of 80%. Allowing for an approximate 15% drop-out rate for follow-up, we will recruit approximately 100 patients. Based on estimated recruitment form centres currently treating SABR lung cancer, this sample size should be easily achievable. STATA SE version 11 was used for sample size calculation (one sample). Proportions for local control at 24 months will be described as percentage with 95% CI.

Analysis for secondary endpoints will be descriptive.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Gosford Hospital - Gosford</hospital>
    <hospital>Lismore Base Hospital - Lismore</hospital>
    <hospital>Coffs Harbour Base Hospital - Coffs Harbour</hospital>
    <hospital>Port Macquarie Base Hospital - Port Macquarie</hospital>
    <hospital>Calvary Mater Newcastle - Waratah</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Private Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Eric Hau</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Cancer Care Centre
St George Hospital
Gray Street, Kogarah, NSW 2217</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to investigate the efficacy of stereotactic ablative radiation therapy for treatment of Stage I non-small cell lung cancer. Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above and have a diagnosis of Stage I non-small cell lung cancer. You must be able to lie flat and comply with the requirements of simulation and treatment. Participants in this study will be treated with stereotactic ablative radiation therapy with one of three dose and fractionation regimens. For peripheral lesions treatment dose will be 48 Gy in 4 fractions or 54 Gy in 3 fractions, depending on tumour size. For central lesions 50 Gy will be administered in 5 fractions. Overall treatment duration will vary from 11  14 days. Local control at 24 months is the primary endpoint of the study and is assessed by CT scans. Patients will be followed up until 5 years post treatment. A total of 100 patients will be recruited in this study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Conference presentations:

Collaborative implementation of stereotactic ablative body radiotherapy. A model for the safe implementation of complex radiotherapy techniques in Australia. Hau E, Hegi-Johnson F, ,Barber J, Best S, Browne L, Chin Y, Downes S, Dwyer P, Eade T, Graham PH, Lu D, Rains M, Small K, Unicomb K, West K, White S, Wong W, van Tilburg K, Yeghiaian-Alvandi R. 2014 Annual Scientific Meeting, Melbourne Australia

I Love a Sunburnt Country...Tripartite Collaborative Approaches to Bring Stereotactic Ablative Radiotherapy (SABR) Lung to the People of Regional Australia. Fiona Hegi-Johnson, Eric Hau, Kylie Unicomb, Jeff Barber, Melissa Rains,Dan Lu, Michael Bailey, Matthew Foote, Roland Yeghiaian-Alvandi. 15th World Conference on Lung Cancer, 
October 2013, Sydney Australia</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room G71 East Wing
Edmund Blacket Building
Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick, NSW, 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/12/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/240 (HREC/13/POWH/781)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cancer Institute NSW</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 9, 8 Central Avenue, Australian Technology Park, Eveleigh, NSW 2015</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/12/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/CIC/22 (2011C/09/170)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eric Hau</name>
      <address>Cancer Care Centre
St George Hospital
Gray Street, Kogarah, NSW, 2217</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9113 3835</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Eric.Hau@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Dan Lu</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit
Pitney Clinical Sciences Building
St George Hospital
Gray Street, Kogarah, NSW, 2217</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9113 4825</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9113 4822</fax>
      <email>Dan.Lu@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Fiona Hegi-Johnson</name>
      <address>Central Coast Cancer Centre
Gosford Hospital
Holden Street, Gosford, NSW, 2250</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4320 9811</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Fiona.Hegi-Johnson@health.nsw.gov.au or fionahegi@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Dan Lu</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit
Pitney Clinical Sciences Building
St George Hospital
Kogarah, NSW, 2217</address>
      <phone>(612) 9113 4825</phone>
      <fax>(612) 9113 4822</fax>
      <email>Dan.Lu@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>