<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369764">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000003471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving health in breast cancer survivors, a novel dietary approach</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Will an adapted Mediterranean diet (BC-MED) improve health in breast cancer survivors?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1174-8542 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>BC-Med</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Dietary education will occur monthly for 6 months at the Clinical Research Centre in Grafton (85 Park Road, Grafton).  Both BC-Med and Healthy Diet intervention will receive education (conducted by a Registered Dietitian and Dietetic student) and newsletters (sent by email). Face-to-face group education will occur once-monthly, with the newsletter sent two weeks thereafter.  

Questionnaires will be administered and bloods taken at baseline, at completion of intervention (6 months) and 6 months post intervention (12 months). Body weight, a blood test and questionnaires will be measured at baseline, post intervention and follow-up. 

Participants will be placed into one of three arms of a dietary intervention study.  Each arm will consist of 15 women. Women on Arm 1 will be asked to adhere to a BC-MED diet and will receive dietary support and education. The BC-Med diet will consist of increasing the intake of olive oil, flaxseed oil, vegetables, fruit, legumes, fish, nuts, onions, leeks, garlic and turmeric while limiting the intake of red meat, butter, margarine, cream, carbonated drinks and pastries. The treatment diet will not restrict food volumes, just alter food types. 

Those placed in Arm 2 will be asked to adhere to a New Zealand healthy eating diet and will receive dietary support and education.  The healthy eating diet will follow guidelines from the Nutrition Guidelines and will advocate fruit and vegetable consumption, low fat dairy, low fat meat, wholegrains and adequate hydration.  The treatment diet will not restrict food volumes. An educational newsletter will be provided to the BC-MED and healthy eating groups once a month during the intervention. The intervention period will be 6 months. 

Changes in gene expression levels will be calculated and used to determine the pathways and networks affected by the change in dietary intake. Study participants will be genotyped in order to account for some of the risk associated with hereditary factors and differences in response to the diet. Diet adherance will be determined via attendance at education sessions, and on analysis of the food diaries completed mid way through the intervention, and change in PREDIMED questionnaire.

Participants in each group will be matched for receptor expression and histology, breast cancer grade and use of hormone therapy. Research will be conducted at the Clinical Research Centre at Grafton campus of The University of Auckland.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Women in Arm 3 will be asked to continue as usual and will receive no education or support until study completion. The no treatment control will be provided all the education material of the most successful group once the study has been completed.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight. Measured on calibrated, ISAK accredited body weight scales in the clinical centre by an ISAK accredited anthropometrist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of intervention (6 months), and 6 months post intervention (12 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood lipids (LDL-chol, Total cholesterol). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of intervention (6 months), and 6 months post intervention (12 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HbA1c (whole blood), assessed using ion exchange chromotography</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of intervention (6 months), and 6 months post intervention (12 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DNA damage (The comet assay)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of intervention (6 months), and 6 months post intervention (12 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life questionnaire (FACT-B)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of intervention (6 months), and 6 months post intervention (12 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary intake questionnaire (PREDIMED) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of intervention (6 months), and 6 months post intervention (12 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>C-RP (serum sample)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of intervention (6 months) and 6 months post intervention (12 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatty acid profile (FAMES assay)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of trial (6 months) and 6 months post intervention (12 months)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Those aged 50 or above, diagnosed with grade 1-3 breast cancer and three or more months following active treatment and a body mass index (BMI) &gt;25 will be enrolled. Participants can be on hormonal therapy. Participants will need to provide medical information regarding their breast cancer grade. We request participants provide receptor expression and use of hormone therapy, but those who wish to keep this information private will still be eligible.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>We will exclude those on anti-inflammatory medication; those who drink more than 2 standard alcoholic beverages per day; those diagnosed with diabetes mellitus or those who smoke tobacco. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Each participant will be allocated an identification number from 1-45. The participants will be block allocated to one of three groups. Set 1 will be arm 1, set 2 arm 2 and set 3 no treatment control. Allocation to treatment will occur via central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>On-line randomiser (www.randomizer.org) will be used to perform a block allocation, ensuring (to our best effect) equal weighting to breast cancer grade, receptor expression and use of hormone therapy. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The study is powered for the primary outcome, weight loss, at 80% power to detect a 3% weight loss (p&lt;0.05) in the intervention group, yielding a target sample size of ten participants per group. Studies of similar design have experienced 25% drop out, therefore 15 participants per group will be recruited. Randomisation will be determined a priori by a researcher not involved with the intervention. Group assignment will not be revealed to the participant until the completion of all baseline testing.
Data will be analysed following log transformation to reduce the effects of non-uniformity of error and express outcomes as percent. The two-tailed Students t distribution will be used to analyse pre-post changes. We will use the standardised (Cohen) change of 0.20 times the between-subject standard deviation for the baseline measure in the control condition as the substantial threshold; a modified classification system (trivial, 0.00.2; small, 0.20.6; moderate, 0.61.2; large, 1.22.0; very large, &gt;2.0) will be used to interpret the magnitude of the standardized change. An effect will be deemed unclear if the confidence interval overlapped both the upper and the lower thresholds for substantiveness. Otherwise, the likelihood of a substantial increase or decrease will be classified as follows: &lt;0.5%, almost certainly not; 0.5%5%, very unlikely; 5%25%, unlikely; 25%75%, possible; 75%95%, likely; 95%99.5%, very likely; and &gt;99.5%, almost certain. When the majority (&gt;50%) of the confidence interval lies between the threshold for substantially positive and negative effects, the likelihood of the effect being trivial (negligible) will be qualified.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>14/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>5/02/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>38</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/09/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>85 Park Road,
Grafton, Auckland
New Zealand, 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Programme Seeding Fund, The University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019,
Auckland Mail Centre,
Auckland, 1142
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: Breast cancer is the most common cancer amongst women in western countries, including New Zealand. Following the introduction of the national breast screening programme and increased breast cancer awareness, mortality rates in New Zealand have dropped. Despite this, more than 600 women die each year from the disease. Age, gender and genotype have been identified as risk factors for breast cancer, but are beyond individual control. Fortunately, modifiable factors such as diet, weight, alcohol consumption, tobacco use and physical activity have been shown to reduce breast cancer risk. Many of these modifiable factors influence inflammation, and chronic inflammation is associated with an increased risk of cancer development, progression and recurrence. Recent studies demonstrate that cancers are associated with an inflammatory microenvironment that promotes tumour growth. In addition to the microenvironment, there is also a connection between obesity, metabolic syndrome, and poor outcomes in breast cancer patients. Excess weight at diagnosis, weight gain following diagnosis and android body fat distribution all negatively impacts disease-free survival and local recurrence of breast cancer. Our hypothesis is: the Mediterranean diet will reduce excess weight, metabolic syndrome and improve the inflammatory profile, and therefore may offer the breast cancer survivor specific benefits. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Northern Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/STH/184</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrea Braakhuis</name>
      <address>The University of Auckland
Faculty of Medical and Health Science
85 Park Road
Grafton, Auckland,
New Zealand, 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 22 350 2926</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.braakhuis@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrea Braakhuis</name>
      <address>The University of Auckland
Faculty of Medical and Health Science
85 Park Road
Grafton, Auckland,
New Zealand, 1142</address>
      <phone>+64223502926</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.braakhuis@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrea Braakhuis</name>
      <address>The University of Auckland
Faculty of Medical and Health Science
85 Park Road
Grafton, Auckland,
New Zealand, 1142</address>
      <phone>+64223502926</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.braakhuis@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>