<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371484">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000087358p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Treatment optimisation trial in the first-line treatment of advanced stage Hodgkin lymphoma; comparison of 6 cycles of escalated BEACOPP with 6 cycles of BrECADD.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Treatment optimisation trial in the first-line treatment of advanced stage Hodgkin lymphoma; comparison of 6 cycles of escalated BEACOPP with 6 cycles of BrECADD.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>GHSG HD21</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ClinicalTrials.gov ID: NCT02661503</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>EudraCT No: 2014-005130-55</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>Sponsor Code: Uni-Koeln-1762</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>ALLG HD10</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Advanced stage Hodgkin lymphoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hodgkin's</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is an international, prospective, randomised and open-label phase III trial.  The aim of this trial is to prove that the new chemotherapy regimen, BrECADD, is non-inferior to BEACOPP as first line treatment in advanced stage classical Hodgkin lymphoma.

Patients will be randomised in a 1:1 ratio to either arm1 or arm2.

Arm1 (standard group): Patients will receive 6 cycles of the escalated BEACOPP regimen as follows- Cyclophosphamide (1250 mg/m^2, IV over 60 minute infusion, day 1); Adriamycin (35 mg/m^2, IV over 30 minute infusion, day 1); Etoposide (200 mg/m^2 per day, IV over 60 minute infusion, day 1 to day 3); Procarbazine (100 mg/m^2 per day, oral capsule, day 1 to day 7); Prednisone (40 mg/m^2 per day, oral tablet, day 1 to day 14); Vincristine (1.4 mg/m^2, IV bolus, day 8); Bleomycin (10 mg/m^2, IV bolus, day 8); Pegylated G-CSF ( 6 mg, subcutaneous injection, day 4).
Each cycle is 21 days.

Arm2 (experimental group): Patients will receive 6 cycles of the BrECADD regimen as follows- Brentuximab vedotin (1.8 mg/kg, IV over 30 minute infusion, day 1); Cyclophosphamide (1250 mg/m^2, IV over 60 minute infusion, day 2); Adriamycin (40 mg/m^2, IV over 30 minute infusion, day 2); Etoposide (150 mg/m^2 per day, IV over 60 minute infusion, day 2 to day 4); Dacarbazine (250 mg/m^2 per day, IV over 120 minute infusion, day 3 to day 4); Dexamethasone (40 mg/m^2 per day, oral tablet, day 2 to day 5); Pegylated G-CSF (6 mg, subcutaneous injection, day 5).
Each cycle is 21 days.

In both groups, restaging will take place in the last week of the second treatment cycle (PET-2), at the end of chemotherapy (PET-6), and at the end of radiotherapy if given (restaging after radiotherapy).  In both groups, PET-2 is to take place in the last week of the 2nd chemotherapy cycle (between day 17 and day 21) PET-6 is to take place within 3 weeks after day 21 of the 6th chemotherapy cycle.  
Patients will undergo restaging by FDG-PET with low dose CT, of the whole trunk of the body; images of the lower extremities are only required if a primary tumour was located there.  Each restaging will always include an examination of all initially involved lymph nodes or organs using adequate methods.  The objective of the PET-2 interim restaging is to document the response to chemotherapy, and to reassess if the patient is still qualified for the trial.  The objective of the PET-6 restaging is to document the response to chemotherapy, and to recommend patients for radiotherapy where tumour masses are greater than or equal to 2.5 cm after chemotherapy. If a patient is scheduled for radiotherapy following PET-6 restaging, an additional FDG-PET will take place within 6 weeks after completion of radiotherapy.  The decision and organisation of the radiotherapy is up to the discretion of the treating physician on site.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm1 (standard group): Patients will receive 6 cycles of the escalated BEACOPP regimen as follows- Cyclophosphamide (1250 mg/m^2, IV over 60 minute infusion, day 1); Adriamycin (35 mg/m^2, IV over 30 minute infusion, day 1); Etoposide (200 mg/m^2 per day, IV over 60 minute infusion, day 1 to day 3); Procarbazine (100 mg/m^2 per day, oral capsule, day 1 to day 7); Prednisone (40 mg/m^2 per day, oral tablet, day 1 to day 14); Vincristine (1.4 mg/m^2, IV bolus, day 8); Bleomycin (10 mg/m^2, IV bolus, day 8); Pegylated G-CSF ( 6 mg, subcutaneous injection, day 4).
Each cycle is 21 days.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome of the trial is the determine if non-inferior efficacy of 6 cycles of BrECADD compared to 6 cycles of escalated BEACOPP, each followed by radiotherapy to PET-positive residual lesions greater than or equal to 2.5cm, improves PFS rates.   </outcome>
      <timepoint>Progression free survival is the time from the date of randomisation until the date of the first occurrence of:
- progression of disease;
- relapse; or
- death from any cause.
The PFS will be censored at the data of the last information on tumour status if none of these events have occurred.
The date of disease progression or relapse will always be the diagnosis date (date of biopsy taken, if available) even if it is not diagnosed at a scheduled visit.
Patients without a tumour assessment post-baseline will be censored at the date of randomisation. Patients will neither be censored nor deemed failures if more than one visit is missed, or if an additional anti-cancer treatment is initiated without evidence of objective progression. Each patient will be follow up for  a period of at least 5 years.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The co-primary endpoint for this trial is the rate of serious treatment-related morbidity- "TRMorbidity". 
TRMorbidity is defined as any CTCAE organ toxicity of grade 3 or 4 or severe haematological toxicity of grade 4 during primary chemotherapy of the following SOC categories as documented on the CTCAE toxicities section of the eCRF:
- Cardiac disorders grade 3 or 4;
- Gastrointestinal disorder grade 3 or 4 (excluding vomiting, nausea and mucositis);
- Hepatobiliary disorders grade 3 or 4;
- Nervous system disorder grade 3 or 4;
- Renal and urinary disorders grade 3 or 4;
- Respiratory, thoracic, and mediastinal disorders grade 3 or 4;
- Anaemia grade 4;
- Thrombocytopenia grade 4, and 
- Infections grade 4.


PFS and TRMorbidity are not considered composite endpoints for this study.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>TRMorbidity will be assessed during protocol conform therapy in both arms, and until 30 days after the last dose of chemotherapy.  Events occurring after this time-period have to be reported if they are rated to be at least possibly related to chemotherapy.

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival (OS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calculated from the date of the initial staging until the date of death.  If the patient is alive, the OS is censored at the date of last information including follow up visits and quality of life questionnaires.. Each patient will be in follow up for  a period of at least 5 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tumour response (final treatment outcome)- the rate of complete remissions at the restaging after the primary study treatment including radiotherapy if applicable.
A complete remission has been attained if one of the following conditions is met:
- complete radiologic response with regress of all residual masses to less than or equal to 1.5 cm in the largest diameter in the absence of signs of active lymphoma
- Complete metabolic response (score 1-3) with or without residual masses in absence of clinical signs of active lymphoma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Tumour response will be measured at CT-2/PET-2 (between days 17-21 of the 2nd chemotherapy cycle) and CT-6/PET-6 (following 6 cycles of chemotherapy, within 3 weeks after day 21 of the last cycle).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Infertility rate at 1 year will be measured using a questionnaire used previously in GHSG advanced Hodgkin Lymphoma trials- HD15 and HD18. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At screening (before treatment, at time of restaging after end of chemotherapy, and 12 months after the end of chemotherapy.  It is to be decided at the discretion of the treating physician, in consultation with the patient, if and when further examinations should be performed.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Malignancies- including Acute Myeloid Leukaemia and Myelodysplastic Syndrome .   The documentation in medical records and adverse event reports must include the date of diagnosis and the type of secondary malignancy (leukaemia/MDS, NHL, solid tumour).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomisation, during chemotherapy, and until end of follow up.  Each patient will be in follow up for  a period of at least 5 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Histologically proven classical Hodgkin lymphoma;
- First diagnosis, no previous treatment, 18 to 60 years of age;
- Stage IIB with large mediastinal mass and/or extranodal lesions, stage III or IV.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Composite lymphoma or nodular lymphocyte predominant Hodgkin lymphoma;
- Previous malignancy (exceptions: basalioma, carcinoma in situ of the cervic uteri, completely resected melanoma TNMpT1);
- Prior chemotherapy or radiotherapy;
- Concurrent disease which precludes protocol treatment;
- Pregnancy, lactation;
- Non-compliance.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/10/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/11/2025</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Cologne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Cologne University Hospital
50935 Koln
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Germany</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Millennium Pharmaceuticals</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Takeda Oncology
40 Landsdowne Street
Cambridge, Massachusetts
02139
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Ground Floor, 35 Elizabeth Street
North Richmond, VIC, 3121</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to examine whether new chemotherapy regimen, BrECADD is non-inferior to BEACOPP as first line treatment in advanced stage classical Hodgkin lymphoma.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above and have first histologically proven classical Hodgkin lymphoma at stage IIB with large mediastinal mass and/or extranodal lesions, stage III or IV.

Study details
Patients will be randomised in a 1:1 ratio to either 6 cycles of the escalated BEACOPP regimen (standard of care) or 6 cycles of the BrECADD regimen (experimental) . Treatment in both arms will involve intravenous infusions and oral tablets to be administered on specific days during the treatment cycle to deliver specific drugs in each treatment arm. Patients will receive treatment in 21 day cycles until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or withdrawal or consent. Patients will be followed up for a period of at least 5 years after chemotherapy completion to assess progression free survival.

It is hoped that this trial will determine if BrECADD is non-inferior to escalated BEACOPP as first line treatment in advanced stage classical Hodgkin lymphoma.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.allg.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South East Sydney Local Health District </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>G71, East Wing, Edmund Blackett Building
Prince of Wales Hospital
Cnr Avoca and High Streets
Randwick NSW 2031
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Hertzberg</name>
      <address>Department of Haematology
Prince of Wales Hospital
Barker St . 
Randwick, NSW, 2031
AUSTRALIA
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 9036</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mark.hertzberg@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Delaine Smith </name>
      <address>Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group 
Ground Floor 
35 Elizabeth St 
Richmond 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8373 9701 </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9429 8277</fax>
      <email>Delaine.Smith@allg.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Hertzberg </name>
      <address>Department of Haematology
Prince of Wales Hospital
Barker St
Randwick, NSW, 2031
AUSTRALIA
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 9036</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mark.hertzberg@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Delaine Smith </name>
      <address>Ground Floor 
35 Elizabeth St 
Richmond 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8373 9701 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>delaine.smith@allg.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>