<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368053">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000268549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of Smartphone applications in diagnosing and detecting melanoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For a patient with naevi, do smart phone applications when compared to diagnosis by gold standard histo-pathological report/dermatologist provide an effective way for individuals to self-detect melanoma.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1167-5675</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil 
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>melanoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Non melanoma skin cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Study of the efficacy of use of Dr Mole, Skinvision and Spotmole Plus smartphone applications in the self diagnosis of melanoma from images of naevi.  Photos of naevi will be taken by smartphones.  A dermatology consultation will determine if lesions are suspicious or benign.  For patients with suspicious lesions, photos will be taken prior to the traditional dermatological intervention involving excision of the lesion.  The smartphone photo's will be submitted to each of the smartphone applications for evaluation.  The smartphone application evaluations will then be compared to the histo-pathological report and dermatologist diagnosis for suspect lesions, and to the dermatologist diagnosis for benign lesions (as no histo-pathological diagnosis will be available for benign lesions).</interventions>
    <comparator>Histo-pathological report/Dermatologist diagnosis of naevi images</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Statistically significant results from analysis of outcomes of original image evaluations by the smartphone applications compared to gold standard histo-pathological reports/dermatologist diagnosis.  Overall sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value and negative predictive value for each application will be determined.  McNemar chi-square test will be used to compare the respective sensitivities of the various smartphone applications.  This is a composite primary outcome to determine the overall accuracy of the smartphone applications in detecting suspicious lesions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary timepoint is when the smartphone application evaluation of the smartphone naevi photo is compared to the gold standard histo-pathological report/dermatologist diagnosis of the same naevi</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Statistically significant results from analysis of outcomes of smartphone photo's taken from high quality printouts of original images (original smartphone photos of the actual naevi on the patient), with evaluations by the smartphone applications compared to gold standard histo-pathological report/dermatologist diagnosis. Overall sensitivity, specificity positive predictive value and negative predictive value for each application will be determined.  McNemar chi-square test will be used to compare the respective sensitivities of the various smartphone applications.  This is a composite secondary outcome to determine the overall accuracy of the smartphone applications for detecting suspicious lesions when using smartphone photos of high quality printouts of the original naevi photos (rather than the original naevi photos taken and used in Primary Outcome 1).</outcome>
      <timepoint>High quality print outs of the original naevi photo's will be made.  Smartphone photo's of these print outs will be taken and submitted to the smartphone applications for evaluation.  These secondary photo evaluations by the smartphone applications with be compared to the gold standard histo-pathological report/dermatologist diagnosis of the same naevi.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with suspected melanoma and/or clinically benign lesions</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No suspected melanoma or clinically benign lesions</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Each of the applications will be presented with each skin lesion. Each result will be determined as positive, negative or unevaluable. The percentage of images presented to each application that are evaluable will be described. For each photo, we will assign the app a score of correct if it identified a melanoma as such, and incorrect if a melanoma received a different or benign diagnosis, using the histo-pathological reports as the gold standard. For benign lesions, the clinical diagnosis by a board certified dermatologist will be used as the gold standard. Histology and clinical diagnosis are both best clinical practice in each respective case and hence there is no confounding effect. We will assign a score of correct to benign lesions which were identified as such by the apps, and incorrect if it was given a higher grade of suspicion. Statistical analysis of these results will be performed using commercially available software. Overall sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value (PPV) and negative predictive value (NPV) for each application will be determined for both real time imaging and photos taken later from printouts.
Within the study period we expect to be able to recruit 10 patients with a suspected melanoma and 20 patients with clinically benign lesions. Allowing for 10% of these lesions being unavailable for photographing due to exclusion criteria (lesions with uncertain histological diagnoses, Spitz nevi, pigmented spindle cell nevus of Reed and other uncommon or potentially ambiguous lesions), this will leave 9 melanomas and 18 benign lesions for evaluation. This estimated number of suitable lesions for evaluation will allow an estimation of sensitivity with a confidence interval of 95%. We will use McNemar chisquare test to compare the respective sensitivities of the various apps. All statistical significance will be accepted at p&lt;0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/03/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dermatology Research Centre, School of Medicine, University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Translational Research Institute (TRI)
37 Kent St,
Woolloongabba, QLD, 4102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dermatology Research Centre, School of Medicine, University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Translational Research Institute (TRI)
37 Kent St,
Woolloongabba, QLD, 4102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to determine whether the smartphone applications for skin screening are effective at providing an accurate diagnosis of melanoma.
Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above and have a suspected melanoma and/or clinically benign skin lesion.
Study details.
The accuracy of smartphone applications will be tested by taking photos of the skin lesions and comparing the smartphone applications evaluation against the histological gold standard diagnosis by a dermatologist.
If the study shows that these applications are accurate, this will allow greater acceptance of them for medical use.  If inaccurate, it will raise concerns about the need for regulation of these applications due to the health risk posed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Centres for Health Research
Lvl 7, Translational Research Institute,
37 Kent St,
Woolloongabba, QLD, 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/QPAH/473</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland Institutional Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Queensland
UQ Research and Innovation
Cumbrae-Stewart Building,
St Lucia, QLD, 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014001372</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>H. Peter Soyer</name>
      <address>Dermatology Research Centre
Level 5, Translational Research Institute
37 Kent St,
Woolloongabba, QLD, 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3443 8017</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.soyer@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Payne</name>
      <address>Dermatology Research Centre
Level 5, Translational Research Institute
37 Kent St,
Woolloongabba, QLD, 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3443 7397</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.payne@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Payne</name>
      <address>Dermatology Research Centre
Level 5, Translational Research Institute
37 Kent St,
Woolloongabba, QLD, 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3443 7397</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.payne@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Payne</name>
      <address>Dermatology Research Centre
Level 5, Translational Research Institute
37 Kent St,
Woolloongabba, QLD, 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3443 7397</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.payne@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>