<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362960">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000925842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Testing strategies to improve breathlessness and related symptoms in people with lung cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study of a multicomponent non-pharmacological intervention to reduce breathlessness and associated symptoms in people with lung cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1133-9671</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Lung cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Non small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Mesothelioma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention combines breathing re-training with individualised psychosocial support, delivered using evidence based psycho-educational strategies to improve breathlessness and additional intervention components which focus on reducing the impact of co-occurring symptoms on dyspnoea (cough, pain, fatigue, anorexia) in the form of a face-to-face instructional session of about 60 minutes delivered by experienced registered nurses, followed by weekly phone calls for 3 weeks. The instruction is supplemented by a range of resources to reinforce intervention delivery and promote self-management, including audio recordings, printed fact sheets, an individualised management plan, as well as communication and referral to a relevant health provider in the community (GP, Practice Nurse or Community/Domiciliary Nurse).</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients allocated to the control group will similarly receive a face-to-face instructional session on breathlessness management comprising of breathing retraining and psychosocial support of about 60 minutes delivered by experienced nurses, followed by weekly phone calls for 3 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome of this pilot study is to the feasibility of a multicomponent non-pharmacological intervention in improving cancer patients' ability to manage breathlessness and the related cluster of symptoms associated with breathlessness. Assessment of feasibility includes recruitment issues, likely attrition rates and acceptability of interventions (measured by dropout rates due to the nature of intervention during the study), which are essential for consideration in planning a larger clinical trial. It will also help determine the effect size for sample size estimation to adequately power a future larger clinical trial.</outcome>
      <timepoint>T1 (at recruitment), T2 (4 weeks post intervention), T3 (8 weeks post intervention).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance status assessed by the Australia-modified Karnofsky Performance Scale;</outcome>
      <timepoint>T1 (at recruitment), T2 (4 weeks post intervention), T3 (8 weeks post intervention).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Breathlessness severity, distress and impact - 5 items 11 point Numeric Rating Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>T1 (at recruitment), T2 (4 weeks post intervention), T3 (8 weeks post intervention).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety and depression assessed using the 14-item 4-point Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale;</outcome>
      <timepoint>T1 (at recruitment), T2 (4 weeks post intervention), T3 (8 weeks post intervention).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of co-occurring symptoms (cough, pain, fatigue, anorexia) assessed by the 7-item 11-point (0-10) Symptom  Assessment Scale;</outcome>
      <timepoint>T1 (at recruitment), T2 (4 weeks post intervention), T3 (8 weeks post intervention).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Use of non-pharmacological methods for managing breathlessness and co-occurring symptoms at 4 and 8 weeks; the scale includes two sub-scales: the first including items assessing use of strategies for improving breathing efficiency and effectiveness, and the second assessing use of psychosocial support strategies. For each item, patients report whether or not they have used the specific strategy in the past week and, if used, to rate on a four point scale from 'not at all' to 'very much' how useful the strategy was in reducing their breathlessness.</outcome>
      <timepoint>T1 (at recruitment), T2 (4 weeks post intervention), T3 (8 weeks post intervention).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosed with a primary or secondary lung cancer; life expectancy of at least 3 months; completed first line therapy;
have an average dyspnoea rating &gt; 2 on an 11 point numeric rating scale in the past week</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>&lt; 18 years; have an intellectual or mental impairment; primary language other than English</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potentially eligible patients will be first approached by Clinical staff and asked if they would like to participate in the study. If patients agree, the research nurses will then approach the patients and provide them with an information sheet explaining the study. Patients will be asked for permission to obtain relevant clinical and demographic information from their records for use only in this study. Consent for access to this information is also included in the Information Sheets and Consent Forms. Patients will be allowed as much time as necessary to consider their involvement in the study, and if they agree to participate, written consent will be obtained. Participants will have the opportunity to ask questions before completing the consent form.

Using a computer generated table of random sequence, all recruited patients will be allocated randomly within each study site to one of two conditions (intervention/control). After informed consent is obtained, a central project manager randomly allocates the patient to intervention or control groups. Staff involved in baseline and follow up assessments are different to those delivering the interventions.</concealment>
    <sequence>simple randomisation by using a computer generated table by SPSS</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The research staff involved in pre and post intervetion assessments will not be informed of participant allocation</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Nursing, Queensland University of Technology, Victoria Park Rd, Kelvin Grove, QLD 4059</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland University of Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Nursing, Queensland University of Technology, Victoria Park Rd, Kelvin Grove, QLD 4059</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Prince Charles Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rode Rd, Chermside, QLD 4032</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>199 Ipswich Rd, Woolloongabba, QLD 4102</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to test the feasibility and effectiveness of a multi-component non-pharmacological intervention in improving breathlessness management for lung cancer patients. Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above, and have been diagnosed with a primary or secondary lung cancer with a life expectancy of at least 3 months. You should have completed first line therapy, and have an average breathlessness rating of &gt;2 on an 11 point scale in the past week. Trial details Participants in this trial will be randomly (by chance) allocated to one of two groups. Participants in one group will receive a multi-component intervention that incorporates a range of strategies to manage breathlessness and related symptoms (e.g. breathing retraining, psychosocial support and management of other co-occurring symptoms) at one face-to-face instructional session of about 60 minutes, followed up by weekly calls to reinforce the interventions for 3 weeks. It will be delivered by experienced registered nurses trained in these techniques who will facilitate follow-up with relevant primary care/community supports. Participants in the other group will receive standard non-pharmacological interventions to manage breathlessness. Participants will be assessed at recruitment and at 4 weeks and 8 weeks post treatment in order to determine the feasibility and efficacy of the intervention in improving breathlessness, anxiety, depression and co-occurring symptoms (cough, pain fatigue, anorexia).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>199 Ipswich Rd, Woolloongabba, QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/09/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Patsy Yates</name>
      <address>School of Nursing, Queensland University of Technology Victoria Park Road Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3138 3835</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.yates@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Patsy Yates</name>
      <address>School of Nursing, Queensland University of Technology Victoria Park Road Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3138 3835</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.yates@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Isabella Zhao</name>
      <address>60 Musk Ave, Kelvin Grove, QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 6122</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>isabella.zhao@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>