<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362741">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000759897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study of Focal Ablative Stereotactic Radiosurgery for Cancers of the Kidney or Isolated Adrenal Metastases.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study of the feasibility of performing Focal Ablative Stereotactic Radiosurgery for Cancers of the Kidney or Isolated Adrenal Metastases.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1132-5574</utrn>
    <trialacronym>FASTRACK</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Primary Renal Cell Carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Metastatic non-small cell carcinoma to the adrenal gland</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>For lesions less than 5cm - Image guided single fraction radiosurgery to26Gy prescribed to covering isodose. This is a single session of radiotherapy taking approximately 1 hour.
For lesions greater than or equal to 5cm - Image guided fractionated Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy (SBRT) to 45Gy in 3 fractions prescribed to covering isodose. This is 3 sessions of radiotherapy, delivered at least 48 hours apart, taking approximately 1 hour per session.
Prior to radiotherapy commencing, both treatment groups require a planning visit which will last approximately 1 hour, as well as a further 'mock-up' visit which will last approximately 45 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of patients who complete prescribed treatment. This is defined as patients who successfully receive the treatment plan as prescribed, achieving all nominated dose constraints, and are able to tolerate the treatment(s).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Toxicity of SBRT in study patients measured using CTCAE V4.0
Specific toxicities will include, but are not limited to:
-Gastrointestinal (nausea, vomiting, diarrhoea, acute ulceration)
-Pulmonary (atelectasis, cough, dyspnoea, hypoxia, pleural effusion, fibrosis). 
-Skin/chest wall (radiation dermatitis, rib fracture) 
-Kidney (acute renal dysfunction)
Freedom from severe toxicity will be reported and defined as: time from treatment delivery until first recorded grade 4, or 5 toxicity as measured by CTCAE v 4.0</outcome>
      <timepoint>Between 2-4 weeks after radiotherapy and 3  monthly for 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy of stereotactic radiosurgery 
Effective SBRT is defined as a treatment which results in local control at 1 year after treatment. Local control is defined as lack of progression of the target lesion as measured by RECIST criteria.  RECIST criteria are an CT evaluation of change in tumour size.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year after treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of using Diffusion weighted-MRI for Response Assessment: Feasibility will be measured by the quality of image of the Diffusion weighted-MRI scan recorded by the investigating radiologists.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Baseline, 14 days (+/-3 days) and at the definitive respose assessment (70 days (+/- 10 days)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Age &gt; 18 years old 
-All patients must have radiological diagnosis or biopsy confirmed diagnosis of either:
(a) Cohort 1: renal cell carcinoma with a single lesion within kidney, or with primary kidney tumour intact and no more than 5 documented metastases,  or
(b) Cohort 2: solitary adrenal metastases with with primary disease controlled
-ECOG performance of 0-2 inclusive. 
-Either medically inoperable, technically high risk for surgery or decline surgery.
-Informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Cytotoxic chemotherapy within 3 weeks of commencement of treatment, or concurrently with treatment. Targeted agents (such as sunitinib) are allowable.
-Any patient who is currently pregnant or breastfeeding.
-Previous high-dose radiotherapy to upper abdomen</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>To register a patient onto the trial, an adequately qualified and authorized member of the research team at the trial site must complete the registration and eligibility Case Report Forms (CRFs) and forward them to the trials coordinator at the Peter MacCallum Centre Department of Radiation Oncology.
Prior to patient enrolment, the investigator should ensure that all of the following requirements are met:
*The patient meets all inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion criteria should apply. 
*The patient has signed and dated the consent form
*All pre-treatment investigations and assessments have been performed.
*The eligibility checklist has been completed, signed and dated.
The Trial Coordinator will verify the completeness of the eligibility checklist upon receipt of the document and follow up with the participating investigator in the event of a discrepancy.</concealment>
    <sequence>Non-randomised</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>FASTRACK is a 2 -cohort, non-randomised prospective feasibility study.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Shankar Siva</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place 
East Melbourne
Vic 8006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>CASS Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 111 Collins Street
Melbourne 
Victoria 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Stereotactic body radiotherapy (SBRT) is an new form of cancer treatment involving highly precise radiotherapy. SBRT appears to be effective in controlling cancer in other sites in the body, including the lung and the liver. We aim to test the ability of this new technique to control cancers in the kidney. This is the first step of the research, and is a pilot study. 
Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged greater than 18 years and have a radiological diagnosis or biopsy confirmed diagnosis of either renal cell carcinoma or solitary adrenal metastases. Trial Details If you participate in this study, you will have either a single session of stereotactic body radiotherapy (SBRT) or three sessions of SBRT, depending on how big your cancer is. In order to deliver this treatment, you will need to attend a planning session where your body measurements are taken in the position that you will be lying in for your radiotherapy. This visit takes approximately one hour. Once the radiotherapy treatment has been planned, a further mock-up visit is required to ensure that the radiotherapy plan can be physically delivered when it comes to the time of treatment. This session will take approximately 45 minutes. When the treatment starts, the total time required to deliver the treatment will be one hour. In addition to the visits required to plan and deliver the radiotherapy, blood samples will be taken as part of this research. These will be taken at the same time as blood is collected to assess your kidney function (which would be standard care). Therefore will not require any additional blood collection visits than would be routinely performed to treat your cancer. Both the kidney function blood sample (standard of care) and the research related blood sample will be taken a total of 3 times; once before treatment, two weeks after treatment, and approximately 70 days to 3 months after treatment. Follow-up will involve a visit at approximately 2.5 to 3 months, and then at 6 months, 9 months, and 12 months from treatment. If you have a primary kidney cancer (renal cell carcinoma), then in addition to the steps outlined above you will have a research related Diffusion weighted-MRI scan performed a total of three times; once before treatment, two weeks after treatment, and approximately 70 days to 3 months after treatment. The Diffusion weighted-MRI scan is similar to a standard MRI scan, but is taken over a longer period of time. Each Diffusion weighted-MRI scan takes approximately 30 minutes. For those patients with adequate kidney function, you will also have a contrast injection at the time of the MRI, which will add an additional 10 minutes to the scan time. The MRI allows us to examine the blood flow into kidneys and the cancer. 
To assess the function of the kidney after the SBRT treatment, a positron emission tomography (PET) scan will be taken at approximately the same timepoints as the perfusion scans; once before treatment, two weeks after treatment, and approximately 70 days to 3 months after treatment. This will involve injection of a radioactive tracer and a subsequent scan which will take approximately 30 minutes to capture.  This will require you attending the PET Centre for a period of 2 or 3 hours. Participation in this study will involve no extra cost due to either having these scans or the treatment. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
10 St Andrews Place
East Melbourne 
Vic 8006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/04/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>11_106</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Shankar Siva</name>
      <address>Department of Radiation Oncology
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place 
East Melbourne 
Vic 8006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96561111</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9656 1424</fax>
      <email>shankar.siva@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Shankar Siva</name>
      <address>Department of Radiation Oncology
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place 
East Melbourne 
Vic 8006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96561111</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9656 1424</fax>
      <email>shankar.siva@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lisa Selbie</name>
      <address>Department of Radiation Oncology
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place 
East Melbourne 
Vic 8006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96561760</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9656 1424</fax>
      <email>lisa.selbie@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Shankar Siva </name>
      <address>Department of Radiation Oncology Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre St Andrews Place East Melbourne Vic 8006 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 96561111 </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9656 1424  </fax>
      <email>shankar.siva@petermac.org </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>