<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368755">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000881538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Safety Study of Oraxol (HM30181 + oral paclitaxel) in Cancer Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Safety Study of Oraxol (HM30181 + oral paclitaxel) in Cancer Patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1170-6641</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>KX-ORAX-003</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cancer requiring treatment with IV paclitaxel</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Approximately 40 participants will be treated with a daily dosage regimen of Oraxol 205 mg/m2 on Days 1, 2, and 3 every week (i.e. a total Oraxol dose of 615mg/m2 over three days of dosing), or as adjusted in KX-ORAX-002 to achieve bioequivalence to IV paclitaxel 80 mg/m2 infused over 1 hour. Oraxol will be administered once daily for 3 consecutive days on a weekly basis as 15 mg oral HM30181AK-US tablet plus oral paclitaxel capsules. Oral paclitaxel is administered one hour after the HM30181AK-US tablet. Participants must fast for 8 hours prior to administration of Oraxol and for four hours afterwards. Participants will be asked to return their daily Oraxol dose cards to check for compliance. Doses during the PK sampling week (Week 4 or later) will be administered at the study site.
Participants may enter this study after completion of a previous study involving Oraxol (KX-ORAX-002). The study procedures are the same regardless of whether a participant was in the previous study or not; however some data (e.g. medical history) collected for the previous study would not need to be collected again for this study. The dose and administartion of Oraxol to be used in this study will be the same as the dose in the previous study that is confirmed to be equivalent to the administration of IV Paclitaxel at 80mg/m2.
Participants may continue to receive treatment in this study until any of the following occur: death, successful completion of the course of treatment prescribed by the investigator, progression of disease, AEs not associated with progression of disease, withdrawal of consent, termination of the study by the Sponsor, or other specified reason.  
If needed at any time, treatment may be delayed for up to 2 weeks to allow a participant to recover to less than or equal to Grade 1 Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) toxicity from prior chemotherapy.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability as assessed by the incidence of adverse events. Treatment-emergent AEs (TEAEs) are defined as those AEs with an onset after dosing and those pre-existing AEs that worsen during the study.  
AEs will include those reported by participants as well as those observed by the clinical team, or clinically significant changes in lab tests, vital signs and ECGs. Possible AEs may include gastrointestinal effects and abdominal pain but as this is an early phase clinical trial and the likely AE profile is not yet known.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From screening until final visit (within 28 days after the last dose of study drug was taken, and preferably before the participant receives any additional chemotherapy).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability as assessed by the results of routine laboratory safety tests (i.e. haematology, biochemistry and urinalysis).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At screening/baseline, weekly (within 72hrs prior to the start of dosing each week), and at the final visit (within 28 days after the last dose of study drug was taken, and preferably before the participant receives any additional chemotherapy).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability as assessed by the severity and relationship of adverse events. Treatment-emergent AEs (TEAEs) are defined as those AEs with an onset after dosing and those pre-existing AEs that worsen during the study.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>From screening until final visit (within 28 days after the last dose of study drug was taken, and preferably before the participant receives any additional chemotherapy).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oraxol PK data from this study will be compared with Oraxol PK data from study KX-ORAX-002. The PK parameters to be used are AUCs, clearance, Cmax and Tmax.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From pre-dose until 8 hours post-dose on Day 3. This time period is shorter to the time period used in the KX-ORAX-002 study, where PK blood samples are being collected until 144 hours post-dose on Day 3. PK samples will be collected during dosing for Week 4; or may be done during a later dosing week at the investigator's discretion and/or at the participant's convenience. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety as assessed by the use of concomitant medications, as recorded in their clinical notes and reported by participant's during their weekly contact with the study site.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From screening until final visit (within 28 days after the last dose of study drug was taken, and preferably before the participant receives any additional chemotherapy).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety as assessed by vital signs. Vital signs include pulse rate, systolic/diastolic blood pressure, respiratory rate, and temperature.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Vital signs are measured at Screening/Baseline, before dosing on Day 1 of every 3rd week (Weeks 1, 4, 7, 10, etc), and before dosing during the inpatient dosing week and at the Final Visit (within 28 days after the last dose of study drug was taken, and preferably before the participant receives any additional chemotherapy).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety as assessed by Physical Examinations. A complete PE will include an assessment of HEENT, gastrointestinal, cardiovascular, respiratory, integumentary, muscular- skeleton, neurological and endocrine/metabolism systems.  Complete PEs will be performed at Screening/Baseline and at the Final Visit.  All other physical examinations do not require complete examinations but will be targeted to the signs and symptoms related to Adverse Event Reporting.  Additional examinations will be performed as clinically indicated to assess adverse events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At screening/baseline, Weeks 1, 4, 7 10 etc, and at the final visit (within 28 days after the last dose of study drug was taken, and preferably before the participant receives any additional chemotherapy). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety as assessed by Eastern Co-operative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At screening/baseline, Weeks 1, 4, 7 10 etc, and at the final visit (within 28 days after the last dose of study drug was taken, and preferably before the participant receives any additional chemotherapy). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety, as assessed by ECGs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At screening/baseline, Weeks 1, 4, 7 10 etc, and at the final visit (within 28 days after the last dose of study drug was taken, and preferably before the participant receives any additional chemotherapy). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible participants are cancer patients for whom treatment with IV paclitaxel at 80 mg/m2 has been recommended by their oncologist, either as monotherapy or in combination with other agents. 
At Screening/Baseline, they must have 
Adequate hematologic status: 
- Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) greater than/equal to 1.0 x 10^9/L
- Platelet count greater than/equal to 100 x 10^9/L
- Hemoglobin greater than/equal to 90g/L
Adequate liver function as demonstrated by: 
- Total bilirubin of less than/equal to 20 micromol/L or less than/equal to 30 µmol/L for participants with liver metastasis
Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) less than/equal to 3 x upper limit of normal (ULN) or less than/equal to 5 x ULN if liver metastasis is present
Alkaline phosphatase (ALP) less than/equal to 3 x ULN or less than/equal to 5 x ULN if liver or bone metastasis is present
Adequate renal function as demonstrated by serum creatinine less than/equal to 177 micromol/L or creatinine clearance greater than 50 mL/min as calculated by the Cockroft and Gault formula.
Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 1; and life expectancy of at least 3 months.
They must be willing to fast for 8 hours before and 4 hours after Oraxol administration; willing to abstain from alcohol consumption for 3 days before the first dose of Oraxol through the completion of protocol specified PK sampling for that treatment week; willing to refrain from caffeine
consumption for 12 hours before the first dose of Oraxol through the completion of protocol-specified PK sampling for that treatment week. Women must be postmenopausal (more than 12 months without menses) or surgically sterile (ie, by hysterectomy and/or bilateral oophorectomy) or, if sexually active, must be using effective contraception (ie, oral contraceptives, intrauterine device, double barrier method of condom and spermicide) and agree to continue use of contraception for the duration of their participation in the study. Women of childbearing potential must agree to use contraception for 30 days after their last dose of study drug. Sexually active male participants must use a barrier method of contraception during the study and agree to continue the use of male contraception for at least 30 days after the last dose of study drug.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Study participants must not be:
Currently taking a prohibited concomitant medication; 
- a medication known to be a P-gp inhibitor (e.g., verapamil) or inducer (rifampin) within 7 days prior to the first dose of Oraxol
- an oral medication with a narrow therapeutic index known to be a P-gp substrate (eg, digoxin or dabigatran) within 24 hours prior to the first dose of Oraxol 
- a medication known to be a strong CYP3A4 strong inhibitor (e.g., ketoconazole) or strong inducer (e.g., rifampin or St. John's Wort) within 14 days prior to the first dose of Oraxol 
- a medication known to be a strong inhibitor (e.g., gemfibrozil) or inducers (e.g., rifampin) of CYP2C8 within 14 days prior to the first dose of Oraxol 

Other exclusions are: unresolved toxicity from prior chemotherapy; 
have received investigational agents within 14 days or 5 half-lives prior to the first study dosing day, whichever is longer. Other exclusions are women of childbearing potential who are pregnant or breast feeding; uncontrolled intercurrent illness; major surgery to the upper gastrointestinal tract, or have a history of GI disease or other medical condition that, in the opinion of the Investigator may interfere with oral drug absorption; known history of allergy to paclitaxel (Participants whose allergy was due to the IV solvent (such as Cremophor [Registered Trademark]) and not paclitaxel will be eligible for this study); any other condition which the investigator believes would make a subjects participation in the study not acceptable.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is an open label safety study (an extension of KX-ORAX-002 and for other eligible patients after the dose of Oraxol has been confirmed in KX-ORAX-002) and all participants are treated with Oraxol.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Primary endpoints: Treatment-emergent AEs (TEAEs) are defined as those AEs with an onset after dosing and those pre-existing AEs that worsen during the study.  Verbatim terms on the CRFs will be mapped to preferred terms (PTs) and system organ classes (SOCs) using the Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities (MedDRA; version 16.1 or later).  The CTCAE criteria (version 4.03 or later) will be used to grade the severity of the AEs.  Participant incidence of AEs will be displayed by SOC.  Adverse events will also be summarized by severity and relationship to the study drug.  Participant incidence of SAEs will also be displayed. Laboratory parameters will be summarized using descriptive statistics at baseline and at each subsequent time-point.  Changes from baseline will also be summarized.  In addition, shift tables (ie, low-normal-high at baseline versus low-normal-high at follow-up in a 3-by-3 contingency table) will be provided to assess changes in laboratory values from baseline to follow-up. 
Secondary endpoints: Oraxol PK data from this study will be compared with Oraxol PK data from study KX-ORAX-002.
Using the PK samples collected at designated timepoints, a population PK analysis will be explored and then used to estimate individual AUCs or clearance (CL) of paclitaxel.  The effect of patient factors on paclitaxel PK will be explored that may explain interpatient variability in PK parameters.  Both inter- and intra-patient variability in paclitaxel AUC will also be assessed.  Paclitaxel AUC, as well as Cmax, will then be tested for association changes with toxicity endpoints, such as neutropenia or incidence of neuropathy.  If an observable trend exists among changes in any of these AEs, a PK/PD model will be developed to evaluate the exposure-response relationship between the time course of paclitaxel plasma exposure (eg, AUC, Cmax) in relation to changes in neutropenia and/or neuropathy.  Demographic and clinical data (ie, ethnicity, age, BSA, ECOG status, etc.) will be utilized to assess inter-patient variability in the model.
The results of other safety assessments (concomitant medications, vital signs, physical examinations, ECGs, and ECOG performance status) will also be evaluated.
Safety data will be summarized using descriptive statistics (eg, n, mean, SD, median, minimum, maximum for continuous variables; n [%] for categorical variables).  
A sample size of 40 patients is based on practical considerations, participant safety, and the goal of assessing the safety and tolerability of Oraxol. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/05/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Kinex Pharmaceuticals Inc</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>20 Commerce Drive
Cranford
New Jersey 07016</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Kinex Pharmaceuticals Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Commerce Drive
Cranford
New Jersey 07016</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Zenith Technology Corporation Ltd.</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>156 Frederick Street
Dunedin 9016</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Oraxol is a combination of an oral tablet, HM30181 methanesulfonate, and capsules that contain paclitaxel.  HM30181 is a drug that helps the body absorb paclitaxel, a drug used to treat cancer. Initially this study is intended as an extension study of KX-Orax-002 pharmacokinetic study for patients who wish to continue Oraxol treatment and who are eligible to participate. Once the dose of Oraxol has been confirmed in the KX-ORAX-002 study, then enrolment of patients who have not participated in the KX-ORAX-002 study will be allowed.  The purpose of this study is to check the safety and tolerability of Oraxol when it is administered on a weekly basis and to confirm that the blood levels of paclitaxel after several doses of Oraxol are similar to the levels expected. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>C/- Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/STH/88</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/06/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christopher Jackson</name>
      <address>Department of Oncology
Dunedin Hospital 
Southern District Health Board
201 Great King Street 
Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+64 3 474 0999 ext 9698</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Christopher.jackson@southerndhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Linda Folland</name>
      <address>Zenith Technology Corporation, Ltd. 156 Frederick Street Dunedin 9016</address>
      <phone>+643 477 9669</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Linda.Folland@Zenithtechnology.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>E. Douglas Kramer</name>
      <address>Kinex Pharmaceuticals, Inc. 20 Commerce Drive Cranford New Jersey
07016</address>
      <phone>+1 908-272-0628</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dkramer@kinexpharma.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Lockhart</name>
      <address>Pharmaceuticol Ltd
51 Woodside Road, 
Mt Eden, 
Auckland 1024</address>
      <phone>+649 623 6639</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michellelockhart@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>