<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82818">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/05/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/05/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000254392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Aprepitant for Germ Cell Chemotherapy:  A phase II multi-centre trial of a seven day Aprepitant schedule for the prevention of chemotherapy induced nausea and vomiting in patients receiving five day cisplatin-based chemotherapy for germ cell tumours.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Aprepitant for Germ Cell Chemotherapy:  A phase II multi-centre trial of a seven day Aprepitant schedule for the prevention of chemotherapy induced nausea and vomiting in patients receiving five day cisplatin-based chemotherapy for germ cell tumours.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Aprepitant for germ cell chemotherapy</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ANZUP 0801</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting for patients being treated for germ cell tumours.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Anti-emetic regimen during five day Cisplatin-based chemotherapy Aprepitant 125mg Per Oral (PO) day 1 and 80mg Per Oral (PO) days 2 to 7. 5HT3 Antagonist days 1 to 5 Dexamethasone days 1 to 8.</interventions>
    <comparator>Historical control group based on the rate of emesis in the good prognosis germ cell trial conducted by the Australian and New Zealand Germ Cell Group (ANZGCTG) between 1994-2000 (Reference: Toner GC, Stockler MR, Boyer MJ, et al. Comparison of two standard chemotherapy regimens for good-prognosis germ-cell tumours: a randomised trial. Australian and New Zealand Germ Cell Trial Group. Lancet 2001;357(9258):739-45).</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary endpoint of the study is the proportion of patients with no emesis (vomoting or dry retching) during day 1 (1st 24 hour period) and days 1 to 8 (7 X 24 hour periods) of cycle 1 chemotherapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At day 8 after first day of chemotherapy.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with no emesis (vomiting or dry retching) during day 1 to 8 of subsequent cycles of chemotherapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During day 1 to 8 of subsequent cycles of chemotherapy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients achieving the following outcomes during day 1 and day 1 to 8 of cycle 1 and subsequent cycles of chemotherapy.
i) No significant nausea (&lt;2 out of 10)
ii) No use of rescue medication
iii) Complete response (no emesis and no use of rescue medication)</outcome>
      <timepoint>During day 1 to 8 of subsequent cycles of chemotherapy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of emetic episodes on each of days 1 to 8 of chemotherapy of cycle 1 and subsequent cycles of chemotherapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from day 1 to 8 of subsequent chemotherapy of cycle 1 and subsequent cycles of chemotherapy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance with study medication.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily from day 1 to 8 of subsequent chemotherapy of cycle 1 and subsequent cycles of chemotherapy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patient is 18 years or older.
2. Patient has a histologically or cytologically confirmed germ cell tumour.
3.  Patient is scheduled to recieve a 5 day Cisplatin (20mg per metre square) based chemotherapy. Ie: Any of: BEP (Cisplatin, Etoposide, Bleomycin: Indiana Regimen); Accelerated BEP (ANZGCTG Regimen); VIP (Cisplatin, Ifosfamide, Etoposide); VeIP (Cisplatin, Ifosamide, Vinblastine); or TIP (Paclitaxel, Ifosfamide, Cisplatin).
4. Patient has a predicted life expectancy of 4 months or more.
5. Patient has an ECOG performance score of 3 or less.
6. Patient is able to read, understand and complete patient diary.
7. Patient is able to understand study procedures and agrees to participate in the study by giving written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patient has vomited in the 24 hours prior to Treatment Day 1.
2. Previous chemotherapy.
3. Patient has a symptomatic metastatic CNS malignancy.
4. Patient has recieved radiation therapy to the abdomen or pelvis in the week prior to treatment, or will recieve radiation therapy to the abdomen or pelvis during days one to eight of treatment.
5. Patient has an active infection (e.g. pneumonia) or any uncontrolled disease except for malignancy (e.g diabetic ketoacidosis, gastrointestinal obstruction) which, in the opinion of the investigator, might confound the results of the study or pose unwarranted risk.
6. Patient has a history of any illness that, in the opinion of the investigator, might confound the results of the study or pose unwarranted risk.
7. Patient has current evidence of alcohol abuse as determined by the investigator.
8. Patient is mentally incapacitated or has a significant emotional or psychiatric disorder that, in the opinion of the investigator, precludes study entry.
9. Patient has a history of hypersensitivity to Aprepitant, Ondansetron, or Dexamethasone.
10. Patient has previously participated in a study with Aprepitant.
11. Patient has taken any of the following CYP3A4 substrates during the 7 days of treatment day 1: Terfenadine, Cisapride, Astemizole, or Pimozide.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Nonrandomized trial</allocation>
    <concealment>N/A - No allocation concealment. This is a single-arm nonrandomised trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A - Not randomised.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC,QLD,SA,TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2050, 3690, 7000, 5000, 5042, 3002, 4102, 2137, 3065</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre Level 6 Medical Foundation Building 92-94 Parramatta Road Camperdown NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian and New Zealand Urogenital and Prostate Cancer Trials Group (ANZUP) formerly the Australian and New Zealand Germ Cell Trials Group (ANZGCTG) and Australasian Prostate and Urogenital Cancer Trials Group (APUG)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>NHMRC Clinical Trial Centre Level 6 Medical Foundation Building 92-94 Parramatta Road Camperdown NSW 2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>MSD Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4, 66 Waterloo Road
North Ryde  NSW  2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a trial of the drug Aprepitant for the prevention of chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting in people being treated for germ cell tumours with cisplatin-based chemotherapy. 

Who is it for? 
You can join this study if you: - have germ cell cancer that is at early or local, locally advanced or locally recurrent stage - are being treated with cisplatin-based chemotherapy. 

Trial details 
All participants receive anti-emetic (anti-vomiting or dry retching) treatment with Aprepitant for seven days while they are receiving their first cycle of Cisplatin-based chemotherapy. The study will measure the number of participants with no emesis during day 1 to 8 of chemotherapy. Chemotherapy-induced nausea and vomiting is an unpleasant side effect of chemotherapy for germ cell tumours, and this study hopes to minimise this.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.anzup.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>D B Thomson, P  S Grimison, M D Chatfield,  M R Stockler, G C Toner, V Gebski, R A Harrup, C Underhill, G Kichenadasse,  N Singhal, A L Boland, A McDonald, I  N Olver, Australian and New Zealand Urogenital and Prostate Cancer Trials Group. hase II trial of aprepitant on days 1 to 7 for patients with germ cell tumors having cisplatin on days 1 to 5 [Abstract]  J Clin Oncol 29: 2011 (suppl; abstr e19577), ASCO Annual Meeting, Chicago, USA, June 2011 (Presented)

Thomson D B, Grimison P S, Chatfield M, Stockler M R, Toner, G C, Gebski, V., Harrup R A, Boland A L, McDonald A, Olver I, Australian and New Zealand Urogenital and Prostate Cancer Trials Group. Phase 2 trial of aprepitant on days 1-7 for patients with germ cell tumours having cisplatin on days 1-5[Poster] Medical Oncology Group of Australia  Annual Scientific Meeting, Adelaide , Australia, 10-12 August 2011 (Presented)

Olver I, Grimison P S, Chatfield M, Stockler M R, Toner, G C, Gebski, V., Harrup R A, Underhill C, Kichenadasse K, Singhal N, Boland A L, McDonald A, Thomson DB, Australian and New Zealand Urogenital and Prostate Cancer Trials Group. Phase 2 trial of aprepitant on days 1-7 for patients with germ cell tumours having cisplatin on days 1-5[ Poster] Multinational Association of Supportive Care in Cancer (MASCC) Symposeum, Athens, Greece, 23-25 June 2011 (Presented)</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cancer Institute NSW Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Cancer Institute NSW Australian Technology Park
Level 9, 8 Central Avenue
EVELEIGH NSW 2015</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/07/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008C/06/056</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Smorgon Family Building
St Andrew's Place
East Melbourne VIC 8006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/02/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/64</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/10/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>New ethics HREC. Please modify.</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/09/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincent's Hospital
Melbourne VIC 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/01/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>New ethics HREC. Please modify.</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Flinders Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flinders Medical Centre
Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>307/08</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/10/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>081015</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (Tasmania) Network</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services
University of Tasmania
Churchill Avenue
Sandy Bay TAS 7005</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/08/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H10627</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)
Princess Alexandra Hospital 
199 Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/02/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008/197</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>ANZUP Associate Oncology Program Manager</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>(02) 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax>(02) 9562 5094</fax>
      <email>anzup@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>ANZUP Associate Oncology Program Manager</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>(02) 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax>(02) 9562 5094</fax>
      <email>anzup@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>ANZUP Associate Oncology Program Manager</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>(02) 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax>(02) 9562 5094</fax>
      <email>anzup@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>