<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335253">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/03/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/03/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000217000</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of Different Types of Surgery in Treating Patients With Stage IA Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study of patient with small peripheral resectable non-small cell lung cancer (&lt;2cm) to determine whether sublobar resection results in the same disease-free survival as lobectomy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>NCT00499330
Issued by the US National Institutes of Health</utrn>
    <trialacronym>WORLD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>CALGB-140503
Issued by Cancer and Leukemia Group B</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>ECOG-40503
Issued by Eastern Co-operative Oncology Group</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Lung Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Non small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Sublobar resection (removal of less than one lobe of lung) consists of either segmentectomy or wedge resection of lung.
Segmentectomy refers to identifying and cutting the specific blood supply and airway to the particular segment of the lobe of lung containing the lung cancer.  The procedure takes 2-3 hours.
Wedge resection refers to calculating a margin of normal tissue that allows full removal of the cancer, then removing that from the lobe of the lung using a cutting stapler. The procedure takes about one hour.
Sublobar resection can be done through a thoracotomy (large cut on the side of the chest) or with Video-Assisted Thoracic Surgery (VATS), which uses small incisions and a telescope to achieve the same internal operation.</interventions>
    <comparator>Lobectomy refers to identifying and cutting the specific blood supply and airway to the lobe of lung containing the lung cancer.  The procedure takes 2-3 hours.
Lobectomy can be done through a thoracotomy (large cut on the side of the chest) or with Video-Assisted Thoracic Surgery (VATS), which uses small incisions and a telescope to achieve the same internal operation.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease-free survival as assessed by chest X-rays and computed tomography (CT Scan) of the chest. Additional investigations such as positron emission tomography (PET scan) and biopsies will also be used if clinically indicated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quarterly up to two years then annually up to five years post-surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival as determined by physical examination</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quarterly up to two years then annually up to five years post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of loco-regional and systemic recurrence as assessed by chest X-rays and computed tomography (CT Scan) of the chest. Additional investigations such as positron emission tomography (PET scan) and biopsies will also be used if clinically indicated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quarterly up to two years then annually up to five years post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pulmonary function as measured by expiratory flow rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 1 month prior to surgery and at 6 months post-surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Suspected or proven non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC), meeting both preoperative and intraoperative criteria:
Preoperative criteria - Peripheral lung nodule = 2 cm by computed tomography (CT scan) AND Center of the tumor must be located in the outer third of the lung in either the transverse, coronal, or sagittal plan AND Tumor location must be suitable for either lobar or sublobar resection (wedge resection or segmentectomy) AND No pure ground opacities or pathologically confirmed N1 or N2 disease
Intraoperative criteria - Histologically confirmed NSCLC AND Confirmation of N0 status by frozen section examination of nodal levels 4, 7, and 10 on the right side and 5, 6, 7, and 10 on the left side (Levels 4 and 7 nodes may be sampled up to 6 weeks preoperatively by mediastinoscopy, endobronchial ultrasound (EBUS), and/or endoscopic ultrasound (EUS), or at the time of thoracotomy or video-assisted thoracoscopic surgery (VATS) exploration)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Evidence of locally advanced or metastatic disease
Prior chemotherapy or radiotherapy for this malignancy
Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance status &gt; 2
Any other malignancy within the past 3 years except for non-melanoma skin cancer, superficial bladder cancer, or carcinoma in situ of the cervix</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Concealed allocation until intra-operative randomization</concealment>
    <sequence>Centralized computer generated sequence via Duke University Durham, North Carolina, USA</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/02/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>15</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>3/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The National Cancer Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Building 31, Room 11A-16
9000 Rockville Pike
Bethesda, MD 20892</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>American College of Surgeons Oncology Group (ACOSOG)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Duke University
Durham, NC 27705</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Cancer Trials Support Unit of the National Cancer Institute (CTSU)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Cancer Trials Support Unit
The National Cancer Institute
Building 31, Room 11A-16
9000 Rockville Pike
Bethesda, MD 20892</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Cancer and Leukemia Group B (CALGB)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>CALGB Central Office
230 West Monroe, Suite 2050
Chicago, IL 60606</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Lobectomy (or removal of one of the lobes of the lung) is the standard operation for lung cancer that is amenable to surgery.  For patients with insufficient breathing reserve, a sublobar resection (segmentectomy or wedge resection) can be offered as it involves the removal of much less lung.  The question that surgeons do not know the answer to is how much lung needs to be removed to completely clear around a small lung cancer at the edge of the lung.  It may or may not require the removal of the whole lobe, and this study will determine whether a sublobar resection is as good at controlling the cancer as a lobectomy.  This is similar to studies in breast cancer that showed that the whole breast did bot have to be removed to control a small breast cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.cancer.gov/search/ViewClinicalTrials.aspx?cdrid=555324&amp;version=patient</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil results yet</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC-A)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research &amp; Grants Unit
41 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy VIC 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/02/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09/0137</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin M Wright</name>
      <address>Director of Surgical Oncology
St Vincent's Hospital
5th Floor
55 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9419 2477</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9417 1694</fax>
      <email>lung_surgeon@mac.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ms Jane Mack</name>
      <address>Cardiothoracic Research Office
4th Floor
Inpatient Services Building
St Vincent's Hospital
41 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9288 4615</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9288 4616</fax>
      <email>Jane.Mack@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ms Jane Mack</name>
      <address>Cardiothoracic Research Office
4th Floor
Inpatient Services Building
St Vincent's Hospital
41 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9288 4615</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9288 4616</fax>
      <email>Jane.Mack@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin M Wright</name>
      <address>Director of Surgical Oncology
St Vincent's Hospital
55 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94192477</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94171694</fax>
      <email>gavin.wright@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>