<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372928">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000741381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Nivolumab in renal transplant recipients with cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Nivolumab in renal transplant recipients with poor prognosis cancers - a safety study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Protocol CA209-993ISR</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Renal Transplant</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This Phase 1, multicenter, open label, two tier safety study is designed to assess the safety of standard dosing of Nivolumab in kidney transplant patients with pretreated incurable cancer or defined metastatic solid tumours.  Patient recruitment will be stratified by entry median fluorescent intensity (MFI) antibodies to donor antigens such that we envisage two tiers: patients at low immunological risk with no HLA donor specific antibodies; and intermediate immunological risk (HLA antibodies 600-4000 MFI). Nivolumab (3mg/kg) will be administered as an intravenous infusion over 60 minutes every 2 weeks (1 cycle) per cancer specific protocols and study treatment will continue as long as there is tumour response for up to 2 years. .   </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of irretrievable renal graft rejection in transplant recipients with solid tumours not curable using standard treatment paradigms receiving a standard schedule of Nivolumab. Renal function will be measured and any rise in creatinine deemed to be significant by the treating physician will lead to renal transplant biopsy. Complete loss of kidney function with return to dialysis is the definition of irretrievable graft loss. </outcome>
      <timepoint>2-4 cycles of Nivolumab</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the safety (as per NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (v4.03: June 14, 2010)) of Nivolumab in recipients of renal transplants. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tumour response to Nivolumab in patients with incurable, locally advanced or metastatic malignancy following failure of curative treatment tumours. Tumour must be known to be potentially responsive to Nivolumab as defined by Phase II and III studies. Tumour response defined by RECIST criteria.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient  survival in patients treated with Nivolumab.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Renal allograft survival in patients treated with Nivolumab</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Patient has provided written informed consent prior to initiation of any study specific activities/procedures.	
*Recipient of renal transplant aged 18 years or older more than 3 months post-transplant
*Recipients of multiple renal transplants will be allowed 
*Incurable locally advanced or metastatic, histologically proven tumours, progressing on standard first line therapy or metastatic solid tumours requiring palliative treatment (the latter group of patients are not required to have had prior anti-cancer therapy) or in-operable tumours where standard curative treatment approaches will either have failed or are not applicable.
*ECOG 0-1 and 2 by discussion with medical monitor 
*Disease that is measurable by RECIST
*Eligible tumour types include:
		a. SCC of the skin
		b. SCC of head and neck
		c. Melanoma
		d. Merkel Cell Carcinoma
		e. NSCLC Lung cancer
		f. Urothelial cancer
		g. Colorectal cancer which is MSI-H
.		h. Breast cancer (triple negative) 
		i. Any other solid tumour which is MSI-H
		j. Any tumour which is deemed to be sensitive to PD-1 blockade 
*Co-morbid conditions are stable
*Life expectancy &gt;3 months 
*Patient has adequate organ and bone marrow function within 14 days of study entry
		a. Neutrophil count &gt;1.5 x109/L
		b. Platelets &gt;100 x109/L
		c. Hb &gt;80g/L
		d. Total bilirubin &lt;1.5 upper limit of normal, (ULN) 
		e. ALT and AST &lt;3.0 x ULN
		f. Serum creatinine &lt;1.5 x ULN 
		g. PT and APTT &lt;1.3 x ULN
*Willing to stay on, restart or have no contraindications to immunosuppressive agents including calcineurin inhibitors, antiproliferative agents and prednisolone if deemed appropriate by the study investigators.
*For females of reproductive potential-negative pregnancy test prior to study entry and use of highly effective contraception
*For males of reproductive potential: use of condoms
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>An individual who meets any of the following criteria will be excluded from participation:
*Within 3 months of transplantation and at the time of initiation of Nivolumab.
*Unable to provide informed consent
*Not prepared or unable to re-join a renal dialysis program
*Unable to undertake monitoring for signs of rejection, toxicity or anti-tumour effect
*The patient has uncontrolled or significant intercurrent or recent illness including:
a) Auto-immune disorder or uncontrolled endocrinopathy
b) Cardiac disorder such as uncontrolled cardiac failure, unstable angina or NSTEMI or myocardial infarction, uncontrolled arrhythmia
c) Stroke or thromboembolic event within 3 months of study commencement
d) Active or uncontrolled severe infection
e) Active coagulopathy/bleeding diathesis
f) Cirrhosis, chronic active or untreated persistent hepatitis
* The patient is pregnant or lactating
* The patient doesnt agree to use highly effective methods of contraception.
* Prisoners or subjects who are involuntarily incarcerated
* Subjects who are compulsorily detained for treatment of either a psychiatric or
physical (eg, infectious disease) illness
* Donor specific antibody with MFI &gt;4000 units</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>With a sample size of 30 patients, we will consider a Simons two stage accrual process whereby accrual will be halted if we see greater than 2 allograft rejections amongst the first 15 patients and greater than 3 amongst the first 30 patients. Given these stopping thresholds, if the true underlying rate of allograft rejections is 0.07 then the overall probability of discontinuation after stage 2 of accrual is 20% and if the true underlying rate of allograft rejections is 0.24 then the overall probability of discontinuation after stage 2 of accrual is 95% However, since the original statistical analysis (defining minimal rejection rate and hypothesized rejection rates) there have been additional cases reports to further define rates of rejection. It is hoped that with careful patients selection and monitoring a rejection rate of 15% would be clinically acceptable and based on these data, greater than 2 rejections in the first 8 for each of the immunological tiers and a total of 8 rejections in the first 30 (for the combined low and intermediate risk groups) would be the stopping parameters.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>15/05/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/01/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Central Northern Adelaide Local Health Network, Royal Adelaide Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide 
SA5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main focus of this study it to determine if giving immune activating anti-cancer therapy (Nivolumab) is safe in kidney transplant patients with incurable cancer.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a recipient of renal transplant (at least 3 months post- transplant) aged 18 years or above and have been diagnosed with an incurable cancer.

Study details
All study participants will receive Nivolumab (3mg/kg) as an intravenous infusion over 60 minutes every 2 weeks and study treatment will continue as long as there is clinical benefit up to 2 years.
Nivolumab is an antibody (a type of human protein) that is being tested to see if it will allow the bodys immune system to work against tumour cells. That is using the bodys immune reaction to destroy cancer cells. 
Currently kidney transplant patients are excluded from clinical trials of this anti-cancer therapy - because they are taking anti-rejection medication. This trial is about trying to decide the balance between giving anti-rejection drugs and anti-cancer therapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide  Hosptial </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
SA5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/RAH/508</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Robert Peter Carroll</name>
      <address>Central Northern Adelaide Renal and Transplantation Service
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
SA5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82220900</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82220970</fax>
      <email>robert.carroll@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Robert Peter Carroll</name>
      <address>Central Northern Adelaide Renal and Transplantation Service
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
SA5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82220900</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82220970</fax>
      <email>robert.carroll@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Robert Peter Carroll</name>
      <address>Central Northern Adelaide Renal and Transplantation Service
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
SA5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82220900</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82220970</fax>
      <email>robert.carroll@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Carroll</name>
      <address>Central Northern Adelaide Renal and Transplantation Service
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
SA5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82220900</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82220970</fax>
      <email>robert.carroll@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>