<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368477">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000516583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A single centre, open label, first in human, phase 1 dose escalating study to evaluate the safety, tolerability and preliminary efficacy of an autologous cancer vaccine, RGSH4K, administered intradermally in patients with advanced cancers. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with advanced solid tumours, is an autologous cancer vaccine (RGSH4K), safe and tolerable, and can a biologically active dose be identified? </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ACTIVATE trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Advanced solid tumours</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>RGSH4K is a vaccine formulated from a patient's own tumour material. Briefly, the tumour cells are lysed or burst to release the proteins and tumour associated antigens. The proteins are further processed in a proprietary procedure and combined with streptavidin, a novel immunostimulant. No live, viable cells remain in the vaccine. Vaccines are prepared on study entry, are stored frozen, and provided individually for injection at Weeks 1, 4 and 7. 

Three (3) doses of streptavidin are being assessed in this study: 100 ug, 250 ug, and 500 ug. Each set of vaccines manufactured is unique to each patient and will therefore be a unique batch. 

The vaccine is admixed with 200 uL of Freund's Incomplete Adjuvant immediately before administration. Three (3) vaccines in total are administered: Week 1, Week 4, and Week 7. Each vaccine is given as a single, small volume injection intradermally. </interventions>
    <comparator>This is an open label, first in human study in patients with advanced cancer. There is no comparator or control treatment. </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of RGSH4K as measured by the incidence and nature of adverse events using the CTCAE grading scale for adverse events. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse events are collected from the time of informed consent and at each study visit: Weeks 1, 4, 7, 10, 12, and 24. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of RGSH4K as measured by vital signs, physical examinations, ECG and laboratory assessments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Vital signs, ECG, physical examinations and laboratory assessments are measured at the following visits: Weeks 1, 4, 7, 10, 12, 24. At week 12, laboratory assessments are not done. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determination of a biologically active dose of RGSH4K as measured by CT/MRI (whichever method is most appropriate for the cancer type)</outcome>
      <timepoint>CT/MRI is done at screening, week 12, and at week 24. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determination of a biologically active dose of RGSH4K as measured by immunology biomarkers: white cell differential, mast cells, B cells (CD20+, CD40+, CD80+) and cytokines (VEGF, IL-6, IFN, TNF)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immunology biomarkers are assessed at weeks 1, 4, 7, 12, and 24. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determination of a biologically active dose of RGSH4K as measured by blood cancer markers relevant to the type of cancer a patient has. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Relevant blood cancer markers will be assessed at weeks 1, 7, 12, and 24. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Summary:
- aged 18 years or over
- has banked approximately 1 gram of fresh frozen tumour in the Regeneus tumour bank
- have advanced solid tumours which are inoperable or refractory to treatment, or chemoradiotherapy is contraindicated, or where standard treatments have failed or do not exist, or in a palliative setting where the patient has refused chemotherapy or it is contraindicated.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Rapidly progressing malignancy
- History of organ transplant and/or current immunosuppressive therapy, current systemic corticosteroids
- concurrent anticancer therapy, or within 4 weeks of vaccine
- Autoimmune disease
- known positive HIV or tests positive to HIV </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>21</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Regeneus Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>25 Bridge St
Pymble  2073  NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Regeneus Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>25 Bridge St
Pymble  2073  NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to evaluate the safety, tolerability and preliminary efficacy of 3 different doses of a cancer vaccine, manufactured from a patient's own tumour. 

Who is it for? 
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above, have banked a tumour sample in the Regeneus Tumour Bank (ACTRN12615000476538) and your tumour is inoperable and non-treatable or current treatment is refractory. 

Study details 
All patients enrolled in this safety and tolerability study will have their banked tumour samples used to develop a tumour specific vaccine. In brief, the vaccine is manufactured from the tumour, which is homogenised, processed and combined with streptavidin, an immunostimulant. Tumour cells are burst open during this process so that only the tumour proteins remain, i.e. no viable tumour cells remain in the vaccine. At the bedside, the vaccine is mixed with Freunds Incomplete Adjuvant (FIA), which assists in immune recognition. Patients are given a single, small volume vaccine into the skin on Weeks 1, 4, and 7. Three different dose levels of streptavidin will be assessed (100, 250 or 500 ug) to identify the dose that is biologically active.  

Safety and tolerability will be assessed over a 24 week period by recording adverse event information, vital signs, physical examinations and various laboratory assessments. CT or MRI scans and blood samples will also be taken over this period for determination of your response to the vaccine. 

It is hoped that this study will aid in the treatment of solid tumours by harnessing a patient's own immune system to target and destroy cancer proteins. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Ltd</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road 
Eastwood 
South Australia 5063 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/05/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015-02-099</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen Clarke</name>
      <address>Northern Cancer Institute
Level 1
38 Pacific Highway 
ST LEONARDS NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9437 1900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>info@northerncancerinstitute.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Iona Nicolson-Bowles</name>
      <address>Northern Cancer Institute
Level 1
38 Pacific Highway 
ST LEONARDS NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8037 4100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>info@northerncancerinstitute.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Janet Wilson</name>
      <address>Regeneus Ltd
25 Bridge St
Pymble  2073  NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9499 8010</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>janet.wilson@regeneus.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Janet Wilson</name>
      <address>Regeneus Ltd
25 Bridge St
Pymble  2073  NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9499 8010</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>