<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1050">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/02/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/02/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000050550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Physiotherapy following breast cancer surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Early strengthening and stretching exercises to improve arm mobility for women following breast cancer surgery: a randomised controlled study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Women following breast cancer surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Exercise Group: Commencing week 4 following surgery, women will attend weekly physiotherapy sessions comprising stretching exercises, resistance training and functional tasks and commence a daily home program of similar exercises for 8 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care: women will receive the same care as is now given in three hospitals (Royal Prince Alfred, Concored General and Strathfield Private Hospitals). They will not be given a home program of exercises, apart from those described in a pamphlet provided to all patients.  To control attention from the therapist, they will be telephoned at the same time intervals as women in the exercise group, but no specific advice will be given about exercise and management.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arm symptoms on the operated side from 3 items of the Breast Module (BR 23).  The BR23 is a 23 item survey specific to women with breast cancer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 8 weeks (at the end of intervention) and 6 months intervals up to 3 years after the surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Several aspects of quality of life will be measured using the European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire Version 3 (QLQ-C30). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline (4-5weeks after surgery), at 8 weeks (at the end of intervention), and 6 months intervals up to 3 years after surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Passive forward flexion, extermal rotation, horizontal abduction and active abduction at the shoulder will be assessed. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline (4-5weeks after surgery), at 8 weeks (at the end of intervention), and 6 months intervals up to 3 years after surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3. Maximal isometric shoulder strength of forward flexion, abduction, and horizontal abduction and adduction will be measured objectively using a standardised protocol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline (4-5weeks after surgery), at 8 weeks (at the end of intervention), and 6 months intervals up to 3 years after surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4. Pain at the end of passive range of each movement will be measured using a standardised 10 cm visual analogue scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline (4-5weeks after surgery), at 8 weeks (at the end of intervention), and 6 months intervals up to 3 years after surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5. Multiple frequency bio-impedanced analysis (MFBIA) will be used to identify early changes in tissue density, and in particular, extracellular fluid. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline (4-5weeks after surgery), at 8 weeks (at the end of intervention), and 6 months intervals up to 3 years after surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6. Limb circumference measures of each arm will be determined using a standardised measurement technique.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline (4-5weeks after surgery), at 8 weeks (at the end of intervention), and 6 months intervals up to 3 years after surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>If they have breast cancer intervention that included surgery to the axilla.* they can attend for treatment and follow-up, and* they understand English and consent to participate and be randomised to either treatment group.Women will be excluded if they have:* not had surgery to the axilla,* undergone bilateral operations,* received previous treatment for breast cancer, or metastatic disease, * sustained a fracture, undergone surgery in the upper limbs or suffer any neurological deficit or other injury to either upper limb that may intefere with the test procedures, or* undergone breast reconstruction and whom their specialist has indicated that they are not to participate.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Not stated</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No exclusion criteria</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>numbered opaque sealed envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated random allocation stratified by whether the woman received axillary node resection or sentinel node biopsy</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Council NSW</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Breast cancer affects nearly 10,000 Australian women each year.  Because the treatment of the cancer is so invasive and aggressive, and there is insufficient rehabilitation, women often report the presence of symptoms such as stiffness, weakness, swelling and pain months and years after treatment.  These symptoms can impact on the quality of life and interfere substantially with activities of daily living for the cancer survivor.  We will investigate whether an early intervention program of daily stretching and strengthening for muscles about the shoulder prevents occurence of these symptoms.  We will compare the outcomes of patients randomly assigned to either an exercise group or a usual care (control) group.  Subjects allocated to the exercise group will perform exercises daily, and will be supervised by a physiotherapist once a week for 8 weeks.  At the end of the 8 weeks, subjects will be given a home-based training program to continue indefinitely.  Subjects in the 'Usual care' group will receive the same care as is now typically received, a vist by the physiotherapist and occupational therapist while an inpatient, and receipt of pamphlets.  All subjects will be measured at baseline, 8 weeks, and 6 months intervals up to 3 years.  The primary measure is arm symptoms, derived from a Breast Cancer specific questionnaire (BR32).  In addition, range of motion, strength, swelling, pain and quality of life will be assessed.  This study will determine whether the secondary problmes associated with treatment of breast cancer can be prevented by exercise, and provide the basis for successful rehabilitation.  Additionally, it will identify whether strengthening exercises reduces the incidence of swelling.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney human ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital human ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sharon Kilbreath</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health Sciences
University of Sydney
C42
PO Box 170
Lidcombe NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93519272</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93519160</fax>
      <email>s.kilbreath@fhs.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sharon Kilbreath</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health Sciences
University of Sydney
C42
PO Box 170
Lidcombe NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93519272</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93519160</fax>
      <email>s.kilbreath@fhs.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>