<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83436">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/12/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000937910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Irreversible  Electroporation (IRE) for the treatment of  focal liver, kidney and lung cancer ablation: a pilot study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Irreversible  Electroporation (IRE) for the treatment focal liver, kidney and lung cancer ablation: a pilot study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>IRE study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NA</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Focal tumours of the liver</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Focal tumours of the lung</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Focal tumours of the kidney</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Liver</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is ablation using Irreversible electroporation (direct current) which disrupts the cell membrane killing the tumour cells.

The whole procedure takes between 2 to 3 hours.  Once the needle electrodes are in place the ablation takes approximately one minute. Depending on the size of the tumour the needle electrodes may be repositioned and further ablations (2 to approximately 10)  may be performed.  If complete ablation is not achieved a second procedure can be performed.</interventions>
    <comparator>none</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety - Determined by the composite number of adverse events

The risks of ablation procedures include:

* Pain and nausea:  nearly all patients experience some pain and nausea.

* Delayed ablation syndrome where you may have a fever/ malaise - 25%. Roughly one in four patients may develop a "post-ablation syndrome" with flu-like symptoms that appear three to five days after the procedure and usually last about five days. An occasional patient may remain ill for two to three weeks.  Paracetamol taken by mouth is commonly used to control fever. 

* For patients with lung tumours there is a 50% chance of pheumothorax .  Pneumothorax is when air collects between the lung and inner chest and this causes the lung to collapse.  This can be treated by placing a chest tube between the ribs into the space around the lungs to drain the air out of the space and to allow the lung to re-expand.  If pneumothorax results you will be required to stay in hospital as an inpatient until the pneumothorax is resolved and the chest tube can be removed.

* Infection (very rare). Any procedure where the skin is penetrated carries a risk of infection. The chance of infection requiring antibiotic treatment appears to be less than one in 1,000. 

* Post operative haemorrhage requiring transfusion (very rare). Some cases of bleeding have been reported but it usually stops on its own. If bleeding is severe, an additional procedure or surgery may be needed to control it. 

* Injury to surrounding tissue (none noted to date in animal studies and human prostate studies of the Angiodynamics System). RFA however, because it relies on heat to damage cells, depending on the site of treatment, it may cause brief or, rarely, long-lasting shoulder pain; inflammation of the gallbladder that subsides after a few weeks; damage to the bile ducts resulting in biliary obstruction - a blockage in the tubes that carry a liquid called bile from the liver to the gallbladder and small intestine; this liquid helps digest fat.  An operation may be needed to rectify the problem;  or thermal damage to the bowel (3-5%).

* Death (extremely rare). 

Having a drug injected or blood taken may cause some discomfort or bruising. Sometimes, the blood vessel may swell, or blood may clot in the blood vessel, or the spot from which tissue is taken could become inflamed. Rarely, there could be a minor infection or bleeding. If this happens, it can be easily treated.

Medical treatments often cause side effects. You may have none, some or all of the effects listed above, and they may be mild, moderate or severe. If you have any of these side effects, or are worried about them, talk with your doctor.  Your doctor will also be looking out for side effects.  

Many side effects go away shortly after treatment ends. However, sometimes side effects can be serious, long lasting or permanent. If a severe side effect or reaction occurs.  Tell your doctor if you have any problems. Your doctor will discuss the best way of managing any side effects with you

Computer Tomography (CT) imaging uses X-rays and therefore exposes you to ionising radiation.  Ionising radiation represents a significant risk to unborn children. Therefore, all women of childbearing age will be screened for pregnancy. This screening is standard procedure for all women of childbearing age prior to undergoing a X-ray or CT. This screening may include a blood or urine pregnancy test. If you think that you may be pregnant or plan to become pregnant you should not participate in this study. If you become pregnant during this study, immediately contact your research doctor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Procedure, 1 month, 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy of ablation - Determined by contrast enhanced computer tomography</outcome>
      <timepoint>At one then every 3 months post procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>n/a</outcome>
      <timepoint>n/a</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Ages 35-85 years, Signed informed consent, Failed conventional treatment, Ability to visualize cancer foci adequately on imaging.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients not deemed suitable for ablation procedure.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/11/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Alfred Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Alfred Hospital Melbourne, Vic 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Angiodynamics Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>603 Queensbury Avenue
Queensbury, New York 13805</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In cases where patients have inoperable tumours, direct destruction of focal tumours using various energy sources such as heat (radiofrequency ablation, microwaves), cold (cryotherapy) or ethanol injection have been used for the last twenty years.  A needle is placed into the tumour under image guidance in a similar way to taking a biopsy.  The energy used, heat or cold, destroys the tumour.  Currently not all inoperable tumours can be treated in this way because tumours may lie close to vital structures that may be affected and therefore pose a large risk to patients.  The new technology, irreversible electroporation, does not use heat or cold and therefore spares vital structures.  Direct electrical current is used to destroy the outer membrane of the tumour cells. We are testing the safety and effectiveness of this form of ablation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Thomson KR, Cheung W, Ellis SJ, Federman D, Kavnoudias H, Loader-Oliver D, Roberts S, Evans P, Ball C, Haydon A.  Investigation of the Safety of Irreversible Electroporation in Humans. J Vasc Interv Radiol 2011 May;22(5):611-21</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Commercial Road
Melbourne, Vic 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/09/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/08/0204</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Helen Kavnoudias</name>
      <address>The Alfred
Commercial Road
Melbourne, Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 3606</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 2153</fax>
      <email>h.kavnoudias@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Helen Kavnoudias</name>
      <address>Radiology Department
The Alfred
Commercial Road
Melbourne, VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 3606</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 2153</fax>
      <email>h.kavnoudias@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>