<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372885">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000714381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised trial of nonselective versus selective adjuvant therapy in high risk apparent stage 1 endometrial cancer.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised trial of nonselective versus selective adjuvant therapy in high risk apparent stage 1 endometrial cancer.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>STATEC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ClinicalTrials.gov NCT02566811
</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>University College London:  UCL/13/0630</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>Cancer Research UK: CRUK/14/043</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>ANZGOG: ANZGOG1311/2016 </secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre: CTC 0129 </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>endometrial cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Womb (Uterine or endometrial cancer)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>STATEC is testing the use of a surgical procedure called lymphadenectomy (or lymph gland removal) to help guide further treatment in women with endometrial (womb) cancer.   In patients who undergo lymph gland removal, the results of the lymph gland removal (e.g. node negative or node positive) will be used to select further (adjuvant) treatment.
Patients will be randomised to one of the following two arms, either prior to surgery or following hysterectomy and bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy (BSO):
Group 1: Randomised treatment will be hysterectomy and BSO, plus lymphadenectomy. Patients randomised prior to hysterectomy and BSO will receive the lymphadenectomy as part of the same operation as the hysterectomy and BSO.  Patients randomised after hysterectomy and BSO will receive the lymphadenectomy as a separate operation. Adjuvant treatment will then be determined by lymph node status. Node positive patients will receive adjuvant treatment to include chemotherapy with or without external radiotherapy, while node negative patients will receive brachytherapy (internal radiotherapy) only.
Group 2: Randomised treatment will be a hysterectomy and BSO without lymphadenectomy. Patients randomised after hysterectomy and BSO will receive no further surgery. Patients will then receive adjuvant treatment to include chemotherapy with or without external radiotherapy.
The chemotherapy, external radiotherapy and/or brachytherapy for patients in both Group 1 and Group 2 will be given as per standard practice at the treating hospital. </interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator treatment is surgery (hysterectomy and BSO) with NO lymph glands removed.  After the surgery, all of the women in this group will receive chemotherapy with or without radiation therapy as per standard practice at the treating institution. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival (measured from the date of randomisation until the date of death from any cause)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until death from any cause</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease-free survival (measured from the date of randomisation until date of first recurrence, a new secondary tumour or death from any cause, whichever occurs first)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until date of first recurrence or death</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endometrial cancer-event free survival (measured from the date of randomisation until recurrence or death from endometrial cancer, or treatment related deaths, whichever occurs first)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until recurrence or death from endometrial cancer</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endometrial cancer-specific survival (measured from the date of randomisation until death from endometrial cancer, or treatment-related deaths)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until death from endometrial cancer or treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pelvic and extra-pelvic relapse-free survival (composite outcome as assessed by radiological imaging at time of relapse with documentation of site/s of relapse)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until relapse</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness (using the EQ-5D-5L for economic evaluation)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time frame: 5 years after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Surgical adverse events (acute and late) as assessed by the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events v4.03</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time frame: 3 months after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Histologically confirmed high risk apparent International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics (FIGO) stage I endometrial cancer according to one of the following criteria. Confirmation must be based on either diagnostic endometrial sampling or hysterectomy and BSO specimen if randomisation occurring after hysterectomy and BSO:
a.FIGO grade 3 endometrioid or mucinous carcinoma
b.High grade serous, clear cell, undifferentiated or dedifferentiated carcinoma or mixed cell adenocarcinoma or carcinosarcoma

* Surgery to be performed &lt;= 5 weeks after randomisation in patients randomised prior to hysterectomy and BSO. Patients randomised after hysterectomy and BSO must have undergone hysterectomy and BSO &lt;= 28 days prior to randomisation. Patients randomised after hysterectomy and BSO who are allocated lymphadenectomy must undergo lymphadenectomy &lt;= 5 weeks after randomisation

* Written informed consent

* No prior anticancer therapy for endometrial cancer

* Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (EGOC) performance status 0-2

* Life expectancy &gt; 3 months

* Age &gt;= 16 years

* Adequate organ and bone marrow function

* Ability to undergo post-operative chemotherapy with or without radiotherapy

* Adjuvant treatment to commence &lt;= 8 weeks after surgery

* Willingness and ability to complete Quality of Life questionnaires</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Grossly enlarged node(s) of &gt;= 10 mm short axis on baseline radiological imaging

* Invasion of the cervical stroma on baseline radiological imaging or obvious cervical disease on clinical examination

* Involvement of uterine serosa or metastatic disease seen outside the uterus on baseline radiological imaging

* Small cell carcinoma with neuroendocrine differentiation

* Concurrent anti-cancer therapy

* Previous malignancy &lt; 5 years prior to randomisation or concurrent malignant disease with the exception of:
a.carcinoma in situ of cervix
b.non-melanoma skin cancer
c.basal cell carcinoma
d.melanoma in situ

* Women who are pregnant or lactating</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will occur centrally by computer.  Patients will be randomised in a 1:1 ratio according to the following stratification factors:
a. participating site
b. histology:
c. lymphovascular space invasion 
d. timing of hysterectomy and BSO </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The study plans to enrol 2000 participants internationally (including 240 in Australia/New Zealand).
The overall non-inferiority margin of 5 percentage points was agreed by the investigators to be clinically acceptable to patients and surgeons.
Using the exponential parameter of 0.0040, allowable hazard ratio of 1.272, and assuming 48 months accrual then a further 48 months study follow up (i.e. a maximum length of follow up of 96 months), requires 2000 patients to be recruited (500 deaths), with 85% power, and 5% two-sided statistical significance. With 80% power, the sample size is 1720 patients (430 deaths), and this would be the minimum target.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>5/07/2021</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>12/04/2026</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Camperdown
NSW, 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University College London</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>90 Tottenham Court Road
London
W1T 4TJ

</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United Kingdom</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is testing the use of a surgical procedure called lymphadenectomy (or lymph gland removal) to help guide further treatment in women with endometrial (womb) cancer. 

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a woman aged 16 years or above, have histologically confirmed high risk apparent International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics (FIGO) stage I endometrial cancer.

Study details
Patients will be randomly allocated to one of two groups, Group 1 or Group 2. 

Patients in Group 1 will have surgery with lymph glands removed. The results of the lymph glands will be used to decide on the further treatment. Women with cancer in their lymph nodes (node positive) will receive chemotherapy with or without radiotherapy. Women with no cancer in their lymph nodes (node negative) will only receive an internal form of radiotherapy called brachytherapy and will not be given chemotherapy or external radiotherapy. 

Patients in Group 2 will have surgery with no lymph glands removed. After surgery, all women in this group will then receive chemotherapy with or without external radiotherapy.

Specifics of the chemotherapy and radiotherapy will vary depending on the specific institution and individual doctor conducting the study.

The purpose of this study is to find out whether there is any difference in clinical response between patients in Group 1 and those in Group 2 and to determine whether lymph gland removal improves quality of life in some patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>RPAH Zone of the Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics and Governance Office
Suite 210A 
RPA Medical Centre 
Cnr Missenden Road and Carillon Avenue 
NEWTOWN NSW 2042
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/06/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X17-0001 &amp; HREC/17/RPAH/1</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Alison Brand</name>
      <address>c/o STATEC Study Team
NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown, NSW
1450</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Alison.Brand@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>STATEC Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>c/o STATEC Study Team
NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown, NSW
1450</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>statec@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Alison Brand</name>
      <address>c/o STATEC Study Team
NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown, NSW
1450</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Alison.Brand@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>STATEC Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>c/o STATEC Study Team
NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown, NSW
1450</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>statec@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>