<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372305">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000691347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Melanoma Genomics Managing Your Risk Study: examining the impact of personal melanoma genomic risk information on prevention behaviours in the general population</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Melanoma Genomics Managing Your Risk Study: a randomised controlled trial of the efficacy of personal melanoma genomic risk of information, compared to standard prevention advice, in motivating reduced exposure to ultraviolet radiation in the general population </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>melanoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants randomly allocated to the intervention arm will receive:
1.	A mailed saliva collection kit for subsequent DNA extraction and genotyping.
2.	Personal genetic risk of melanoma information. About 2-3 months after providing a saliva sample, participants will receive their genetic risk information in a hardcopy booklet sent via postal mail. The booklet, developed as part of our pilot trial (ACTRN12615000356561), presents and describes participants individual genetic risk of melanoma using evidence-based risk communication strategies, such as numerical and visual presentations of lifetime absolute risk. Participants reported high satisfaction with the genetic risk booklet in the pilot trial, and we have made minor modifications to enhance clarity for participants in the Managing Your Risk Study. The risk information includes:  
*An absolute risk percentage showing their remaining lifetime risk of developing melanoma. For example, our pilot study observed remaining lifetime genomic risk estimates of up to 20% but the average risk was around 2-4%.
* A risk level: higher than average = top 25% of genomic risk, average = middle 50%, lower than average = bottom 25%; based on quartile cut-points within each age, sex and state strata. 
The genetic risk booklet also contains simple explanatory information about how a persons risk is calculated, and what they can do to reduce their risk. 
3.	A telephone call from the study genetic counsellor. The genetic counsellor will contact all participants in the intervention arm within two-weeks after their genetic risk information is sent via postal mail. The purpose of the phone call is to confirm receipt of the booklet and to answer any potential questions. We expect the phone call will last approximately 10 minutes, depending on the number of questions or discussion points raised by participants. 
4.	An educational booklet on melanoma preventive behaviours and skin examinations. The educational booklet, developed for our pilot trial (ACTRN12615000356561), is based on SunSmart campaign resources. It includes information on risk factors for melanoma and other skin cancers, recommendations for optimal sun exposure and sun protection behaviours, information about skin examinations including an online video showing step-by-step skin self-examination, and information about Vitamin D. Educational materials are widely used by the Australian general public and, as such, are considered standard care. In the pilot trial, this educational booklet was rated highly (more than 8 out of 10) in terms of satisfaction by participants.

</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomly allocated to the control arm will receive the same educational booklet provided to intervention arm participants on melanoma preventive behaviours including sun exposure, sun protection and skin examinations </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is total daily Standard Erythemal Doses (SEDs), an objective measure of ultraviolet radiation (UVR) exposure, measured 12 months after the baseline assessment. SEDs will be measured using time-stamped electronic dosimeter badges, mounted in light-weight custom-made wristbands attached to the left wrist (similar to wearing a watch) during daylight hours. UV dosimeters will be worn by all participants for 10 days at baseline, 1-month after receipt of the booklet/s, and again 12-months after baseline. The data collected on weekdays will be averaged over 5 days and the data collected on weekends will be averaged over 2 days to enable an average weekly and average daily dose to be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily Standard Erythemal Doses (SEDs) during: a) peak-time, b) morning, and c) afternoon periods of day. SEDs will be measured using time-stamped electronic dosimeter badges, mounted in light-weight custom-made wristbands attached to the left wrist (similar to wearing a watch) during daylight hours. UV dosimeters will be worn by all participants for 10 days at baseline, 1-month after receipt of the booklet/s, and again 12-months after baseline. The data collected on weekdays will be averaged over 5 days and the data collected on weekends will be averaged over 2 days to enable an average weekly and average daily dose to be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1-month from receiving genomic risk information, and 12-months from baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sun protection behaviours, measured as the frequency of: sunscreen use, wearing a shirt with sleeves, wearing a hat, seeking shade, wearing sunglasses, limiting peak-time sun exposure. This will be measured Uuing questionnaire items, including the sun protection habits index, calculated as the mean of six protective behaviours on a 4-point Likert scale (1=never or rarely, 4=always). During the past month, when outside, how often did you... wear sunscreen? wear a shirt with sleeves that cover your shoulders? wear a hat? stay in the shade or under an umbrella? wear sunglasses? limit your time in the sun during midday hours? </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1-month from receiving genomic risk information, and 12-months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skin examinations (self-, partner- or doctor-conducted). This will be measured using questionnaire items: frequency of skin examinations conducted by participants, their partners and doctors. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1-month from receiving genomic risk information, and 12-months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intentional tanning frequency, measured using a questionnaire item How often do you spend time in the sun in order to get a tan? measured on a 5-point Likert scale (1=never, 5=always). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1-month from receiving genomic risk information, and 12-months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sunburn frequency, measured using a questionnaire item: sunburn frequency recalled over the previous month.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1-month from receiving genomic risk information, and 12-months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skin cancer-related worry, measured using 3 questionnaire items shown to be associated with the frequency of skin self-examination in people without melanoma. These items have been adapted from other research on skin examination behaviour (Kasparian et al, Skin Examination Behavior, Arch Dermatol. 2012;148(10):1142-1151)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1-month from receiving genomic risk information, and 12-months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress and well-being, measured using the 5-item version of the Mental Health Inventory (MHI-5) designed for primary care settings.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1-month from receiving genomic risk information, and 12-months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The cost-effectiveness of the genomic risk intervention compared to standard prevention advice alone, from the Australian health system perspective. This will be a two-stage analysis:
(i)	A within-trial economic evaluation at 12 months, reporting the cost for a defined reduction in daily SEDs, stratified by phenotypic risk group (i.e. primary outcome).
(ii)	A modelled evaluation will extrapolate the intermediate trial outcomes over the longer term to report definitive health outcomes including the cost per melanoma or other skin cancer avoided, and the cost per life year saved.
Resource use will be identified and valued from questionnaire data and Medicare Benefits Schedule (MBS) claims data. As part of the consent process, participants will be asked to consent to linkage of their study data to MBS data (linkage is then straightforward and timely), to Australian cancer registries for future follow-up of melanoma incidence and to the National Death Index. This data linkage will add considerable value to the study by enabling collection of future melanoma incidence through cancer registries and non-melanoma incidence through MBS data. Hospital costs will be valued using relevant Australian-Refined Diagnosis Related Groups. The cost of the intervention will be calculated using trial costs, and sensitivity analyses will be conducted for variations in these costs. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-month from receiving genomic risk information, and 12-months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Demographic characteristics and covariates will include age, country of birth, education, marital status, employment status, socioeconomic index; family history of melanoma, personal history of keratinocyte skin cancers, skin colour, skin reaction to repeated sun exposure, time spent outdoors on weekdays and weekends, and phenotypic risk factors e.g. hair colour, moles using valid, reliable questions. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Demographic factors will be collected at baseline only. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We will measure possible mediators of behaviour change using questions previously developed, tested and widely implemented for skin cancer research and based on well-established health behaviour theories: the Health Belief Model (related to risk perception, barriers and benefits) and Social Cognitive Theory (related to self-efficacy, social norms and environmental influences). These factors have been shown to be important influences on sun-related behaviours. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1-month from receiving genomic risk information, and 12-months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feelings of genetic fatalism will be measured using questionnaire items adapted from other research studies examining the psychological and ethical aspects of delivering genomic risk information. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1-month from receiving genomic risk information, and 12-months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant satisfaction with the study and the general educational booklet will be measured using questionnaire items developed for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-month from receiving genomic risk information, and 12-months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For participants in the intervention arm, we will measure participant satisfaction with the genetic risk booklet and genetic counsellor follow-up call using questionnaire items developed for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-month from receiving genomic risk information, and 12-months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We will measure the specific impact of result disclosure after genetic testing using the validated Multidimensional Impact of Cancer Risk Assessment (MICRA) scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-month from receiving genomic risk information, and 12-months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health literacy will be measured using a questionnaire item "how confident are you filling out medical forms by yourself?" </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Risk taking behaviours will be measured using "A Domain-Specific Risk-Taking (DOSPERT) scale for adult populations" </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>People from the general population aged 18-69 years with European ancestry, who have never had a melanoma (since this study is primarily aimed at prevention), and have sufficient English to complete the study questionnaires.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>69</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Outside the eligible age range, personal history of melanoma, no European ancestry, insufficient English to complete the study questionnaires  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The biostatistician performing the randomisation will assign participants to their study group (intervention or control) based on a list of study numbers and stratification factors. The biostatistician will not have access to participants’ identifying details such as participant names or contact details. Randomisation will be performed in batches where possible. Staff involved in the day-to-day running of the project will not be involved in the randomisation process apart from providing the list of variables to the biostatistician.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation to the intervention or control arm (allocation ratio 1:1) will be conducted by a biostatistician not involved in the day-to-day running of the project using a computer-based system after collection of baseline data. A minimisation procedure will be used, to ensure that the groups are balanced by phenotypic risk (low, high), sex, state of residence and age-group (18–44, 45–69).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size: 
Sample size calculations are based on detecting a 20% difference in the primary outcome of average daily SEDs between intervention and control arms, in each of the low- and the high-risk phenotype groups. Due to the skewed nature of the SED exposure data, the sample size was calculated using a t-test with a geometric mean in the control arm of 1.6, coefficient of variation 0.9, and based on detecting a 20% difference in SEDs; this is equivalent to an absolute mean difference of 0.4 SEDs/day, or median difference of 0.3 SEDs/day, between intervention and control groups. Our calculations were based on 80% power and a (type I error) of 0.05. 

Based on these calculations, our target sample size for the primary outcome comparison is 800 people, of which 400 in the high-risk phenotype group and 400 in the low-risk phenotype group, split evenly between the intervention and control arms. Allowing up to 15% with incomplete follow-up at 12 months, we will need to recruit 944 people (472 in each of intervention and control arms). A secondary analysis unstratified by phenotypic risk will give enough power to detect a 15% difference between the intervention and control groups. 

Analysis plan: 
The primary analysis will be an intention-to-treat comparison of intervention and control arms for mean differences in UVR exposure measured as log-transformed daily SEDs at 12 months, stratifying by phenotypic risk (high, low). UV dosimeter values will be log-transformed because of their right-skew distribution, and log-transformed values will be interpreted as a percentage change in the geometric mean of SEDs/day. Secondary analyses will follow a similar approach, i.e. an intention-to-treat comparison of intervention and control arms for mean differences in outcomes, stratifying by phenotypic risk (high, low). For continuous outcome measures including log-transformed SEDs, we will use ANCOVA adjusted for baseline values to estimate the mean difference and 95% confidence intervals between intervention and control groups. For binomial outcome variables, we used log-binomial models to estimate relative risks and 95% CI, adjusted for baseline values. We will use mixed models to account for repeated measures when comparing behavioural outcomes over time. Two-sided tests will be used for all analyses. Statistical significance will be inferred at P &lt;0.05. A secondary analysis will be performed for outcome variables unstratified by phenotypic risk. Mediator analyses will use autoregressive mediation path models for individual mediators in Mplus.

The following subgroup analyses will also be performed because the effect of the intervention on behaviour change or psycho-social outcomes may be influenced by these factors:
* Sex: male vs. female
* Age: 1844 vs. 4569 years
* State of residence: Qld, NT, WA, NSW vs. SA, Vic, Tas
* Health literacy: good vs. poor
* Family history of melanoma or a personal history of non-melanoma skin cancer: yes vs. no
* Education: school-only vs higher education
* Socio-Economic Indexes for Areas (SEIFA) Index: high vs. low using median cut-point
* Has children: yes vs. no
* Genomic risk level among the intervention group only: higher than average vs. average vs. lower than average
* Discordant genotype/phenotype groups: 
 (i) low-risk phenotype but high-risk genotype, vs.
 (ii) high-risk phenotype but low-risk genotype, vs.
 (iii) all other combinations
* Risk taking propensity: risk-averse vs risk-seeking

We will use a chi-square test to see if the attrition rate differs by arm. If more than 15% of participants drop out we will use logistic regression to compare baseline characteristics of participants who completed the intervention versus those who did not. Each variable will be examined for the presence of missing data and if &gt;10% is observed on key variables, sensitivity analysis will be performed using complete case analysis or multiple imputation methods. 

Some analyses will also be conducted on the intervention arm participants, to investigate the broader impact of receiving genetic testing results. These analyses will be stratified by genetic risk level (lower than average, average, higher than average).
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/02/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>944</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/07/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney Camperdown NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>16 Marcus Clarke St Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of the Managing Your Risk Study is to evaluate the efficacy of personal genetic risk of melanoma information, compared to standard prevention advice, in motivating preventative behaviours in the general population.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to enroll in this trial if you are aged between 18 and 69 years, have European ancestry, and have never had a melanoma.

Study details
All participants enrolled in this trial will be randomly allocated (by chance) to receive personalised genetic risk of melanoma information and an educational booklet on melanoma preventive behaviours, or to receive the educational booklet only. Participants allocated to the group receiving their genetic risk information will provide a saliva sample using the kit sent via postal mail. This will be used for genetic testing and 2-3 months later, these participants will receive a booklet in the mail containing information on their personal genetic risk of melanoma. With their genetic risk information, participants will be given an educational booklet on melanoma preventive behaviours including sun exposure, sun protection and skin examinations. Within 2 weeks of receiving the mailed booklets, participants will receive a phone call from a genetic counsellor to answer any questions about the information. The other group of participants will receive the educational booklet only, and no genetic risk information information or phone call. All participants will have be able to contact a study-dedicated genetic counsellor at the time of consent to ask any questions they may have. 

All participants will be asked to complete questionnaires and to wear a specialised wrist-worn device (similar in appearance to a watch or a fitbit) which measures sun exposure for 10 days. The questionnaires will be completed and the wrist-worn device will be worn at 3 time points: baseline, at 1 month after participants are sent their booklets, and again at 12 months after baseline.

It is hoped that the findings from this trial will provide information on whether providing information on personalised genetic risk of melanoma motivates people to undertake preventative and early detection behaviours. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Under development</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics and Research Integrity, Margaret Telfer Building (K07) University of Sydney NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Project no. 2017/163</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anne Cust</name>
      <address>The Lifehouse, Level 6 - North
119-143 Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1565</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anne.cust@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amelia Smit</name>
      <address>The Lifehouse, Level 6 - North 
119-143 Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1530</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amelia.smit@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anne Cust</name>
      <address>The Lifehouse, Level 6 - North 
119-143 Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1565</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anne.cust@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anne Cust</name>
      <address>The Lifehouse, Level 6 - North 
119-143 Missenden Rd 
Camperdown NSW 2050
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1565</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anne.cust@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>