<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366597">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000694617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>BRCA-D, a pilot study evaluating a new breast cancer prevention strategy for BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers and high risk, non-BRCA carriers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pre-operative window study evaluating the biological effects of the RANK-Ligand (RANKL) inhibitor Denosumab on normal breast tissue from BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers and high risk, non-BRCA carriers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>BRCA-D</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Denosumab 120 mg monthly subcutaneous injections for 3 months</interventions>
    <comparator>No control</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Ki67 expression assessed by immunohistochemistry in breast epithelium of BRCA1 mutation carriers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Between baseline and after 3 months of denosumab </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of denosumab. Measurements to evaluate this will include vital signs, clinical laboratory tests (haematology, hepatic, renal functions and assessment of albumin-adjusted calcium). Adverse events and project-specific adverse events (osteonecrosis of the jaw, hypocalccemia, wound complications and infections during related to surgery) will also be recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse events will be assessed up to 1 month after the last administration of denosumab. Project specific adverse events will also be recorded up to 3 months after the last administration of denosumab. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in c-KIT, ALDH1 and RANK immunostaining</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 42 days post-final dose of denosumab</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in RANK and RANKL expression in epithelial and stromal cells assessed by immunohistochemistry and gene expression profile</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 42 days post-final dose of denosumab</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in ER and PR expression and associated genes (e.g. BCL-2) using immunohistochemistry and gene expression profiling.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 42 days post-final dose of denosumab</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in luminal cell expression of CK5/6 using immunohistochemistry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 42 days post-final dose of denosumab</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decrease in C-terminal telepeptide (CTX), calcium and free calcium levels using serum assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 42 days post-final dose of denosumab</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in breast tissue parenchymal enhancement using BIRADS score on MRI scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 42 days post-final dose of denosumab</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Documented BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation, or high risk, non-BRCA carriers according to NBOCC guidelines
2. ECOG 0-1
3. Premenopausal status
4. Serum calcium or albumin adjusted calcium &gt;2.0mmol/L and &lt;2.9 mmol/L
5. Must agree to take Calcium and Vitamin D supplementation 
6. Subjects with reproductive potential must be willing to use acceptable methods of effective contraception (with the exception of hormonal contraception)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. BRCA1 or BRCA2 variants that are considered to be non detrimental or where pathogenicity is unknown
2. Active breast cancer
3. Previous irradiation of the breast to be studied
4. Previous bilateral oophorectomy
5. Pregnancy and lactation
6. Hormonal contraception (Mirena IUD is allowed) with a washout period of at least 3 months prior to first dose of study drug
7. Endocrine therapy use in the last 6 months for the purpose of risk reduction
7. History of non-breast malignancies within the last 5 years, except cervical carcinoma in-situ, melanoma in-situ, skin BCC or SCC or Stage 1 thyroid cancer
8. Prior history or current evidence of osteonecrosis of the jaw
9. Active dental/jaw condition requiring oral surgery including tooth extraction
10. Previous treatment with denosumab</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/11/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Melbourne Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Royal Melbourne Hospital, 300 Grattan Street, Parkville, VIC 3050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Amgen</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>115 Cotham Road, Kew, Victoria 3101</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will determine the effects of Denosumab on normal breast tissue in women with BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutations, as well as in women without BRCA mutations but who are at high risk of developing breast cancer based on family history.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a pre-menopausal woman aged between 18 years to 50 years and have documented BRCA1 or BRCA2 mutation considering prophylactic mastectomy, OR willing to undergo two breast biopsies on separate occasions. You may also be eligible if you are not known to carry a BRCA mutation, but meet certain criteria that would deem you to be at high risk of developing breast cancer due to your family history.

Study details
This is a proof-of-concept pilot study to determine if short-term treatment with Denosumab is a feasible chemoprevention option against breast cancer for BRCA1 and BRCA2 mutation carriers, as well as high risk, non-BRCA carriers. All women participating in the study will receive 3 doses of 120mg per dose of Denosumab subcutaneously (injected into the skin) monthly for three months. Women will then proceed to their surgery as planned, or have their second breast biopsy. Participants will be followed up for up to 3 months after the last treatment dose.

The change in the number of doses of Denosumab (from 4 to 3) was implemented in September 2015, after 6 patients had been enrolled.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health HREC Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Melbourne Hospital
300 Grattan Street
Parkville, Victoria, 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014.015</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Geoffrey Lindeman</name>
      <address>Department of Medical Oncology
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
300 Grattan Street
Parkville, 3050 Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61-3-93427151</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lindeman@wehi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kylie Shackleton</name>
      <address>The Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research
1G Royal Parade
Parkville, VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61-3-9345-2805 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shackleton@wehi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sheau Wen Lok</name>
      <address>The Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research
1G Royal Parade
Parkville, VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61-3-9345-2805 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sheau.lok@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>