<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308093">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/10/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000870257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Using n-of-1 trials to determine the effectiveness of paracetamol in advanced
cancer patients on opioids</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>advanced cancer patients  on opioids using n-of-1 trials to determine the effectiveness of paracetamol compared to placebo 
outcome: Difference in mean visual analog scale (VAS) for average pain over the last 24 hours on days 2 and 3 of each cycle pair.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>advanced cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The patient will undergo 3 pairs of 3 day treatments (cycles), making a total of 18 days. The order of drugs in each cycle will be determined by random allocation, blinded to both clinician and patient. Patients complete a daily diary recording pain scores, side effects, which treatment they prefer, and their estimate of which drug they are taking at the time. Data from days 2 and 3 will be used for analysis of that cycle to allow for washout (so day 1 is use das a washout). The drugs being used are long-acting paracetamol 665 mg, and placebo, orally, two capsules three times daily.  

At the end of the trial, the order of medications is unmasked, and compared with the patients observations. Repeated results in the same direction favouring the treatment can be reported in terms of a probability that the result is true. The clinical importance of the result is described by comparing it to a predetermined clinically important change.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator is identical placebo 665 mg,  orally, two capsules three times daily.  At this stage we are working out what the placebo will be made of (an inert filler). The patient will undergo 3 pairs of 3 day treatments (cycles), making a total of 18 days. So 9 days will be on active para- cetamol and 9 days will be on comparator.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in mean VAS for average pain over the last 24 hours on days 2 and 3 of each cycle pair.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each pair of treatment periods</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>As for the primary endpoint, but using subscales of the Brief Pain Inventory (BPI) (worst pain, pain over last 24 hours, pain right now); Patient's Global Impression of Change (PGIC), changes in physical performance on the AKPS (Australian Karnofsky Performance Scale); changes in use of breakthrough pain relief; and frequency and type of paracetamol side effects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>a) Baseline: Age, sex, cancer diagnosis, duration and site of chronic pain, pre-trial analgesia (dose and frequency) and concomitant medications will be collected.
b) Daily self-recording of VAS, BPI, PGIC, any side effects, number of breakthrough medication doses, and any changes in baseline analgesia or concomitant analgesia. The staff will record AKPS at the end of each three day pair.
c) Patient guess of which drug they are taking after each 3 days, and their preferred medicine at the end of each cycle.
d) Compliance check: medication compliance and extent of diary completion at 18 days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients aged &gt;18 years, with: 1) a clinical diagnosis of chronic cancer-related pain (predominantly nocioceptive rather than neuropathic in origin, Leeds Assessment of Neuropathic Symptoms and Signs (LANNS) score (27) &lt;12), with a Brief Pain Inventory (BPI) (28) average pain score of = 3; 2) a stable baseline dose of opioid (excluding codeine or tramadol) with no more than 2 breakthrough doses of opioid per day. The opioid dose will have been stable for at least 5 days prior to commencing the trial; 3) a stable dose of other regular medications for at least five days before the trial commences. Patients already on paracetamol are eligible, but must stop paracetamol 3 days before the trial; 4) no intervention eg radiotherapy, chemotherapy, surgery that might alter pain levels during the 2 weeks prior to the study period or plans to undergo such during the study period. 5) an intact small bowel (necessary for absorption of extended release preparations), no bowel obstruction 6) satisfactory liver function (Aspartate transaminase (AST), Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) = 1.5x upper limit of normal, total bilirubin within
normal range); 7) no known allergy or sensitivity to paracetamol; 8) ability to give fully informed written consent and complete daily pain diaries.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with: 1) an alcohol intake of &gt;3 units/day; 2) cognitive impairment that in the clinicians opinion would preclude fully informed consent or ability to complete study requirements; 3) a poor understanding of written English; 4) life expectancy less than 6 weeks.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/10/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St Lucia Brisbane Queensland 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Gold Coast Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Gold Coast Health Service District
108 Nerang St
Southport Queensland Brisbane 4215</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to determine the effectiveness of paracetamol for treating pain relief in people with advanced cancer who are currently taking opioids. 


Who is it for?
You can join this study if you have advanced cancer with chronic cancer-related pain and you are currently taking opioids to control the pain. 

Trial details
Participants will either start treatment with paracetamol in addition to regular opioids or they will start treatment with a non-active compound (*placebo) plus regular opioids. Participants will then cross-over to receive either placebo (if they started by tak! ing paracetamol) or to receive paracetamol (if they started by taking a placebo).

Participants will undergo 3 pairs of 3 day treatments (cycles), making a total of 18 days. The drugs being used are  paracetamol 500 mg, and placebo, orally, two capsules three times daily. Participants complete a daily diary recording pain scores, side effects, which treatment they prefer, and their estimate of which drug they are taking at the time. 

The study aims to determine the efficacy of paracetamol in alleviating pain in patients with advanced cancer who are taking routine opioids. It will also allow an evaluation of the study techniques (n-of-1 trial design which is when one patient is randomised from one treatment and then to another to allow comparison) and development of appropriate statistical techniques for the analysis of trial data, and where appropriate, provide a means of adjusting for illness progression.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Lucia Brisbane Queensland 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jane Nikles</name>
      <address>School of Medicine
The University of Queensland 
Herston Rd
Herston 4006</address>
      <phone>61 7 3374 3898</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>uqjnikle@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jane Nikles</name>
      <address>School of Medicine
The University of Queensland 
Herston Rd
Herston 4006</address>
      <phone>61 7 3374 3898</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>uqjnikle@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jane Nikles</name>
      <address>School of Medicine
The University of Queensland 
Herston Rd
Herston 4006</address>
      <phone>61 7 3374 3898</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>uqjnikle@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>