<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373444">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001190392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An open label dose-finding, safety and tolerability study of Panitumumab, Irinotecan, Trifluridine/Tipiracil in RAS wild-type patients with metastatic colorectal cancer.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open label phase IB/II, non-randomised, dose-finding, safety and tolerability study of Panitumumab, Irinotecan, Trifluridine/Tipiracil in RAS wild-type patients with metastatic colorectal cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1200-3961 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>PIT Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>colorectal cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Irinotecan (180mg/m2), and Panitumumab  (6mg/Kg), will be administered intravenously (IV) on Day 1 of every 14 day cycle.
Trifluridine/tipiracil will be administered orally (PO) twice a day (BD) on Days 1-5 of every 14 day cycle. Trifluridine/tipiracil will be supplied as 15 mg (comprising 15 mg trifluridine/6.14 mg tipiracil) and 20 mg (comprising 20 mg trifluridine/8.19mg tipiracil)  immediate-release film-coated tablets and the number of tablets needed to achieve the assigned dose will be determined according to the patients body surface area.
Dosing of trifluridine/tipiracil in the dose escalation phase (phase Ib) will be as follows:

Dose Level	Trifluridine/tipiracil
 1 (starting dose)	25 mg/m2 orally, BD
 2	                  30 mg/m2 orally, BD
 3	                  35 mg/m2 orally, BD

The dose escalation phase (phase Ib) will recruit participants who have received and failed one prior chemotherapy regimen for metastatic colorectal cancer (mCRC). It is anticipated that this phase of the study will take 6 months to complete.
The maximum (MTD) will be assessed during the dose escalation phase, where participants will be enrolled in cohorts. Each cohort will consist of a minimum of 3 newly enrolled evaluable patients.  If there is no dose-limiting toxicities (DLT) in the first 3 patients within a cohort, a new cohort at the next dose level will commence. 
If safety data show one patient in a cohort experiencing a DLT, then the cohort will be increased to a maximum of six evaluable patients. If no more than one of the six patients experiences a DLT, then the next dose level may be evaluated. If two or more patients entered in any cohort experience a DLT, then the MTD has been exceeded, and the previous dose level will be considered the MTD. If no dose level has 2 or more DLT`s, then dose level 3 will be considered the MTD. A minimum of 6 evaluable patients will be treated at the dose level before the dose can be declared as the MTD and enrolment into the phase II component can begin.
Cohorts may also be expanded at any dose level to further assess safety parameters as required. If a dose level is opened and patients in the previous cohort subsequently develop unexpected toxicities the cohort will be closed and the previous cohort will be re-assessed with further patients enrolled into the previous cohort as required. 
The maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of tipiracil/trifluridine will be the dose level administered in the expansion phase (phase II). The expansion phase (phase II) will recruit participants that have received no prior treatment for mCRC, and is anticipated to take up to 18 months to complete.
Treatment will continue until disease progression or withdrawal criteria are met.
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase IB: To determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of trifluridine/tipiracil when given in combination with panitumumab, irinotecan.

Dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) will be assessed to determine the MTD. DLTs will be defined as the occurrence of specific drug related adverse events (AEs) during cycle 1 or 2.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During dose escalation phase (Phase Ib) the MTD will be assessed, where participants will be enrolled in cohorts in order to establish the maximum tolerated dose of trifluridine/tipiracil when given in combination with panitumumab, irinotecan. Safety monitoring of DLT's will be conducted at least 4-weekly, or more
frequently if required.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression Free Survival (PFS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>PFS, as assessed by CT scan in accordance with RECIST 1.1, will be assessed at 6 months post enrolment for participants treated at the MTD during the dose expansion phase (Phase II).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and toxicity: Incidence and grade of adverse events (AEs)
Proportions of patients who experience given grades of toxicity will be reported in as well as rates of Grade 3/4 toxicities as defined by the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE v4.03).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety and toxicity will be continuously assessed during the study until 30 days after the last study participant has finished treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective Response Rate (ORR). Objective response rates will be calculated as the number of patients achieving CR or PR using RECIST 1.1 as a proportion of the number of patients who are evaluable for tumour response.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Tumour imaging will be conducted 8 weekly until disease progression. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival (OS). </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured from the date of enrolment to date of death from any cause. Patients remaining alive or lost to follow-up will be censored at the date of last follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria
	Provide a signed and dated Participant Information and Consent Sheet
	Age greater than or equal to 18 years
	Histological diagnosis of colorectal cancer that is RAS/BRAF wild type.
	Metastatic disease not amenable to resection, including borderline resectable cases.
	Measurable disease as assessed by CT scan in accordance with RECIST v1.1 criteria.
	Phase Ib group only: Received and failed one, and only one, prior chemotherapy regimen for mCRC consisting of first-line fluoropyrimidine-based chemotherapy (Treatment failure is defined as radiological progression per RECIST v1.1 criteria after therapy for metastatic disease, prior adjuvant therapy completed &lt;6 months prior to metastatic disease, or toxicity limiting further therapy). 
Phase II group only: previously untreated mCRC.
	Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1 during screening..
	Adequate bone marrow function with haemoglobin &gt;100 g/L, platelets &gt;100 X 109/L; neutrophils &gt;1.5 X 109/L within 7 days of enrolment.
	Adequate renal function, with calculated creatinine clearance &gt;40 ml/min (Cockcroft and Gault) within 7 days of enrolment.
	Adequate hepatic function with serum total bilirubin greater than or equal to 1.25 x upper limit of normal (ULN) range and ALT or AST greater than or equal to 2.5xULN (or greater than or equal to 5xULN if liver metastases present) within 7 days of enrolment
	Magnesium greater than or equal to lower limit of normal within 7 days of enrolment.
	Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.
	Negative pregnancy test within 7 days before commencing study treatment (women of childbearing potential only).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria
	Phase  Ib group only: any history of prior pelvic radiotherapy
	Phase Ib group only: history of prior systemic chemotherapy, immunotherapy, approved proteins/antibodies or any investigational agent within 4 weeks prior to commencing study treatment.
	Radiotherapy within 14 days of commencing study treatment.
	Unresolved toxicities greater than or equal to grade 2 resulting from prior systemic therapy or radiotherapy.
	Any medical or psychiatric conditions that compromise the patients ability to give informed consent or to complete the protocol.
	Prior treatment with EGFR targeting therapies such as cetuximab, panitumumab or erlotinib.
	Prior therapy with irinotecan.
	History of interstitial pneumonitis, pulmonary fibrosis or evidence of interstitial pneumonitis, or pulmonary fibrosis on baseline chest CT scan.
	History of Gilbert syndrome.
	Known cirrhosis, chronic active hepatitis, or chronic persistent hepatitis.
	Patients with active bleeding diathesis.
	Any uncontrolled clinically significant cardiac disease, arrhythmias or angina pectoris
	Active inflammatory bowel disease or other bowel disease causing chronic diarrhoea (defined as Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) greater than or equal to grade 2 [version 4.03])
	Chronic treatment with immunosuppressives.
	Patients with a known history of HIV seropositivity.
	Patients who have any severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions or infections
	Patients who have a history of another primary malignant disease apart from non-melanotic skin cancer or carcinoma in situ of the uterine cervix or any other cancer treated with curative intent &gt;2 years previously without evidence of relapse.
	Known brain metastasis.
	Pregnancy or lactation.
	Women and partners of women of childbearing potential who are not using effective contraception. Highly effective contraception must be used throughout study treatment and for 6 months following the completion of all study treatment.
	Patients with history of serious drug adverse reactions.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Single arm phase Ib/II dose-finding safety and tolerability study.

During the dose-finding (phase Ib) portion participants with mCRC that have received and failed one prior chemotherapy regimen will be enrolled into cohorts in order to establish the maximum tolerated dose of trifluridine/tipiracil in combination with panitumumab and irinotecan.
Once the MTD is established the dose expansion phase (Phase II) participants that have received no prior treatment for mCRC will be recruited.
It is anticipated that approximately 50 patients will be enrolled over a period of 12 months.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>During the dose escalation phase patients will be enrolled in cohorts. Each cohort will consist of a minimum of 3 newly enrolled evaluable patients. If there are not DLTs in the first 3 patients within the cohort, we will proceed to a new cohort at the next dose level (Please refer to the Description of Interventions/exposure). If safety data show one patient in a cohort experiencing a DLT, then the cohort will be increased to a maximum of six evaluable patients. If no more than one of the six patients experiences a DLT, then the next dose level may be evaluated. If two or more patients entered in any cohort experience a DLT, then the MTD has been exceeded, and the previous dose level will be considered the MTD. If no dose level has 2 or more DLT`s, then dose level 3 will be considered the MTD. A minimum of 6 evaluable patients will be treated at the dose level before the dose can be declared as the MTD and enrolment into the phase II component can begin. 
Once the MTD is declared an additional 50 patients will be enrolled in the expansion phase to enable inclusion of a total of 50 measurable patients treated at the MTD.

The primary analysis will be based on the proportion of patients (calculated as the Kaplan-Meier product-limit estimate) who have not progressed by 6 months. Estimates of activity will be described together with the 95% confidence intervals. Time to progression and overall survival will be displayed using Kaplan-Meier survival curves.  Analyses for treatment activity performed on all enrolled patients and, if appropriate, those who have commenced the first cycle of treatment. Exploratory analyses will be performed using univariate and multivariate regression (linear, logistic and proportional hazards) methods.

Objective response rates will be calculated as the number of patients achieving complete or partial response (CR/PR) using RECIST 1.1 as a proportion of the number of patients who are evaluable for tumour response. This rate will also be reported excluding deaths/withdrawals within one month. These rates will be summarised using percentages together with the appropriate 95% confidence intervals. Toxicity will be analysed for patients having received at least one dose of assigned therapy and according to treatment received. Proportions of patients who experience given grades of toxicity will be reported in as well as rates of Grade 3/4 toxicities.
Patients receiving ongoing therapy at a dose level lower than the MTD can dose escalate to the MTD however they will not be evaluable for the phase II component.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/02/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital - Woodville</hospital>
    <hospital>Lyell McEwin Hospital - Elizabeth Vale</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>5011 - Woodville</postcode>
    <postcode>5112 - Elizabeth Vale</postcode>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Central Adelaide Local Health Network Incorporated</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 3, Margaret Graham Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital,
North Terrace, Adelaide
South Australia, 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Institute de Researches Internationales Servier (I.R.I.S.) – Servier Laboratories (Australia) Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50 Rue Carnot 
92284 Suresnes Cedex
France</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>France</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Amgen Australia Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 7
123 Epping Road
North Ryde
NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and assess the efficacy of panitumumab, irinotecan and trifluridine/tipiracil when given in combination for participants with RAS/BRAF wild-type (WT) metastatic colorectal cancer (mCRC).

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above and have a confirmed diagnosis of metastatic colorectal cancer that is RAS/BRAF wild type.

Study details
This study will be conducted in two parts: phase Ib and phase II. The study will commence with a phase Ib dose escalation phase, during which participants will be administered Irinotecan (180mg/m2) and Panitumumab (6mg/Kg) intravenously (IV) on Day 1 of every 14 day cycle, in combination with oral Trifluridine/tipiracil twice a day on Days 1-5 of every 14 day cycle. Dosing of trifluridine/Tipiracil will commence at 25 mg/m2 orally twice a day in the first group. If tolerated, the dose will be elevated for subsequent groups up to a maximum of 35 mg/m2 orally twice a day. Phase II of the study will enrol a separate group of participants who will receive the maximum tolerated dose determined in phase Ib. Treatment in both phases will continue until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity or participant withdrawal.

Participants will be regularly assessed throughout the study in order to monitor safety and tumour response. Follow-up visits will occur every 12 weeks after the end of treatment visit until death or study closure.

It is hoped that this study will provide evidence for further research into this combination, and improve health outcomes for patients with this disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>HREC approved, awaiting Research Governance approval.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (TQEH/LMH/MH)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
Ethics: DX465101
Ground Floor, Basil Hetzel Institute
28 Woodville Road
WOODVILLE SOUTH SA 5011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/08/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/17/TQEH/93</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Timothy Price</name>
      <address>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
Haematology and Oncology
28 Woodville Road
Woodville South
South Australia 5011</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 6000</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 7486</fax>
      <email>PITstudy@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jerneen Williams</name>
      <address>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
Haematology and Oncology
28 Woodville Road
Woodville South
South Australia 5011</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 6410</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 7486</fax>
      <email>PITstudy@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Timothy Price</name>
      <address>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
Haematology and Oncology
28 Woodville Road
Woodville South
South Australia 5011</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 6000</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 7486</fax>
      <email>PITstudy@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jerneen Williams</name>
      <address>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
Haematology and Oncology
28 Woodville Road
Woodville South
South Australia 5011</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 6410</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 7486</fax>
      <email>PITstudy@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>