<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367176">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001092684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot study to assess the effect of Brazil nuts on plasma selenium levels in healthy male volunteers aged 65 years and over
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot study to assess the effect of Brazil nuts on plasma selenium levels in 30 healthy male volunteers aged 65 years and over</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Healthy male volunteers aged 65 years and older. The health condition for which the intervention may be indicated is prostate cancer.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a dose ranging feasibility study. Participants will be assigned to 1 of 3 groups and asked to consume 2, 5 or 10 Brazil nuts, daily for 30 days. At baseline volunteers wil complete a questionnaire on dietary habits, supplement use, and demographic details. Height will be measured at baseline and weight will be measured at baseline and endpoint. Volunteers will be asked to avoid selenium enriched foods (e.g. fish, liver, kidney, and additional Brazil nuts) during the study period, but otherwise they will be asked to continue eating as normal. A 24-hour dietary recall and food frequency questionnaire will be used to verify the types of foods consumed at baseline and endpoint of the study period. Confounding factors will be accounted for.
The Brazil nut (Bertholletia excelsa) is the best source of selenium, a trace element and mineral that is nutritionally essential for human health. Concentration varies between 8 and 83 micrograms/g. Brazil nuts provide a rich natural source of selenium, however limited studies have investigated the bioavailability of selenium in humans.
This pilot study will aid to inform a second pilot study. Pilot study 2 will be in men with advanced prostate cancer (n=20). The study timeframe and Brazil nut dosage will be determined from pilot study 1. The objective is to look at biomarkers of progression observed in prostate cancer. Pilot study 2 will be registered with ANZCTR in the near future.</interventions>
    <comparator>The three different dose groups are being compared, i.e. 2 vs. 5 vs. 10 Brazil nuts daily for 30 days</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in mean selenium response from baseline to 30 days</outcome>
      <timepoint>A blood sample (60 mL of whole blood) will be collected on 3 occasions: at baseline (day 0), midpoint (day 15) and endpoint (day 30) of the intervention. Plasma selenium levels will be assessed.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutritional biomarkers: plasma and whole blood GPx </outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary outcome blood sample will also be used to measure the secondary outcomes. A blood sample (60 mL of whole blood) will be collected on 3 occasions: at baseline (day 0), midpoint (day 15) and endpoint (day 30) of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Selenoprotein P
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary outcome blood sample will also be used to measure the secondary outcomes. A blood sample (60 mL of whole blood) will be collected on 3 occasions: at baseline (day 0), midpoint (day 15) and endpoint (day 30) of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inflammatory marker: C-reactive protein (CRP)</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary outcome blood sample will also be used to measure the secondary outcomes. A blood sample (60 mL of whole blood) will be collected on 3 occasions: at baseline (day 0), midpoint (day 15) and endpoint (day 30) of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible participants include healthy, non-smoking men aged 65 years and older</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Ineligible participants include the presence of nut-allergies and the regular use of a selenium supplement and not willing to discontinue use during the research study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The subjects will be studied consecutively and allocated to one of the three arms in a non-randomised fashion. The first 10 volunteers (Group 1) will receive 2 Brazil nuts daily for 30 days, the following 10 volunteers (Group 2) will receive 5 Brazil nuts daily for 30 days and the last group of 10 volunteers (Group 3) will receive 10 Brazil nuts daily for 30 days.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The statistical methods used for the study objectives/hypotheses (e.g. t-test, chi-squared, multivariate modelling) will be sufficiently detailed. A statistician will be consulted.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/11/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Dietetics Research (C-DIET-R)
School of Human Movement Studies (B#26)
Cnr Blair Drive and Union Road
St Lucia QLD 4072
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Clinical Oncological Society of Australia (COSA)
Funded under the ImoGEX-PC-LycTM Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 14, 477 Pitt Street
Sydney NSW 2000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to investigate the efficacy of Brazil nuts in increasing selenium status in healthy males aged 65 years and older, as this is the average age of prostate cancer diagnosis in Australia. 

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a healthy, non-smoking male aged 65 years or older, who does not have any nut allergies, and does not regularly use a selenium supplement. 

Study design:
Participants in this study will be assigned to 1 of 3 groups and asked to consume 2, 5, or 10 Brazil nuts daily for 30 days. At baseline volunteers will complete a questionnaire on dietary habits, supplement use, and demographic details. Height and weight will also be measured. Volunteers will be asked to avoid selenium enriched foods (e.g. fish, liver, kidney, and additional Brazil nuts) during the study period, but otherwise they will be asked to continue eating as normal. A 24-hour dietary recall and food frequency questionnaire will be used to verify the types of foods consumed at baseline and endpoint of the study period. Participants will also be required to give blood samples at the end of the 30 day study period in order to evaluate blood levels of selenium and other nutritional markers. 

The Brazil nut (Bertholletia excelsa) is the best source of selenium, a trace element and mineral that is nutritionally essential for human health. This antioxidant is the focus of significant recent research in prostate cancer, as it is proposed that selenium may reduce tumour growth and cancer progression. The data from this study will be explored to inform future nutrition intervention studies in men with advanced prostate cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>TBA</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil at present</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Institutional Human Research Ethics Approval</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Queensland 
St Lucia QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014000872</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Vanessa Getliffe</name>
      <address>PhD Candidate
Centre for Dietetics Research (C-DIET-R)
School of Human Movement Studies (26B)
The University of Queensland
Cnr Blair Drive and Union Road
St Lucia Qld 4072
</address>
      <phone>(+61) 7 3365 6669</phone>
      <fax>(+61) 7 3365 6877</fax>
      <email>v.getliffe@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Vanessa Getliffe</name>
      <address>PhD Candidate
Centre for Dietetics Research (C-DIET-R)
School of Human Movement Studies (26B)
The University of Queensland
Cnr Blair Drive and Union Road
St Lucia Qld 4072</address>
      <phone>(+61) 7 3365 6669</phone>
      <fax>(+61) 7 3365 6877</fax>
      <email>v.getliffe@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Olivia Wright</name>
      <address>The University of Queesland
School of Human Movement Studies building (26B)
Room 407, Level 4
St Lucia Qld 4072</address>
      <phone>(+61) 7 3365 6669</phone>
      <fax>(+61) 7 3365 6877</fax>
      <email>o.wright@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Vanessa Getliffe</name>
      <address>PhD Candidate
Centre for Dietetics Research (C-DIET-R)
School of Human Movement Studies (26B)
The University of Queensland
Cnr Blair Drive and Union Road
St Lucia Qld 4072</address>
      <phone>(+61) 7 3365 6669</phone>
      <fax>(+61) 7 3365 6877</fax>
      <email>v.getliffe@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>