<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369852">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000272493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Natural history and properties of naevi in advanced melanoma patients receiving treatment</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A longitudinal, observational study investigating pigmentation genotypes and phenotypic correlations with dermoscopic naevus types and distribution in two participant groups; advanced stage melanoma patients undergoing targeted and/or immunotherapies, and a 'high risk' melanoma patient group. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1178-0726 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>None</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Melanoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will undergo total body examination and mole count, including eye/hair/skin colour and density of freckling.  In addition to total body photography, dermoscopic mole images will be captured using a digital dermoscope. We will require a saliva sample for genetic analysis. Study participants will be followed up every 4 months for one year (4 visits in total). If participants have any moles that are considered atypical by their dermatologist and therefore require excision, we would like to have residual tissue provided following clinical evaluation and diagnosis by the pathologist.  this tissue sample would be used for further genetic analysis. During follow up visits, naevi which show clinical and dermoscopic changes in pigmentation are sampled using a microbiopsy device. DNA and RNA can be isolated from these samples for somatic genotyping.  We will also take shave biopsies of other lesions (up to 3) for histopathology and genetic analysis. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will consist of people considered high risk for melanoma (either by personal or family history, or by atypical mole syndrome), who are not currently undergoing any treatment for melanoma.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early Detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome for the study is from the statistical analysis of the correlation of changing naevi pigmentation characteristics with genotyping and SNP typing of candidate genes in patients receiving treatment for advanced stage melanoma.

Naevi pigmentation characteristics are assessed using total body photography and individual dermoscopic images of naevi &gt; 3mm. 

Genotyping and SNP typing will be done by isolating DNA from saliva samples. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>every 4 months for 1 year.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in somatic genotype/RNA expression profile of naevi that are characteristic of changeable naevi.

Analysis on somatic variations are possible by isolating DNA/RNA from individual naevi skin samples using either the microbiopsy or shave biopsy. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 4 months for 1 year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome for the study is from the statistical analysis of the correlation of changing naevi pigmentation characteristics with genotyping and SNP typing of candidate genes in a volunteer high risk cohort.

Naevi pigmentation characteristics are assessed using total body photography and individual dermoscopic images of naevi &gt; 3mm. 

Genotyping and SNP typing will be done by isolating DNA from saliva samples. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 4 months for 1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Cohort 1: melanoma patients with stage III and IV enrolled for treatment with targeted therapies and/or immunotherapies at the Cancer Services (PA Hospital). Baseline visit must be within 6 weeks of beginning melanoma treatment. 

Cohort 2: participants considered high risk for melanoma under at least one of the following three subcategories;
a)	Personal history of melanoma (stage I-IV, not in situ)
b)	First degree family history of melanoma (stage I-IV, not in situ)
c)	Atypical mole syndrome, defined as grater then 100 naevi, 6 (or more) atypical naevi (confirmed using dermoscopy), AND at least 1 naevus 8 mm (or greater) in dimension.

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>All participants must be able to give informed consent.

All participants are asked to commit to 4 visits to the PA Hospital to participate in the trial over a 12 month period (months 0, 4, 8 and 12), as long as they are able to (Participants can withdraw from the study at any time for any reason). 

Participants in cohort 2 must not be currently undergoing any treatment for melanoma. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>For the cross sectional data, descriptive statistical analyses including counts and proportions will be used to describe the number of naevi (&gt; 3mm) and the average number of dysplastic naevi by participant sex, age and body site. Participants will be grouped by phenotype, or pigmentation/naevus genotype, and the number and type of naevi by body site in each of these subgroups will be summarised. Descriptive statistics will also be used to summarise dermoscopic features of naevi by body site. Depending on the distribution of the outcomes, parametric or non-parametric approaches to bivariate analyses will be considered. 

To assess the unadjusted and adjusted strength of association between participants phenotypic or genotypic characteristics and naevi outcomes, linear or logistic regression models will be fitted, depending on whether the outcome is used in continuous or categorical format. These models will be conducted in crude and adjusted form to ascertain the independent contribution of explanatory factors (for example skin type) on the outcomes.  Interaction terms will also be fitted where appropriate (for example phenotype and genotype) to explain naevus counts or distributions.  

At each timepoint the cross sectional analyses will be repeated, and in addition changes in numbers of naevi over time will be calculated. Repeated measures models will be built to assess changes in naevus number, type or severity over time.

As this is an exploratory observational study, no formal sample size calculation was performed.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>170</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>TRI, 37 Kent Street, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421, Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>none</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to identify genetic differences and dermatological characteristics that pose greater risk for development of skin cancer. 

Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or more and are either undergoing targeted therapies and/or immunotherapies at the Cancer Services (PA Hospital) for stage III or IV melanoma OR if you are considered to be at a high risk of melanoma. 

Study details: This is an observational prospective study (no additional treatment) on the natural history of naevi in advanced melanoma patients receiving treatment. This will include observations of molecular and genetic differences associated with changing naevi and melanoma risk. Patients will be followed up every 4 months for 1 year (4 visits in total) with 3D whole body photography and dermoscopy of all naevi larger than 3mm. The germline genotype is determined by collecting saliva together with baseline demographic data along with images. During follow up visits, naevi which show clinical and dermoscopic changes in pigmentation are sampled using a microbiopsy device. DNA and RNA can be isoalted from these samples for somatic genotyping. The same naevus can be sampled several times over the course of its growth and following visits. Additional shave biopsies (up to 3) will also be taken for comparative purposes. It is hoped that this study will lead to better understanding of genetic and phenotypic characteristics that lead to high risk of melanoma development and that may then assist in early diagnosis and preventative behaviours of skin cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.naevi.centre.uq.edu.au

(not currently live)</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>TRI, Level 7, 37 Kent Street, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QPAH/037</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Queensland
St Lucia
Brisbane </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016000429</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>H. Peter Soyer</name>
      <address>Dermatology Research Centre, School of Medicine, The University of Queensland
TRI, 37 Kent Street, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>61 7 3443 8017</phone>
      <fax>61 7 3443 7779</fax>
      <email>p.soyer@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Clare Primiero</name>
      <address>Dermatology Research Centre, School of Medicine, The University of Queensland
TRI, 37 Kent Street, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>61 7 3443 7496</phone>
      <fax>61 7 3443 7779</fax>
      <email>c.bover@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Clare Primiero</name>
      <address>Dermatology Research Centre, School of Medicine, The University of Queensland
TRI, 37 Kent Street, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>61 7 3443 7496</phone>
      <fax>61 7 3443 7779</fax>
      <email>c.bover@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Clare Primiero</name>
      <address>Dermatology Research Centre, School of Medicine, The University of Queensland
TRI, 37 Kent Street, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>61 7 3443 7496</phone>
      <fax>61 7 3443 7779</fax>
      <email>c.bover@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>