<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368736">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000941561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Australasian Decrease in IntraPelvic Obesity for Surgery trial: Efficacy of a very low energy diet (VLED) to reduce weight and improve outcomes in obese patients undertaking laparoscopic rectal cancer surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Australasian Decrease in Intra-Pelvic Obesity for Surgery trial - A phase III prospective randomised trial comparing using VLEDs to reduce weight in obese patients undergoing laparoscopic rectal cancer surgery versus usual care prior to laparoscopic rectal cancer surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ADIPOSe </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ADIPOSe</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>rectal cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The VLED will be using the Optifast product which is an oral, nutritionally complete, very low calorie diet and limits energy intake to less than 800 calories per day.This involves the use of soups and shakes plus low starch vegetables, calorie free fluids and calorie free lollies and mints in small amounts.The duration is 4-6 weeks prior to surgery.The patients will keep a food diary to monitor adherence..</interventions>
    <comparator>To determine whether the addition of a Very Low Energy Diet (VLED) in the preoperative phase compared to usual care prior to laparoscopic rectal resection for rectal cancer in obese patients improves short term outcomes. Usual care would be dietary advice to lose weight 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite score of surgical factors that are indicative of a standard enhanced recovery following non restorative and restorative proctectomy for rectal cancer.
The composite surgical score of quality will include: Haemaglobin drop of greater than 20g/l and no transfusion, conversion, Anastomotic Leaks or pelvic sepsis, wound complications, 1.	No other complications (including DVT/PE, cardiac or respiratory complications), ambulation by day 2, tolerating normal diet by day 4, and discharge by day 7.  A score out of 8 will be assigned without weighting.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pathological quality:
*Circumferential margin greater than or equal to 1mm.



</outcome>
      <timepoint>at the end of surgery once procedure completed, assessed by Pathologist
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oncological Outcomes:
*Disease free survival and local pelvic recurrence (composite outcome)at three and five year visits from review of hospital records

</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 5 years post surgery completion
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of technical difficulty of the surgery as assessed by the NASA task load index </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-operative - upon surgery completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adipose tissue volume reduction assessed by MRI (abdominal and pelvic)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and Post VLED , Pre-operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance with VLED (calculated as the number of days the patient maintained a VLED as per the patient diary)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately prior to surgery at pre-op visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life (sexual function, bowel and bladder function and recovery parameters) up to 1 year, by questionnaires 
FSFI -female sexual function index
IIEF - the international index of erectile function
IPSS - the international prostate symptom score
EORTC QLQ C30
EORTC QLQ CR29
EORTC QLQ PR25</outcome>
      <timepoint>4-6 weeks, 3months, and 12months post op</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost-effectiveness, both within the trial period and extrapolated to long-term outcomes by review of labour force and income Questionnaires
Labour force and income impacts of illness - at baseline, 3months, 6months and 12months</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pathological quality * Distal resected margin greater than or equal to 2cm (or greater than or equal to 1cm with clear frozen section in the low rectum).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at end of surgery once procedure completed, assessed by Pathologist
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pathological quality *Completeness of TME (A complete TME is defined as a rectal resection specimen which has an intact mesorectum and covering peritoneal envelope all the way to the level of rectal transaction with no coning in of the mesorectum above the point of transection. The surface of the peritoneal covering should be smooth and shiny with no defects exposing the underlying fat.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at the end of surgery once procedure completed, assessed by Pathologist
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pathological quality *Lymph node yield (after Carnoys solution if used)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at the end of surgery once procedure completed, assessed by Pathologist
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oncological outcomes *Overall survival at five years from review of hospital records</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Histological diagnosis of adenocarcinoma of the rectum (where the distal margin of the tumour is less than 15cm from the anal verge as measured at rigid sigmoidoscopy).
T 1-3 N0 M0, T1-3 N1 M0 or T1-3 N0-1 M1 disease as determined by pre-treatment CT scans and or pelvic MRI (or endorectal ultrasound if MRI contraindicated) for rectal cancers.
Body Mass Index (BMI) greater than or equal to 30.
Age greater than or equal to 18 years.
Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status: 0, 1 or 2.
Able and willing to provide written informed consent
Ability to comply with the study protocol (as judged by the responsible surgeon)
Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy or breast feeding.
Any uncontrolled concurrent medical condition.
Any co-morbid disease that would increase risk of morbidity.
Participation in any investigational drug study within the previous 4 weeks.
Evidence of T4 disease extending to circumferential margin of rectum or invading adjacent organs.
Evidence of systemic disease (cardiovascular, renal, hepatic, etc.) that would preclude surgery, or other severe incapacitating disease, i.e. ASA IV (a patient with severe systemic disease that is a constant threat to life) or ASA V (a moribund patient who is not expected to survive without the operation).
History of conditions that would preclude use of a laparoscopic approach (e.g. multiple previous major laparotomies, severe adhesions).
Concurrent or previous invasive pelvic malignancy (cervical, uterine and rectal) within five years prior to registration.
Short course radiotherapy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>On confirmation of eligibility, patients will be recruited through the hospital, clinic or surgeons' rooms at each site.  Only authorised staff are eligible to access the randomisation system. Upon verification of site accreditation, patient eligibility, that documentation is correct and complete, a check is performed to ensure that patient duplication will not occur, before allocation to either treatment arm is performed. This allocation is by an electronic randomisation system which generates patient study ID and treatment arm using a computer.
Patients will be randomised to either VLED or usual care prior to laparoscopic resection of rectal carcinoma.
Confirmation of randomisation, patient ID and treatment arm is then established</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)
Stratified allocation by
 - BMI =30-40, &gt;40
 - Pre-op treatment</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary analysis will be according to the intention-to-treat (ITT) principal. Comparisons on the proportion of successful resections in each treatment group will be performed using a test of proportions and the difference between the control and intervention groups together with the 95% CI will be presented. Non-inferiority will be declared if the lower bound of the one-sided 95% CI for the difference between proportions is 8%. The notional significance level is 5%. Secondary analyses will adjust for significant prognostic factors using suitable regression models. Results will be provided with estimates and the appropriate confidence intervals where feasible. Time to event outcomes will be described using Kaplan-Meier curves (if appropriate) and proportional hazards models will be used to examine the impact of predictors on these outcomes.The outcome tested is mean testing of a composite score for surgical morbidity. This score has been summarized above. The investigators anticipate that a mean of 6.75 out of 8 will be anticipated in the patients who comply with VLED treatment. In the group whom do not take the VLED pre-therapy, we expect a mean score of 4.5 out of 8. 
Using a two- sided significance level of 95% with a power estimate of 80%, and with the ratio of sample size of exposed to non-exposed being 1. Using Fleiss calculations for sample size and adjusting for continuity correction we would anticipate requiring 48 patients in each arm, and therefore in total 96 patients. The investigators will therefore aim to accrue 100 patients. This means we will accrue 50 in each arm. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/10/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>8</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>Cabrini Hospital - Malvern - Malvern</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>The Wesley Hospital - Auchenflower</hospital>
    <hospital>St Andrew's War Memorial Hospital - Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Holy Spirit Northside - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>John Hunter Hospital - New Lambton</hospital>
    <hospital>Newcastle Private Hospital - New Lambton Heights</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast University Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
    <postcode>3144 - Malvern</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>4006 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>4066 - Auchenflower</postcode>
    <postcode>4000 - Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
    <postcode>2305 - New Lambton</postcode>
    <postcode>2305 - New Lambton Heights</postcode>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Takapuna, Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suite 27
Cabrini Medical Centre
Isabella St,
Malvern VIC 3144 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cabrini Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>181-183 Wattletree Road
Malvern VIC 3144 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Colorectal Surgical Society of Australia and New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>9 Church St, 
Hawthorn 3122
Victoria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Private donor</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>unknown</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>none</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to determine whether a very low energy diet (VLED) can reduce weight and improve outcomes in obese patients undergoing surgery for rectal cancer. Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or over with a BMI greater than or equal to 30 and have been diagnosed with adenocarcinoma of the rectum for which surgery has been prescribed. Study details Participants will be randomly allocated (by chance) to either the Optifast diet treatment, or the usual care treatment. Participants on the Optifast diet treatment will be restricted to  800 calories  or less per day for 4 - 6 weeks before the surgery, using the Optifast diet products including nutritionally complete soup sand shakes. Participants in the usual care treatment group will receive care and advice prior to their surgery as normal. Patient outcomes will then be assessed at visits in the hospital stay at day three, then at day 14, four to six weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, 12 months, 18 months and 24 months after discharge. Further long-term follow-up will be conducted annually for an additional three (3) years after the 24 months follow up visit at which participants will undergo a blood sample and physical examination. It is hoped that the findings of this trial will increase understanding of the potential benefits of a VLED prior to surgery in obese patients with rectal cancers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Health
55 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004
PO Box 315 Prahran
VIC 3181 Australia
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/Alfred/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Stephen Bell</name>
      <address>Suite 27
Cabrini Medical Centre
Isabella St,
Malvern
Victoria
3144</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9509 8033</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>swbell@acgroup.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name> Stephen Bell</name>
      <address>Suite 27
Cabrini Medical Centre
Isabella St,
Malvern
3144
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9508 3525</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ADIPOSe@cabrini.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name> Stephen Bell</name>
      <address>Suite 27
Cabrini Medical Centre
Isabella St,
Malvern
Victoria
3144</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9508 3525</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ADIPOSe@cabrini.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Michelle Hooy</name>
      <address>Clinical Trial Centre  CCRE in Therapeutics
Department of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine
School of Public Health and Preventive Medicine
Monash University
Caulfield Hospital
Grnd Floor, Fethers Block
260 Kooyong Road, 
Caulfield VIC 3162




 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 6166</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 6249</fax>
      <email>michelle.hooy@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>