<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362222">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000931875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Melatonin versus placebo for prevention of delirium in inpatients with advanced cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised double blind placebo controlled pilot phase II trial of oral melatonin for the prevention of delirium in hospital in people with advanced cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1133-5010</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Advanced cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Delirium</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Oral, prolonged-release melatonin (2mg) every night for the duration of inpatient admission.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (amino methacrylate co-polymer tablet)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of eligible patients screened who progress to be randomised and complete study intervention</outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge or death</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preliminary data on efficacy of melatonin versus placebo on number of delirium events and time to first incident delirium to inform sample size calculation for a definitive Phase III trial (defined as equal to or greater than 17.75 on Delirium Rating Scale-98-Revised [DRS-98-R])</outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge or death</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preliminary data on efficacy of melatonin versus placebo on delirium symptom and time profile, subtype, severity and duration (as measured by DRS-98-R)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily during delirium episodes until discharge or death</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preliminary data on efficacy of melatonin versus placebo on sleep quality (as measured by Insomnia Severity Index [ISI])</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, then every 5 days for duration of inpatient admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preliminary data on toxicity of melatonin, in particular sedation (measured by Richmond Agitation Sedation Scale [RASS])</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily during inpatient admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preliminary data on pathophysiology via levels of neuronal apoptosis markers, and melatonin, serotonin and tryptophan (serum assays)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and upon occurrence of any delirium episodes until discharge or death</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preliminary data on health outcomes (function, survival, medical complications associated with delirium such as falls, pressure areas, pneumonia) and health services utilisation (length of stay and in hospital resource utilisation) to inform an economic evaluation component of the definitive phase III study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge or death</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of advanced cancer defined by the intent of treatment being no longer curative; 

Admission to an acute or subacute inpatient palliative care or oncology facility;

Capacity to give written informed consent;

English speaking;

Participant is capable of completing assessments and complying with the study procedures.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability to communicate in English;

Inability to take medications orally or via gastrostomy tube;

Delirium on admission as defined by the cut-off score on DRS-98-R equal to or greater than 17.75 indicative of delirium;

Australian Karnofsky Performance Status (AKPS) less than 31;

Known allergy to melatonin or placebo content;

Active seizure disorder defined as seizure within last one month, or seizure disorder not on anticonvulsants (due to pro-convulsive effect of melatonin in children and severe epilepsy);

Concomitant cimetidine use (CYP2D Inhibitor increases melatonin plasma levels by 1.7 fold);

Patients with a current history of abuse of alcohol (alcohol reduces melatonin levels);

In people taking warfarin a markedly nontherapeutic international normalized ratio (INR) defined as less than 1 or more than 4 (due to melatonin both causing increase and decreased INR);

Moderate to severe dementia as defined by clinical diagnosis of dementia and a Short Blessed Test (SBT) score of equal to or greater than 10;

Current use of melatonin for other indication, or use of melatonin within last 14 days;

Pregnancy or breastfeeding;

Participants who have participated in a clinical study of a new chemical entity within the month prior to study entry.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>At each centre, people referred to the study will be sequentially allocated an ID number.  This ID number will be used for all subsequent study documentation for that participant.

On notification of a participant, the pharmacist at each site will consult the strata table according to the strata determined by supplied randomization schedule, and will allocate the next code available according to the supplied strata table and dispensed the active or inactive medicine delivered in the labeled bottle. The participant ID, allocation code, dates of request, preparation, and dispensing will be recorded in a log maintained by the pharmacist and supplied to the central registry on each randomisation.

At all times, from eligibility screening to completion of the study, all study staff are unaware of the treatment allocation. Allocation is concealed from the investigator at the time of the participant inclusion in the trial; the allocation is determined by contacting the site pharmacy.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation schedules will be developed for each site using random number tables, generated at an independent central registry.  Treatment for each participant will be allocated according to a block randomisation schedule in a 1:1 ratio.  Block randomisation will ensure even allocation to each code.  The central registry will supply site randomisation schedules to each site pharmacy.  There will be stratification at the randomisation level for this study by site of admission (palliative care and oncology).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>12/03/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Braeside Hospital - Prairiewood</hospital>
    <hospital>Calvary Mater Newcastle - Waratah</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Barwon Health - McKellar Centre campus - North Geelong</hospital>
    <postcode>2164</postcode>
    <postcode>2310</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Royal Melbourne Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>3215 - North Geelong</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Flinders University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Flinders Drive, Bedford Park, SA 5042.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Institute NSW</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Australian Technology Park
Level 9, 8 Central Avenue
EVELEIGH NSW 2015
AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Bruyere Continuing Care</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Palliative Care Administration
Bruyere Continuing Care
43 Rue Bruyere St
Ottawa
Ontario
K1N 5C8</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Canada</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will determine the feasibility and acceptability of using melatonin for the prevention of delirium in patients with advanced cancer.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above, and have a diagnosis of advanced cancer defined by the intent of treatment being no longer curative. You need to also be an inpatient at a palliative care or oncology facility. Trial details Participants in this trial will be randomly (by chance) allocated to one of two groups. Participants in one group will take 2mg of melatonin by mouth every night for the duration of inpatient admission, and those in the other group will take a placebo (sham) treatment instead. Participants will not know which group they are in. Participants will be assessed during their admission to evaluate the efficacy of melatonin in preventing delirium events and to evaluate any effects on sleep quality, toxicity and other health outcomes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cancer Institute NSW</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/CIC/8</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Western Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 7103, Liverpool BC, NSW 1871</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/12/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/LPOOL/350</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/11/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Meera Agar</name>
      <address>Braeside Hospital, Locked Bag 82, Wetherill Park, NSW 2164</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9616 8654</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9616 8657</fax>
      <email>meera.agar@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tim Luckett</name>
      <address>University of Technology Sydney (UTS), Faculty of Health, Building 10, Level 7, 235-253 Jones St, Ultimo, NSW 2007</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4861</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9514 4474</fax>
      <email>t.luckett@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tim Luckett</name>
      <address>University of Technology Sydney (UTS), Faculty of Health, Building 10, Level 7, 235-253 Jones St, Ultimo, NSW 2007</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4861</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9514 4474</fax>
      <email>t.luckett@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Meera Agar</name>
      <address>Braeside Hospital, Locked Bag 82, Wetherill Park, NSW 2164 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9616 8654 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9616 8657  </fax>
      <email>meera.agar@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>