<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362100">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000473864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised phase 2 study of carboplatin with oral vinorelbine followed by maintenance therapy with oral vinorelbine or erlotinib in elderly patients with metastatic non-small cell lung cancer.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized phase 2 study to evaluate the effect of carboplatin with oral vinorelbine (navelbine [Registered Trademark]) followed by maintenance therapy with oral vinorelbine (navelbine [Registered Trademark]) or erlotinib (Tarceva [Registered Trademark]) on quality of life and progression free survival in metastatic non-small cell lung cancer in elderly patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>OMEN</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non Small Cell Lung Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Non small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Oral Vinorelbine 60mg/m2 on day 1 and day 8 of 21 day cycle for 1st 2 cycles and then escalated to 80mg/m2 on day 1 and day 8 for further 2 cycles if no grade 3 toxicities were noticed, in combination with intravenous carboplatin at a  dose calculated according to the formula of Calvert at AUC of 5, on day 1 of 21 day cycle. This induction treatment will be given  for up to four cycles. Then maintenance treatment with either oral vinorelbine at dose given at the last cycle of induction therapy on day 1 and day 8 of 21 day cycle or Erlotinib 150mg orally continuously every day. The maintenance treatment with vinorelbine or Erlotinib will commence 3 weeks after the last cycle in induction phase of chemotherapy and will continue until documented disease progression, unaccepable toxicities, patient's refusal or investigatior's decision based on the best interests of the patient.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparison is between maintainence treatment with either Erlotinib 150 mg orally every day or oral Vinorelbine at the same dose given at the last cycle of induction chemotherapy on day 1 and day 8 of 21 day cycle to be commenced after 3 weeks of completion of induction treatment. Both groups will receive the same induction treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 1: To determine quality of life using the EORTC QLC 30 and LC 13 subscale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary Endpoint: assessed by qauality of life questionaire (EORTC QLC 30 and LC 13 subscale) every 6 weeks until disease progression, death or unacceptible toxicities.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 2: To determine the progression free survival (defined as time from randomization till disease progression or death due to any reason) of elderly patients receiving maintenance therapy with oral vinorelbine or erlotinib following combination chemotherapy with up to 4 cycles of carboplatin and oral vinorelbine.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome 2:assessed by performing CT scans every 6 weeks until disease progression, death or unacceptible toxicities.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 1: To further determine the response rate, duration of response, and overall survival.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcome 1: assessed by performing CT scans every 6 weeks until disease progression, death or unacceptible toxicities.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 2: To assess the safety and toxicity profile of maintenance therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcome 2: Assessed every 3 weeks in induction phase by history, clinical examination and blood tests and 6 weekly in maintenance phase</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients &gt; 70 years old, 
2. Histologically or cytologically proven non-small cell lung cancer,
3. Stage 3B (not suitable for radical radiotherapy) or stage 4(7th IALC staging edition),
4. PS  0-1
5. Life expectancy &gt; 12 weeks
6. Adequate bone marrow, hepatic and renal function</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>70</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Known hypersensitivity to drugs with similar chemical structures to study medication,
2. Active CNS disorder, symptomatic brain or leptomeningeal metastasis or CNS disease requiring steroid therapy,
3. Symptomatic neuropathy (sensory) &gt; grade 1 according to the NCI Common Toxicity Criteria,
4. Cardiovascular disease (uncontrolled cardiac failure, or myocardial infraction within the previous 3 months, uncontrolled hypertension or arrhythmia),
5. Active infection requiring i.v. antibiotics within 2 weeks before the beginning of treatment,
6. Superior vena cava syndrome,
7. Long term oxygen therapy,
8. Unstable pleural effusion,
9. Unstable ascites or pericardial effusion,
10. History of another malignancy within the past five years except basal cell carcinoma of the skin or carcinoma in situ of the cervix,
11. Radiotherapy within the previous 2 weeks,
12. Concomitant treatment with any other anticancer agent,
13. Uncontrolled hypercalcaemia,
14. Unstable concomitant disease,
15. Concomitant treatment with corticosteroids except chronic treatment ( &gt; 1 month) at low dosing ( &lt; 20 mg/ day of methylprednisolone or equivalent),
16. Significant malabsorption syndrome or disease affecting the gastro-intestinal tract function,
17. Participation to another clinical trial with any investigational drug study (whatever the use, curative, prophylactic or diagnostic intent) within 30 days prior to study screening.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All eligible patients will be given induction chemotherapy with oral Vinorelbie with Carboplatin every 3 weeks for up to 4 cycles. Pateints with non progressive disease will be randomised to receive either oral Vinorelbine or oral Erlotinib until disese progression, unacceptable toxicities, death of patient withdrawal from the study. Method used for allocation concealment will be through central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Southern Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton
Vic 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Pierre Fabre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 3B, 1 Richardson Place
North Ryde
NSW 2113
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will evaluate the safety and efficacy of induction chemotherapy followed by maintenance with one of the two different drugs in elderly patients with metastatic non-small cell lung cancer.

Who is it for?
you may be eligible to join this study if you are male or female above 70 years and you have been diagnosed with metastatic non-small cell lung cancer.

Trial details
All participants will undergo upto 4 x 3 weeks cycles of induction chemotherapy with the drugs vinorelbine (taken as an oral tablet) and carboplatin administered into the vein (intravenously). Participants whose disease has not progressed will then be randomly (by chance) allocated to one of two groups. One group will take a vinorelbine capsule on day 1 and 8 of 3 week cycle. Participants in the other group will take one Erlotinib tablet every day. Participants in both groups will take the treatment till progression of disease, unacceptable side effects or if patient chooses not to continue the treatment.
Participants will be assessed every 3-6 weeks until disease progression, death or unacceptable toxicities in order to determine quality of life and response to treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton
Vic 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>11371A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Peter Briggs</name>
      <address>Director of Medical Oncology
Monash Medical Centre
823-865 Centre Road
East Bentleigh
Victoria 3165</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9928 8120</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 3 9928 8341</fax>
      <email>peter.briggs@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Peter Midolo</name>
      <address>Oncology Trials Manager
Monash Medical Centre
823-865 Centre Road
East Bentleigh
Victoria 3165</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9928 8195</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 3 9928 8341</fax>
      <email>peter.midolo@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Laima Muceniekas</name>
      <address>Monash Medical Centre
823-865 Centre Rd
East Bentleigh 
Victoria 3165</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 99288754</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 3 99288909</fax>
      <email>Laima.Muceniekas@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>