<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1472">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/07/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/07/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000314527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Multi-Center, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Parallel Design, 2-Arm Study to Investigate the Effect of Aprotinin on Transfusion Requirements in Patients Undergoing Surgical Procedures for Lung Cancer or Esophageal Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Multi-Center, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Parallel Design, 2-Arm Study to Investigate the Effect of Aprotinin on Transfusion Requirements in Patients Undergoing Surgical Procedures for Lung Cancer or Esophageal Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Bay a0128 / 11800</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ClinicalTrials.gov: NCT00306137</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Lung Cancer or Esophageal Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Oesophageal (gullet)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Mesothelioma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Non small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This trial is a randomized, double-blind, multi-center, 2 arm, parallel design study of aprotinin (Trasylol) versus placebo in subjects  undergoing selected surgeries on the  lung consisting of  planned complete primary pneumonectomy or other pulmonary resection with high likelihood of blood transfusion, completion pneumonectomy or decortication for lung cancer, or undergoing esophagectomy (by transthoracic or transhiatal approach) for esophageal cancer. Prior to skin incision 2 million kallikrein-inhibiting units (KIU) of aprotin will be given by intravenous infusion, followed by 500,000 KIU/hour until the of surgery.</interventions>
    <comparator>Prior to skin incision matching placebo will be given by intravenous infusion, followed by 500,000 KIU/hour until the of surgery.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The objective of this study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of aprotinin as compared to placebo, in reducing the need for blood transfusion in patients undergoing surgery for lung cancer or esophageal cancer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of units of blood or packed red cells transfused. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The intra-operative blood loss.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The drainage volume from the operative site. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Transfusion of platelets, colloids, plasma and number of patients requiring these products</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change from preoperative hemoglobin concentration to postoperative hemoglobin concentration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Surgeons assessment of the degree to which bleeding obscures his/her view of the surgical field, relative to past, similar procedures.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in blood markers related to inflammation and blood coagulation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to discontinuing of mechanical ventilation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in the patients health related quality of life (HRQoL) measured using the Functional Assessment of cancer therapy-Esophageal Cancer (FACT-E) or Functional Assessment of cancer therapy-Lung Cancer (FACT-L) questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subjects requiring protocol specified oncological surgery. Subjects must have histological or cytological confirmation of malignancy in lung or esophagus.Documented, signed, dated informed consent obtained prior to any study specific procedures being performed. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects with previous exposure to aprotinin in the last 6 months. Subjects with a known or suspected allergy to aprotinin.Subjects undergoing laparoscopic surgery resection.Subjects undergoing thoracoscopic resection or simple lobectomy as the planned procedure.Subjects undergoing any palliative operation.Subjects with sepsis.Subjects with mesothelioma.Subjects with impaired renal function.Subjects with a history of bleeding diathesis or known coagulation factor deficiency. Subjects with failure of a major organ system or any active significant medical illness that in the opinion of the Investigator is likely to affect the subjects ability to complete the study or precludes the subjects participation in the study.Subjects who refuse to receive allogenic blood products for religious or other reasons.Subjects whose preoperative red blood cell volume is so low that a blood transfusion will have to be given perioperatively.Subjects with a history of deep vein thrombosis or pulmonary embolism.Subjects who are pregnant or women of childbearing potential in whom the possibility of pregnancy cannot be excluded by a negative serum pregnancy test at screening and who are not using a reliable method of contraception.Women of childbearing potential who are not using a reliable method of contraception. Use of other antifibrinolytic agents.Subjects on a chronic anti-coagulant treatment with warfarin vitamin K antagonists where it can not be discontinued presurgery for the surgical procedure.Subjects on an investigational drug in the 30 days prior to screening or during the trial before the 6 week follow-up visit. Subjects involved in trials of marketed cancer therapy medications (including those approved for another indication) or combination with radiotherapy are allowed. Subjects with known drug hypersensitivity, subjects with an allergic diathesis, and subjects who have been treated with aprotinin more than 6 month ago. For subjects for whom there is a suspicion of previous treatment with aprotinin, they may be included in the study only if precautions as outlined in the protocol are undertaken.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The packaging and dosage will be such, that the different treatment groups will appear identical. Ana interactive voice response system will be used to accomplish a blind allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated random code.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/07/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>696</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bayer Australia Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>875 Pacific Highway Pymble NSW 2073</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bayer Australia Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>875 Pacific Highway, Pymble NSW 2073</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This trial is a randomized, double-blind (investigator and patient), multi-center, 2 arm, parallel design study of aprotinin (Trasylol) versus placebo in subjects  undergoing selected surgeries on the  lung consisting of  planned complete primary pneumonectomy or other pulmonary resection with high likelihood of blood transfusion, completion pneumonectomy or decortication for lung cancer, or undergoing esophagectomy (by transthoracic or transhiatal approach) for esophageal cancer. The aprotinin or placebo will be given by intravenous infusion until the end of the surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queen Elizabeth Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress> Adelaide, South Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/07/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>20060307</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Medical Services Manager</name>
      <address>Bayer Australia Limited PO Box 903 Pymble NSW 2073</address>
      <phone>02 9391 6147</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jane.worrallo@bayerhealthcare.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clinical Research Manager</name>
      <address>Bayer Australia Limited PO Box 903 Pymble NSW 2073</address>
      <phone>02 9391 6140</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alana.chandler@bayerhealthcare.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>