<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367450">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/12/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001279617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Body composition assessment of children undergoing treatment for cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Study to examine the body composition of children undergoing treatment for cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1164-1982 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>NAT Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Leukaemia &amp; Lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Brain</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Other</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All children participating in the study will have their height and weight measured on arrival at the centre. The Paediatric Oncology Assessment Tool will be completed before any body composition measurements are taken.  Mid arm circumferences will be taken using a tape measure and following standard guidelines. Skinfolds will be measured using calibrated calipers and following the strict standard site protocol. Measurements will be taken at the biceps, triceps, subscapular and suprailiac sites. 

Total body potassium (TBK) analysis will be performed using a shadow shield whole-body counter (Accuscan, Canberra Industries, MA, USA), which contains three sodium iodide crystal scintillation detectors arranged above a scanning bed. The crystals detect the 1.46MeV gamma rays being emitted by the potassium-40 (40K) found in the body.  As a fixed proportion of the bodys potassium occurs as the natural isotope 40K, TBK can be determined. The measurement of TBK will require the subject to lie supine on a bed that is moved under the detectors. Two 1100sec scans will be performed for each subject with all personal metallic objects having been removed. Background and sensitivity checks will be completed daily and considered in each measurement, with TBK in grams being reported. Body cell mass (BCM) will then be calculated from TBK and adjusted for body size (BCM/HTp). BCM/HTp will be expressed as a Z score relative to laboratory reference data. 

ADP measurement will be performed using the Bod Pod (registered trademark)  Body Composition System, adhering to the manufacturers instructions (Life Measurement Inc, Concord, CA, USA; software version 1.69). Prior to each measurement, the Bod Pod will be calibrated at zero litres and with a standard calibration cylinder of 50 litres. The child is required to wear a swimming costume and swimming cap (both may be provided by the laboratory, specially laundered, if the child does not have their own) during the test.  Body volume measurements will be taken as the subject sits inside the chamber for a 50 second period. The measurement will be completed twice or until the body volume measurements are within 150ml or 0.2% of each other, whichever was the smallest (maximum of three attempts). The average of the two successful measurements will be taken. The thoracic gas volume is then measured using the Bod Pod while the child breaths into a disposable tube.  The ADP measurement will take approximately 10 minutes. Percent fat measurement will be estimated from the body volume measurements, using child specific equations. 
All testing will take place during 1 visit and take approximately 1.5 hours. </interventions>
    <comparator>Patients will be compared to age and sex healthy matched controls</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Cell Mass using total body potassium counting</outcome>
      <timepoint>During treatment - Cross-sectional study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent Fat using air displacement plethysmography (bodpod)</outcome>
      <timepoint>During treatment - cross sectional study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Mass Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>During Treatment - cross sectional study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Being treated for cancer at Royal Children's Hospital</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>2) Too unwell to undergo testing</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>14/12/2004</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>8/05/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>64</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Children's Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Royal Brisbane Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Alexia Murphy</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Children's Nutrition Research Centre
Level 4 RCHF Building
Herston Rd
RCH, Herston QLD,  4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Children's Nutrition Research Centre, The University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Queensland 
CNRC 
Level 4 RCHF Building
Herston Rd
Herston. QLD 4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Peter Davies</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Children's Nutrition Research Centre
Level 4 RCHF Building
Herston Rd
RCH, Herston QLD,  4029</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to validate the Pediatric Oncology Nutrition Assessment Tool against body composition measurements of nutritional status. Once the Tool has been validated it will play an essential part in the overall assessment of pediatric oncology patient in centers throughout Australia and assist in the prevention of severe nutritional problems in pediatric oncology patients. 

Patients diagnosed with an oncological disease between the ages of 5.00 and 17.99 years will be recruited from the Royal Childrens Hospital. Caregivers will be asked to accompany the patient to the Body Composition Laboratory for approximately an hour and a half period. Firstly, the Paediatric Oncology Assessment Tool will be completed by the investigator. Height, weight, total body potassium, air displacement plethysmography, skinfolds and mid arm circumference measurements will then be taken on all patients. Children and/or parent, may choose to have all or any combination of measurements. All tests performed will be non-invasive, painless and pose no known physical risk to patients.  


</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>White M, Murphy AJ, Davies PSW. (2011). Correlation between nutrition assessment data and percent body fat via plethysmography in pediatric oncology patients. Journal of Parental and Enteral Nutrition. 35(6):715-22.

Murphy AJ, White MS, Davies PSW. (2010). Body Composition of children with cancer. American Journal of Clinical Nutrition. 92(1):55-60. 

Murphy AJ, White MS, Davies PSW. (2009). The Validity of Simple Methods to Detect Malnutrition in Pediatric Oncology Patients. British Journal of Nutrition. 101(9):1388-92. 
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/11/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alexia Murphy</name>
      <address>Children's Nutrition Research Center
Level 4 RCHF Building
Herston Rd
Royal Children's Hospital Herston Qld 4029</address>
      <phone>+61733464994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alexia.murphy@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alexia Murphy</name>
      <address>Children's Nutrition Research Center
Level 4 RCHF Building
Herston Rd
Royal Children's Hospital Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61733464994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alexia.murphy@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alexia Murphy</name>
      <address>Children's Nutrition Research Center
Level 4 RCHF Building
Herston Rd
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61733464994</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alexia.murphy@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>