<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372692">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000707369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prospective randomised controlled study of pharyngo-oesophageal  dilatation in Head and Neck cancer therapy-induced dysphagia: Evaluation of efficacy and safety</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective randomised controlled study of pharyngo-oesophageal  dilatation in Head and Neck cancer therapy-induced dysphagia: Evaluation of efficacy and safety</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NHMRC APP1046882 </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>dysphagia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>head and neck cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Head and neck</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Recruited participants are randomised into 2 groups: 1) treatment arm; 2) placebo arm. 

All participants will undergo a diagnostic endoscopic examination (standard of practice) using a gastroscope with an outer diameter of 9.2mm (Olympus GIF-H190, Olympus Corp, Tokyo), at Day Surgery St Goerge Hospital. Sedation is administered by anaesthesiologists using fentanyl, midazolam, and propofol. 

Participants allocated to the treatment arm will receive a series of endoscopic dilatations at of the pharyngo-oesophageal junction at the time endoscopy. Endoscopic dilatations are performed using bougie dilators (Savary-Gilliard, Wilson-Cook Medical, Winston-Salem, NC, USA). The selection of initial dilator size is based on an estimated lumen diameter from endoscopic view as determined by experienced gastroenterologist consultants. Dilators are passed sequentially in increments of 1mm diameter with periodic inspection following some or all dilator passages until one or more of the following is reached: 1) mucosal tear identified upon re-inspection, or 2) a maximal dilator diameter of 16mm is passed. Based on our pilot data [Paramsohthy, S et al. Gastroenterology 2012 suppl), a median of 3 dilatations per patient was necessary to achieve an adequate clinical response. Hence, patients are re-scheduled for repeat dilatation at 2 weekly intervals until 1) satisfactory clinical response is achieved on global assessment; or 2) a maximal dilator of 16mm is passed; or 3) further increment in dilator size is considered unsafe. 

Participants allocated to placebo arm will receive no endoscopic dilatation. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants who are randomised into the placebo arm will undergo one session of endoscopic examination with no dilatation of the pharyngo-oesophageal junction. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Short-term clinical response 3-months after the endoscopic dilatation, defined as 1) a decrease in Sydney Swallow Questionnaire score by 200 or more; and 2) satisfactory response based on the global assessment. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3-months after treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relapse of dysphagia, defined as 1) an increase in Sydney Swallow Questionnaire score to within 20% of pre-dilatation baseline; and 2) clinical need for intervention. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up up to 24 months post-dilatation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) self-reported problematic pharyngeal dysphagia 12 months beyond the surgeries and chemoradiation for head and neck cancer; 2) abnormal Sydney Swallow Questionnaire score (above 234). </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) local cancer recurrence; 2) any neurological disorders known to cause pharyngeal dysfunction (e.g. Parkinson's disease, cerebral vascular accident, inflammatory myopathy, motor neuron disease). </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer will generate allocation sequence for recruited participants. Allocation envelopes are sealed in opaque envelopes that are kept off-site. Concealed envelopes are provided to the proceduralists, and are opened once the participants are under sedation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation involving 2 strata:
1) Head and Neck Cancer treatment history: Chemoradiation only vs. Total Laryngectomy. 
2) Dysphagia treatment history: Previous Dilatation vs. No Previous Dilatation. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation: The therapeutic response rate of endoscopic dilatation in the target popultion in existing case series ranged between 67% to 75%. Accepting 65% response rate and 20% placebo response, a total sample size of 44 (22 patients per treatment arm) was estimated (a 0.05 and power 0.8, Fishers exact test).

Statistical analysis: Categorical baseline variables were compared using chi-square tests. Continuous baseline variables are presented as means with 95% confidence intervals, and were compared using unpaired Students t-test. Intention to treat analysis will be used to compare the clinical response rate between the two treatment groups, using Chi-squares test. Paired Students t-test will be used to compare the within-subject changes in Sydney Swallow Questionnaire score. Chi-squares test was used for subgroup and risk factor analysis. Kaplan-Meier analysis was used to determine dysphagia relapse rate. Cox regression was used to determine risk factors for relapse of dysphagia. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>31/01/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>44</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/03/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St George &amp; Sutherland Clinical School, University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Clinical Sciences (WRPitney) Building, Short Street, St George Hospital, Kogarah NSW 2217</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>16 Marcus Clarke Street, Canberra City, ACT 2600 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this trial is to evaluate the efficacy of pharyngo-oesophageal dilatation for improving ease and comfort of swallowing in patients with head and neck cancer therapy-induced swallowing difficulty.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to enroll in this trial if you are aged 18 or over and have been diagnosed with head and neck cancer for which surgery and chemoradiation therapy finished at least 12 months previously, which has caused ongoing difficulty swallowing.

Study details
All participants enrolled in this trial will be randomly allocated (by chance) to receive either the dilatation procedures, or to receive a single oeosophageal endoscopy during which no dilatation is provided. Participants in the dilatation group will receive a series of dilatation procedures. These involve passage of dilators to expand the calibre of the oesophagus under sedation and will occur at 2-3 weekly intervals. All participants will be followed up for 2 years following the final procedure to evaluate swallowing symptoms and satisfaction with the treatment.

It is hoped that this trial will provide information on whether pharyngo-oesophageal dilatation may be an effective method for reducing symptoms of difficulties swallowing which have been caused by cancer therapies for head and neck cancer patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office, Level 6 deLacy Building, St Vincent's Hospital, 390 Victoria Street 
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/03/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10/197</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/06/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ian Cook</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, St George Hospital, Gray St, Kogarah, NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+61 2 91132817</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 91133993</fax>
      <email>I.Cook@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Wu</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, St George Hospital, Gray St, Kogarah, NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+61 2 91132817</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 91133993</fax>
      <email>peteriungchiang.wu@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Wu</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, St George Hospital, Gray St, Kogarah, NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+61 2 91132817</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 91133993</fax>
      <email>peteriungchiang.wu@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Wu</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, St George Hospital, Kogarah, NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+61 2 91132817</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 91133993</fax>
      <email>peteriungchiang.wu@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>