<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362792">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000800820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Combined Infusion of Immune Cells and Vaccination to Boost Immunity to Infection After Bone Marrow Transplantation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In haemopoietic stem cell transplant patients, does infusion of infection-specific T-cells combined with vaccination (compared to no vaccination) enhance immune reconstitution safely?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1132-8656</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CynTax Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Post haemopoietic stem cell transplant infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Acute leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - Low grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Donor derived infection-specific T-cells (with activity against CMV, Adenovirus, EBV, VZV, Influenza, BKV and Aspergillus), 2x10^7 cells/m^2 intravenously after day+28 post transplant;
and vaccination (with Fluvax and Varivax), 0.5ml each by subcutaneous injection 24-72 hours post T-cell infusion.

3 SEQUENTIAL groups, each compared to historical controls.
1) 6 patients receiving multi-infection specific T-cells alone
2) 6 patients receiving multi-infection specific T-cells plus Fluvax
3) 6 patients receiving multi-infection specific T-cells plus Fluvax and Varivax</interventions>
    <comparator>Donor derived infection-specific T-cells alone administered to 50 haemopoietic stem cell transplant recipients at Westmead Hospital and Childrens Hospital Westmead between 2003 and 2011</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of infection-specific T-cell infusion and vaccination

Acutely- pulse, BP, Oxygen saturation and respiratory rate every 30 minutes for 2 hours post T-cell infusion.
Thereafter assessed clinically with history and physical examination and with full blood count, renal and liver function tests. Adverse events graded according to the NCI common toxicity criteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 2 weeks, 3 weeks 4 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, 12 months
(post T-cell infusion)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Infection specific immune reconstitution.
Assessed by response to viral and fungal antigens by ELISPOT or cytokine flow cytometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 2 weeks, 3 weeks 4 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, 12 months
(post T-cell infusion)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of CMV, AdV, EBV, VZV, Influenza, BKV and Aspergillus reactivation and infection.
Assessed by weekly PCR for CMV and EBV, clinically for signs of infection and further testing as indicated (eg immunofluorescence and PCR for other pathogens) on blood, urine and tissue samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 2 weeks, 3 weeks 4 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, 12 months
(post T-cell infusion)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CMV, EBV and BKV load based on quantitative PCR</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 2 weeks, 3 weeks 4 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, 12 months
(post T-cell infusion)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Use of specific anti-viral pharmacotherapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 2 weeks, 3 weeks 4 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, 12 months
(post T-cell infusion)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Use of systemic anti-fungal drugs including amphotericin and azoles</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 2 weeks, 3 weeks 4 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, 12 months
(post T-cell infusion)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of acute and chronic GVHD.
Assessed by history and physical examination and tissue confirmation (eg gastric or skin biopsy) in patients with symptoms or signs of GVHD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 2 weeks, 3 weeks 4 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, 12 months
(post T-cell infusion)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of in-hospital days following first discharge post transplant</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 2 weeks, 3 weeks 4 weeks, 3 months, 6 months, 9 months, 12 months
(post T-cell infusion)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients undergoing myeloablative or non-myeloablative allogeneic transplantation from an HLA (A, B and DR) identical or 1-3 antigen mismatched family or unrelated donor.
2. Transplant performed for any type of non-malignant condition or haematological malignancy including but not limited to acute and chronic leukaemia, myelodysplasia, non Hodkgins and Hodgkins lymphoma or myeloma. 
3. Recipients of peripheral blood or bone marrow stem cells. 
4. Adequate hepatic and renal function (&lt; 3 x upper limit of normal for AST (SGOT), ALT (SGPT), &lt; 2 x upper limit of normal for total bilirubin, serum creatinine).
5. Estimated life expectancy of at least 6 months.
6. Patient (or legal representative) has given informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Use of anti-lymphocyte globulin (ALG, ATG, Campath or other broad spectrum lymphocyte antibody) given in the 4 weeks immediately prior to infusion or planned within 4 weeks after infusion.
2. Grade II or greater graft versus host disease within 1 week prior to infusion.
3. Prednisone or methylprednisone at a dose of &gt; 1 mg/kg (or equivalent in other steroid preparations) administered within 72 hours prior to cell infusion.
4. Allergies to eggs or components of the Fluvax or Varivax vaccines.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allogeneic donor recipient pairs fulfilling inclusion criteria for the trial will be identified at planning meetings of the Blood and Marrow Transplant Unit of Westmead Hospital or Children’s Hospital Westmead. Donors and recipients will be approached by the principal investigator or by associate investigators working on the Blood and Marrow Transplant Unit who will explain the purposes and procedures of the trial. For unrelated donors, a request for consent will be made through the Australian Bone Marrow Donor Registry or via overseas registries once appropriate approvals have been obtained. Once donors and patients have received information sheets and given informed consent, the transplant will be registered on the trial and the following details will be recorded by the Clinical Trials Unit of the Haematology Department of Westmead Hospital: Westmead Hospital unique patient number (UPN) of recipient, donor and recipient age, donor and recipient viral serostatus, recipient diagnosis, planned conditioning therapy.</concealment>
    <sequence>Non-randomised</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>3 SEQUENTIAL groups, each compared to historical controls.
1) 6 patients receiving multi-infection specific T-cells alone
2) 6 patients receiving multi-infection specific T-cells plus Fluvax
3) 6 patients receiving multi-infection specific T-cells plus Fluvax and Varivax</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>18</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor DJ Gottlieb</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Medicine, 
Westmead Hospital, 
Hawkesbury Rd, Westmead, 
Sydney, NSW 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Professor P. Shaw</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Oncology Unit
Children's Hospital Westmead
Cnr Hawkesbury Rd and Hainsworth St, Westmead, 
Sydney, NSW 2145</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to assess the safety and efficacy of combined infusion of immune cells and vaccination to boost immunity to infection after bone marrow transplantation. 

Who is it for? 
You may be eligible to join this study if you are undergoing bone marrow transplantation for any type of non-malignant condition or haematological malignancy including but not limited to acute and chronic leukaemia, myelodysplasia, non Hodgkins and Hodgkins lymphoma or myeloma.

Trial details
Participants in this trial will be allocated to one of three groups. The first group will receive multi-infection specific T-cells intravenously (via the vein) 28 days after bone marrow transplantation. The second group will also receive this treatment in addition to the Fluvax vaccination. The third group will undergo the immune cell infusion, Fluvax vaccination and Varivax vaccination.

All participants will be assessed regularly over a period of 12 months in order to determine the safety of this treatment, and to determine whether it can prevent viral and fungal infection following allogeneic blood or marrow stem cell transplantation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office, Room1072 Education Block
Level 1 Westmead Hospital
Hawkesbury Rd
Westmead, NSW 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/05/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/WMEAD/298</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor DJ Gottlieb</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine, 
Westmead Hospital, 
Hawkesbury Rd, Westmead, 
Sydney, NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+612-9845-6033</phone>
      <fax>+612-9687-2331</fax>
      <email>david.gottlieb@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor DJ Gottlieb</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine, 
Westmead Hospital, 
Hawkesbury Rd, Westmead, 
Sydney, NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+612-9845-6033</phone>
      <fax>+612-9687-2331</fax>
      <email>david.gottlieb@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor DJ Gottlieb</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine, 
Westmead Hospital, 
Hawkesbury Rd, Westmead, 
Sydney, NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+612-9845-6033</phone>
      <fax>+612-9687-2331</fax>
      <email>david.gottlieb@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>