<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347946">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000097842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can exercise reduce treatment toxicity during the initial phase of testosterone suppression in prostate cancer patients?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can exercise ameliorate treatment toxicity during the initial phase of testosterone suppression in prostate cancer patients; is this more effective than delayed rehabilitation and what is the time course and persistence of benefits?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1127-1223</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prostate Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Immediate Exercise Group:
The exercise program involves resistance (e.g. lifting weights), aerobic (e.g. walking, cycling, rowing ergometer) and impact-loading (e.g. hopping, jumping) exercises undertaken 3 times per week for 6 months in an exercise clinic. Sessions will take approximately 60 minutes including the warm-up and cool-down periods. The sessions will be conducted in small groups of up to 6-10 participants under the supervision of exercise physiologists. The exercise program will be tailored to each participant. Target intensity will be 60-85% estimated maximum heart (220  age) for aerobic exercise and 6-12 repetition maximum (i.e. a 6 repetition maximum is how much weight can be lifted 6 times) for resistance exercise.</interventions>
    <comparator>Delayed Exercise Group:
Participants will remain on their usual care for the initial 6 months, then will receive the same, 6 month exercise intervention as the Immediate Exercise Group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Areal Bone Mineral Density (BMD): BMD of the hip, lumbar spine as well as whole body bone mineral content (BMC, g) will be assessed by dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Volumetric BMD and Bone Architecture: volumetric BMD and micro-architecture at the tibia will be assessed by peripheral quantitative computed tomography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Composition: regional and whole body lean mass and fat mass will be assessed by dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood Markers: Testosterone, prostate specific antigen (PSA), insulin, glucose, hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c), C- reactive protein (CRP), bone formation [alkaline phosphatase, Pro collagen Type 1 N-Terminal Pro peptide (PINP)] and resorption [C-terminal telopeptide of type I collagen (CTX)] markers and lipid profile levels will be measured commercially by an accredited Australian National Association of Testing Authorities (NATA) laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood Pressure and Arterial Stiffness: blood pressure and arterial stiffness will be measured using standard protocols using a validated oscillometric device and the SphygmoCor system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle Strength: Dynamic muscular strength of majour upper and lower body muscles will be assessed by standard 1RM protocol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance: static and dynamic balance will be assessed using the Neurocom Smart Balancemaster. Falls self-efficacy will be determined using the Activities-Specific Balance Confidence scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physicall Function: funcation performance will be assessed using standard measures including 1) 400m walk, 2) repeated chair rise, 3) stair climb, 4) 6-meter backward tandem walk, and 5) 6-meter walk, usual and fast pace.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity: physical activity and sedentary time will be assessed using triaxial accelerometry, the godin leisure-time questionnaire and sedentary time questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity Motivation: physicaal activity motivation will be assessed using Theory of Planned Behaviour (TBP) constructs (affective and instrumental attitude, injunctive and descriptive norm, self-efficacy, perceived behavioural control, intention, and planning) in a standard TPB Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life: quality of life will be assessed using the SF-36, EORTC QLQ-C30, EORTC QLQ-PR25 and EPIC-26 questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological Distress: psychological distress will be assessed using the Brief Symptom Inventory-18, Impact of Events Scale and Memorial Anxiety Scale for Prostate Cancer questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue: Fatigue will be assessed using the Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-Fatigue questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep Quality: sleep quality will be assessed using the the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Men initiating androgen supression therapy (AST) for the treatment of prostate cancer</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Prior exposure to AST (e.g. those re-initiating AST from intermittent programs)
2) Established metastatic bone disease
3) Established osteoporosis
4) Taking medications known to affect bone metabolism (e.g. bisphosphonates),
5) Any acute illness, musculoskeletal, cardiovascular or neurological disorder that could inhibit a participant's
ability to participate in the exercise program or put them at risk of injury or illness.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomization by computer. Written informed consent will be required prior to any testing or randomisation. Subjects who dropout prior to completion of baseline testing will not be randomised.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation). Randomisation is at the level of the individual patient, and will be stratified by age and smoking status.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The two groups of participants receive different interventions during the same time span of the study, however the delayed exercise group receive the intervention after 6 months of usual care.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>124</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Edith Cowan University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup WA 6027</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 14, 300 Elizabeth Street, SURRY HILLS NSW 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Robert Newton</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Edith Cowan University
270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup WA 6027</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to determine if immediate exercise therapy can improve health by reducing initial adverse effects during the initial phase of AST and if this provides superior benefits to delayed exercise therapy.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a man with prostate cancer who is about to initiate AST.

Trial details.
Participants in this trial will be randomly (by chance) allocated to one of two groups. One group will immediately undergo supervised exercise training 3 times per week for 6 months. This involves aerobic (walking/jogging, cycling, rowing), resistance (lifting weights), and impact (hopping, jumping) exercises and then monitored (without training) for a further 6months. The other group will be assigned to usual care for the first 6 months. After this time participants in this group will commence the exercise program for the next 6 months.

Participants will have measurements of bone mineral density, body composition, blood markers, blood pressure, arterial stiffness taken at 4 occasions (baseline, 3-, 6-, and 12-months). Participants will also complete tests of their muscle strength, balance and physical function as well as complete a series of questionnaires at these time points.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.ecuhealthwellnessinstitute.org/research-activity/projects</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Edith Cowan University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Edith Cowan University
270 Joondalup Drive, Joondalup WA 6027</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/01/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Robert Newton</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University
ECU Health and Wellness Institute
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 08 6304 5037</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.newton@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Robert Newton</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University
ECU Health and Wellness Institute
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 08 6304 5037</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.newton@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Robert Newton</name>
      <address>Edith Cowan University
ECU Health and Wellness Institute
270 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA 6027</address>
      <phone>+61 08 6304 5037</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.newton@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>