<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83679">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/03/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/03/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000159257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessment of Efficacy of AZD2281 in Platinum Sensitive Serous Ovarian Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase II Randomised, Double Blind, Multicentre Study to Assess the Efficacy of AZD2281 in the Treatment of Patients With Platinum Sensitive Serous Ovarian Cancer Following Treatment With Two or More Platinum Containing Regimens</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Platinum Sensitive Serous Ovarian Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>AZD2281 or Olaparib is a potent inhibitor of polyadenosine 5-diphosphoribose
polymerase (PARP) that is being developed as an oral treatment for patients with BRCA (Breast Cancer Gene Type) related cancer. The molecular targeting of olaparib to specific subsets of tumours may
provide an opportunity for less toxic cancer monotherapy and adjuvant therapy, compared with currently available regimen. In this study, AZD2281 will be given orally 400mg twice daily. Participants will be receiving AZD2281 till their tumour assessment (via imaging scans) show disease progression according to the protocol. They can chose to stop participating in the study and hence stop receiving the drug. Their doctors or the sponsor may also stop them from receiving the study drug if it was discovered that patient is at risk, non-compliant, or for other reasons.</interventions>
    <comparator>Matching placebo capsule (sugar capsule with no active drug) which looks like the study drug. Participants will be given orally and twice daily. Participants will be receiving this till their tumour assessment (via imaging scans) show disease progression according to the protocol. They can chose to stop participating in the study and hence stop receiving the drug. Their doctors or the sponsor may also stop them from receiving the study drug if it was discovered that patient is at risk, non-compliant, or for other reasons.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of this study is to determine the efficacy (assessed by progression free survival [PFS]) of AZD2281 compared to placebo in this patient population. Progression free survival is defined as the time from randomisation (when the patient starts taking the study drug on Day 1 of study) to the earlier date of objective assessment of progression (per Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours [RECIST] criteria determined via evaluations of tumours using imaging scans) or death (by any cause in the absence of progression).</outcome>
      <timepoint>CA-125 measurements will be performed every 28 days till the patient stops taking the study drug. Radiological tumour assessments will be performed every 12 weeks for 1st 60 weeks patient is in the study and then every 24 weeks there-after till the patient has disease progression.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>One of the secondary objectives of this study is to determine the efficacy of AZD2281 compared to placebo by assessment of best overall response.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Best overall response will be determined by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours [RECIST] criteria determined via evaluations of tumours using imaging scans. Radiological tumour assessments will be performed every 12 weeks for 1st 60 weeks patient is in the study and then every 24 weeks there-after till the patient has disease progression.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>One of the secondary objectives of this study is to determine the safety and tolerability of AZD2281 compared to placebo. Safety and tolerability will be determined via evaluation of adverse events, physical examination, vital signs, laboratory findings and so on during study visits.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be evaluated for safety and tolerability at weekly study visits for the first 2 months and at monthly study visits there-after. The patients will come for monthly visits till they discontinue from the study. Patients will also have a follow-up visit 30 days after they discontinue from study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Female patients with histologically diagnosed serous ovarian cancer or recurrent serous ovarian cancer. 
Patients must have completed at least 2 previous courses of platinum containing therapy; the patient must have been platinum sensitive to the previous 2 chemo regimens. 
For the last chemotherapy course prior to enrolment on the study, patients must have demonstrated an objective stable maintained response (partial or complete response) and this response needs to be maintained until completion of chemotherapy. 
Patients must be treated on the study within 8 wks of completion of their final dose of the platinum containing regimen.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous treatment with polyadenosine 5-diphosphoribose polymerase (PARP) inhibitors including AZD2281 
Patients with low grade ovarian carcinoma. 
Patients who have had drainage of their ascites during the final 2 cycles of their last chemotherapy regimen prior to enrolment on the study 
Patients receiving any chemotherapy, radiotherapy (except for palliative reasons), within 2 weeks from the last dose prior to study entry (or a longer period depending on the defined characteristics of the agents used).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/08/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>5000</postcode>
    <postcode>5065</postcode>
    <postcode>NSW 2031</postcode>
    <postcode>3084</postcode>
    <postcode>4560</postcode>
    <postcode>4101</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state>Brussel, Leuven</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state>Wiesbaden, Kiel, Marburg, Ulm, G?ttingen, Essen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state>Tel-Aviv, Jerusalem, Tel-Hashomer, Nahariya, Zerifin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Szczecin, Lublin, Poznan,</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Iasi, Suceava, Baia Mare, Cluj-Napoca,</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ukraine</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Astra Zeneca</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>AstraZeneca
SE1 K/1, Parklands 
Alderley Park, Macclesfield, 
Cheshire
England
SK10 4TG</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United Kingdom</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AstraZeneca</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>SE1 K/1, Parklands 
Alderley Park, Macclesfield, 
Cheshire
England
SK10 4TG</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of the study is to determine the efficacy of the study drug AZD2281 compared to placebo by looking at progression free survival of the patients. Progression will be determined by tumour assessments and evaluations and patients will have regular imaging scans. The study hypotheses that AZD2281 given after an objective stable maintained response on completion of platinum containing chemotherapy improves progression free survival compared to placebo in platinum sensitive serous advanced ovarian cancer patients who have previously received two or platinum containing regimens.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Yap TA, Carden CP, Kaye SB. Beyond chemotherapy: targeted therapies in ovarian cancer. Nat Rev Cancer. 2009 Mar;9(3):167-81.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cancer Institute NSW Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/01/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00414</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/09/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ian Kearns</name>
      <address>AstraZeneca R&amp;D Charnwood
AZD2281
Study Delivery, Bakewell Road, Loughborough, Leics LE11 5RH, England</address>
      <phone>+44 (0)1509 644642</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ian.kearns@astrazeneca.com</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ian Kearns</name>
      <address>AstraZeneca R&amp;D Charnwood
AZD2281
Study Delivery, Bakewell Road, Loughborough, Leics LE11 5RH, England</address>
      <phone>+44 (0)1509 644642</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ian.kearns@astrazeneca.com</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sara Miner Medel</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+ 1 410 744 9335</phone>
      <fax>+ 1 410 744 9338</fax>
      <email>sara.miner-medel@parexel.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>