<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82019">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/05/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/05/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000264482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>QUARTZ - Quality of Life After Radiotherapy and Steroids</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Quality of Life After Radiotherapy &amp; Steroids. A Phase III Multi-Centre Randomised Controlled Trial to Assess Whether Optimal Supportive Care Alone (Including Dexamathasone) is As Effective (in terms of Patient Assessed Quality Adjusted Life Years) as Optimal Supportive Care (Including Dexamethasone ) Plus Whole Brain Radiotherapy in the Treatment of Patients With Inoperable Brain Metastases From Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TROG 07.02</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ClinicalTrials.gov: NCT00403065</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Brain and Central Nervous System Tumors
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Lung Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Non small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Brain</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Experimental Arm: Optimal Supportive Care (including dexamethasone) alone
Optimal supportive care (OSC) includes a prescription of a proton pump inhibitor while on dexamethasone, parallel nursing support, access to additional specialists (e.g., pain-relief service, palliative care team, medical social worker, or physiotherapist), and open access to follow-up in a specialist clinic. OSC may also include analgesics, bronchodilators, and other supportive treatment as needed.
Dexamethasone: the dexamethasone dose for patients in both arms of the study should be titrated down to the minimum required to control the patients symptoms of brain metastases. The timing and rate of dose reduction should be appropriate to the individual patient and be under the control of the treating clinician. Administration is orally. The duration also depends on individual patients requirments.
OSC in both arms will continue as required by the patient until death.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control Arm: Optimal Supportive Care (OSC, including dexamethasone) with whole brain radiotherapy (WBRT, 20 Gy in 5 consecutive daily fractions) </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient-assessed quality adjusted life years (QALY)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quality of Life forms will be completed at baseline and every week, for the first 12 weeks, and then at least 4-weekly thereafter (until death), by the nurse phoning the patient (or face-to-face if the patient attends the hospital). The responses obtained each week for each patient will be converted (using the standard EQ5D scaling) to a utility score (between 0 and 1) which can be plotted over time. A QALY (equivalent to the Area Under the Curve) can then be calculated for each patient.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival: </outcome>
      <timepoint>Overall survival is the time between date of randomisation and date of death from any cause. Follow up will consist of weekly telephone assessments from randomisation, for a minimum of 12 weeks and then at least every 4 weeks until death. Also the patient should be reviewed in clinic by the investigating clinician at 4-weekly intervals unitl death.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Karnofsky performance status: </outcome>
      <timepoint>Performance Status will be assessed weekly and the trial groups compared at specific timepoints (6 and 12 weeks).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient symptoms: </outcome>
      <timepoint>Symptoms will be assessed by asking specific questions on a weekly basis for 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment and measurement of caregiver concerns: </outcome>
      <timepoint>Carers concerns will be assessed by asking specific questions on a weekly basis for 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Histologically or cytologically proven primary Non Small Cell Lung Cancer- Computed Tomography(CT)/Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) confirming brain metastases - Inoperable brain metastases as assessed by a lung cancer Multi-Disciplinary Team (MDT) or patients for whom surgery is deemed inappropriate- Clinician and patient uncertain of the role of WBRT- Patient able and willing to respond to questions in a weekly telephone assessment- Patient able and willing to give informed consent- Baseline Patient Assessment Form completed.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Clinician and / or patient certain that WBRT will be of benefit- Clinician and / or patient certain that WBRT will not be of benefit  - Previous or current illness, which has not been brought under control and/or is likely to interfere with protocol treatment or comparisons- Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor (EGFR) inhibitors within one week prior to randomisation- Chemotherapy (last cycle) within one month prior to randomisation- Previous radiotherapy to the brain- Surgery for brain metastases within one month prior to randomisation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central Randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by computer.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/03/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>8/09/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>9</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Tanya Holt</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Queensland Radium Institute Mater Centre Raymond Terrace South Brisbane QLD 4101</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group Seed Funding</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Edith St 
Waratah
NSW 2298</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC Palliative Care Research Program Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, 20 Allara Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Edith St 
Waratah
NSW 2298</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>RATIONALE: Steroid therapy, such as dexamethasone, may reduce swelling, pain, and other symptoms of inflammation and may be effective in treating some of the problems caused by cancer and cancer treatment. Supportive care improves the quality of life of patients with a serious or life-threatening disease, and prevents or treats symptoms of cancer, side effects of treatment, and other problems related to cancer or its treatment. Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays to kill tumor cells. It is not yet known whether dexamethasone given together with supportive care is more effective with or without whole-brain radiation therapy in treating patients with brain metastases. 

PURPOSE: This randomized phase III trial is studying dexamethasone and supportive care to see how well it works with or without whole-brain radiation therapy in improving the quality of life of patients with non-small cell lung cancer that has spread to the brain and cannot be removed by surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.trog.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/02/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Brisbane</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tanya Holt</name>
      <address>Queensland Radium Institute
Mater Centre
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 38403222</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 38403399</fax>
      <email>Tanya_holt@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kacy Baumann</name>
      <address>Queensland Radium Institute
Mater Centre
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 38403219</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 38403298</fax>
      <email>Kacy_Baumann@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Erin Nolan</name>
      <address>Department of Radiation Oncology Locked Bag 7 Hunter Region Mail Centre NSW 2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 1685</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 1465</fax>
      <email>Erin.Nolan@trog.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tanya Holt</name>
      <address>Queensland Radium Institute Mater Centre Raymond Terrace South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 38403222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Tanya_holt@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>