<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335799">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/08/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/08/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000641099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Eltrombopag therapy for low platelets in patients on azacitidine treatment for myelodysplastic syndrome and acute myeloid leukaemia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A single arm pilot study of azacitidine in myelodysplastic syndrome / acute myeloid leukaemia, with eltrombopag support for thrombocytopenia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>AZA-E</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Myelodysplastic Syndromes (MDS)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Low marrow blast count acute myeloid leukaemia (AML)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Acute leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Eltrombopag given orally every day for a 1-2 week pre-phase (50mg for a week, with a potential to go straight to combination therapy at 1 week or to maintain eltrombopag at the same dose as monotherapy for a second week in eligible patients, followed by azacitidine with or without eltrombopag. Individualised dose escalation of eltrombopag adapted according to response (dose range from 50-150mg in patients of East Asian extraction, 50-300mg in patients of predominantly non-East Asian extraction). Azacitidine administered by subcutaneous injection 75mg/m2 days 1-5, 8,9 per cycle for 6 cycles, for a total of 54 days treatment, with ongoing azacitidine offered those deriving clinical benefit.</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Grade III/IV non-haematological toxicity possibly, probably or definitely related to the combination of eltrombopag and azacitidine based on clinical assessments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6  cycles of therapy (approx 6 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 1:
To gather preliminary evidence of the clinical efficacy of eltrombopag to improve platelet counts in this setting, and the appropriate dose at which this may be achieved based on data obtained from clinical assessments, up to 4 bone marrow biopsies, and peripheral blood tests.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: approximately 2.5 years after the last accrued patient completes study treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To explore laboratory findings to correlate with the response of the combination of 5-azacitidine and eltrombopag in patients with MDS and low marrow blast count AML</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: approximately 2.5 years after last accrued patient completes study treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with low platelet count (&lt;=150 x109/L) and in addition disease diagnosis of either MDS (by World Health Organization Criteria, those with refractory anemia with high blast counts and refractory anemia with ringed sideroblasts to also have at least one clinically significant cytopenia), nonproliferative Chronic Myelomonocytic Leukaemia (CMML) or low marrow blast count AML not suitable for induction chemotherapy; Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) 2 or less with life expectancy at least 3 months, adequate contraception and adequate renal and hepatic function; written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects with the diagnosis acute promyelocytic leukaemia; Prior treatment with 5-azacitidine or any other methyl-transferase inhibitor, eltrombopag, romiplostim, or other Trombopoietin T (TPO)-receptor agonist;AML or MDS requiring cytoreductive therapy (eg hydroxyurea, ara-c, thioguanine etc) in the month prior to study entry; known pro-thrombotic condition; history of Ischaemic neurological event (Transient Ischaemic Attack (TIA) or stroke) within the preceding 2 years;active or uncontrolled infections</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/11/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3002</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Peter Mac Callum Cancer Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St Andrews Place, East Melbourne Victoria, 3002</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victorian Cancer Agency</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>12 Victoria St. Carlton
Victoria, Australia, 3053</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>GlaxoSmithKline Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1061 Mountain Highway
Boronia, Victoria, Australia, 3155</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Celgene Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Celgene Australia Melbourne Level 7, 607 St Kilda Rd. Melbourne, Victoria 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Victorian Epigenetic Group</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Dr Melita Kenealy (coordinator) 
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Pl. East Melbourne
Victoria 3002</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Myelodysplastic Syndrome (MDS) is a disease of the bone marrow characterized by anemia, neutropenia, and thrombocytopenia (low red blood cell, white blood cell, and platelet counts).  MDS patients with thrombocytopenia who fail standard therapies require regular platelet transfusions which are expensive and inconvenient, and are a risk for further serious bleeding complications. The new treatment of MDS using azacitidine has shown to increase the survival rate of MDS patients including to improve platelet production over time. However, in the early cycles of treatment with azacitidine, the low platelet counts tend to exacerbate before they provide any clinical benefit. 

Eltrombopag is a drug designed to activate the thrombopoietin receptor. Eltrombopag has been able to increase platelet counts in healthy volunteers and in patients with chronic Immune Thrombocytopenia Purpura (ITP), a disease where patients destroy their own platelets very rapidly and thus develop thrombocytopenia. Eltrombopag is administered orally and is Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA) approved for the treatment of thrombocytopenia in patients with chronic ITP who failed to respond to standard treatment. 

This study is a single arm pilot study to evaluate the safety and tolerability of Eltrombopag in the treatment of low platelet counts in adult subjects with MDS treated using azacitidine

This study also incorporates a correlative laboratory component designed to determined the mechanism of action of 5-azacitidine +/- Eltrombopag and to determine a baseline profile which may predict those most responsive. These studies will incorporate gene methylation and expression, and immunoprofiling.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Andrews Pl, East Melbourne
Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10/78</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/08/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kirsten Herbert</name>
      <address>c/o Department of Haematology and Medical Oncology, Peter Mac Callum Cancer Centre
Locked Bag 1
ABeckett Street. Melbourne VIC 8006
Country: Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9656 1701</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Kirsten.Herbert@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kirsten Herbert</name>
      <address>c/o Department of Haematology and Medical Oncology, Peter Mac Callum Cancer Centre
Locked Bag 1
ABeckett Street. Melbourne VIC 8006
Country: Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9656 1701</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Kirsten.Herbert@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>