<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="357">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000279628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Interventions to improve participation in bowel cancer screening: the value of lay advocacy and positive framing of risk.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Interventions to improve participation in bowel cancer screening: the value of lay advocacy and positive framing of risk.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Screening for bowel cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Anal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Small bowel (duodenum and ileum</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention 1: the use of a bowel cancer screening invitation letter to that contains photographs of 2 previous screenees who were diagnosed with early bowel cancer through their participation in a bowel cancer screening program, and with simple program advocacy statements from them.
Intervention 2: the use of a bowel cancer screening invitation letter that contains enhanced positive framing and generalised risk messages.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control: A generic invitation letter</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Completion of faecal immunochemical test within 12 weeks of offer</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Test positivity rate</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Yield of neoplasia</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Present on the electoral roll of the Australian Electoral Commission, who reside in one of a set of defined postcodes adjacent to Flinders Medical Centre or Repatriation General Hospital Daw Park.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People already participating in bowel cancer screening research and service programs coordinated from the Bowel Health Service, Repatriation General Hospital Daw Park.Self exclusion by invitees - people who have specific heart and lung conditions that would preclude them from diagnostic and surgical follow-up following a positive screening test. All people who have specific medical conditions that would invalidate the screening test results. All people who have had a colonoscopy or stool screening test within the last year.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Invitees are randomised to one of three screening programs differing in intvitation content.  Allocation to invitation group is not concealed from the investigators and office staff who print and package invitation kits for postal delivery, but there is no direct contact netween investigators and invitees.  Invitees are unaware that there are more than one invitation type.  A help line is available and inquiries are answered without knowledge of invitation type.</concealment>
    <sequence>Group sizes of 600 each were determined by power analysis assuming that an intervention that produces a 10% increase in participation over control is a significant program improvement. All eligible people were assigned a random number using the MicroSoft Excel RAND function. The listing was ordered by ascending random number. The first 600 people were assigned to the intervention group 1 (Lay advocacy), the second 600 to Intervention group 2 (risk framing) and the third 600 to the control group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1800</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof. Graeme Young MD, FRACP</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC project grant 187644</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mr Stephen Cole</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Improved participation in screening for bowel cancer is desirable. Currently population scale bowel cancer screening program delivery is by mailed offer from a central screening service and invitations include a faecal occult blood detection kit. Invitees may decline the offer because they do not feel they are at risk, or because they do not engage with the program.  We have developed invitation letters to that include either improved risk messages or messages from previous screening participants in order to overcome these barriers.
We will randomly select invitees from the electoral roll and compare population screening participation between groups with or without the preliminary letter to determine which program results in the greater participation rate. Improved participation in screening will ultimately reduce deaths from bowel cancer</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Repatriation General Hospital Daw Park</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Daws Rd, Daw Park, SA 5041</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Stephen Cole</name>
      <address>Bowel Health Service
Repatriation General Hospital Daw Park
Daws Road
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751838</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82751083</fax>
      <email>scoles@rgh.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Alicia Smith</name>
      <address>Bowel Health Service
Repatriation General Hospital Daw Park
Daws Rd
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751075</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alicia.smith@rgh.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>