<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368995">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001105538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A clinical research study that is testing whether Penthrox (methoxyflurane) plus local anaesthetic reduces pain and discomfort for men having their first transrectal ultrasound-guided prostate biopsy compared to local anaesthetic alone</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A phase 3 double-blind placebo-controlled randomized trial of methoxyflurane with periprostatic local anaesthesia to reduce the discomfort of transrectal ultrasound-guided prostate biopsy (Pain-Free TRUS B)
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1172-4458 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>Pain-Free TRUS B</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ANZUP 1501</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Biopsy of the prostate for a raised PSA or an abnormal digital rectal examination.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Inhaled methoxyflurane, provided as a commercial pack of one Penthrox (Registered Trademark) Inhaler, containing 3mL methoxyflurane, of which participants choose how many puffs they feel they need. 
Administration will commence approximately one minute before insertion of the rectal probe.
To use the inhaler, the patient will put their lips around the mouthpiece and take normal sized breaths as required. Participants may choose to inhale throughout the entire procedure, however will only receive one pack, and therefore a maximum of 3mL methoxyflurane.
All participants will subsequently receive standard therapy (PILA) as standard of care. PILA consists of periprostatic injections of approximately 2.5mL of 2% lignocaine into each of the two sides of the base of the prostate gland at the junction of the seminal vesicle, using a 23g needle, administered about 5 minutes before doing the first biopsy.
The Pharmacy Department will maintain a record of drugs dispensed for each participant as well as a record of drug receipt and drug destruction as appropriate. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (inhaled 0.9% saline), provided as one Penthrox registered trademark Inhaler containing 3mL 0.9% saline, of which participants choose how many puffs they feel they need.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain rated by participants will be self-rated using a numeric rating scale with verbal anchors from 0 (no trouble at all) to 10 (worst I can imagine). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pain will be assessed twice: at about 15 minutes after and 7 - 35 days after the TRUS biopsy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite Secondary Outcome: Other aspects of the biopsy experience rated by participants including how troubled they were by: discomfort, feeling embarrassed, the sounds, fear of the biopsy, fear of the results, drowsiness, feeling dizzy or light-headed, nausea, vomiting, and the whole experience. Participants will also rate How much better or worse than expected were the pain, the discomfort, and the whole experience, again rated on 10 point scale from 0 (much better) to 5 (as expected) to 10 (much worse).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Rated at 15 minutes and 7-35 days after the biopsy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Willingness to undergo a biopsy in the future assessed by a questionnaire designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Rated at 15 minutes and 7-35 days after the biopsy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urologist's ratings of the participant's biopsy experience, assessed by a questionnaire designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>On the same day as the TRUS biopsy </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biopsy completion is defined as performance of 80% or more of the planned number of biopsies. The number of planned biopsies is recorded by the urologist before the TRUS Biopsy. The number of biopsies performed is recorded by the urologist after the TRUS biopsy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Defined as performance of 80% or more of the planned number of biopsies after the TRUS biopsy, after completion of all study participant biopsy procedures. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of specified adverse events. Surgical adverse events of interest (complications) include nausea, vomiting, dizziness, vasovagal episodes, fever, infection, urinary retention, or death within 30 days of the TRUS biopsy. the Clavien-Dindo Classification will be used to grade the most severe complication and SUSARS will be coded using the NCI CTCAEv4.03.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse events will be recorded after the TRUS biopsy (before the participant leaves the clinic), and 7-35 days after the biopsy.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of hospitalisation by reviewing hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Details will be recorded for each emergency department visit and each non-elective hospital admission that occurs within 30 days of the TRUS biopsy. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Males older than 18 years scheduled to undergo a TRUS biopsy of the prostate.
2.	No history of significant liver disease
3.	No history of significant renal disease
4.	Willing and able to complete questionnaires in English
5.	Willing and able to undergo TRUS biopsy within 7 days of randomisation
6.	Willing and able to comply with all study requirements, including treatment, timing and/or nature of required assessments 
7.	Signed, written informed consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Previous TRUS biopsy of the prostate
2.	Personal or family history of malignant hyperthermia
3.	Hypersensitivity to fluorinated anaesthetics or other inhalational anaesthetics
4.	Concurrent use of barbiturates or tetracycline antibiotics
5.	Concurrent illness that may jeopardise the ability of the patient to undergo the procedures outlined in this protocol with reasonable safety
6.	Presence of any psychological, familial, sociological or geographical condition potentially hampering compliance with the study protocol and follow-up schedule, including alcohol dependence or drug abuse.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants must meet all of the eligibility criteria.
Randomisation will be carried out by site staff via an internet based central randomisation system.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be in a 1:1 ratio and stratified by the following characteristics:
1)	Age (18-60 years versus older than 60)
2)	Study site
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary analysis will be a comparison between treatment groups on the pain score (following biopsy) using an analysis of variance with centre fitted as a covariate.  Additional covariates will be added as part of a secondary analysis to explore the potential of baseline characteristics as prognostic factors or effect modifiers.  Comparisons between treatment groups on other continuous secondary endpoints will be undertaken using a comparable approach to that used on the primary endpoint.  Binary (and ordinal) secondary endpoints (e.g. treatment completion) will be undertaken using (ordinal) logistic regression with centre fitted as a covariate. A descriptive analysis of the safety data will be undertaken. 
420 participants provides over 85% power at the two-sided 5% level of significance to detect a 0.80 point difference in mean pain scores (on scale from 0-10) assuming a standard deviation of 2.5 whilst allowing for missing data. A 0.80 point shift in mean pain scores should correspond to a reduction of more than 1/3 in the proportion of men reporting troublesome levels of pain. 

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/11/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/01/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>420</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>119</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Casey Hospital - Berwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Sydney Adventist Hospital - Wahroonga</hospital>
    <postcode>2137 - Concord</postcode>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
    <postcode>6150 - Murdoch</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>3806 - Berwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2076 - Wahroonga</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>North and South Islands</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6
Jane Foss Russell Building GO2
University of Sydney NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 14, 
300 Elizabeth Street
Sydney NSW 2000
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Prostate Cancer Foundation of Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>15-17 Queen St
Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian and New Zealand Urogenital and Prostate (ANZUP) Cancer Trials Group</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Lifehouse, Level 6
119-143 Missenden Road 
Camperdown NSW 2050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to see if the discomfort of a prostate biopsy can be reduced by a drug called methoxyflurane (Penthrox) given with a simple inhaler, popularly known as the green whistle, and widely used by ambulance officers and first aid services. Methoxyflurane is already approved in Australia for the relief of pain in patients having surgical procedures. 
Who is it for? 
You may be eligible to participate in this study if you are a male, aged 18 or over, who has been scheduled for your first transrectal ultrasound-guided prostate biopsy. 
Study Details 
All participants have injections of a local anaesthetic (lignocaine) around their prostate before the biopsy. This is the standard way of reducing the discomfort of a prostate biopsy. Before having the local anaesthetic, all participants are given the study treatment which is a green whistle inhaler after being shown how to use it. After their biopsy, participants fill out short, simple forms to let us know how they felt. In this study, one half of the participants are given inhalers loaded with methoxyflurane (the active inhaler group). The other half are given inhalers that look and smell the same, but are loaded with saline solution alone (the placebo inhaler group). 
Comparing the results in these two groups at the end of the study will show how good methoxyflurane is at reducing the discomfort of a prostate biopsy. It is hoped that this study will improve understanding of drugs which may be used to reduce discomfort of prostate biopsies for future patients. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SLHD Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Research Development Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X15-0217 &amp; HREC/15/RPAH/286</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/06/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jeremy Grummet</name>
      <address>The Alfred Hospital
322 Glenferrie Rd
Malvern VIC 3144</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9562 5094</fax>
      <email>trusb@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>TRUS B Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC CTC
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9562 5094</fax>
      <email>trusb@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>TRUS B Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC CTC
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9562 5094</fax>
      <email>trusb@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>TRUS B Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC CTC
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9562 5094</fax>
      <email>trusb@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>