<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365587">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000078651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Immediate expander/implant breast reconstruction followed by post-mastectomy  radiotherapy for breast cancer: Aesthetic and quality of life outcomes.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A retrospective observational study of women with breast cancer who have had mastectomy, immediate breast reconstruction and post-mastectomy radiotherapy (PMRT), and one-off assessment at six months post-stage 2 reconstruction, of aesthetic and quality of life outcomes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Quality of life and aesthetic outcomes in women following mastectomy, immediate breast reconstruction and PMRT, as measured by a one-off set of surveys six months after second-stage reconstruction. A subset of these women will also have a clinical examination and photos taken, at a minimum of six months post-stage 2 reconstruction, as part of their routine follow up. </interventions>
    <comparator>Not applicable - Observational study</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the psychological and quality of life outcomes of patients undergoing mastectomy, immediate reconstruction and PMRT through the following surveys:
Breast Q - reconstruction module (post operative)
Body Image Scale
Impact of Event Scale
Decision Regret Scale
FACT-B
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months following second-stage reconstruction.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the surgical, radiotherapy and oncological outcomes of patients undergoing mastectomy, immediate reconstruction and PMRT through patient records and clinical examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months following second-stage reconstruction.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the aesthetic outcomes of patients undergoing mastectomy, immediate reconstruction and PMRT through patient surveys (Breast Q). In addition, a sub-set of these women will have a clinical assessment form completed by the surgeon and photos taken.</outcome>
      <timepoint>A minimum of six months following second-stage reconstruction.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To report types of breast reconstruction chosen by women undergoing post-mastectomy radiotherapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of final breast reconstruction.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Female gender
2) Undergoing mastectomy for breast cancer (unilateral or bilateral)
3) Undergoing immediate reconstruction with implant/tissue expander
4) Undergoing post-mastectomy radiotherapy
5) Willing to give written informed consent.
6) Willingness to participate to and comply with the study requirements.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Male
2. Women unable to read and write English to a level required for completion of informed consent form and questionnaires.
3. Women unwilling to give consent for the study.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size will be determined by the number of eligible patients identified from the database, but a sample size of 50 is anticipated. Descriptive statistics will be used to analyse and describe the data obtained from questionnaires and surgeon aesthetic ratings.
The questionnaires are all standardised and validated, and will be scored according to standard scoring criteria published in the literature. Comparison of subgroups may be possible in some cases, for example if there are variations in dose of radiation, aesthetic and psychological outcomes at different doses will be analysed. Options for analysis of outcomes in different age groups and body habitus may also be explored.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>Six</followup>
    <followuptype>Months</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Psychosocial</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Retrospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/05/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/08/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>6/08/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>50</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Mater Sydney - North Sydney</hospital>
    <postcode>2060 - North Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Breast &amp; Surgical Oncology at the Poche Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>40 Rocklands Rd, North Sydney
NSW 2060</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mater Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rocklands Rd, North Sydney
NSW, 2060</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will assess the quality of life of women from a surgical oncology practice in North Sydney, Australia, who have undergone mastectomy for breast cancer, have chosen to have immediate breast reconstruction (IBR) and have also required post-mastectomy radiotherapy (PMRT). The purpose of this research is to provide evidence about the oncological safety and levels of patient satisfaction in this group of women.

Study details
All participants in this study will be asked to complete five surveys, six months after their final breast reconstruction operation, about their satisfaction with the aesthetic outcomes of their surgery, and its affect on their psychological wellbeing and quality of life. These patient-reported outcomes will be assessed alongside measures of their clinical outcomes, including any post-operative or post-radiotherapy complications, taken from their patient record. A subset of these women will also have a clinical examination and photos taken at six months following their final reconstruction procedure. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>The following journal article is under review with Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery. Immediate expander/implant breast reconstruction followed by post-mastectomy radiotherapy for breast cancer: Aesthetic, surgical, satisfaction and quality of life outcomes in women with high-risk breast cancer.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>390 Victoria St,
Darlinghurst, NSW, 2010.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/12/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>11/156</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Spillane</name>
      <address>Breast &amp; Surgical Oncology at The Poche Centre
40 Rocklands Rd, North Sydney,
NSW 2060.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99117381</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.spillane@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kathy Flitcroft</name>
      <address>Breast &amp; Surgical Oncology at The Poche Centre
40 Rocklands Rd, North Sydney,
NSW 2060.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99117381</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kathy.flitcroft@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Meagan Brennan</name>
      <address>Breast &amp; Surgical Oncology at The Poche Centre
40 Rocklands Rd, North Sydney,
NSW 2060.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99117381</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>meagan.brennan@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kathy Flitcroft</name>
      <address>Breast &amp; Surgical Oncology at The Poche Centre
40 Rocklands Rd, North Sydney,
NSW 2060.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99117381</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kathy.flitcroft@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>