<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366568">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000838617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigating the Prevention of Endometrial CAncer with Metformin (PECAM Study)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigating the Prevention of Endometrial CAncer with Metformin (PECAM Study)- a study involving postmenopausal women with hormone receptor positive breast cancer who are currently on tamoxifen therapy for at least 6 weeks.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1158-2065</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PECAM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Endometrial cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Womb (Uterine or endometrial cancer)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Metformin 850mg oral twice daily for 12 months commencing with commencement of tamoxifen. Adherence will be monitored by return tablet count.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo will be identical tablets to the metformin 850mg tablets</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is the effect of metformin therapy on the expression of genes in endometrial tissue on biopsy encoding:
1)	proteins in the LKB1/AMPK pathway, which inhibits cell proliferation; 
2)	mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR), which stimulates endometrial growth;
3)	the cytochrome P450 enzyme, aromatase, which is essential for oestrogen biosynthesis in the endometrium, and hence endometrial growth.
These are co-primary outcomes as they are dependent variables
</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effects of metformin, versus placebo, after 52 weeks of treatment on endometrial thickness, assessed by TVU+ saline infusion sonohysterography (SIS), and development of any other endometrial abnormalities on TVU (polyps, hyperplasia, subendometrial thickening or fibroids).


</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effects of metformin, versus placebo, after 52 weeks of treatment on endometrial histopathology of the endometrial biopsy tissue.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Associations between the effects of metformin on the endometrium ( by transvaginal ultrasound) and clinical characteristics and biochemistry, including fasting glucose, insulin, adiponectin and leptin ( by blood tests).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between TVU+SIS findings and endometrial pathology on biopsy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Postmenopausal women, aged &lt; 75 years, who are currently taking  tamoxifen therapy for at least 6 weeks for treatment of hormone receptor positive breast cancer.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>74</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Women who are premenopausal / perimenopausal / &gt; 75 years old
2.	Women with advanced breast cancer and likely to have progression of their disease within the study period, as assessed by their treating oncologist.

3.	Women with any of the following on screening: 

a)Use of any systemic hormones in the last 6 months;
b) serious endocrine disorder with systemic disease; 
c) alcohol consumption greater than 3 standard drinks per day; 
d) known acute or chronic renal, liver disease or cardiovascular disease; 
e) insulin dependent diabetes mellitus or use of an oral hypoglycemic agent; 


4. &lt;6 months amenorrhoea so that the likelihood of ovulatory cycles during the study will be small.

5. EH with atypia or ECa on endometrial biopsy or hysteroscopy and curettage.
6. Women who, in the opinion of the investigator, are a poor medical or psychiatric risk for treatment in a research protocol. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>1:1 randomization. 

Allocation concealment will be strictly maintained. The investigators, study centre personnel and participants will remain blinded throughout the study. 

The investigators, study centre personnel and participants will remain blinded throughout the study.

In order to maintain allocation concealment, a piece of paper with the group allocation (metformin or placebo) assigned to each study number in the randomization list will be put into opaque envelopes numbered consecutively 1- 120. Randomization will occur when the envelope with the patient’s study number on it is opened. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be independently computer generated and stratified by body mass index (BMI) such that there will be equal numbers of women with BMI &gt; 30kg/m2 per group. 

</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary study outcome is the effect of metformin on the pathway whereby metformin inhibits mTOR action, the pathway whereby it stimulates p53 and inhibits the cell cycle, and the pathway whereby it inhibits aromatase expression via AMPK and sequestration of CRTC2 in the endometrium of women at high risk of, or who have, EH. 
In an earlier study, hyperproliferative and hyperplastic endometrial tissue from 24 women receiving tamoxifen exhibited higher phosphorylation levels at specific amino residues of AKT in the order of (2.6 to 3.5 fold) and for mTOR (10 to 20 fold) compared with benign endometrial tissue from non treated patients (n=28). Our hypothesis is that metformin therapy will reverse this effect. 
Based on our previous research, we anticipate about 20% of women will not have evaluable endometrial biopsy samples. Thus, taking a pragmatic approach, we will recruit 130 women and randomise half (65) to each treatment. Allowing for a conservative 20% non completion rate and 20% unevaluable samples, we aim to have evaluable endometrial tissue and study data for 40 women per treatment arm. 
The distribution of the data will be examined and non normally distributed data will be transformed. Baseline levels in the treatment groups will be examined. If there are no significant between- group differences at baseline, comparison of between-group differences at the end of the study would be by t-test (or non-parametric equivalent). If there is any chance baseline difference, then an analysis of variance will be performed, adjusting for the baseline difference. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>23/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>130</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>112</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/08/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3004 - St Kilda Road Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wellington Rd Clayton VIC Australia 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council of Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Building Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke St, Canberra ACT 2601, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>none</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Mitchell Chipman</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Victorian Breast Oncology Group
Level 2,166 Gipps Street,East Melbourne Vic 3002</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>A/Prof Shane White</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress> Medical Oncologist, Suite 13, Warringal Medical Centre, 214 Burgundy Street, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3081</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Camberwell Ultrasound for Women</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>64 Auburn Grove, Hawthorn East VIC 3123, </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Kristy Brown</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>MIMR-PHI Institute
27-31 Wright Street, Clayton VIC 3168</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to determine if we can prevent the development of uterine cancer in women who need to take tamoxifen therapy. 

We will investigate whether metformin, commonly used to treat diabetes, blocks cell pathways by which tamoxifen (and oestrogen) stimulates growth of the lining of the uterus.

This study will enable us to determine if there is a potential role for metformin
a) to prevent changes to the uterine lining in women treated with tamoxifen 
b) possibly prevent cancer of the uterus 

This study also offers a unique opportunity for us to determine whether all women with breast cancer should have ultrasound of their uterus before starting tamoxifen and after one year of therapy. 

Reasons for the study:
Over 75% of women diagnosed with breast cancer in Australia have hormone sensitive cancer. Of these, at least 1/3 will be treated with a drug called tamoxifen, which blocks oestrogen action. A recent large study has shown that 10 years of tamoxifen therapy is more effective than 5 years in prolonging survival. 

However, a downside of tamoxifen therapy is a 75% increase in the risk of uterine (endometrial) cancer. 

Presently there is no treatment to prevent endometrial cancer in women treated with tamoxifen, or for that matter for women in general. Endometrial cancer, the most common gynaecologic cancer, affects approximately 1 in 73 Australian women by the age of 75 years and 1 in 52 by the age of 85 years. 

We do know that: 
	tamoxifen is associated with a 7 fold increase in endometrial cancer over 5 years
	most women who develop an endometrial abnormality on tamoxifen do so in the first year of treatment
	1 in 5 women have an endometrial abnormality before starting tamoxifen (this increases the risk for tamoxifen-induced changes)


We will recruit women with hormone receptor positive breast cancer who are
	postmenopausal, 
	less than 75 years old 
	not diabetic.  
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://womenshealth.med.monash.edu.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash University
Wellington Rd
Clayton VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF13/3870. 2013001982</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Susan Davis</name>
      <address>Women's Health Research Program, 
Department of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine
School of Public Health and Preventive Medicine
Monash University 
99 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61399030827</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>susan.davis@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Susan Davis</name>
      <address>Women's Health Research Program, 
Department of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine
School of Public Health and Preventive Medicine
Monash University 
99 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61399030827</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>susan.davis@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Susan Davis</name>
      <address>Women's Health Research Program, 
Department of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine
School of Public Health and Preventive Medicine
Monash University 
99 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61399030827</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>susan.davis@monash.edu </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Susan Davis</name>
      <address>Women's Health Research Program, 
Department of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine
School of Public Health and Preventive Medicine
Monash University 
99 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61399030827</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>susan.davis@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>