<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364011">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000487718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>High Dose Melphalan: A pilot study to evaluate pharmacokinetic-based dose determination in patients with multiple myeloma scheduled to undergo autologous stem cell transplantation 
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>High Dose Melphalan: A pilot study to evaluate pharmacokinetic-based dose determination in patients with multiple myeloma scheduled to undergo autologous stem cell transplantation 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1141-6361</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Myeloma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Myeloma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>On Day -4 prior to autologous stem cell transplantation, a test dose of 20 mg/m2 melphalan will be administered by intravenous infusion. A series of six blood samples will be collected after the end of the infusion. The plasma will be separated, frozen and sent for pharmacokinetic assessment, which will be completed by the end of Day -2 to allow calculation of the full melphalan dose, that will target a melphalan exposure level that chosen by the treating physician. On Day -1 the full melphalan dose will be administered, with repeat blood sampling to check whether the expected exposure was achieved. The treating physician will administer either the remaining 180 mg/m2 dose or another dose based on the test pharmacokinetic results targeting a melphalan exposure at or just above the median levels achieved in previous drug testing. The initial 10 mg/m2 test dose produced low melphalan concentration in two patients (close to the limit of detection of the assay), making it difficult to make predictions for full dose melphalan exposure.  In December 2013, the test dose was therefore increased to 20 mg/m2 to improve the quality of the predictions. </interventions>
    <comparator>This is an uncontrolled pilot study</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the feasibility of real-time pharmacokinetics in a multi-centre setting using a test dose of melphalan, followed by therapeutic drug monitoring (measuring the drug levels in repeated blood samples after it is infused) of a targeted dose of melphalan in patients with multiple myeloma</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood sampling occurs at 5 min, 15 min, 30 min, 40 min, 1h 15 min and 2h 30 min after the end of the melphalan infusions for the test and full doses, which are administered between Day -4 and Day -1 before autologous stem cell transplantation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the influence of genetic factors on the pharmacokinetics of melphalan. An EDTA blood sample will be withdrawn prior to High dose melphalan for DNA extraction and evaluation of genetic polymorphisms in enzymes involved in drug metabolism and detoxification, such as the glutathione transferase enzymes. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately prior to beginning the melphalan infusion for the test dose. It is not needed before the full dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To record transplant toxicity and engraftment parameters.
This includes
- Gastrointestinal toxicity, which will be graded daily using CTCAE v 4.03 criteria for the first 28 days post autologous stem cell transplant. Oral mucositis will also be graded daily using WHO criteria.  
- Occurrence of any toxicity of Grade 3 or above (as defined in CTCAE version 4.03), including abnormal liver or renal function or cardiac or pulmonary toxicities. 
- Occurrence of febrile neutropenia 
- Recovery of neutrophils and platelets unsupported by blood transfusions

</outcome>
      <timepoint>One month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To record disease outcomes in terms of Time to Progression and Overall survival</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 5 years post autologous stem cell transplant </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients of any age scheduled to receive single agent high dose melphalan and autologous stem cell rescue for multiple myeloma. 
2. Written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those for whom written informed consent cannot be obtained.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Not applicable. </concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/01/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>17/07/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>38</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>17/07/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Gosford Hospital - Gosford</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Royal Park campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Wollongong Hospital - Wollongong</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord Repatriation Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2250 - East Gosford</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2520 - Wollongong</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Children's Hospital at Westmead</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hawkesbury Rd.,
Westmead, NSW, 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>KRI Bridging Grant at The Children's Hospital at Westmead</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kids Research Institute, 
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Hawkesbury Rd.
Westmead, NSW, 2145</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to evaluate whether a test dose of melphalan can be used successfully to target a desired exposure in patients with multiple myeloma scheduled to undergo autologous stem cell transplantation. Higher drug exposure is associated with improved disease control and survival post transplant.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a male or female of any age who is scheduled to receive single agent high dose melphalan and autologous stem cell rescue for multiple myeloma.

Trial details
All participants in this trial will receive a test dose of 20 mg/m2 melphalan 4 days prior to scheduled autologous stem cell transplantation.  This drug will be administered intravenously (i.e. into the vein). A series of six blood samples will be collected after the test dose to allow pharmacokinetic assessment and predictions of exposure for the full dose. The treating clinician will decide the actual full dose to be administered. Whatever dose is given, blood sampling and pharmacokinetic assessment of the full dose will allow determination of whether the test dose exposure accurately predicts the full dose exposure. The test dose amount was increased from 10 mg/m2 in an amendment which was approved in December 2013 to improve the quality of the predictions.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Conference Proceedings: 
1. Trotman J, Shaw PJ, Tiley C, Ramanathan S, Grigg A, Larsen S, Presgrave P, Kwan YL, Newman E, Estell J, Nath CE. Evaluation of pharmacokinetic-based dose predictions of high dose melphalan in patients with multiple myeloma. Inaugural National Myeloma Meeting, Victoria Aug 2016. 
2. Trotman J, Shaw PJ,  Tiley C, Ramanathan S,  Grigg A, Larsen SR,  Presgrave P, Yiu-Lam Kwan YL, Newman E, and Nath CE. Evaluation of Pharmacokinetic-based Dose Predictions of High Dose Melphalan in Patients with Multiple Myeloma. ASH poster presentation 2015. Blood  2015 126:4314. 
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Children's Hospitals Network Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kids Research Institute,
The Children's Hospital at Westmead,
Hawkesbury Rd.
Westmead, NSW, 2145
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/03/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/SCHN/441</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christa Nath</name>
      <address>Department of Biochemistry, 
The Children's Hospital at Westmead, 
Hawkesbury Rd,
Westmead, NSW, 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 98453287</phone>
      <fax>+61 (02) 98453332</fax>
      <email>christa.nath@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Judith Trotman</name>
      <address>Department of Haematology,
Concord Repatriation Hospital, 
Hospital Rd, 
Concord, NSW, 2139</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 97677243</phone>
      <fax>+61 (02) 97677650</fax>
      <email>Judith.Trotman@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christa Nath</name>
      <address>Department of Biochemistry, 
The Children's Hospital at Westmead, 
Hawkesbury Rd,
Westmead, NSW, 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 98453287</phone>
      <fax>+61 (02) 98453332</fax>
      <email>christa.nath@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christa Nath</name>
      <address>Department of Biochemistry, 
The Children's Hospital at Westmead, 
Hawkesbury Rd,
Westmead, NSW, 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 98453287</phone>
      <fax>+61 (02) 98453332</fax>
      <email>christa.nath@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>