<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336756">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000534987</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>What test is best for you? A bowel cancer family history risk website for patients and their GP's.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised trial of consumer-led familial cancer risk tool &amp; GP triage on risk-appropriate colorectal cancer screening</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bowel (Colorectal) Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Individuals from intervention General Practices who opt in to the study will be given a password, allowing them to access the Family History Website tool. This online tool will collect information about their family history of colorectal cancer and encourage discussion with their relatives so that they can gather accurate information. Upon completion of the questionnaire, individuals will be assigned to a NHMRC designated risk category for developing CRC, which will be accompanied by the appropriate screening recommendations, with a personalised summary of their information. This information will be accessible to their GP via a shared access facility, and participants will be encouraged to discuss their results with their GP within the following consultation. The completion of the family history website and GP consultation thereafter, is known as Assessment 1 at time = 0. Participants will be followed up 12 months after their completion of the Family History Website, where they will be required to self report their five year screening behaviour; while their GPs will complete a file audit and a survey about the utility of the Family History Website tool in addition to their knowledge about CRC risk and screening guidelines. This will be known as assessment 2 at time =1</interventions>
    <comparator>Individuals from control practices will not be contacted or recruited until time =1, 12 months after the intervention group opt in to the study. At time=1, control participants will be recruited and their self report five year screening behaviour will be recorded, along with a GP file audit, their known family history and demographic information such as age, gender and educational attainment. Consequently, screening behaviour will be measured during the same time for both the intervention and control groups. GPs from control practices will also be surveyed about their knowledge about CRC risk and screening guidelines.  Following the reporting of screening behaviour and the GP survey at time=1, the control group and their GPs will be able to access Family History Website tool if they so wish.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Outcome Aim:  Risk appropriate screening uptake as measured by the participants' five year screening behaviour  in  relation to their colorectal cancer risk category   

Five year screening behaviour- All participants will have their five year screening behaviour   recorded at time=1 by self report</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 to 18 months after randomisation, t=1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Colorectal cancer risk category- Intervention practice participants will receive a CRC risk category after completing the 'Family History Website' tool., at some time within the 12 month time period t=0. However, participants from control practices will asked about their 'known family history'  at time=1, and will not be allowed access to the 'Family History Website' tool, until after that information is collected.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 12 months of the intervention , t=0 for the intervention  group and one year after randomisation, t=1 for the control group</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP audit and survey- The GP audit will serve to validate self reported screening behaviour for both groups. The GP survey will collect valuable primary care feedback regarding the utility of the family history website (intervention group only), and gauge GP's general awareness of family history risks and current screening recommendations.  Additionally, practice demographic information and related characteristics will be recorded. This will also serve as a form of continuing education for GP's and they will be eligible to receive QA and CME points for participating in the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 to 18 months after randomisation, t=1.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants demographic information- Demographic information from participants will collected from intervention and control participants. This information will include socio-economic (educational attainment and employment status), gender, family size, age and ethnicity status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be collected when participants self report their five year screening behaviour 12 to 18 months after randomisation, t=1.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>25-74 year olds living in Australia, who are able to give informed consent and have English language literacy, with no prior diagnosis of colorectal cancer.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>74</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Individuals under 25 or over 74 years of age
- A previous/current diagnosis of colorectal cancer
- No internet access
- Inability to read/or write English at a year 8 level</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a random clustered trial, and recruitment will be randomised by practice not participants. General Practices will be sent a letter of invitation. If they agree to participate they will be randomly divided between control and intervention practices.  Practices will be expected to be involved in the study at some time over a 12 to 18 month period and will be blind to allocation. Participants will receive an invitation of participation in the study, from their GP practice. Intervention practices will be contacted at t=0 to send out letters of invitation and control practices 12 to 18 months later. Allocation is not concealed from the researchers as this will be required for follow- up.</concealment>
    <sequence>GP Practices that opt in to the study will be entered into a database and assigned to intervention or controlled group using a random sequence generator.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>7360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
School of Public Health
Sydney Medical School
Rm 125, Lvl 1, Edward Ford Building A27
NSW 2006
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Postal address:  PO Box 1201, DICKSON ACT 2602</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study will evlaute if implementing a web based tool allowing consumers time to gather information about their family history of bowel (colorectal) cancer , (to be used in conjunction with GP triage), will reduce the proportion of average risk people having an unnecessary colonoscopy; while correctly indentifying and appropriately referring at-risk individuals to Familial Cancer Services and/or offering a colonoscopy. It aims to significantly reduce the public burden of bowel cancer by ensuring that the most effective screening can take place.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>S. Naicker,  L. Trevena,  B. Meiser, A. Goodwin, T. Dobbins, K. Barlow-Stewart, A. OBrien, J. Emery, M. Pirotta, J. Kirk. What test is best for you? - Evaluating a Family History Assessment tool to assist GP triage in appropriately screening for Colorectal Cancer, Primary Healthcare Conference 2011 Abstracts: Posters, Brisbane, QLD (2011).
 
S. Naicker,  L. Trevena,  B. Meiser, A. Goodwin, T. Dobbins, K. Barlow-Stewart, , J. Emery, M. Pirotta, J. Kirk , Developing a consumer-led  online familial cancer risk in screening for bowel cancer, Emerging Health Policy Research Conference, University of Sydney (2011).
 
S. Naicker,  L. Trevena,  B. Meiser, A. Goodwin, T. Dobbins, K. Barlow-Stewart, , J. Emery, M. Pirotta, J. Kirk. A pilot study to evaluate the utility of an online familial risk tool to screen for colorectal cancer. COSA: Annual scientific meeting 2011 Abstracts: posters, Perth, WA (2011).
 
S. Naicker,  L. Trevena,  B. Meiser, A. Goodwin, T. Dobbins, K. Barlow-Stewart, , J. Emery, M. Pirotta, J. Kirk. Implementation of a consumer led online familial risk tool to screen for colorectal cancer: Implications and findings, CRN Postgraduate Research Symposium, University of Sydney, (2011).</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee at the University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>14105</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/08/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Lyndal Trevena- Chief Investigator</name>
      <address>Associate Professor Lyndal Trevena
Sydney School of Public Health
Director, Office for Global Health
Sydney Medical School,
Room 321b, Edward Ford Building (A27)
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 7788</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lyndal.trevena@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Angela O'Brien-Research Assistant</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
Sydney Medical School
Rm 125, Lvl 1, Edward Ford Building A27
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 96367699</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>angela.obrien@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sundresan Naicker- PhD Candidate</name>
      <address>PhD Candidate

School of Public Health
Sydney Medical School
Rm 125, Lvl 1, Edward Ford Building A27
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>snai2338@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>