<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370989">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001170415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A phase 2 trial of durvalumab with first line chemotherapy in mesothelioma with a safety run in.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A phase 2 trial of durvalumab with first line chemotherapy in mesothelioma with a safety run in. 

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DREAM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>CTC 0142/ALTG 15/003</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malignant Pleural Mesothelioma (MPM).</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Mesothelioma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A safety run-in phase will be conducted to confirm the tolerability of the standard dose of durvalumab. The safety run-in of the study will be done at a limited number of study sites, once the durvalumab dose is confirmed recruitment will be expanded to all sites for the remainder of the trial.

Durvalumab 1125mg (dose to be confirmed by safety run in) AND chemotherapy (cisplatin 75mg/m2 and pemetrexed 500 mg/m2) are all given intravenously (IV) on day 1, repeated every 3 weeks for a maximum of 6 cycles. If there is no progression, continue durvalumab 1125mg IV on day 1 every 3 weeks for a maximum of an additional 12 cycles (18 cycles in total).

The study intervention will be delivered by experienced medical oncologists and their teams within a hospital based treatment facility.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression free survival at 6 months (PFS6) according to mRECIST for MPM.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months PFS measured from the date of trial entry until the date that disease progression is first observed, or the date of death from any cause, whichever occurs first.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The objective tumour response rate is defined as the proportion (percentage) of participants with a confirmed response of either Complete Response (CR) or Partial Response (PR) assessed by the investigator according to modified RECIST criteria for assessment of response in malignant pleural mesothelioma and according to modified immune-related response criteria (modified irRC).</outcome>
      <timepoint>For each participant, objective response will be based on evaluable response assessments performed up until progression or commencement of non-protocol anti-cancer therapy, whichever occurs first.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency and severity of adverse events (as per CTCAE v4.03).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse Events will be recorded from the first dose of study treatment until 90 days after cessation of study treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression free survival (PFS) according to mRECIST for MPM and mirRC.</outcome>
      <timepoint>PFS is measured from the date of registration until the date that disease progression is first observed, or the date of death from any cause, whichever occurs first.  The date of first disease progression based on imaging is that of the first positive scan, even if this is determined in retrospect.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival (OS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>OS is defined as the interval from the date of registration to the date of death from any cause.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Adults (18 years or over) with a histological or cytological diagnosis of malignant pleural mesothelioma that is not amendable to curative surgical resection
2.	Measurable disease as per modified RECIST criteria for assessment of response in malignant pleural mesothelioma 
3.	ECOG performance status of 0 or 1
4.	Tumour tissue (FFPE) available for PD-L1 testing at a central laboratory 
5.	Must have measurable disease without prior radiotherapy to these sites
6.	Adequate bone marrow function (done within 28 days prior to registration and with values within the ranges specified below).  Blood transfusions are permissible.
* Haemoglobin greater than or equal to 90 g/L
* Absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1.5 x 109/L
* Platelets greater than or equal to 100 x 109/L
7.	Adequate liver function (done within 28 days prior to registration and with values within the ranges specified below):
* Alanine transaminase less than or equal to 3 x upper limit of normal (ULN), unless liver metastases or invasion are present, in which case it must be less than or equal to 5 x ULN
* Aspartate aminotransferase less than or equal to 3 x ULN, unless liver metastases or invasion are present, in which case it must be less than or equal to 5 x ULN
* Total  bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 x ULN (except participants with Gilberts Syndrome, who are eligible with bilirubin less than or equal to 2.5 ULN)
8.	Adequate renal function (done within 28 days prior to registration and with values within the ranges specified below):
* Serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 x ULN 
or 
* Creatinine clearance (CrCl)  greater than or equal to 60 mL/min (use Cockroft-Gault formula)
9.	Willing and able to comply with all study requirements, including treatment, timing and/or nature of required assessments 
10.	Signed, written informed consent
11.	Women must be post-menopausal, infertile, or use a reliable means of contraception.  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test done within 24 hours prior to enrolment.  Men must have been surgically sterilised or use a (double if required) barrier method of contraception if they are sexually active with a woman of child bearing potential.  
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Prior chemotherapy or other systemic anti-cancer or immunotherapy for MPM
2.	Active, known or suspected autoimmune disease.  Participants are not excluded if they have vitiligo, type 1 diabetes mellitus, Graves disease, residual hypothyroidism due to an autoimmune condition requiring only hormone replacement, or psoriasis not requiring systemic treatment within the past 2 years.
3.	Any condition requiring systemic treatment with either corticosteroids (&gt;10mg daily prednisone or equivalent dose of an alternative corticosteroid) or other immunosuppressive medications within 28 days of durvalumab administration.  Intranasal, inhaled or topical steroids are permitted in the absence of active autoimmune disease.    
4.	Participants with symptomatic or uncontrolled brain metastases or leptomeningeal disease are excluded. Controlled brain metastases are those which have been treated and are radiologically and/or clinically stable, and the patient is asymptomatic and does not require corticosteroids. 
5.	Prior therapy with an anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, (including durvalumab) anti-PD-L2, anti-CTLA-4 antibody, or any other antibody or drug specifically targeting T cell co-stimulation or immune checkpoint pathways
6.	Current treatment or treatment within the last 12 months with any investigational products
7.	Life expectancy of less than 24 weeks
8.	History of another malignancy within 5 years prior to enrolment. Participants with a past history of adequately treated carcinoma-in-situ, basal cell carcinoma of the skin, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or superficial transitional cell carcinoma of the bladder are eligible. Participants with a history of other malignancies are eligible if they have been continuously disease free for at least 5 years after definitive primary treatment.
9.	Mean QT interval corrected for heart rate (QTc) greater than or equal to 470 ms calculated from 3 electrocardiograms using Fridericias Correction (QTc equal to QT/RR1/3) 
10.	Hearing loss or peripheral neuropathy considered by the investigators to contraindicate cisplatin administration
11.	History of hypersensitivity to investigational product, cisplatin/pemetrexed or any excipient
12.	Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active infection, symptomatic congestive cardiac failure, uncontrolled hypertension, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, active peptic ulcer disease or gastritis, active bleeding diatheses, hepatitis B, hepatitis C or human immunodeficiency virus
13.	Known history of interstitial lung disease from any cause 
14.	Known history of primary immunodeficiency, allogeneic organ transplant, inflammatory bowel disease (e.g. Crohns disease or ulcerative colitis), pneumonitis or active tuberculosis
15.	Receipt of live attenuated vaccination within 30 days prior to enrolment or within 30 days of receiving durvalumab  
16.	Specific comorbidities or conditions or concomitant medications which may interact with the investigational product(s)
17.	Any condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would interfere with evaluation of study treatment or interpretation of patient safety or study results
18.	Serious medical or psychiatric conditions that might limit the ability of the patient to comply with the protocol.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Not applicable</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The study will begin with an initial safety run-in using a 3+3 design and an expected accrual of 6 participants. These participants will be included in the total sample size of 54 evaluable participants, consisting of 31 recruited in stage 1, and another 23 recruited in stage 2. The null hypothesis is that the true PFS6 rate is 45%, which is in keeping with standard therapy and would be considered not worthy of further evaluation. With a one-sided type I error rate of 5%, the two-stage design provides greater than 90% power if the true PFS6 rate is 65% (alternate hypothesis).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/12/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>54</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/10/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Northern Cancer Institute - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>The Chris O’Brien Lifehouse - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Coffs Harbour Base Hospital - Coffs Harbour</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>Albury Wodonga Health - Albury campus - Albury</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre - Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Border Medical Oncology - Wodonga</hospital>
    <hospital>Murray Valley Private Hospital - Wodonga</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2450 - Coffs Harbour</postcode>
    <postcode>2747 - Kingswood</postcode>
    <postcode>2640 - Albury</postcode>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3690 - Wodonga</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland and Christchurch Hospitals</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Level 6, Medical Foundation Bld (K25)
92-94 Parramatta Rd
Camperdown NSW 2050
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AstraZeneca Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>66 Talavera Rd
Macquarie Park
NSW   2113

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will investigate the effectiveness of durvalumab in combination with standard chemotherapy for mesothelioma. 

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above, have had a diagnosis of malignant pleural mesothelioma that is not amenable to curative surgical resection.

Study details
All participants in the study will receive standard first-line chemotherapy for mesothelioma and the new treatment, durvalumab, intravenously on day 1 of each 3 week cycle for a maximum number of 18 cycles. 

Participants will be followed-up for a minimum of 12 months to determine progression free survival and tumour response rate.

Durvalumab is an antibody (a type of human protein) that works by blocking a body substance called PD-L1. Blocking PD-L1 helps the bodys immune system to attack cancer cells. Research has shown that durvalumab can slow tumour growth and shrink tumours in some people with cancer. We plan to enrol 54 participants in this study from hospitals and clinics throughout Australia. Durvalumab is currently an experimental treatment. This means that it is not yet approved for the treatment of mesothelioma, or any other condition, in Australia, or in other countries.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.ctc.usyd.edu.au/our-research/clinical-trials/oncology/lung-cancer/active-trials.aspx
</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SLHD Ethics Committee (RPAH zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Suite 210A 
RPA Medical Centre 
Cnr Missenden Road and Carillon Avenue 
NEWTOWN NSW 2042
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X-16-0234 and HREC/16/RPAH/287</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Anna Nowak</name>
      <address>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
c/o Medical Oncology
Hospital Ave
Nedlands
WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6151 1078 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tracey.hayward@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Hannora Jurkovic</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown
NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dream@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Anna Nowak</name>
      <address>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
c/o Medical Oncology
Hospital Ave
Nedlands
WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6151 1078 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tracey.hayward@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Hannora Jurkovic</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown
NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dream@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>