<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83527">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/01/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/02/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000160033</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised, placebo-controlled, trial of
concurrent cediranib [AZD2171] (with platinum-based chemotherapy) and concurrent and maintenance cediranib in
women with platinum-sensitive relapsed ovarian cancer.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>ICON6 is a randomised three-arm, three stage, double-blind, placebo-controlled multicentre Gynaecologic Cancer InterGroup (GCIG) phase III trial, designed to evaluate the safety and efficacy of platinum-based chemotherapy in
combination with cediranib in women with platinum-sensitive relapsed ovarian cancer. Cediranib (AZD2171) will be administered
during platinum-based chemotherapy only (concurrent cediranib), or given during
chemotherapy and continued as single agent (maintenance therapy) for up to 18 months(concurrent and maintenance cediranib).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ICON6</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>EUDRACT: 2007-001346-41</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Platinum sensitive relapsed ovarian cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Cediranib is an oral targeted small molecule inhibitor of a key signalling molecule and acts through blockade of a key receptor. Cediranib will be administered as a daily 20mg tablet (ie oral) during platinum-based chemotherapy only (concurrent cediranib), OR given as an oral 20mg tablet during chemotherapy and continued daily as single agent maintenance therapy for up to 18 months (concurrent and maintenance cediranib).</interventions>
    <comparator>All patients, regardless of the arm they are randomised to, will be planned to receive 6
cycles of platinum-based chemotherapy.   ICON6 patients are treated with carboplatin AUC6 over 30-60 minutes, in combination with paclitaxel 175 mg/m2 over three hours, three weekly for six cycles, assuming that the patient is fit enough to receive this. Those not be fit enough to receive combination therapy due to additional toxicity, or those patients who decline combination therapy will be eligible  to receive six cycles of single agent carboplatin.  This is considered 'standard therapy' in this group of women.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stage 2 primary outcome; progression free survivial (PFS).
If a minimal level of activity of cediranib based on PFS and overal survival (OS) is not detected, the trial could be stopped early. Analysis will be performed when both at least 50 deaths and at least 90 progressions or deaths have occurred in the reference arn (Arm A) which is anticipated after 150 patients are randomised to Arm A and 450 patients total randomised to Arms B and C.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Stage 2; 2 years after stage 1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stage 3- progression free survival, toxicity and Quality of Life.
To evaluate the nature, severity and frequentcy of toxicities.
Quality of life will be assessed by patient self reported questionnaires administered during treament and three monthly until progression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Stage 3; 6 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stage 2- overall survival and toxicity.
Determined by seeing whether a minimal level of activity of cediranib can be detected by comparing OS in patients receiving chemotherapy alone (Arm A) with PFS in patients receiving chemotherapy and cediranib (arm B plus C).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Stage 2; 2 years after stage 1</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Histologically proven diagnosis of epithelial ovarian carcinoma, fallopian tube carcinoma
or primary serous peritoneal carcinoma
requiring treatment with further platinum-based chemotherapy &gt; 6 months after
their last cycle of first-line chemotherapy and 6 weeks after maintenance that is
not chemotherapy based (computed tomographic scan [CT] or Magnetic Resonance Imaging [MRI] proven relapsed disease (measurable or non-measurable). 
Adequate bone marrow function.
Adequate liver function (within 14 days before randomisation).
Adequate renal function.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Non-epithelial ovarian cancer, including malignant mixed Mullerian tumours and
mucinous carcinoma of the peritoneum.
Poorly controlled hypertension (persistently elevated &gt; 150/100mmHg, either
systolic or diastolic or both, despite anti-hypertensive medication).
History of inflammatory bowel disease (Crohns Disease or Ulcerative Colitis).
Arterial thrombotic event (including transient ischaemic attack [TIA],
cerebrovascular accident [CVA] and peripheral arterial embolus) within the
previous 12 months.
Significant haemorrhage of &gt; 30ml in a single episode within 3 months or any
haemoptysis.
Evidence of severe or uncontrolled cardiac disease.
Prolonged QTc (corrected) interval of &gt; 470msec on electrocardiogram [ECG], or a family history of long QT syndrome.
History or clinical suspicion of brain metastases or spinal cord compression.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is concealed because central randomisation is by phone /fax /computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures>After stage 1 (safety): if there are more than 15% of patients with grade 3 or 4 adverse events the study could be stopped or modified.
Stage 2 (activity). If a minimal level of activity of cediranib was not detected after 600 patients wererandomised, the trial could be stopped early.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC,QLD,WA,TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2000</postcode>
    <postcode>3000</postcode>
    <postcode>4000</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>North and South Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AstraZenica</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>5 Alma Rd
North Ryde 2113</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medical Research Council Clinical Trial Unit</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>222 Euston Road
London NW1 2DA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to investigate whether the benefits of chemotherapy can be improved in women with relapsed ovarian cancer, by adding a new drug called Cediranib. Chemotherapy describes drug treatments which kill or control the growth of cancer cells. Cediranib is a targeted therapy rather than a chemotherapy drug. As cancers grow they need to develop their own new blood supply to survive and this development of new blood supply vessels is known as angiogenesis. Cediranib works by slowing or stopping the growth of these new blood vessels which will hopefully interfere with the tumours ability to grow and spread to other parts of the body. It may also make the planned chemotherapy more effective. We believe that this may be an important new way to treat cancer. Although there are good scientific reasons from laboratory studies why Cediranib should work on ovarian cancer cells, it has not yet been tested in a large number of women with ovarian cancer.  Cediranib is an investigational medical product which is not licensed for use in treatment of ovarian cancer or any other cancer</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cancer Institute of NSW</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Cancer Institute NSW
Australian Technology Park
Biomedical Building
Suite 101, 1 Central Avenue
EVELEIGH  NSW  2015</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2009C/03/087</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/03/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Julie Martyn</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trial Centre 
Level 2 
6-10 Mallett St
Camperdown 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5092</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9562 5094</fax>
      <email>julie.martyn@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kerri Carlton</name>
      <address>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC )Clinical Trial Centre 
Level 2 
6-10 Mallett St
Camperdown 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5067</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9562 5094</fax>
      <email>kerri.carlton@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kerri Carlton</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trial Centre 
Level 2 
6-10 Mallett St
Camperdown 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5067</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9562 5094</fax>
      <email>kerri.carlton@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>