<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362725">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001002875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised Controlled Trial to Compare Administration of Prothrombin Complex Concentrate with Standard Haemostasis Management in Adult Patients Undergoing Peritoneal Cytoreductive Surgery Requiring Massive Transfusion.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of prothrombin complex in achieving haemostasis compared to standard treatment in adult patients undergoing peritoneal cytoreductive surgery requiring massive transfusion.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1132-5054</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients undergoing peritoneal cytoreductive surgery</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Peritoneal cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients to receive early administration of prothrombin complex concentrate. It may be administered after surgery has commenced and based on the peritoneal carcinomatosis index (PCI) count, it is considered that the patient is at high risk of massive transfusion. Prothrombinex will be administered at a dose of 20IU/kg ( up to a maximum of 50IU/kg), given intravenously. The dose given will be at the discretion of the physician.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients will receive usual standard haemostasis management- this includes administration of blood products (FFP, cryoprecipitate) according to laboratory coagulation results.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy of Prothrombinex in achieving haemostasis compared to standard treatment. Achievement of haemostasis shall be defined as stable haematocrit and no increase in drain losses with blood.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in the number of units of blood products transfused in the first 24 hours, including the time of surgery.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measured blood loss and other fluid loss (cell saver, etc). This will be assessed by visual assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Volume of other fluids received</outcome>
      <timepoint>During surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Requirement for take-back to operating theatre (OT)  to control bleeding within 7 days of surgery</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 7 days of surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thrombotic events to be recorded as adverse events</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 7 days of surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Age greater than or equal to 18 years
2.	Planned for peritonectomy
3.	Informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Known bleeding disorder
2.	Known requirement for anti-coagulation e.g. prior DVT/PE requiring anti-coagulation, requirement for caval filter
3.	Known hypersensitivity to any pooled-blood or recombinant blood products
4.	Known hypersensitivity to any constituents in Prothrombinex-VF, including know allergy to heparin or a history of heparin-induced thrombocytopenia
5.	 Evidence of active thrombosis or disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible patients will be pre-consented for participation in the study prior . As only a proportion of patients will be eligible for randomization (as explained below in study procedures) and in view of the logistic impossibility of real-time consenting, patients will be pre-consented for participation prior to surgery. During surgery, and at the discretion of the surgical and anaesthetic teams, the patient will be determined to be suitable for randomisation based on their anticipated risk of massive transfusion. Eligible participants will be randomised to standard care or early use of Prothrombinex-VF.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation: If the patient is at risk of massive transfusion (as evaluated by the anaesthetist and surgeon), the patient will be randomised to either arm by contacting an independent data manager holding the code. The randomisation code will be one to one using variable block sizes to allocate the patient to either arm.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St George Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Gray St, Kogarah, NSW 2217</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St George Public Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Gray St, Kogarah, NSW 2217</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian New Zealand Society of Blood Transfusion</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>145 Macquarie St, 
Sydney NSW 2000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to investigate whether the early use of a blood clotting drug during peritonectomy surgery reduces the amount of bleeding that occurs and so reduces the amount of blood transfusion you may need. Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above and are scheduled to undergo a peritonectomy. Trial details: Peritonectomy surgery is associated with a high risk of bleeding and many patients will require what is known as massive blood transfusion. This typically involves a transfusion of at least 10 units of blood or roughly your whole blood volume. In this research we hope to compare two treatments. Half the participants will receive the standard treatment used in this hospital. This involves the use of blood clotting factors and blood transfusion. In addition patients who have persistently high blood loss are sometimes given a treatment called recombinant factor VIIa. The other half of the participants will receive a product known as Prothrombinex-VF early in the operation when the anaesthetist suspects that there will be high blood loss. Prothrombinex-VF is a commercial product that contains blood clotting factors  these help the blood clot. All other treatment will be the same as usual practice. With this research we hope to be able to show that early use of Prothrombinex-VF reduces the need for blood transfusion and the overall need for blood products such as blood clotting factor preparations.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SESLHD Human Research Ethics Committee (Southern Sector)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St George and sutherland Hospital research Office,
Level 3 James Law House, St George Hospital, Gray St, Kogarah NSW 2217</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Shir-Jing Ho</name>
      <address>Department of Haematology,
St George Hospital, Gray st, Kogarah NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>61 2 91133851</phone>
      <fax>61 2 91133942</fax>
      <email>shir-jing.ho@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Roslyn Ristuccia</name>
      <address>St George Hospital Clinical Trials Unit, Ground FLoor, Pitney Building, St George Hospital, Gray St, Kogarah, NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>61 2 91132977</phone>
      <fax>61 2 91132960</fax>
      <email>RistucciaR@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Shir-Jing Ho</name>
      <address>Department of Haematology,
St George Hospital, Gray st, Kogarah NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>61 2 91133851</phone>
      <fax>61 2 91133942</fax>
      <email>shir-jing.ho@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>