<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336363">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/12/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000085976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of Lenalidomide Maintenance Versus Placebo in Responding Elderly Patients With Diffuse Large B cell Lymphoma (DLBCL) and Treated With Rituximab, Cyclophosphamide, Doxorubicin, Vincristine, and Prednisone (R-CHOP)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Double blind randomized phase III study of
Lenalidomide (Revlimid Registered Trademark) maintenance versus
Placebo in responding elderly patients with
diffuse large B cell lymphoma (DLBCL) and treated with Rituximab, Cyclophosphamide, Doxorubicin, Vincristine, and Prednisone (R-CHOP) in first line</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>REMARC</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Clinical trials.gov NCT01122472</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diffuse large B cell lymphoma (DLBCL) in elderly patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - Low grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>25mg daily lenalidomide for 21 days of a 28 day cycle of maintenance therapy for up to 26 cycles. Lenalidomide is an oral tablet.</interventions>
    <comparator>placebo oral tablet contains the excipients used for the drug product without the active ingredient and it conforms to the colour and size for blinded study. It is taken daily for 21 days of a 28 day cycle of maintenance therapy for up to 26 cycles.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>to determine the benefit estimated by the progression-free survival associated with lenalidomide maintenance compared to placebo in responding patients treated with R-CHOP for diffuse large B-cell lymphoma. Progression will be measured by tests such as CT scan, PET scan and Bone Marrow examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary endpoint will be analysed when a total of 160 progression or death events have occurred, or at the latest, when 5 years median follow-up has been met.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival (OS) in both groups of patients (with and without lenalidomide maintenance)</outcome>
      <timepoint>OS is from the date of randomization to the date of death from any cause. An interim analysis of OS will be performed at the time of PFS analysis. At study closure, the final analysis of OS will be conducted.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number and percentage of patients who convert from partial response (PR) at the end of induction treatment
to complete response (CR) at the end of maintenance treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomisation until end of maintenance therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>efficacy according to the response to R-CHOP and will be measured by tests such as CT scan, PET scan and Bone Marrow examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization to the end of the 24 months maintenance</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>safety of lenaliodmide in maintenance and will be measured by medical reviews and blood tests</outcome>
      <timepoint>60 days after last dose of study treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Response rate at the end of maintenance treatment will be measured by tests such as CT scan, PET scan, Cheson 2007 criteria, blood tests, tumor biopsy and Bone Marrow examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From randomization to the end of 24 months maintenance</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Second relapse/progression (PFS2) as measured by time from randomisation to objective tumour progression on next-line treatment or death from any cause, Time to event analysis will be conducted. The recurrent event approach will also be used to take account of the first and second progression. </outcome>
      <timepoint>An interim analysis of second relapse/progression (PFS2) will be performed at the time of PFS analysis. At study closure, the final analysis of PFS2 will be conducted.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>For patients registered at the time of initial diagnosis

initial diagnosis of histologically confirmed CD20+ DLBCL
previously untreated with chemo- or radiotherapy

For patients registered after response evaluation to first line treatment with R-CHOP:

Diagnosis of histologically confirmed CD20+ diffuse large B-Cell Lymphoma 
Have reached a CR or PR after first line treatment with at least 6 cycles of R-CHOP 14 regimen or up to 8 cycles of R-CHOP21 
Previously untreated with Radiotherapy

For all patients:

aged from 60 to 80 years at time of initial diagnosis 
Ann Arbor stages II-IV at time of initial diagnosis 
age-adjusted International Prognostic Index greater than 1 at time of initial diagnosis 
Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status 0-2 
Minimum life expectancy of 3 months 
Following laboratory values at screening:

absoloute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1000x10^6/Litre and Platelets greater than or equal to 60000x10^6/Litre 
Aspartate transaminase (AST) less than or equal to 5x Upper limit of normal (ULN), Alanine transaminase (ALT) less than or equal to 5xULN, Total Bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5xULN 
Creatinine clearance&gt;30mL/min 
Women of childbearing potential are using effective contraception, are not pregnant and agree not to become pregnant during participation in the trial and after end of study. Men agree to use a condom during sexual contact with a female, even if they have had a vasectomy, and to not donate semen or sperm throughout study drug therapy, during any dose interruption and during the 12 months thereafter. 
Having previously signed a written informed consent form</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any other histological type of lymphoma, Burkitt included.
Any history of treated or non-treated small B-cell lymphoma
Central nervous system or meningeal involvement by lymphoma
Contraindication to any drug contained in the chemotherapy regimen.
Myocardial infarction during last 3 months or unstable coronary disease or uncontrolled chronic
symptomatic congestive heart insufficiency New York Heart Association III-IV
Uncontrolled hypertension
Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus as defined by the investigator
Active systemic infection requiring treatment.
Previously known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive serology
Active hepatitis B or C
Prior history of malignancies other than lymphoma within 3 years (except for complete resection of basal cell carcinoma, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, or in situ malignancy)
Serious medical or psychiatric illness likely to interfere with participation in this clinical study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients can be either registered before induction therapy or after induction therapy. Randomization should occur after documentation of CR or PR and maintenance treatment will start within 8 weeks after the first day of the last R-CHOP cycle. Randomisation will occur through a central registration centre.</concealment>
    <sequence>random number allocated by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/03/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>13/05/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>54</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC,ACT,QLD,SA,WA,TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3002</postcode>
    <postcode>2137</postcode>
    <postcode>3690</postcode>
    <postcode>3084</postcode>
    <postcode>5000</postcode>
    <postcode>4215</postcode>
    <postcode>7001</postcode>
    <postcode>6000</postcode>
    <postcode>6009</postcode>
    <postcode>2217</postcode>
    <postcode>3065</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6, 372 Albert St
East Melbourne, Victoria, 3002</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>GELA</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Centre Hospitalier Lyon Sud - Secteur Sainte Eugenie
(Batiment 6D) - Chemin du Grand Revoyet 
69310 Pierre Benite</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>France</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 6, 372 Albert St
East Melbourne, Victoria, 3002</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Celgene Global</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Celgene Corporation
86 Morris Avenue
Summit, NJ 07901
1-908-673-9000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>GELA</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre Hospitalier Lyon Sud - Secteur Sainte Eugenie
(Batiment 6D) - Chemin du Grand Revoyet 
69310 Pierre Benite</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>France</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In patients between 60-80 years with diffuse large B cell lymphoma (DLBCL), the current standard treatment is R-CHOP chemotherapy (consisting of the drugs Rituximab, Cyclophosphamide, Doxorubicin, Vincristine, and Prednisone). However the probability of being alive and free of lymphoma 5 years after diagnosis is only 54%. Lenalidomide is an immune system modulating drug that has anti-lymphoma properties demonstrated in smaller studies of patients with relapsed/refractory DLBCL. Given the high risk of relapsed DLBCL in this older patient population this study is aimed at determining whether Lenalidomide maintenance taken orally for 21 days every 4 weeks can safely reduce the risk of progression/relapse of DLBCL. Who is it for? This study is open to patients aged between 60 and 80 years and currently underoing R-CHOP combination therapy for diffuse large B-cell lymphoma. Trial details Participants will be randomised into one of two arms, (1) 25mg daily lenalidomide for 21 days of a 28 day cycle of maintenenace therapy for up to 26 cycles, or (2) a placebo instead of the active drug over the same period. The aim of the study is to reduce the risk of progression/relapse of DLBCL</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/02/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Judith Trotman</name>
      <address>Concord Repatriation General Hospital
Hospital Road
Concord, NSW, 2139</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9767 7243</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>judith.trotman@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Narmatha Kuru</name>
      <address>Biostatistics and Clinical Trials
Peter Mac Cancer Centre
Level 2/10 St Andrews place
East Melbourne, VIC, 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9656 5807</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>narmatha.kuru@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Delaine Smith</name>
      <address>Australasian Leukaemia &amp; Lymphoma Group, Ground Floor, 35 Elizabeth St, Richmond, VIC 3121.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>delaine.smith@allg.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Judith Trotman</name>
      <address>Concord Repatriation General Hospital Hospital Road Concord, NSW, 2139 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9767 7243 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>judith.trotman@sswahs.nsw.gov.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>