<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368458">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001296527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of personal ultraviolet radiation (UVR) devices and the SunSmart phone application on sun protection habits.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of personal ultraviolet radiation (UVR) devices and the SunSmart phone application on sun protection habits in the adult population in Queensland.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SknTec</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Skin Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Non melanoma skin cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: UVR Device Group
We will recruit male and female volunteers from the general community in Queensland. We wish to assess whether receiving daily UVR information or a personal UVR feedback device will increase the mean sun protection habits index score (compared to the control group) by half a standard deviation one week after the intervention, and whether this score will be sustained for 3 months after the intervention. This group will be asked to wear the UVR dosimeter feedback device pinned to clothing during daylight hours for 1 month (manufactured by Healthtronics SunSafe). This device provides information to the participant on current UVR dose and whether they fall within a safe range. A daily diary will be used to monitor adherence. 

Arm 2: SunSmart App Group
We will recruit male and female volunteers from the general community in Queensland. We wish to assess whether receiving daily UVR information or a personal UVR feedback device will increase the mean sun protection habits index score (compared to the control group) by half a standard deviation one week after the intervention, and whether this score will be sustained for 3 months after the intervention. This group will be asked to use the SunSmart phone application on their phone for 1 month with daily UV notification alerts (programmed by Cancer Council Victoria).The SunSmart notifies participants when sun protection is required . A daily diary will be used to monitor adherence.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 3: No Intervention Control Group
We will recruit male and female volunteers from the general community in Queensland. We wish to assess whether there is a difference over time between the control group and intervention groups on sun protection habits, sun exposure behaviours, sunburn, and physical activity levels. Participants in this group will not receive any devices or technology and will be asked to go about their normal everyday activities.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sun Protection Habits Score (Using Sun Protection Habbits Index). </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 1-week, and 3-months after intervention commencement. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sunburn Incidence (Using questionnaire designed specifically for this study) </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 1-week, and 3-months after intervention commencement. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>physical activity levels (Using questionnaire designed specifically for this study) </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 1-week and 3 months after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>satisfaction with use of device/technology (Using questionnaire designed specifically for this study) </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 month after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Understand sufficient English; cognitive ability for consent; own a private mobile phone; Fitzpatrick skin type 1-3: no previous melanoma; individuals who do not use the SunSmart application on a regular basis. Drawing from our experience and previous studies, we estimate 85% of interested volunteers will fulfil these criteria. We will assess pigmentation and skin cancer history during screening using a questionnaire developed from our previous studies. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>This trial has no exclusion criteria related to age, socio economic status, gender, or ethnicity. This means that individuals with characteristics associated with poorer outcomes (e.g., younger age, lower socio-economic status, and those living in rural areas) will be eligible to participate. Randomisation of participants, and presenting or providing material to a standard English level (ILR Level 3) will help to minimise any equity issues that may arise during the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants (males and females 18-35 years) will be recruited from the local community on a volunteer basis via media campaigns and flyers. While it is possible that this recruitment strategy will not provide a fully representative sample, other recruitment methods have their own biases and are less suitable for young populations (e.g., using the white pages or the electoral roll). The RCT design of our study will ascertain internal validity. While the intervention would be suitable to people all over Australia, we will first test it in Queensland where the UV Index is high (&gt;3) throughout the year, requiring sun protection almost all year round. To alleviate the impact of seasonal variation the intervention will run over the summer months with enrolment of participants during spring.  Central randomisation by computer will be used.</concealment>
    <sequence>Once the baseline visit is completed, randomisation will be conducted by a computerised random-number generator, stratified by gender (male/female), Fitzpatrick skin type (1-3), and age group (18-35 years), in permuted blocks.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Continuous data will be summarised by presenting the descriptive statistics (e.g., mean, standard deviation). We will use suitable tests to assess differences between groups (t tests for simple tests; ANOVA and regression for multivariate assessments). Categorical data will be summarised by presenting the number and percentage in each category, and the chi square statistic test will be calculated for association. All statistical tests of significance will be performed at the 5% level of significance and will be 2-sided unless otherwise stated. 
The intention-to-treat principle will be used for the analysis of the primary hypotheses. One of the main strengths of RCT design is that the effect of potential confounders should be equalised between groups at baseline. The intervention groups will be compared to the control group with respect to baseline characteristics and outcome measures using analysis of variance, and other generalised linear models as appropriate (depending on the measurement scale of the outcome). A dichotomous variable representing the intervention arm (UVR dosimeter or UVR app versus control) will be included to enable assessment of the independent effect of the respective intervention group, compared to the control group. Linear and logistic regression models with the intervention versus control arm as the between-subjects factor will be used to analyse the outcome measures between the study arms at three-months follow-up, with Poisson models used to count data. These analyses will allow us to identify the independent effect of the intervention on participants behaviour in relation to sun protection habits and sunburn. For the longitudinal analysis we will adopt a generalised estimating equation approach to model the repeated binary outcomes. We will also examine whether there is a dose-response relationship between degree of device use and outcomes. Satisfaction with the use and recall of the dosimeter alarm or app messages, and attitudes and intentions will be analysed using descriptive statistics. 
Sample size estimation: Using the data gathered from our earlier research project, which assessed the impact of personalised mobile phone messages on improving skin protection behaviours in young adults, we observed a standard deviation of 0.5 among a similar Queensland study sample 18 to 42 year olds (Janda et al. 2013). Our sample size calculations are based on a similar common standard deviation, and will allow us to detect a difference in the mean score of 0.3 between the intervention and control group (e.g., an increase in the mean score from 2.3 to 2.6 at follow-up in the intervention group while the control group mean score remains constant at 2.3). Corresponding with an effect size of 0.4, given a common standard deviation of 0.5 between three groups, where two of the groups are compared to one control group (based on the Dunnett multiple comparison test). Our sample of 201 participants (67 participants per intervention group) will allow for attrition rates of up to 10%. We have previously found attrition rates less than 10% in this population (Hacker et al. 2013). As this is an emerging new field of research, the magnitude of anticipated effects may be larger. Evidence from feedback devices in physical activity research suggests that it may induce an improvement in intervention group behaviours compared to the control group of a moderate effect size (King et al. 2013, Stephens et al. 2013).    </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>7/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>9/11/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>201</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>125</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>5/04/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4059 - Kelvin Grove</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>60 Musk Ave,
Kelvin Grove, Brisbane, Queensland, 4059</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Council Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>553 Gregory Terrace, Fortitude Valley
Spring Hill, Brisbane, Queensland, 4001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor John Lowe</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of the Sunshine Coast
90 Sippy Downs Drive, Sippy Downs QLD 4556</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will determine the effect of personal ultraviolet radiation (UVR) devices and the SunSmart phone application on sun protection habits in adult volunteers from the general community. 

Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18  35 years old, own a private mobile phone, have Fitzpatrick skin type 1-3 and no previous melanoma.

Study details Participants in this study are randomly allocated (by chance) to one of three groups. Participants in one group will be asked to wear a UVR dosimeter feedback device on daily basis for 1 month. Participants in another group will be asked to download and use the the SunSmart phone application on their phone for 1 month. While the third group will not be given access to either technology and will continue their normal everyday activities.

Participants will be asked to use the technologies daily for 1 month. Participants will be followed up at 1 week and 3 months after the intervention commences with questionnaires to determine changes in sun protection and exposure habits, sunburn incidence and satisfaction with use of technologies.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland University of Tecnology Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>60 Musk Ave,
Kelvin Grove, Brisbane, Queensland, 4059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1400000302</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elke Hacker</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
School of Public Health and Social Work
Victoria Park Road
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 9674</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elke.hacker@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elke Hacker</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
School of Public Health and Social Work
Victoria Park Road
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 9674</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elke.hacker@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elke Hacker </name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
School of Public Health and Social Work
Victoria Park Road
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 9674</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elke.hacker@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elke Hacker</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
School of Public Health and Social Work
Victoria Park Road
Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 9674</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>elke.hacker@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>