<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372396">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000296336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Robotic and Open Surgery for Prostate Cancer: A Prospective, Multi-centre, Comparative Study of Functional and Oncological Outcomes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Robotic and Open Surgery for Prostate Cancer: A Prospective, Multi-centre, Comparative Study of Functional and Oncological Outcomes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1193-2808 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>ROSE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prostate Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Robot-Assisted Laparoscopic Prostatectomy (RALP) using "da Vinci Xi" (Registered Trademark) Intuitive Surgical Surgical System (average 3-4hrs duration) by participating surgeons at RPAH.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Open Radical Prostatectomy (ORP) using conventional open surgery (average 3-4hrs duration) by participating surgeons at either CRGH or RPAH.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To prospectively assess differences in post-operative patient continence between RARP and ORP:
This will be assessed using patient-reported QOL (SF-36 and ICIQ-UI) questionnaires and urinary pad weight tests (1hr and 24hr).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operatively, then post-operatively at 6 weeks, 3-, 6- and 12- months, 2-, 5-, and 10- years.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To prospectively assess differences in post-operative urinary function between RARP and ORP:
Urinary function will be assessed by measuring urodynamic parameters, including Qmax, detrusor leak point and pressure, bladder compliance, storage dysfunction (OAB) and voiding dysfunction (BOO, detrusor underactivity, stress or urgency incontinence), pelvic floor contraction and mobility. These will be measured using urodynamic tests and imaging. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operatively and post-operatively at 12-months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To prospectively assess differences in post-operative erectile function between RARP and ORP: 
Sexual function will be assessed using patient reported QOL (IIEF and IPSS) questionnaires and genitosensory analyses that involves the measurement of penile sensation to various stimuli (hot,cold, and vibratory).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once up to 4-weeks Pre-operatively, then post-operatively at 12-months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To prospectively assess differences in oncological outcomes between RARP and ORP: 

Oncological outcomes will be assessed by comparing patient clinical stage, biopsy gleason score and Prostate volume (PV). These measures will be determined by pathology tests and imaging.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once up to 4-weeks pre-operatively

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To prospectively assess differences in pre- and post-operative clinical outcomes between RARP and ORP: 

The clinical outcomes will be assessed by BMI, ASA, PSA, mpMRI/CT, Pelvic cavity index, prostate volume, and mortality. These measures will be determined by patient medical records, pathology tests and imaging. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Once up to 4-weeks pre-operatively and post-operatively at 2- and 6-weeks, 3- and 12-months. PSA also at 5- and 10-years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To prospectively assess differences in intra-operative clinical outcomes between RARP and ORP.
Intra-operative outcomes will be assessed by surgical access, number and degree of complications (details in Cancer Fields section of application), surgery conversions, blood loss, operative time, pain rating (NPRS), length of hospital stay, transfusion volume, and mortality. These measures will be determined from operation reports and hospital medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intra-operatively (i.e. on the day of surgery), and up to 1-week post-operatively (depending on when patient is discharged from hospital).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To prospectively assess differences in health economic outcomes between RARP and ORP, Economic evaluation will be assessed by calculating difference between resource use and costs, patient out-of-pocket costs and economic benefit analysis (such as quality adjusted life years). These measures will be determined from patient medical records, hospital financial reports and patient reported healthcare utilisation questionnaire. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once up to 4-weeks pre-operatively, post-operatively at 6-weeks and 6-months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To prospectively assess differences in patient decision regret between RARP and ORP, assessed by the Decision Regret Scale questionnaire.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-operatively at 6-weeks, 3- and 12-months, 5- and 10-years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To prospectively assess differences in patient reported quality of life between RARP and ORP, assessed by SF-36v, EPIC and ICIQ-UI questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once up to 4-weeks pre-operatively, then post-operatively at 6-weeks, 3-, 6-, and 12-months, 5- and 10-years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Adult men aged 18 years and over;
2. Undergoing prostatectomy for prostate cancer at RPA or Concord Hospitals;
3. Clinically suitable for robotic prostatectomy;
4. Cognitively able to give written informed consent for participation;
5. Elective procedure.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. The patient lacks the ability to consent for themselves;
2. Patients unwilling to undergo pre- and post-operative evaluation according to protocol;
3. Patient or tumour factors precluding robotic surgery.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed. 
Assignment to Robotic or Open surgery will be determined by the treating surgeon</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Demographic and clinical characteristics of patients who undergo robotic and open prostatectomy will be compared using chi-square tests and Fishers test. Perioperative outcomes (e.g. operative time / console time, conversion to open, blood loss, transfusion, complications) will be compared between groups using chi-square tests and t tests. Patient reported outcome measures (including symptom scores and quality of life measures) will be scored according to the developers instructions. The mean change in scores between baseline and 6 months and baseline and 12 months will be compared between groups using t tests or Wilcoxon rank sum tests depending on the distribution of the data. For patients who have a robotic procedure, univariate associations between clinical factors and poor functional outcomes will be assessed. Multivariate regression modelling will be used to identify which factors are statistically significant and independent predictors of poor outcomes. A P &lt;0.05 will be considered as statistically significant.
The sample size of 220 patients (110 per trial arm) was calculated for a trial with 80% power to detect a 10% difference from the null hypothesis with 95% confidence.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>7/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>220</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sydney Local Health District</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 11, KGV Building
Missenden Road
Camperdown
NSW 
2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sydney Local Health District</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 11, KGV Building
Missenden Road
Camperdown
NSW 
2050

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will compare the effect of robotic and open surgery for prostate cancer on functional and oncological outcomes

Who is this study for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above, are undergoing prostatectomy for prostate cancer at RPA or Concord Hospitals and are clinically suitable for robotic prostatectomy.

Study details
Participants will either have robotic assisted laparascopic surgery or conventional open surgery as determined by the treating surgeon.

All participants will undergo tests to determine urinary and erectile function, biopsies to determine oncological outcomes and questionnaires to assess quality of life. These assessments will be conducted pre-operatively, post-operatively and at certain follow-up timepoints up to 10 years.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital Ethics Review Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown
NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/RPAH/377; Protocol X16-0294; NEAF (AU/1/2717218</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Scott Leslie</name>
      <address>Missenden Medical Centre
Suite 7B
54-60 Briggs St
Camperdown
NSW
2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95502713</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>info@scottleslie.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruban Thanigasalam</name>
      <address>Inner West Urology
12 Mary St
Auburn
NSW
2144</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9643 1223</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drruban.urology@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruban Thanigasalam</name>
      <address>Inner West Urology
12 Mary St
Auburn
NSW
2144</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9643 1223</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drruban.urology@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Daniel Steffens</name>
      <address>Surgical Outcomes Research Centre
Level 9, Building 89
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown
NSW
2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9515 3203</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Daniel.Steffens@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>