<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370086">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000187448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Bright light therapy to improve sleep and quality of life in children with acute lymphoblastic leukaemia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does bright light therapy improve sleep, reduce fatigue and improve quality of life in children (3-9 years old) with acute lymphoblastic leukaemia during maintenance therapy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1179-3707</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukaemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sleep Disorders</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fatigue</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Quality of Life</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Leukaemia &amp; Lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The participants (children 3-9 years of age with Acute Lymphoblastic Leukaemia) will be randomly assigned to the treatment group. They will wear a Feel Bright Light Visor (Physicians Engineered Products, Maine, USA) for 30 minutes as soon as awakening in the morning, for the 84 days of the second cycle of maintenance treatment. This device delivers 8,000 lux of light in the wavelength range of 460 nm to 550 nm. In addition to the light visor, the children will be asked to wear a small device attached to their clothing at the same time (HOBO Pendant (Registered Trademark) 8K Temperature/Light Data Logger (Onset Computer Corporation, Bourne, MA, USA), which measures light intensity and will be used to assess compliance. </interventions>
    <comparator>Children 3-9 years of age with Acute Lymphoblastic Leukaemia) will be randomly assigned to the control group. They will have no light therapy intervention and will also be studied during the the 84 days of the second cycle of maintenance treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite outcome of sleep quantity and quality, using a combination of actigraphy, sleep diary and the Tayside Childrens Sleep Questionnaire.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Comparing the five days before  light therapy to the last five days of the second cycle of maintenance treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life using the PedsQL - Cancer module and the Mood and Feelings Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Comparing the five days before  light therapy to the last five days of the second cycle of maintenance treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daytime sleepiness using the Modified Epworth Sleepiness Scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Comparing the five days before  light therapy to the last five days of the second cycle of maintenance treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental  stress  using the Parenting Stress Index  short form </outcome>
      <timepoint>Comparing the five days before  light therapy to the last five days of the second cycle of maintenance treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite outcome of sleep quantity and quality, using a combination of actigraphy, sleep diary and the Tayside Childrens Sleep Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months after completion of 84 days of light therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue using the Peds QL Multidimensional Fatigue Scale (Primary outcome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Comparing the five days before  light therapy to the last five days of the second cycle of maintenance treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Family quality of life using the Peds QL Family Impact Module</outcome>
      <timepoint>Comparing the five days before  light therapy to the last five days of the second cycle of maintenance treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life using the PedsQL - Cancer module and the Mood and Feelings Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months after completion of 84 days of light therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daytime sleepiness using the Modified Epworth Sleepiness Scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months after completion of 84 days of light therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue using the Peds QL Multidimensional Fatigue Scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months after completion of 84 days of light therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Family quality of life using the Peds QL Family Impact Module</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months after completion of 84 days of light therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental Stress using the Parenting Stress Index  short form </outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months after completion of 84 days of light therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children 3 to 9 years of age
Undergoing maintenance treatment for acute lymphoblastic leukaemia
White cell count less than 50,000 cells per microliter
Favourable cytogenetics, i.e. no extreme hypodiploidy with &lt; 44 chromosomes/cell; MLL gene rearrangement; Philadelphia chromosome positivity; Internal amplification of chromosome 21 
No cerebrospinal disease</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>9</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children who are blind
Have a history of diagnosed retinal problems
On photo-sensitive medication, such as azole anti-fungal medication (risk of photosensitivity
On medications which alter/induce sleep
On psychotropic medications
Non-English speaking and/or non-English speaking parents
Have pre-existing developmental disabilities
Have epilepsy or migraines
Wear tinted glasses
Are in foster care or with documented protective services involvement.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Our primary aim is to determine whether light therapy significantly improves the quality of life in children with ALL Based on the number of children meeting the study criteria in 2016 from both MMC and RCH, and an 86% participation rate in our pilot study, we expect to recruit 80 children over the three years of the project from both sites. As there are no previous studies of light therapy in children with cancer upon which to base a power calculation, we have based our power calculation on a study that investigated the change in quality of life in children with ALL when being administered dexamethasone compared to no dexamethasone (Pound CM, et al. Corticosteroids, behavior, and quality of life in children treated for acute lymphoblastic leukemia; a multicentered trial. J Pediatr Hematol Oncol 2012;34:517-23). A mean difference in the pain and hurt scale of the PedsQL_cancer module of -17.4, SD 26.9 between the on-dexamethasone and off-dexamethasone time-points was significant (p&lt;0.001). Using these data, our sample size of 40 children per group, will allow the detection of a significant difference between the light therapy and comparison groups with a power of 83% and alpha level of 0.05.
In this study, the effect of light therapy on sleep parameters (sleep pattern, total sleep time, sleep onset latency, wake after sleep onset), and scores from the Tayside Childrens Sleep Questionnaire, Epworth Sleepiness Scale, PedsQL-Cancer module, PedsQl-Fatigue module, Mood and Feelings Questionnaire, PedsQL-Family Impact module and the Parenting Stress Index will be analysed using linear mixed model analyses to allow for random effects over repeated observations. Group and time will be entered as fixed effects. Age and SES will be entered as covariates. Subject code will be used as the random factor. When there is a significant interaction between group and time in the mixed model analyses, post-hoc one-way-ANOVAs with Bonferroni adjustments will be used. Separate analysis at six month follow-up will compare sleep parameters and questionnaire scores between the groups using Students T-tests with Bonferroni correction to account for multiple tests.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/03/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lisa Walter</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Ritchie Centre, 
Hudson Institute of Medical Research
27-31 Wright St,
Clayton
Victoria 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Ritchie Centre, Hudson Institute of Medical Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>27-31 Wright St,
Clayton
Victoria 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Children's Cancer Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4,
4 Freshwater Place, 
Southbank 
VIC 3006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of bright light therapy for improving sleep and quality of life in children undergoing treatment for acute lymphoblastic leukaemia.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to participate in this study if you are aged 3 to 9 years of age, and undergoing maintenance treatment for acute lymphoblastic leukaemia.

Study details
All participants enrolled in this study will be randomly allocated (by chance) to receive either bright light therapy or standard leukaemia care with no bright light therapy. Participants allocated to the bright light therapy group will be asked to wear a bright light visor for 30 minutes immediately after waking up each morning for the 84 days of the second maintenance treatment cycle.

To assess sleep, fatigue, mood, and quality of life measures, researchers will use a combination of home-based assessment of sleep (actigraphy), a detailed sleep diary and questionnaires. The questionnaires will be completed by both the child and the parents at the beginning and the end of the light therapy, and six months after therapy, and will take approximately 30 minutes to complete at each time point.

It is hoped that bright light therapy will provide a cost-effective method of improving sleep and quality of life for children undergoing treatment for acute lymphoblastic leukaemia who are a group at risk of development of potentially long-term sleep problems, increased psychological distress, poor treatment resilience and low quality of life.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Services
Monash Health
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd
Clayton Victoria 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16047A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital, Research Ethics and Governance</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>50 Flemington Rd, 
Parkville 
VIC 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa Walter</name>
      <address>The Ritchie Centre
Hudson Institute of Medical Research
27-31 Wright St
Clayton
Victoria 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 385722834</phone>
      <fax>+61 395946811</fax>
      <email>lisa.walter@hudson.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa Walter</name>
      <address>The Ritchie Centre
Hudson Institute of Medical Research
27-31 Wright St
Clayton
Victoria 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 385722834</phone>
      <fax>+61 395946811</fax>
      <email>lisa.walter@hudson.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa Walter</name>
      <address>The Ritchie Centre
Hudson Institute of Medical Research
27-31 Wright St
Clayton
Victoria 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 385722834</phone>
      <fax>+61 395946811</fax>
      <email>lisa.walter@hudson.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa Walter</name>
      <address>The Ritchie Centre
Hudson Institute of Medical Research
27-31 Wright St
Clayton
Victoria 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 385722834</phone>
      <fax>+61 395946811</fax>
      <email>lisa.walter@hudson.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>