<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336410">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000047998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Endoform (Trademark)  Regenerative Template  Tumour Resection Case Studies (MESCS102)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Cosmetic Outcomes Following the Use of Endoform(Trademark) Regenerative Template in Single-Stage Split Thickness Grafting Procedures Following Tumor Resection</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>URA/10/11/080 - Upper South A Regional Ethics Committee
Ministry of Health, 4th Floor, 250 Oxford Terrace, Christchurch, New Zealand</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dermal regeneration following tumour resection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Non melanoma skin cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Study participants will recieve a full thickness tumor resection. Endoform (Trademark) Regenerative Template (Ovine forestomach matrix) will be applied to the tissue deficit and the split skin graft applied to the ovine forestomach matrix. The wound will be dressed according to standard care. Participants will receive one surgical procedure and will be subsequently examined at 1, 3, and 6 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the device for use as a substrate in a single-stage split skin graft procedure. Assessment will be conducted using a standardized clinical questionaire  utilising semi-structured questions and free text. Clinical examination will be conducted during the course of the study by those trained in the art. Photographic images will be collected through the course of the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 1, 3 and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate healing outcomes including pain, scarring and cosmesis. Assessment will be conducted using a standardized clinical questionaire  utilising semi-structured questions and free text. Clinical examination will be conducted during the course of the study by those trained in the art. Photographic images will be collected through the course of the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 1, 3 and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Define the procedural use of the device in single-stage SSG procedure. Assessment will be conducted using a standardized clinical questionaire  utilising semi-structured questions and free text. Clinical examination will be conducted during the course of the study by those trained in the art. Photographic images will be collected through the course of the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 1, 3 and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Document detailed written and pictorial case histories and make notes of particular clinical success.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 1, 3 and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	&gt;18 years old.
2.	At least one non-melanoma skin cancer without metastatic disease.
3.	Malignancies that require full-thickness excision.
4.	Post excision wounds that would normally be reconstructed with a split skin graft.
5.	Compliant.
6.	Competent.
7.	Tumour located on the scalp, neck or upper limbs.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Any cutaneous malignancies with metastatic disease.
2.	Diagnosed with malignant melanoma.
3.	Systemic malignancy.
4.	Under suspicion of metastatic disease.
5.	Pregnant or lactating.
6.	Clinically significant cardiac, pulmonary, renal, hepatic, neurologic and/or immune dysfunction that may affect wound healing.
7.	Known allergy to collagen or ovine (sheep) materials. Any previous reaction to a collagen product.
8.	Family or personal history of severe allergies (including asthma, hay fever and atopic dermatitis).
9.	Allergies to foods, especially meat products.
10.	Unable to remain in study for 6 months.
11.	Diabetes mellitus.
12.	Declined, unable or unwilling to make informed consent.
13.	Not fluent in English or Maori  requires interpreter.
14.	Religious or ethical objections to sheep-derived product.
15.	Previous radiotherapy at the defect site.
16.	Immunosuppressant medication (prednisone &gt;5mg /day or equivalent).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/01/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>5</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mesynthes Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>69 Gracefield Road, 
Lower Hutt, 5040
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mesynthes Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>69 Gracefield Road, 
Lower Hutt, 5040
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aims of the study are to find out whether the new type of medical device is acceptable to participants and plastic surgeons for use during the removal of cancerous skin tumours. The study aims to understand if the device leads to acceptable cosmetic outcomes (e.g. reduced scarring) following use.  The study product is called the Endoform Regenerative Template. The device is made mainly from collagen, a protein that also occurs naturally in the human body.  Studies have shown that collagen-based products can trigger cell movement into a wound and improve the speed and quality of wound healing. Collagen based products have been used extensively to help close the defect following the removal of skin tumours. The Endoform Regenerative Template is a new product which has not previously been used to repair surgical sites following removal of tumors. Endoform has however been used to treat a number of wounds including chronic venous and diabetic ulcers. The use of the Endoform Regenerative Template following tumour resection could potentially reduce the surgical time, time to wound healing and improve the quality of the healed wound.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Jeremy Simcock</name>
      <address>Department of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery
Christchurch Hospital
Riccarton Avenue
Private Bag 4710
Christchurch
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>64 3 364-6660</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jeremy.Simcock@cdhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Jeremy Simcock</name>
      <address>Department of Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery
Christchurch Hospital
Riccarton Avenue
Private Bag 4710
Christchurch
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>64 3 364-6660</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jeremy.Simcock@cdhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Barnaby C. H. May</name>
      <address>Mesynthes Limited
69 Gracefield Road, 
Lower Hutt, 5040
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>64 21 056 9995</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>barnaby.may@mesynthes.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>