<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82263">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/09/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/10/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000512426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of melanoma brain metastases</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  A randomised phase III trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>WBRTMel</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ANZMTG 01-07</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Melanoma brain metastases</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Whole brain radiotherapy - a minimum of 30 Gy in 10 fractions given as one fraction per day within 4 weeks of randomisation</interventions>
    <comparator>Observation of local and distant brain metastases by MRI, quality of life, ECOG performance status, neurocognitive function and survival until death or the end of the trial (12 months after the final patient is randomised). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with distant intracranial failure as determined by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to intracranial failure (local, distant and overall (local+ distant)) as determined by MRI</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post randomisation to intracranial failure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life as measured by EORTC QLQ-C30 and BN-20</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and every 2 months post randomisation until distant intracranial failure, death or the end of the trial (12 months after the final patient is randomised). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neurocognitive function as measured by Hopkins Verbal Learning Test, Controlled Oral Word Association Test, Trail Making Test Part A and B, Stroop - Colour and Word Test, Digit Span (Forwards and Backwards)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and every 2 months post randomisation until distant intracranial failure, death or the end of the trial (12 months after the final patient is randomised). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post randomisation to death</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance status as measured by ECOG</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and every 2 months post randomisation until death or the end of the trial (12 months after the final patient is randomised). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incremental cost-effectiveness ratio (ICER) reported in AUD per life year gained (LYG) and ICER per quality adjusted life year (QALY) gained.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post randomisation of the final patient</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. 1-3 intracranial metastases on MRI from melanoma, locally treated with either surgical excision and/or stereotactic irradiation. 2. Life expectancy of at least 6 months 3. Aged 18 years or older 4. WBRT must be within 8 weeks of completion of localised treatment and within 4 weeks of randomisation 5. Able to have an MRI brain scan with contrast. estimated Glomerular Filtrate Rate (eGFR) is adequate at the discretion of the radiologist and capable of having gadolinium-containing contrast medium for MRI as per practice guidelines 6. Complete localised treatment of all these metastases no more than 6 weeks prior to randomisation 7. An Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 2 or less at randomisation 8. CT scan of chest, abdomen and pelvis as a minimum prior to randomisation. Scans must be within 12 weeks of randomisation 9. Serum Lactate Dehydrogenase (LDH) must be = or &lt; 2 x upper limit of normal 10. Able to provide written informed consent </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Any untreated intracranial disease
2.	Any previous intracranial treatment (surgical excision and/or stereotactic irradiation treatment and/or WBRT) prior to this diagnosis of intracranial melanoma
3.	Evidence of leptomeningeal disease on pre-local treatment MRI scan
4.	Patients with prior cancers, except:
o	Those diagnosed more than five  years ago with no evidence of disease recurrence within this time;
o	Successfully treated basal cell and squamous cell skin carcinoma;
o	Carcinoma in-situ of the cervix
5.	A medical or psychiatric condition that compromises ability to give informed consent or complete the protocol
6.	Positive urine pregnancy test for women of childbearing potential within a week of registration onto the trial</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone using IVRS.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Minimisation will be used as the randomisation method for patients in this trial.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/04/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>220</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2022</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC,QLD,SA,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Institute - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Calvary Mater Newcastle - Waratah</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>The Townsville Hospital - Douglas</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Adult Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Genesis Cancer Care - Gateshead</hospital>
    <hospital>Genesis Cancer Care - Tugun - Tugun</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Darwin Hospital - Tiwi</hospital>
    <postcode>2050</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode>2310 - Hunter Region</postcode>
    <postcode>2751 - Penrith</postcode>
    <postcode>8006 - Abeckett Street</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Royal Brisbane Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <postcode>4814 - Douglas</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>2290 - Gateshead</postcode>
    <postcode>4224 - Tugun</postcode>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
    <postcode>0810 - Tiwi</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state>Oslo, Trondheim</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Oxford, Wirral, Norwich, Surrey, Leeds, Middlesex, Birmingham, Cardiff </state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australia and New Zealand Melanoma Trials Group (ANZMTG), University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Poche Centre, 40 Rocklands Road, North Sydney NSW 2060</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO BOX 1201
Dickson ACT 2602</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>SNOG (Sydney Neuro-Oncology Group)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Royal North Shore Hospital
St. Leonards
NSW</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Radiation Oncology Newcastle Mater Hospital Locked Bag 7, Hunter Region Mail Centre NSW 2310 </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Oncology Clinical Trials Office (OCTO), University of Oxford</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Clinical Oncology
University of Oxford
Old Road Campus Research Building
Roosevelt Drive
Headington
Oxford OX3 7DQ
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United Kingdom</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>People with brain metastases from melanoma are offered different treatment options after local treatment of their brain metastases via surgery or stereotactic irradiation. Depending on the treating institution and the clinician involved a patient may or may not be offered whole brain radiotherapy (WBRT) after their brain metastases are excised or treated with stereotactic irradiation. This trial seeks to determine if WBRT reduces the spread of brain metastases and lengthens the time to recurrence. The trial also examines the effect of WBRT on quality of life and brain functions such as memory, speech and concentration. Participants will be randomised after local treatment of their brain metastases to either WBRT or observation. 200 people will be recruited from sites in Australia, Norway, the UK, the US and other international sites.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://anzmtg.org/trialdetails.aspx?trialno=5</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Publications

2017
Clarke K, Fogarty GB, Lo S, Izard M, Hong A (2017) Optic Nerve Movement May Need to be Considered When Treating with Stereotactic Radiosurgery. J Nucl Med Radiat Ther 8: 321. doi:10.4172/2155-9619.1000321

Martin Tio, Xuan Wang, Matteo S Carlino, Brindha Shivalingam, Gerald B Fogarty, Alex Guminski, Serigne Lo, Angela Hong, Alexander M Menzies, Georgina V Long. Survival and prognostic factors of metastatic melanoma patients with brain metastases. Submitted

Luiz Paulo Barros de Moraes, Ivan Burchett,  Stephanie Nicholls, Elizabeth Paton, Emily Forward,  Gerald B. Fogarty. Large solitary distant metastasis of cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma to skin graft site with complete response following definitive radiotherapy. 
Accepted IJB  March 2017

Carney GR, McLaren KR, Moutrie Z, Fogarty GB (2017) Adaptive Split Course Radiotherapy for Skin Cancers Decreases Toxicity and Improves Compliance. Int J Radiol Radiat Ther 2(1): 00015. DOI: 10.15406/ijrrt.2017.02.00015

C Chen. Cumulative Intracranial Tumor Volume (CITV) augments the prognostic value of the disease-specific Graded Prognostic Assessment (dsGPA) model for melanoma
cerebral metastases. Neurosurgery. Submitted 

Ee Siang Choong, Serigne Lo, Martin Drummond, Gerald Fogarty, Alexander M. Menzies, Alexander Guminski, Brindha Shivalingam, Kathryn Clarke, Georgina V. Lon, Angela M Hong. Survival of patients with melanoma brain metastasis treated with SRS and active systemic drug therapies. European Journal Of Cancer Ms. Ref. No.:  EJC-D-16-01642R1 in press

Alexander HR Varey,  Angela M Hong, Graham J. Mann, Gerald Fogarty,  Jonathan R. Stretch, Robyn P. Saw, Andrew J. Spillane, Kerwin Shannon, Kenneth Lee,  John F. Thompson, Richard A. Scolyer  "Neurotropic melanoma: clinical behavior and radiotherapy responsiveness in a series of 671 patients treated at a single center" submitted by John F Thompson.

Clarke K, Fogarty GB, Lo S, Izard M, Hong A (2017) Optic Nerve Movement May Need to be Considered When Treating with Stereotactic Radiosurgery. J Nucl Med Radiat Ther 8: 321. doi:10.4172/2155-9619.1000321

2016

Fogarty, GB, Hong A, Gondi V, Burmeister B, Jacobsen KD, Lo S, Paton E, Shivalingam B, Thompson JF. Debate: Adjuvant whole brain radiotherapy or not? More data is the wiser choice. BMC Cancer July 2016. 

Radiotherapy treats a greater volume than surgery using an axillary sentinel node model:  a short report. Timothy Wong, April Wong, Raef Awad, Lauren Haydu, Nicole Dougheney, Gerald Fogarty Int. J. Bioautomation Vol. 20(4)/2016

Hippocampal avoidance whole brain radiation therapy is associated with preservation of hippocampal volume at six months Angela Hong; Harry Hallock; Michael Valenzuela; Serigne Lo; Elizabeth Paton; Diana Ng; Haryana Dhillon; Kari Jacobsen; Claudius Reisse; Gerald Fogarty BMC Cancer.  Submitted 07/16

Liniker E, Menzies AM, Kong BY, Cooper A, Ramanujam S, Lo S, Kefford RF,
Fogarty GB, Guminski A, Wang TW, Carlino MS, Hong A, Long GV. Activity and safety of radiotherapy with anti-PD-1 drug therapy in patients with metastatic melanoma. Oncoimmunology. 2016 Aug 19;5(9):e1214788. PubMed PMID: 27757312.


Pulvirenti T, Hong A, Clements A, Forstner D, Suchowersky A, Guminski A, McNeil C, Hersey P, Fogarty G, Kefford R, Long GV, Wang W. Acute Radiation Skin Toxicity Associated With BRAF Inhibitors. J Clin Oncol 2016;34:e17-20

2015

Fogarty GB, Hong,  A, Thompson JF. Should patient with melanoma brain metastasaes receive adjuvant whole brain radiotherapy? The Lancet Oncology 2015 05:1470-2045

Keen, CE. WBRT benefits for melanoma patients with brain metastases: Status of a clinical trial. Applied Radiation Oncology May 18 2015

Fogarty GB, Hong A, Dolven-Jacobsen K, Reisse C, Burmeister B, Haydu L, Dhillon H, Steel V, Shivalingam B, Drummond K, Vardy J, Nowak A, Hruby G, Scolyer R, Mandel C, Thompson JF. First interim analysis of a randomised trial of whole brain radiotherapy in melanoma brain metastases confirms high data quality. BMC Research Notes 2015 8:192

Fogarty GB, Hong A, Paton E, Li P. In Regard to Sahgul et al. International Journal of Radiation Oncology, Biology, Physics 2015 Sep 1;93(1):219-20

Fogarty GB, Hong A Book Chapter: Ch11. Brain Metastases in Melanoma Patients: Treatment with Adjuvant Postoperative Whole-Brain Radiotherapy. In: Part IV Brain Metastases in Melanoma; In: Brain Metastases from Primary Tumours, Ed: MA Hayat, Volume 2, Pgs 123-30, ISBN: 978-0-12-801419-6; posted 30-12-2014. Elsevier Publishers.

Du Four S, Hong A, Chan M, Charakidis M, Duerinck J, Wilgenhof S, Wang W, Feng L, Michotte A, Okera M, Shivalingam B, Fogarty G, Kefford R and Neyns B. Symptomatic Histologically Proven Necrosis of Brain following Stereotactic Radiation and Ipilimumab in Six Lesions in Four Melanoma Patients, Case Reports in Oncological Medicine 2014 (In press)

Gerald B Fogarty, Angela Hong, Kari D Jacobsen, Claudius H Reisse, Brindha Shivalingam, Bryan Burmeister, Lauren E Haydu, et al. Accrual to a randomised trial of adjuvant whole brain radiotherapy for treatment of melanoma brain metastases is feasible, BMC Research Notes 2014, 7:412

Hong A, Chao Suo, Valenzuela M, Haydu L, Jacobsen K, Reisse C, Fogarty G, Low incidence of melanoma brain metastasis in the hippocampus, Radiotherapy and Oncology, 111 (2014) 59-62

Fogarty G, Hong A , Radiation Therapy for Advanced and Metastatic Melanoma, Journal of Surgical Oncology, e-pub ahead of print, 2013

Fogarty G; Guminski A, Shannon K, How important is multidisciplinary treatment of melanoma metastases? Expert Review of Dermatology 8.4 (Aug 2013): 339-341

Awad R, Fogarty G, Hong A, Kelly P, Ng D, Santos D and Haydu L. Hippocampal avoidance with volumetric modulated arc therapy in melanoma brain metastases - the first Australian experience; Radiation Oncology 2013; 8(1):62. http://www.ro-journal.com/content/pdf/1748-717X-8-62.pdf

G. Fogarty, E Paton. The emerging roles of radiotherapy for Melanoma; St Vincents Hospital Proceedings Volume 20 1 Dec 2012.

Thompson JF, Hong A, Fogarty G. Publication and Interpretation of Clinical Trial Results: The Need for Caution; Annals of Surgical Oncology 2012; 19(6):1745-7.

Carlino MS, Fogarty GB, Long GV. Treatment of melanoma brain metastases: a new paradigm, Cancer Journal, 2012, Mar-Apr;18(2):208-12

Hong A, Fogarty G, Izard M. The role of radiation therapy in the management of metastatic melanoma in the brain; International Journal of Surgical Oncology 2012.

Fogarty G, Ng D, Liu G, Haydu L, Bhandari N. Volumetric modulated arc therapy is superior to conventional intensity modulated radiotherapy - a comparison among prostate cancer patients treated in an Australian centre, BMC Radiation Oncology 2011; 6:108.

Oral and Poster Presentations

GB Fogarty, Hong A, Burmeister B, Foote M, Guitera P, Wang T. Five high quality Australian trials are helping define the role of radiotherapy in Melanoma. Australasian Melanoma Conference 2016, Friday 28 October 2016 - Saturday 29 October 2016. Sofitel Wentworth, Sydney. (Oral)

GB Fogarty, Hong A, Burmeister B, Foote M, Guitera P, Wang T. Five high quality Australian trials are helping define the role of radiotherapy in Melanoma. Sydney Cancer Conference 2016 23rd September 2016. (Oral)

GB Fogarty, Hong A, Burmeister B, Foote M, Guitera P, Wang T. Five high quality Australian trials are helping define the role of radiotherapy in Melanoma. Australasian Melanoma Conference 2016, Friday 28 October 2016 - Saturday 29 October 2016. Sofitel Wentworth, Sydney. (Oral)

Fogarty GB, Hong A, Foote M, Guitera P, Wang T, Paton E, Burmeister B. Ongoing High-Quality Randomised Trials Will Determine Whether Radiotherapy is an Effective Treatment Modality in Melanoma. HemOnc Today Melanoma and Cutaneous Malignancies 2016, 18th  19th March 2016, New York USA (Poster presentation)

Nobes, J. (2016, January). Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma. Update on Cerebral Metastases, East Of England Cancer Research Network  CNS Meeting, 26th January 2016, London UK (Oral presentation)

Hong, A. (2015, October). Randomised Trials to Define the Role of Radiation Therapy in Melanoma. Presented at Veneto Institute of Oncology meets Melanoma Institute Australia, Padua, Italy.

GB Fogarty A Hong, M Foote, KD Jacobsen, C Riesse, P Guitera, T Wang, MR Middleton, E Paton, B Burmeister Ongoing high quality randomised trials are helping define the role of Radiotherapy in melanoma COSA ASM 2015, 17th November 2015, Hobart TAS (Oral presentation)

GB Fogarty, A Hong, KD Jacobsen, C Reisse, B Shivalingam, MR Middleton, E Paton, H Wijaya, B Burmeister;  An update on the ANZMTG 01.07 WBRTMel trial  The role of Adjuvant whole brain radiotherapy for patients with melanoma brain metastases; COSA Annual Scientific Meeting 2015, 17th November 2015, Hobart TAS (Poster presentation)

A Hong Change in the hippocampal volume after whole brain radiation therapy with or without hippocampal avoidance technique American Society for Radiation Oncology (ASTRO) Annual Meeting, 18th  21st October 2015, San Antonio, USA (Poster presentation)

A Hong Change in the hippocampal volume after whole brain radiation therapy with or without hippocampal avoidance technique 11th EADO Congress and 8th World Meeting of Interdisciplinary Melanoma/Skin Cancer Center, 28th  31st October 2015, Marseille, France (Poster presentation)

A Hong, KD Jacobsen, C Reisse, B Shivalingam, MR Middleton, E Paton, H Wijaya, B Burmeister; An update on the ANZMTG 01.07 WBRTMel trial  The role of Adjuvant whole brain radiotherapy for patients with melanoma brain metastases; Nordic Melanoma Meeting 2015, Gothenburg Sweden Friday 4th September 2015 (Oral presentation)

GB Fogarty, A Hong, M Foote, KD Jacobsen, C Riesse, P Guitera, T Wang, MR Middleton, E Paton, B Burmeister; Ongoing high quality randomised trials are helping define the role of Radiotherapy in melanoma; Nordic Melanoma Meeting 2015, Gothenburg Sweden Friday 4th September 2015 (Oral presentation)

G B Fogarty ANZMTG 01.07- An update on the WBRTMel trial; Adjuvant whole brain radiotherapy  wisdom requires more data, and less dogma Inaugural Melanoma &amp; Skin Cancer Special Interest Group (MELSIG) Mini-Symposium, 16th July 2015, Sydney, Australia (Oral presentation)

G B Fogarty, 08.05 (WBRT): Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial. TROG 27th Annual Scientific Meeting, Newcastle, Australia, 24th  26th March 2015 (Oral presentation)

K Drummond, G B Fogarty, A Hong, K Dolven-Jacobsen, C H Reisse, B Burmesiter, E Paton, V Steel, L Haydu, H Dhillon, B Shivalingam, J Vardy, A Nowak, G Hruby, R Scolyer, C Mandel, J F Thompson. ANZMTG 01.07 WBRTMel: Randomised Trial of Whole Brain Radiotherapy in Melanoma Brain Metastases  First Interim Analysis, Co-operative Trails Group for Neurooncology Annual Scientific Meeting (COGNO  ASM), Melbourne, Australia, 24th  25th October 2014 (Poster presentation) 

G B Fogarty. ANZMTG 01.07 TROG 08.05  Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma. Update on the WBRTMel trial, 2nd National Melanoma Conference 2014, Perth, Australia, 11th October 2014 (Oral presentation) 

G B Fogarty. ANZMTG 01.07 TROG 08.05  Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma. Update on the WBRTMel trial, Australia and New Zealand Melanoma Trials Group (ANZMTG) Annual Scientific Meeting (ASM), Perth, Australia, 9th October 2014 (Oral presentation) 

K Drummond, G B Fogarty, A Hong, K Dolven-Jacobsen, C H Reisse, B Burmesiter, E Paton, V Steel, L Haydu, H Dhillon, B Shivalingam, J Vardy, A Nowak, G Hruby, R Scolyer, C Mandel, J F Thompson. ANZMTG 01.07 WBRTMel: Randomised Trial of Whole Brain Radiotherapy in Melanoma Brain Metastases  First Interim Analysis, Neurosurgical Society Australia Annual Scientific Meeting (NSA ASM), 2nd-4th October, Perth, Australia, (Oral presentation)

G B Fogarty, A Hong, K Dolven-Jacobsen, C H Reisse, B Burmeister, V Steel, L Haydu, H Dhillon, B Shivalingham, K Drummond, J Vardy, A Nowak, G Hruby, R Scolyer, C Mandel, J F Thompson. ANZMTG 01.07 WBRTMel: Randomised Trial of Whole Brain Radiotherapy in Melanoma Brain Metastases  First Interim Analysis, American Society for Radiation Oncology (ASTRO), San Francisco, USA, 14th-17th September 2014, (Poster presentation)

K Dolven-Jacobsen, G B Fogarty, A Hong, C H Reisse, E Paton, V Steel, V Neve, B Burmeister, J F Thompson. ANZMTG 01.07 WBRTMel: Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of Melanoma Brain Metastases, Nordic Melanoma Group, Turku, Finland, 4th-5th September 2014, (Oral presentation)

G Fogarty, Accrual to a randomised trial of whole brain radiotherapy in melanoma brain metastases is feasible, Global Controversies in Skin Cancer, Brisbane, Australia, 21st-24th November, 2013, (Oral presentation)

R Morton, Methods for the economic evaluation of whole brain radiotherapy alongside a randomised controlled trial, Global Controversies in Skin Cancer, Brisbane, Australia, 21st-24th November, 2013, (Poster presentation)

G Fogarty, Accrual to a randomised trial of whole brain radiotherapy in melanoma brain metastases is feasible, Clinical Oncological Society of Australia, Adelaide, Australia, 13th November, 2013, (Poster presentation)

A Hong, Distance of melanoma metastasis to the hippocampus: estimated safety of hippocampal sparing whole brain radiation therapy, Cooperative Trials Group for Neuro Oncology (COGNO) ASM, Sydney, Australia, 25-26th October, 2013, (Oral presentation)

C Mandel, Intracranial melanoma metastases: imaging appearances and current management e-poster and oral presentation, The Royal College of Australian Radiologists AGM, Auckland New Zealand, 17th-20th October 2013, (Poster presentation)

G Fogarty, Update on whole radiotherapy and clinical trials, Melanoma Institute Australia Research Retreat, Sydney, Australia, 23rd August 2013, (Oral presentation)

G Fogarty, Accrual to a randomised trial of whole brain radiotherapy in melanoma brain metastases is feasible, World Congress on Melanoma, Hamburg, Germany, 17-21st July 2013, (Oral presentation)

G Fogarty, Accrual to a randomised trial of whole brain radiotherapy in melanoma brain metastases is feasible, World Congress on Melanoma, Hamburg, Germany, 17-21st July 2013, (Poster presentation)


R Morton, Methods for the economic evaluation of whole brain radiotherapy alongside a randomised controlled trial, World Congress on Melanoma, Hamburg, Germany, 17-21st July 2013, (Poster presentation)

Society of British Neurological Surgeons May 24th 2013, Sheffield, UK, Prof Mark Middleton, ANZMTG 01/07 TROG 08/05 - Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma - A randomised phase III trial (Oral presentation)

C Mandel, CNS melanoma metastases  update on imaging and management, Australian and New Zealand Society of Neuroradiology Annual Scientific Meeting (ANZSNR ASM), 22-24 March 2013, Hobart, Australia (Oral presentation)

B Burmeister. Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial (ANZMTG 01/07; TROG 08/05), Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group Annual Scientific Meeting (TROG ASM), February 2013, Wellington, New Zealand (Oral presentation)

G Fogarty. Five current ANZMTG trials will help define the role of Radiotherapy in Melanoma, 6th World Meeting of Interdisciplinary Melanoma Skin Cancer Centres &amp; 8th EADO Congress, November 2012, Barcelona, Spain (Oral presentation)  Awarded Best Oral Presentation

V Steel, E Paton, E Lin, A Lucas, G Fogarty. Its all about the numbers!  Strategies to Increase Melanoma Trial Participation, Clinical Oncological Society of Australia (COSA) Annual Scientific Meeting, November 2012, Brisbane, Australia (Poster presentation)

V Steel, E Paton, E Lin, A Lucas, G Fogarty. Its all about the numbers!  Strategies to Increase Melanoma Trial Participation, Scott Kirkbride Melanoma Research Centre (SKMRC) Melanoma Conference, October 2012, Perth, Australia (Poster presentation)

G Fogarty. Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial (ANZMTG 01/07; TROG 08/05), Scott Kirkbride Melanoma Research Centre (SKMRC) Melanoma Conference, October 2012, Perth, Australia (Oral presentation)

K Drummond. Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial (ANZMTG 01/07; TROG 08/05), Victorian Cooperative Oncology Group (VCOG), October 2012, Melbourne, Australia (Oral presentation)

J Nobes. Radiotherapy and Melanoma, UK Melanoma Study Group, October 2012, London, UK (Oral presentation)

G Fogarty. Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial (ANZMTG 01/07; TROG 08/05), The Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Radiologists, Faculty of Radiation Oncology Annual Scientific Meeting (RANZCR FRO ASM), July 2012, Cairns, Australia (Oral presentation)

E Paton. Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial (ANZMTG 01/07; TROG 08/05), Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group Annual Scientific Meeting (TROG ASM), May 2012, Darwin, Australia (Oral presentation)

R Morton, Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial, Oxford University Oncology Clinical Trials Group (OCTO), January 2012, Oxford, UK (Oral presentation)

G Fogarty and E Paton; Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial (ANZMTG 01/07; TROG 08/05),
ANZMTG WBRT Investigator Meeting and Trial Update, November 2011, Tampa, USA (Oral presentation)

G Fogarty; E Paton; A. Hong; B. Shivalingam; K. Dolven Jacobsen; B. Burmeister; J. Thompson. Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial (ANZMTG 01/07; TROG 08/05), Society of Melanoma Research, November 2011, Florida USA (Poster presentation)

M.Gonzalez, M.Cronin, A.Hong, G.Fogarty, A.Grierson, H.Dhillon, J.F.Thompson, J.Vardy, Quality assurance of data collection of neurocognitive function testing in a pilot whole brain radiotherapy clinical trial for metastatic melanoma, Society of Melanoma Research, November 2011, Florida USA (Poster presentation)

V Jakrot, E Paton, G Fogarty, B Shivalingam, A Hong, R Scolyer, G Mann, J Thompson. Melanoma Brain Metastases Trials and Bio-specimen Banking; Society of Melanoma Research, November 2011, Florida USA (Poster presentation)

E Paton, G Fogarty, A Hong, C Mandel, H Fuentes, H Dhillon, G Hruby, R Scolyer, A Nowak, J Thompson. ANZMTG 01.07 WBRT Mel Trial  2011 Quality Assurance; COSA ASM 2011, Perth, November 2011 (Poster presentation)

G Fogarty, E Paton, A Hong, B Shivalingam, K Dolven Jacobsen, B Burmeister, J Thompson. Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial (ANZMTG 01/07; TROG 08/05); COSA ASM 2011, Perth, November 2011 (Poster presentation)  
 
M.Gonzalez, M.Cronin, A.Hong, G.Fogarty, A.Grierson, H.Dhillon, J.F.Thompson, J.Vardy, Quality assurance of data collection of neurocognitive function testing in a pilot whole brain radiotherapy clinical trial for metastatic melanoma, COSA ASM 2011, Perth, November 2011 (Poster presentation)

V Jakrot, E Paton, G Fogarty, B Shivalingam, A Hong, R Scolyer, G Mann, J Thompson. Melanoma Brain Metastases Trials and Bio-specimen Banking; 9th Annual Australasian Biospecimen Network Association Meeting, Perth, November 2011 (Poster presentation)

Fogarty G. et al. Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Radiologists (RANZCR) Annual Scientific Meeting, October 2011, Melbourne, VIC (Oral presentation)

Fogarty G. et al. Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial Medical Oncology Group of Australia (MOGA) Annual Scientific Meeting, August 2011, Adelaide, SA (Oral and poster presentation) 

Dolven Jacobsen, K. et al. Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial; European Post-ASCO Meeting, July 2011, Munich, Germany (Oral presentation)

Middleton M. et al. Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial. UK Melanoma Study Group Summer Meeting, June 2011, Manchester, UK (Oral presentation)

Byrne M et al. Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial. Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG) Annual Scientific Meeting, April 2011, Adelaide, Australia. (Oral presentation)

Nowak A et al. Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial. WA Neurosurgical Grand Round meeting, Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital, March 2011, Perth, Australia (Oral presentation)

Fogarty G et al. Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial. Sydney Neuro-oncology Group (SNOG) Executive Meeting, RNSH, February 2011, Sydney, Australia (Oral presentation) 

Fogarty G et al. Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial. Meeting of Interdisciplinary Melanoma / Skin Cancer Centres, November 2010, Sydney, Australia (Oral presentation)

Fogarty G et al. Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial. ANZMTG WBRT Investigator Meeting and Trial Update, November 2010, Sydney, Australia (Oral presentation)

Fogarty G. Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial. Clinical Oncological Society of Australia Annual Scientific Meeting, November 2010, Melbourne, Australia (Poster presentation)

Fogarty G et al. Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial. Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG) Trials Review Meeting, October 2010, Melbourne, Australia. (Oral presentation)

Fogarty G et al. Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial. The Royal Australian and New Zealand College Radiologists (RANZCR) ASM, October 2010, Perth, Australia. (Oral presentation)
 
Fogarty G et al. Whole Brain Radiotherapy following local treatment of intracranial metastases of melanoma  a randomised phase III trial. UK Melanoma Study Group Summer Meeting, June 2010, University of Leeds, UK. (Oral presentation)

Byrne M. ANZMTG 01/07 Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial  Trial Update. Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG) Annual Scientific Meeting, March 2010, Queenstown, NZ. (Oral presentation)   

Fogarty G.  ANZMTG 01/07 Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial Overview.  Fresenius Kabi - FORCE meeting, January 2010, Mactan Shangri-La Cebu, Philippines. (Oral presentation)

ANZMTG 01/07 Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial. 3rd annual International Melanoma Centres Meeting, November 2009, Berlin Germany. (Poster presentation)

ANZMTG 01/07 Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial. Clinical Oncological Society of Australia Annual Scientific Meeting, November 2009, Gold Coast, Australia (Poster presentation)

Shivalingam B. ANZMTG 01/07 Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial, Annual Scientific Meeting for the Asia Pacific College of Neurosurgeons, September 2009, Alice Springs, NT (Oral presentation)

Fogarty G. ANZMTG 01/07 Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial, 7th World Congress on Melanoma &amp; 5th Congress of the European Association of Dermato-Oncology (EADO)  Conference, May 2009, Vienna, Austria (Oral presentation)

Paton E. ANZMTG 01/07 Whole Brain Radiotherapy Following Local Treatment of 1-3 Intracranial Metastases of Melanoma  A Phase III Trial  Trial Update, Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG) Annual Scientific Meeting, March 2009, Shoal Bay, Australia (Oral presentation)



</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cancer Institute NSW Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 9, 8 Central Avenue, Australian Technology Park, Eveleigh, NSW 2015</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/12/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Research Ethics and Governance Office (REGO)
 Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
 Missenden Road
 CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X13-0329 HREC/13/RPAH/465</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/12/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gerald Fogarty </name>
      <address>Department of Radiation Oncology, Mater Hospital, Crows Nest NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9458 8000 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9458 8088</fax>
      <email>Gerald.Fogarty@cancer.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Paton</name>
      <address>The Australia and New Zealand Melanoma Trials Group (ANZMTG), The Poche Centre, 40 Rocklands Rd, North Sydney NSW 2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9911 7354</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9954 9435</fax>
      <email>wbrt@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Narelle Williams</name>
      <address>The Australia and New Zealand Melanoma Trials Group (ANZMTG), The Poche Centre, 40 Rocklands Rd, North Sydney NSW 2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9911 7322</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9954 9435</fax>
      <email>wbrt@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gerald Fogarty</name>
      <address>Department of Radiation Oncology, Mater Hospital, Crows Nest NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9458 8000 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Gerald.Fogarty@cancer.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>