<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364238">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000737730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An open label, single centre, phase II pilot study of neoadjuvant dabrafenib + trametinib in patients with resectable AJCC Stage IIIB-C BRAF V600 mutation positive melanoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open label, single centre, phase II pilot study to determine the pathological response rate to 12 weeks of neoadjuvant dabrafenib + trametinib in patients with resectable AJCC Stage IIIB-C BRAF V600 mutation positive melanoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1143-0183 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Protocol Number 200332</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Melanoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Dabrafenib tablet 150 mg orally twice daily and trametinib tablet 2 mg orally once daily as neoadjuvant treatment for 3 months followed immediately by complete lymph node dissection surgery. Three days following surgery, patients will recommence dabrafenib 150 mg twice daily and trametinib 2 mg once daily for a further 9 months. Compliance will be monitored by asking patients to keep a dosing diary and at the end of each cycle, the patient will return to clinic with the diary and drug containers and study coordinators will check compliance.</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The percentage of patients with a partial pathological response (a reduction in the proportion of viable melanoma tissue) or complete pathological response (no viable melanoma tissue) at 12 weeks post neoadjuvant treatment. The pathological response is assessed by the % of viable melanoma cells after 12 weeks of neoadjuvant treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks after commencement of neoadjuvant study treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effects of neoadjuvant study treatment on surgical outcomes: episodes of infection requiring antibiotics, time from surgery to removal of drain, episodes of seroma formation requiring drainage and episodes of bleeding requiring return to theatre and/or transfusion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks after commencement of neoadjuvant study treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>&gt;18 years of age
Written informed consent
Histologically confirmed AJCC Stage IIIB or IIIC cutaneous melanoma or unknown primary and V600 mutation positive with sufficient nodal disease to enable 4 biopsies (core, excisional or incisional).
Able to swallow and retain oral medication
Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of 0-1
Adequate organ function
Women of childbearing potential: negative serum pregnancy test and effective contraception from 14 days prior to study treatment until 4 months after the last dose
Men with female partner of childbearing potential to use effective contraception from 14 days prior to study treatment until 4 months after the last dose
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Mucosal or ocular melanoma or any in-transit metastases
Distant metastatic disease on screening
Prior systemic anti-cancer treatment (except surgery)
Any investigational drug within 28 days or 5 half-lives
Current or expected use of a prohibited medication
Known immediate or delayed hypersensitivity reaction or idiosyncrasy to drugs chemically related to the study treatments
Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV)
Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency
Another malignancy or concurrent malignancy unless disease-free for 3 years and with a life expectancy of &gt; 5 years
Cardiovascular risk including: QTc =480 msec, uncontrolled arrhythmias, acute coronary syndromes, coronary angioplasty or stenting within 6 months, NYHA = Grade 2 heart failure, intra-cardiac defibrillator or permanent pacemaker, abnormal cardiac valve morphology (= Grade 2), treatment refractory hypertension systolic&gt; 140 mm Hg and/or diastolic &gt; 90 mm Hg
Evidence/risk of retinal vein occlusion or central serous retinopathy
Serious or unstable pre-existing medical conditions or other conditions that could interfere with the subjects safety, consent, or compliance
Pregnant or breastfeeding females</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The overall response rate will be calculated as the number of patients with a complete or partial RECIST 1.1 response divided by the total number of patients. Pathological response will be calculated as the proportion of patients with either a complete pathological response (no viable melanoma tissue) or a reduction in the proportion of viable melanoma tissue at lymph node dissection compared with baseline. Complete and partial pathological responses will also be reported separately. Exact confidence limits calculated with the Clopper-Pearson method will be reported together with the overall response and pathological response rates.

Sample size is based on a complete pathological response rate of &lt;10% for unsuccessful treatment or &gt;30% for successful treatment.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>20/04/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>35</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>35</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>20/04/2022</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Poche Centre, Melanoma Institute Australia - North Sydney</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Melanoma Institute Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>40 Rocklands Rd, Wollstonecraft NSW 2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>GlaxoSmithKline Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4, 436 Johnston Street Abbotsford  Victoria 3067</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is evaluating the effect of the drugs dabrafenib and trametinib given prior to surgery and after for the treatment of melanoma.
Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above and have been diagnosed with AJCC (American Joint Committee on Cancer) Stage IIIB or IIIC BRAF V600 mutation positive melanoma.
Trial details: All participants in this study will take dabrafenib 150 mg tablets twice daily and trametinib 2 mg tablets once daily for 3 months. They will then undergo complete lymph node dissection surgery, followed by treatment with twice daily dabrafenib 150 mg and once daily trametinib 2 mg for a further 9 months. Participants will be assessed at 12 weeks post treatment in order to evaluate treatment response and surgical outcomes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress>Translational Research Centre, 97-105 Boundary Street, Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/07/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Georgina Long</name>
      <address>Melanoma Institute Australia
40 Rocklands Road, Wollstonecraft NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9911 7363</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Georgina.Long@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Maria Gonzalez</name>
      <address>Melanoma Institute Australia
40 Rocklands Road, Wollstonecraft NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9911 7200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Maria.Gonzalez@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Maria Gonzalez</name>
      <address>Melanoma Institute Australia
40 Rocklands Road, Wollstonecraft NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9911 7200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Maria Gonzalez@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Maria Gonzalez</name>
      <address>Melanoma Institute Australia
40 Rocklands Road, Wollstonecraft NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9911 7200</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Maria Gonzalez@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>