<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363222">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001170819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Observational study of frequency and causes of impaired liver metabolism of cyclophosphamide in breast cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Observational study of frequency and causes of impaired liver metabolism of cyclophosphamide in breast cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The LIME Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participant patients will be dispensed with a 200 mg dose of the probe drug, proguanil on two separate occasions. The patients will be requested to take two tablets containing 100 mg each, by mouth three hours before the commencement of chemotherapy. The patients will also be requested to take two tablets containing 100 mg each, by mouth three hours prior to the commencement of the 3rd cycle of chemotherapy.
The duration between the 1st and 3rd cycles of chemotherapy will be dependent on the patients own chemotherapy schedules.</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no comparator or control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To elucidate whether compromised CYP2C19 activity occurs in women with breast cancer at 3 hours post administration of proguanil. CYP2C19 functional activity will be measured by plasma samples at 3 hours post administration of proguanil  and at 3 hours and 15 minutes post administration of proguanil.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 hours post administration of proguanil and at 3 hours and 15 minutes post administration of proguanil. The plasma samples will be taken prior to the patients routine 1st and 3rd cycle of chemotherapy.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To elucidate whether compromised CYP2C19 activity results in decreased activation of cyclophosphamide in women with breast cancer. CYP2C19 functional activity will be measured by plasma samples at 15 minutes and 30 minutes following the completion of the 1st cycle of the cyclophosphamide infusion and the 3rd cycle of the cyclophosphamide infusion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 15 minutes and 30 minutes following the completion of the 1st cycle of the cyclophosphamide infusion. At 15 minutes and 30 minutes following the completion the 3rd cycle of the cyclophosphamide infusion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To elucidate whether there is a relationship between compromised CYP2C19 and pro-inflammatory mediators, such as cytokines in women with breast cancer as measured by plasma samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 30 minutes following the completion of the 1st cycle of the cyclophosphamide infusion. At 30 minutes following the completion the 3rd cycle of the cyclophosphamide infusion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To elucidate whether a combination of genetic (i.e. CYP2C19/CYP2B6) and additional non-genetic factors, such as markers of inflammation, influence the metabolism of cyclophosphamide in women with breast cancer as measured from plasma samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All patients will have blood collected at baseline for determination of CYP2C19 genotype.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age&gt;18
ECOG (Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group) Performance Status 0-2
Histologically confirmed breast cancer
To receive intravenous cyclophosphamide as part of adjuvant, neoadjuvant or first line chemotherapy for breast cancer as part of standard care.
Staging investigations in process (should not be greater than 2 weeks after start of chemotherapy).
Patients must be able to provide written informed consent
Aspartate transaminase (AST), Alaninine transaminase (ALT) =&lt; 2.5 X upper limit of normal (ULN) for institution
Alkaline phosphatase &lt;5x ULN
Bilirubin =&lt; ULN, except when due to Gilberts Disease
Creatinine &lt;1.5 ULN</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>19</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients receiving medication which is either a CYP2C19 inhibitor or inducer, and where a washout period of 5 days is not clinically feasible
Chronic inflammatory condition such as systemic lupus erythematosis, inflammatory bowel disease, other autoimmune phenomenon or active chronic infection
Active infections (e.g. wound) at time of chemotherapy
Pregnant or breast feeding
Other active malignancy within the last 5 years, excluding non-melanoma skin cancers, or preinvasive cervical cancer that has been treated definitively</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences,
University of Auckland, 
85 Park Road
Grafton
Auckland 1023</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Genesis Oncology Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Genesis Oncology Trust 
PO Box 17188 
Greenlane 
Auckland 1546</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Society of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Cancer Society of New Zealand
PO Box 12700
Wellington 6144</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Auckland District Health Board</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Private Bag 92189
Auckland Mail Centre
Auckland 1142</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Evidence suggests that that cancer may affect the activity of a liver enzyme (CYP2C19) that helps to activate the anticancer drug cyclophosphamide, an important agent in the treatment of breast cancer. 
There are large differences in the way each person responds to anticancer drugs. Some of these differences relate to the way the body processes drugs using enzymes found in the liver. One reason for different reactions to cancer treatment may be differences in amounts of these liver enzymes or differences in the way they work. The liver enzyme that we are studying is called CYP2C19. Most of the activity of CYP2C19 is inherited. CYP2C19 can activate cyclophosphamide, a drug used in your treatment. Our recent work suggested that in the activity of this CYP2C19 gene is regulated differently in cancer patients than in healthy people, so that some cancer patients may have extremely low drug processing activity. 
It is possible to measure CYP2C19 activity by giving them a small dose of a drug called proguanil. This medication is often taken by travellers for prevention of malaria and is processed by the body in a similar way to cyclophosphamide. 
In this study we would like to measure the activity of this CYP2C19 enzyme by measuring proguanil blood concentrations after a test dose and also directly measure the activation of cyclophosphamide in blood samples. 
By learning more about the things that influence a persons ability to process drugs, we might be better able in the future to fine-tune the dose of cancer drugs to the individual.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Health and Disability Ethics Committees
1 the Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTX/12/06/052</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nuala Helsby</name>
      <address>Molecular Medicine and Pathology
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences,
University of Auckland, 
85 Park Road
Grafton
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 9831</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.helsby@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nuala Helsby</name>
      <address>Molecular Medicine and Pathology
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences,
University of Auckland, 
85 Park Road
Grafton
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 9831</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.helsby@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>