<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347671">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/11/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001160921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Testing an educational program to improve sun protective behaviour of Queensland teenagers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>You can still be HOT! in the shade: Testing an educational program to improve sun protective behaviour of Queensland teenagers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>HOT! project</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sun preventative-behaviours</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Non melanoma skin cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention focuses on: (1) encouraging supportive sun protective attitudes and beliefs, (2) fostering perceptions of normative support for sun protection behaviour, and (3) increasing perceptions of control/self-efficacy over using sun protection. The study will involve 4 public and 4 private schools in Queensland. Intervention sessions will be facilitated by trained persons from either Cancer Council Queensland or Queensland University of Technology. Facilitators and Queensland University of Technology researcher staff will be authorised to deliver the intervention with secondary school students during school hours, and all study staff directly involved with the participants and the running of the intervention will have a current Positive Notice Blue Card (a safety check card that allows access to work with children). The facilitators and Queensland University of Technology researcher staff will follow the directions of supervising school staff regarding access to child participants and the location of testing. Testing will take place in an accessible area designated by the school principal or supervising teacher, in proximity to normal classroom activities. As required by the Health &amp; Safety requirements for Queensland schools, the supervising teacher will be aware of the intervention testing circumstances. Assistance will be available from school staff when required. The facilitators and Queensland University of Technology researcher staff will follow the required procedures for visitors to the school. 

Each intervention session of 1 hour per session and occurring once a week over a three week timeline will address a different construct. Week one will be designed to encourage supportive sun protection related attitudes and beliefs. Week two will focus on fostering perceptions of friendship group normative support for sun protection. Week three will aim to increase perceptions of control/self-efficacy over using sun protection.  Activities for the intervention will include group based discussions, practical sessions on being sun safe (e.g., applying sunscreen correctly), watching relevant sun safety DVDs, and students creating their own internet and/or text message campaigns to encourage sun safety amongst young people. At the conclusion of each session, participants and facilitators will evaluate program content, materials, and delivery.</interventions>
    <comparator>A no-treatment control group is used but participants randomised to the control group will be offered the opportunity to receive the intervention material at the completion of the project (a wait-list control group).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' sun protective-behaviour as measured by self-report using standard theory of planned behaviour items</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and at 1 and 4 weeks post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' intentions to sun-protect as measured by self-report using standard theory of planned behaviour items</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and at 1 and 4 weeks post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' attitude toward sun-protection as measured by self-report using standard theory of planned behaviour items</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and at 1 and 4 weeks post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' perception of normative support for sun-protection as measured by self-report using standard theory of planned behaviour items</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and at 1 and 4 weeks post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' perception of control/self-efficacy toward sun-protection as measured by self-report using standard theory of planned behaviour items</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and at 1 and 4 weeks post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligibility criteria includes male and female students aged 12 to 17 years from public and private secondary schools across metropolitan and regional areas of Queensland, Australia.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>17</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A convenience sample of schools will be recruited using a maximum variation sampling method to ensure participating schools range in social-demographic status and geographical location. Schools will be approached to participate by the study team using an information package by phone, email and face-to-face discussions. The information package will include a letter to the school principal, background information about the study, questionnaire items, and the participant intervention workbook. Consenting schools will be requested to identify teachers (and their students) that will be accessible to the research team. Active consent will be obtained from both the student participating and their legal guardian. Consenting schools will then be randomised to the intervention or a wait-listed control group and allocated to these groups via a process involving the contacting of the holder of the allocation schedule who is “off site”.</concealment>
    <sequence>Consenting schools will be randomised in a 1:1 ratio to the intervention or a wait-listed control group using a computer-generated random number sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/10/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4068</postcode>
    <postcode>4170</postcode>
    <postcode>4551</postcode>
    <postcode>4567</postcode>
    <postcode>4207</postcode>
    <postcode>4670</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cancer Council Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>553 Gregory Terrace 
Fortitude Valley QLD 4006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 11 Lancaster Place
Majura Park ACT 2609</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to test an educational program to improve sun protective behaviour of Queensland teenagers. 

Who is it for? 
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a male or female student aged 12 to 17 years who attends a public or private secondary school in metropolitan or regional Queensland, Australia.

Trial details
Participants in this trial will be randomly (by chance) allocated to one of two groups. Participants in one group will receive the intervention straight away. Participants in the other group will receive the intervention on completion of the study. The intervention involves 3 x 1 hour sessions over a 3 week period. The sessions are delivered during school hours by a trained facilitator, and will focus on encouraging supportive sun protective attitudes and beliefs, fostering perceptions of normative support for sun protection behaviour, and increasing perceptions of control/self-efficacy over using sun protection.

Participants will be asked to complete questionnaires before and after the program. The study will provide valuable information about the effectiveness of the program in improving the sun protective behaviour of adolescents, which is important to prevent future skin cancers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University Human Research Ethics Committee, Queensland University of Technology</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Queensland University of Technology,  88 Musk Avenue Kelvin Grove Campus, GPO Box 2434, BRISBANE   QLD   4001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/07/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1100000768</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Department of Education and Training</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>DET, Education House, 30 Mary St Brisbane, PO Box 15033 City East QLD 4002</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>550/27/119</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Catholic Education Archdiocese of Brisbane</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Brisbane Catholic Education GPO Box 1201, Brisbane QLD 4001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/08/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>A11.096 JS:em ref:172</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Katherine White</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Counselling, Queensland University of Technology, Victoria Park Road,  Kelvin Grove. Brisbane, Queensland 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31384689</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 31384660</fax>
      <email>km.white@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Katherine White</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Counselling, Queensland University of Technology, Victoria Park Road,  Kelvin Grove. Brisbane, Queensland 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31384689</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 31384660</fax>
      <email>km.white@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Katherine White</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Counselling, Queensland University of Technology, Victoria Park Road,  Kelvin Grove. Brisbane, Queensland 4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 31384689</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 31384660</fax>
      <email>km.white@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>