<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82400">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/11/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/11/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000589482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Brivanib and Cetuximab versus Cetuximab and Placebo in treating patients with metastatic colorectal cancer who have been previously treated with combination chemotherapy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase III randomised study of Brivanib Alaninate (BMS-582664) in combination with Cetuximab (Erbitux 'Registered trade mark') versus placebo in combination with Cetuximab (Erbitux 'Registered trade mark') in patients with K-Ras wild type tumours previously treated with combination chemotherapy for metastatic colorectal carcinoma to compare overall survival.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CO.20</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NCICCTG-CO.20 (National Cancer Institute of Canada Clinical Trials Group)</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>BMS-CA182009 (Bristol Myers-Squibb, Canada)</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>AGITG-NCICCTG-CO.20 (Australian Gastrointestinal Trials Group)</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This ia a randomised, double-blind, multicentre study. Patients will be stratified by centre and ECOG (Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group) perfomance status (ie: 0 or 1 versus 2) into one of two treatment arms. 
Arm I: Patients will receive Brivanib 800mg orally daily, in addition to an initial loading dose infusion of Cetuximab (Erbitux) 400mg/m2 over 120 minutes. Thereafter, patients will receive weekly maintenance infusions of Cetuximab 250mg/m2 over 60 minutes. 
Arm II: Patients will receive placebo orally daily, and an initial loading dose of Cetuximab 400mg/m2 IV over 120 minutes. Thereafter, the patients will receive a weekly maintenance infusion of Cetuximab 250mg/m2 IV over 60 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment Arm II is the comparator (control) group. These patients will receive the placebo, in addition to a loading dose of Cetuximab 400mg/m2 intravenously, followed by weekly maintenance infusions of Cetuximab 250mg/m2.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the overall survival of patients with previously treated metastatic colorectal cancer treated with Brivanib in combination with Cetuximab with those treated with placebo and Cetuximab</outcome>
      <timepoint>At interim analysis point (ie: &gt; 263 deaths) and end of study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare progression-free survival in both treatment groups
Compare objective response rate and duration of response in both treatment groups.
Compare quality of life in both treatment groups.
Compare health utilities in both treatment groups.
Conduct a comparative economic evaluation of both treatment groups.
Evaluate safety profile of Cetuximab and Brivanib and Cetuximab alone in this patient population.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age &gt; 18 years Histologically confirmed metastatic colorectal cancer Confirmed K-Ras wild type tumour Previously treated with thymidylate synthase inhibitor Previously failed treatment with irinotecan-containing regimen and oxaliplatin-containing regimen where failure is defined as either progression of disease or intolerance to the regimen due to severe allergic reaction or delayed recovery from toxicity. Measurable or evaluable disease Minimum 4 weeks have elapsed since recent surgery, chemotherapy, treatment with another investigational agent, or radiation therapy ECOG performace status of 0, 1, or 2 Provision of blood/tumor speciments for correlative studies</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>K-Ras mutant, indeterminate, or no tumour tissue available for testing History of other malignancies other than non-melanoma skin cancer, in-situ cancer of the cervix, or other curatively treated solid tumors with no evidence of disease for &gt; 5 years Any active disease condition which would render protocol treatment dangerous or does not permit compliance with protocol Uncontrolled or significant cardiovascular disease, hypertension, or a history of thromboembolic event in last 6 months Central nervous system metastases Prior treatment with Cetuximab or other EGFR (epidermal growth factor receptor) pathway targetting agent or murine monoclonal antibody</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be enrolled and randomised to the study via a web-based registration &amp; randomisation system (ie: MANGO), housed at Queen's University, Kingston, Ontario, Canada.</concealment>
    <sequence>Dynamic Minimisation procedure</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/03/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>750</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC,QLD,SA,WA,NT,TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3000 - 3999</postcode>
    <postcode>4000 - 4999</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - 5999</postcode>
    <postcode>6000 - 6999</postcode>
    <postcode>7000 - 7999</postcode>
    <postcode>2000 - 2999</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australasian Gastro-Intestinal Trials Group (AGITG)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Sydney
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown NSW, 1450</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australasian Gastro-Intestinal Trials Group (AGITG)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Sydney
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown NSW, 1450</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>National Cancer Institute of Canada</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>10 Alcorn Avenue, Suite 200
Toronto, Ontario, M4V 3B1</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Canada</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is assessing two different chemotherapy treatments  Brivanib and Cetuximab versus Cetuximab and standard treatment  in treating people with metastatic (secondary distant) colorectal (K-Ras Wild Type) cancer who have previously been treated with combination chemotherapy. 

Who is it for?

You can join this study if you have completed the standard chemotherapy for metastatic colorectal cancer. 

Trial details

Participants will be randomly divided into two groups. One group will receive a combination of a compound known as oral Brivanib in combination with Cetuximab; the other will receive standard treatment in combination with Cetuximab. The trial will eventually assess if there is a difference in overall survival between the two groups.

Brivanib blocks a compound known as vascular endothelial growth factor receptor 2 (VEGFR2) and this may result in the inhibition of tumour blood vessel growth. Cetuximab blocks another factor called the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) and so inhibits cell growth. If your cancer has increased in size on standard treatment for metastatic colorectal cancer (which might included 5-fluorouracil, oxaliplatin and irinotecan), your treatment options are limited. Cetuximab works in this setting but it is not part of the standard treatment. This purpose of this trial is to test if the combination of Brivanib and Cetuximab versus Cetuximab alone improve survival if the treatment you have been receiving has not worked.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cancer Institute NSW</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 1, Biomedical Building 
Australian Technology Park 
1 Central Avenue, EVELEIGH, NSW, 2015</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2007C/09/016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/08/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Jeremy Shapiro</name>
      <address>Dept of Medical Oncology
Cabrini Hospital
Suite 19, 183 Wattletree Road
MALVERN, VIC, 3144</address>
      <phone>+613 9509 1866</phone>
      <fax>+613 9509 6014</fax>
      <email>jeremy.shapiro@med.monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Jeremy Shapiro</name>
      <address>Dept of Medical Oncology
Cabrini Hospital
Suite 19, 183 Wattletree Road
MALVERN, VIC, 3144</address>
      <phone>+613 9509 1866</phone>
      <fax>+613 9509 6014</fax>
      <email>jeremy.shapiro@med.monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Fabyolla El-Tahche</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
University of Sydney
Locked Bag 77
CAMPERDOWN, NSW, 1450</address>
      <phone>+61295625370</phone>
      <fax>+61295625094</fax>
      <email>fabyolla.el-tahche@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>