<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372711">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000540314p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>EGFR inhibitor for the treatment of KRAS wild-type unresectable or metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor (EGFR) inhibitor Panitumumab for the treatment of KRAS wild-type unresectable or metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>KRAS wild-type unresectable or metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pancreatic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Following determination of KRAS status, verification of eligibility for this study and informed consent participants will receive study treatment. KRAS wild type patients will be enrolled in the treatment arm, and will be administered panitumumab at a dose of 6mg/kg IV once every 2 weeks. The study drug, panitumumab, will be given as a sole agent for 3 months. Participants can receive chemotherapy in addition to the study treatment after the first three months, at the discretion of the treating clinician in consultation with the patient. Participants can continue on study treatment for up to 24 months.

Premedication should be given as per local sites usual practices and supportive care provided at each treating clinicians discretion and the local institutions normal standard of care. Prophylactic antibiotic therapy to prevent or reduce the severity of the rash is highly recommended. Adherence to therapy will be monitored by medical review prior to each cycle. 

Treatment assessments will include routine history and physical examination, evaluation for adverse events, routine laboratory testing, quality of life questionnaires (EORTC QLQ-C30 version 3.0), and CT scans of the chest, abdomen and pelvis. PET-CT and Ca19.9 will be performed at 4 and 8 weeks for all KRAS wild type patients who remain on panitumumab, and objective tumour response will be evaluated every 8 weeks according to RECIST criteria version 1.1.
</interventions>
    <comparator>In the observation arm of the study, two KRAS mutant patients undergoing alternative/standard second line chemotherapy will be enrolled for every one patient enrolled into the treatment arm. Following the enrolment of a patient in the treatment arm, the next two KRAS mutant patients who are both eligible and give consent will be selected for entry into the observation arm.  The assessments will be identical to the treatment cohort. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Metabolic Response Rate (MRR) to Panitumumab, assessed by PET scan and serum Ca19.9 levels. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at four and eight weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Freedom from progression (FFP) rate as defined by RECIST criteria version 1.1 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of selecting patients for personalized therapy, defined as the proportion of the screened patients who  start study treatment 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At conclusion of trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression free survival, as measured in days from the date of treatment initiation to the date of first evidence of disease progression or death, whichever occurs first.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed by PET/CT at 8 weeks, then CT chest, abdomen and pelvis every 8 weeks according to RECIST criteria version 1.1. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival, measured in days from the date of treatment initiation to date of death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following completion of therapy, patient status will be monitored every 8 weeks for survival assessment.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Objective tumour response rate (OTRR), defined as the sum of the partial and complete responders (as defined by RECIST criteria version 1.1) expressed as a proportion of the total number of patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed as per RECIST criteria version 1.1 every 8 weeks for up to 2 years. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety (including toxicity and morbidity of treatment). Adverse events will be graded and recorded at each assessment, using the NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (NCI-CTCAE) version 4.0.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse events will be graded and recorded every 2 weeks while on study treatment, and after finishing treatment once more at a 30 day follow up assessment, </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The EORTC QLQ-C30 version 3.0 questionnaire will be used to evaluate participant quality of life every 4 weeks for the first 12 weeks, then at the end of treatment.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i. Adults, age 18 years or over, male or female 
ii. Locally advanced (unresectable) or metastatic biopsy-proven pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC)
iii. KRAS wild-type PDAC (for panitumumab treatment arm) 
iv. ECOG performance status 0-2 
v. Measurable disease as per the response evaluation criteria in solid tumours (RECIST) guideline version 1.1 
vi. Progressive disease following first line chemotherapy - defined as an increase in Ca19.9 of 30% above that recorded at the end of first line therapy (confirmed on 2 blood draws) or evidence of progressive disease on imaging according to RECIST criteria 
vii. Adequate bone marrow function; (ANC equal or greater than 1500/mcL, platelets equal or greater than 100 000/mcL, haemoglobin equal or greater than 9g/dL) 
viii. Adequate renal function; calculated creatinine clearance (CrCl) greater than or equal to 50ml/min (Cockcroft-Gault formula) or Creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 XULN 
ix. Adequate hepatic function; serum total bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 times ULN, ALT/AST less than or equal to 2.5 times ULN (or less than or equal to 5 times ULN with documented liver metastases), ALP less than or equal to 5 times ULN, and INR less than or equal to 1.5 
x. Provision of informed consent for participation in the study </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>i. Pancreatic neuroendocrine tumours, cholangiocarcinoma affecting the supra-pancreatic bile duct and tumours metastic to the pancreas (e.g. renal cell carcinoma) 
ii. Children, persons younger than 18 years of age 
iii. Pregnancy or lactation 
iv. Active or uncontrolled infection 
v. Previous treatment with EGFR inhibitor  
vi. Previous radiotherapy to the pancreas if this is the only site of disease. 
vii. Hypersensitivity to study drug 
viii. Previous or current interstitial lung disease  
ix. Previous or current pulmonary fibrosis 
x. History of another malignancy within 2 years prior to allocation. (NB. Patients with adequately treated carcinoma in-situ, curatively treated uterine cervix carcinoma in-situ or non-melanoma skin carcinoma, or superficial transitional cell carcinoma of the bladder remain eligible even if diagnosed less than 2 years earlier. Patients with a history of other malignancy are eligible if they have been continuously disease-free for at least 2 years following definitive treatment.) 
xi. Any severe or uncontrolled medical conditions within 3 months prior to allocation, including but not limited to: 
* Unstable cardiac disease, myocardial infarction or uncontrolled arrhythmia 
* Cirrhosis, untreated hepatitis 
* Active bleeding diathesis 
* Renal failure 
* Unstable diabetes </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>In the observation arm of the study, two KRAS mutant patients undergoing alternative/standard second line chemotherapy will be enrolled for every one patient enrolled into the treatment arm. Following the enrolment of a patient in the treatment arm, the next two KRAS mutant patients who are both eligible and give consent will be selected for entry into the observation arm. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>In this study, 100-200 patients will be screened. With an expected prevalence of KRAS mutation of 80%, we will recruit up to 19 patients for the therapeutic component of the study. There will be stopping rules for futility after 8 patients. 

A study of initially 8 patients is proposed on the basis of ruling out futility if at least one MRR is observed and/or at least one patient is free of progression at 3 months. In the absence of more than one MRR being observed in the first eight patients, a decision to continue the study and recruit a further 11 patients (making 19 in total) may be made guided by the strength of the FFP at 3 months rate.  If all 8 patients have progressed within 3 months and no MRR is observed, then consideration will be given to either modifying the design or stopping the study for futility.  The MRR and FFP at 3 months rates in the full cohort could then be determined together with the degree of uncertainty surrounding these rates. 

The further 11 patients will be recruited in a stepwise fashion.  After 13 patients have been enrolled and assessed, if still only 1 MRR is observed then the study could re-assessed as to whether to continue to the 19 or stop for futility depending on the rate of FFP. If all 13 patients have also progressed by 3 months then the study may stopped at this point. However if at least one patient has as a FFP &gt; 3 months then continuing to the 19 patients may still be an option. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>15/05/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Daniel Croagh</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Surgery
Upper GI and HPB
Monash Medical Centre 
246 Clayton Rd, Clayton VIC 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Amgen Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 7, 123 Epping Road 
 North Ryde, NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash Comprehensive Cancer Consortium</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>27-31 Wright Street
Clayton Victoria 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Epworth Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>185-187 Hoddle St, 
Richmond VIC 3121</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cook Medical </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>95 Brandl St
Brisbane Technology Park
8 Mile Plains, Queensland 4113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>246 Clayton Rd 
Clayton VIC 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to test if panitumumab is a potentially useful treatment for pancreatic cancers which do not have mutations in the KRAS gene. Panitumumab has been shown to be effective in colon cancer, but only in those patients with cancers that lack a mutation in the KRAS gene. The fact that 90% of patients with pancreatic cancer have a mutation in the KRAS gene may explain why panitumumab has not been found to be effective when it has been administered to all patients with pancreatic cancer. 

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to enroll in this trial if you are aged 18 or over and have been diagnosed with locally advanced (unresectable) or metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) which has progressed following first line chemotherapy.

Study details
Participants enrolled who have KRAS wild-type PDAC will be allocated to the treatment arm. These participants will receive panitumumab by injection, once every two weeks for up to 24 months, with chemotherapy started at 3 months if your treating doctor determines that this would be beneficial. Participants enrolled who have KRAS mutated PDAC will be allocated to the observation group. These participants will receive standard treatment as determined by their treating doctor, and will simply complete trial assessments. Assessments for all participants will include PET and CT scans and blood tests to monitor cancer progression for up to two years.

It is hoped that the findings from this trial will provide information on whether panitumumab is an effective therapy for KRAS wild-type PDAC.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd, Clayton VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Daniel Croagh</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery
Upper GI and HPB
Monash Medical Centre 
246 Clayton Rd, Clayton VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9543 5311</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9543 3805</fax>
      <email>dan.croagh@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joanne Lundy</name>
      <address>Monash Medical Centre 
246 Clayton Rd, Clayton VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9594 6207</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>joanne.lundy@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Daniel Croagh</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery
Upper GI and HPB
Monash Medical Centre 
246 Clayton Rd, Clayton VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9543 5311</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9543 3805</fax>
      <email>dan.croagh@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>