<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366588">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001054606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot study to evaluate the prognostic and metabolic effects of metformin during treatment of metastatic prostate cancer with androgen deprivation therapy </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot study to evaluate the prognostic and metabolic effects of metformin during treatment of metastatic prostate cancer with androgen deprivation therapy </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ADMET – ADjuvant METformin in metastatic prostate cancer with ADT

</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metastatic prostate cancer </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a two-arm study. Both Arm 1 and Arm 2 will be receiving androgen deprivation therapy (ADT). The ADT used is a combined androgen blockade with luteinizing hormone releasing hormone (LHRH) agonist (45mg EligardTrademark) and AR antagonist (50mg Cosudex/bicalutamide) for the first 4 weeks as per standard of care. After that, EligardTrademark will continue as monotherapy 6 monthly unless clinically indicated for complete androgen blockade. At 12 weeks into ADT, participants will receive 1500mg metformin (3x500mg daily, with meals) or placebo depending on the treatment arm allocated after randomization.

Metformin or Placebo tablets will be dispensed every 12 weeks. Participants will need to return the unused tablets to the research team before or after each dispensing for drug accountability purpose. Moreover, participants will have 6 weekly medical review.

Arm 1
Metformin hydrochloride 500mg tablet 
Dosage: 1500mg daily
Duration: 30 weeks
Mode of administration: Oral

</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 2 
Placebo
Duration: 30 weeks
Mode of administration: Oral

The placebo are biconvex, film coated tablets. They have everything the same as the Metformin tablet except without active ingredient. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to progression of disease defined as biochemical, radiographic or clinical progression</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prostate specific antigen and 6 weekly clincial review will be used to determine biochemical and clinical progression: every 6 weeks for 42 weeks and at week 54 (end-of-study visit)

CT scan and bone scan will be used to determine radiographic progression: if clinically indicated. Radiographically, Prostate Cancer Working Group (PCWG) 2 criteria will be used.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes to metabolic parameters including fasting insulin by blood test , fasting glucose by blood test, body mass index, and serum biomarkers (Leptin, adiponectin, ghrelin)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks for 42 weeks and at week 54 (end-of-study visit)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Molecular changes to the circulating tumour cells.  
Circulating tumour cells will be isolated using Stemcell Technology RosetteSep.  The isolated cells will be lysed. The chages will be assessed by real-time polymerase chain reaction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 12 weeks for 36 weeks and at week 54 (End-of-Study Visit)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Age above 18 years
2.	Competent to understand information and provide written informed consent
3.	Metastatic prostate adenocarcinoma defined by radiological diagnosis (TNM staging), PSA greater or than equal to 20 in the presence of tissue diagnosis or abnormal prostate examination, PSA recurrence post surgery or radiotherapy
4.	No prior chemotherapy for prostate cancer
5.	Not on insulin control medications [Insulin, oral hypoglycaemic agents, systemic corticosteroid of any dosage, atypical antipsychotic drugs of any dose]
6.	Adequate renal function (Creatinine equal to 177mmol/L, GFR greater than 30 mls/min)
7.	Adequate hepatic function (Bilirubin must be equal to 1.5 x upper limit of normal range, ALT and ALP must be equal to 2.5 x upper limit of normal) 
8.	Life expectancy greater than 6 months
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Known brain metastasis
2.	Malignant disease other than prostate cancer at the time of enrolment, apart from completely treated non-melanomatous skin malignancy
3.	Prior chemotherapy for prostate cancer
4.	Prior primary radiotherapy within 6 weeks
5.	Previously treated with ketoconazole for greater than 7 days
6.	Prior systemic treatment with an azole drug within 4 weeks
7.	Prior antiandrogen treatment within 6 weeks
8.	History of lactic acidosis 
9.	History of pituitary or adrenal dysfunction
10.	Cardiac (heart failure NYHA class II or greater, acute myocardial infarct, unstable angina, arterial-thromboembolic event within past 6 months) or respiratory insufficiency (active pulmonary embolism, severe chronic obstructive pulmondary disease), severe liver failure (cirrhosis with a Child-Pugh level of B or greater), severe infection that is likely to increase the risk of lactic acidosis 
11.	Medical or psychiatric conditions that compromise the patient's ability to give informed consent
12.	History of pituitary or adrenal dysfunction
13.	Participants will be discharged from the study if unable to tolerate metformin due to adverse reactions or develop medical conditions such as renal failure or diabetes requiring additional agents other than metformin
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrolment: Consecutive patients with metastatic prostate cancer suitable for trial who has been referred to service areas of Princess Alexandra Hospital
Randomization: Central randomisation by computer to treatment groups
</concealment>
    <sequence>Central randomisation by computer</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Epworth Richmond - Richmond</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <postcode>3121 - Richmond</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>2, George Street, Brisbane, QLD 4122, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>2014 Princess Alexandra Hospital Research Support Scheme Grants</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PA Research Foundation, Princess Alexandra Hospital, Centres for Health Research, Translational Research Institute, 37 Kent Street, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Tolmar Australia Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Building 2, Leve 2, Suite 4, 20 Bridge Street
PYMBLE NSW 2073</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will investigate the effects of combining metformin with androgen deprivation therapy (ADT) in men with metastatic prostate cancer.

You may be eligible to join this study if you are male, aged 18 years or above and have been diagnosed with metastatic prostate adenocarcinoma, for which you have not received any ADT.

Study details
Participants in this study are randomly allocated (by chance) to one of two groups. Participants in one group will take 3 x 500mg oral tablets of metformin hydrochloride daily for 30 weeks, whilst participants in the other group will take 3 oral tablets of placebo (inactive treatment) daily for 30 weeks. 
Participants will be followed-up every 6 weeks for 54 weeks, in order to determine metabolic and tumour responses and tumour progression.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Health service District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Alexandra Hospital, Centres for Health Research, Level 7, Translational Research Institute, 37 Kent Street, Woolloongabba QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00167</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland University of Technology Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Unit, Office of Research, Level 4, 88 Musk Ave, QUT Kelvin Grove QLD 4059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00171</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Epworth HealthCare Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>89 Bridge Road, Richmond VIC 3121
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00217</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Colleen Nelson</name>
      <address>Australian Prostate Cancer Research Centre  Queensland
Level 1, Building 1, Princess Alexandra Hospital, 199 Ipswich Road, Brisbane QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 7443 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>colleen.nelson@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Colleen Nelson</name>
      <address>Australian Prostate Cancer Research Centre  Queensland
Level 1, Building 1, Princess Alexandra Hospital, 199 Ipswich Road, Brisbane QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 7443 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>colleen.nelson@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Colleen Nelson</name>
      <address>Australian Prostate Cancer Research Centre  Queensland
Level 1, Building 1, Princess Alexandra Hospital, 199 Ipswich Road, Brisbane QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 7443 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>colleen.nelson@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Maggie Fung</name>
      <address>Australian Prostate Cancer Research Centre  Queensland
Level 1, Building 1, Princess Alexandra Hospital, 199 Ipswich Road, Brisbane QLD 4102</address>
      <phone />
      <fax>+61 7 31767449</fax>
      <email>maggie.fung@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>