<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369586">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/12/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001333505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessing the acceptability and feasibility of a program to assist people diagnosed with cancer to talk about and plan for future medical care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot randomised controlled trial testing the acceptability and feasibility of an intervention to assist people diagnosed with with cancer to discuss and document wishes for future medical care</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Advance care planning (ACP) involves a person discussing with their treatment team and family the medical care they would prefer in case they became too ill in the future to express their wishes, documenting their wishes in a written statement and/or appointing a substitute-decision maker. Patients randomised to the intervention will receive the following three strategies at study recruitment designed to increase engagement in ACP:
(1) Provision of a prescriptive letter. Participants will receive a letter at the appointment informing them of the importance of undertaking ACP, The letter will emphasise that the oncologist provides advice to all their patients to plan for their future medical care, regardless of diagnosis or prognosis. The letter will include: (i) an explanation of the purpose and importance of future planning; (ii) state-specific information about enduring guardianship and advance directives, including their purpose and benefits.
(2) Use of Start2Talk and/or DVD. Participants will be encouraged to access the Start2Talk website to facilitate documentation of an advance care plan (http://www.start2talk.org.au/); and/or watch the DVD of a practicing clinician explaining advance care planning to a simulated patient. Patients will be encouraged to complete the provided worksheets to document an advance care plan. In particular they will be encouraged to complete Worksheets 1.4 and 1.5, which involve completing a statement of values and wishes and a more specific directive. 
(3) SMS prompts. Participants will receive an SMS prompt from the research team 2 weeks and 4 weeks after recruitment reminding them to access the Start2Talk website and/or watch the DVD. The SMS message will include a toll free telephone number to enable contact with a research team member to answer any questions they may have. 
Participants will self-report use of the website and/or DVD, and receipt of reminders and letter.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard care
ACP occur relatively rarely and often very close to death. Patients with cancer under the care of medical oncologists in Australia rarely complete advance care directives. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility: number of times each of the intervention components was accessed (i.e. Start2Talk website, DVD, SMS prompts) as assessed using a self-report survey with patients. The survey was designed specifically for this study. Consent rates, attrition rates will also be assessed as a measure of feasibility.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants will self-report in the survey designed for the study about acceptability of the intervention components including: whether the letters and SMS prompts were useful; and whether the Start2Talk website and/or DVD was easy to understand. </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Uptake of advance care planning: 
1) Proportion of patients who have appointed an enduring guardian (or equivalent) and/or completed an advance directive. Participants will be asked to respond yes/no/unsure. If the participants indicates yes, they will be asked to provide a time estimate of when this was done (last week/fortnight/month).
2) Proportion of patients who intend to appoint an enduring guardian (or equivalent) and/or completed an advance directive.  Participants will be asked to respond yes/no/unsure. </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Barriers to ACP: 12 items on patient knowledge, attitudes and behaviour in relation to advance care planning will be assessed using a self-report survey designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 months post-recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>People diagnosed with cancer, receiving care from participating  oncology outpatient clinics; able to read and write English at a level that allows completion of surveys; able to provide informed consent; judged by service staff to be cognitively, emotionally and physically able to participate.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People whose primary language is other than English (LOTE); Children and/or young people (ie. &lt;18 years); People with an intellectual or mental impairment. Participants under the age of 18 have been excluded as they are unable to give informed consent. While it would be of interest to include non-English speaking participants, they have been
excluded due to anticipated difficulties in responding to the written survey and using the intervention which will be produced in English only. Given informed consent is required as well as completing surveys and accessing web-based and audio-visual information (for the intervention group), people with an intellectual or mental impairment have also been excluded. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The randomisation schedule will be delivered via secure web-based interface. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will occur as a consequence of a computer-generated random list overseen by an independent statistical unit.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Comparison of the secondary outcome (uptake ACP) between treatment arms will be achieved using a chi-square test and 95%CIs for the difference in proportions between each arm and usual care will be estimated. Assuming a 75% consent rate, 110 patients will be approached to give completed data for 80 patients. This will allow detection of a 30% difference between treatment arms and usual care with 80% power and 5 % significance for the preliminary effectiveness aim. Analysis will be done using the intention to treat framework. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/01/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>4/04/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>18/04/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>85</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>19/09/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Calvary Mater Newcastle - Waratah</hospital>
    <postcode>2298 - Waratah</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Newcastle
University Drive Callaghan NSW 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hunter Cancer Research Alliance (HCRA)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked Bag 7, Hunter Region, Mail Centre NSW 2310 (Internal Mailbox 12) </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Hunter New England Local Health District</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Hunter New England Local Health District 
Locked Bag 1 New Lambton NSW 2305</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to assess the feasibility and accessibility of a series of interventions which aim to increase participation in advance care planning (ACP) for patients who have been diagnosed with cancer. ACP involves patients discussing and documenting their preferences for future medical care in case they are not able to communicate these later. Who is it for? You may be eligible to participate in this study if you are aged 18 or over, have been diagnosed with cancer of any kind and are receiving care from participating oncology outpatient clinics. Study details Participants in this study will be randomly allocated (by chance) to receive either the usual care regarding ACP, or to receive a number of prompts to encourage them to participate in ACP. These prompts include a letter from their oncologist and access to a website and DVD which all outline the purpose and benefits of ACP and provide information and worksheets to get started, as well as two text message prompts to encourage use of these tools. Participants will be asked to complete surveys regarding their use of the tools and how useful they were. It is hoped that the findings of this study will provide information as to whether these prompt strategies are feasible for increasing the uptake of ACP among cancer patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Local Health District HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked bag 1, New Lambton, NSW, 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HNEHREC Reference No: 15/09/16/4.06 NSW HREC Reference No: HREC/15/HNE/351 NSW SSA Reference No: SSA/15/HNE/428</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amy Waller</name>
      <address>Health Behaviour Research Group (HBRG)
Level 4 West Wing
HMRI Building
University Drive
University of Newcastle
Callaghan NSW 2308 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 40420708</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amy.waller@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amy Waller</name>
      <address>Health Behaviour Research Group (HBRG)
Level 4 West Wing
HMRI Building
University Drive
University of Newcastle 
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 40420708</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amy.waller@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amy Waller</name>
      <address>Health Behaviour Research Group (HBRG)
Level 4 West Wing
HMRI Building
University Drive
University of Newcastle 
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 40420708</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amy.waller@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amy Waller</name>
      <address>Health Behaviour Research Group (HBRG)
Level 4 West Wing
HMRI Building
University Drive
University of Newcastle 
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 40420708</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>