<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335395">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000506099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Single Arm  Phase II Study of the Efficacy of Tamoxifen in Triple Negative (oestrogen receptor alpha negative, progesterone receptor negative, HER-2 negative) but Oestrogen Receptor Beta Positive Metastatic Breast Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Women over 18 years with Triple Negative (oestrogen receptor alpha negative, progesterone receptor negative, HER-2 negative) but Oestrogen Receptor Beta Positive Metastatic Breast Cancer will be treated with Tamoxifen to assess the efficacy of this treatment</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SORBET</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ANZ 1001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Triple Negative Metastatic Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To assess the efficacy of tamoxifen 20 mg (oral tablet) daily in triple negative (oestrogen receptor alpha negative, progesterone receptor negative, HER-2 negative) but oestrogen receptor beta positive metastatic breast cancer. Tamoxifen will be administered for duration of the trial (no set time limit - patients will continue to take tamoxifen until progression, withdrawal of consent or unacceptable toxicity).</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall response rate to tamoxifen defined as the proportion of all patients on study who commenced tamoxifen and who satisfy the Reponse Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumours (RECIST1.1) criteria for either a complete response or partial response</outcome>
      <timepoint>RECIST evaluated at baseline and then every 8 weeks for the duration of the trial (patients will continue being on study until progression, withdrawal of consent or unacceptable toxicity). It is anticipated that patient accrual will take approx. 4 years for this study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression free survival, defined as the duration of time from registration to time of progression, will be displayed using Kaplan-Meier survival curves.</outcome>
      <timepoint>RECIST evaluated at baseline and then every 8 weeks for the duration of the trial (patients will continue being on study until progression, withdrawal of consent or unacceptable toxicity). It is anticipated that patient accrual will take approx. 4 years for this study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical benefit rate (complete response or partial response or stable disease for 24 weeks). The Clinical Benefit Rate, defined as CR + PR + SD for 24 weeks, will be calculated after completion of the second stage of the study expected to be 12 months after the last patient starts treatment. A 95% confidence interval will also be reported</outcome>
      <timepoint>The clinical benefit rate, defined as CR + PR + SD for 24 weeks, will be calculated after completion of the second stage of the study expected to be 12 months after the last patient starts treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Female patients, greater than or equal to 18 years with histologically or cytologically confirmed triple negative (oestrogen receptor alpha (ERa) absent, PgR (progesterone receptor) absent, Human Epidermal growth factor Receptor 2 (HER2) In situ hybridisaton (ISH) negative or immunohistochemistry ((IHC) 0 or 1)) breast cancer. All IHC results for ERa and PgR on all tumour specimens must not show any staining in the tumour (i.e. ERa and PgR absent staining in all tumour specimens). 2. Metastatic disease for which, in the investigators opinion, chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy is currently not indicated. 3. Metastatic disease amenable to biopsy or previously biopsied. All patients must have a biopsy from a metastatic disease site, including patients presenting with de novo metastatic disease. A biopsy from axillary or supraclavicular nodes is acceptable for the following: a) Patients with no distant metastatic disease but with axillary or supraclavicular nodal disease that is considered incurable, either: i) Axillary nodes (ipsilateral or contralateral), that are measurable by RECIST and can be followed for response ii) Supraclavicular nodes (ipsilateral or contralateral) that are measurable by RECIST and can be followed for response. b) Patients with distant metastatic disease which is not amenable to biopsy Note that for a) part i) and b) the biopsy confirming triple negative, ER beta positive breast cancer in the axillary node must have occurred at a time point when the disease was considered incurable, i.e. the original pathology from initial sentinel node biopsy or axillary dissection undertaken as part of curative therapy is NOT acceptable. 4. ER beta positive in the metastatic breast cancer sample. (ERbeta1 will be measured with IHC and nuclear ERbeta1 staining with Allred score &gt;3 defined as positive). 5. At least one measurable lesion as defined by revised Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours 1.1 (RECIST) (at least one lesion that can be accurately measured in at least one dimension with longest diameter to be recorded as greater than or equal to 20 mm with conventional techniques or as greater than or equal to 10 mm with spiral computed tomography (CT scan). Measurable lesions in a previously irradiated field are excluded unless progression in the lesion post radiotherapy is documented according to RECIST criteria on the CT scan. 6. At the time of registration, patients must fulfill one of the following: a) Disease is currently progressing - last administration of systemic anti-cancer therapy for metastatic disease (if given) must have ceased greater than or equal to 21 days prior to registration. OR b) Disease is currently not progressing - last administration of systemic anti-cancer therapy for metastatic disease (if given) must have ceased greater than or equal to 42 days prior to registration. 7. Life expectancy of 12 weeks or more. 8. Eastern cooperative oncology group (ECOG)performance status less than or equal to 2. 9. Provision of written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Patients with any positive staining for ERa and/or PgR in ANY sample of invasive breast cancer (including any biopsy of earlier stage disease).

2.	Rapidly progressive metastatic disease which, in the investigators opinion is not suitable for endocrine therapy.

3.		Last dose of chemotherapy &lt; 21 days before the start of tamoxifen. Patients must not have concurrent chemotherapy and tamoxifen.

4.		Treatment with an investigational drug &lt; 21 days prior to registration.

5.	Only measurable lesions in a previously irradiated field without evidence of progression.

6.	Patients who have had previous hormonal therapy for breast cancer (includes Selective Oestrogen Receptor Modulators and Aromatase Inhibitors).

7.	Newly diagnosed or uncontrolled intracerebral metastases. Previously treated, asymptomatic brain metastases are permissible; patients must be stable and off steroid therapy and have a life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.  

8.	History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic composition to tamoxifen.

9.	Receiving any medications or substances that are inhibitors or inducers of CYP3A4 and CYP2D6.  
10.	Previous or concomitant invasive malignancy (except breast cancer). The exceptions are:
a)	patients with non-breast malignancy greater than or equal to10 years ago, treated with curative intent and without 	evidence of recurrence 
b)	basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin
c)	in situ carcinoma without invasion (includes in situ breast carcinoma)
d)	the following non-breast invasive malignancy diagnosed greater than or equal to 5 years ago and without recurrence:
i) stage I papillary thyroid cancer
ii)stage Ia carcinoma of the cervix
iii) borderline or stage I ovarian cancer
iv) superficial bladder cancer

11.	Psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study requirements.

12.	Pregnancy or breast feeding (women of child-bearing potential must agree to use adequate non-hormonal contraception).  A serum or urine test must be carried out on all women of child-bearing potential to exclude pregnancy.

13.	Patients with a history of thrombosis should only participate if considered medically suitable by their doctor.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be recruited from investigator’s clinical practices. Patients will sign a ‘consent to screen’ form at the pre-registration step. A separate written informed consent must also be signed by the patient and investigator prior to registration.

All patients in this trial will be started on the same dose and schedule of tamoxifen. No dose reductions will be permitted. Following registration, patients must begin protocol treatment within 72 hours.</concealment>
    <sequence>Nil</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/07/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/03/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>28/11/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>66</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>5</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>22/08/2014</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>22/08/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australia and New Zealand Breast Cancer Trials Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>ANZBCTG Trials Coordination Department PO Box 155 Hunter Region Mail Centre NSW 2310</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australia and New Zealand Breast Cancer Trials Group</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>ANZBCTG Trials Coordination Department PO Box 155 Hunter Region Mail Centre NSW 2310</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study looks at the effectiveness of the drug tamoxifen in treating breast cancer which is classified as triple negative (oestrogen receptor alpha negative, progesterone receptor negative, HER-2 negative) and oestrogen receptor beta positive, where the cancer has spread to distant sites (metastases).

Who is it for?
You can join this study if you are a woman with triple negative metastatic breast cancer that is oestrogen receptor beta positive and chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy is currently not considered appropriate.  Prior to entering the study, a sample of metastatic tumour must be tested and confirmed to be oestrogen receptor beta positive.

Trial details

Some breast cancer cells contain receptors which the female hormone oestrogen binds to, causing the cancer to grow. The study aims to find out whether tamoxifen may be useful for treating metastatic breast cancer that contains the oestrogen beta receptor. Tamoxifen is an anti-oestrogen drug which is frequently used to treat breast cancers that contain the oestrogen alpha receptor but has not been used specifically to treat breast cancers that contain  the oestrogen beta receptor.
Participants will all receive one oral tablet (20mg) of tamoxifen daily, unless they suffer unacceptable side effects, or their breast cancer progresses.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.anzbctg.org</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Phillips KA, Kiely BE, Francis PA, Boyle FM, Fox SB, Murphy L, Gebski V, Lindsay DF,  Sutherland RL, Badger HD, Forbes JF.  ANZ1001 SORBET: Study of oestrogen receptor beta and efficacy of tamoxifen, a single arm, phase II study of the efficacy of tamoxifen in triple negative but estrogen receptor beta positive metastatic breast cancer. J Clin Oncol 2012. 30 (Supp):TPS1136 (Abstract)</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Center HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/06/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor John F Forbes, Director of Research</name>
      <address>ANZBCTG
PO Box 155
Hunter Region Mail Centre  NSW  2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 0159</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 4985 0141</fax>
      <email>enquiries@anzbctg.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John F. Forbes</name>
      <address>ANZBCTG
PO Box 155
Hunter Region Mail Centre NSW 2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 0159</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 4985 0141</fax>
      <email>enquiries@anzbctg.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John F. Forbes</name>
      <address>ANZBCTG
PO Box 155
Hunter Region Mail Centre NSW 2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 0159</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>enquiries@anzbctg.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>