<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364271">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000658718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>ANZ 1301 (DOMINO):  Exploring decision making about neoadjuvant chemotherapy for operable breast cancer.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>ANZ 1301 (DOMINO): Women who have had a diagnosis of invasive breast cancer in the last 5 years and were offered or discussed neoadjuvant chemotherapy as a treatment option, will participate in a telephone questionnaire to identify factors influencing their decisions about neoadjuvant chemotherapy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DOMINO</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Factors influencing decisions regarding neoadjuvant chemotherapy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Telephone questionnaire.

Each participant will do the questionnaire once. The questionnaire will take approximately 30 minutes.

The first few questions are to check that the interview is right for the participant.  The next questions are for general information on age, location (postcode only) and some general information about health insurance and where the participant was treated (public or private hospital).
The rest of the questions will ask about:
* Breast cancer diagnosis
* What things the particpant thought about, or might think about, to help them decide whether or not to have chemotherapy before breast cancer surgery
* What treatments the participant had for their breast cancer
* What were their worries and concerns while they were having treatment for breast cancer
* What information women should have, before deciding whether or not to have chemotherapy before breast cancer surgery.

Some questions will have different answers to choose from and others also allow for comments to be made.

Ten to twenty interviews will be conducted to identify the majority of relevant issues. The aim is for issue saturation, where no major new issues are raised in three consecutive interviews.</interventions>
    <comparator>Not applicable</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To identify the information needs for women who have considered or have had neoadjuvant chemotherapy treatment within the last five years for initially operable breast cancer by analysing the results of all completed telephone questionnaires</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of all participant telephone interviews</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To identify the issues faced and their prevalence and impact on decision-making for women who have considered or have had neoadjuvant chemotherapy treatment within the last five years for initially operable breast cancer by analysing the results of all completed telephone questionnaires</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of all participant telephone interviews</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To identify the level of distress associated with treatment for women who have considered or have had neoadjuvant chemotherapy treatment within the last five years for initially operable breast cancer by analysing the results of all completed telephone questionnaires</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of all participant telephone interviews</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>N/A</outcome>
      <timepoint>N/A</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Participants must be female, &gt;=18 years
2) Participants have had a diagnosis of invasive breast cancer in the last 5 years
3) Participants have been offered, or have discussed, neoadjuvant chemotherapy as a treatment option
4) Participants have completed surgical intervention for breast cancer
5) Participants are capable of giving informed consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Hearing or other impairment that would preclude a phone interview
2) Insufficient English language skills for participation
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The primary analysis will include all registered participants. 
Interviews will be transcribed and analysed thematically using Nvivo (Registered Trademark) qualitative research software. Participants will continue to be enrolled and interviewed until thematic saturation has occurred, indicated by no major new issues being identified in 3 consecutive interviews. 
Thematic analysis will involve the researchers reading and re-reading transcripts to identify mutually exclusive themes. Initially two researchers will read five transcripts and code independently. They will then meet to discuss and resolve discrepancies, documenting refined coding rules. A draft thematic structure will be constructed and applied to the remaining transcripts. Where necessary, new themes will be identified and applied retrospectively to transcripts coded earlier. Characteristic quotes illustrating each theme will be identified.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Psychosocial</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Retrospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/08/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>26/08/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>20</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/08/2013</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>29/08/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australia and New Zealand Breast Cancer Trials Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 155
HRMC  NSW  2310</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ANZBCTG</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 155
HRMC  NSW  2310</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study aims to identify relevant issues and information needs of women who have considered or have had neoadjuvant chemotherapy treatment within the last five years for initially operable cancer, and incorporate them into a prospective questionnaire and decision aid for women diagnosed with operable breast cancer considering neoadjuvant chemotherapy.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged over 18 years, have had a diagnosis of invasive breast cancer in the last 5 years, have been offered or have discussed neoadjuvant chemotherapy as a treatment option and have completed a surgical intervention for breast cancer.

Trial details
Participants in this study will be interviewed once over the phone to identify the issues faced and their prevalence and impact on decision making, and the level of distress associated with treatment for women who have considered or have had neoadjuvant chemotherapy treatment within the last five years for initially operable breast cancer. The findings will be incorporated into a prospective questionnaire and subsequent decision aid for women considering neoadjuvant chemotherapy for operable breast cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Zdenkowski N, Forbes JF, Butow P, Boyle F. ANZBCTG: DOMINO - Exploring decision making about neoadjuvant chemotherapy for operable breast cancer .HMRI Conference on Translational Research, Newcastle, Australia 2013; PP40.

Zdenkowski N, Butow PN, Fewster S, Beckmore C, Wells K, Forbes JF, Boyle FM. Exploring decision making about neoadjuvant chemotherapy for early breast cancer. J Clin Oncol 2014; 32, (suppl; e20578)

Zdenkowski N, Butow P, Fewster S, Beckmore C, Wells K, Forbes J, Boyle F.DOMINO: Exploring decision making about neoadjuvant chemotherapy for operable breast cancer. 2014; MOGA ASM 2014 Poster.

Zdenkowski N, Butow P, Mann GB, Fewster S, Beckmore C, Isaacs R, Boyle FM, on behalf of the ANZBCTG. Neoadjuvant systemic therapy for breast cancer: A survey of Australian and New Zealand (ANZ) specialists. St Gallen 2015 2015; P199.
 
Zdenkowski N, Butow P, Mann B, Fewster S, Douglas C, Boyle FM. Decisions about neoadjuvant systemic therapy for breast cancer: a survey of Australian and New Zealand specialists. ANZ Journal of Surgery. 2015; 85(11):797-799.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 1
New Lambton NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/07/17/5.07</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/06/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicholas Zdenkowski</name>
      <address>ANZBCTG
PO Box 155
HRMC  NSW  2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 7985 0134</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>enquiries@anzbctg.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicholas Zdenkowski</name>
      <address>ANZBCTG
PO Box 155
HRMC NSW 2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 0134</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>enquiries@anzbctg.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicholas Zdenkowski</name>
      <address>ANZBCTG
PO Box 155
HRMC  NSW  2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 0134</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>enqiries@anzbctg.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>