<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="497">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000462684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The influence of initial screening test technology on participation in rescreening for colorectal cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The influence of initial screening test technology on participation in rescreening for colorectal cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Screening for bowel cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim is to determine the effect of the type of test offered in a first round of a screening program for colorectal cancer on participation in a second round.
Group 1: First round of screening Hemoccult II Sensa, low technology test. Second round of screening: InSure test, high technology.
Group 2: First round of screening: FlexSure OBT, mid technology test. Second round: InSure OBT, high technology.
Group 3: First round of screening: InSure OBT, high technology test. Second round: InSure OBT, high technology.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Paricipation in screening defined as return of a screening kit 12 weeks from offer.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Test positivity rate</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Yield of neoplasia</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>First round of screeningInclusion: Present on the electoral roll of the South Australian Electoral Commission on 01/02/2001.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>69</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None but invitees provided with a list of conditions and settings where faecal occult blood based screening is inappropriate and requesting self-exclusion by not participating.Second round of screening.Inclusion: Selected for the first round of screening invitationsExclusion: People identified during Round 1 as having gastrointestinal conditions that invalidate screening results, people identified with mental and physical disabilities that prevent them from following the study protocol, people known to have had a neoplasia negative colonoscopy 5 years prior to a screening offer, people whose first round kits were returned unopened and 'not known at this address', people who informed the screening facility that they did not want further contact.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Invitees are randomised to one of 3 invitation groups that differed by the type of screening test offered. The tests varied by level of technology.  Allocation to invitation group was not concealed from the investigators and office staff who printed and packaged invitation kits for postal delivery, but there was no direct contact between investigators and invitees. Invitees were unaware that there was more than one test type. A help line was available and inquiries were answered without knowledge of test type.</concealment>
    <sequence>roup sizes of 606 each were determined by power analysis assuming that an intervention that produces a 10% increase in participation over control is a significant program improvement. For the first round of offers: The electoral office provided a listing of all people in selected postcodes adjacent to the catchment area of Flinders Medical Centre and the Repatriation General Hospital Daw Park. They were assigned a random number using the MicroSoft Excel RAND function. The listing was ordered by ascending random number.  The first 600 people were assigned to the Intervention group 1  the second 600 to Intervention group 2  and the third 600 to the Intervention group 3</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/04/2001</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1818</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof. Graeme Young MD, FRACP</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bushel Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mr Stephen Cole</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Colorectal cancer population screening programs commonly suffer from poor participation. Therefore it is important to reduce as many barriers as possible. Some screening tests affect participation, this is associated with level of technology. As screening most effective when conducted regularly, it is important to determine the impact of the initial screening experience on participation in further rounds. 
This study determined the impact of the level of technology of the test used in the first round of offers on participation in a second round where all people were offered the test that elicited the highest participation in the first round (ie the 'preferred' test. 
In the first round there were 3 groups each offered sceening using a different test. Intervention group 1 used Hemoccult II Sensa, a low technology guaiac based test requiring restricted diet for 6 days, sampling stool by spatula and 6 applications of stool to collection device, Intervention group 2 used FlexSure OBT, a mid level technology immunochemical test without restricted diet, sampling stool by spatula, 3 applications of stool to collection device, Intervention group 3 used InSure OBT, high level technology- immunochemical test, without diet, sampling stool by brush, 2 applications of stool sample. Intervention group 3 (InSure) returned the highest participation and was thus considered the preferred test. All people received Insure in the second round of offers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Repatriation General Hospital Daw Park</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Daws Rd, Daw Park, SA 5041</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Stephen Cole</name>
      <address>Bowel Health Service
Repatriation General Hospital Daw Park
Daws Road
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751838 </phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82751083</fax>
      <email>scoles@rgh.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Alicia Smith</name>
      <address>Bowel Health Service
Repatriation General Hospital Daw Park
Daws Rd
Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751075</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 02751083</fax>
      <email>alicia.smith@rgh.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>