<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373311">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001174370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Use of parental stem cells for children requiring a bone marrow transplant</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>TCR a+ß+/CD19+ cell depleted haploidentical donor stem cell transplantation for paediatric patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1199-3727 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>Paßlo (Paediatric aß haploidentical transplantation)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Haematological malignancy
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Bone marrow failure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Primary immunodeficiency</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Inherited metabolic disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Leukaemia &amp; Lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Other</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1 - Group receiving investigational device
Patients will receive a TCR a+ß+/CD19+ cell depleted graft from a haploidentical parental donor. Candidates will only be eligible for Arm 1 of the study if there are no suitable human leucocyte antigen (HLA) matched readily available donors, and no suitably matched umbilical cord blood units available.

Conditioning therapy used will be dependent on HSCT indication. GVHD prophylaxis will include in vivo serotherapy (ATG) (once daily IV dose of 2.5mg/kg for 3 days) and mycophenolate mofetil in non-malignant patients (15mg/kg 3 times a day -2 to day +30, given initially IV with an option to switch to orally dependent on patient tolerability).

Donor product will be peripheral blood stem cells collected via G-CSF stimulated apheresis. Apheresis will be performed as per FACT guidelines, national standards and individual institution protocols. All donor products will be processed in FACT accredited Bone Marrow Transplant laboratories. Fresh donor product will undergo TCR aß+ depletion and CD19+ depletion using Miltenyi CliniMACS® paramagnetic bead technology. The target CD34+ dose will be 10 x10^6/kg recipient weight, with a recommended minimal dose of 5 x 10^6/kg. 

Patients on Arm 1 will be assessed for neutrophil and platelet engraftment, transplant related mortality, graft versus host disease, relapse and overall survival. They will also be assessed for immune reconstitution, economic and quality of life outcomes. 

Arm 2  Control group
Candidates for Arm 2 will be patients undergoing alternate donor HSCT, defined as any donor that is not an HLA matched sibling (e.g., volunteer donor, matched umbilical cord blood units). 

Economic and Quality of Life outcomes will be measured for these patients post-transplant. </interventions>
    <comparator>HSCTs administered to the control group will not be a+ß+/CD19+ HSCTs. Patients will be undergoing alternate donor HSCT, defined as any donor that is not an HLA matched sibling (e.g., volunteer donor, matched umbilical cord blood units). 

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the incidence of donor derived neutrophil recovery post a+ß+/CD19+ HSCT (defined as an absolute neutrophil count &gt;500 x10^6/L for 3 consecutive days).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will undergo regular clinical assessment post HSCT as inpatients, and then be reviewed at a minimum of weekly in an outpatient setting for at least the first 100 days post transplant. 
The incidence of donor derived neutrophil recovery post a+ß+/CD19+ HSCT will be assessed at day 28 post transplant. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the cost of a+ß+/CD19+ HSCT compared to other alternate donor HSCT.

This aspect of the study will assess the equipment, personnel and time resources involved for the acquisition and delivery of a donor product. For each activity, eCRFs will be utilised to collect data from each participating site for each patient on the time and personnel involved in the relevant activity, as well as the quantities of any relevant consumables used (e.g. G-CSF for donor cell mobilisation).

This aspect of the study will also assess post-transplant health service utilisation, which will be based on two key aspects:
1) The use of hospital services. This will be assessed via the completion of an eCRF at study sites for inpatient hospital procedures, and will collect information on the timing and reason for each hospitalisation.
2) The use of medical and pharmaceutical services. For this purpose, patients (or parents/guardians) will be consented to access their Medicare data to allow for information on their medical service use (MBS) and pharmaceutical services (PBS). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. The initial 12 month within trial period 
2. Subsequent patient follow-up (up to five years post HSCT) 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the incidence of  platelet engraftment (defined as a platelet count &gt;20 x109/L for 7 consecutive days without requiring transfusion).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>To confirm platelet engraftment, patients will undergo regular clinical assessment post HSCT as inpatients, and then be reviewed at a minimum of weekly in an outpatient setting for at least the first 100 days post transplant.
 
The incidence of platelet engraftment will be assessed at 100 days post a+ß+/CD19+ HSCT.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The time to neutrophil and platelet engraftment in a+ß+/CD19+ HSCT will be evaluated by clinician definition and prospective data captured on the study database. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will undergo regular clinical assessment post HSCT as inpatients, and then be reviewed at a minimum of weekly in an outpatient setting for at least the first 100 days post transplant.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the incidence of graft versus host disease (GVHD) grade II-IV as per published criteria (1994 Consensus Conference on Acute GVHD Grading). </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 100 days days post a+ß+/CD19+ HSCT. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the incidence of graft versus host disease (GVHD) grade III-IV as per published criteria (National Institutes of Health consensus development project on criteria for clinical trials in chronic graft-versus-host disease). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 100 days post a+ß+/CD19+ HSCT. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine transplant related mortality post a+ß+/CD19+ HSCT by review of data captured on the study database. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 100 days and 365 days post a+ß+/CD19+ HSCT. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the overall survival post a+ß+/CD19+ HSCT.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 years post a+ß+/CD19+ HSCT.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate time to full immune reconstitution in a+ß+/CD19+ HSCT.

Immune reconstitution will be assessed by formal measurement of lymphocyte subsets, including TCR a+ß+ and TCR g+d+ cells. Immunoglobulin levels (IgG, IgM, IgA) will also be performed at the same time points. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 1 year and 2 years post HSCT.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Explore the pattern of chimerism post a+ß+/CD19+ HSCT (assessed by whole blood chimerism evaluation).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At day 30 post HSCT, and then further assessment at day 90, day 180, 1 year and 2 years post HSCT. Lineage specific chimerism, including myeloid, B cell, T cell and NK cell lineages will be performed from day 90 where possible. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life post HSCT will be assessed via the Paediatric Quality of Life (CHU9D) questionnaire and the Pediatric Quality of Life Inventory (cancer module). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires will be completed prior to transplant, at 3 months, 6 months, 12 months, and then annually until 5 years post transplant.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Carer burden post HSCT will be assessed via the Parent/Carer Impact Form (modified Work Productivity and Activity Impairment Questionnaire) (WPAI-GH) and the Care related Quality of Life (CarerQoL-7D) questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires will be completed prior to transplant, at 3 months, 6 months, 12 months, and then annually until 5 years post transplant.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>A patient must meet the following criteria to be eligible for inclusion of Arm 1 of the study:
 Aged between 3 months and 18 years
 The availability of a HLA matched haploidentical donor greater or equal to 5/10
 Absence of readily available matched sibling donor
 Absence of other readily available non-related donors:
                - Unrelated volunteer donors; HLA match less than 9/10
                - UCB units with adequate cell dose; HLA match less than 5/6 on low resolution typing or HLA match less than 6/8 on high resolution typing (8/8 HLA match for non malignant patients)
 Adequate organ function
 Female patients of child bearing age are not pregnant
 Written consent of the patients legal guardian, and assent from the patient if age appropriate

All potential parent donors must undergo high resolution HLA typing, and assessment as to their fitness to undergo peripheral blood stem cell collection via G-CSF stimulated apheresis. 

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria> Patient has undergone HSCT within the last 180 days
 Evidence of HIV infection
 Current uncontrolled bacterial or fungal infection
 The treatment protocol in part or in its entirety is declined by either the patient or their legal guardian
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>94</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2024</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sydney Children's Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>The Children's Hospital at Westmead - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Kids Oncology And Leukaemia TriAls (KOALA)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kids Cancer Centre,
Sydney Childrens Hospital,
High Street,
Randwick, NSW Australia 2031
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian and New Zealand Children's Haematology/Oncology Group (ANZCHOG)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>ANZCHOG Concept Validation Scheme
Hudson Institute
27-31 Wright Street
Clayton, VIC 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Miltenyi Biotech</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Miltenyi Biotech GmbH
Friedrich-Ebert-Straße 68
51429 Bergisch Gladbach,
Germany



</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Germany</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Tour de Cure Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Tour de Cure Ltd. 
Suite 2 (Level 1), 
Building B, 
14 Rodborough Road,
Frenchs Forest NSW 2086

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Children's Cancer Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4, 
4 Freshwater Place, 
Southbank VIC 3006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this trial is to evaluate the efficacy of using parent donors for bone marrow transplants in children, using a particular processing method of the donor blood cells (TCR a+ß+/CD19+ cell depletion) compared to those receiving a standard bone marrow transplant from another donor, We also want to compare cost to the health system of TCR a+ß+/CD19+ cell depletion with that of standard bone marrow transplant procedures, 

Who is it for?
Patients may be eligible to enrol in this trial if they are aged 3 months to 18 years of age, have been diagnosed with haematological malignancies or non malignant disorders requiring a bone marrow transplant, and have an eligible parent donor. 

Study details
Patients who have no fully matched brothers or sisters, and no well matched volunteer donors or umbilical cord blood units available will receive a TCR a+ß+/CD19+ cell depleted graft from a parent donor. Control patients will receive a standard bone marrow transplant from another donor (e.g., volunteer donor) as per institutional practice. 

Patients will undergo clinical assessments at regular intervals for two years following the transplant to evaluate the efficacy of the treatment. Further information, such as quality of life and carer burden, will be collected for up to 5 years following the transplant. 

It is hoped that the findings from this trial will provide information on whether parent donor cells undergoing specialised cell processing can be effectively used for bone marrow transplants in children with haematological malignancies or non malignant disorders.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children’s Health Queensland Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00175)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/06/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/17/QRCH/48</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Mitchell</name>
      <address>Kids Cancer Centre
Level 1, Sydney Children's Hospital
High St, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+612 9382 1690</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.mitchell@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Emma McCormack</name>
      <address>Kids Cancer Centre
Level 1, Sydney Children's Hospital
High St, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+612 9382 3102</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>emma.mccormack@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Mitchell</name>
      <address>Kids Cancer Centre
Level 1, Sydney Children's Hospital
High St, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+612 9382 1690</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.mitchell@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Emma McCormack</name>
      <address>Kids Cancer Centre
Level 1, Sydney Children's Hospital
High St, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+612 9382 3102</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>emma.mccormack@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>