<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362038">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/12/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000001796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Finding My Way: A randomised controlled trial of an online self-help coping program for reducing cancer distress.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing the efficacy of 'Finding My Way' with an information-control in reducing distress for patients with early stage cancer.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>FMW</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Psychological distress</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>'Finding My Way' (FMW) is a 6-week multimedia internet application, where a new module is released to participants each week, with a reminder email to use the program. The frequency in which participants will access these modules will be at the participants' discretion. Modules cover a range of commonly experienced psychosocial issues. Each module of FMW is comprised of three main components: psycho-education, cognitive-behavioural worksheets / strategies, and survivor stories and quotes. An online journal-blog and a resource section is available throughout the duration of the program. </interventions>
    <comparator>An online information-only version of Finding My Way will be simultaneously developed to provide an appropriate attention control for the study. The control condition covers the same 6 module topics, but has no interactive features(i.e., no worksheets, activities, relaxation exercises, or journal-blog). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Negative affect: the total scale score of the Depression, Anxiety, Stress Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, then 3 and 6 months after treatment-completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Traumatic stress: the total scale score of the Post-Traumatic Stress Scale - Self Report. This scale measures cancer-specific distress.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, then 3 and 6 months after treatment-completion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Coping: Helplessness Hopelessness as measured by the mini-MAC</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, then 3 and 6 months after treatment-completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Coping: Anxious Preoccupation as measured by the mini-MAC</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, then 3 and 6 months after treatment-completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Coping: Cognitive Avoidance as measured by the mini-MAC</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, then 3 and 6 months after treatment-completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Coping: Fatalism as measured by the mini-MAC</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, then 3 and 6 months after treatment-completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Coping: Fighting Spirit as measured by the mini-MAC</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, then 3 and 6 months after treatment-completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health Related Quality of Life (QOL): Total QOL 

as measured by the European Organisation for Research on the Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Qustionaire Cancer-30 item scale (QLQ-C30).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, then 3 and 6 months after treatment-completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>QOL: Role functioning, as measured by the EORTC QLQ-C30</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, then 3 and 6 months after treatment-completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>QOL: Physical functioning, as measured by the EORTC QLQ-C30</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, then 3 and 6 months after treatment-completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>QOL: Emotional functioning, as measured by the EORTC QLQ-C30</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, then 3 and 6 months after treatment-completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>QOL: Cognitive functioning, as measured by the EORTC QLQ-C30</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, then 3 and 6 months after treatment-completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>QOL: Social functioning, as measured by the EORTC QLQ-C30</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment, then 3 and 6 months after treatment-completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Cancer being treated with curative intent (e.g., breast, prostate, colorectal, testicular, lymphomas, haematologic or gynaecologic malignancies)
2. Currently receiving active cancer treatment (surgery, chemotherapy, radiotherapy)
3. Age 18 years or over
4. Sufficient English language literacy
5. Access to the internet (home or work)
6. Provide an active email address and phone number</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Diagnosis of advanced cancer
(While advanced cancer patients will not be targeted for recruitment, this is a population that asks for interventions and may self-refer to the program. Therefore individuals who specifically request to participate will be enrolled, but not included in primary analyses. If a large enough sub-sample self-refers to the program, a sub-analysis will be conducted.)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The allocation is concealed until interventions are assigned: This process will be automated within the website, therefore it is central randomisation by computer. </concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation with stratification: A computer sequence generation algorithm in blocks to either ‘intervention’ or ‘attention control’, and each condition is assigned in random order within the block. The stratification variable is 'gender' - to ensure balance across conditions within gender.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>n/a</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>17/11/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>188</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>191</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>26/06/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,QLD,SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5042</postcode>
    <postcode>3181</postcode>
    <postcode>3002</postcode>
    <postcode>3050</postcode>
    <postcode>4001</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Flinders University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide
SA, 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The internet is increasingly utilised by people with cancer to obtain information and support. However, to date no randomised controlled study has evaluated the effectiveness of a structured online self-help therapeutic program. Therefore, the present study aims to examine how helpful 'Finding My Way' is, an interactive online 6-week self-help coping program, compared to receiving online information only, in improving distress, coping and quality of life after cancer diagnosis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.findingmyway.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>TRIAL-RELATED PUBLICATIONS
1. Beatty, L., Koczwara, B., &amp; Wade, T. (2011). Cancer Coping Online: A pilot trial of a self-guided CBT internet intervention for cancer-related distress. Electronic Journal of Applied Psychology, 7, 17-25.
2. Beatty, L., Kemp, E., Wade, T., &amp; Koczwara, B. (2015). Finding My Way: protocol of a randomised controlled trial evaluating an internet self-help program for cancer-related distress. BMC Cancer, 15, 328. DOI: 10.1186/s12885-015-1322-x.
3. Beatty, L., Koczwara, B., &amp; Wade, T. (2016). Evaluating the efficacy of a self-guided web-based CBT intervention for reducing cancer-distress: A pilot randomised controlled trial. Journal of Supportive Care in Cancer, 24, 1043-1051. DOI: 10.1007/s00520-015-2867-6. 
4. Beatty, L., Kemp, E., Binnion, C., Turner, J., Milne, D., Butow, P., Lambert, S., Yates, P., Yip, D., &amp; Koczwara, B. (in submission, Oct 2016). Uptake and adherence to an online intervention for cancer-related distress: older age is not a barrier to adherence but may be a barrier to uptake. Journal of Supportive Care in Cancer.
5. Beatty, L., Binnion, C., Kemp, E., &amp; Koczwara, B., (in submission, Oct 2016). A qualitative exploration of barriers and facilitators to adherence to an online self-help intervention for cancer-related distress. Journal of Supportive Care in Cancer.
PRESENTATIONS
1. Beatty, L., Koczwara, B., &amp; Wade, T. (2012, November). iCanCope: the internet Cancer Coping guide  a preliminary evaluation of an online self-directed intervention for reducing distress in early stage cancer patients. International Psycho-Oncology Society (IPOS) 14th World Congress. November 13-15, Brisbane, Australia.
2.	Binnion C., Beatty L., Kemp E., &amp; Koczwara B. (2015, February). 'Finding My Way: An interim analysis of predictors of adherence to an internet self-help program for cancer-related distress. Flinders Centre for Innovation in Cancer 2015 Survivorship Conference, Adelaide, Australia.
3.	Beatty L., Kemp E., Wade T., Katris P., Wootten A., Yip D., Lambert S., Turner J., Yates P., Butow P., &amp; Koczwara B.  (2014, November). Finding My Way: preliminary findings from a RCT evaluating an internet self-help program for cancer-related distress. Clinical Oncology Society of Australia, 41st Annual Scientific Meeting, Melbourne, Australia
4.	Beatty, L. (2016). Symposium Chair and presenter. Symposium: Online psychological interventions for cancer-related distress.  Presentation: who uses, and how do they benefit from, online psychotherapuetic interventions for cancer-related distress? An outcomes analysis of Finding My Way. International Congress of Behavioral Medicine. December 7-10, Melbourne, Australia.
5.	INVITED SPEAKER: Beatty L. (2016). Finding My Way: A Web-Based Psychosocial Intervention For Cancer Related Distress - An Outcomes Analysis Of A Multicentre RCT. Clinical Oncology Society of Australias 43rd Annual Scientific Meeting. November 15-17, Gold Coast, Australia.
6.	INVITED SPEAKER:  Beatty L. (2016). Online self-directed psychosocial interventions for cancer-related distress.  Multinational Assocation for Supportive Care in Cancer Annual Scientific Meeting. June 23-25, Adelaide, Australia.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Petrina Kasperski, Executive Officer 
The Flats, G5 - Rooms 3 and 4
Flinders Drive
Flinders Medical Centre
Bedford Park SA 5042
email: research.ethics@health.sa.gov.au</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/10/0372</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa Beatty</name>
      <address>School of Psychology,
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide, SA, 5001</address>
      <phone>+61882012506</phone>
      <fax>+61882013877</fax>
      <email>lisa.beatty@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa Beatty</name>
      <address>School of Psychology,
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide, SA, 5001</address>
      <phone>+61882012506</phone>
      <fax>+61882013877</fax>
      <email>lisa.beatty@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa Beatty</name>
      <address>School of Psychology,
Flinders University
GPO Box 2100
Adelaide, SA, 5001</address>
      <phone>+61882012506</phone>
      <fax>+61882013877</fax>
      <email>lisa.beatty@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>