<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362312">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/05/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000524897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Trial of Polyethylene Glycol (PEG) Hydrogel to Reduce Rectal Radiation Dose During Radiotherapy for Prostate Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Feasibility of Using Polyethylene Glycol Hydrogel to Increase Prostate-Rectum Separation and Its Impact on Rectal Dose During Radiation Therapy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Rectal toxicity during prostate radiotherapy (brachytherapy and/or external beam radiotherapy)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Single transperineal injection of polyethylene glycol (10-15ml) in the space posterior to Denonvillier's fascia, and anterior to the rectum, under general anaesthetic. Measurement of prostate-rectum separation, and rectal radiation dose in the presence of the polyethylene glycol spacer. There are four patients groups who wo will be considered for the study (2 prostate seed brachytherapy groups, a high dose rate brachytherapy group, and an external beam radiotherapy group). All four patient groups will receive the same intervention as part of te study (PEG hydrogel insertion and measurement of prostate-rectum separation and rectal radiation dose). The type of radiotherapy they receive will be tailored to their disease and own circumstances and is independent of their participation in the study.</interventions>
    <comparator>Historical controls from prostate cancer database from 2005-2010, as well as dose comparison in seed brachytherapy patients before and after spacer injection (the rectal dose before spacer will be different for each patient, but an acceptable rectal radiation dose is less than 2 cubic centimetres of rectum should receive the prescribed radiation dose of 145 Gray).</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of PEG Hydrogel in increasing prostate-Rectum separation and improving rectal dosimetry in prostate brachytherapy and/or external beam radiotherapy patients. Rectal radiation dose data will be collected from radiotherapy planning software used to plan the patients' radiation treatment, and recorded onto paper forms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once after patient has undergone radiotherapy planning, and again 4 weeks after spacer insertion (not continuous).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of transperineal PEG Hydrogel injection. Clinician assessment of rectal, urinary, or other toxicity associated with the procedure will be undertaken on day 0-1 and at 4-6 weeks using CTCAE v4.0 and recorded onto paper forms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0-1, 4-6 weeks (once only at each of these timepoints).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rectal toxicity following prostate brachytherapy and/or external beam radiotherapy in the setting of PEG hydrogel. Clinician assessment of rectal, urinary, or other toxicity associated with the procedure will be undertaken on day 0-1 and at 4-6 weeks using CTCAE v4.0 and recorded onto paper forms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 0-1, 4-6 weeks (once only at each of these timepoints)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stability of PEG Hydrogel and durability of prostate-rectum separation. A CT will be undertaken to measure prostate-rectum separation 4-6 weeks after spacer insertion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4-6 weeks (once only at this timepoint)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life following prostate brachytherapy and/or external beam radiotherapy in the setting of PEG hydrogel. This will be assessed with baseline, 4-6 week, 6 and twelve month patient self-administered questionnaires (EORTC QLQC30 and PR25 and the Expanded Prostate Cancer Index Composite Bowel Assessment).</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 4-6 weeks, 6 months, and 12 months (once only at each of these timepoints)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Histopathologically confirmed, localised prostate cancer, fit for prostate brachytherapy or dose escalated external beam radiotherapy with iducial marker localisation, fit for general anaesthetic. No prior history of bleeding disorder, prior transurethral resection of the prostate (TURP), transurethral incision of the prostate (TUIP), bladder neck resection, perirectal/perianal abscess, rectal/anal fissure. No prior history of prostate or pelvic radiotherapy. Able to provide written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous history of bleeding disorder, prior TURP, TUIP, bladder neck resection, perirectal/perianal abscess, rectal/anal fissure. Prior history of prostate or pelvic radiotherapy. Unfit for general anaesthetic. Unable to provide written informed consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a single arm study. Patients who are referred for consideration of prostate brachytherapy and or external beam radiotherapy who satisfy the study's eligibility criteria will be approached for recruitment. Allocation concealment will not be undertaken.</concealment>
    <sequence>non-randomised.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Patients will be allocated to 4 subgroups based on the type of prostate radiotherapy they will be undergoing (high dose rate brachytherapy group, 2 seed brachytherapy groups, and 1 external beam radiotherapy group). All of these patients however, will receive the same trial intervention (the PEG hydrogel).</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St George Hospital Cancer Care Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1 Short Street, Kogarah
NSW 2217</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Special Purposes and Trust Fund of A/Prof Graham and Associates</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>St George Hospital Cancer Care Centre
1 Short Street, Kogarah
NSW 2217</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>MD Solutions Australasia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>40A Mason Street Newport
Victoria 3015</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study will be assessing whether rectal side effects from radiation treatment can be reduced, by using a spacing agent between the rectum and prostate gland. The agent is a gel, which is injected in the space between the prostate gland and rectum, in order to increase separation between these two structures. The idea is that the rectal radiation dose and hence side effects, will be reduced by the increased separation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District (NHN) HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Office G71,
East Wing Edmund Blacket Building
Prince Of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>1/12/0038</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/03/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nadine Beydoun</name>
      <address>St George Hospital Cancer Care Centre
1 Short Street Kogarah
NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9113 3909</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9113 3958</fax>
      <email>nadine.beydoun@sesiahs.health.nw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nadine Beydoun</name>
      <address>St George Hospital Cancer Care Centre
1 Short Street Kogarah
NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9113 3909</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9113 3958</fax>
      <email>nadine.beydoun@sesiahs.health.nw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>