<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364738">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000633684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Experiences of genitourinary symptoms in postmenopausal women receiving hormonal therapy for early stage breast cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>PEGASUS - Prevalence and severity of genitourinary symptoms in postmenopausal women receiving adjuvant endocrine therapy for early stage breast cancer and impact on sexual function and quality of life: A prospective study
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PEGASUS </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>genitourinary symptoms</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>endocrine therapy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>sexual dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>quality of life</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>PEGASUS is a multi-centre prospective study looking at the potential impact of adjuvant endocrine therapy on genitourinary symptoms in postmenopausal women who are about to commence either tamoxifen (TAM) or aromatase inhibitors (AIs) and then follow their trajectory over time (up to 2 years). It is a questionnaire-based study and as such, women will be asked to complete self-administered questionnaires at baseline (prior to the commencement of endocrine therapy), and  6-, 12- and 24-month follow-ups. </interventions>
    <comparator>We are comparing baseline symptoms (when no adjuvant endocrine therapy is being taken) versus overtime symptoms (when endocrine therapy is being received). In addition, we are comparing symptoms between different types of endocrine therapy (i.e tamoxifen versus aromatase Inhibitors).</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1/2 standard deviation in mean International Consultation on Incontinence Questionnaire on Female Lower Urinary Tract Symptom (ICIQ-FLUTS) sub-domain scores that corresponds to a difference in severity of 1 level on a single question in the ICIQ-FLUTS questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6, 12 and 24 months after baseline.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean International Consultation on Incontinence Questionnaire on Vaginal Symptoms (ICIQ-VS) score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6, 12 and 24 months after baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain intensity during intercourse using Visual Analogue Scale Pain Assessment of Dyspareunia (VAS-DYSPAR)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6, 12 and 24 months after baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sexual function associated with urinary symptoms using the Pelvic Organ Prolapse/Urinary Incontinence Sexual Questionnaire (PISQ-12) short form</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6, 12 and 24 months after baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective hormone-related symptoms using the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - Endocrine Symptoms (FACT-ES) subscale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6, 12 and 24 months after baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General quality of life using the EQ-5D a short generic health-related quality of life instrument that consists of two parts: a self-classifier and a Visual Analogue Scale (EQ VAS). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6, 12 and 24 months after baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible participants for this study will include postmenopausal  women at diagnosis, with early stage breast cancer and hormone receptor-positive tumours, prior to starting adjuvant endocrine therapy (TAM or AIs), are between 18 and 75 years inclusive and are sufficiently competent in English to be able to complete questionnaires written in English. 

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria will include women with locally recurrent cancer or metastatic disease, current use of hormonal replacement therapy (including vaginal oestrogen) and lack of fluency in English as study participation will involve the completion of self-administered questionnaires. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>This project is powered to detect a relatively small difference in the prevalence of genitourinary symptoms in postmenopausal women taking TAM and those taking AIs as adjuvant endocrine therapy for breast cancer. Urinary symptoms will be assessed by the ICIQ-FLUTS. We defined a clinically meaningful difference in ICIQ-FLUTS sub-domain scores as 1/2 standard deviation that corresponded to a difference in severity of 1 level on a single question in the questionnaire. Sample size calculations were performed utilising a 2 group comparison of the difference in mean ICIQ-FLUTS' scores between the two treatment groups (tamoxifen versus aromatase inhibitors). We determined that 210 and 70 patients who have been on aromatase inhibitors and tamoxifen respectively will be needed for a two-sided  alpha error of 0.05 and a power 80%. A total of 280 postmenopausal women with oestrogen receptor positive breast cancer will be recruited to the study. Data will be analysed using SPSS 21.0 (Statistical Program for the Social Sciences). Bivariate associations between the outcome variable and possible confounders will first be examined, using Kendalls rank correlation or Pearsons product correlation coefficient, as appropriate, for continuous variables, using t-tests of Mann-Whitney U tests, as appropriate, where one variable is continuous and the other is binary, and using chi-squared tests where both outcome and predictor variable are binary. Bivariate analyses will be followed by repeated measures multilevel or hierarchical linear or logistic regressions (depending on the outcome of tests for normality) with time as the repeated measures factor. The outcome variable will be dichotomized if its distribution is too far from normal. If the data suggest a need to adjust for confounding variables (such as age, BMI, parity, smoking) or include moderating variables (e.g. group status), these will be included as covariates and/or interaction terms. The regression analyses will be undertaken using multilevel (or hierarchal) modelling, which is tolerant of missing data, in that one missing observation does not mean that the whole case is lost.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>280</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>UNSW Australia, High Street, Kensington, NSW 2052 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>None</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>None</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is investigating the prevalence and severity of genitourinary symptoms in postmenopausal women receiving adjuvant endocrine therapy for early stage breast cancer and the impact on sexual function and quality of life.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to joint this study if you are a postmenopausal female, aged 18 -75 years, with early stage breast cancer and hormone receptor-positive tumours, for which you are about to commence adjuvant endocrine therapy with either tamoxifen (TAM) or aromatase inhibitors (AIs). You will need to be sufficiently competent in English in order to complete the study questionnaires.

Study details
All participants in this study are asked to complete self-administered questionnaires at baseline (prior to starting endocrine therapy), and 6-, 12- and 24-month follow-ups. The standardised questionnaires used relate to genitourinary symptoms, sexual function and quality of life.

The findings from this study could be used to identify patients at risk of developing genitourinary symptoms and also to offer appropriate interventions early to prevent and ameliorate such symptoms which are likely to have a negative impact on quality of life and may contribute to a low compliance with treatment. We believe that this study has the potential to document the extent and impact of genitourinary symptoms in breast cancer survivors about to start adjuvant endocrine therapy and what happens over time. It will also lead to intervention studies in the future.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mariana Sousa</name>
      <address>Psychosocial Research Group
Level4, C25 Lowy Cancer Research Centre
UNSW Australia, Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+610299850024</phone>
      <fax>+610299850033</fax>
      <email>m.desouzaesousa@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mariana Sousa</name>
      <address>Psychosocial Research Group
Level4, C25 Lowy Cancer Research Centre
UNSW Australia, Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+610299850024</phone>
      <fax>+610299850033</fax>
      <email>m.desouzaesousa@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mariana Sousa</name>
      <address>Psychosocial Research Group
Level4, C25 Lowy Cancer Research Centre
UNSW Australia, Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+610299850024</phone>
      <fax>+610299850033</fax>
      <email>m.desouzaesousa@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mariana Sousa</name>
      <address>Psychosocial Research Group
Level4, C25 Lowy Cancer Research Centre
UNSW Australia, Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+610299850024</phone>
      <fax>+610299850033</fax>
      <email>m.desouzaesousa@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>