<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363741">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000337774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot Study of partially Human Leucocyte Antigen (HLA)-mismatched stem cell infusions after chemotherapy for acute myeloid leukaemia in patients over the age of 60.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot Study of partially Human Leucocyte Antigen (HLA)-mismatched stem cell infusions after chemotherapy for acute myeloid leukaemia in patients over the age of 60: an evaluation of incidence of Graft vs Host Disease and treatment related mortality. 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>
    </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Myeloid Leukaemia &gt; 60 yrs</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Acute leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Infusion of Granulocyte Colony Stimulating Factor (G-CSF) mobilised Peripheral Blood Stem Cells (PBSCs) from a partially HLA-mismatched relative after standard induction and consolidation chemotherapy for patient with Acute Myeloid Leukaemia greater than 60 yrs of age.
PBSCs will be harvested by apheresis from the donor on day 9 (of induction chemotherapy for the patient) after administration of GCSF to the donor(10 micrograms/kg subcutaneously daily from days 5 to 8). The minimum stipulated CD34 positive cell dose will be greater than 0.5 x 10^6/kg. The total collection will be divided into 4 aliquots: 3 portions will be cryopreserved for later use and one portion will be infused into patient on the day of collection (day 9).
Induction therapy will consist of 7+3 regimen with continuous Cytarabine (150mg/m2) intravenous infusion for 7 days and Mitoxantrone (10mg/m2) intravenously daily for 3 days, followed by intravenous infusion of GCSF mobilised PBSCs on day 9. Bone marrow biopsy will be performed by day 28 +/- 7 days and if complete remission is confirmed patients will proceed with consolidation chemotherapy. If patient is not in morphologic complete remission then a further cycle of induction followed by PBSC infusion is offered.
If the patient is in remission following induction, 2 cycles of consolidation chemotherapy, comprising the 5 + 2 regimen (Mitoxantrone 10mg/m2 IV days 1 to 2 and Cytarabine 150mg/m2 continuous IV infusion days 1 to 5) will be delivered and each cycle will be followed by IV infusion of PBSCs, 36 to 48 hours after chemotherapy has been disconnected.
All of the above treatments are part of the study intervention.</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cumulative incidence of Graft vs Host Disease assessed clinically every week during treatment phase and then at study time points (every third month for two years).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 21 and 24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment Related Mortality defined as death in remission or related to the treatment, including PBSC infusion.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of complete remission (CR) following induction chemotherapy assessed using morphological assessment of bone marrow aspirate and defined as less than 5% blasts. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>assessed at Day 28 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to neutrophil and Platelet recovery following chemotherapy assessed using daily full blood counts.</outcome>
      <timepoint>post each treatment cycle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of blood products infused by collecting records of packed red blood cell and platelet transfusions for each patient.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28 of each treatment cycle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severe infection rate following induction chemotherapy assessed clinically and with microbiological, radiological investigations during patient care.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of first remission, defined as time from achieving Complete Remission to Relapse (diagnosed clinically, with a full blood count and bone marrow biopsy), Death from other causes or end of followup.</outcome>
      <timepoint>year 1 and year 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall and leukaemia free survival. Overall Survival is defined as time to death and Leukaemia free survival is defined as time from achieving CR to relapse or death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>year 1 and Year 2</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of detectable donor chimerism measured using DNA Short Tandem Repeat (STR) based testing on bone marrow samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28 of each treatment cycle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients aged over 60 with previously untreated AML undergoing induction chemotherapy, who have an available partially HLA-mismatched donor</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patient with Acute Promyelocytic Leukaemia, Chronic Myeloid Leukaemia or unfit for induction chemotherapy or have immunodeficiency (apart from neutropenia)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients over the age of 60 years presenting with previously untreated AML. Patients with Acute Promyelocytic Leukaemia (APmL) or Chronic Myeloid Leukaemia in Blast Crisis (CML-BC) will not be eligible as there are specific targeted therapies for these conditions. The intended donor is a partially HLA-mismatched relative defined as HLA-haploidentity at HLA-A, -B, -C, and –DRB1. In most cases this would mean a biological child, although siblings and grandchildren also have a 50% chance of HLA-haploidentity. Donors must fulfill eligibility criteria as per standards published by BMT Network NSW. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/11/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/11/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>10/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>8/04/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>4</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2015</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis>No data analysis planned</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to determine the effect of partially HLA-mismatched stem cell infusions after chemotherapy for acute myeloid leukaemia in older patients. 
Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged between 60-85 years and have been diagnosed with acute myeloid leukaemia (AML) which has been previously untreated. You should be undergoing induction chemotherapy and have an available partially HLA-mismatched donor. 
Trial details: All participants in this trial will undergo standard induction chemotherapy. Peripheral blood stem cells (PBSCs) will be collected from the available donor, then harvested and administered to the patient on day 9 of induction chemotherapy by intravenous infusion (i.e. directly into the vein). On day 28 a bone marrow biopsy will be performed, and if complete remission is confirmed then patients will proceed with two cycles of consolidation chemotherapy. If the patient is not in complete remission then a further cycle of induction chemotherapy followed by PBSC infusion is offered. Participants will be regularly assessed for up to 24 months in order to determine clinical efficacy and safety of the treatment. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>nil publications, </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/SVH/141</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/05/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sam Milliken</name>
      <address>Kinghorn Cancer Centre
St Vincent's Hospital, sydney
370 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>61 2 9355 5656</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9355 5735</fax>
      <email>SVHCancer_research@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Patricia Plenge</name>
      <address>Kinghorn Cancer Centre
St Vincent's Hospital, sydney
370 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>61 2 9355 5613</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9355 5735</fax>
      <email>SVHCancer_research@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sam Milliken</name>
      <address>Kinghorn Cancer Centre
St Vincent's Hospital, sydney
370 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>61 2 9355 5656</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9355 5735</fax>
      <email>SVHCancer_research@stvincents.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>