<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367687">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/02/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000083594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Sexual Well Being After Breast cancer study - SWAB study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy and safety of intra-vaginal testosterone for the treatment of vulvo-vaginal atrophy (VVA) associated with aromatase inhibitor therapy in women with breast cancer.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Vulvovaginal Atrophy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Menstruation and menopause</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>300mcg intravaginal testosterone cream will be compounded  in the Professional Compounding Centers of America brand Versabase Cream as the base. Application dosing is nightly for 2 weeks then nightly three times a week for 24 weeks. Compliance to treatment will be the use of at least 75% of the medication in each 13 week period ( assessed by weight)
</interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo cream will be the  Professional Compounding Centers of America brand Versabase Cream</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of the efficacy of intravaginal testosterone therapy, for the treatment of sexual dysfunction due to vulvo vaginal atrophy in women who have symptoms estrogen insufficiency having treatment of breast cancer with an aromatase inhibitor (AI) as assessed by the satisfaction domain of the Female Sexual Function Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment  of sexual wellbeing as assessed by
a)	the total score of the Female Sexual Function Index ( FSFI)
b)	the subdomains of desire, arousal, orgasm, satisfaction and sexual pain 
c)	distress associated with female sexual dysfunction  measured by the Female Sexual Distress Scale- revised ( FSDS-R) 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Indices of vaginal health as assessed by: a)	Atrophic vaginitis assessed by clinical examination b) Change in vaginal pH  c)	Change in the proportion of vaginal parabasal and superficial cells d)the Profile of Female Sexual Function (PFSP) questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The presence of urinary incontinence as assessed by the Questionnaire for Urinary Incontinence Diagnosis (QUID)</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The circulating levels of  Estradiol, Estrone, Testosterone, Dihydrotestosterone and their metabolites by liquid chromatography mass spectrometry (LCMS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women:
1.	Who are aged over 18 years with invasive breast cancer treated with an AI 
2.	Who are experiencing at least one symptom of vaginal dryness, itch causing pain with sexual activity for which they seek treatment.
3.	Have less than 5% superficial cells on vaginal smear 
4.	Have a vaginal pH above 5
5.	Have a clinically acceptable Papanicolaou smear (no evidence of malignancy or squamous intraepithelial lesions) within the past 2 years if the cervix is present
6.	Have a clinically acceptable mammogram if 50 years or older as per the management of their breast specialist (oncologist or surgeon).
7.	who are able and willing to participate in the study as evidenced by providing written consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women who have:

a)	undiagnosed genital bleeding
b)	used vaginal hormonal products (rings, creams, or gels) in the past month
c)	sexual dysfunction caused by another medical condition 
d)	used systemic sex steroid therapy (estrogen, testosterone, tibolone or dehydroepiandrosterone) in the preceding 6 months. 
e)	renal disease, history of cerebrovascular disease, thrombo-embolic disorders, myocardial infarction or angina at any time before study entry or thrombo-phlebitis within the last 5 years, or any other major illness that has occurred within the last 6 months.
f)	hypertension equal to or above 160/95 mm Hg
g)	Significant gastrointestinal, liver or gall bladder disease
h)	a condition known to affect steroid metabolism or taken therapy known to affect steroid metabolism other than the AI therapy for breast cancer  (eg, clomiphene, testolactone, ketoconazole, spironolactone, histamine 2 [Histamine 2 receptor blockers, etc.])
i)	a previous diagnosis of cancer, except non melanotic skin cancer
j)	moderate to severe acne or hirsutism, have used anti-androgen therapy for acne or hirsutism in the preceding 5 years, or  who have androgenic alopecia (we will exclude women with clinically meaningful androgen excess)
k)	have a history of, or current evidence of, abuse of alcohol or any drug substance or be a regular drinker of more than 3 standard drinks per day
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited through oncologists, breast specialists and the Breast Cancer Network of Australia. They will beinvited to contact the Women’s Health Research Program (WHRP).  If eligible to participate they will attend the WHRP for 4 visits.

Each participant will be given a unique two-digit participant screening number in sequential ascending order at the Screening visit.  Participants will receive these numbers in the order in which they enter the study and they will retain this number throughout their participation in the study. 

Participants who meet inclusion/exclusion criteria will be assigned a Randomization Number.   The randomization code will be generated independently by the Department of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine, Monash University and randomization and packaging will be undertaken by the compounding pharmacy in the Alfred Hospital, Melbourne.
The participant will receive study drug with their unique Randomization number. 

Treatment randomization will occur 4-6 weeks after screening.

All investigators and clinical staff will remain blinded to allocation of therapy until the statistical data base is cleaned and locked.

</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne 3004
VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne 3004
VIC 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will determine the effectiveness of intravaginal testosterone cream therapy for the treatment of sexual dysfunction due to Genitourinary Syndrome of Menopause (GSM) in women with breast cancer being treated with an aromatase inhibitor (AI). Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above, have been diagnosed with invasive breast cancer, currently being treated with an AI and experiencing at least one symptom of vaginal dryness, itch, or pain with sexual activity for which you are seeking treatment Study details -participants in this study are randomly allocated (by chance) to one of two groups. Participants in one group will apply the intravaginal testosterone cream, whilst participants in the other group will apply the intravaginal placebo cream. Both groups will apply the creams nightly for the first two weeks and then nightly 3 times a week for the remaining 24 weeks. Circulating levels of hormones will be checked before, during and at the end of the treatment period and participants will be asked to answer questionnaires related to sexual function.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress> Human Ethics Office
First Floor, Building 3e
Room 111
Monash Research Office
Clayton Campus
Monash University VIC 3800

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/02/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014002067</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/01/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Susan Davis</name>
      <address>Women's Health Research Program Monash University Level 6, The Alfred
Centre 99 Commercial Rd Melbourne Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0827</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9903 0828</fax>
      <email>susan.davis@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Susan Davis</name>
      <address>Women's Health Research Program Monash University Level 6, The Alfred
Centre 99 Commercial Rd Melbourne Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0827</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9903 0828</fax>
      <email>susan.davis@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Susan Davis</name>
      <address>Women's Health Research Program Monash University Level 6, The Alfred
Centre 99 Commercial Rd Melbourne Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0827</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9903 0828</fax>
      <email>susan.davis@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Susan Davis</name>
      <address>Women's Health Research Program Monash University Level 6, The Alfred
Centre 99 Commercial Rd Melbourne Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0827</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9903 0828</fax>
      <email>susan.davis@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>