<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="334989">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/01/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/01/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000086066</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Nambour Community-based Skin Cancer Prevention Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Community-based trial of daily versus usual sunscreen use and beta-carotene versus placebo supplements to prevent skin cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>basal cell carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>squamous cell carcinoma of the skin</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>solar keratoses</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>photoageing</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>cutaneous melanoma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>blood lipids as assessed by fasting blood tests </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Non melanoma skin cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>"Daily sunscreen, Beta-carotene supplements"
Daily sunscreen: (Sun Protection Factor (SPF) 15+, to be applied to head, neck, arms and hands every morning (and to reapply after heavy sweating, bathing, or long sun exposure), for 5 years. 

Beta-carotene supplements: 30mg once daily as oral capsule, for 5 years.

4 arms in trial viz. Arm 1: daily sunscreen, beta-carotene supplements Arm 2: daily sunscreen, placebo supplements Arm 3: beta-carotene supplements, discretionary sunscreen Arm 4: discretionary sunscreen, placebo supplements</interventions>
    <comparator>"discretionary sunscreen, placebo supplements"
Discretionary sunscreen for 5 years.
Placebo: microcellulose pills, once daily, orally, for 5 years</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>basal cell carcinoma (BCC) incidence: ascertained by clinical examination  and medical records; histologically-confirmed</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years after randomisation; 8 years after cessation of trial (or 13 years after randomisation)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) incidence: ascertained by clinical examination  and medical records; histologically-confirmed</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years after randomisation; 8 years after cessation of trial (or 13 years after randomisation)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>solar keratosis (SK) prevalence: SK clinically diagnosed by dermatologists</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>photogeing severity: assessed clinically and by microtopography using silicon casts of the back of the hand</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years after randomisation; 10 years after cessation of trial (or 15 years after randomisation)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>melanoma incidence: melanomas ascertained through medical records and cancer registry; histologically-confirmed and reviewed</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 years after cessation of trial (or 15 years after randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>blood lipids as assessed fasting blood test</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline for a random sample and at 5 years (end of trial) for majority of trial participants</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Registered on the  state electoral roll for Nambour in Nov 1986</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>76</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Lack of signed consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrolled by acceptance of letter of invitation. Allocation by central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/1992</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/02/1992</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/03/1992</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1850</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Adele Green</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>QIMR Berghofer Institute of Medical Research 
300 Herston Road, Herston QLD 4006
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council of Australia (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 9848
Canberra, ACT  2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Gail Williams</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Population Health
University of Queensland 
Herston Road 
Herston 
QLD 4006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A randomised trial was conducted to assess whether daily application of a sun protection factor (SPF) 15+ sunscreen to the head, neck, arms and hands, or beta-carotene supplementation (30 mg/day) would prevent skin cancers and related tumours and premature skin ageing in comparison with discretionary use of sunscreen or a daily placebo supplement. The The hypothesis was that regular sunscreen use by adult Caucasians prevents the occurrence of skin cancers and related sun-related degenerative skin conditions</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Green A, Battistutta D, Hart V, Leslie D, Marks G, Williams G, Gaffney P, Parsons P, Hirst L, Frost F, Orrell E, Durham K, Lang C, and the Nambour Prevention Study Group. Nambour Skin Cancer and Actinic Eye Disease Prevention Trial: design and baseline characteristics of Participants. Controlled Clin Trials 1994; 15: 512-22.

Ashton BA, Marks GC, Battistutta D, Green A. Under-reporting of energy intake in two methods of dietary assessment in the Nambour Trial. Aust J Nutr Diet 1996; 53: 53-60.

Green A, Williams G, Neale R, Hart V, Leslie D, Parsons P, Marks GC, Gaffney P, Battistutta D, Frost C, Lang C; Russell A. Daily sunscreen application and betacarotene supplementation in prevention of basal-cell and squamous-cell carcinomas of the skin: a randomised controlled trial. The Lancet 1999; 354: 723-29. [erratum The Lancet 1999; 354:1038] 

Neale R, Williams G, Green A. Measuring behavioral interventions by questionnaires and prospective diaries: an example of sunscreen use. Epidemiol 2002; 13: 224-7.

Neale R, Williams G, Green A. Application patterns among participants randomized to daily sunscreen use in a skin cancer prevention trial. Archives Dermatol 2002; 138: 1319-25.

Darlington S, Williams G, Neale R, Frost C, Green A. A randomised controlled trial to assess sunscreen application and betacarotene supplementation in the prevention of solar keratoses. Arch Dermatol 2003; 139: 451-5. 

Valery P, Neale R, Williams G, Pandeya N, Siller G, Green A. The effect of skin examination surveys on the incidence of BCC in a Queensland population: a ten-year longitudinal study. J Invest Dermatol Symp Proc 2004; 9: 148-51. 

Pandeya N, Purdie D, Green AC, Williams G. Repeated occurrences of basal cell carcinoma of the skin and multi-failure survival analysis: follow-up data from the Nambour Skin Cancer Prevention Trial. Am J Epidemiol 2005; 161: 748-54. 

van der Pols JC, Williams GM, Neale RE, Clavarino A, Green AC. Long-term increase in sunscreen use in an Australian community after a skin cancer prevention trial. Prev Med  2006; 42: 171-6. 

Battistutta D, Pandeya N, Strutton GM, Fourtanier A, Tison S, Green AC. Skin texture grading is a  valid measure of skin photoageing. Photoderm Photoimmunol Photomed 2006; 22: 39-45.

van der Pols JC, Williams GM, Pandeya N, Logan V, Green AC. Prolonged prevention of squamous cell carcinoma of the skin with regular sunscreen use. Cancer Epi Biomarkers Prev 2006; 15: 25468.

Gordon L, Scuffham P, van der Pols JC, McBride P, Williams GM, Green AC. Regular sunscreen use is a cost-effective approach to skin cancer prevention in subtropical settings. Jnl Invest Dermatol 2009; 129: 2766-771.

Green AC, Williams GM, Logan V, Strutton G. Reduced melanoma after regular sunscreen use: randomized trial follow-up. J Clin Oncol 2011; 29: 257-263.

Hirst NG, Gordon LG, Scuffham PA, Green AC.  Lifetime cost-effectiveness of skin cancer prevention through promotion of daily sunscreen use. Value in Health 2012; 15: 261-8.

Hughes MC, Strutton GM, Fourtanier A, Green AC. Validation of skin surface microtopography as a measure of skin photoaging in a subtropical population aged 40 and over. Photodermatol Photoimmunol Photomed 2012; 28, 153158.

Hughes MCB, Baker P, Williams GM, Green AC. Sunscreen and prevention of skin aging: a randomized, controlled trial. Annals Int Med 2013; 158: 781-90.

</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>QIMR Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Queensland Institute of Medical Research
PO Royal Brisbane Hospital
Queensland 4029,</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/06/1991</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>18/91</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Adele Green</name>
      <address>QIMR 
PO Royal Brisbane Hospital
Qld 4029</address>
      <phone>+61-7-33620234</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>adele.green@qimrberghofer.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Adele Green</name>
      <address>QIMR 
PO Royal Brisbane Hospital
Qld 4029</address>
      <phone>+61-7-33620234</phone>
      <fax>+61-7-38453503</fax>
      <email>adele.green@qimrberghofer.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Adele Green</name>
      <address>QIMR Berghofer Medical Research Institute
300 Herston Road, Herston QLD 4006
  
</address>
      <phone>+61-7-33620234</phone>
      <fax>+61-7-38453503</fax>
      <email>adele.green@qimrberghofer.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Adele C Green</name>
      <address>QIMR Berghofer Medical Research Institute
300 Herston Road, Herston QLD 4006
  
</address>
      <phone>+61-7-33620234</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>adele.green@qimrberghofer.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>