<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347893">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000020886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A trial of cediranib in the treatment of patients with alveolar soft part sarcoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A phase II trial of cediranib in the treatment of patients with alveolar soft part sarcoma (CASPS)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CASPS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>EudraCT 2010-021163-33</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>NCT01337401 on ClinicalTrials.gov</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>ISRCTN63733470</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alveolar soft part sarcoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sarcoma (also see 'Bone') - soft tissue</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Cediranib; 30mg tablet once daily, orally; until disease progression</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (lactose); 1 tablet once daily, orally; for 24 weeks or until disease progression (whichever occurs first)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy of cediranib in the treatment of ASPS by measuring the percentage change in the sum of target marker lesion diameters from randomisation to week 24 (or progression of sooner) compared to treatment with placebo.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Response rate at week 24, best response using RECISTv1.1 and best reduction (%) in tumour size</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-free survival and percentage alive and progression-free at 12 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 week intervals</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability profile of cediranib in patients with ASPS</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessments at 8-12 week intervals</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Histologically confirmed diagnosis of Alveolar Soft Part Sarcoma (ASPS)(central confirmation not required at study entry)
2. Age 16 years and older
3. Availability of archived tissue blocks to enable confirmation of t(X;17) translocation
4. ECOG Performance Status of 0-1
5. Life expectancy of &gt;12 weeks
6. Progressive disease within 6 months prior to randomisation
7. Measurable metastatic disease using RECISTv1.1, i.e. at least one lesion 10mm in diameter (15mm in short axis for nodal lesions) assessable by spiral CT (or MRI for brain metastases)
8. Patients with brain metastases are permitted provided disease is controlled with a stable dose of coricosteroid and/or non-enzyme inducing anticonvulsent
9. The capacity to understand the patient information sheet and ability to provide written informed consent
10. Willingness and ability to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plans, laboratory tests and other study procedures
11. Able to swallow and retain oral medication</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Inadequate bone marrow reserve as demonstrated by an absolute neutrophil count &lt;=1.5 x 10^9/L or platelet count &lt;=100 x 10^9/L
2. Serum bilirubin &lt;=1.5 x ULN (unless Gilberts syndrome)
3. ALT or AST &gt;= 2.5 x ULN. If liver metastases are present, ALT or AST &gt; 5 x ULN
4. Serum creatinine &gt; 1.5 x ULN or a creatinine clearance (calculated or measured) of &lt;=50mL/min
5. Greater than +1 proteinuria unless urinary protein &lt; 1.5g in a 24 hr period or protein/creatinine ratio &lt; 1.5
6. History of significant gastrointestinal impairment, as judged by the Investigator, that would significantly affect the absorption of cediranib
7. Patients with a history of poorly controlled hypertension with resting blood pressure &gt;150/100 mmHg in the presence or absence of a stable regimen of anti-hypertensive therapy
8. Any evidence of severe or uncontrolled co-morbidities e.g. unstable or uncompensated respiratory, cardiac, hepatic or renal disease, or active and uncontrolled infection
9. Evidence of prolonged QTc &gt;480 msec (using Bazetts correction, for which the formula is: QTc = QT/sqRR) or history of familial long QT syndrome
10. Significant recent haemorrhage (&gt;30mL bleeding/ episode in previous 3 months) or haemoptysis (&gt;5mL fresh blood in previous 4 weeks)
11. Major thoracic or abdominal surgery in the 14 days prior to entry into the study, or a surgical incision that is not fully healed
12. Pregnant or breast-feeding women; women of childbearing potential with a positive pregnancy test prior to receiving study medication; women the intention of pregnancy during study treatment; women of child bearing potential unwilling to have a urine or serum pregnancy test prior to study entry (even if surgically sterilised)
13. Men and women of childbearing potential unwilling to use adequate birth control measures (e.g. abstinence, oral contraceptives, intrauterine device, barrier method with
spermicide, implantable or injectable contraceptives or surgical sterilisation) for the duration of the study and should continue such precautions for 2 weeks after receiving
the last study treatment
14. History of anticancer (including investigational, non-registered) treatment in the four weeks prior to first dose of cediranib, with the exception of palliative radiotherapy for
symptom control
15. Known hypersensitivity to cediranib or any of its excipients
16. History of other malignancies (except for adequately treated basal or squamous cell carcinoma or carcinoma in situ) within 5 years, unless the patient has been disease free for 2 years and there is a tissue diagnosis of the primary cancer of interest from a target lesion
17. Other concomitant anti-cancer therapy (including LHRH agonists) except steroids
18. Recent history of thrombosis
19. Patients with brain metastases if they are symptomatic requiring increasing steroids in the previous six weeks to study entry or those with evidence of recent and/or active
bleeding, or those causing uncontrolled seizures</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The person who determines if a subject is eligible for inclusion in the trial is unaware (when this decision is made) to which group the subject will be allocated.  Allocation is concealed by central randomisation by phone/fax/computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised random allocation to treatment arm with 2:1 ratio cediranib:placebo</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Patients assigned to placebo will switch to cediranib after 24 weeks or disease progression (if sooner)</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/06/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>2050</postcode>
    <postcode>4102</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Institute of Cancer Research / Royal Marsden Hospital NHS Foundation Trust (UK)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Glen House (F125), 2.1
125 Old Brompton Road
London SW7 3RP</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United Kingdom</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Research UK</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Angel Building
407 St John Street
London EC1V 4AD</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AstraZeneca</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Parklands East
Alderley Park
Macclesfield, Cheshire SK10 4TG</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australasian Sarcoma Study Group</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 2, Research Division
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place
East Melbourne VIC 3002</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is investigating whether the drug cediranib might be effective as a treatment for alveolar soft part sarcoma.  It will test cediranib against placebo and measure the effects after 24 weeks.
Who is it for?  You may be eligible for this study if you are aged 16 years and over, have a histologically confirmed diagnosis of alveolar soft part sarcoma and give your consent to take part.  The full inclusion criteria details can be found in the relevant section of this form.
Trial details:  In this study, you will receive either the drug cediranib or placebo in the form of one tablet once a day, taken orally over a total period of 24 weeks.  If you are allocated to placebo, you will switch to cediranib after 24 weeks (or if your disease progresses before this time).  If you are allocated to cediranib, you will continue on this treatment until such time as your disease progresses.  You will be required to attend regular clinic visits for routine tests and assessments.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/01/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/01/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sharina Rosli</name>
      <address>Centre for Biostatistics &amp; Clinical Trials
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place
East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9656 5826</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9656 1420</fax>
      <email>Sharina.Rosli@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sharina Rosli</name>
      <address>Centre for Biostatistics &amp; Clinical Trials
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place
East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9656 5826</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9656 1420</fax>
      <email>Sharina.Rosli@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sharina Rosli</name>
      <address>Centre for Biostatistics &amp; Clinical Trials
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place
East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9656 5826</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9656 1420</fax>
      <email>Sharina.Rosli@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Martin Tattersall</name>
      <address>Chris O'Brien Lifehouse
119-143 Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8514 0759</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martin.tattersall@lh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>