<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336497">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000194965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of an individualised nutrition and exercise support program on quality of life, nutritional status and body composition in cancer patients post-haematopoietic stem cell transplant compared to standard care.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of an individualised nutrition and exercise support program on quality of life, nutritional status and body composition in cancer patients post-haematopoietic stem cell transplant compared to standard care.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1119-2656</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Adult cancer patients treated with autologous haematopoietic stem cell transplant.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each participants of the intervention group will recieve an individualised nutrition program from the hosptal dietitian and an individualised exercise program from the hospital exercise physiologist:

All transplant patients are regularly reviewed by a dietitian as a part of the hospital care but they are not followed up after discharge. Participant of the intervention group will be followed up by a hospital dietitian fortnightly for a 20-30 minutes dietary counselling to address specific nutirtional need (i.e. food choices).

The exercsie intervention will be variable but in general, patients will undertake a home-based exercise program involving a minimum of 5x30 minutes exercise a week for 12 weeks. Initial consultation (1hour) with the exercise physiologist will be conducted face-to-face in the hospital prior to discharge and subsequent follow up will be done fortnightly (20-30 minutes/session) over the phone after patients are discharged.The type of exercise and the intensity of the activity will be dependent on what is manageable by each patient.</interventions>
    <comparator>Autologous haematopoietic stem cell transplant patients treated with usual care. 

Usual care is hospital specific, therefore, the usual care may vary slightly depending on the recruitment site. Transplant patients recieving usual care as defined by this study are transplant patients who are not followed up by a hospital dietitian or exercise physiologist after discharge.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life (EORTC QLQ C30)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-admission (up to 2 weeks before stem cell transplant), 1 month, and 3 months post-transplant</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutritional status as assessed by the patient-generated subjective global assessment (PG-SGA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-admission (up to 2 weeks before stem cell transplant), 1 month, and 3 months post-transplant</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lean body mass as assessed by air-displacement plethysmography (BODPOD) and tetra-polar bioelectrical impedance analysis (BIA).  A sub-sample will be assessed by dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-admission (up to 2 weeks before stem cell transplant), 1 month, and 3 months post-transplant</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult cancer patients undergoing autologous haematopoietic stem cell transplant.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with disability or any other conditions that contradicts physical activity; patient's with a pace maker; allogeneic haematopoietic stem cell transplant; patients who cannot speak English; and patients with cognitive diseases.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Wesley Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>451 Coronation Drive, Auchenflower, QLD, 4066</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Wesley Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>451 Coronation Drive, Auchenflower, QLD, 4066</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The University of Queensland</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Queensland, St. Lucia, Brisbane QLD 4072</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients undergoing haematopietic blood stem cell transplant (HSCT) are primarily treated for haematological cancer. After treatment, these patients can experience a number of side effects affecting their quality of life for up to several years. Common problems observed amongst transplant survivors include weight loss, gastrointestinal symptoms (e.g. nausea, poor appetite, sore mouth and excessive diarrhoea), and fatigue. These symptoms can increase the risks of developing other issues such as poor nutritional status, poorer health status and reduced physical functioning. As a result of the combined factors, some people are unable to return to work or they are unable to perform their usual activities. One of the reasons for physical impairment may be the loss of muscle; and the cause of muscle loss may be the result of reduced physical activity and poor nutritional status. Despite report of these research findings, patients are not routinely followed up by allied health professionals to receive ongoing support. 

This study looks at the effects of a combined nutrition advice and individualised exercise program compared to standard care on quality of life, nutritional status and body composition in cancer patients after undergoing haematopoietic stem cell transplant. 

Who is it for  Eligible participants are adult cancer patient over the age of 18 and scheduled for autologous haematopoietic stem cell transplant at The Wesley Hospital.
Trial details  Participants will be randomised to one of two groups, either (i) an individualised nutrition program from the hospital dietitian combined with an individualised exercise program from the hospital exercise physiologist, or (ii) usual care as provided as standard by the hospital attended. Participants in the combined group will be followed up by a hospital dietitian fortnightly for a 20-30 minute dietary counselling session to address specific nutritional need (i.e. food choices), and the exercise component will be variable but, in general, patients will undertake a home-based exercise program involving a minimum of 5x30 minutes exercise a week for 12 weeks, and the type and intensity of exercise will be dependent on what is manageable by each patient. There will be a 1 hour consultation with the exercise physiologist conducted face-to-face in the hospital prior to discharge, and subsequent follow up will be done fortnightly (20-30 minutes/session) over the phone after patients are discharged. Participants in the usual care group will receive treatment as usual, according to the recruiting hospitals standards, and there will be no follow up by a hospital dietitian or exercise physiologist after discharge for this group. 

The aim of this study is to determine whether a combined nutrition advice and individualised exercise program may help in the quality of life, nutritional status, and body composition of cancer patients post-haematopoietic stem cell transplant compared to standard care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/02/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yui Hung</name>
      <address>The school of Human Movement Studies, Connell Building, The University of Queensland, St. Lucia, QLD 4067</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33656313</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yui.hung@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yui Hung</name>
      <address>The school of Human Movement Studies, Connell Building, The University of Queensland, St. Lucia, QLD 4067</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33656313</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yui.hung@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yui Hung</name>
      <address>The school of Human Movement Studies, Connell Building, The University of Queensland, St. Lucia, QLD 4067</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33656313</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yui.hung@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>