<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336135">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/11/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001047088</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised phase II study evaluating potential predictive biomarkers in the treatment of locally advanced and metastatic pancreatic cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised phase II study evaluating potential predictive biomarkers and examining the efficacy and safety of oxaliplatin, 5-fluorouracil and leucovorin (as mFOLFOX6) compared to gemcitabine in the treatment of metastatic pancreatic cancer.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PAN1</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Locally advanced and metastatic pancreatic cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pancreatic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients randomised to the intervention arm will receive modified FOLFOX6 chemotherapy (mFOLFOX6). Each cycle of mFOLFOX6 will consist of:

- Oxaliplatin 85mg/m2 given as an intravenous (IV) infusion on day 1 of a 2 week cycle.
- 5-Flurouracil 400mg/m2 given as an IV infusion on day 1 of a 2 week cycle.
- Leucovorin 400mg/m2 given as an IV infusion on day 1 of a 2 week cycle.
- 5-Flurouracil 2400mg/m2 given as an IV continuous infusion over 46 hours, commencing on day 1 of a 2 week cycle.

The cycle will be repeated every 2 weeks. 

Patients will continue their assigned treatment until progression, unacceptable toxicity or any of the reasons listed in protocol section 4.4.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients randomised to the control arm will receive gemcitabine chemotherapy. Each cycle of gemcitabine will consist of:


- Gemcitabine 1000mg/m2 given as an IV infusion on days 1, 8, 15 of a 4 week cycle.

The cycle will be repeated every 4 weeks.

Patients will continue their assigned treatment until progression, unacceptable toxicity or any of the reasons listed in protocol section 4.4.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression free survival at 4 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>Progression free survival is measured as the interval between randomisation and documented evidence of disease progression, the occurrence of new disease or death from any cause. Disease progression will be defined by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours (RECIST) v1.1 criteria and assessed every 8 weeks until progression.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy/activity of gemcitabine and FOLFOX as assessed by:
- Overall survival
- Time to progression
- Response rate according to RECIST v1.1
- CA19.9 response</outcome>
      <timepoint>- Overall survival time is measured as the time from the date of randomisation to the date of death due to any cause. Overall survival time will be censored at the date of the last follow-up visit for patients who are still alive.

- Time to documented disease progression is defined as the time from randomisation to the first date of documented disease progression or the occurrence of new disease. Disease progression will be defined by RECIST v1.1 criteria and assessed every 8 weeks until disease progression.

- Response rate according to RECIST v1.1. A tumour responder is defined as any patient exhibiting a best study response of complete response or partial response (based on computed tomography scan (CT scan)). Response will be assessed every 8 weeks until disease progression.

- CA19.9 will be assessed at baseline and 4 weekly from the start of treatment. CA19.9 response will be analysed as an exploratory endpoint using the following definition:
1. To be evaluable for response by CA19.9 requires 1 pre-treatment sample &gt; twice the upper limit of normal in the absence of biliary obstruction, and at least 1 further sample after the start of treatment. 
2. A response to CA19.9 has occurred if there is at least a 20% reduction in levels following the start of chemotherapy.
3. The date of response by CA19.9 is the date of the first sample with a 20% fall. 
4. Documentation of any proven or suspected interval biliary sepsis or stenting is required for correlation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients for whom a hENT1 result is obtained within a clinically useful timeframe.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Tissue samples for hENT1 testing will be collected prior to randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression free survival in each biomarker cohort.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Progression free survival is measured as the interval between randomisation and documented evidence of disease progression, the occurrence of new disease or death from any cause. Disease progression will be defined by RECIST v1.1 criteria and assessed every 8 weeks until progression.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To collect and analyse data from patient biospecimens</outcome>
      <timepoint>Tissue samples will be collected at baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment related toxicity in each chemotherapy group</outcome>
      <timepoint>Toxicity will be assessed according to Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) criteria v4.0 at baseline, prior to starting each chemotherapy cycle, at end of treatment and 30 days after the last study drug administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ascertain if there is a relationship between biomarker status and treatment related toxicity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Toxicity will be assessed according to Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) criteria v4.0 at baseline, prior to starting each chemotherapy cycle, at end of treatment and 30 days after the last study drug administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Establish a tissue bank from patients treated with and without gemcitabine to support further biomarker studies</outcome>
      <timepoint>Tissue samples will be collected at baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Males or females with radiologically and histologically confirmed metastatic pancreatic adenocarcinoma. Eligibility of patients with suspected disease must be confirmed by core biopsy prior to randomisation. 
2. Adult patients; 18 years or over.      
3. No previous treatment, except:
a. If adjuvant systemic therapy was received following resection, study entry is permissible if disease recurrence has occurred at least 6 months after completion of chemotherapy.
b. Previous radiotherapy is permissible if disease progression has occurred outside the radiotherapy field and disease recurrence has occurred at least 6 months after completion of radiotherapy.
c. Previous chemoradiotherapy is permissible if only radiosensitiser dose chemotherapy was used and disease progression has occurred outside of the radiotherapy field at least 6 months after completion of treatment.
4. Informed consent for all trial procedures, including:
a. Consent to undergo core biopsy to obtain tissue for biomarker analysis unless suitable archived paraffin embedded tissue (e.g. surgical specimen) is already available for human equilibrative nucleoside transporter 1 (hENT1) testing and other planned translational studies. 
b. Consent for collection of peripheral blood for pharmacogenomic/pharmacogenetic analysis.
5. World Health Organisation (WHO) performance status 0-2.       
6. Adequate renal, hepatic and haematological function, defined as;
a. Creatinine clearance (Cockcroft-Gault formula) &gt;60mL/min
b. Bilirubin &lt;1.5 x Upper Limit of Normal (ULN), aspartate aminotransferase (AST) + alanine aminotransferase (ALT)  &lt;3.0 x ULN (or &lt;5.0 x ULN with documented liver metastases) 
c. Haemoglobin &gt;100 g/L,  Platelets &gt;150 x109/L and Neutrophils &gt;1.5x 109/L</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Previous systemic treatment for metastatic pancreatic cancer.
2. Pregnant or lactating females or female patients of childbearing potential who have not been surgically sterilized or are without adequate contraceptive measures.
3. Other active malignancy or primary malignancy diagnosed within the previous 5 years, except for treated squamous or basal cell carcinoma of skin or cervical carcinoma.
4. Previous reactions to or suspected hypersensitivity to any of the investigational agents.
5. Peripheral neuropathy of any cause, of grade 2 or worse by CTCAE v4.0 criteria.
6. Seropositive for (Human Immunodeficiency Virus) HIV or Hepatitis C.
7. Active Hepatitis B not suppressed with antiviral treatment.
8. Symptomatic coronary or cardiac insufficiency.
9. History of thromboembolism, myocardial infarction or cardiovascular accident within preceding 3 months. Patients who have experienced deep venous thrombosis or pulmonary embolism within previous 6 months must be maintained on therapeutic levels of anticoagulation.
10. Diarrhoea &gt;grade 2 and/or uncontrolled diarrhoea.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Patients will be randomised to one of the two treatment arms in a 1:1 ratio using the minimisation method and stratified according to Locally advanced vs metastatic disease; Previous adjuvant chemotherapy (yes vs no); WHO performance status (0, 1 vs 2); and Institution.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/04/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>8/02/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>16</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>16/05/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC,ACT,QLD,SA,WA,TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australasian Gastrointestinal Trials Group (AGITG)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>AGITG Coordinating Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown 
NSW 1450</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australasian Gastrointestinal Trials Group (AGITG)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>AGITG Coordinating Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown 
NSW 1450</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Avner Nahmani Pancreatic Cancer Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Sydney</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study looks at whether testing for 'biomarkers' may be used to select the best treatment for patients with metastatic pancreatic cancer. A biomarker is a biological characteristic that can be measured in tumour tissue or blood, which may provide information on the behaviour of cancer or help predict the likely effect of a given treatment. We know that not all cancers or patients are the same, and that some patients may respond better to certain treatments. This study will help increase our understanding of how we might be able to select treatments to suit individual patients and their cancers. By doing this we hope to obtain the best outcomes for future patients while minimising side effects from treatment. 

Who is it for?

You can join this study if you have radiologically and histologically confirmed metastatic pancreatic adenocarcinoma, confirmed by biopsy. 
This is a phase II multicentre, randomised, open label study to evaluate biomarker directed treatment of metastatic pancreatic cancer.

Trial Details

Participants will be in two groups. Group 1 will receive Gemcitabine, and Group 2 will receive a combination of Oxaliplatin, Leucovorin and 5-fluorouracil (mFOLFOX6). Treatment will continue as long as it seems to be helping, provided participants do not have troublesome side effects.

Through this study we hope to gain information about the following: 
1) Can testing for hENT1 help us to identify patients who are more likely to benefit from initial treatment with gemcitabine chemotherapy? 
2) Is it possible to do the tests in patients quickly enough to enable use in routine clinical practice? 
3) How effective is FOLFOX chemotherapy as treatment for metastatic pancreatic cancer? 
4) Are there any other biomarkers in cancer cells or blood that may help us determine the best drug to use against an individual cancer? 

This randomised phase II exploratory study is vital in understanding the optimal design of future studies evaluating this novel approach to the management of pancreatic cancer, and may be expanded to a phase III study if this approach is validated.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cancer Institute NSW Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 41 
Alexandria NSW 1435</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/01/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2010C/11/145</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/11/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SLHD Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)  </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X13-0182 and HREC/13/RPAH/420</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/10/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>PAN1 Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre, Locked Bag 77, Camperdown NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pan1@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>PAN1 Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre, Locked Bag 77, Camperdown NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pan1@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>PAN1 Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre, Locked Bag 77, Camperdown NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pan1@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yu Jo Chua c/- PAN1 Trial Coordinator</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre, Locked Bag 77, Camperdown NSW 1450	</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9562 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pan1@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>