<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368278">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/04/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000399594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomized trial of a minimal psycho-educational intervention for sexual concerns after cancer: A comparison of self-help and professionally delivered modalities</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized trial of a minimal psycho-educational intervention for sexual concerns after cancer: A comparison of self-help and professionally delivered modalities</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sexual functioning</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Psychological wellbeing</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Quality of life</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Health professional intervention: minimal psycho-educational written information provision (self-help booklet) about cancer related sexual changes accompanied by a single session of counselling. 
The health professional consultation consisted of the self-help booklet followed up two weeks later by a one-hour telephone or Skype consultation between the participant and a counsellor trained in discussing sexuality. Concerns or questions raised as a result of reading the booklet were discussed during the consultation, and suggestions for ameliorating sexual problems, based on the specific needs of participants, were offered.
The self-help information booklet is based on accounts of sexual concerns experienced by people with cancer and their partners, consultation with health professionals, and examination of existing written resources on cancer related sexual concerns. It consisted of 68 pages, which provided information about: what is sexuality and intimacy; how cancer and cancer treatment affects sexuality; the body and sex; sexuality across different stages of cancer; talking about sex and intimacy; information for partners and for single people; same-sex relationships; strategies for overcoming sexual concerns, including exploration of non-coital practices and intimacy; and support services available. </interventions>
    <comparator>Self-help intervention: minimal psycho-educational written information provision about cancer related sexual changes.  The self-help information booklet is based on accounts of sexual concerns experienced by people with cancer and their partners, consultation with health professionals, and examination of existing written resources on cancer related sexual concerns. It consisted of 68 pages, which provided information about: what is sexuality and intimacy; how cancer and cancer treatment affects sexuality; the body and sex; sexuality across different stages of cancer; talking about sex and intimacy; information for partners and for single people; same-sex relationships; strategies for overcoming sexual concerns, including exploration of non-coital practices and intimacy; and support services available. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health related quality of life was measured with the Medical Outcomes Study Health Survey Short Form (SF-12) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants completed quantitative measures in a questionnaire pre-intervention at baseline, six weeks post-intervention and at three months follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological wellbeing was measured with the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants completed quantitative measures in a questionnaire pre-intervention at baseline, six weeks post-intervention and at three months follow-up. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sexual function was measured with the Changes in Sexual Functioning Questionnaire (CSFQ-14).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants completed quantitative measures in a questionnaire pre-intervention at baseline, six weeks post-intervention and at three months follow-up. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship satisfaction was measured with the Brief Dyadic Adjustment Scale (DAS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants completed quantitative measures in a questionnaire pre-intervention at baseline, six weeks post-intervention and at three months follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sexual communication was assessed with the Dyadic Sexual Communication Scale (DSCS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants completed quantitative measures in a questionnaire pre-intervention at baseline, six weeks post-intervention and at three months follow-up. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with Sexual Relationship was assessed with a one-item measure that asked participants how satisfied are you with your sexual relationship?, on a 5-point Likert scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants completed quantitative measures in a questionnaire pre-intervention at baseline, six weeks post-intervention and at three months follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Self-nominated person with cancer, or the partner of a person with cancer who had experienced cancer related sexual concerns.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None applied.  No restrictions according cancer type, stage, treatments, time since diagnosis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>In response to a study invitation, participants indicated whether they would like to be considered to take part in the evaluation of an intervention providing information about cancer related sexual changes. Those who agreed to take part were then randomly allocated to one of two conditions: self-help information only (SH), or information plus health professional consultation (HP). Randomization was stratified according to gender and cancer classification.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using coin-toss.
Allocation was not concealed.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The SH and HP interventions were offered on a couple basis for those in a relationship, following previous suggestions that couple based interventions are most effective. However, in order to meet the needs of those who were single,  or those who had partners who did not want to participate, the two interventions were also offered on an individual basis. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Using stratified random sampling of participants in Stage one (survey) of the of the ARC project who agree to take part in stage three (intervention),  160 participants, respectively (proportionally allocated per cancer type stratum) were allocated to each condition. Based upon 0.8 power calculations using a significance level of 0.01 to adjust for multiple comparisons, a sample size of 80 per condition is sufficient to allow for the detection of moderate clinical differences. Strata differentiated by cancer type, including both sexual and non-sexual cancers (prostrate/testicular; breast; gynaecological; other cancers). 
Univariate analyses were conducted to compare participants in the two intervention conditions for each of the socio-demographic variables of interest separately for people with cancer (PWC) and partners of people with cancer (PPWC). For continuous variables, one-way ANOVA were conducted with intervention, participant type, or gender used as the grouping variable, and the chi square test for independence used for frequency data.  Descriptive frequency analyses were used to examine baseline/follow-up retention rates across intervention conditions and participate type.  Descriptive analyses examined program evaluation measures. To allow for dichotomous analysis and facilitate interpretation, ratings of program usefulness were recoded into not useful and useful (a little &gt; extremely), reflecting the direction and meaning of the original Likert scales. The Fishers Exact Test (FET) was performed upon the categorical data associated with the perceived usefulness of the booklet in managing sexual changes and communication about sexual changes across the SH and HP intervention conditions.  In these analyses, the FET calculates the exact probability of significant differences in the reported assignments of participants in the two intervention conditions.  Independent sample t-tests were performed on outcome variables to assess baseline differences between the SH and HP intervention conditions according to participant type.  A series of separate mixed repeated measures ANOVA were conducted on scores on each outcome variable across the three time conditions, pre-test, post-test and follow-up as the within-subjects variables, with intervention condition (SH or HP), participant type (PWC or PPWC), gender (men or women) and cancer type (sexual or non-sexual) as the between-subjects factors.  An alpha level of .05 was used for all statistical tests.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/12/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/05/2011</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>8/06/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Jane Ussher</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Health Research
School of Medicine
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith  NSW  2751</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 2702. Canberra ACT 2601.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Janette Perz</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Health Research
School of Medicine
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith  NSW  2751</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Sexuality and intimacy are key aspects of quality of life detrimentally affected by cancer, resulting in significant reductions in well-being  for people with cancer and their partners  However, health professionals  rarely address this important health problem, and little is known about the factors which predict difficulties or re-negotiation of sexuality post-cancer   This study will examine the experience and construction of intimacy and sexuality post-cancer, from the perspective of people with cancer, their partners, and health professionals, and elucidate pathways to difficulty or re-negotiation   Based on these findings, programs of targeted couple interventions will be developed, and evaluated in a randomised controlled trial.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Western Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith  NSW  2751</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/10/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H6545</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jane Ussher</name>
      <address>Centre for Health Research, School of Medicine
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith  NSW   2751</address>
      <phone>+61246203953</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.ussher@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jane Ussher</name>
      <address>Centre for Health Research, School of Medicine
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith  NSW   2751</address>
      <phone>+61246203953</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.ussher@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jane Ussher</name>
      <address>Centre for Health Research, School of Medicine
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith  NSW   2751</address>
      <phone>+61246203953</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.ussher@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>