<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366417">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000796684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Impact of Exercise on Growth Hormone Deficient Adolescent and Young Adult Survivors of Childhood Cancer: a pilot study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Impact of Exercise on Metabolic Parameters of Growth Hormone Deficient Adolescent and Young Adult Survivors of Childhood Cancer: A Randomised Cross-Over study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1157-3978 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>GHDEx</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>survivor of childhood cancer
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>growth hormone deficiency</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Other</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The exercise program consists of thrice weekly supervised exercise sessions aimed at increasing exercise capacity. Each session will last for about 1 hour and consist of a small group with each participant having a personally tailored program. This will continue for 6 months. Intensity will be monitored during exercise sessions using heart rate monitors and rate of perceived exertion (Borg scale). During the intervention phase, exercise intensity will be maintained in the moderate intensity and not enter into vigorous intensity (&gt;60% VO2R). The key components of the exercise intervention include resistance training to increase lean muscle mass, and aerobic training to increase aerobic fitness.  Each exercise program will be fully supervised and designed in accordance with the American College of Sports Medicine (ACSM) guidelines(Franklin BA, Whaley MH, and Howley ET. ACSM's Guidelines for exercise testing and prescription (6 ed.). Philadelphia: Lippincott Williams and Wilkins, 2000). The program will consist of a 10 min warm up period, with light stretching, followed by 30-45 min of a circuit-based program which will use a combination of both endurance (65-85% of HRmax, monitored continuously using a Polar heart rate monitor) and resistance (55-70% maximal voluntary contraction) exercises, and a 10 min cool down.  Intensity and duration will be increased, first by extending the number of sets, then by the weight lifted. We have previous experienced high levels of compliance and participation using this form of training in a similar population group, who are young, and generally not highly motivated to participate in physical activities. </interventions>
    <comparator>In this study half the participants will be offered the exercise program for the first 6 months while the other half are not offered any program but encouraged to continue with their normal routines. After 6 months the control group will be offered the exercise program and the exercise group will become a control (although their data will be evaluated in the context of having just completed the exercise program). The second group to exercise will also have testing 6 months after their program finishes (ie 18 months into the study so that the washout effect of exercise can be examined in both groups). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>impact of exercise on metabolic parameters including: Oral glucose tolerance test results (analysed using HOMA2 scores), serum HbA1c, fasting lipid profile and auxological data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>after 6 months of exercise. 
Levels will also be checked after 3 months to identify early changes in parameters and after 12 months to identify hangover effect from the intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impact of exercise on cardiovascular parameters:
Every candidate will have an echocardiogram within the 12 months prior to commencing the program. This will be repeated at the end of the 6 month exercise program. Furthermore, endothelial function will be assessed using flow mediated dilation which has been demonstrated to be an independant predictor of cardiac events.
Flow mediated dilation is assessed as follows:
Following a one minute recording of resting brachial artery diameter by ultrasound, a forearm cuff placed distal to the olecranon process, will be inflated to 220mmHg for five minutes. Diameter and blood flow recordings will resume 30 seconds before cuff deflation and continue for three minutes.  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 6 months of exercise.
Tests will also be performed after 3 months to identify early changes in parameters and after 12 months to identify hangover effect from the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impact of exercise on psychosocial wellbeing:
A series of psychological assessments will be administered at baseline and again after the exercise intervention. The psychometric battery will include face-to-face assessments and parent-report questionnaires. 
Tests used:
Wechsler Abbreviated Scale of Intelligence (WASI)
Test of Everyday Attention (TEA)
Wechsler Memory Scale  3rd Edition (WMS-III)
Grooved Pegboard
ASEBA Youth Report (YSR)
ASEBA Adult Self-Report (ASR)
Behavior Assessment System for Children  Self-report (BASC-2)
Adaptive Behavior Assessment System  2nd Edition (ABAS-II)
Behavior Rating Inventory of Executive Function  Adult (BRIEF-A)
PedsQL 4.0 (Generic Version)
Parent-reported questionnaires:
Behavior Assessment System for Children  2nd Edition, parent-report  (BASC-2)
Behavior Rating Inventory of Executive Function (BRIEF)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 6 months of exercise.
Tests will also be performed after 3 months to identify early changes in parameters and after 12 months to identify hangover effect from the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Survivor of childhood brain cancer or cranial irradiation at a dose sufficient to potentially result in GH deficiency
2. Current age 15-23
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>23</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Currently on GH therapy
Acutely unwell
Pregnant 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Details of eligable patients are obtained via the oncology and endocrinology databases. 
Patients who appear likely fit the inclusion and exclusion criteria are mailed an information letter. 
Patients are called 2 weeks later and participation in the trial is proposed. 
Willing candidates attend PMH for detailed description of the trial and baseline studies.
Patients are randomised to exercise or non-exercise group using a web-based program.
Crossover of groups occurs after 6 months.</concealment>
    <sequence>The exercise physiologist contacts central administration ("off-site") who use a web-based program to randomly allocate participants into exercise or control groups (control group being the one who will exercise in the second 6 months)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Half the participants will be assessed at baseline and 6 months later after no intervention. These will act as pure control subjects. They will then commence the exercise intervention and be assessed 3 months into that, at its end and again 6 months later. The other half will be assessed at baseline, 3 months into their exercise program, at the end of the exercise program and 6 months after the intervention. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>18/09/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Roberts Rd, Subiaco WA 6008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Princess Margaret Hospital Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Roberts Rd, Subiaco WA 6008</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Western Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>35 stirling Highway, Crawley WA 6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to investigate the impact of a tailored supervised exercise program on the metabolic, psychosocial and cardiovascular risk factors of adolescent and young adult survivors of childhood cancer. 

Who is it for? 
You or your child may be eligible to join this study if you/they are aged between 15-23 years and have had either brain tumours or cranial irradiation. 

Study details:
Participants in this study will be randomly (by chance) allocated to one of two groups. The first group will take part in a 6 month supervised exercise program which is administered by an exercise physiologist (personal trainor)for 3 x 1 hour sessions per week. 
Participants in the other group will receive no intervention initially, but will take part in the exercise program after a period of 6 months. 
Proir to and on completion of the program participants will undergo clinical tests and complete some questionnaires in order to evaluate the impact of exercise on metabolic, cardiovascular and psychosocial wellbeing. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Roberts Rd, Subiaco, WA 6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013059EP</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shoshana Rath</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital (PMH), Roberts Rd Subiaco, WA, 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93408222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nooshi.rath@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shoshana Rath</name>
      <address>PMH, Roberts Rd Subiaco, WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61893408222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nooshi.rath@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shoshana Rath</name>
      <address>PMH, Roberts Rd Subiaco, WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61893408222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nooshi.rath@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Shoshana Rath</name>
      <address>PMH, Roberts Rd Subiaco</address>
      <phone>+61893408222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nooshi.rath@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>