<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370023">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000175471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Using wearable technology activity monitors to increase physical activity and decrease sitting time amongst breast cancer survivors:  the ACTIVity And TEchnology (ACTIVATE) Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Using wearable technology activity monitors to increase physical activity and decrease sitting time amongst breast cancer survivors:  the ACTIVity And TEchnology (ACTIVATE) Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1178-9881</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ACTIVATE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Physical activity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sedentary behaviour</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>- change of Study Coordinator (intervention now delivered by health coaches - staff with public health qualifications)
- physical function and cognitive function testing not administered</interventions>
    <comparator>Wait-list control arm. The wait-list control arm will receive the abridged version of the intervention after a 12 week wait period. The abridged version of the intervention includes only the initial information and training session; and the wearable technology activity monitor to wear for 12 weeks. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Moderate-vigorous physical activity, assessed by acceleroemter over a one week period at T2. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon completion of primary intervention (T2; 12 weeks after commencement of intervention).  Data to be collected over seven consecutive days of accelerometer wear.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sedentary behaviour, assessed by ActivPAL inclinometer over a one week period at T2</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon completion of primary intervention (T2; 12 weeks after commencement of primary intervention).  Data to be collected over seven consecutive days of inclinometer wear.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maintenance of physical activity change approximately 12 weeks after conclusion of primary intervention (primary intervention group only). Change in physical activity assessed by data collected over a one week period by accelerometer at T3.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon completion of maintenance phase (12 weeks post T2).  Acelerometer to be collected over seven consecutive days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy of an abridged intervention (wait-list control group only) on physical activity assessed by accelerometer data collected over a one week period at T3.  Within group change in physical activity between T2 and T3 examined.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On completion of abridged intervention phase  at T3 (T3; 12 weeks post T2).  Pre-post design employed for change analysis.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tests of physical function no longer administered</outcome>
      <timepoint>Tests of physical function no longer administered</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tests of cognitive function no longer administered</outcome>
      <timepoint>Tests of cognitive function no longer administered</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maintenance of change in sitting time 12 weeks after conclusion of primary intervention (primary intervention group only). Sitting time assessed by data collected over a one week period  by inclinometer at T3.  Change score derived by subtracting T3 sitting time from T2.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon completion of maintenance phase (12 weeks post T2).  ActivPAL inclinometer data to be collected over seven consecutive days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy of an abridged intervention (wait-list control group only) on sitting time assessed by data collected over a one week period by inclinometer at T3. Pre-post design employed for change analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On completion of abridged intervention phase  at T3 (T3; 12 weeks post T2).  Pre-post design employed for change analysis.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Post-menopausal breast cancer survivors, diagnosed with stage I-III breast cancer, who have completed primary treatment (surgery, chemotherapy, radiation therapy  ongoing hormone therapy is acceptable). Other eligibility criteria include: engaging in more than six hours of sitting each day; less than 75 minutes of moderate-vigorous physical activity per week; able to speak/write fluently in English; having daily access to a smart phone, mobile device or personal computer.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pre-menopausal women. Women diagnosed with breast cancer still undergoing primary treatment. Those engaging in less than six hours of sitting each day; more than 75 minutes of moderate-vigorous physical activity per week.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Initial telephone screening is conducted by the Study Coordinator.  Eligible participants are sent a baseline sociodemographic questionnaire, accelerometer/inclinometer and consent form.  If these baseline data collection measures are completed and returned, along with the consent form, to the study team, participants are then randomised by another team member who will have no personal contact with participants.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using the ‘ralloc’ Stata module.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>A two-arm design of which part 1 is a traditional randomised control trial; part 2 combines a maintenance phase for the intervention participants of part 1 plus an abridged intervention phase for the control participants of part 1.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Baseline characteristics will be summarised across the treatment groups. Should unexpected imbalances between the two groups occur by chance, they will be corrected in an adjusted analysis. To determine the effect of the intervention on both physical activity and sitting time, the trial analysis will be performed following the intention-to-treat principle. The analysis will therefore include all participants who were randomized (n=92) regardless of their compliance levels. Intervention effects will be assessed using linear mixed models for continuous variables. This model includes random effects associated with the units of analysis (participants), and allows the residuals associated with the longitudinal measures on the same unit of analysis to be correlated. This approach includes all available data at each time point, and may be adjusted for covariates if imbalances between groups are noted.  
Linear mixed models will also be used to address the secondary aims of the study. Here, we will only consider the within-group change (aims 2 and 3 do not have a control condition). All analyses will be conducted using Stata statistical software version 12 (Statacorp, College Station, TX, USA).
Our sample size calculation is based on Aim 1:  determining the efficacy of the primary intervention (use of wearable technology, coupled with brief behavioural counselling and goal setting) in increasing physical activity and reducing sitting time. The sample size for this study enables detection of a difference in physical activity between primary intervention and wait-list control groups at T2 of 75 minutes per week. Assuming a standard deviation of change of 120 minutes and allowing 10% attrition, 46 women per group (92 participants in total; 82 at end of intervention) will be needed to detect this minimum difference in total physical activity between groups with 80% power and a type I error of 5% (two-tailed). With a final sample size of 82 we will have 99% power to detect a difference of 75 minutes per day of sitting time between groups, assuming a standard deviation of change of 107 minutes.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/06/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>92</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>83</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>17/11/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cancer Council Victoria</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>615 St Kilda Road, 
Melbourne, 
Victoria, 
3004, </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>World Cancer Research Fund International</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Second Floor
22 Bedford Square
London, 
WC1B 3HH
UK
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Breast Cancer Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 9 
50 Pitt Street 
Sydney  
NSW  
2001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to determine whether using wearable technology activity monitors coupled with brief behavioural counselling and goal setting can increase physical activity and decrease sitting time amongst breast cancer survivors. 
Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a post-menopausal breast cancer survivor who was diagnosed with stage I-III breast cancer, and who has completed primary treatment (ongoing hormone therapy is acceptable). Eligible participants will also engage in less than 75 minutes of moderate-vigorous physical activity per week, more than six hours of sitting each day.
Study details
Participants in this study will be randomly allocated (by chance) to one of two groups. Participants in one group receive a novel 12 week intervention which involves: 1) Attending an initial information and training session; 2) wearing a technology activity monitor daily to enable real-time monitoring of physical activity and sitting time; and 3) receiving five behavioural counselling and goal setting sessions via telephone. The intervention will be followed by a 12 week maintenance period. Participants in the other group will receive no intervention for the first 12 weeks. After this time they will attend an information and training session and wear the activity monitor for 12 weeks. They will not receive the behavioural counselling and goal setting sessions.
All participants will complete assessments by wearing an accelerometer and inclinometer at baseline, after 12 weeks, and after 24 weeks in order to evaluate physical activity and sitting time. The proposed intervention has the potential to be an inexpensive and sustainable addition to usual care provided by clinicians, allied health professionals or via telephone-delivered cancer information and support services (such as those delivered by Cancer Councils across Australia).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.cancervic.org.au/research/epidemiology/cecprograms/activate-trial.html</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (Cancer Council Victoria)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>615 St Kilda Road, 
Melbourne, Victoria, 3004, </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brigid Lynch</name>
      <address>Cancer Council Victoria
615 St Kilda Road, 
Melbourne, 
Victoria, 
3004,</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9514 6209</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9514 6800</fax>
      <email>brigid.lynch@cancervic.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brigid Lynch</name>
      <address>Cancer Council Victoria
615 St Kilda Road, 
Melbourne, 
Victoria, 
3004,</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9514 6209</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9514 6800</fax>
      <email>brigid.lynch@cancervic.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brigid Lynch</name>
      <address>Cancer Council Victoria
615 St Kilda Road, 
Melbourne, 
Victoria, 
3004,</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9514 6109</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9514 6800</fax>
      <email>brigid.lynch@cancervic.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brigid Lynch</name>
      <address>Cancer Council Victoria
615 St Kilda Road, 
Melbourne, 
Victoria, 
3004,</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9514 6109</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9514 6800</fax>
      <email>brigid.lynch@cancervic.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>