<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320899">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/12/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000480088</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An efficacy study of Chemo-Radiotherapy in Positron Emission Tomography (PET) Merkel Cell Carcinoma of the Skin</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG) 09.03 - A Phase II Efficacy Study of Chemo-Radiotherapy in Positron Emission Tomography (PET) Stage II and III Merkel Cell Carcinoma of the Skin</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MP3</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>ClinicalTrials.gov ID NCT01013779</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Merkel Cell Carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Non melanoma skin cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm A: Experimental. Treatment: drugs - Carboplatin. During Radiotherapy: Carboplatin (dose calculated using Calvert formula with Area Under the Curve (AUC) 2.0) commences on day 1 of radiation and is repeated at weekly intervals on days 8, 15, 22 and 29 (of radiation). Carboplatin is administered intravenously over 20-30 minutes.
After radiotherapy: 3 weeks after completing radiotherapy, 3 cycles of 3 weekly carboplatin (dose calculated using Calvert formula using AUC4.5) intravenously on day 1.

Treatment: drugs - Etoposide. After radiotherapy: 3 weeks after completion of radiotherapy, 3 cycles of 3 weekly etoposide (80mg/m2/day), given intravenously days 1-3.

Treatment: other - Radiotherapy. Micrscopic Disease: 50 Gy in 2Gy doses over 25 fractions (5 weeks).
Macroscopic Disease: 54 Gy in 2Gy doses over 27 fractions (5 1/2 weeks).</interventions>
    <comparator>Not Applicable</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to loco-regional Failure curve. Measure of the effectiveness of treatment at the primary and nodal sites. Measured through imaging madality such as Computed Tomography (CT), PET or bone scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured from date of registration to time of failure. Patients will be assessed at baseline, weekly during treatment, 9 weeks post radiotherapy, 3 monthly for 2 years, 4 monthly for 1 year and 6 monthly for 2 years.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of grade 3 and 4 toxicity and incidence of febrile neutropenia. Measured using National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTC AE) v 4.0.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed weekly ( 5 weeks) during radiotherapy and Chemotherapy (at 3, 6 and 9 weeks post radiotherapy)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival (OS) and time to distant failure curves. OS measures the proportion of patients who die from any cause; time to distant failure measures proportion of patients who develop metastatic disease.
Measured upon relapse, diagnosis by clinical assessment confirmed by pathology or imaging (assessment at discretion of treating centre)</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of registration to 5 years post registration. Patients will be assessed at baseline, weekly during treatment, 9 weeks post radiotherapy, 3 monthly for 2 years, 4 monthly for 1 year and 6 monthly for 2 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients for which PET can influence management. Measured by comparing initial Computed Tomography (CT) staging scan and PET imaging.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post radiotherapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Positive Predictaive Value (PPV) and Negative Predictive Value (NPV) of PET. This will measure the accuracy of PET in detecting Merkell Cell Carcinoma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post radiotherapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-Treatment PET complete response rate for patients with unresected disease. Measured by Post Treatment PET scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post radiotherapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients may be included in the trial only if they meet all of the following criteria:
· Age 18 years or older
· Written informed consent to participate in the study
· Able to undergo 18-Fluoro Deoxy Clucose (FDG) PET scan (no uncontrolled diabetes mellitus or severe
claustrophobia).
· Available for follow-up.
· Using adequate contraception if capable of child bearing
· High risk disease with no evidence of distant spread: Biopsy proven Merkel Cell Carcinoma (MCC) with a primary that is &gt; 2cm (T2N0M0= Stage II) and/or regional nodes (any T, N1M0= Stage III); OR Recurrent MCC not previously treated with radiation treatment; Dermal or in-transit metastasis with or without nodes; Occult primary with involved nodes
· Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) 0-2.
· Full Blood Count (FBC) should be satisfactory ( Haemoglobin &gt; 10g/dl, neutrophils &gt; 2.0 x 109 /l and platelets &gt; 100 x 109 /l) and renal function (Glomerular Filtration Rate (GFR) &gt; 50 ml/min) and hepatic function (Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &lt; 5 X upper limit normal, bilirubin &lt; 1.5 X upper limit normal)
· No evidence of metastases on CT staging; OR If CT is suggestive of multiple metastases, they must be PET negative.
· No evidence of other malignancy in the past 5 years other than non-melanoma skin
cancer</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who fulfil any of the following criteria are not eligible for admission to the trial:
· Previous chemotherapy in the past 5 years or prior radiotherapy to the area of concern
· Unable to comply with treatment protocol eg dementia
· Other malignancy in the past 5 years other than non-melanoma skin cancer.
· Women who are pregnant or lactating.
· Clinical evidence of metastatic disease.
· Immunosuppression from long term steroid use or immunosuppressive drugs.
· Chest CT showing multiple nodules greater than 10mm which are PET positive.
· Any serious illness or medical condition that precludes the safe administration of the chemotherapy including:
(a) Active infection
(b) Uncontrolled or unstable cardiac disease including unstable angina, myocardial infarction within the last 3 months, and recurrent ventricular arrhythmias</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Prior to patient enrolment, the investigator should ensure that all of the following
requirements are met:
· The patient meets all inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion criteria should apply.
· The patient has signed and dated all applicable consent forms.
· All baseline assessments and investigations have been performed.
· The eligibility checklist has been completed, signed and dated.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not Applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/06/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/06/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>20/01/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>43</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>St Andrew's Toowoomba Hospital - Toowoomba</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Barwon Health - Geelong Hospital campus - Geelong</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Institute - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Calvary Mater Newcastle - Waratah</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Campbelltown Hospital - Campbelltown</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Adult Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Genesis Cancer Care QLD - Tugun</hospital>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>4350 - Toowoomba</postcode>
    <postcode>4224 - Tugun</postcode>
    <postcode>4006 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>2570 - Camden</postcode>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>3220 - Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <postcode>3002 - East Melbourne</postcode>
    <postcode>2298 - Waratah</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>TROG Central Office
PO Box 88
Waratah NSW 2298</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Australia and Cancer Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO BOX 1201
Dickson ACT 2602</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The overall objective of this study is to develop a well tolerated chemo-radiotherapy regimen for patients with Merkel Cell Carcinoma (MCC) of the skin that achieves high rates of control. 

You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 or over and have been diagnosed with stage II or stage III Merkel Cell Carcinoma of the skin with no evidence of distant spread. 

All participants in this study will undergo radiation therapy for 5 days per week for 5 weeks whilst being administered Carboplatin intravenously (i.e. directly into the vein) once per week. Three weeks after the end of radiation therapy, patients will commence 3 x 3-week cycles of intravenous Carboplatin, administered on day 1 of each cycle, and intravenous Etoposide, administered on days 1-3 of each cycle. 

Patients will be assessed by PET scan, CT and/or bone scan, and monitored for therapy side effects and survival every 3-6 months for 5 years. The PET scans will be used to assist in staging and planning the patient's treatment as well as assessing response at the conclusion of treatment.
 
It is hoped that the findings of this trial will lead to a greater understanding of the effect and toxicity of Carboplatin-Etoposide chemotherapy in combination with radiation therapy for stage II and III Merkel Cell Carcinoma. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.trog.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development and Ethics, Level 2, Building 35, Centres for Health Research
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road
Woollongabba QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/11/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Narelle Wallace</name>
      <address>Radiation Oncology  Mater Centre
31 Raymond Tce
South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3840 3322</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>narelle.wallace2@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Narelle Wallace</name>
      <address>Radiation Oncology  Mater Centre 31 Raymond Tce South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3840 3322</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3840 3298</fax>
      <email>narelle.wallace2@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>TROG Administrator</name>
      <address>TROG Central Office
PO Box 88
Waratah NSW 2298</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4014 3910</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4014 3902</fax>
      <email>administrator@trog.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Poulsen</name>
      <address>Radiation Oncology  Mater Centre
31 Raymond Terrace 
South Brisbane , QLD
4101
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 7 3840 3255</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael_poulsen@health.qld.gov.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>