<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364641">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000866707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A clinical trial of adoptive T-cell immunotherapy for patients with Epstein-Barr virus-associated nasopharyngeal carcinoma.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase I/II open-label clinical trial of autologous Epstein-Barr virus-specific T cell therapy as consolidative treatment following chemotherapy for metastatic EBV-associated nasopharyngeal carcinoma.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metastatic nasopharyngeal carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Head and neck</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>EBV-specific T cell adoptive immunotherapy. Initially, all patients will receive standard chemotherapy (first-line intravenous gemcitabine 1000mg/m2 in combination with cisplatin/carboplatin for up to 6 cycles, according to standard clinical practices). Following its completion, the immunotherapy will commence at the clinicians discretion. A dose of 2x10^7/m^2  LMP/EBNA1-specific autologous T cells will be given by intravenous infusion at weeks 2,4,6,8,10 and 12</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary endpoint will be progression free survival. Progression free survival is defined as the time from recruitment to time of disease progression, death or last follow-up, whichever occurs first. It is anticipated that treatment of 30 NPC patients (including 5 percent dropout) with metastatic disease will allow us to have preliminary assessment of the efficacy of such combined chemotherapy and immunotherapy approach. Assessed by: MRI/CT, Nasendoscopy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: MRI/CT scans will be done as per standard clinical practice, usually prior to receiving any chemotherapy, after receiving 3 cycles, and then at 6-12 monthly intervals.  Where clinically indicated nasendoscopy will be performed.  Blood tests will be done at baseline  1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 24 and 38 weeks. Follow-up is for 6 months following the final infusion. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Another primary endpoint will be assessment of tolerability and safety of administering a combination therapy based on chemotherapy and autologous LMP/EBNA1-specific T cells Assessed by: Physical examinations, vital signs, bloods test for FBC, E/LFT as well as for immunological and virological parameters</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: Baseline, 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 24 and 38 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Our secondary endpoint will be overall survival.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Overall survival will be assessed as the time from enrollment until death from progressive NPC disease.  The maximum duration of follow-up is 3 years post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immune functional and correlative studies (induction and persistence of EBV-specific immune response and changes in EBV DNA levels).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immune functional and correlative studies will be done by collecting blood and isolating white blood cells for immunological analysis and EBV DNA load analysis at baseline 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 24 and 38 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Age 18 years or above
2.	Histologically proven NPC
3.	Provision of Informed consent (approved hospital interpreters will be used for patients who do not have sufficient understanding of English for informed consent to be obtained without the use of an interpreter)
4.	ECOG performance status 0, 1, or 2 
5.	Life expectancy of at least 6 months, as determined by the clinical investigator
6.	Adequate haematological and biochemical function
7.	No history of other malignancy other than basal cell carcinoma of skin
8.	 Completion of a medical questionnaire 
9.	 Patient is suitable to commence standard chemotherapy for metastatic NPC</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. EBV negative tumour
2. Positive serology and/or NAT for HIV
3. Positive serology and/or nucleic acid testing (NAT) for human immunodeficiency virus  
4. Serology and/or NAT indicating active HBV infection or carrier status for HBV (N.B. Positive serology for HBV indicating previous but cleared infection with HBV would not be an exclusion criteria)
5. Serology and/or NAT indicating active HCV infection
6. Positive serology for syphilis or HTLV I/II 
7. Significant non-malignant disease (e.g. severe cardiac or respiratory dysfunction)
8. Psychiatric, addictive or any conditions which may compromise the ability to participate in this trial
9. Inability to provide informed consent, including patients with severe cognitive impairment, intellectual disability or mental illness
10. Prior cancers, except those diagnosed greater than 5 years ago with no evidence of disease recurrence and clinical expectation of recurrence of less than 5 percent, or successfully treated nonmelanoma skin cancer, or carcinoma in situ of the cervix. 
11. Currently receiving immunosuppressive therapy, including corticosteroids. At the discretion of the clinical investigator the patient can receive anti-emetics
12. Pregnant, or unwilling to use adequate contraception.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Overall survival  and progression free survival will be estimated using Kaplan-Meier method separately. Median progression free survival will be determined using this methodology and 95% confidence interval will be calculated. Response rate and clinical benefit rate will be estimated with 95% confidence interval. Survival curves will be estimated by the Kaplan-Meier method and differences will be tested using log-rank test statistics. p values less than 0.05 will be considered statistically significant. Historically, NPC patients with recurrent/metastatic disease receiving conventional chemotherapy at Queen Mary Hospital (Hong Kong) have median progression free survival of 6 months and overall survival of 10.3 months.  If we are to compare to the historical median progression free survival time of 6 months, then a median survival time of 10.6 months in our study of 30 patients will allow us to conclude with 5% significance and 80% power that the therapy has increased median progression free survival time. This calculation is performed assuming an accrual time of 36 months and follow-up of 6 months.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>QIMR Berghofer Medical Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>300 Herston Road, Herston, Brisbane, QLD, 4006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>QIMR Berghofer Medical Research Institute Immunotherapy Flagship Program</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>300 Herston Road, Herston, Brisbane, QLD, 4006 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Princess Alexandra Hospital (PAH)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>199 Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba,
Queensland, Australia 4102
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is evaluating the effect of using T cell immunotherapy following standard chemotherapy for the treatment of nasopharyngeal cancer (NPC).

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above and have been diagnosed with metastatic nasopharyngeal cancer and your clinician is planning to treat you with standard chemotherapy.

Trial details
All participants in this study will receive standard chemotherapy with gemcitabine and cisplatin according to their clinicians standard clinical care. Following this, they will undergo the experimental immunotherapy. This involves infusing Epstein-Barr Virus (EBV) specific T-cells intravenously (i.e. directly into the vein) up to 6 times, at fortnightly intervals. 

Participants will be regularly assessed for up to 38 weeks in order to evaluate their response to treatment, and the safety and tolerability of treatment.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland Institute of Medical Research Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Queensland Institute of Medical Research HREC
Queensland Institute of Medical Research
300 Herston Rd
Herston QLD 4006

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>P1486</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>199 Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba, QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/QPAH/436</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rajiv Khanna</name>
      <address>QIMR Berghofer Centre for Immunotherapy and Vaccine Development
Tumour Immunology Laboratory
Level 10, CBCRC, 300 Herston Road
Herston, QLD 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0385</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3845 3510</fax>
      <email>Rajiv.Khanna@qimrberghofer.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Neller or Katherine Matthews</name>
      <address>QIMR Berghofer Medical Research Institute 
300 Herston Road
Herston, QLD 4006</address>
      <phone>+61-7-3362 0412</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3845 3510</fax>
      <email>immunotherapy@qimrberghofer.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rajiv Khanna</name>
      <address>QIMR Berghofer Medical Research Institute 
QIMR Berghofer Centre for Immunotherapy and Vaccine Development
Tumour Immunology Laboratory
300 Herston Road
Herston, QLD 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0385</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3845 3510</fax>
      <email>Rajiv.Khanna@qimrberghofer.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Sashika Naidoo</name>
      <address>QIMR Berghofer Medical Research Institute 
300 Herston Road
Herston, QLD 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0433</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3362 0109</fax>
      <email>Sashika.naidoo@qimrberghofer.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>