<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6199">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02980731</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study Evaluating Venetoclax in Subjects With Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia Whose Cancer Has Come Back or Who Had No Response to Previous Cancer Treatments Including Subjects Missing Part of Their Chromosome 17, or TP53 Gene Mutation; or Who Received Prior Treatment With a B-Cell Receptor Inhibitor</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Open-Label, Single Arm, Phase 3b, Multi-Center Study Evaluating the Impact of Venetoclax on the Quality of Life of Relapsed/Refractory Subjects With Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL) Including Those With the 17p Deletion or TP53 Mutation OR Those Who Have Received Prior Treatment With B-Cell Receptor Inhibitor</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2016-001097-15</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>M15-889</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia (CLL)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Acute leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Chronic leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Leukaemia &amp; Lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Venetoclax

Experimental: Venetoclax - Venetoclax will be administered orally 20 mg once daily (QD) beginning with a dose-titration phase, and then escalated up to 400 mg QD.


Treatment: drugs: Venetoclax
Tablet

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Global Health Status/Quality of Life (GHS/QoL) subscale of the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Core Questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30) - EORTC-QLQ-C30 is a 30-item subject self-report questionnaire composed of both multi-item and single scales, including a global health status/quality of life (GHS/QoL) scale. Participants rate items on a four-point scale, with 1 as "not at all" and 4 as "very much." A change of 5 - 10 points is considered a small. A change of 10 - 20 points is considered a moderate change.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Screening (Baseline) up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia Module (EORTC QLQ-CLL16), - EORTC QLQ-CLL16 is comprised of 16 questions that address 5 domains of HRQoL important in CLL. Participants rate items on a 4-point scale, with 1 as "not at all" and 4 as "very much." A negative change in score from baseline represents an improvement in symptoms. A change of 5 - 10 points is considered a small change. A change of 10 - 20 points is considered a moderate change.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Screening (Baseline; Day 0) up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EuroQoL 5 Dimension 5 Level Questionnaire (EQ-5D-5L) - The EQ-5D-5L has five dimensions: mobility, self-care, usual activities, pain/discomfort and anxiety/depression. These dimensions are measured on a 5-level scale: no problems, slight problems, moderate problems, severe problems, and extreme problems. The scores for the 5 dimensions are used to compute a single utility index score ranging from zero (0.0) to 1 (1.0) representing the general health status of the individual. The EQ-5D-5L also contains a visual analog scale (VAS) to assess the subject's overall health.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Screening (Baseline; Day 0) up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the remaining subscales/items from the EORTC QLQ-C30. - The QLQ-C30 is a 30-item subject self-report questionnaire composed of both multi-item and single scales, including 5 functional scales (physical, role, emotional, social, and cognitive), 3 symptom scales (fatigue, nausea and vomiting, and pain), and 6single items (dyspnea, insomnia, appetite loss, constipation, diarrhea, and difficulties). Subjects rate items on a four-point scale, with 1 as "not at all" and 4 as "very much." A change of 5 - 10 points is considered a small change. A change of 10 - 20 points is considered a moderate change.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Screening (Baseline; Day 0) up to Week 48</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complete Remission rate (complete remission [CR] + complete remission with incomplete marrow recovery [CRi]) - Complete remission rate (CR + CRi) defined as the proportion of subjects achieving a CR or CRi as their best response (per the investigator assessment) based on IWCLL NCI -WG criteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>When all participants have completed Week 48 disease assessment, or after all enrolled participants have discontinued venetoclax, whichever is earlier.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Response Rate (ORR) - ORR assessed as the proportion of participants with an overall response (CR + CRi + Nodular Partial Remission [nPR] + Partial Remission [PR]) based on the 2008 Modified International Workshop on Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia National Cancer Institute-Working Group Guidelines (IWCLL NCI-WG) criteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured up to 2 years after the last participant has enrolled in the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Overall Response (DOR) - DoR is defined as the number of days from the date of first response (CR, CRi, nPR, or PR) to the earliest recurrence or progressive disease.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured up to 2 years after the last participant has enrolled in the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Progression (TTP) - TPP defined as the number of days from the date of first dose of venetoclax to the date of disease progression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured up to 2 years after the last participant has enrolled in the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Progression-Free Survival (PFS) - PFS defined as the number of days from the date of first dose of venetoclax to the date of disease progression or death, whichever occurs first.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured up to 2 years after the last participant has enrolled into the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival (OS) - OS defined as number of days from the date of first dose of venetoclax to the date of death for all dosed participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured up to 2 years after the last participant has enrolled into the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance score of less than or equal to
             2.

          -  Participant has relapsed/refractory disease (received at least one prior therapy).

          -  Diagnosis of CLL that meets published 2008 Modified International Workshop on CLL
             National Cancer Institute - Working Group (IWCLL NCI-WG) Guidelines and:

               -  has an indication for treatment according to the 2008 Modified IWCLL NCI-WG
                  Guidelines

               -  has clinically measurable disease (lymphocytosis &gt; 5 × 109/L and/or palpable and
                  measurable nodes by physical exam and/or organomegaly assessed by physical exam)

        In addition, Participants:

          -  may harbor 17p deletion or TP53 mutation, assessed by a local laboratory in bone
             marrow or peripheral blood AND / OR

          -  may have been previously treated with a prior B-cell receptor inhibitor - Adequate
             bone marrow function.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>99</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  Participant has developed Richter's transformation or Prolymphocytic leukemia (PLL).

          -  Participant has previously received venetoclax.

          -  History of active malignancies other than CLL within the past 2 years prior to first
             dose of venetoclax, with the exception of:

               -  adequately treated in situ carcinoma of the cervix uteri

               -  adequately treated basal cell carcinoma or localized squamous cell carcinoma of
                  the skin

               -  previous malignancy confined and surgically resected (or treated with other
                  modalities) with curative intent.

          -  Active and uncontrolled autoimmune cytopenias (within 2 weeks prior to screening),
             including autoimmune hemolytic anemia (AIHA) or idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura
             (ITP), despite low dose corticosteroids.

          -  Prior allogeneic stem cell transplant.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>13/12/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>17/01/2023</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>St. George Hospital /ID# 154212 - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital /ID# 154950 - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Perth Blood Institute Ltd /ID# 154949 - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre /ID# 154948 - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast University Hospital /ID# 150833 - Southport</hospital>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2170 - Liverpool</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>3000 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Hong Kong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state>Budapest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Newtown Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Chorzow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Lodz</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warsaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Moscow</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Russian Federation</country>
      <state>Penza</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taichung City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei City</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AbbVie</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this open-label, single-arm study is to evaluate the impact of venetoclax on
      the quality of life of participants with chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL; a type of cancer
      affecting the blood and the bone marrow) including those with the 17p deletion or TP53
      mutation (local lab assessed) OR in CLL participants who have received prior B-Cell Receptor
      Inhibitor (BCRi) therapy. The starting dose of venetoclax is 20 mg once daily. The dose must
      be gradually increased over a period of 5 weeks up to the daily dose of 400 mg. Participants
      may continue receiving venetoclax for up to 2 years. After the treatment period, participants
      may continue on into a 2-year follow-up period.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02980731</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Viktor Komlosi, MD</name>
      <address>AbbVie</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>AbbVie_Call Center</name>
      <address />
      <phone>847-283-8955</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>abbvieclinicaltrials@abbvie.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>