<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="135">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/11/1999</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/11/1999</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT00002529</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Hormone Therapy and Chemotherapy in Treating Perimenopausal or Postmenopausal Women With Node-Positive Breast Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Adjuvant Therapy for Post/Perimenopausal Patients With Node Positive Breast Cancer Who Are Suitable for Endocrine Therapy Alone.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>12-93</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>IBCSG-12-93</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>CDR0000078385</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - cyclophosphamide
Treatment: drugs - doxorubicin hydrochloride
Treatment: drugs - epirubicin hydrochloride
Treatment: drugs - tamoxifen citrate
Treatment: drugs - toremifene

Experimental: AC with concurrent tamoxifen - AC for 4 cycles with concurrent tamoxifen for 5 years

Experimental: AC followed by tamoxifen - AC for 4 cycles followed by tamoxifen to 5 years from randomization.

Experimental: Tamoxifen alone - Tamoxifen alone for 5 years.

Experimental: AC with concurrent toremifene - AC for 4 cycles with concurrent toremifene for 5 years.

Experimental: AC followed by toremifene - AC for 4 cycles followed by toremifene to 5 years from randomization.

Experimental: Toremifene alone - Toremifene alone for 5 years.


Treatment: drugs: cyclophosphamide
cyclophosphamide 600 mg/m2 i.v. day 1) every 21 days

Treatment: drugs: doxorubicin hydrochloride
doxorubicin 60 mg/m2 i.v. day 1) every 21 days, intravenous.

Treatment: drugs: epirubicin hydrochloride
epirubicin 90 mg/m2 i.v. day 1) every 21 days, intravenous.

Treatment: drugs: tamoxifen citrate
Tamoxifen 20 mg daily.

Treatment: drugs: toremifene
Toremifene 60 mg daily.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival - Time from randomization to death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>17 years after randomization</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease-free and systemic disease-free survival. - Time from randomization to recurrence, metastasis, appearance of a second primary tumor or death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>17 years from randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life - Quality of life will be assessed using QL Questionnaires of IBCSG.</outcome>
      <timepoint>17 years from randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Toxicity - Assessment of toxicity according to standard criteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>17 years after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically proven stage T1-3, pN1, M0 carcinoma of the breast
        considered suitable for adjuvant treatment with endocrine therapy alone Estrogen receptor
        at least 10 fmol/mg cytosol protein or positive on immunohistochemical assay Potentially
        curative resection within 6 weeks of entry by one of the following: Total mastectomy with
        negative margins Breast-conserving procedure (lumpectomy or quadrantectomy) for tumors less
        than 5 cm Adequate re-resection or mastectomy within 4 weeks of initial surgery required if
        margins are positive after initial surgery Axillary clearance (not sampling) required at
        surgery, with at least 1 node positive upon histopathologic examination of at least 8 nodes
        Suspicious manifestations of metastatic disease (e.g., hot spots on bone scan, skeletal
        pain of unknown cause) must be proven benign No bilateral breast cancer Any mass in
        contralateral breast must be proven benign by biopsy

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 70 and under Sex: Women only Menopausal status:
        Peri/postmenopausal, i.e.: More than 6 months since last normal menstrual period (LNMP)
        with no prior hysterectomy and no hormone replacement therapy (HRT) Prior hysterectomy and
        no HRT and either age greater than 55 or age 55 or less with postmenopausal LH, FSH, and E2
        levels On HRT and either age 50 or greater or LNMP more than 6 months prior to starting HRT
        Performance status: Not specified Hematopoietic: WBC greater than 4,000 Platelets greater
        than 100,000 Hepatic: Bilirubin less than 1.1 mg/dL (20 micromoles/L) AST less than 60 IU/L
        Renal: Creatinine less than 1.3 mg/dL (120 micromoles/L) Other: No nonmalignant systemic
        disease that would preclude protocol therapy or prolonged follow-up No psychiatric or
        addictive disorder that would preclude informed consent No prior or concurrent second
        malignancy except: Nonmelanomatous skin cancer Adequately treated in situ carcinoma of the
        cervix Geographically accessible for follow-up

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: No prior therapy for breast cancer other than potentially
        curative surgery (see Disease Characteristics)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria />
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/05/1993</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>452</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/08/2010</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Newcastle Mater Misericordiae Hospital - Newcastle</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, Sydney - Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Anti-Cancer Council of Victoria, Melbourne - Carlton South</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital, Perth - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>NSW 2310 - Newcastle</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3053 - Carlton South</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Perth</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Aviano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Brescia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Milano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Rimini</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Rome</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovenia</country>
      <state>Ljubljana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state>Cape Town</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state>Gothenburg (Goteborg)</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Basel</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Bern</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Lausanne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Neuchatel</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Saint Gallen</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Zurich</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>International Breast Cancer Study Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>RATIONALE: Estrogen can stimulate the growth of breast cancer cells. Hormone therapy may
      fight breast cancer by blocking the uptake of estrogen. Drugs used in chemotherapy use
      different ways to stop tumor cells from dividing so they stop growing or die. Combining
      chemotherapy with hormone therapy may kill more tumor cells. It is not yet known which
      treatment regimen is more effective for breast cancer.

      PURPOSE: Randomized phase III trial to compare the effectiveness of hormone therapy during or
      after combination chemotherapy or hormone therapy alone in treating perimenopausal or
      postmenopausal women who have stage II or stage IIIA breast cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00002529</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Gianni L, Gelber S, Ravaioli A, Price KN, Panzini I, Fantini M, Castiglione-Gertsch M, Pagani O, Simoncini E, Gelber RD, Coates AS, Goldhirsch A. Second non-breast primary cancer following adjuvant therapy for early breast cancer: a report from the International Breast Cancer Study Group. Eur J Cancer. 2009 Mar;45(4):561-71. doi: 10.1016/j.ejca.2008.10.011. Epub 2008 Dec 4.
Kenne Sarenmalm E, Odén A, Ohlén J, Gaston-Johansson F, Holmberg SB. Changes in health-related quality of life may predict recurrent breast cancer. Eur J Oncol Nurs. 2009 Dec;13(5):323-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ejon.2009.05.002. Epub 2009 Jul 12.
Pagani O, Gelber S, Simoncini E, Castiglione-Gertsch M, Price KN, Gelber RD, Holmberg SB, Crivellari D, Collins J, Lindtner J, Thürlimann B, Fey MF, Murray E, Forbes JF, Coates AS, Goldhirsch A; International Breast Cancer Study Group. Is adjuvant chemotherapy of benefit for postmenopausal women who receive endocrine treatment for highly endocrine-responsive, node-positive breast cancer? International Breast Cancer Study Group Trials VII and 12-93. Breast Cancer Res Treat. 2009 Aug;116(3):491-500. doi: 10.1007/s10549-008-0225-9. Epub 2008 Oct 25.
Pestalozzi BC, Zahrieh D, Mallon E, Gusterson BA, Price KN, Gelber RD, Holmberg SB, Lindtner J, Snyder R, Thürlimann B, Murray E, Viale G, Castiglione-Gertsch M, Coates AS, Goldhirsch A; International Breast Cancer Study Group. Distinct clinical and prognostic features of infiltrating lobular carcinoma of the breast: combined results of 15 International Breast Cancer Study Group clinical trials. J Clin Oncol. 2008 Jun 20;26(18):3006-14. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2007.14.9336. Epub 2008 May 5.
Keshaviah A, Dellapasqua S, Rotmensz N, Lindtner J, Crivellari D, Collins J, Colleoni M, Thürlimann B, Mendiola C, Aebi S, Price KN, Pagani O, Simoncini E, Castiglione Gertsch M, Gelber RD, Coates AS, Goldhirsch A. CA15-3 and alkaline phosphatase as predictors for breast cancer recurrence: a combined analysis of seven International Breast Cancer Study Group trials. Ann Oncol. 2007 Apr;18(4):701-8. Epub 2007 Jan 20.
Gianni L, Panzini I, Li S, Gelber RD, Collins J, Holmberg SB, Crivellari D, Castiglione-Gertsch M, Goldhirsch A, Coates AS, Ravaioli A; International Breast Cancer Study Group (IBCSG). Ocular toxicity during adjuvant chemoendocrine therapy for early breast cancer: results from International Breast Cancer Study Group trials. Cancer. 2006 Feb 1;106(3):505-13.
International Breast Cancer Study Group, Pagani O, Gelber S, Price K, Zahrieh D, Gelber R, Simoncini E, Castiglione-Gertsch M, Coates AS, Goldhirsch A. Toremifene and tamoxifen are equally effective for early-stage breast cancer: first results of International Breast Cancer Study Group Trials 12-93 and 14-93. Ann Oncol. 2004 Dec;15(12):1749-59.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Edda Simoncini, MD</name>
      <address>Spedali Civili di Brescia</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>