<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="2883">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/08/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/08/2010</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01189968</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of Carboplatin and Pemetrexed Plus Demcizumab (OMP-21M18) in Subjects With Non-Squamous Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1b Study of Carboplatin and Pemetrexed Plus Demcizumab (OMP-21M18) as 1st-line Treatment in Subjects With Non-Squamous Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>M18-004</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non Small Cell Lung Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Mesothelioma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Non small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Demcizumab

Experimental: Carboplatin and Pemetrexed plus demcizumab - Carboplatin and Pemetrexed plus demcizumab

Experimental: Pemetrexed plus demcizumab - Pemetrexed plus demcizumab


Treatment: drugs: Demcizumab
The 6 subjects in the first cohort will receive demcizumab 5 mg/kg once every 3 weeks; the 6 subjects in the subsequent cohort will be treated with 10 mg/kg once every 3 weeks; and the 6 subjects in the final cohort will be treated with 15 mg/kg once every 3 weeks. A Data Safety Monitoring Board (DSMB) will review the data for the 6 subjects in each dose cohort after the last subject in that cohort has been on study for 56 days and then decide whether it is safe to escalate to the next highest dose cohort. Once the dose-escalation portion of the study has been completed, 14 additional subjects will be treated at the highest dose level that the DSMB deems as safe.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To the determine the maximum tolerated dose of demcizumab (OMP-21M18) plus carboplatin and pemetrexed</outcome>
      <timepoint>When each patient in the dose cohort reaches Day 56</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the safety of carboplatin and pemetrexed plus demcizumab (OMP-21M18)</outcome>
      <timepoint>until treatment termination plus 30 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the rates of immunogenicity of carboplatin and pemetrexed plus demcizumab (OMP-21M18)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 12 weeks post treatment termination</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the preliminary efficacy of carboplatin and pemetrexed plus demcizumab (OMP-21M18)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until disease progression</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine population pharmacokinetics</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 21 and 63</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the exploratory biomarker changes of carboplatin and pemetrexed plus demcizumab (OMP-21M18)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until Day 112</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria

          1. Subjects must have histologically confirmed unresectable, locally advanced, recurrent,
             or metastatic non-squamous NSCLC. Subjects may not have received prior therapy for
             their unresectable, locally advanced, recurrent, or metastatic non-squamous NSCLC.
             Subjects may have received prior surgery, prior radiotherapy, and/or prior neoadjuvant
             or adjuvant chemotherapy (they must have discontinued prior neoadjuvant or adjuvant
             chemotherapy at least 12 weeks prior to study entry).

          2. Age &gt;21 years

          3. ECOG performance status &lt;2 (see Appendix B)

          4. Life expectancy of more than 3 months

          5. Subjects must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

               -  Leukocytes &gt;3.5 x 109/L

               -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt;1.25 x 109/L Hemoglobin &gt;100 g/L

               -  Platelets &gt;125 X 109/L

               -  Total bilirubin &lt;2 X institutional upper limit of normal (ULN)

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST/SGOT) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT/SGPT) &lt;5
                  X institutional ULN

               -  Alkaline phosphatase &lt;5 X institutional ULN

               -  International normalized ratio (INR) and activated partial thromboplastin time
                  (aPTT) within institutional ULN

               -  Calculated creatinine clearance &gt;60 mL/min using the Cockcroft and Gault formula
                  as follows:

             Creatinine clearance (mL/min) = (140 - age) x ideal body weight [kg] 0.814 x serum
             creatinine [µmol/L] For women multiply the value from the equation above by 0.85.
             Where age is in years, weight is in kg, and serum creatinine is in µmol/L.

          6. Women of childbearing potential must have had a prior hysterectomy or have a negative
             serum pregnancy test and be using adequate contraception prior to study entry and must
             agree to use adequate contraception from study entry through at least 6 months after
             discontinuation of study drugs. Men must also agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or barrier method of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and
             from study entry through at least 6 months after discontinuation of study drugs.
             Should a woman enrolled in the study or a female partner of a man enrolled in the
             study become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this study or
             within 6 months after discontinuation of the study drugs, the Investigator should be
             informed immediately.

          7. Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria

        Subjects who meet any of the following criteria will not be eligible for participation in
        the study:

          1. Subjects receiving any other investigational agents or anti-cancer therapy.

          2. Subjects with brain metastases (subjects must have a CT scan or MRI of the head within
             28 days prior to enrollment to rule out brain metastases), uncontrolled seizure
             disorder, or active neurologic disease

          3. History of a significant allergic reaction attributed to humanized or human monoclonal
             antibody therapy

          4. Significant intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia,
             or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
             requirements

          5. Pregnant women or nursing women

          6. Subjects with known HIV infection

          7. Known bleeding disorder or coagulopathy

          8. Subjects receiving heparin, warfarin, or other similar anticoagulants. Note: Subjects
             may be receiving low-dose aspirin and/or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents.

          9. Subjects with known clinically significant gastrointestinal disease including, but not
             limited to, inflammatory bowel disease

         10. New York Heart Association Classification II, III, or IV (See Appendix D)

         11. Subjects with a blood pressure of &gt;140/90 mmHg. The BP should be taken using the
             method described in Section 9.3. Subjects taking antihypertensive medications must be
             taking = 2 medications to obtain this level of BP control.

         12. Subjects with metastases that are currently involving the lumen of the
             gastrointestinal tract

         13. Subjects with squamous cell carcinoma of the lung

         14. Subjects with recent (within the last 8 weeks) hemoptysis &gt;2.5 mL and subjects with
             serious bleeding from another site within this timeframe

         15. Subjects with current evidence of cardiac ischemia or heart failure within the last 6
             months, subjects who are receiving any medications for cardiac ischemia, subjects with
             a B-type natriuretic peptide (BNP) value of &gt;100 pg/mL, subjects with a LVEF &lt;50%,
             subjects with pulmonary hypertension defined as a peak tricuspid velocity &gt;3.4 m/s on
             doppler echocardiogram or subjects that have received a total cumulative dose of =400
             mg/m2 doxorubicin.

         16. Subjects with ECG evidence of ischemia or = Grade 2 ventricular arrhythmia, subjects
             who have a history of acute myocardial infarction within 6 months, or subjects with
             unstable angina.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/09/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,SA,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Ashford Cancer Centre Research - Kurralta Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>5037 - Kurralta Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>OncoMed Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Novotech (Australia) Pty Limited</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to test the safety and determine the optimal dose of a new drug,
      demcizumab (OMP-21M18), when given in combination with carboplatin and pemetrexed, a standard
      drug treatment regimen for non-squamous non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC). Participants must
      not have received prior chemotherapy for their NSCLC. Demcizumab is a humanized monoclonal
      antibody (a protein made in the laboratory) developed to target cancer stem cells. The way
      the body handles demcizumab will also be investigated.

      Up to 50 subjects will be enrolled at up to 8 centers in Australia, New Zealand, and Spain.
      Up to 28 days (4 weeks) prior to treatment you will undergo testing to determine your
      eligibility to take part in this study, and then if enrolled in the study you will receive
      intravenous (in the vein) infusions of the demcizumab, carboplatin, and pemetrexed
      administered on the same day, every 21 days for 4 cycles, or until it has been shown that
      your cancer has progressed. If your physician decides to delay treatment with one of the
      agents due to side effects, the other agents may still be administered as scheduled. After 4
      cycles, if you have stable or improved disease, you will continue to receive pemetrexed once
      every 21 days as maintenance therapy. You will undergo assessments every 8 weeks to determine
      the status of your disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01189968</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>