<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="3251">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02883049</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Combination Chemotherapy in Treating Young Patients With Newly Diagnosed High-Risk B Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia and Ph-Like TKI Sensitive Mutations</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase III Randomized Trial for Newly Diagnosed High Risk B-Lymphoblastic Leukemia (B-ALL) Including a Stratum Evaluating Dasatinib (NSC#732517) in Patients With Ph-like Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitor (TKI) Sensitive Mutations</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NCI-2011-03797</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>NCI-2011-03797</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>B Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Bone Necrosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Central Nervous System Leukemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive Side Effects of Cancer Therapy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Neurotoxicity Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pain</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Ph-Like Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Testicular Leukemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Therapy-Related Toxicity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Untreated Adult Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Untreated Childhood Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Acute leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Chronic leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Leukaemia &amp; Lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - High grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lymphoma (non Hodgkin's lymphoma) - Low grade lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Poisoning</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Clofarabine
Treatment: drugs - Cyclophosphamide
Treatment: drugs - Cytarabine
Treatment: drugs - Dasatinib
Treatment: drugs - Dexamethasone
Treatment: drugs - Doxorubicin Hydrochloride
Treatment: drugs - Etoposide
Treatment: drugs - Hydrocortisone Sodium Succinate
Other interventions - Laboratory Biomarker Analysis
Treatment: drugs - Leucovorin Calcium
Treatment: drugs - Mercaptopurine
Treatment: drugs - Methotrexate
Treatment: drugs - Pegaspargase
Treatment: drugs - Prednisone
Treatment: other - Radiation Therapy
Treatment: drugs - Thioguanine
Treatment: drugs - Vincristine Sulfate

Active Comparator: Arm A (VHR B-ALL C) - Patients receive consolidation therapy comprising cyclophosphamide IV over 30-60 minutes on day 29; cytarabine IV over 1-30 minutes or SC on days 29-32 and 36-39; mercaptopurine PO QD on days 29-42; vincristine sulfate IV over 1 minute on days 43 and 50; and pegaspargase IV over 1-2 hours on day 43. Treatment continues for 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

Active Comparator: Arm A (VHR B-ALL DI) - Patients receive DI therapy comprising cyclophosphamide IV over 30-60 minutes on day 29; cytarabine IV over 15-30 minutes or SC on days 29-32 and 36-39; thioguanine PO QD on days 29-42; methotrexate IT on days 29 and 36; vincristine sulfate IV over 1 minute on days 43 and 50; and pegaspargase IV over 1-2 hours on day 43. Treatment continues for 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

Experimental: Arm B (VHR B-ALL C) - Patients receive consolidation therapy comprising cyclophosphamide IV over 15-30 minutes on days 29-33; etoposide IV over 60-120 minutes on days 29-33; vincristine sulfate IV over 1 minute on days 43 and 50; and pegaspargase IV over 1-2 hours on day 43. Treatment continues for 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

Experimental: Arm B (VHR B-ALL DI) - Patients receive DI therapy comprising cyclophosphamide IV over 15-30 minutes on days 29-33; etoposide IV over 60-120 minutes on days 29-33; methotrexate IT on days 29 and 36; vincristine sulfate IV over 1 minute on days 43 and 50; and pegaspargase IV over 1-2 hours on day 43. Treatment continues for 28 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

Experimental: Arm C (VHR B-ALL C) - Patients receive clofarabine IV over 2 hours on days 29-33 and consolidation therapy as in Arm B VHR B-ALL C. (Closed as of 9/12/2014)

Experimental: Arm C (VHR B-ALL DI) - Patients receive clofarabine IV over 2 hours on days 29-33 and DI therapy as in Arm II B VHR B-ALL DI. (Closed as of 9/12/2014)

Active Comparator: Arm I (HR B-ALL C) - Patients receive Consolidation therapy comprising cyclophosphamide IV over 30-60 minutes on days 1 and 29; cytarabine IV over 1-30 minutes or SC on days 1-4, 8-11, 29-32, and 36-39; mercaptopurine PO QD on days 1-14 and 29-42, methotrexate IT on days 1, 8, 15, and 22; vincristine sulfate IV over 1 minute on days 15, 22, 43, and 50; and pegaspargase IV over 1-2 hours on days 15 and 43. Patients with continuing clinical evidence of testicular leukemia undergo RT QD, 5 days a week, for approximately 2½ weeks (12 fractions total). Treatment continues for 56 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

Active Comparator: Arm I (HR B-ALL DI) - Patients receive DI therapy comprising vincristine sulfate IV over 1 hour on days 1, 8, 15, 43, and 50; dexamethasone PO or IV BID on days 1-7 and 15-21; doxorubicin hydrochloride IV over 1-60 minutes on days 1, 8, and 15; methotrexate IT on days 1, 29, and 36; pegaspargase IV over 1-2 hours on days 4 and 43; cyclophosphamide IV over 30-60 minutes on day 29; cytarabine IV over 1-30 minutes or SC on days 29-32 and 36-39; and thioguanine PO QD on days 29-42. Treatment continues for 56 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

Active Comparator: Arm I (HR B-ALL IM) - Patients receive IM therapy comprising vincristine sulfate IV over 1 minute on days 1, 15, 29, and 43; high-dose methotrexate IV over 24 hours on days 1, 15, 29, and 43; leucovorin calcium PO or IV on days 3-4, 17-18, 31-32, and 45-46; methotrexate IT on days 1 and 29; and mercaptopurine PO on days 1-56. Treatment continues for 63 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

Active Comparator: Arm I (HR B-ALL M) - Patients receive maintenance therapy comprising vincristine sulfate IV over 1 minute on days 1, 29, and 57; methotrexate IT on day 1 (also day 29 of courses 1-4); prednisone PO BID on days 1-5, 29-33 (may receive methylprednisolone IV if PO is not tolerated), and 57-61; mercaptopurine PO QD on days 1-84; and methotrexate PO on days 8, 15, 22, 29, 36, 43, 50, 57, 64, 71, and 78. Treatment repeats every 12 weeks for 2 years (females) or 3 years (males) in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

Experimental: Arm II (HR B-ALL C) - Patients receive Consolidation therapy as patients in Arm I HR B-ALL C. Patients also receive ITT comprising methotrexate, hydrocortisone sodium succinate, and cytarabine on days 1, 8, 15, and 22. Patients with testicular leukemia also undergo RT as in Arm I HR B-ALL C.

Experimental: Arm II (HR B-ALL DI) - Patients receive ITT on days 1, 29, and 36 and DI therapy as in Arm I HR B-ALL DI.

Experimental: Arm II (HR B-ALL IM) - Patients receive ITT on days 1 and 29 and IM therapy as in Arm I HR B-ALL IM. Treatment continues for 63 days in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

Experimental: Arm II (HR B-ALL M) - Patients receive ITT on day 1 (also day 29 of courses 1-4) and maintenance therapy as in Arm I HR B-ALL M. Treatment repeats every 12 weeks for 2 years (females) or 3 years (males) in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

Experimental: Ph-like TKI-sensitive kinase mutation - Patients receive dasatinib PO QD on days 1-56, cyclophosphamide IV over 30-60 minutes on days 1 and 29, cytarabine IV over 1-30 minutes or SC on days 1-4, 8-11, 29-32 and 36-39, mercaptopurine PO on days 1-14 and 29-42, methotrexate IT on days 1, 8, 15 and 22, vincristine IV over 1 minute on days 15, 22, 43 and 50, and pegaspargase IV over 1-2 hours on days 15 and 43.


Treatment: drugs: Clofarabine
Given IV

Treatment: drugs: Cyclophosphamide
Given IV

Treatment: drugs: Cytarabine
Given IT, IV or SC

Treatment: drugs: Dasatinib
Given PO

Treatment: drugs: Dexamethasone
PO or IV

Treatment: drugs: Doxorubicin Hydrochloride
Given IV

Treatment: drugs: Etoposide
Given IV

Treatment: drugs: Hydrocortisone Sodium Succinate
Given IT

Other interventions: Laboratory Biomarker Analysis
Correlative studies

Treatment: drugs: Leucovorin Calcium
Given PO or IV

Treatment: drugs: Mercaptopurine
Given PO

Treatment: drugs: Methotrexate
Given IT and IV

Treatment: drugs: Pegaspargase
Given IV

Treatment: drugs: Prednisone
Given PO or IV

Treatment: other: Radiation Therapy
Undergo radiation therapy

Treatment: drugs: Thioguanine
Given PO

Treatment: drugs: Vincristine Sulfate
Given IV

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of DFS of children with HR B-ALL receiving post-Induction age adjusted ITT on an MBFM-IMHDM backbone compared to age adjusted IT MTX - Compared using 2-sided log rank test, alpha = 5%.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 5 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DFS of children, adolescents, and young adults with VHR B-ALL between arms - DFS of children, adolescents, and young adults with VHR B-ALL will be compared in all arms using 1-sided log rank test, alpha 0.025.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 4 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Children and young adults with Ph-like B-ALL and a predicted TKI-sensitive mutation treated with dasatinib plus MBFM-IMHDM</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 10 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increase of greater than or equal to 65% of 5-year DFS and less than 10% induction mortality in patients with DS and HR B-ALL treated with modified Induction and post-Induction therapy regimen with MBFM-IMIDM</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OS rate for HR B-ALL patients - Compared informally between arms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OS rate for VHR B-ALL patients - Compared informally between arms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 4 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of VHR-ALL patients randomized to control versus experimental arms that attain MRD less than or equal to 0.01% upon recovery from consolidation - Compared between control vs experimental arms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 13-14</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Toxicity and tolerability of Experimental arm and Control arm in patients with VHR B-ALL - Graded using the Version 4.0 CTCAE of the NCI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 10 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Toxicity and tolerability of MBFM-IMIDM in children with Down syndrome - Graded using the Version 4.0 CTCAE of the NCI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 10 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Toxicity and tolerability of post-induction age-adjusted ITT compared to age-adjusted IT MTX in children with HR B-ALL - Graded using the Version 4.0 Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) of the NCI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 10 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-  Patients must be enrolled on AALL08B1 prior to enrollment on AALL1131

          -  White Blood Cell Count (WBC) Criteria

               -  Age 1-9.99 years: WBC &gt;= 50 000/uL

               -  Age 10-30.99 years: Any WBC

               -  Age 1-30.99 years: Any WBC with:

                    -  Testicular leukemia

                    -  CNS leukemia (CNS3)

                    -  Steroid pretreatment

          -  Patients must have newly diagnosed B lymphoblastic leukemia (2008 World Health
             Organization [WHO] classification) (also termed B-precursor acute lymphoblastic
             leukemia); patients with Down syndrome are also eligible

          -  Organ function requirements for patients with Ph-like ALL and a predicted
             TKI-sensitive mutation patients identified as Ph-like with a dasatinib-sensitive
             kinase mutation must have assessment of organ function performed within 3 days of
             study entry to be eligible for the dasatinib arm of AALL1131

          -  Creatinine clearance or radioisotope glomerular filtration rate (GFR) &gt; 70mL/min/1.73
             m^2 or a serum creatinine based on age/gender as follows:

               -  Age: Maximum Serum Creatinine (mg/dL)

               -  1 to &lt; 6 months: 0.4 (male) 0.4 (female)

               -  6 months to &lt; 1 year: 0.5 (male) 0.5 (female)

               -  1 to &lt; 2 years: 0.6 (male) 0.6 (female)

               -  2 &lt; 6 years: 0.8 (male) 0.8 (female)

               -  6 to &lt; 10 years: 1.0 (male) 1.0 (female)

               -  10 to &lt; 13 years: 1.2 (male) 1.2 (female)

               -  13 to &lt; 16 years: 1.5 (male) 1.4 (female)

               -  &gt; 16 years: 1.7 (male) 1.4 (female)

          -  Direct bilirubin =&lt; 3 x upper limit of normal (ULN) for age, and

          -  Serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase (SGPT) (alanine aminotransferase [ALT]) =&lt; 10 x
             upper limit of normal (ULN) for age

          -  Shortening fraction &gt;= 27% by echocardiogram, or ejection fraction &gt;= 50% by gated
             radionuclide study

               -  Patients must have an electrocardiogram (EKG) fewer than 6 days prior to
                  enrollment on the dasatinib arm; patients who have had cardiac assessments by
                  echocardiogram or radionuclide scan at the beginning of induction do not need to
                  have these repeated prior to study entry; correct QT interval (QTc) &lt; 450 msec on
                  baseline electrocardiogram as measured by the Frederica or Bazett formula

               -  No major conduction abnormality (unless a cardiac pacemaker is present)

          -  No evidence of dyspnea at rest, no exercise intolerance, and a pulse oximetry &gt; 94% at
             sea level if there is clinical indication for determination

          -  Patients with seizure disorder may be enrolled if on anticonvulsants and well
             controlled; however, drugs that induce CYP3A4/5 (carbamazepine, oxcarbazepine,
             phenytoin, primidone, phenobarbital) should be avoided

          -  Eligibility criteria for the Incidence and Natural History of Osteonecrosis study

               -  Patients must be 10 years of age or greater at the time of B-ALL diagnosis,
                  enrolled on AALL1131

               -  Patients with Down syndrome or Ph-like with a predicted TKI-sensitive mutation
                  are not eligible

          -  Eligibility criteria for the Longitudinal, Computerized Assessment of Neurocognitive
             Functioning study

               -  Patients must be aged 6 to 11 years at time of B-ALL diagnosis, enrolled on
                  AALL1131

               -  Patients must be English-, French- or Spanish-speaking (languages in which the
                  assessment is available)

               -  Patients must have no known history of neurodevelopmental disorder prior to
                  diagnosis of B-ALL (e.g., Down syndrome, Fragile X, William's Syndrome, mental
                  retardation)

               -  Patients must have no significant visual impairment that would prevent computer
                  use and recognition of the visual test stimuli

          -  Eligibility criteria for the National Cancer Institute (NCI) standard risk patients
             from AALL0932 enrolling on this study at the end of Induction

          -  Patients enrolled on AALL0932, without Down syndrome, meeting the following criteria
             will NOT be eligible to continue on AALL0932 but WILL BE eligible to enroll on the HR
             B-ALL stratum of this study at the end of Induction:

               -  Without favorable cytogenetics (no ETV6-RUNX1 or double trisomies 4+10), with day
                  8 peripheral blood (PB) minimal residual disease (MRD) &gt;= 1% and day 29 BM MRD &lt;
                  0.01%

               -  With favorable cytogenetics (ETV6-RUNX1 or double trisomies 4+10), with any day 8
                  PB MRD and day 29 bone marrow (BM) MRD &gt;= 0.01%

               -  Both NCI standard risk (SR) and HR patients without Down syndrome and with
                  testicular disease at diagnosis, who do not meet other VHR criteria, will be
                  eligible for the HR stratum

          -  Patients enrolled on AALL0932, without Down syndrome, meeting the following criteria
             will NOT be eligible to continue on AALL0932 but WILL BE eligible to enroll on the VHR
             B-ALL stratum of this study at the end of Induction:

               -  Intrachromosomal amplification of chromosome 21 (iAMP21)

               -  Mixed-lineage leukemia (MLL) rearrangement

               -  Hypodiploidy (n &lt; 44 chromosomes and/or a deoxyribonucleic acid [DNA] index &lt;
                  0.81)

               -  Induction failure (M3 BM at day 29)

               -  Without favorable cytogenetics (no ETV6-RUNX1 or double trisomies 4+10), with day
                  29 BM MRD &gt;= 0.01%

          -  Patients enrolled on AALL0932, with Down syndrome, meeting the following criteria will
             NOT be eligible to continue on AALL0932 but WILL BE eligible to enroll on the DS HR
             B-ALL stratum of this study at the end of Induction:

               -  Day 29 MRD &gt;= 0.01%

               -  MLL rearrangement

               -  Hypodiploidy (n &lt; 45 chromosomes and/or DNA index &lt; 0.81)

          -  DS HR B-ALL patients initially enrolled on AALL0932 or this study who have Induction
             failure (M3 BM day 29) or Philadelphia chromosome (BCR-ABL1) will not be eligible for
             post-Induction therapy on either trial (AALL0932 or AALL1131)

          -  All patients and/or their parents or legal guardians must sign a written informed
             consent

          -  All institutional, Food and Drug Administration (FDA), and NCI requirements for human
             studies must be met</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Year</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-  With the exception of steroid pretreatment or the administration of intrathecal
             cytarabine, patients must not have received any prior cytotoxic chemotherapy for
             either the current diagnosis of B-ALL or any cancer diagnosed prior to the initiation
             of protocol therapy on AALL1131; patients cannot have secondary B-ALL that developed
             after treatment of a prior malignancy with cytotoxic chemotherapy; patients receiving
             prior steroid therapy may be eligible for AALL1131

          -  Patients with BCR-ABL1 fusion are not eligible for post-induction therapy on this
             study but may be eligible to enroll in a successor Children's Oncology Group (COG)
             Philadelphia positive (Ph+) ALL trial by day 15 Induction

          -  DS HR B-ALL patients with Induction failure or BCR-ABL1

          -  Female patients who are pregnant are ineligible

          -  Lactating females are not eligible unless they have agreed not to breastfeed their
             infant

          -  Female patients of childbearing potential are not eligible unless a negative pregnancy
             test result has been obtained

          -  Sexually active patients of reproductive potential are not eligible unless they have
             agreed to use an effective contraceptive method for the duration of their study
             participation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>27/02/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>5437</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Suspended</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>John Hunter Children's Hospital - Hunter Regional Mail Centre</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Children's Hospital-Brisbane - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Lady Cilento Children's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Women's and Children's Hospital-Adelaide - North Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Center-Clayton Campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Children's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>2310 - Hunter Regional Mail Centre</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>5006 - North Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>6008 - Perth</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alabama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Alaska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arizona</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Arkansas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Colorado</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Connecticut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Delaware</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>District of Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Georgia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Hawaii</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Idaho</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Illinois</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Indiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Iowa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Kentucky</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Louisiana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maine</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Maryland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Massachusetts</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Michigan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Minnesota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Mississippi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Missouri</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nebraska</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Nevada</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Hampshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Jersey</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New Mexico</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>North Dakota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Ohio</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oklahoma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Oregon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Rhode Island</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Carolina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>South Dakota</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Tennessee</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Utah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Vermont</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Washington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>West Virginia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Wisconsin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Manitoba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Newfoundland and Labrador</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Nova Scotia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Saskatchewan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <state>Co Dublin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Puerto Rico</country>
      <state>San Juan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Geneva</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state>Lausanne</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This randomized phase III trial studies how well combination chemotherapy works in treating
      young patients with newly diagnosed B acute lymphoblastic leukemia that is likely to come
      back or spread, and in patients with Philadelphia chromosome (Ph)-like tyrosine kinase
      inhibitor (TKI) sensitive mutations. Drugs used in chemotherapy work in different ways to
      stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping them from dividing,
      or by stopping them from spreading. Giving more than one drug (combination chemotherapy) and
      giving the drugs in different doses and in different combinations may kill more cancer cells.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02883049</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael Burke</name>
      <address>Children's Oncology Group</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>