<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="5708">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/11/2014</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT02296905</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pharmacokinetics and Safety of ABT-493 and/or ABT-530 in Subjects With Normal and Impaired Hepatic Function</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pharmacokinetics and Safety of ABT-493 and/or ABT-530 in Subjects With Normal and Impaired Hepatic Function</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>M13-604</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hepatic Impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Liver</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - ABT-493
Treatment: drugs - ABT-530

Experimental: Group I - Subjects with mild hepatic impairment

Experimental: Group II - Subjects with moderate hepatic impairment

Experimental: Group III - Subjects with severe hepatic impairment

Experimental: Group IV - Subjects with normal hepatic function


Treatment: drugs: ABT-493
Up to 2 single doses of ABT-493 will be given orally in combination with ABT-530.

Treatment: drugs: ABT-530
Up to 3 single doses of ABT-530 will be given orally alone or in combination with ABT-493.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall measurement of pharmacokinetic parameter values of ABT-493 and ABT-530 - Pharmacokinetic parameter values include the maximum plasma concentration (Cmax), the terminal phase elimination rate constant (B), the area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC) from time 0 to time of the last measurable concentration (AUCt).</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall measurement of safety parameters - Measurement of safety parameters include physical examinations, clinical laboratory tests, 12-lead ECGs (electrocardiograms) and vital signs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 38 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of subjects with adverse events</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 58 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All Subjects

          -  If female, subject must be either postmenopausal for at least 2 years or surgically
             sterile (bilateral tubal ligation, bilateral oophorectomy or hysterectomy).

          -  Females must have negative results for pregnancy test performed:

               -  At Screening on a urine specimen obtained within 28 days prior to initial study
                  drug administration, and

               -  On a serum sample obtained on Study Day -1 of Period 1.

          -  Males must be surgically sterile or practicing at least one of the following methods
             of birth control (sperm donation within the study period is not allowed):

               -  Abstinence

               -  Partner(s) using an Intrauterine Device (IUD)

               -  Partner(s) using oral, injected, or implanted methods of hormonal contraceptives

               -  Subject and/or partner(s) using double-barrier method.

        Subjects with Normal Hepatic Function

        In addition to the inclusion criteria above for all subjects, the following criteria must
        be met for subjects with normal hepatic function enrolled in Group IV:

          -  Judged to be in general good health based upon the results of a medical history,
             physical examination, laboratory profile (including liver function parameters within
             the limits of normal) and 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG).

          -  Negative hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) and hepatitis C virus antibody (HCV Ab)
             test results.

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) is = 18 to &lt; 38 kg/m2, inclusive.

        Subjects with Hepatic Impairment

        In addition to the inclusion criteria for all subjects, the following criteria must be met
        for all subjects with hepatic impairment enrolled in Groups I, II and III:

          -  Judged to be in stable condition and acceptable for study participation based upon the
             results of a medical history, physical examination, laboratory profile and ECG.

          -  BMI is = 18 to &lt; 38 kg/m2, inclusive, for subjects with hepatic impairment without
             ascites or subjects with subclinical ascites detected only by ultrasound or other
             imaging. For subjects with hepatic impairment and clinically significant ascites, BMI
             is permitted in the range between = 18 to &lt; 40 kg/m2, inclusive.

          -  Child-Pugh classification of Categories A (mild), B (moderate), or C (severe).

          -  Medical history of chronic liver disease including and not limited to chronic
             hepatitis B, history of alcoholic liver disease and chronic hepatitis C.

          -  Presence of clinically significant hepatic impairment as indicated by either:

               1. Evidence of liver cirrhosis OR

               2. Medical history of at least one of the following criteria:

                    -  Clinical diagnosis of liver disease

                    -  Total bilirubin, &gt; 2 mg/dl, with indirect/direct ratio &lt; 1 or prolonged
                       prothrombin time elevation &gt; 1.7 or an albumin value below the lower limit
                       of the laboratory reference range and excluding non-hepatic causes of the
                       previous laboratory abnormalities.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- History of significant sensitivity to any drug.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding female.

          -  Recent (6-month) history of drug or alcohol abuse.

          -  Positive test result for hepatitis A virus immunoglobulin M (HAV-IgM) or human
             immunodeficiency virus antibody (HIV Ab). Negative HIV status will be confirmed at
             Screening and the results will be maintained confidentially by the study site.

          -  Detectable HCV RNA.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Basic Science</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/10/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize />
    <actualsamplesize>24</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/09/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Florida</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Grafton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AbbVie</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is an open-label, single-dose study designed to assess the pharmacokinetics and safety
      of ABT-493 and/or ABT-530 in subjects with impaired hepatic function and compare them to
      those in subjects with normal hepatic function.

      Twenty-four subjects will be selected and enrolled according to the subject selection
      criteria: 6 subjects with mild stable chronic hepatic impairment (Group I), 6 subjects with
      moderate stable chronic hepatic impairment (Group II), 6 subjects with severe stable chronic
      hepatic impairment (Group III) and 6 subjects with normal hepatic function (Group IV).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02296905</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>David Pugatch, MD</name>
      <address>AbbVie</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>