<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='ctgovTransform.xsl'?>
<CT.GOV_Trial requestNumber="6621">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/12/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/12/2011</approvaldate>
  <nctid>NCT01506856</nctid>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Intraperitoneal Therapy For Ovarian Cancer With Carboplatin Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized Phase II/III Trial of Intravenous (IV) Paclitaxel Weekly Plus IV Carboplatin Once Every 3 Weeks Versus IV Paclitaxel Weekly Plus Intraperitoneal (IP) Carboplatin Once Every 3 Weeks in Women With Epithelial Ovarian, Fallopian Tube or Primary Peritoneal Cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>iPocc</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>UMIN000003670</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>GOTIC-001/JGOG3019</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Epithelial Ovarian Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fallopian Tube Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Primary Peritoneal Carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Womb (Uterine or endometrial cancer)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment: drugs - Paclitaxel(intravenous) + Carboplatin(intravenous)
Treatment: drugs - Paclitaxel(intravenous) + Carboplatin(intraperitoneal)

Active Comparator: Standard treatment: dd-TCiv therapy - Paclitaxel administered by IV infusion weekly plus concurrent carboplatin administered by IV infusion once every 3 weeks

Experimental: Study treatment: dd-TCip therapy - Paclitaxel administered by IV infusion weekly plus concurrent carboplatin administered by IP injection once every 3 weeks


Treatment: drugs: Paclitaxel(intravenous) + Carboplatin(intravenous)
Paclitaxel(intravenous) + Carboplatin(intravenous) Paclitaxel : 80mg/m2, IV infusion, Day1, 8, and 15 Carboplatin: AUC=6.0, IV infusion, Day1 A total of 6 to 8 cycles will be repeated.

Treatment: drugs: Paclitaxel(intravenous) + Carboplatin(intraperitoneal)
Paclitaxel(intravenous) + Carboplatin(intraperitoneal) Paclitaxel : 80mg/m2, IV infusion, Day1, 8, and 15 Carboplatin: AUC=6.0, IP injection, Day1 A total of 6 to 8 cycles will be repeated.

</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-free survival(PFS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of randomization until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed until 510 events are observed or until 3 years from the last patient is randomized to the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival (OS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>weekly during the protocl treatment, then every 3 months for the first 2 years, 6-month for the following 2 years, and once a year thereafter</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tumor response (only patients with evaluable disease)</outcome>
      <timepoint>every 2 cycles [after 2 cycles, after 4 cycles, after 6 cycles, (after 8 cycles)], the time of discontinuation of the protocol treatment and then at least annually during follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events</outcome>
      <timepoint>weekly during the protocl treatment, then every 3 months for the first 2 years, 6-month for the following 2 years, and once a year thereafter</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment completion rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the last cycle of the protocol teatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life (QOL) assessments</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, after 3 cycles, 6 cycles, 36 week, 60 weeks and 84 weeks from the start of protocol treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost-utility analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, after 3 cycles, 6 cycles, 36 week, 60 weeks and 84 weeks from the start of protocol treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients assumed to have a stageII-IV epithelial ovarian, fallopian tube, or primary
             peritoneal cancer as a pre-surgery diagnosis

          2. Patients scheduled to undergo laparotomy

             *Both optimal and suboptimal patients will be eligible for the study (Suboptimal
             patients, as well as those who undergo only exploratory laparotomy, are eligible.)

          3. ECOG Performance Status: 0-2

          4. Patients who provide consent for placement of the IP port system, if randomized to
             Regimen II (Study treatment: dd-TCip therapy)

          5. Patients expected to receive the first protocol treatment within 8 weeks after the
             comprehensive staging surgery

          6. Lab data and clinical examination: Data within 28 days before the scheduled date of
             surgery

               -  Neutrophil count ? 1,500 /mm3

               -  Platelet count ? 100,000 /mm3

               -  AST (GOT) ? 100 IU/L

               -  ALT (GPT) ? 100 IU/L

               -  Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 mg/dL

               -  Serum Creatinine &lt; 1.5 mg/dL

               -  Electrocardiogram (ECG): Patients with normal ECG, Asymptomatic patients with
                  abnormal ECGs not requiring medical intervention

               -  Neuropathy(Both motor and sensory) ? Grade1 (CTCAE Version 4.0)

          7. Patients expected to survive longer than 3 months from the start date of the protocol
             treatment

          8. Patients aged 20 years and older at the time of tentative registration (with no upper
             age limit)

          9. Patients who provide written informed consent for participation in this trial</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Female</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients assumed to have a borderline malignancy of the ovary, fallopian tube, or
             primary peritoneal cancer

          2. Patients who have received previous chemotherapy or radiation therapy to treat the
             current disease

          3. Patients who have a synchronous malignancy or who have been progression-free less than
             5 years for a metachronous malignancy (Patients with basal and squamous cell carcinoma
             of the skin, as well as carcinoma in situ, and intramucosal carcinoma cured by local
             treatment, are eligible for the study)

          4. Patients with serious medical complications, such as serious heart disease,
             cerebrovascular accidents, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, uncontrolled hypertension,
             pulmonary fibrosis, interstitial pneumonitis, active bleeding, an active
             gastrointestinal ulcer, or a serious neurological disorder

          5. Patients who have had a hypersensitivity reaction to polyoxyethylated or hydrogenated
             castor oil

          6. Patients with a pleural effusion requiring continuous drainage

          7. Patients with an active infection requiring antibiotics

          8. Patients who are pregnant, nursing or of child-bearing potential

          9. Patients with evidence upon physical examination of brain tumor and any brain
             metastases

         10. Patients for whom completion of this study and/or follow-up is deemed inappropriate
             for any reason

         11. Patients with any signs/symptoms of interstitial pneumonia</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>654</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/05/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States</country>
      <state>Pennsylvania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Pokfulam Road</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Aichi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Aomori</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Chiba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Ehime</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Fukui</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Fukuoka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Gunma</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hiroshima</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Hyogo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Ibaraki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Iwate</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Kagoshima</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Kanagawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Mie</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Miyagi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Nagano</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Nagasaki</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Nara</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Niigata</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Okinawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Osaka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Saitama</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Shizuoka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tochigi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tokyo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Tottori</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Yamaguchi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Kyoto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Gongneung-Dong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      <state>Seoul</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state>Bukit Timah</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state>Lower Kent Ridge Road</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Gynecologic Oncology Trial &amp; Investigation Consortium</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Japanese Gynecologic Oncology Group</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress />
      <othercollaboratorcountry />
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is:

      Phase A: To confirm the feasibility of paclitaxel administered by intravenous (IV) infusion
      weekly plus concurrent carboplatin administered by intraperitoneal (IP) injection once every
      3 weeks (dd-TCip therapy).

      Phase B: To compare the efficacy and safety of the following two treatment regimens as
      first-line chemotherapy in women with epithelial ovarian, Fallopian tube or primary
      peritoneal cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01506856</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Bristow RE, Tomacruz RS, Armstrong DK, Trimble EL, Montz FJ. Survival effect of maximal cytoreductive surgery for advanced ovarian carcinoma during the platinum era: a meta-analysis. J Clin Oncol. 2002 Mar 1;20(5):1248-59.
Neijt JP, Engelholm SA, Tuxen MK, Sorensen PG, Hansen M, Sessa C, de Swart CA, Hirsch FR, Lund B, van Houwelingen HC. Exploratory phase III study of paclitaxel and cisplatin versus paclitaxel and carboplatin in advanced ovarian cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2000 Sep;18(17):3084-92.
Piccart MJ, Bertelsen K, James K, Cassidy J, Mangioni C, Simonsen E, Stuart G, Kaye S, Vergote I, Blom R, Grimshaw R, Atkinson RJ, Swenerton KD, Trope C, Nardi M, Kaern J, Tumolo S, Timmers P, Roy JA, Lhoas F, Lindvall B, Bacon M, Birt A, Andersen JE, Zee B, Paul J, Baron B, Pecorelli S. Randomized intergroup trial of cisplatin-paclitaxel versus cisplatin-cyclophosphamide in women with advanced epithelial ovarian cancer: three-year results. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2000 May 3;92(9):699-708.
Ozols RF, Bundy BN, Greer BE, Fowler JM, Clarke-Pearson D, Burger RA, Mannel RS, DeGeest K, Hartenbach EM, Baergen R; Gynecologic Oncology Group. Phase III trial of carboplatin and paclitaxel compared with cisplatin and paclitaxel in patients with optimally resected stage III ovarian cancer: a Gynecologic Oncology Group study. J Clin Oncol. 2003 Sep 1;21(17):3194-200. Epub 2003 Jul 14.
Katsumata N, Yasuda M, Takahashi F, Isonishi S, Jobo T, Aoki D, Tsuda H, Sugiyama T, Kodama S, Kimura E, Ochiai K, Noda K; Japanese Gynecologic Oncology Group. Dose-dense paclitaxel once a week in combination with carboplatin every 3 weeks for advanced ovarian cancer: a phase 3, open-label, randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2009 Oct 17;374(9698):1331-8. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(09)61157-0. Epub 2009 Sep 18.
Alberts DS, Liu PY, Hannigan EV, O'Toole R, Williams SD, Young JA, Franklin EW, Clarke-Pearson DL, Malviya VK, DuBeshter B. Intraperitoneal cisplatin plus intravenous cyclophosphamide versus intravenous cisplatin plus intravenous cyclophosphamide for stage III ovarian cancer. N Engl J Med. 1996 Dec 26;335(26):1950-5.
Markman M, Bundy BN, Alberts DS, Fowler JM, Clark-Pearson DL, Carson LF, Wadler S, Sickel J. Phase III trial of standard-dose intravenous cisplatin plus paclitaxel versus moderately high-dose carboplatin followed by intravenous paclitaxel and intraperitoneal cisplatin in small-volume stage III ovarian carcinoma: an intergroup study of the Gynecologic Oncology Group, Southwestern Oncology Group, and Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group. J Clin Oncol. 2001 Feb 15;19(4):1001-7.
Armstrong DK, Bundy B, Wenzel L, Huang HQ, Baergen R, Lele S, Copeland LJ, Walker JL, Burger RA; Gynecologic Oncology Group. Intraperitoneal cisplatin and paclitaxel in ovarian cancer. N Engl J Med. 2006 Jan 5;354(1):34-43.
Miyagi Y, Fujiwara K, Kigawa J, Itamochi H, Nagao S, Aotani E, Terakawa N, Kohno I; Sankai Gynecology Study Group (SGSG). Intraperitoneal carboplatin infusion may be a pharmacologically more reasonable route than intravenous administration as a systemic chemotherapy. A comparative pharmacokinetic analysis of platinum using a new mathematical model after intraperitoneal vs. intravenous infusion of carboplatin--a Sankai Gynecology Study Group (SGSG) study. Gynecol Oncol. 2005 Dec;99(3):591-6. Epub 2005 Aug 10.
Fujiwara K, Armstrong D, Morgan M, Markman M. Principles and practice of intraperitoneal chemotherapy for ovarian cancer. Int J Gynecol Cancer. 2007 Jan-Feb;17(1):1-20. Review.
Demets DL. Futility approaches to interim monitoring by data monitoring committees. Clin Trials. 2006;3(6):522-9. Review.
Huang HQ, Brady MF, Cella D, Fleming G. Validation and reduction of FACT/GOG-Ntx subscale for platinum/paclitaxel-induced neurologic symptoms: a gynecologic oncology group study. Int J Gynecol Cancer. 2007 Mar-Apr;17(2):387-93.
Calvert AH, Newell DR, Gumbrell LA, O'Reilly S, Burnell M, Boxall FE, Siddik ZH, Judson IR, Gore ME, Wiltshaw E. Carboplatin dosage: prospective evaluation of a simple formula based on renal function. J Clin Oncol. 1989 Nov;7(11):1748-56.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview />
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Keiichi Fujiwara, MD, PhD</name>
      <address>Saitama Medical University International Medical Center Comprehensive Cancer Center</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</CT.GOV_Trial>