<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367546">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/12/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000016538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effect of Computerised Training on Academic Achievement in Primary School Students</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of computerised cognitive training on executive function, academic achievement and fluid intelligence in Year 3 and Year 5 students.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Executive Functioning</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fluid Reasoning</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Academic Achievement</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This research will test the efficacy of a computerised cognitive training program. The training program runs 5 days per week for 6.5 weeks with 1 x 20 minute session per day. The training will be completed in a classroom with the researcher providing instructions and supervising administration. Progress of individual participants can be monitored by the researcher using an online portal.

The training program involves the completion of a number of game-like cognitive training programs (e.g. selecting a picture that matches a pre-determined rule; selecting coloured balls based on a pre-determined rule; selecting an appropriate card to complete a pattern).

One year after the training is completed, the whole training process is completed over again using the same procedure as outlined above.</interventions>
    <comparator>A computerised touch-typing training program as the control group intervention. The program instructs participants how to touch-type using the correct posture and finger position. It is a graded program that begins with the easier keys and progresses to more complex typing tasks (e.g. capital letters, numbers and symbols).

The control group intervention runs in the same manner as the experimental group: 5 days per week for 6.5 weeks with 1 x 20 minute session per day. The training will be completed in a classroom with the researcher providing instructions and supervising administration. Progress of individual participants can be monitored by the researcher using an online portal.

One year after the training is completed, the whole training process is completed over again using the same procedure as outlined above.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Executive Function Scores based upon 3 tasks each for Working Memory (Reading Span Task; Operation Span Task, Symmetry Span Task), Shifting Ability (Switcher Test, Connections Test, Card Sorting Test) and Inhibition (Flanker Test, Go No-Go Test, Numerical Stroop Test).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre- and Post-training assessments, then again one year after training this is repeated (pre- and post-assessments &amp; retraining).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Academic Achievement as measured by the Progressive Achievement Tests (Maths &amp; Reading).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-training assessment and then one year later.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fluid Reasoning Measure (Naglieri Non-verbal Achievement Test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre- and post-training assessment and then repeated again one year later (pre- and post-training assessment &amp; retraining)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Implicit Theory of Intelligence measure (survey)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-training assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Behavioural observation by teacher and parent of executive functioning abilities (using the Comprehensive Executive Functioning Inventory).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre- and post-training assessment and then repeated one year later (pre- and post-training assessment &amp; retraining).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement expectancy measure (survey assessment). This measure has been designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Given one week after the commencement of training course.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>A random sample of Year 3 and Year 5 students from a boys-only school.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Previous research using sample sizes of 20-30 for the experimental group has found effect sizes for near transfer (i.e. working memory) in the range 0.41 to 4.66. However, the same sample sizes for far transfer (i.e. academic achievement, fluid reasoning) have found non-significant (p&gt;0.05) small effect sizes (~0.25). It has been suggested that this is due to small sample sizes and a lack of power. Therefore, this research will use larger sample sizes to pick up the effect of training on far transfer.

Data analysis will determine if there is a treatment effect on executive function dependent variables by using latent growth modelling. Latent growth models use structural equation modelling techniques to model trajectories of change, assess effects of treatment, and consider the relationships among multiple outcome variables and multiple time points simultaneously (Stull et al., 2011). As outlined by Muthen and Curran (1997), the effect of treatment is assessed by comparing the set of trajectories in the treatment population with those in the control population.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>10/10/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>28/08/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>115</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>24/09/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2061 - Milsons Point</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney, Dr Paul Ginns</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>A35 Education Building
University of Sydney
Sydney NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>David Hegarty</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO BOX 3082
Dural 2158</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research aims to test the efficacy of a computerised, adaptive, cognitive training program by looking at near-transfer to executive function components and far-transfer to higher order cognitive abilities (fluid intelligence and academic achievement).

This research will address previous criticisms of the existing cognitive training literature by: (a) using a cognitive training program that is more aligned to current executive function theory than previous research, by training executive level processes; (b) using multiple measures for each executive function construct to estimate latent scores of executive functions; (c) using randomly allocated experimental and active control groups that utilise similar computer-based tasks and have the same face-to-face contact time so that a realistic comparison can be made as to the efficacy of the cognitive training program; (d) determining the impact of cognitive training on executive functions, fluid intelligence and academic achievement by following a cohort of children over a period of one year; (e) measuring processing speed to determine if this is a potential mediating variable in cognitive training; and (f) assessing the impact of different training expectancies between the experimental and control group and its impact upon training gains. In addition to these student-based measures, behaviourally- based reports from teachers and parents will provide additional sources of evidence of the programs effects. Lastly, the potential moderating effect of an individual's implicit theory of intelligence on training gains will be assessed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, Jane Foss Russell The University of Sydney NSW 2006 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014/780</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Paul Ginns</name>
      <address>Room 914
A35 Education Building
University of Sydney
Sydney, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61293512611</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.ginns@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Hegarty</name>
      <address>PO BOX 3082
Dural NSW 2158

Work:
St Aloysius' College
29 Burton Street
Milsons Point
NSW 2061</address>
      <phone>+61414627911</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dheg5471@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Hegarty</name>
      <address>PO BOX 3082
Dural NSW 2158

Work:
St Aloysius' College
29 Burton Street
Milsons Point
NSW 2061</address>
      <phone>+61414627911</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dheg5471@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Hegarty</name>
      <address>PO BOX 3082
Dural NSW 2158</address>
      <phone>+61414627911</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dheg5471@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>