<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370166">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000256471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exploring the link between alcohol and atrial fibrillation recurrence:  a multicentre randomised controlled trial (ETOH-AF)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Exploring the link between alcohol and atrial fibrillation recurrence:  a multicentre randomised controlled trial (ETOH-AF)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1179-9127</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ETOH-AF</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atrial fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Atrial flutter</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Alcohol abuse</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiomyopathy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive sleep apnoea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Alcohol abstinence: All patients in this arm will be encouraged and counselled to abstain completely from all forms of alcohol for a 12-month period. They will have a one-on-one 15-minute session with a specialist physician at 0,3,6,9 and 12 months, as would occur in routine clinical practice (note patients with alcohol dependence are excluded from the study). Attendance will be recorded. They will be provided written advice and links to online resources to assist them. Patients with initial difficulty in abstaining from alcohol will be referred to a clinician with specialized expertise in alcohol-related counselling, brief intervention and anti-craving therapy. Compliance will be monitored by weekly alcohol consumption diaries, weekly phone calls, as well as random urine testing for alcohol metabolites (urine ETG, pending funding).

Patients in both arms will have a 1 month run-in phase prior to being formally randomized - they will be required to submit weekly alcohol diaries. This will assess their compliance and also ensure they meet the inclusion criteria for alcohol intake.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control arm: Patients in this control group will be advised they can continue their usual alcohol consumption. However, they will be provided written &amp; verbal information about recommended safe levels of drinking and encouraged to have regular follow-up with their usual treating clinician.

Patients in both arms will have a 1 month run-in phase prior to being formally randomized - they will be required to submit weekly alcohol diaries. This will assess their compliance and also ensure they meet the inclusion criteria for alcohol intake.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Atrial fibrillation / flutter (AF) burden - percentage of time spent in AF during the follow-up period (as assessed by either 3-monthly 7-day Holter monitor + symptom review with ECG, loop recorder or dual-chamber pacemaker).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>From start of intervention to 6 months later (NB: For ABSTAIN-PVI patients only, analysis will occur after a 2-month blanking period after their ablation procedure) </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first AF recurrence (by either Holter monitor, loop recorder, dual-chamber pacemaker, or ECG during symptoms)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within the first 6 months from start of intervention (NB: For ABSTAIN-PVI patients only, analysis will occur after a 2-month blanking period after their ablation procedure) </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospitalisations for AF (by review of medical records and ECGs during hospitalisation)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within the first 12 months from start of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure (over brachial artery, measured by sphygmomanometer)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 0, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight (measured by digital scales)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 0, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AF symptom severity, as measured by AF symptom severity questionnaire (AFSS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 0, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life, as assessed by SF-36 Quality of Life Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6, 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression, as assessed by % with Beck depression score &gt; 10</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6, 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Left atrial size, as assessed by echocardiography (LA diameter, LA area, LA volume)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Left ventricular hypertrophy (left ventricular mass &amp; LV mass index) as assessed by echocardiography</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Left atrial strain on echocardiography (pending software availability)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF), as assessed on echocardiography</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI LV end-diastolic volume index (LVEDVI) (optional sub study, pending funding) 


</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 - 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of AF recurrences (as measured by either Holter monitor, loop recorder, dual-chamber pacemaker, or ECG during symptoms)</outcome>
      <timepoint>In first 12 months from start of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Metabolic profile (serum fasting lipids and glucose)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI LV mass index (optional sub study, pending funding) 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 - 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI LV ejection fraction (optional sub study, pending funding) 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 - 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI LV tissue characterisation (optional sub study, pending funding) using T1 mapping, STIR, late Gadolinium enhancement
</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 - 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI left atrial function - using strain, LA ejection fraction, LA passive emptying fraction (optional sub study, pending funding)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 - 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI left atrial volume (optional sub study, pending funding)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 - 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI left atrial tissue characterisation with T1 mapping (optional sub study, pending funding)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 - 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac MRI left atrial area (optional sub study, pending funding)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 6 - 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Liver function (serum LFTs)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Atrial fibrillation / flutter (AF) burden - percentage of time spent in AF during the follow-up period (as assessed by either 3-monthly 7-day Holter monitor + symptom review with ECG, loop recorder or dual-chamber pacemaker). </outcome>
      <timepoint>From start of intervention to 12 months later (NB: For ABSTAIN-PVI patients only, analysis will occur after a 2-month blanking period after their ablation procedure)
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first AF recurrence (by either Holter monitor, loop recorder, dual-chamber pacemaker, or ECG during symptoms)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within the first 12 months from start of intervention (NB: For ABSTAIN-PVI patients only, analysis will occur after a 2-month blanking period after their ablation procedure)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in AF burden  comparison between percentage of time spent in AF during the follow-up period (as assessed by either 3-monthly 7-day Holter monitor + symptom review with ECG, loop recorder or dual-chamber pacemaker) and baseline burden 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Comparison between 0 &amp; 6 months, comparison between 0 &amp; 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>European Heart Rhythm Association (EHRA) score for AF-related symptoms</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Paroxysmal AF (atrial fibrillation and/or flutter) with minimum 2 episodes in the last 6 months or persistent AF requiring direct cardioversion
- Average alcohol intake at least 10 standard drinks per week (120 g/week).

To be eligible for the sub-study (ABSTAIN-PVI), patients will need to have had a previous pulmonary vein isolation (AF ablation) procedure (in addition to the above criteria).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Evidence of alcohol dependence (as determined by CAGE  &amp; AUDIT-C questionnaires)
- Presence of significant psychiatric comorbidity or cognitive impairment
- Permanent AF (where sinus rhythm cannot be restored)
- Advanced heart failure, as defined by left ventricular ejection fraction &lt; 35%.
- Limited life expectancy (less than 24 months) due to co-morbid non-cardiac illness, including liver failure, end-stage renal disease or advanced malignancy. 

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>There will be initial concealment of allocation from study investigators (using central randomisation by a computer)</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>For ETOH-AF, the sample size calculation for the primary endpoint of time to AF recurrence assumes an annual recurrence rate of 30% based on preliminary data. To detect a minimum absolute difference in recurrence of 20% between groups, we will need to enrol 70 patients in each group to provide a power of 0.8 at an alpha value of 0.05.

For the ABSTAIN-PVI sub-study, we estimate a recurrence rate of 35% in abstainers and 81% in drinkers based on preliminary data. To detect a minimum absolute difference in recurrence of 20% between groups, we will need to enrol 17 patients in each group to provide a power of 0.8 at an alpha value of 0.05.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/04/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>174</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Western Hospital - Footscray</hospital>
    <hospital>Sunshine Hospital - St Albans</hospital>
    <hospital>Cabrini Hospital - Malvern - Malvern</hospital>
    <hospital>Melbourne Private Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3011 - Footscray</postcode>
    <postcode>3020 - Sunshine</postcode>
    <postcode>3144 - Malvern</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Peter Kistler</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Heart Centre, Alfred Hospital, Commercial Rd, Prahran, Vic, 3181</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Prof Peter Kistler</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Heart Centre, Alfred Hospital, Commercial Rd, Prahran, Vic, 3181</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Aleksandr Voskoboinik</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Heart Centre, Alfred Hospital, Commercial Rd, Prahran, Vic, 3181</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Prof Jonathan Kalman</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Cardiology, Royal Melbourne Hospital, Grattan St, Parkville, Vic, 3052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Emily Kotschet</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Cardiology, Monash Medical Centre, Clayton Rd, Clayton, Vic, 3168</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Michael Wong</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Cardiology, Western Hospital, Gordon St, Footscray, Vic, 3011</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>A/Prof Omar Farouque</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Cardiology, Austin Hospital, Studley Rd, Heidelberg, Vic, 3084</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>ETOH-AF trial:
While the association between binge drinking and atrial tachyarrhythmias is well-established, even moderate alcohol consumption has recently been identified as a significant risk factor for atrial fibrillation and/or flutter (AF) in a dose-dependent manner. To date, there have been no randomised-controlled trials looking at the impact of alcohol abstinence on AF outcomes. Moreover, we are keen to look at the overall effects of alcohol abstinence on other cardiovascular outcomes (inc. blood pressure, cardiac structure and function, sleep apnoea) and non-cardiovascular outcomes (inc. quality of life, mood). We hypothesise that alcohol abstinence will reduce AF recurrences, AF burden, AF symptoms and AF hospitalisations, as well as resulting in reductions in LV size, LA size, sleep apnoea parameters and blood pressure, and improvements in LA &amp; LV function, mood and quality of life.

We intend to recruit at least 140 patients and randomise them to either an alcohol Abstinence or Control arm, and follow them up for 12 months (with a 1 month run-in phase prior). Alcohol consumption in both arms will be monitored using weekly alcohol diaries, urine ETG (pending funding) and blood tests (inc. MCV, GGT).

Monitoring for AF recurrences will occur by either:
(i) Insertion of an implantable loop recorder OR
(ii) Wearing a 7-day Holter monitor every 3 months +/- ECG transmission using the AliveECG smartphone app (if available) +/- ECG during symptoms of AF
(iii) Interrogation of permanent pacemakers/defibrillators every 3 months in those with pre-existing dual chamber devices.

Baseline and follow-up data collected includes:
12-lead ECG - 0 and 12 months.
Blood pressure and weight - 0,3,6,9,12 months.
Sleep study	- 0 and 12 months.
Basic bloods (lipids, glucose, FBE, UEC, LFT, BNP) - 0,6,12 months.
Transthoracic echocardiogram (inc. LV size &amp; EF, LA size, LA strain) - 0 and 12 months.
AF symptom severity questionnaire (AFSS) &amp; Medical questionnaire - 0,3,6,9,12 months.
Mood &amp; quality of life questionnaires - 0 &amp; 12 months.
Cardiac MRI substudy (pending funding) - 0 and 6-12 months.

We will also be looking at a subgroup of patients who have had a previous pulmonary vein isolation  (ABSTAIN-PVI substudy) to determine whether alcohol abstinence is beneficial in this sub-population. The trial protocol is unchanged (inc. outcomes) for these patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil to date</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>If you have  atrial fibrillation or flutter and consume more than 10 drinks of alcohol per week, and are keen to enrol in a trial looking at the effects of alcohol abstinence, please email etoh.af@gmail.com</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Hospital, Commercial Rd, Prahran, Vic, 3181</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/01/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/Alfred/84</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Kistler</name>
      <address>Heart Centre, Alfred Hospital, Commercial Rd, Prahran, Vic, 3181</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1427</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.kistler@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Aleksandr Voskoboinik</name>
      <address>Heart Centre, Alfred Hospital, Commercial Rd, Prahran, Vic, 3181</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90762000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 80800747</fax>
      <email>a.voskoboinik@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Aleksandr Voskoboinik</name>
      <address>Heart Centre, Alfred Hospital, Commercial Rd, Prahran, Vic.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90762000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 80800747</fax>
      <email>a.voskoboinik@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Aleksandr Voskoboinik</name>
      <address>Heart Centre, Alfred Hospital, Commercial Rd, Prahran, Vic.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90762000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 80800747</fax>
      <email>a.voskoboinik@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>