<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369584">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000733471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does treatment of Obstructive Sleep Apnoea in patients with Mild Cognitive Impairment improve cognition and mood?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of Positive Airway Pressure therapy on cognition and mood in patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnoea and Mild Cognitive Impairment</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>COMM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnoea</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Phase 1.
The STOP-bang questionnaire will be used in memory clinics to screening for patients who are at risk of having obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA). Patients with memory impairment and have a moderate-high risk of having OSA based on the questionnaire (STOP-bang score of 3 or more) will be invited to take part in Phase 1 which includes an overnight sleep study and a neuropsychological testing session. The overnight diagnostic sleep study will be conducted in-lab at the RMIT Sleep Laboratory, Bundoora or at-home with a portable sleep recording device by a trained sleep lab staff. On the following morning, a baseline 90-minute neuropsychological testing session will be conducted. The sleep study will be reviewed by the study's sleep physician. Participants with moderate to severe obstructive sleep apnoea and recommended CPAP by the study's sleep physician will proceed into Phase 2.

Phase 2. 
Auto Positive Airway Pressure (AutoPAP) therapy will be used as the intervention. Positive airway pressure therapy involves a AutoPAP machine with three basic parts: (i) an air pump; (ii) a mask that fits over the nose or/and mouth and; (iii) a tube that connects the machine and mask. The AutoPAP machine will be used daily during sleep for 3 months.

An introductory Auto CPAP session along with a mask fitting session will be conducted by trained sleep lab staff. Participants will be required to use the machine at home daily following the initial 30-minute introductory session. The AutoPAP machine adjusts and varies the pressure breath to breath throughout the night automatically, with a minimum pressure of 4 and maximum pressure of 20.

Participants will be followed-up via phone calls throughout the 3-month intervention to troubleshoot issues and encourage optimal usage. Phone calls will be conducted on the day after first AutoPAP usage followed by, weekly phone calls for the first month and monthly phone calls for the next two months.</interventions>
    <comparator>This study is a randomised partial cross-over study. The study intervention will be compared against those who are not receiving the positive airway pressure treatment. The control group will be offered CPAP intervention 3 months after the baseline test-battery was administered. Prior to starting the intervention, the control group will be required to undergo a second test-battery.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Addenbrooke's Cognitive Examination-Revised (ACE-R) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Geriatrics Depression Scale (GDS) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>STOP-bang questionnaire score (Prevalence of those who are at low, moderate and high risk of having Obstructive Sleep Apnoea)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase prior to baseline </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rey-Osterrieth complex figure test (ROCF) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Verbal Paired Associates score from the Wechsler Memory Scale (WMS-IV)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Logical Memory score from the Wechsler Memory Scale (WMS-IV)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital Anxiety-Depression Scale (HADS) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Coding and Symbol Search sub-tests score from the Weschler Adult Intelligence Scale (WAIS-IV)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Digit Span sub-test score from the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale (WAIS-IV)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trail Making A &amp; B test score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The key inclusion criteria includes untreated Obstructive Sleep Apnoea with an Apnoea-Hypopnoea Index (AHI) of 15 or more, clinically significant memory impairment and English fluency.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if memory impairment is due to stroke, epilepsy or traumatic brain injury. Other exclusion criteria includes sleep disorders other than OSA, learning disability and alcohol or drug dependence .</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involves contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is at the central administration site.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Partial-crossover</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>.GPower (version 3.1.7) analysis was conducted to calculate the sample size required to detect statistical significance with 70% power, alpha = .05, a small to medium effect size f = .20, and an assumed correlation of 0.5, based on previous evaluations of CPAP intervention for OSA in elderly patients. This indicated that a sample size of N=30 (i.e. 15 participants in each group) is required. To account for attrition, we have included 20% additional participants, thus require N = 36 (18 participants in each group).

The statistical analysis will be a mixed effects analysis of variance (ANOVA), which will account for systemic individual difference in outcome measures between the control and patient group for Phase 1, and between the immediate CPAP and waitlist group in Phase 2.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>5/11/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/08/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital - Heidelberg West</hospital>
    <hospital>The Northern Hospital - Epping</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3076 - Epping</postcode>
    <postcode>3083 - Bundoora</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>RMIT University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>RMIT University, Plenty Road, Bundoora VIC 3083</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>RMIT University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>RMIT University, Plenty Road, Bundoora VIC 3083</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Sleep-related breathing disorder has been commonly reported in elderly individuals with mild cognitive impairment. This project is interested in examining the prevalence of Obstructive Sleep Apnoea (OSA) in patients attending the Cognitive, Dementia, and Memory Service (CDAMS) at Northern Health and Austin Health. Also, this project aims to determine if 3 months of CPAP therapy for OSA in patients with memory impairments improves mood and memory.

Firstly, patients attending CDAMS with memory impairment will be screened for OSA and patients who have a high risk of OSA will be invited to take part in Phase 1. Interested participants will be invited to attend the RMIT Sleep Laboratory for a 90-minute neuropsychological testing session and an overnight diagnostic polysomnography (PSG). Healthy age-matched controls will also undergo the same neuropsychological testing and overnight PSG to investigate differences in cognition and memory of individuals with memory impairment and healthy individuals.

Patients who are diagnosed with OSA and recommended Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) by the study physician will be invited to participate in Phase 2 the project. Participants will be randomised to either an immediate CPAP group or a 3-month wait-list group. Participants in the immediate CPAP condition will be given an auto-titrating PAP machine and asked to use their CPAP at home. After 3 months of CPAP therapy, participants will attend a second appointment at the Sleep Laboratory to complete follow-up tests and questionnaires. Patients in the wait-list condition will commence CPAP after 3 months and the same follow-up procedures will be followed as per the immediate CPAP group.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Northern Health,
The Northern Hospital,
185 Cooper Street
Epping Victoria 3076</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/NH/7</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>L8 Harold Stokes Building, Austin Health
145 Studley Road, Heidelberg, 3084 VIC </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/Austin/393</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>RMIT Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>RMIT University
GPO Box 2476
Building 91, Level 2
MELBOURNE  VIC  3001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/09/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>19269</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Melinda Jackson</name>
      <address>RMIT University
School of Health and Biomedical Sciences 
RMIT University, PO Box 71
Bundoora, Vic. 3083, Australia</address>
      <phone>+613 9925 7564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>melinda.jackson@rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>V Vien Lee</name>
      <address>RMIT University
School of Health and Biomedical Sciences 
RMIT University, PO Box 71
Bundoora, Vic. 3083, Australia</address>
      <phone>+613 9925 6548</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vvien.lee@rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Melinda Jackson</name>
      <address>RMIT University
School of Health and Biomedical Sciences 
RMIT University, PO Box 71
Bundoora, Vic. 3083, Australia</address>
      <phone>+613 9925 7564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>melinda.jackson@rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>V Vien Lee</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>