<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362152">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/03/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000260820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Utility of ultrasound when using shock wave therapy to treat painful calcification in shoulder tendons, achilles tendons and plantar fasciitis with heel spur.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised controlled trial comparing ultrasound-guided to patient-guided extracorporeal shock wave therapy (ESWT) for calcific soft tissue pathologies (including tendinopathy) when assessing patient outcomes of decreased pain, improved function and reduced calcification size.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1128-8348</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Painful calcific soft tissue pathologies including tendinopathy.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients will receive active treatment i.e. shockwave therapy, with the SHOCK WAVE  THERAPY PROTOCOL described as below:
 
1. NUMBER &amp; FREQUENCY OF TREATMENT SESSIONS: 
3-5 treatment sessions. 
Treatment sessions will be spaced at 1 week intervals.
(NB.Number of  sessions of treatment are based on patient's response to treatment. All patients will receive 3 treatment sessions. Patients who feel they have not had a decrease in their pain or improvement in function can have an additional 2  treatment sessions). 

2. DURATION OF TREATMENT SESSIONS: 
Each treatment session will take  between 20-30mins depending on the arm of the study.
 Arm 1 (patient-guided shockwave treatment) will take about 20 mins. Arm 2 ( ultrasound-guided  shockwave treatment) will take about 30 mins with the additional 10 mins needed to locate the calcification on ultrasound prior to treatment.  All session times also include filling out questionnaire prior to treatment, setting up the patient for treatment  and arranging the follow up appointment or answering any questions. The shockwave treatment itself  takes less than 5 mins.
  
3.SHOCKWAVE MACHINE SETTINGS: 
2000 Impulses, 20 Hz , over a range of 1.4-2 bar.

4. THE TWO STUDY ARMS  OF PARTICIPANTS:
Arm 1: Patient-guided shock wave therapy to the area where the most pain is felt in relation to the area of calcification. 
Arm 2: Ultrasound-guided shock wave therapy to the  exact site of calcification.</interventions>
    <comparator>Shockwave therapy protocol: 3-5 sessions, at 1 week intervals. Shock wave settings at: 2000 Impulses, 20 Hz , over a range of 1.4-2 bar. 

Active control:  (Arm 1 as above) patient-guided shockwave therapy to the area where the most pain is felt in relation to the area of calcification.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient pain - using  a 10 cm visual analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline; during treatment ( prior to each weekly shock wave therapy); following the final shock wave therapy at 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Function - using patient-filled questionnaires relevant to the site of calcification: Constant &amp; Murley Score for shoulder function  in calcific shoulder tendinopathy; Victorian Institute of Sport Achillles ( VISA-A)  for insertional achilles tendinopathy and; Maryland Foot Score for plantar fasciitis with heel spur.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline; during treatment ( prior to each weekly shock wave therapy); following the final shock wave therapy at 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Calcification size- measured using the investigators ultrasound machine</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured following the final shock wave therapy at 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pain in one of 3 areas - either shoulder rotator cuff tendon, achilles tendon or plantar fascia; Proven calcification visible on previous imaging;Calcification visible  on our ( the investigator's) ultrasound machine; Males and non-pregnant females; fluent in english; able to give informed consent; seeking to try shockwave treatment as a method to resolve  the pain; willing and able to follow the research protocol</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Calcification unable to be seen on our ( the investigator's) ultrasound machine; unable to follow the protocol; unable to tolerate the shock wave treatment according  to the protocol because it is too painful; corticosteriod injection to the area inthe last 3 months ( as this may affect treatment efficacy); pregnancy or suspected pregnancy during the study; cancer; local lesions or non-intact skin; osteoarthritis at treatment site; Polyneuropathy; bleeding or clotting conditions; anticoagulation medications; allergy to ultrasound gel.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Letters of recruitement for study will be sent to health care professionals (eg. orthopaedic surgeons, general practitioners, sports medicine doctors, podiatrists).  Patients fitting inclusion criteria will be referred to our clinic. Referred, voluntary patients  eligible for the study will be randomly allocated to either the "patient-guided" or "ultrasound guided " . Allocation will be by concealment in opaque envelopes. The person giving the shock wave therapy and the patient will not be aware as to which group the patient is in until the envelope is opened prior to the first shock wave treatment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Stratified randomisation.  Randomisation done by generating three random number lists (based on site of calcification either shoulder, achilles or plantar fascia) using an excel computer programme. Numbers in each list allocated to either arm 1 ( patient-guided shock wave therapy) or arm 2 ( ultrasound-guided shock wave therapy). Treatment arm put in an opaque envelope. Envelopes numbered sequentially on the outside according to participant number at presentation for treatment.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr John Orchard</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Sports Clinic at Sydney University
University of Sydney
Cnr Western Ave &amp; Physics Road
Camperdown
NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>DJO international</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>P.O Box 2057
Normanhurst, NSW 2076</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Masiiwa Njawaya</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Sports Clinic at Sydney University
University of Sydney
Cnr Western Ave &amp; Physics Road
Camperdown
NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Tim Driscoll</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>A27 Edward Ford Building
University of Sydney,
Camperdown
NSW 2006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Jessica Orchard</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>NSW Cancer Council
153 Dowling St
Woolloomooloo
NSW 2011</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the study is to determine the best shock wave therapy protocol for a widely used  treatment for calcific soft tissue conditions in musculoskeletal medicine. We would like to see whether the addition of ultrasound to shock wave therapy in treatment of calcific soft tissue pathologies improves patient outcome as determined by decrease in pain, improvement of function and decrease in size of the calcification. We believe that treatment outcome may be similar between groups. However it is possible that for superficial conditions patient guided protocols may be slightly superior. In deep structures such as the shoulder tendon the addition of ultrasound to target the exact area of calcification may be slightly superior .  This study will hopefully help answer these questions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level6
Jane Foss Russell Building G02
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14497</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Masi Njawaya</name>
      <address>The Sports Clinic at Sydney University
Cnr University of Sydney
Camperdown
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93518118</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93518123</fax>
      <email>masinjawaya@thesportsclinic.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Masi Njawaya</name>
      <address>The Sports Clinic at Sydney University
University of Sydney
Camperdown
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 93518118</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 93518123</fax>
      <email>masinjawaya@thesportsclinic.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Masi Njawaya</name>
      <address>The Sports Clinic at Sydney University
University of Sydney
Camperdown
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 93518118</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 93518123</fax>
      <email>masinjawaya@thesportsclinic.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>