<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372316">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000255381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Community Jury: Case finding for dementia, what do community members think General Practitioners (GPs) should do? </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Community Jury: Case finding for dementia, what do community members think GPs should do? </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We will conduct a community jury (CJ) to consider the potential benefits and harms of case finding for dementia in primary care and ask the jury to propose a recommendation for the question, Should the health system encourage GPs to practice case finding of dementia in people over 50? 
The CJ will be facilitated by the lead researcher, Dr Rae Thomas, a Psychologist with over 20 years experience. The jurors will watch and discuss prerecorded presentations from leading researchers in the field addressing the aforementioned question. The jury will be held on Saturday and Sunday at Bond University, with followup questionnaires mailed to participants three months later.</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early Detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Our primary outcome will be juror recommendations for the posed question: Should the health system encourage GPs to practice case finding of dementia in people over 50?</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of Community jury (i.e. after two days of presentations and deliberation)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The time point at which jurors achieve consistency in their individual responses to the jury question (i.e. enough information has been given for the jury to no longer change their answer).  This will be assessed through surveying of jurors using OLT KeePad electronic clickers throughout the presentations and deliberation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of Community jury (i.e. after two days of presentations and deliberation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of jurors that made an informed decision. 
This will be assessed through a combination of adequate knowledge concept questions and congruence between attitude to case finding and intention to test (dichotomous outcome).  It will also be assessed through qualitative analyses of deliberations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of Community Jury (i.e. after two days of presentations and deliberation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Individual's intention to be tested for MCI or dementia will also be measured, given the current tests and treatments available.  This will be assessed through survey questions assessing attitudes to case finding for dementia and individual likelihood to test for dementia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of Community Jury (i.e. after two days of presentations and deliberation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Individual's knowledge of dementia will be assessed through a researcher developed survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of Community Jury (i.e. after two days of presentations and deliberation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Individual's knowledge of dementia will be assessed through a researcher developed survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intention to test for dementia.  This will be assessed through survey questions assessing attitudes to case finding for dementia and individual likelihood to test for dementia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three month follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Living on the Gold Coast, Australia.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>We will exclude individuals who have been, have immediate family members (e.g. partner, parents, sisters/brothers, sister/brother-in-laws), diagnosed with MCI, dementia, or Alzheimer's, or who are carers for a person diagnosed with any of these conditions,  We will also exclude individuals actively taking cognitive enhancing medications.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Quantitative and Qualitative analyses.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/03/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>17/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>18/03/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>10</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bond University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>14 University Drive, Robina, QLD 4226</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bond University Vice-Chancellor Research Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>14 University Drive, Robina, QLD 4226</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Government policy on health care should seek to reflect the views of the community but current methods for community engagement are limited. Strategies such as opinion polling, community forums, and engaging consumer representatives on decision making panels may not be able to fully consider issues that are complex, require a greater understanding of potential benefits and harms, and may provide only a limited number of viewpoints from the community. A community jury is a deliberative process that can help to establish the communitys preferences and values on a particular topic. This research team has successfully conducted the first randomised controlled trial of a community jury process in health and demonstrated proof of concept that this form of public engagement could be potentially beneficial to health policy. Our findings demonstrated a community jury was capable of considering complex information on the harms and benefits of screening, and to distinguish individual from community choices. Our community jury also identified an innovative solution to the question being deliberated. 
Cognitive impairment ranges from mild impairment to severe dementia. It causes problems with memory, learning, and organising and mild cognitive impairment can be a precursor for dementia. The benefit evidence for case finding for dementia is scarce, the medication benefits not significant, and the nonpharmacological interventions mostly ineffective. 
We will conduct a community jury to consider the potential benefits and harms of case finding for dementia in primary care and ask the jury to propose a recommendation for the question, Should the health system encourage GPs to practice case finding of dementia in people over 50?</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bond University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>14 University Drive, Robina, QLD, 4226</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RO15810</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rae Thomas</name>
      <address>Bond University, 14 University Drive, Robina, QLD, 4226.</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5595 5521</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rthomas@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rae Thomas</name>
      <address>Bond University, 14 University Drive, Robina, QLD, 4226.</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5595 5521</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rthomas@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rae Thomas</name>
      <address>Bond University, 14 University Drive, Robina, QLD, 4226.</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5595 5521</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rthomas@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>