<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373158">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000924358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Novel processed carrot-based products to supplement vegetable intake in healthy adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigating whether consumption of processed carrot powder is an effective strategy to supplement vegetable intake compared to fresh carotenoid-rich vegetables, as assessed by changes in plasma carotenoid levels in healthy adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Poor diet
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>After 4 days of following a low carotenoid diet participants will consume 2 servings (2 tablespoons)/day of carrot powder added to suitable foods e.g. a broth style soup, pasta sauce, gravy, casserole, smoothie, yoghurt, juice etc in addition to usual vegetable intake for 4 weeks. The carrot powder will be provided to participants. Participants will receive detailed dietary instructions (developed in consultation with a dietitian), both orally and in writing, on how to follow the intervention. The amount of carrot powder is equivalent to 2 large carrots (2x72g carrot, also equivalent to 2 servings of vegetables). Participants will complete a daily checklist throughout the study to assess compliance to the intervention. </interventions>
    <comparator>After 4 days of following a low carotenoid diet participants will consume 2 servings/day of fresh carotenoid-rich vegetables (e.g. carrots, tomatoes, broccoli, etc.) in addition to usual vegetable intake for 4 weeks. Participants will be given a voucher to purchase the vegetables themselves. Participants will receive detailed dietary instructions (developed in consultation with a dietitian), both orally and in writing, on how to follow the intervention. Participants will complete a daily checklist throughout the study to assess compliance to the intervention. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in plasma carotenoid levels analysed using HPLC.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Consumer Attitudes: Liking using a validated 9-point hedonic score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and week 1, 2, 3 and 4 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Consumer Attitudes: Desire to consume product using a validated 7-point categorical scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and week 1, 2, 3 and 4 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Consumer Attitudes: Boredom using a validated visual analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1, 2, 3 and 4 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Consumer attitudes: Effort to incorporate a new habit using an adapted question from the Self-Report Habit Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1, 2, 3 and 4 after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Consumer attitudes: Adherence to natural food using the validated sub-scale of Social representation theory scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4 weeks after study commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Consumer attitudes to inclusion of carrot-based processed foods assessed using a preference scale (fresh vs. processed) specifically designed for the study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in buccal cell carotenoids</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in colour and vascularity of the retina and macula using the Fundus Camera. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in cognitive function assessed using a battery of automated tasks delivered via the iPad: Reaction time (attention/psychomotor speed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in cognitive function will be assessed using a battery of automated tasks delivered via the iPad: Coding (perceptual speed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in cognitive function will be assessed using a battery of automated tasks delivered via the iPad: Digit Span (Working Memory)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in body composition assessed using Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis (BIA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in fruit and vegetable intake and diet quality (composite secondary outcome) will be assessed using a validated online diet index score.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commenced. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Healthy Male or Female adults
2.	BMI between 18.5-30 kg/m2 
3.	Blood pressure &lt;140/90 mmHg
4.	Understand study and agree to participate
5.	Adhere closely to the prescribed food consumption as per the research protocol



</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	History of chronic disease, e.g. type 2 diabetes, heart disease, cancer, atherosclerotic disease, hypertension, stomach ulcers, drug abuse or alcoholism
2.	History of pancreatic insufficiency or other conditions resulting in fat malabsorption - chronic pancreatitis, cystic fibrosis, coeliac disease, crohns disease, gastric bypass surgery, small bowel resection, abnormal thyroid function
3.	History of smoking during 6 months prior to study
4.	Extended absences due to travel or other commitments
5.	Known allergy to the test foods, and anyone with severe food allergies - even in trace amounts. 
6.	Pregnancy or breastfeeding
7.	Medication or nutritional supplements that may affect the study outcomes
8.	On any weight-loss programs</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation of eligible participants will be conducted by a different person than the person who decides that a participant is eligible for inclusion in the trial. Hence the person who makes decisions regarding eligibility will not be aware at the time and have no influence over which groups participant's are allocated too. </concealment>
    <sequence>Eligible participants will be assigned to the interventions using stratified random assignment based on sex and age. The randomization scheme will be computer generated. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based on previous data from our laboratory 20 participants per group (total n=40) will provide 80% power (two-tailed, a=0.05) to detect a mean difference of 0.6 µg/mL in total plasma carotenoids (assuming a 2x greater efficiency of carrot powder to increase plasma carotenoid concentrations compared to fresh vegetables), using a SD of change of 0.67 µg/mL. A total of 44 participants will be recruited to account for a 10% dropout. A greater dropout is not expected due to the short duration (4 weeks) of the trial.
Main intervention effects (differences between groups) will be assessed using Independent Samples T-test, Mann-Whitney U tests and chi-square tests for parametric, non-parametric and categorical data, respectively using IBM SPSS statistics for WINDOWS. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>44</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>25/08/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Commonwealth Scientific Industrial Research Organisation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>South Australian Health and Medical Research Institute building, North Terrace, Adelaide, South Australia,
5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Commonwealth Scientific Industrial Research Organisation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>South Australian Health and Medical Research Institute building, North Terrace, Adelaide, South Australia,
5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>People all over the world do not meet the recommended intake for fruit and vegetables. New strategies and options are needed to help people to boost their vegetable consumption. Carrots are an exceptional source of carotenoids, as well as fibre. Carotenoids are a precursor for vitamin A, one of the most common deficiencies worldwide, essential for eye health and may have various other health benefits through their antioxidant activity. 
The primary hypothesis of the study is that daily consumption of processed carrot powder added to foods is an effective, convenient and consumer accepted strategy to supplement vegetable intake, as shown by greater increases in carotenoid status after 4 weeks compared to daily consumption of carotenoid-rich vegetables.  
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CSIRO Health and Medical Research Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box 2583, Brisbane, Queensland, 4001, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/06/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>6/2017</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/04/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Welma Stonehouse</name>
      <address>CSIRO
PO Box 10041, Adelaide, South Australia, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8919</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>welma.stonehouse@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Welma Stonehouse</name>
      <address>CSIRO
PO Box 10041, Adelaide, South Australia, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8919</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>welma.stonehouse@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Welma Stonehouse</name>
      <address>CSIRO
PO Box 10041, Adelaide, South Australia, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8919</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>welma.stonehouse@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Welma Stonehouse</name>
      <address>CSIRO
PO Box 10041, Adelaide, South Australia, 5000</address>
      <phone>+ 8 8303 8919</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>welma.stonehouse@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>