<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367061">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001103651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of preferred retinal locus (PRL) training on Visual Acuity and Reading speed in patients with Macular Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of preferred retinal locus (PRL) training on visual acuity and reading speed in patients with stable macular disease. 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>End stage macular disease </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Immediate Training Group

Participants enrolled into this group will have weekly training sessions for 10 weeks where baseline and outcome measurements will be performed by the 'examiner' which will be an ophthalmic assistant. 

Followed by preferred retinal locus (PRL) training by the 'trainer' who will be an orthoptist, this involves using the macular integrity assessment (MAIA)  micro perimeter to assess macular function and determine a viable PRL. Once a PRL has been established training will be done using a program available on the MAIA where a biofeedback system is used to gain better use out of the PRL and improve fixation stability. 

Each visit will take approximately 45min to complete. 

On the first visit patients will also be randomised into the exercise or non exercise group. Participants will be given exercises which include pictures and words on a page to practice using their PRL. </interventions>
    <comparator>Delayed Training Group 

Patients enrolled into the delayed training program will be referred to the Royal Society for the Blind (RSB) for assessment with conventional low vision aids. 

After the 10 weeks the participants will follow the same protocol as the immediate training program. 

Once training has begun a second phase of randomisation will occur to establish if participants require regular stimulation of their PRL with take home exercises or if training in the clinic using the MAIA is enough to establish a viable PRL. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effects of PRL training will have on a participants vision for distance 

 
Examiner   First Visit 
 -	Assess best corrected visual acuity (BCVA) for distance using the early treatment of diabetic retinopathy study (ETDRS) vision chart, each eye separately and both eyes together 
-	Potential visual acuity (PVA) using the Markowitz PVA cards assessed at 50cm

Repeat Visits 
-	Assess BCVA for distance using the ETDRS vision chart, each eye separately and both eyes together 

Final visit at 10 weeks 
-	Assess BCVA for distance using the ETDRS vision chart, each eye separately and both eyes together 
-	Potential visual acuity using the Markowitz PVA cards assessed at 50cm

-	Follow up visit at 3 and 6 months
-	Assess BCVA for distance using the ETDRS vision chart, each eye separately and both eyes together 


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each of the baseline and outcome measurements will be performed at each visit over the 10 week time period. 

Then re-measured at 3 and 6 months looking for regression and perhaps the need for "top up" training. 

The outcomes will be assessed at the end of the 10 week time period looking for plateau effects. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To develop a protocol for PRL training in a clinical setting</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the completion of the 10 week training program the results from the baseline and follow up tests will be analysed looking at those tests that are sensitive enough to show improvement or are deemed necessary in monitoring at participants PRL training outcomes. As well as looking for plateau effects to determine how many sessions are required. 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To look at the effects that PRL training has on a participants quality of life 

the IVI questionnaire will be completed by each participant prior to training and post training.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>A the end of the 10 weeks the questionnaires will be analysed looking for a change in their answers pre and post PRL training. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if take home exercises are necessary to enhance PRL training in between visits 

Exercises include pictures and words where participants have to practice reading whilst using their PRL</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the 10 weeks the results from the MAIA will be analysed mainly fixation stability to determine if exercises in between visits have a positive impact on a patients in office PRL training. 


</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effects PRL training will have on reading speed - please note this is a primary outcome 

-	Assess near vision acuity using an age appropriate reading add using the MNREAD acuity charts, each eye separately and both eyes together 
-	Assess reading speed measured in words per minute using MNREAD acuity charts using an age appropriate reading add, each eye separately and both eyes together 

The above will be measured at all visits first, repeat, 3 months and 6 months. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The tests will be performed weekly for 10 weeks 

The outcomes will be assessed at the end of the 10 week time period looking for plateau effects. 

These will be remeasured at 3 and 6 months looking for regression and perhaps the need for "top up" training </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria  patients with stable macular disease not undergoing active treatment for their macular disease, those undergoing intravitreal injections as a maintenance treatment. The macular disease must be considered stable for 6 months. VA 6/18 or worse in their better eye, score of 1-3 on the global deterioration scale (GDS) from the SMMSE mini-mental exam. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria  patients with active macular disease, VA better than 6/18, score &gt;4 on the GDS from the SMMSE mini-mental exam. Participants whose macular disease becomes active during the training will be excluded from the study and able to re-join once the disease process is stable again. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Suitable participants will be referred to the clinic by ophthalmologists or from low vision services these recruiters do not have any involvement in the study. Once deemed suitable  participants will read through and sign the informed consent form. 

They will then complete the SMMSE exam to determine that the participant will have the cognitive abilities to complete the training and will either be included or excluded form the study based on these results. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>phase 1 of randomisation will involve being selected to the immediate training group or the delayed training group. Randomisation will be by the masked choice of a red or green counter from a closed bag by the patient. There will be an equal number of each colour. Green will be assigned to immediate training, and Red to delayed training groups. 

The second phase of randomisation will involve being selected into the exercise group or non-exercise group. Participants will be given “eccentric viewing take home kits”, and will be asked to complete a series of exercises in between training sessions or the non-exercise group where participants will rely on what they learn from the training sessions held in the clinic. This will occur once training has begun and will involve both sets of participants i.e. the immediate and delayed training group. The same process of randomisation using Green and Red counters will be used. 

Randomisation will be done by the participant in the presence of the 'trainer' and allocation to the groups will be concealed from the 'examiner' </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>ANCOVAs (repeated measured within and between)

We also calculated the power using G*Power version 3.1.9.2. To obtain a power of 0.95 a total of 60 participants (i.e.30 in the Immediate group, 30 in the Delayed group) will need to be recruited. If 20 in each group managed to be recruited the power is 0.8</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eyemedics Opthalmologist </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 1
57 Greenhill Road
Wayville 
SA
5063</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>LaTrobe University 
Faculty Health Sciences
School Allied Health 
Department of Clinical Vision Sciences 
</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>LaTrobe University 
Faculty Health Sciences
School Allied Health 
Department of Clinical Vision Sciences 
HS2-312 
Melbourne Bundoora
Victoria 3083</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to determine the effects of preferred retinal loci (PRL) training in patients with macular disease, especially macular degeneration. Age-related macular degeneration (AMD) ranks third among the global causes of visual impairment with a blindness prevalence of 8.7%. 

Macula degeneration leads to a loss of central vision affecting reading, recognising peoples faces, driving or other fine detailed tasks, which causes a large impact on a patients quality of life and independence. Patients are never completely blind from macular degeneration since the remaining peripheral retina is healthy and is then useful for navigational purposes. 

It is reported in the literature that some patients spontaneously use another area of the healthy retina known as a PRL when the macula is compromised. This project aims to determine the patients PRL using the MAIA micro perimeter and over a series of  10 training sessions to establish wether PRL training improves a patients visual acuity, fixation stability and reading speed, thus having a positive impact on a patients quality of life. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Australian and New Zealand College of Ophthalmologists (RANZCO) Human Research Ethics Comm (EC00396)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367061-SMMSE exam.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367061-IVI questionnaire .docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367061-Clinical Protocol_final .doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367061-Participant Information Sheet and Consent Form_Final.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367061-Letter to Drs and RSB.doc</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Russell Phillips </name>
      <address>Eyemedics 
Level 1 
57 Greenhill Road
Wayville
SA 
5063</address>
      <phone>+61882731600</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ruspp@adam.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Shandell Wishart </name>
      <address>Eyemedics 
Level 1 
57 Greenhill Road
Wayville
SA
5063</address>
      <phone>+61882731600</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shandell@eyemedics.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Shandell Wishart </name>
      <address>Eyemedics 
Level 1 
57 Greenhill Road
Wayville
SA
5063</address>
      <phone>+61882731600</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shandell@eyemedics.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Shandell Wishart </name>
      <address>Level 1 
57 Greenhill Road
Wayville
SA
5063</address>
      <phone>+61882731600</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shandell@eyemedics.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>