<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83514">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/01/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000691246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Azithromycin versus Amoxicillin for Treatment of Acute otitis media in Aboriginal Children (AATAAC)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In Indigenous children aged 6 months to 6 years with a diagnosis of acute otitis media, does Azithromycin given as a single dose (compared to 7 days of standard dose amoxicillin) result in a reduction in the proportion of children with signs of persistent disease after treatment?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>AATAAC</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute otitis media in Indigenous children aged 6 months to 6 years</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Ear</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other ear disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A single dose of the macrolide antibiotic azithromycin 30mg/kg administered orally. Placebo syrup identical in smell, taste and apprearance was used in a doubel dummy fashion.</interventions>
    <comparator>Amoxicillin 50 mg/kg/day twice a day administered orally for minimum of 7 days, 14 days for a diagnosis of acute otitis media (AOM) with perforation. persistent infection was referred to local health care providers for standard treatment.  Placebo syrup identical in smell, taste and apprearance was used in a doubel dummy fashion.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical failure: Proportion of children with persistent pain or bulging or middle ear discharge or withdrawn due to complications or side effects. Assessment by health care professionals using video otoscopy and tympanometry and standardised.</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 6 to 11 post commencement of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical failure: Proportion of children with active perforation. Assessment by health care professionals using video otoscopy and tympanometry and standardised.</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 6 to 11 post commencement of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical failure (symptomatic): proportion of children with peristent ear pain or middle ear discharge.Assessment by health care professionals using video otoscopy and tympanometry and standardised.</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 6 to 11 post commencement of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical failure (by follow up): proportion of children with peristent ear pain or bulging or middle ear discharge or withdrawn due to complications or side effects (children lost to follow up excluded). Assessment by health care professionals using video otoscopy and tympanometry and standardised.</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 6 to 11 post commencement of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical failure (by treatment received): proportion of children with peristent ear pain or bulging or middle ear discharge or withdrawn due to complications or side effects (children whoreceived 80% of recommended medications).Assessment by health care professionals using video otoscopy and tympanometry and standardised.</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 6 to 11 post commencement of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Failure to improve (all) Proportion of children with no improvement(children lost to follow up assumed to be failures).Assessment by health care professionals using video otoscopy and tympanometry and standardised.</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 6 to 11 post commencement of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Failure to improve (by follow up):  Proportion of children with no improvement (children lost to follow up excluded). Assessment by health care professionals using video otoscopy and tympanometry and standardised.</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 6 to 11 post commencement of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complications: proportion of children withdrawn due to complications. Assessed by review of child's medical records. Complications may include diarrhoea, vomiting.</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 6 to 11 post commencement of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Side Effects: proportion of children withdrawn due to side effects (such as gastrointestinal upset). Assessed by review of child's medical records for indication that child's health carer had recommended cessation of the trial medication following side effects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 6 to 11 post commencement of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Antibiotic resistance; Proportion of children with carriage of resistant bacterial pathogen. Assessed using E-test to measure minimum inhibitory concentration and recommended breakpoints.</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 6 to 11 post commencement of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aboriginal. Betwen age 6 mo and 6 years. New diagnosis of acute otitis media (AOM) without perforation or AOM with perforation.  Children willing to attend for follow-up at day 6 to 11, and day 12-21 for children with perforation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Randomised previously in the same study. Received antibiotics in the previous 7 dyas. Current severe illness requiring intravenous or intramuscualar antibiotics within the next 7 days. Allergy to penicillin or azithromycin. Perforation in affected ear(s) greater than 2%</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All age eligible children in the remote community received screening ear examination. Those who met inclusion criteria were invited to participate.  Allocation was concealed by means of double sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated. Varying block sizes. Allocation was stratified according to i)health centre ii) child's weight iii) diagnosis of AOM (with or without perforation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>double dummy placebo. Placebos were  identical in smell, taste and appearance to the active medications.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2002</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>330</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>NHMRC</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>POBox 1421
Canberra 2601
ACT</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>POBox 1421
Canberra 2601
ACT</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the study is to determine whether single dose azithromycin is superior to standard therapy (7 days amoxicillin) in resolving acute otitis media in Aboriginal children at high risk of tympanic membrane perforation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication>not yet published</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC) of Northern Territory Department of Health and Families and Menzies School of Health Research</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>C/- Menzies School of Health Research
POBox 41096 Casuarina NT. 0811</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>02/44</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Amanda J Leach</name>
      <address>PO Box 41096 
Casuarina. 0811
NT</address>
      <phone>+61 8 89228196</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 89275 187</fax>
      <email>amanda@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Amanda J Leach</name>
      <address>PO Box 41096 
Casuarina. 0811
NT</address>
      <phone>+61 8 89228196</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 89275 187</fax>
      <email>amanda@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Amanda J Leach</name>
      <address>PO Box 41096 
Casuarina. 0811
NT</address>
      <phone>+61 8 89228196</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 89275 187</fax>
      <email>amanda@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>