<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363195">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001151820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Immunonutrition in liver surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Preoperative Immunonutrition on Outcome in Patients Undergoing Partial Hepatectomy: A Randomised Pilot Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients with liver cancer requiring resection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Liver</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will be randomised to either preoperative supplemental nutrition with IMPACT (Nestle) or to standard care (usually, no supplementation). 
Patients randomized to the treatment arm will be provided with a prescription for IMPACT and instructions on intake. They will be asked to consume 3 x 237 ml tetra packs daily (1000 kcal providing 12.6 g arginine and 3.3 g eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA)), in addition to their usual intake of their normal meals and snacks, for the 5 consecutive days immediately preceding day of surgery.</interventions>
    <comparator>Those randomized to the control arm will be advised to continue with their usual oral intake. If any of these patients are found to have malnutrition, defined as involuntary weight loss of at least 5% or 10% of their usual body weight in 1 or 6 months respectively, or a BMI of &lt; 18.5 (ASPEN 2002), they will be provided with an alternative nutritional supplement drink (Ensure Powder) and will be advised to take 50 grams of powder with 200ml of milk or 80 grams of powder with 200mls of water (1.5kcal/ml) twice daily, in addition to their usual intake of their normal meals and snacks, for the 5 consecutive days immediately preceding day of surgery.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative immune and inflammatory status which includes C-reactive protein, total lymphocytes, CD3, CD4, CD8,  tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-alpha) and interleukin-6 (IL-6). These will be assessed on blood samples by ELISA (cytokines), flow cytometry (CD3,4,8), and standard laboratory techniques (CRP, lymphocytes).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperative days 1, 3, and 5.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative infectious complications (for example, wound infection, urinary tract infection, pneumonia). These will be assessed usng bedside chart review according to relevant signs and symptoms, positive cultures and whether antibiotic treatment is prescribed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed daily over the first 30 postoperative days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in total body protein as measured by neutron activation scanning.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at three individual time points; day prior to surgery and postoperative days 7 and 30.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ischaemia-reperfusion injury to the liver assessed on biopsied tissue taken at surgery from the resected liver by measuring mitochodrial function and oxidative stress. Antioxidant status, as it pertains to mitochondrial function, will be determined using TBARS (thiobarbituric acid reactive substances) as an index of lipid peroxidation and oxidative stress in tissue samples. Reactive oxygen species determination will be performed and markers of damage (for example protein carbonyls, lipid peroxides etc) assessed using commercially available kits. Mitochondrial respiration flux will be determined using a high resolution respirometry oxygraph (OROBOROS Oxygraph 2K, Anton paar, Graz, Austria) with a substrate inhibitor protocol that allows rapid analysis of respiratory chain function and integrity in tissue homogenates obtained from the liver sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day of surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Scheduled for hepatic resection of primary or secondary liver cancer</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Diabetes
2.	Immunosuppression
3.	Cirrhosis (biopsy proven or fibroscan result)
4.	Chemotherapy within the 3 weeks prior to study entry
5.	Taking fish oil supplements
6.	Not able to take oral supplements
7.	Pregnant or likely to become pregnant during the study period</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is by sequentially numbered sealed envelope following enrolment of eligible patients at pre-admission clinics.</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation with randomisation sequence generated by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/11/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Assoc. Prof. Lindsay Plank</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Surgery, University of Auckland, Private Bag 92019, Auckland 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dietitians New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>P O Box 5065, Lambton Quay, Wellington 6145</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Adam Bartlett</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Surgery, University of Auckland, Private Bag 92019, Auckland 1142</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Immunonutrition enriched in arginine and omega-3 fatty acids (from fish oil) provided as a preoperative supplement to patients undergoing gastrointestinal surgery has been shown to almost halve postoperative infectious complications. To date, this treatment has not been investigated in patients undergoing liver surgery, except in one small study published in a Japanese medical journal. We will randomise patients scheduled for liver resection to an immunonutrition supplement to be taken preoperatively for 5 days or to standard care. Body composition assessments will be performed pre- and post-surgery and patients will be followed for 30 d post-surgery for complications. During liver resection, the liver is rendered ischaemic for a period of time before reperfusion occurs. Liver dysfunction together with mitochondrial dysfunction resulting in oxidative stress and an increased inflammatory reaction is a consequence of this ischaemia-reperfusion injury. This has been demonstrated in animal studies in which arginine and omega-3 acids have been shown to ameliorate the injury. Liver tissue samples will be collected at time of surgery for analysis of mitochondrial function and oxidative stress. The current pilot study is intended to examine the effects of preoperative nutrition with immune-modulatory properties on postoperative outcome in these patients in terms of liver mitochondrial function and oxidative stress, inflammatory response, muscle loss, and complication rates. These data will provide the foundation for a larger scale study with infectious complications as a primary end-point.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTX/12/06/056</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Lindsay Plank</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery, University of Auckland, Auckland Hospital Support Building, Private Bag 92019, Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 6949</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 377 9656</fax>
      <email>l.plank@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kylie Becker</name>
      <address>Auckland City Hospital
Nutrition Services
Level 8 Building 1
Park Road, Grafton
Private Bag 92024
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 307 4949 x 25084</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 377 5075</fax>
      <email>kbecker@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>