<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336713">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/06/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000566932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Validation of the Perth Chest Pain Rule</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Validation of protocols for safe early discharge of patients presenting to Emergency Departments with chest pain</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MiMiC-2</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chest Pain</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Suspected Acute Coronary Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>An additional 10ml of blood will be drawn with the initial blood taken for standard clinical management. An extra venepuncture of 10ml of blood will be drawn at two hours post presentation to the Emergency Department (ED). At some sites, an additional 5ml of blood will be drawn from the sample taken for standard management at 8-12 hour post presentation.

Data will be collected using a standardised data collection form. Patients will be managed and discharged as determined by their treating clinician as per their clinical judgement - trial blood sample will not be available to clinicians.

Patients will be recuited for six months with the aim for at least 600 patients.

Patients wil be telephoned by research nurses at approximately 30 days post ED discharge and asked a series of standard questions regarding their health and investigations since ED discharge. Hospital discharge summaries and results of investigations will be obtained by research staff.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard Clinical Management of Chest Pain including serial troponin measurement</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute Myocardial Infarction. Final outcome adjudication will be made by two Emergency Physician Investigators or one Emergency Physician and one Cardiologist. When agreement cannot be reached a second Cardiologist or Emergency Physician will be consulted. All clinical, ECG and laboratory data will be made available (except for investigation blood tests). 

The definition of Acute Myocardial Infarction will be that of the European Society of Cardiology/American Heart association and is:
1.	Rise and/or fall &gt;20% of standard laboratory troponin (I or T) with at least at least one value exceeding the 99th percentile of the distribution in healthy population or the lowest level for which a 10% coefficient of variation can be demonstrated, across at least two blood draws over at least 6 hours, together with at least one of the following
a.	Symptoms consistent with ACS
b.	ECG changes indicative of new ischaemia (new ST-T changes or new LBBB)
c.	Development of pathological Q waves on ECG
d.	Imaging evidence of new loss of viable myocardium or new regional wall motion abnormality
OR 
2.	Sudden, unexpected cardiac death, with cardiac arrest, associated with symptoms of myocardial ischaemia and presumed new ST-elevation or LBBB, or evidence of coronary thrombosis at angiography or autopsy, but death occurring before biomarker samples could be obtained, or before their likely appearance in the blood.
OR
3.	Pathological findings of AMI at autopsy</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 30 days of Emergency Department attendance</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All cause mortality. Death will be determined from hospital records or the hospital morbidity system which is regularly updated from the WA Births and Deaths Registry</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 30 days of Emergency Department attendance</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emergency or urgent coronary revascularisation. Coronary revascularisation is a hard end point. Determination of emergency/urgent will be made by the treating cardiologist. 

AHA/ESC definitions will again be used and are:

Emergency 	procedure required as emergency because of clinical instability ? eg cardiogenic shock, pulmonary oedema, ischaemic dysfunction, unresolved symptoms despite maximal non-invasive therapy, or evolving myocardial infarction

Urgent	Not emergency, not elective, and performed during present admission to minimise risk of deterioration</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 30 days of Emergency Department attendance</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Significant  non-cardiac diagnoses such as Pulmonary Embolism and aortic dissection, and the time point at which the alternate diagnosis was determined.

Diagnoses will be determined from hospital records including discharge summaries and investigation results. Where appropriate, discussions will be held with the treating clinician.</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 30 days of Emergency Department attendance</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients attending Emergency Departments with chest pain undergoing serial troponin measurement for exclusion of acute coronary syndrome</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>single troponin measurement, unable to consent, unlikely to be able to obtain follow-up (eg. overseas visitors), pregnant</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/02/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Yusuf Nagree</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Fremantle Hospital Emergency Medicine Research Unit
PO Box 480
Fremantle WA 6959</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Health, WA</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>189 Royal Street
Perth WA 6004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Stephen Macdonald</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Armadale Health Service
PO Box 460
Armadale WA 6992</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chest pain is a common reason for presentation to an Emergency Department. Current management usually involves observing patients in an Emergency Department over 8-12 hours doing repeated heart tracings and blood tests. 
 
A large trial in Perth and overseas studies have suggested that it is possible to shorten this observation period to 2 hours using a panel of blood tests and looking at particular patient characteristics. The aim of this study is to ensure that changing to this method of management will not cause an increase in adverse patient outcomes</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>the results of the cohort trial (MIMIC study) are currently being written up for publication</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Metropolitan Area Health Service HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Fremantle Hospital
PO Box 480
Fremantle WA 6959</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/10/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/10/0375</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yusuf Nagree</name>
      <address>Fremantle Hospital Emergency Medicine Research Unit
Fremantle Hospital
PO Box 480
Fremantle WA 6959</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9431 3733</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yusuf.nagree@health.wa..gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yusuf Nagree</name>
      <address>Fremantle Hospital Emergency Medicine Research Unit
Fremantle Hospital
PO Box 480
Fremantle WA 6959</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9431 3733</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9431 3711</fax>
      <email>yusuf.nagree@health.wa..gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yusuf Nagree</name>
      <address>Fremantle Hospital Emergency Medicine Research Unit
Fremantle Hospital
PO Box 480
Fremantle WA 6959</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9431 3733</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yusuf.nagree@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>