<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335198">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/02/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/03/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000191099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating stress reduction therapy in cardiothoracic surgical patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluating stress reduction therapy in cardiothoracic surgical patients using massage therapy or standard care ('quite time').</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate, pain, anxiety and tension.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Two 20 minute swedish massage therapy sessions, performed between days 3 and 6 post-operative.  20 minutes of hands-on massage will be performed and focused on the areas requested by the patient.     Depending upon the area identified by the patient to be massaged, the gentle massage procedure may consist of; back and neck, arm and hands, or foot, leg and hips.</interventions>
    <comparator>Two 20 minute 'quiet time' (standard care) sessions,  performed between dasy 3 and 6 post-operative. Where a sign is placed on the door or curtain, stating that patient is not be disturbed for 20 minutes. The patient is then left alone in the room and asked to refrain from reading or watching television during the 20 minutes 'quite time'.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare the level of pain, anxiety and tension before and after a 20 minute massage therapy session provided by a trained therapist between days 3 and 6 post cardiac surgery.  Assessment tools used; blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate, a visual analogue scale and a Short Form (SF36) questionaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after each 20 minute treatment session.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare the level of pain, anxiety and tension before and after a 20 minute massage therapy session provided by a trained therapist between days 3-6 post cardiac surgery. Assessment tools used; blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate, a visual analogue scale and a SF36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after each 20 minute treatment session.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare the level of pain, anxiety and tension before and after 20 minutes of quiet time provided between days 3-6 post-operative. Assessment tools used; blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate, a visual analogue scale and a SF36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after each 20 minute treatment session.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Identify the difference in amount of change in pain, anxiety and tension for those patients that received massage therapy versus those patients that received 'quiet time' for two periods after surgery. Assessment tools used; blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate, a visual analogue scale and a SF36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>after 1 year when trial completed.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Identify change in blood pressure, heart rate and respiratory rate before and after massage therapy compared to standard care. Mechanical vital sign machine will be used to assess the above.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after each 20 minute treatment session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Describe patient reported areas of discomfort before and after massage therapy. Assessed by massage therapist using a diagramatic representation of the body.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after each 20 minute treatment session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Report overall satisfaction with the experience of massage therapy. Assessed using SF36 and VAS (visual analogue scale).</outcome>
      <timepoint>after each 20 minute treatment session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Identify challenges that are encountered by nursing staff and massage therapists while providing this service. Methods used will include a focus group session as well as written feedback by massage therapist post each treatment session.</outcome>
      <timepoint>after 1 year when trial completed</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients scheduled for coronary artery bypass surgery or cardiac valve surgery or both.
Patients that have given consent to participate.
Patients who are medically able to participate in massage therapy between days 3-6 post-operatively.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with chronic pain or a psychiatric history will be excluded from the study.
Patients with prolonged bleeding or intubation greater than 24 hours.
Patients that decide not to participate post operatively.
Patients that are not alert enough to participate in the data collection.
Patients that would not be able to get a massage due to complexity of medical care including active cellulitis, phlebitis, complex wounds and multiple drains.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All elective cardiac surgery patients presenting at the preadmission clinic are approached by the Research nurse and invited to participate in the study if eligible. Allocation is not concealed. Patient are given study information and consent forms.  Consenting participants are allocated to either massage therapy or standard care using computor generated number tables. Patients are unaware regarding what group they are allocated too.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computor generated randomised numbers.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/03/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Franklin Rosenfeldt</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Alfred
Cardiothoracic Surgery Unit
Commercial Road
PO Box 315
Prahran
VIC 3181</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Integrative therapies such as massage have gained support in the literature as methods to improve the overall patient experience.  Massage therapy (MT) has been widely accepted as a therapy to help with pain and anxiety and, in fact, many healthcare institutions have integrated massage into their standard of care for patients.  Although there are studies that indicate the specific benefits of massage therapy, there are a limited number of studies looking at the specific benefits for cardiac surgical patients.  Cardiac surgical patients undergo long surgical procedures and in the immediate post-operative period, commonly complain of back and shoulder pain that may be related to the surgical procedure, bed positioning or general stress and tension.  
Given the promising, yet insufficiently researched, effects of massage therapy as a symptom relief strategy for alleviating pain and anxiety, we plan to conduct a study to provide evidence of the efficacy and feasibility of massage therapy delivered in a cardiovascular surgery setting.  Our planned program of research focuses on the question: Can a massage therapy intervention be delivered within a busy clinical cardiovascular surgery setting in an efficacious manner to alleviate patient pain, anxiety and tension?</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Reasearch Commitee, The Alfred</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Commercial Road 
Prahan
VIC 3181</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>27/09/2010</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/02/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Franklin Rosenfeldt</name>
      <address>The Alfred PO Box 315
VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90763691</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>F.Rosenfeldt@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cathy Reardon</name>
      <address>The Alfred PO Box 315
VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90762679</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.reardon@med.monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cathy Reardon</name>
      <address>The Alfred PO Box 315
VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90762679</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.reardon@med.monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>