<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347729">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/12/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001258943</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessment of implication of Massive Transfusion Guidelines in conjunction with incidence of coagulopathy and outcome in the Northern Tasmania</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessment of implication of Massive Transfusion Guidelines in conjunction with incidence of coagulopathy and outcome in the Northern Tasmania</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MTP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Massive bleeding defined by the replacement of one blood volume in a period of 24 hrs or replacement of 50% of the total blood volume within three hours, or a rate of loss of 150 ml/hr, which is more relevant in the acute clinical setting.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Clotting disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients that are requiring massive transfusion protocol (MTP) are included in this study after the initial issue and use of 4 Packed Red Cells Units (about half of blood volume) with foreseeable further blood transfusion. 
The MTP is activated as following 
MTP; Phase I protocol:
4 units Packed Red Cells + 2 units Fresh Frozen Plasma (300 ml each) + 1 Adult dose of platelets (depending upon availability)
When notifying the ward that blood products are ready ask if they are continuing with the Massive Transfusion Protocol, if so continue by: 
Alternating with
MTP; Phase II protocol:
4 units Packed Red Cells + 2 units Fresh Frozen Plasma (300 ml each) + 10 units Cryoprecipitate
The requested physician at (Emergency Dept, Intensive care Unit (ICU) ot Theatre) will be asked when the blood products are delivered if they are continuing with the Massive Transfusion Protocol, and if so will continue alternating the above products as per protocol.
After 10 units of packed cells have been issued ABO and Rh compatible blood may be issued at the discretion of the on-call Clinical Haematologist.

This protocol was established by A/Professor A. Khalafallah in Sept 2007 at the Launceston General Hospital, Tasmania, Australia.
The observation will be for 6 months for each subject.</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of outcome of use of MTP in a single institution since 2007.
Tools/methods: Full blood count (FBC), Coagulation parameters; use of different blood products and outcome of MTP.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be assessed by the end of study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of the incidence Disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC).
Tools: Coagulation parameters such as APTT, PT, Fibrinogen and Di Dimer; use of different coagulation factors such as FFP, Cryopricipitate and others (ativated factor VIIa, prothrombin complex etc..).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be assessed by the end of study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients from both sexes who presents with masive bleeding during the study period and who required MTP defined by transfusion of whole blood volume within 24 hours or replacement of half blood volume within 4 hours with ongoing need for transfusion.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who are not considered as per definition as massive transfusion</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/09/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/01/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>105</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>none</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>none</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Launceston General Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Charles street
Launceston, Tasmania 7250</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Clifford Craig Medical Trust Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5
Launceston General Hospital
Charles street
Launceston, Tasmania 7250
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Tasmania, School of Human Life Sciences</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Human Life Sciences and School of Medicine
Charles street
Launceston, Tasmania 7250
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Massive transfusion (MT) is associated with serious often fatal complications including intractable disseminated intravascular coagulopathy (DIC). Therefore there is a growing need for guidelines and protocols that are addressing this issue. At a single institution we have implemented a MT-Protocol (MTP) in late 2007 and studied prospectively all patients (105) from Jan 2008 to Jan 2011 who required MT defined by replacement of half of blood volume within 4 hours with ongoing need for transfusion. The MTP included two phases and incorporated fixed volume of fresh frozen plasma (FFP), cryoprecipitate  and platelets in addition to packed RBCs.
The Launceston General Hospital is a tertiary referral centre for the North of Tasmania. This study will analyse data for the entire cohort of patients in Northern Tasmania who required Massive Transfusion.The main objective of the MTP is to provide appropriate and standardized different blood component therapy to prevent exsanguination, coagulopathy and thrombocytopaenia from occurring with subsequent inferior outcome. 
This study is aiming to avoid DIC and cease microbleeding as early as psossibel in MT setting and hence improving outcome. We conducted this study to demonstrate whether replacement of coagulation factors and platelets in timely fashion will influence outcome and also reduce DIC.
 This study, if published will deliver evidence based on local practice for a cohort of approximately 100-150 patients. This evidence would substantially improved evidence-based practice in trauma, surgery and emergency medicine.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Khalafallah A, Albarzan AM, Ganguly A, Bates G, Gavin F, et al.
(2012) Application of Massive Transfusion Protocol is Associated with Low
Incidence of Coagulopathy and Mortality Rate. J Blood Disord Transfus 3:123.
doi:10.4172/2155-9864.1000123
http://www.omicsonline.org/application-of-massive-transfusion-protocol-is-associated-with-a-low-incidence-of-coagulopathy-and-mortality-rate-2155-9864.1000123.pdf</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tasmanian Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Tasmania
Private Bag 01
Hobart, Tas 7001
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0011432</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Alhossain A. Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital
Charles Street, Launceston, TAS 7250
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61373487111</phone>
      <fax>+61373487695</fax>
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Alhossain A. Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital
Charles Street, Launceston, TAS 7250
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61373487111</phone>
      <fax>+61373487695</fax>
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Alhossain A. Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital
Charles Street, Launceston, TAS 7250
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61373487111</phone>
      <fax>+61373487695</fax>
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Alhossain Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital 
Charles Street
TAS 7250 
</address>
      <phone>+61367776777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>