<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362384">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000426886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of Strain-Counterstrain
treatment for people with neck pain selected using a
treatment based classification system</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of Strain-Counterstrain
treatment for people with neck pain selected using a
treatment based classification system with the Neck Disability Index as primary outcome measure</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U111-1129-9316</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non-specific acute neck pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Strain-Counterstrain treatment treatment will involve passive positioning of the participant, with varying degrees of cervical flexion/extension, lateral flexion and rotation, such that there is a two-thirds reduction in tenderness at a monitored digitally tender point (Jones et al 1995). This is to be determined by having participants rate their tenderness to palpation at digitally tender points on a numerical pain scale where 10 represented initial tenderness and 0 no tenderness. In addition to reported tenderness with intermittent digital probing, perceived tissue tension will be used to guide the experimenter to the appropriate passive position (Jones et al 1995). The participant will be passively maintained at this point by the experimenter for approximately 90 seconds, with intermittent digital probing at 30-sec intervals to ensure correct positioning, before being slowly and passively returned to a neutral position (Jones et al 1995, Kusunose and Wendorff 1990, Kusunose 1993). Treatment using a digitally tender point will be considered successful if tenderness is reduced by 70% or more (3/10 or less with digital probing) (Kusunose 1993, Kusunose and Wendorff 1990), however the intention will be to reduce tenderness to a numerical pain rating of 1/10 or less with digital probing.  This treatment is to be provided in two half hour sessions in a one week period.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo Strain-Counterstrain treatment is to be the same as Strain-Counterstrain treatment except, that once the appropriate passive position is reached, the participant will be passively, deliberately and significantly moved out of this position. Intermittent digital probing of the digital tender point will not be performed since this has been shown to significantly reduce tenderness at digitally tender points identified using Strain-Counterstrain procedures (Lewis et al 2010).  This intervention is to be provided in two half hour sessions in a one week period.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neck Disability Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial assessment, 1 week, 6 weeks, 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SF-36 health questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial assessment, 1 week, 6 weeks, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual analogue scale for pain rating</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial assessment, 1 week, 6 weeks, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global rating of change</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fear avoidance beliefs questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Neck pain (Merskey and Bogduk 1994) of less than 30 days duration
2) Between 18 and 60 years 
3) Initial VAS pain rating less than 7/10
4) Initial neck disability index score between 20 and 52
5) Able to lie supine for 10 minutes
6) Displaying a minimum of four digitally tender points at examined sites (Kusunose and Wendorff 1990) at their initial assessment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Whiplash mechanism of injury
2) Signs of nerve root compression
3) Symptoms distal to the elbow
4) Chief complaint of headaches with neck pain</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be referred by public and private medical practitioners for treatment of neck pain or will be recruited through posted notices and advertisement in local papers. Randomised group allocation will be achieved by consecutively- numbered sealed opaque envelopes containing randomly generated numbers, prepared by an independent investigator.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer is to be used to provide randomly generated numbers.  These will be placed in consecutively numbered  envelopes.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>85</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Stanthorpe Health Services</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>8 McGregor Terrace 
Stanthorpe 
Qld 4380</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cynan Lewis</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 273
Stanthorpe
Qld 4380</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Michele Sterling</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Edith Cavell Building
RBWH
Herston
Qld 4209</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Question: Is Strain-Counterstrain treatment (manual therapy treatment using passive positioning) more effective than sham Strain-Counterstrain intervention in reducing levels of pain and disability in people with neck pain selected using a treatment-based classification system? Design: Randomised trial with concealed allocation, assessor blinding, and intention-to-treat analysis. Participants: 85 participants (male and female) between 18 and 60 years experiencing non-specific neck pain for less than 30 days.  Intervention: Participants are to attend two treatments in a week. The experimental group is to receive Strain-Counterstrain treatment and the control group sham Strain-Counterstrain intervention. Following the initial intervention period, participants are to receive standard Physiotherapy treatment for neck pain for up to 6 weeks. Outcome measures: The primary outcome is to be the Neck disability questionnaire, measured at 1 week (ie, end of initial intervention), 6 weeks, and 28 weeks. Secondary outcome measures are to include the Fear avoidance beliefs questionnaire, SF-36, visual analogue scale pain ratings and a 7-point global rating of change.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HREC Darling Downs Hospital and Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>HREC Coordinator
The Undercroft
Mount Lofty Heights Nursing Home 
Cnr Stuart St and Rifle Range Road
MOUNT LOFTY QLD 4350</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>(EC00182)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/05/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cynan Lewis</name>
      <address>PO Box 273
Stanthorpe
Qld 4380</address>
      <phone>+61 7 46815250</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cynan_lewis@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cynan Lewis</name>
      <address>PO Box 273
Stanthorpe
Qld 4380</address>
      <phone>+61 7 46815250</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cynan_lewis@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>