<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368734">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000904572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Feasibility trial for PINTO: pre-diabetes in pregnancy, can early intensive management and lifestyle advice improve outcomes?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For pregnant women with a first trimester HbA1c in the pre-diabetes range, does intensive management including  blood sugar monitoring to maintain normoglycaemia, compared to standard weight gain and dietary advice, improve pregnancy outcome. A feasibility trial for PINTO.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1162-3277</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PINTO feasibility study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prediabetes in pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Group B  Intervention group 

Attend a diabetes in pregnancy clinic, from before 14 weeks' gestation, in combination with standard care from their usual lead maternity carer (community midwife or obstetrician).  

Commence blood sugar monitoring four to six times daily, fasting and one hour after all meals, using a finger prick and handheld glucose monitoring device. 

Attend one 1-hr group lifestyle education session (dietary, weight-gain and exercise advice) with our clinic dietitian. Have ongoing individual lifestyle education (diet and exercise) with a clinic dietitian at a 20 minute clinic appointment every 4 weeks, written dietary advice and examples of meal plans will be provided.  

Medication, as required, will be prescibed by a clinic physician in order to maintain blood glucose levels within the usual targets for pregnancy.  This group will attend clinic appointments approximately once per month throughout pregnancy. 

Adherence to treatment will be monitored through participant blood glucose diaries, downloading data from glucometers, recording patient weight at clinic appointments, dietary and exercise questionnaire at trial entry, 36 weeks' gestation and at three months postpartum.

Group B will not perform an OGTT in pregnancy. </interventions>
    <comparator>Group A  Care as per the New Zealand Ministry of Health Gestational Diabetes (GDM) guideline.  
Follow-up with their usual lead maternity carer (community midwife or obstetrician) as per routine care.  

Attend one 1-hr group lifestyle education session (dietary, weight-gain and exercise advice) at or before 14 weeks gestation with our clinic dietitian.  Written dietary advice and examples of meal plans will be provided.  

Perform an oral glucose tolerance test (75g, with bloods taken at 0-hour, 1-hour, and 2-hour time points) to screen for GDM at 24-28 weeks gestation and refer to a diabetes in pregnancy service if this test is positive.  

Adherence to lifestyle intervention will be monitored by recording patient weight-gain in pregnancy at 36 weeks gestation by the lead maternity carer and a dietary and exercise questionnaire at trial entry, 36 weeks' gestation and at three months postpartum.


</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal Primary outcome: Preeclampsia
Diagnosis confirmed by Obstetrician as per SOMANZ (Society of Obstetric Medicine Australia and New Zealand) diagnostic guidelines. </outcome>
      <timepoint>at delivery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neonatal primary outcome: composite of preterm delivery, small for gestational age (SGA), and perinatal death.  Assessed by review of hospital records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 1 month postpartum</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neonatal: birth weight and customised birth weight centile. Assessed from hospital records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-care costs - Resources used and their unit prices will be determined from the time of randomisation until 28 days postpartum for the mother and baby.  Costs considered will include medications, outpatient visits and hospital admissions, tests of maternal and fetal wellbeing, and neonatal care. Assessed by review of hospital records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days postpartum</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal: weight gain in pregnancy. Assessed from participants maternity records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 36 weeks gestation and / or at delivery if earlier</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal: gestational hypertension as assessed by an obstetrician and according to SOMANZ diagnostic guidelines</outcome>
      <timepoint>At delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal: change in HbA1c level (indicating glycaemic control). Assessed by blood test at 36 weeks' gestation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>36 weeks' gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal: induction of labour. Assessed from hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal: mode of delivery. Assessed from hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal: trauma at delivery (third or fourth degree tear). Assessed from hospital records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal: psychological outcomes (wellbeing).  Assessed by maternal questionnaire at trial entry and at 36 weeks' gestation.  

Questionnaire modified from the WHO (Five) Well-Being Index designed by the Psychiatric Research UNIT, WHO Collaborating Center for Mental Health, for the DAWN study: www.dawnstudy.com. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At trial entry and at 36 weeks' gestation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal: change in dietary intake.

Assessed by maternal questionnaire at trial entry and at 36 weeks' gestation.  Questionnaire modified from the questionnaire designed for the MiG study: N Engl J Med 2008;358:2003-15</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 36 weeks' gestation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neonatal: composite of admission to the neonatal intensive care unit for &gt;4 hours, respiratory support for &gt;4 hours, hypoglycaemia &lt;2.3mmol/L, need for i.v dextrose, jaundice requiring phototherapy.  Assessed from hospital records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 72 hours post delivery. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neonatal:  composite of neonatal trauma (shoulder dystocia requiring obstetric manoeuvre, erbs palsy or fracture).  Assessed from hospital records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At delivery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal: change in exercise frequency / level.  
Assessed by maternal questionnaire at trial entry and at 36 weeks' gestation. 
Questionnaire modified from the WHO Global Physical Activity Questionnaire (GPAQ): http://www.who.int/chp/steps/GPAQ/en/</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 36 weeks' gestation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria: Women with an HbA1c level of 41-46mmol/mol and who are &lt;14 weeks gestation with an ongoing pregnancy.    </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria:  Women with HbA1c levels greater than or equal to 47mmol/mol.  Women with known diabetes. Women carrying a fetus with a known lethal congenital anomaly and / or an abnormal karyotype / chromosomal abnormality.  Women planning to terminate the pregnancy.  Women taking metformin to manage pre-diabetes or polycystic ovarian syndrome will be excluded from the study and referred to the local antenatal diabetes clinic, or be advised to have an early 75g oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT) depending on local policy.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/11/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/07/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>47</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>6/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury and Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ruth Hughes</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
University of Otago
Christchurch Women's Hospital
Private Bag 4711
Christchurch 8140

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Physical address: Level 3 - ProCARE Building, Grafton Mews, at 110 Stanley Street, Auckland 1010

Postal address: PO Box 5541, Wellesley Street, Auckland 1141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Janet Rowan</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Obstetrics
National Women's Health
Private Bag 92-024
Auckland City Hospital
Grafton
Auckland 1010</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We hypothesise that in women with HbA1c levels in the pre-diabetes range, that early intervention, including blood glucose monitoring and optimisation of blood glucose levels through dietary measures and medication as required, will reduce preeclampsia, preterm birth, neonatal morbidity and mortality without causing harm, compared with lifestyle advice and screening for gestational diabetes at 24-28 weeks gestation.  This study is important to enable clinicians to decide how to manage women with early pregnancy HbA1c levels in the pre-diabetes range, which is especially relevant now that national and international groups and societies are endorsing the use of HbA1c as a screening test in early pregnancy.   This is a feasibility study for the main randomised control trial. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> New Zealand Health and Disability Ethics Committees </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/NTA/98</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruth Hughes</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
University of Otago
Christchurch Women's Hospital
Private Bag 4711
Christchurch 8140

</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3644031</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ruth.hughes@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruth Hughes</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
University of Otago
Christchurch Women's Hospital
Private Bag 4711
Christchurch 8140

</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3644031</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ruth.hughes@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruth Hughes</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology
University of Otago
Christchurch Women's Hospital
Private Bag 4711
Christchurch 8140

</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3644031</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ruth.hughes@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>