<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368244">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000361505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of acute and long-term apple consumption on risk factors for cardiovascular disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of acute and long-term apple consumption on risk factors for cardiovascular disease in individuals with at least one current risk factor.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1168-7209 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>HHBA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Gut Microbiome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Acute component of study: 1 whole apple (medium size) + 1 apple skin blended with 1/2 cup water.
Measurements will be taken before (baseline) and 2 hours after ingestion of the treatment.


Long-term component of study: 1 whole apple (medium size) + 1 apple skin blended with 1/2 cup water twice a day for 4 weeks. 
Volunteers will be asked to only use 'Pink Lady' apples.

Volunteers will be asked to fill in a diary and we will also be measuring urinary metabolites to monitor adherence to the intervention.

Measurements will be taken on day 1 (baseline) and day 28.

The washout period will be two weeks prior to commencing the study and for two weeks inbetween treatment periods. During these times and throughout the study we will ask volunteers to reduce their flavonoid intake:
- Limit tea to 1 or less cups per day 
- Limit coffee to 2 or less cups per day
- Limit dark chocolate
- Limit red wine 
- Reduced onion intake
- Do not eat any other apples
- Avoid eating large quantities of curly kale, leeks, broccoli, capers and blueberries.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Acute component of study: 1 apple (medium size) without skin blended with 1/2 cup water. Measurements will be taken before (baseline) and 2 hours after ingestion of the treatment.
chronic component of study: 1 apple (medium size) without skin blended with 1/2 cup water twice a day for 4 weeks. 
Volunteers will be asked to only use 'Pink Lady' apples.

Measurements will be taken on day 1 (baseline) and day 28.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome: % Flow-mediated dilatation of the brachial artery assesed by ultrasonogaphy. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint for chronic intervention: Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement 
Timepoint for acute intervention: Baseline and 2 hours after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure assessed using the V100 Dinamap</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint for chronic intervention: Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement 
Timepoint for acute intervention: Baseline and 2 hours after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arterial stiffness measured as pulse wave velocity and augmentation index using the SphygomoCor XCEL device.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint for chronic intervention: Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement 
Timepoint for acute intervention: Baseline and 2 hours after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure during stess assessed by monitoring blood pressure during a cognitive demand battery test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint for chronic intervention: Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement 
Timepoint for acute intervention: Baseline and 2 hours after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma quercetin metabolites assessed by liquid chromatography mass spectromemetry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint for chronic intervention: Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement 
Timepoint for acute intervention: Baseline and 2 hours after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma markers of nitric oxide status assessed by chemiluminescence methods</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint for chronic intervention: Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement 
Timepoint for acute intervention: Baseline and 2 hours after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Levels of plasma F2-isoprostanes assessed by gas chromatography mass spectrometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint for chronic intervention: Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect of the treatment on the gut microflora assessed by collecting faecal samples and measuring the differences in bacteria species</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint for chronic intervention: Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>We are looking for volunteers with one or more of the following:
-	Slightly elevated blood pressure (120 &lt; systolic BP &lt; 160)
-	High blood sugar (5.6 &lt; glucose &lt; 6.5)
-	High cholesterol (5 &lt; total cholesterol &lt; 8)
-	Central obesity (men &gt; 94cm; women &gt; 80cm)
It is critical to the study that participants are not currently taking any blood pressure or cholesterol lowering medication. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Current or recent (12 months) smoking
- Body mass index less than 18 or greater than 40 kg/m2
- History of cardiovascular or peripheral vascular disease
- A systolic blood pressure less than 100 or greater than 160 mmHg.
- A diastolic blood pressure less than 50 or greater than 100 mmHg
- Diagnosed diabetes, and non-diabetic individuals with fasting plasma glucose concentrations greater than 6.5 mmol/L
- A psychiatric illness
- Other major illnesses such as cancer
- Current or recent (within previous 6 months) significant weight loss or gain ( greater than 6% of body weight) or actively trying to lose weight
- Alcohol intake greater than 210g per week for women and greater than 280 g per week for men
- Women who are lactating, pregnant or wishing to become pregnant during the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible participants will be randomly assigned to one of 2 sequence. 30 sealed opaque envelopes, numbered 1-30, each containing one of the 2 sequence orders for intervention diets will be used for randomisation by opening an envelope, in consecutive order, as participants are entered into the study. The computer generated random numbers and sealed opaque envelopes will be completed and held by a person independent of study researchers within the University of Western Australia. The study coordinator will contact the person independent of study researchers to obtain the next available envelope once an individual is deemed eligible. The envelope will be opened and the code will be recorded</concealment>
    <sequence>Using the Mersenne Twister pseudorandom number generator </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analyses will be performed according to a pre-specified statistical analysis plan using IBM SPSS Statistics Version 21 (2012, Armonk, NY: IBM Corp.); SAS software (Version 9.3: SAS Institute Inc); or STATA 12 (StataCorp). The primary analysis will be modified intention to treat (all randomised participants for which we have collected baseline data). Analysis will be performed using mixed models (including all available data). The sample size for this study has been calculated on the primary endpoint of blood vessel function, measured as flow mediated dilation of the brachial artery (FMD). 30 participants will provide more than 80% power to detect a difference between apple flavonoid treatment and control (placebo) treatment. This has been based on a difference of 1.5% FMD and a standard deviation of 2%. We have previously demonstrated in a group of 30 subjects a significant increase in FMD following acute treatment with quercetin-rich apples.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/04/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/04/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>25/11/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>6000 - Perth</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>35 Stirling Highway
Crawley WA 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress> 	GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to determine if a major flavonoid component found in apple skin can improve blood vessel function and blood pressure in human volunteers. The apple variety Cripps Pink, marketed as Pink Lady is particularly rich in the flavonoid quercetin. Our previous short term studies with pure quercetin and apples show improved blood vessel function. We now wish to determine if long term consumption (4 weeks) of apples will improve vessel function and lower blood pressure and try to understand the biochemical mechanism of this beneficial effect.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Western Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>35 Stirling Highway
Crawley WA 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/1/5880</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kevin D. Croft</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia School of Medicine and Pharmacology 
Rear 50 Murray St, Perth WA 6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9224 0275</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kevin.croft@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Nicola Bondonno</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia School of Medicine and Pharmacology 
Rear 50 Murray St, Perth WA 6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9224 0342</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicola.bondonno@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Nicola Bondonno</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia School of Medicine and Pharmacology
Rear 50 Murray St, Perth WA 6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9224 0342</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicola.bondonno@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Nicola Bondonno</name>
      <address>The University of Western Australia School of Medicine and Pharmacology 
Rear 50 Murray St, Perth WA 6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9224 0342</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicola.bondonno@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>