<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1288">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/05/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/05/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000184572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Meeting the Needs of Men with Prostate Cancer Using a Consumer-Driven Multidisciplinary Approach </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a nurse-led, group psychoeducational intervention to reduce psychological morbidity, unmet needs and improve quality of life of men receiving radiotherapy for prostate cancer. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PCRCT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prostate Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention comprises four, 1-hour group psychoeducational consultations led by a clinical nurse consultant, and one individualised nurse session usually in the first week of treatment (15 - 30mins). The consultations occur at critical moments in the illness trajectory: pre-treatment, mid-treatment, end of treatment and 6 weeks post-treatment. The focus of these sessions are to share common concerns, ask questions and receive information. The content of sessions are tailored to patient concerns.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive standard care.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression and anxiety at follow up, measured by the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires administered at baseline (pre-treatment), treatment completion and 6-months post-treatment. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prostate cancer specific quality of life (EPIC-26). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires administered pre-treatment, end and 6 months post treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Unmet supportive care needs (SCNS-SF). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires administered pre-treatment, end and 6 months post treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cancer treatment related concerns (CATS). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global distress (DT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires administered pre-treatment, end and 6 months post treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) has a confirmed diagnosis of prostate cancer; 2) is being treated with curative intent as determined by their treating doctor; 3) scheduled to receive or undergoing radiotherapy; 4) over 18 years; 5) agrees to attend 4 group consultations; 6) is able to understand English.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) has cognitive or psychological difficulties; 2) is too sick; 3) has had previous radiotherapy treatment; 4) is being treated palliatively; or 5) is having seed brachytherapy alone.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A trained research assistant (RA) will screen clinic lists, attend the weekly urology meeting and liaise with clinical staff to identify eligible patients, using an eligibility checklist. The RA will meet with eligible patients after their consultation with their doctor and seek informed written consent.  Consenters will be asked permission to collect basic demographic and clinical information from their medical records.  Reasons for refusal will be obtained. After consenting, patients complete the baseline questionnaire. The RA can then inform the patient of group allocation. Group allocation was concealed with central computer-generated randomisation occuring at the end of the recruitment fortnight. Recruitment procedures will adhere to CONSORT criteria and will be documented in a recruitment manual to enable recruitment to continue if the RA is absent. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>The cluster randomisation by fortnight was guided by outcomes of the pilot study and selected to ensure sufficient patients were recruited at each site to form a single group that could then receive the intervention package (3 or more men) at a similar stage in the treatment trajectory. To reduce potential bias during each fortnight, the result of randomisation will only be revealed to research staff, clinic staff and participants at the end of the fortnight period, and after baseline data collection is complete. The method of randomisation will be by a weighted-biased coin method for each fortnightly group at each site.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Cluster randomised controlled trial.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/01/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>16/12/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>330</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Institute - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Moorabbin campus - East Bentleigh</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St Andrews Pl
East Melbourne VIC 3002</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Council Victoria</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>615 St Kilda Rd
Melbourne VIC  3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Prostate cancer is the most common serious cancer in Australian men. Radiotherapy is a common treatment for prostate cancer, which can result in distressing side effects, including urinary and bowel urgency or incontinence (35%), and erectile dysfunction (41% to 55%). These are complex and often chronic conditions, which can adversely affect the patient's quality of life and psychological morbidity. Men with prostate cancer also experience high unmet needs, particularly in relation to sexuality. 
This research aims to examine the effectiveness of a multi-disciplinary care (MDC) program incorporating consumer involvement to reduce psychological morbidity, unmet needs and improve quality of life in men receiving radiotherapy for prostate cancer using a randomised controlled trial (RCT).  400 men will be recruited and complete baseline measures before being randomised to receive the psycho-educational intervention or usual care. The intervention will comprise of four, 1-hour group consultations led by a clinical nurse consultant, and one individualised nurse session. The consultations occur at critical moments in the illness trajectory: pre-treatment, mid-treatment, end of treatment and 6 weeks post-treatment. The focus of these sessions will be to share common concerns, ask questions and receive information. The content of sessions are tailored to patient concerns.
Follow up questionnaires will be administered at the end of treatment, and 6 months post-treatment. The program will be evaluated by comparing results for the control and intervention groups on measures for anxiety and depression, unmet needs, quality of life, distress and preparation for cancer treatment. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Journal Articles
1.	Kathryn Schubach, Ann Boonzaier, Kathy Troup, Mariko Carey, Sanchia Aranda and Penelope Schofield (2007). Improving outcomes for men, Australian Nursing Journal, 15 (1), 35. ISSN: ISSN: 1320-3185
2.	W Crellin, K Schubach (2008). A consumers journey through a prostate cancer research project, Aust Nurs J, 15 (11), 55-56.
3.	A Boonzaier, K Schubach, S Aranda &amp; P Schofield (2009). Development of a Psycho-educational Intervention for Men with Prostate Cancer, J. Psychosocial Oncol, 27(1) 136-153.
4.	M Carey, R Sanson-Fisher, K Lotfi-Jam, P Schofield, S Aranda (2010). Multidisciplinary care in cancer: Do the current research outputs help? European Journal of Cancer Care, 19 (4): 434-41.
5.	K Sharkey, J Savulescu, S Aranda, P Schofield (2010). Clinician gate-keeping in clinical research is not ethically defensible: an analysis. J Med Ethics, 36 (6): 363-366.
6.	Penelope Schofield, Karla Gough, Kerryann Lotfi-Jam Sanchia Aranda, Validation of the Supportive Care Needs Survey-Short Form 34 (SCNS-SF34) with a simplified response format in men with prostate cancer, Under review at Psycho-Oncology, 2011. Doi: 10.1002/pon.2016. [Epub ahead of print]
7.	W Crellin (2012). Is frequent urination a symptom of prostate cancer? A consumers perspective. Health Issues, Winter 2012: 16. ISSN: 0819-5781
8.	Kerryann Lotfi-Jam, Karla Gough, Penelope Schofield,Sanchia Aranda, Profile and predictors of global distress: can the DT guide nursing practice in prostate cancer? Accepted in Palliative &amp; Supportive Care, January 2013.


Conference Presentations
1.	M Carey, et al. (oral presentation) Development of a multidisciplinary care intervention to improve psychosocial outcomes for men with prostate cancer. AGM of the Australian Prostate Cancer Collaboration, Sydney Oct 4th, 2006.
2.	K Wyatt, et al. (poster presentation) Development of a multidisciplinary care intervention to improve psychosocial outcomes for men with prostate cancer. Clinical Oncology Society of Australia ASM, Melbourne 2006. = published abstract.
3.	W Crellin and K Schubach (oral presentation) A consumers journey through a prostate cancer research project. WCMICS Supportive Care Conference, Melbourne, 17th October 2008.
4.	K Schubach. (oral presentation) From urology nurse to research my involvement in a large randomised controlled trial. Accepted Urological Society of Australia and New Zealand ASM, Gold Coast, March 2009. = published abstract.
5.	K Lotfi-Jam, et al (oral presentation) Unmet needs, psychological distress and quality of life in men commencing radiotherapy for prostate cancer.  12th World Congress of Psycho-Oncology (IPOS), Quebec, May 2010. = published abstract.
6.	K Lotfi-Jam, et al (poster presentation) Unmet needs, psychological distress and quality of life in men commencing radiotherapy for prostate cancer. Clinical Oncological Society of Australia, Melbourne, Nov 2010. = published abstract.
7.	W Crellin, K Schubach: Fore-warned is fore-armed: Supportive care for prostate cancer patients receiving curative radiotherapy. Presented orally at Australasian Heath and Research Data Managers Association, Melbourne, March 2011.
8.	W Crellin, K Schubach: Involving consumers in research: Fore-warned is fore-armed -  Supportive care for men with prostate cancer, The Victorian Healthcare Quality Association and the Centre for Research Excellence in Patient Safety Professional Development Session, Alfred Hospital, Melbourne, Australia 16th May 2011.
9.	P. Schofield, et al (oral presentation) Unmet needs, psychological distress and quality of life in men commencing radiotherapy for prostate cancer. Multinational Association of Supportive Care and Cancer, Athens, Greece, 25th June 2011. = published abstract.
10.	K Gough, et al (oral presentation) Sexual and hormonal quality of life differences between clinical subgroups of men commencing radiotherapy for prostate cancer. Victorian Integrated Cancer Services Supportive Care Conference, Melbourne, 11th July 2011.
11.	P Schofield (oral presentation and poster) A nurse-led group consultation intervention to reduce psychological morbidity and unmet needs in men with prostate cancer during radiotherapy: A randomised controlled trial. 12th Australasian Prostate Cancer Conference, Melbourne, 5th August 2011.
12.	P Schofield (oral presentation and poster) Unmet needs, psychological distress and quality of life in men commencing radiotherapy for prostate cancer. 12th Australasian Prostate Cancer Conference, Melbourne, 5th August 2011.
13.	R Bergin (oral presentation and poster) Patterns and predictors of psychological morbidity, unmet needs and quality of life in men with prostate cancer who receive curative radiotherapy. 12th Australasian Prostate Cancer Conference, Melbourne, 5th August 2011.
14.	K Schubach (poster presentation) The impact of androgen deprivation on physical, psychological and quality of life outcomes in men with prostate cancer. 12th Australasian Prostate Cancer Conference, Melbourne, 5th August 2011.
15.	P Schofield et al, (oral presentation) A nurse-led psycho-educational group intervention to reduce psychological morbidity and unmet needs in men with prostate cancer during radiotherapy: A randomised controlled trial. International Psycho-Oncology Society conference, Anatalya, Turkey, 18th October 2011. = published abstract. Psychooncology 2011, Vol 20:Issue S2, 47-8
16.	W Crellin and K Schubach. (oral presentation) Involving consumers in research: Fore-warned is Fore-armed  Supportive Care for Men with Prostate Cancer. Nurses for Continence ANF (Vic Branch) Special Interest Group Education Day, Melbourne, 24th March 2012
17.	W Crellin (oral presentation) 'A Consumer's Journey through the World of Health Research' to the Department of Health Victoria's forum 'Consumer Issues for Participation in Clinical Trials', Melbourne, Australia, April 27th, 2012.
18.	R Bergin (oral presentation), M Collins, K Hun Tai, F Foroudi, K Lotfi-Jam, W Crellin, S Aranda, P Schofield. Patterns and predictors of psychological morbidity and quality of life in men with prostate cancer who receive curative radiotherapy. International Psycho-Oncology Society conference, Brisbane, Australia, 14th November 2012. = published abstract.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee at Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/06/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06/21</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Penelope Schofield</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
Locked Bag 1
A'Beckett Street
Melbourne VIC 8006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96563560</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 96561337</fax>
      <email>Penelope.Schofield@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Penelope Schofield</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
Locked Bag 1
A'Beckett Street
Melbourne VIC 8006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96563560</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 96561337</fax>
      <email>Penelope.Schofield@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Penelope Schofield</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Pl
East Melbourne
VIC  3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9656 3560</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>penelope.schofield@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>