<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82162">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/07/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/07/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000393459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The influence of Statins on Blood Vessel Function in Severe Sepsis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, placebo-controlled study of the effect of atorvastatin on endothelial function in intensive care patients with severe sepsis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>STREAMS</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Severe sepsis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Endothelial dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other blood disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Randomised allocation to atorvastatin 20mg capsules given orally or enterally once a day for up to 14 days.</interventions>
    <comparator>Identical placebo</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in endothelial function (as measured by peripheral arterial tonometry).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 24 and 48 hours following randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) Intensive Care Unit (ICU), hospital and 28 day mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2) Change in microvascular function as measured by near-infrared spectroscopy </outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the first 24 and 48 hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3) Severity of organ dysfunction (as measured by Sequential Organ Function Assessment (SOFA) scores) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the first 7 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4) Change in plasma arginine:ADMA (Asymmetric DiMethyl Arginine) ratio </outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the first 7 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5) Change in serum markers of endothelial activation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the first 7 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6) Safety of atorvastatin in severe sepsis as measured by frequency of adverse events throughout the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Admitted to the Intensive Care Unit 2) Severe sepsis for less than 24 hours. Severe sepsis is defined as strongly suspected or proven infection, 3 or more SIRS criteria and at least one acute organ dysfunction attributable to the sepsis.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Pregnancy or breastfeeding2) Death is imminent3) History of intolerance to a statin4) Acute liver failure5) Child's C cirrhosis6) ALT&gt;5x upper limit of normal7) CK &gt; 5x upper limit of normal8) Patient unable to take oral or enteral medication9) Patient or next of kin not able to provide informed consent10) Patient, family or treating doctor not in favour of aggressive treatment11) Coagulopathy (INR&gt;2.0 OR APTT&gt;70)12) Severe thrombocytopaenia (Platelets&lt;20)13) Latex allergy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by telephone.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation, in permuted blocks, stratified by previous statin use</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Blinding will apply to the study subjects, the doctors and nurses in the intensive care unit (who will be administering the treatment), the study investigators (who will be enrolling patients and performing measurements), and the chief investigator (who will be analysing the data). That is, the subjects, clinicians, assessors and data analyst will all be blinded as to the treatment assignment.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/08/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>78</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Josh Davis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Dianne Stephens</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>15,000 people are admitted to an Intensive Care Unit in Australia with severe sepsis every year. One third of these will die. Severe sepsis occurs when an infection affects the whole body and causes dysfunction of one or more of the major organs. A significant factor in this illness is that the body's normal response to infection or 'inflammatory response' becomes abnormal. It is not completely understood why the major organs can fail in severe sepsis. Organ failure is thought to be partly due to dysfunction of the small blood vessels that supply oxygen and nutrients to organs and tissues. We have previously shown that small blood vessel function is acutely impaired in patients with severe sepsis.

The statins are a class of medications commonly used to lower cholesterol. Previous research in patients without sepsis suggests that they also have a beneficial effect on inflammation and on the function of small blood vessels. A clinical trial of atorvastatin in severe sepsis commenced in Australia and New Zealand in July 2007(The STATInS trial). The STATInS trial will be evaluating the safety of atorvastatin in severe sepsis and also its effect on inflammation and outcome. 

We propose to enroll a subset of patients from the STATInS trial into our study which will assess the effect of atorvastatin on the function of small blood vessels. 40-60% of our target recruitment will occur after the conclusion of the STATInS study, in a single-centre stand alone continuation of the study. This study will add valuable information to the STATInS trial, to help us answer questions about how and why atorvastatin helps patients with severe sepsis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Darwin Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/07/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>07/34</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Josh Davis</name>
      <address>Menzies School of Health Research
John Matthews Building
Royal Darwin Hospital Campus
Rocklands Drive Tiwi
Casuarina NT 0811</address>
      <phone>(08) 89 228836</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Joshua.Davis@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Josh Davis</name>
      <address>Menzies School of Health Research
John Matthews Building
Royal Darwin Hospital Campus
Rocklands Drive Tiwi
Casuarina NT 0811</address>
      <phone>(08) 89 228836</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Joshua.Davis@menzies.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>