<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372375">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000410358p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Monitoring fetal movements utilising fetal movement monitoring device named as Fetal Kicks</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigating the utility of Fetal Kicks to monitor fetal movements in pregnant women who have experienced a reduction in the perception of fetal movements</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pregnancy - Antenatal</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fetal Movement Monitoring</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will utilise routine cardiotocography (CTG) by obstetrician to monitor the fetal movements of the fetus antenatally. At the same time, a novel device , the Fetal Kicks will be attached to their abdomen to monitor the fetal movement as well. Fetal Kicks utilises a strain gauge sensor to monitor the fetal movements. For this study, Fetal Kicks will not be utilised to guide care and only for passive monitoring. This process will take place for a duration of 30 minutes. Fetal Kicks monitoring will only occur on a single occasion only in each participant.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Cardiotocography (CTG) ,ultrasound based assessment of fetal movement and maternal reporting of fetal movement will be carried out on a single occasion for a duration of 30 minutes at the same time as the intervention device.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation between the signals obtained from Fetal Kicks and routine cardiotocography over a similar time period. This will be done electronically utilising cross correlation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data is collected immediately at the end of each monitoring period of CTG</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation between the signals obtained from Fetal Kicks and ultrasound imaging. This will be compared utilising cross correlation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data is collected immediately at the end of each monitoring period of CTG</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient view on Fetal Kicks (i.e pros, cons, will they recommend it, areas for improvement etc.). This will be measured through a questionnaire designed specifically for the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data is collected immediately at the end of each monitoring period of CTG</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sensitivity, specificity, negative predictive value and positive predictive values of Fetal Kicks in comparison to CTG</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data is collected immediately at the end of each monitoring period of CTG</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Have a singleton pregnancy
Should be pregnant and above 28 weeks of pregnancy
Should be aware of what normal fetal movements are
Have experienced a reduction in the perception of fetal movements from what they are usually used to
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women below 18 years of age
Patients with an intellectual or mental impairment
People in existing dependent or unequal relationships with any member of the research team, the researcher(s) and/or the person undertaking the recruitment/consent process
People highly dependent on medical care 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>For the following study, a sample size of 50 was estimated based on similar proof of concept studies. This was based on the assumption that the level of a was set at 0.05 and a power of 90% This was based on an estimated recruitment rate of 55 with non responders of 10%. 
For the primary objective, statistical tests will be utilised to test the device agreement with routine CTG for measurement of the fetal movement considered to be the gold standard. 
For device concordance, outputs on Fetal Kicks and the CTG, ultrasound and maternal reports of fetal movement will be measured and compared electronically using cross correlation. Signal to Residue Ratio (SRR) will be used to compare similarity and how much different the signal from Fetal Kicks is from the control and a Root Mean Square Error (RMSE) will be used for the error for each point in the plot. For UA, a cross correlation statistic will be utilised. 
Measurement of device diagnostic accuracy will be made by calculating the sensitivity, specificity  negative predictive value and positive predictive values of Fetal Kicks to regular CTG. This will be done by comparing the assessments by clinicians of the CTGs through the reporting tool provided.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>2/04/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>2/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University - Monash Institute of Medical Engineering MIME</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>20 Research Way, Clayton 3168 VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University - Monash Institute of Medical Engineering MIME</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Research Way, Clayton 3168 VIC</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Fetal Kicks is a novel device developed by Monash MIME to monitor fetal movement. For the following study, the current phase entails a proof of concept in women antenatally to assess the quality of signals obtained on Fetal Kicks. For this, Fetal Kicks will be utilised together with the conventional cardiotocography (CTG) to ascertain the equivalence of Fetal Kicks with conventional fetal movement counting

Aims
1. Accurately corroborating maternal perceptions of movements on the CTG (via sensor imprints) to device captures of fetal movements
2. Accurately corroborating maternal perceptions of movements on the ultrasound (via sensor imprints) to device captures of fetal movements

Research design
The following study is a cross sectional survey with a cohort design. The following design has been chosen as it is considered to be the design of choice in evaluating a diagnostic test- in this case, Fetal Kicks. Utilising the following design, measurements of test accuracy and precision will be carried out on Fetal Kicks in comparison to CTG and conventional fetal movement countings.

Primary Outcomes
1. Correlation between the signals obtained from Fetal Kicks and routine cardiotocography over a similar time period. This will be done electronically utilising cross correlation.
2. Correlation between the information obtained from Fetal Kicks and CTG as interpreted by clinicians. This will be measured on a CTG reporting tool designed specifically for the study. 

Secondary Outcomes:
1. Patient view on Fetal Kicks (i.e pros, cons, will they recommend it, areas for improvement etc.). This will be measured through a questionnaire designed specifically for the study</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health Human Research Ethics Committee A</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Road, Clayton VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vinayak Smith</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Monash University
Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Road
Clayton, VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61431330754</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vinayak.smith@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vinayak Smith</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Monash University
Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Road
Clayton, VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61431330754</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vinayak.smith@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vinayak Smith</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Monash University
Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Road
Clayton, VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61431330754</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vinayak.smith@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vinayak Smith</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Monash University
Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Road
Clayton, VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61431330754</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vinayak.smith@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>