<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83386">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/11/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/01/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000075280</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Is the Health Management Coaching model effective at improving risk factor status and increasing adherence to monitoring requirements in people with diabetes?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is the Health Management Coaching model effective at improving risk factor status and increasing adherence to monitoring requirements in people with diabetes?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 and Type 2 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention for this study is telephone coaching. Involves and Health Management Coach / Dietitian conducting telephone coaching sessions with patients every 4-6 weeks for a period of 6 months. Each telephone call will take  20 to 45 minutes. Telephone coaching will occur in addition to the patient's usual care. During coaching sessions, participants will be coached to understand	: 1) what risk factor needs to be monitored - for example HbA1C should be checked 2)	When each risk factor needs to be checked  in the case of HbA1C, every 3 months 3) And for risk factors not at target level  how to modify these through changes to diet, lifestyle and in consultation with their General Practitioner (GP), medications.</interventions>
    <comparator>Active Control - standard treatment (usual diabetes care under existing healthcare team) Usual care will vary for each patient depending on their individual needs, but generally refers to the healthcare arrangements existing when the patient enters the research project and those which may evolve at the discretion of the patient and their healthcare team during the patients time in the study. Health professionals who may contribute to their usual care include GP, endocrinologist, dietitian, psychologist, podiatrist, diabetes educator, exercise preofession, optomotrist / opthalmologist. Patients will  continue their usual care for the duration of the trial (i.e. 18 months)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HbA1C will be measured by blood sample. Researchers will provide patients with a pathology slip that for HBA1C, fasting lipids, fasting glucose and urinary albumin excretion. Blood and urine samples will be taken at a St Vincent's Pathology collection centre and the below outlined timepoints.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting blood glucose will be measured by blood sample. Researchers will provide patients with a pathology slip that for HBA1C, fasting lipids, fasting glucose and urinary albumin excretion. Blood and urine samples will be taken at a St Vincent's Pathology collection centre and the below outlined timepoints.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood lipid levels will be measured by blood sample. Researchers will provide patients with a pathology slip that for HBA1C, fasting lipids, fasting glucose and urinary albumin excretion. Blood and urine samples will be taken at a St Vincent's Pathology collection centre and the below outlined timepoints.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood Pressure - Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will measure the participant's blood pressure using a sphygmometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Mass Index - Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will measure the patient height and weight and calculate their BMI during this visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist Circumference - Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will measure the participant's waist circumference using a tapemeasure during this visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cigarette consumption - Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will interview the participants and ask their smoking status.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol intake - Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will interview the patient and ask them to report their alcohol intake (eg drinks per week and number of alcohol free days per week.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity level  - Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will interview the patient and ask them to report the number of minutes of moderate intensity physical activity they perform each week.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to minimum monitoring requirements for regular checks of blood glucose levels. Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will interview the patient and ask them to report how often they currently measure blood glucose levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to minimum monitoring requirements for regular checks of HbA1C. Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will interview the patient and ask them to report when they last had their HbA1C measured.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to minimum monitoring requirements for regular checks of fasting lipid levels. Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will interview the patient and ask them to report when they last had fasting lipid levels measured.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to minimum monitoring requirements for regular checks of fasting blood pressure. Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will interview the patient and ask them to report how often in the past 6 months they have had their blood pressure measured.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to minimum monitoring requirements for regular checks of urinary albumin excretion. Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will interview the patient and ask them to report when they last had their urinary albumin excretion measured.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to minimum monitoring requirements for regular checks of feet. Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will interview the patient and ask them to report when they last had a food check.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to minimum monitoring requirements for regular checks of eyes. Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will interview the patient and ask them to report when they last had their eyes checked.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance with guidelines recommending regular Electrocardiogram (ECG). Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will interview the patient and ask them to report when they last had an ECG.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance with guidelines recommending regular vaccinations for influenza and pneumococcal. Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will interview the patient and ask them to report when they last were vaccinated against influenza and pneumococcal.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compliance with guidelines recommending prescription of prophylactic aspirin. Patients will be asked to return to St Vincent's hospital at the below outlined timepoints. A researcher will interview the patient and ask them to report whether they are currently prescribed prophylactic aspirin</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6, 12, and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients attending Diabetes Clinic, aged 18 years or over with an HbA1C = 7.0% and eligible for Hospital Admission Risk Program(HARP) Services (i.e. defined as people with chronic diseases and complex needs who frequently use hospitals or who are at risk of hospitalisation)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients unable to provide informed consent including those with insufficient English to adequately communicate; patients intoxicated with alcohol, or who are cognitively impaired. Also, those receiving palliative care and patients unable to easily or accurately communicate over the telephone due to severe hearing impairment or lack of telephone access</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Over six months, a convenience sample of eligible people aged =18 years attending the Diabetes Clinic will be approached directly by researchers for study participation. Eligible people will be approached in the Outpatient waiting area. The study will be explained to each person; consent to participate will be obtained; the participant will be randomised into either the intervention or control group and the researcher will collect baseline and demographic information from the participant and their medical record. After consenting the participant will be randomised to one of two groups. Allocation concealment will occur by way of the researcher opening a blank envelope containing a computer generated random allocation for the recruited participant into either the intervention or control group. This will occur after the patient has consented to being involved in the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>After consenting the participant will be randomised to one of two groups. The researcher will open a blank envelope containing a computer generated random allocation for the recruited participant into either the intervention or control group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>94</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 2900, Fitzroy 3065 VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 2900, Fitzroy 3065 VIC</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Department of Human Services</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Human Services
50 Lonsdale Street
Melbourne, Victoria
Australia 3000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The proposed study examines the impact of a specific telephone coaching intervention on HbA1C. HbA1C reflects average glucose concentration over ~3months. Secondary outcomes will include fasting glucose, lipids and blood pressure. Adherence to monitoring requirements will also be measured e.g. regular checks of HbA1C, lipids, feet &amp; eyes. The intervention in question is currently in use in the cardiac population where its efficacy has been demonstrated by two Randomised Controlled Trials (RCTs).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Professional Secretariate of Human research Ethics comittee - A (HREC-A)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>HREC-A
C/o Research and Grants Unit
St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne
PO Box 2900, Fitzroy VIC 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/12/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>134/08</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jane Varney</name>
      <address>PO Box 2900, Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92882740</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 92882787</fax>
      <email>jane.varney@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jane Varney</name>
      <address>PO Box 2900, Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92882740</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 92882787</fax>
      <email>jane.varney@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jane Varney</name>
      <address>PO Box 2900, Fitzroy VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92882740</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 92882787</fax>
      <email>jane.varney@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>