<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347961">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000086864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Townsville Diabetes Home Monitoring Project</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Among patients with poorly controlled Type II diabetes will remote access to clinical care supported by the National Broadband Network (NBN) telehealth technologies, compared with usual diabetes care lead to improved diabetes control</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1127-2155</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type II diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is 12 months in duration.  Using NBN telehealth technologies patients will receive online diabetes care from a doiabetes educator nurse (DEN) via an in-home broadband monitoring and communication device that can prompt the capture of clinical measures including: regular blood pressure monitoring (at least once a week depending on patient); regular blood glucose monitoring (at least once a week depending on patient) ; 6 monthly participation in monitored online health questionnaires to reinforce diabetes self management and assist early detection of complications; participation in clinical video conferencing sessions as required with diabetes educator nurse and GP (on a case by case basis).</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive usual clinical diabetic care as determined by their own GP and participate in the clincial measurement of health assessment components of the evaluation. The trial does not seek to alter the care of this group in anyway, apart from the collection of data required for comparison with the intervention group. Guidelines encourage GPs and practices to adopt a systematic approach to diabetes care.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>With 210 completing participants (105 in each arm) we will be able to detect intervention effects over usual care effects of at least a 0.4% reduction in HbA1c.  This will be assessed by measuring HbA1c from patients' blood analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3months, 6months, 9months and 12months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved biomedical outcomes (Cholesterol) which will be assessed by blood analysis of patients' cholesterol levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12months after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved biomedical outcome (Renal function) which will be assessed by measuring serum creatine/eGFR via analysis of patients' blood</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved biomedical outcomes (blood pressure-systolic and diastolic) which will be assessed via patients' blood pressure meaurement using a blood pressure monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3months, 6months, 9months and 12months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved biomedical outcomes (Weight and waist circumference).  Patients' weight and waist circumference will be assesed via clinical assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and monthly until end of intervention at 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of diabetes related complications (derived from clinical record audit data)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life measures (quality of life questionnaire; Patient assessment of chronic illness care questionnaire; clinical depression and mental health questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved experience of care derived from questionnaires administered to both patients and care providers</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months and 12months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Utilisation of technology derived from questionnaires administerd to intervention patients and care givers</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months, 6 months and 12months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved service utilisation and efficiency of healthcare workforce assessed via data on health care utilisation by patients for primary care services and admissions to public hospitals.  The intervention arm will also incur the costs of intervention including set up (home monitors) and operating costs (diabetes educator nurse)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly until end of intervention at 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>For a patient to be included in the trial:
Have a regular GP providing primary care
The practice should have a diabetes register (using Canning data extractor tool or equivalent)
Patients should:
Be diagnosed with type 2 Diabetes (not type 1)
Live in a National Broadband Network (NBN) connected area in their home (not a residential aged care facility) &amp; be willing to connect to NBN at no cost
Be an adult, aged 18 years or over
Have recorded a HbA1c greater than or equal to 7.5 % at any time in the previous 12 months (or if no result available,  HbA1c greater than or equal to  7.5 % when tested)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients should be excluded if they have any of the following conditions or characteristics:
Pregnancy
Cancer (except non-melanotic skin cancer) diagnosed in the previous 12 months 
Palliative care
Intellectual and mental impairment  (that would preclude use of technology)
Dementia (that would preclude use of technology)
Primary language other than English
Chronic kidney disease  and on dialysis or likely to be on dialysis within the timeframe of the trial
Severe vision impairment (if deemed unable to use technology)
Severe unstable co-morbidities as assessed by GP as unlikely to survive for the 12 month period of the trial
Current enrolment in another health intervention trial</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>People will be recruited based on having type 2 diabetes and living in a geographically defined area with access to the National Broadband Network. They must be under the care of a GP in the same geographic area and provide written consent to participate. 
A letter will be sent by their GP advising that they are eligible for the trial. Information about the trial and phone contact details of the trial team,will be enclosed with the letter, as will a consent form. Information meetings for potential participants will also be arranged by the trial team and details included in the GP letter.
Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using procedures like coin tossing and dice rolling</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/01/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>210</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4814</postcode>
    <postcode>4812</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Townsville Mackay Medicare Local (TMML)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>UNIT 3/106 DALRYMPLE SERVICE ROAD CURRAJONG Q 4812</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Broadband, Communications and Digital Economy under the Digital Regions Initiatives National Partnership Agreement</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Broadband, Communications and the Digital Economy, 38 Sydney Avenue  Forrest ACT 2603 (postal address GPO Box 2154, Canberra ACT 2601, Australia)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Queensland Health Building, 147-163 Charlotte Street, Brisbane, Queensland 4000 (postal address GPO Box 48 Brisbane, Queensland 4001)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Paul Scuffham</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>L03 2.43 School of Medicine
Logan Campus
Griffith University
Meadowbrook QLD 4131
Griffith University</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This randomised controlled trial will explore whether remote access to clinical care, supported by telehealth technologies over high speed broadband, leads to improved diabetes control in a way that benefits patients, carers and clinicians, and improves the overall health system. People with poorly controlled type 2 diabetes mellitus who reside in the suburbs connected to the national broadband network will be recruited from general practices (GP). People in the intervention arm of the trial will receive additional diabetes care from a diabetes educator nurse via an in-home broadband communication device that can capture clinical measures, provide regular health assessments and videoconference with other health professionals when required. The GPs will continue to manage their patients care in partnership with the diabetes educator nurse (DEN). The intervention period is 12 months. Each care plan will include frequency for remote monitoring of clinical measures and patient health assessments, and protocols for managing changes in the clinical status of the patient. The DEN will be in close communication with the GPs throughout the trial. Patients in the control arm of the trial will receive usual care from their GP and participate in the clinical measurement and quality of life components of the evaluation. On completion of the trial, the control patients will be offered remote DEN care for a three month period. The trial evaluation will include biomedical, psychological, self management and quality of life measures. Data on utilisation rates and satisfaction with the technology will be collected, and cost -effectiveness analyses undertaken. The role of this technology on health care reform will be explored.
The trial aims to answer the following specific questions about remote telehealth monitoring:
Does it improve health outcomes?
Does it improve the experience of care for patients , their carers and clinicians?
Does it improve primary care capacity and integration of care?
Does it improve service utilisation and efficiency of the healthcare workforce?
How well does it utilize the high speed broadband network?</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>RACGP National Research and Evaluation Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>College House, 1 Palmerston Crescent, South Melbourne Vic 3205</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/10/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NREEC 11-006</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Robin Warren</name>
      <address>Unit 3/106 Dalrymple Service Road Currajong QLD 4812, PO Box 7780 Garbutt BC QLD 4814</address>
      <phone>+61  7 4725 8915</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 4725 8921</fax>
      <email>rwarren@tmml.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Robin Warren</name>
      <address>Unit 3/106 Dalrymple Service Road Currajong QLD 4812, PO Box 7780 Garbutt BC QLD 4814</address>
      <phone>+61  7 4725 8915</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 4725 8921</fax>
      <email>rwarren@tmml.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Karen Carlisle</name>
      <address>Unit 3/106 Dalrymple Service Road Currajong QLD 4812, PO Box 7780 Garbutt BC QLD 4814</address>
      <phone>+61  7 4725 8915</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 4725 8921</fax>
      <email>kcarlisle@tmml.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>