<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373771">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001428358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Diagnostic ability of the breakup time measurements in detecting dry eye disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Diagnostic ability of the breakup time measurements with and without sodium fluorescein instillation in detecting dry eye disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dry eye disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this investigator-masked randomised crossover study, the tear film breakup time of participants will be assessed in triplicate, with and without sodium fluorescein instillation, in a randomised order, by two independent observers. A 30-minute interval between measurements will ensure subsidence of reflex tearing.

In the intervention arm, sodium fluorescein was applied to the bulbar conjunctiva from a fluorescein impregnated strip (Haag-Streit) wetted with 1 drop (10-20µl) of saline and shaken to remove excess fluid. Following fluorescein instillation, participants were then instructed to blink naturally over a 1 minute period to facilitate even distribution over the ocular surface. Tear film breakup time was then assessed in triplicate under blue light with a Wratten yellow filter.
</interventions>
    <comparator>In the control arm, tear film breakup time was measured using non-invasive automated Keratograph 5M (Oculus, Wetzlar, Germany) without sodium fluroescein instillation.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fluorescein breakup time measured under blue light with a Wratten yellow filter. Non-invasive tear film breakup time measured using automated Keratograph 5M readings (Oculus, Wetzlar, Germany).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 minute following fluorescein instillation in the intervention arm.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Discriminative ability (area under receiver operator characteristic curve) and diagnostic accuracy (Youden optimal cut-off sensitivity and specificity) of fluorescein and non-invasive tear film breakup time in detecting dry eye disease (Ocular Surface Disease Index score greater than or equal to 13).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Ocular Surface Disease Index questionnaire administered during study enrolment, and completed within 2 hours prior to assessment of clinical tear film parameters.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be enrolled into two age and gender matched groups, with and without symptomatic dry eye (Ocular Surface.Disease Index score greater than or equal to 13).
Age of 18 years or older
No history of major systemic disease.
No history of ocular surgery.
No use of topical or systemic medications known to affect the eye. 
Able to provide written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Under 18 years of age.
History of major systemic or ocular disease.
History of ocular surgery.
Current use of topical or systemic medications known to affect the eye.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The order in which tear film breakup time measurements are conducted, with and without fluorescein instillation, will be randomised centrally by computer. The two types of tear film breakup time measurements will be conducted by two independent observers, and a third investigator will conduct study enrolment and administer the OSDI questionnaire to ensure investigator masking.</concealment>
    <sequence>The order in which first tear film breakup time measurements are conducted will be determined via random number generation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The distributions of tear film breakup time measurements will be assessed using the DAgostino-Pearson omnibus normality test, and then undergo logarithmic transformation before further parametric analysis if necessary. Intra-group and inter-group comparisons of medians will be conducted with paired and unpaired t-tests, respectively, and variances analysed by F-tests. Pearson's correlation anlaysis between breakup time measurements and Ocular Surface Disease Index will be peformed and Bland-Altman analysis will be conducted between breakup time measurements. A receiver operative characteristic curve will be constructed to assess the diagnostic ability of the breakup time measurements in detecting whether subjects has dry eye disease. The area under the curve (C-statistic) and diagnostic accuracy values at the Youdens optimal diagnostic cut-off were then calculated. All tests will be two-tailed and p &lt; 0.05 considered significant.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>26/05/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>3/10/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>62</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>74</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>3/10/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study compares two commonly used clinical methods of tear film breakup time measurement. Participants from two age and gender matched groups, with and without dry eye disease, will be enrolled into a prospective, randomised, investigator-masked, crossover study. Two independent observers measured tear film breakup time in triplicate, respectively, in a randomised order, following fluorescein instillation under blue light, and using non-invasive automated Keratograph 5M readings. A 30-minute interval between measurements ensured subsidence of reflex tearing. The median and distribution of breakup time measurements will be compared, and Bland-Altman and Pearson correlation analysis will be conducted. A receiver operative characteristic curve will then be constructed to assess the diagnostic ability of the breakup time measurements in detecting whether subjects has dry eye disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>UAHPEC 011368</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer P Craig</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+6499238173</phone>
      <fax>+6493677173</fax>
      <email>jp.craig@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer P Craig</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+6499238173</phone>
      <fax>+6493677173</fax>
      <email>jp.craig@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer P Craig</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+6499238173</phone>
      <fax>+6493677173</fax>
      <email>jp.craig@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer P Craig</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+6499238173</phone>
      <fax>+6493677173</fax>
      <email>jp.craig@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>