<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320848">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/11/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/11/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609001004257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised Controlled Trial of the Bioenterics Intragastric Balloon (BIB) Versus Lifestyle Intervention Alone on Weight Loss and Reversal of Weight Related Diseases in Obese Adolescents.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Obese adolescents in randomized control trial of the intragastric balloon and lifestyle intervention combination versus lifestyle intervention alone in reducing weight and associated health risks.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>BIB Study</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity in adolescents, and obesity-related comorbidities</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants randomised to the lifestyle intervention plus BIB will receive a Bioenterics Intragastric Balloon (BIB) for a duration of six months. The BIB is a smooth silicone, saline filled temporary device placed in the stomach. Participants will be admitted under the gastroenterology team at Princess Margaret Hospital (PMH) for 3 days duration for insertion. Both insertion and removal procedures involve a short general anaesthetic followed by inspection of the stomach and duodenum using an endoscope. The balloon device is inserted into the stomach; the balloon is inflated with saline and methylene blue and then disconnected. The insertion equipment is withdrawn. 
A detailed post operative dietary plan has been developed to slowly wean participants from liquid diet back to solids. A liquid vitamin and mineral supplement will be taken for the first week until the participant is back on a nutritionally balanced diet. Participants will have an individualized nutrition plan drawn up based on Australian dietary guidelines for children and adolescents.
Removal of the balloon will occur after 6 months duration.</interventions>
    <comparator>No balloon. 
All participants will be enrolled into the Changes in Lifestyle Are Successful in Partnership (CLASP) program. The program is part of standard clinical care for children with obesity or impaired glucose tolerance (IGT) and is run through the Department of Endocrinology and Diabetes at Princess Margaret Hospital. The program is run by a multidisciplinary team consisting of a dietician, psychologist, social worker, nurse, exercise physiologist, physiotherapist and physician. Achieving a healthy diet, learning how to self-monitor, behavioural changes and improving physical activities are taught in detail to both the participant and parent/guardian through a series of individual and group sessions. This program comprises of two and a half hour sessions held once a week for 10 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adiposity: Body mass index (BMI) raw score and Z score will be used as indicators of total adiposity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6 and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anthropometry: Height, weight, waist circumference, hip circumference and bi-acromial distance, percentage of body fat will be measured using standard measures.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6 and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemical tests: Changes in biochemical markers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6 and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical symptoms and signs of obesity complications, assessed through clinic visits and biochemical markers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6 and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fitness, physical activity and sedentary behaviour, using validated questionnaires. Fitness will be assessed by the 6-minute walk test, step test and balance test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6 and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary habits and intake changes, using a three-day food diary and an eating habits questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6 and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological scores on validated questionnaires</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6 and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerance and adverse events, including nausea, vomiting and abdominal pain. This will be measured by assessing the postoperative requirement for antiemetics and documentation of symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at 1 week, 2 weeks, 4 weeks, 10 weeks, 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure, measured using a handheld aneroid sphygmomanometer .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, 6 and 18 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must fulfil the following criteria:
1. Living in metropolitan Perth and willing to attend outpatient appointments.
2. No significant weight loss despite = 3 months attempted lifestyle improvements.

Participants must have a BMI Z-score &gt;+3 OR a BMI Z-score&gt;+2 AND 2 or more of the following co-morbidities.
1. Hyperlipidaemia
2. Impaired glucose tolerance/hyperinsulinaemia
3. Hepatitis steatosis
4. Hypertension,
5. Polycystic ovarian syndrome
6. Obstructive sleep apnoea
7. Benign intracranial hypertension
8. Degenerative joint disease.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>17</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Previous gastrointestinal resections
2. Structural abnormalities of the gastrointestinal tract.
3. Psychiatric/eating disorder
4. Rural dwelling,
5. Active oesophagitis (Grade1) / active gastric ulcer or its previous complications/hiatus hernia (&gt;5cm)
6. Pregnancy
7. Type 2 diabetes
8. Patient on anticoagulants or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs gastric irritants, unwilling to make lifestyles changes or attend regular clinic appointments.
9. Unwilling to accept the probability of nausea and vomiting in the postoperative period.
10. Physical inability to maintain regular follow-up
11. Obstructive sleep apnoea requiring a continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) machine</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All doctors seeing adolescents for their obesity and/or obesity related complications will follow a step-by-step guide on assessing patients for possible entry into the study. The subject’s doctor will refer any eligible and interested patients to Investigators, who will contact the family via telephone within 2 weeks of referral.  In the event of the treating Dr being the investigator a different member of the research team will discuss the study with the adolescent and their family.
Informed consent from the participant’s guardian will be obtained prior to the baseline assessment. Participants will be contacted by a member of the research team for consent as an adult when they reach 18 years of age.
A detailed assessment will be conducted to ensure that the participant meets the inclusion criteria/exclusion criteria and to collect data at baseline. Eligible consented participants will be randomised to the control group lifestyle/CLASP or the intervention (BIB) group plus lifestyle/ CLASP. Randomisation will occur in blocks of 6 in a one-to-one ratio and will be performed using a computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>The random allocation sequence was generated by a computer-based random number-producing algorithm in block lengths of six to ensure an equal chance of allocation to each group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>In the event of a significant difference between the groups being observed before completion of the study, the study will be ceased.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Elizabeth Davis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Department of Endocrinology and Diabetes
Roberts Road
Subiaco, WA 6008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council, GPO Box 1421, Canberra, ACT, 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Jacqueline Curran</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Department of Endocrinology and Diabetes
Roberts Road
Subiaco, WA 6008</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Colin Sherrington</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Department of Gastroenterology
Roberts Road
Subiaco, WA 6008</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Timothy Jones</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Department of Endocrinology and Diabetes
Roberts Road
Subiaco, WA 6008</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the study is to determine if an intra-gastric balloon in combination with a lifestyle program has a benefit for obese adolescents, compared to a lifestyle program alone.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Roberts Road
Subiaco, WA 6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/10/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1489EP</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jacqueline Curran</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Roberts Road, Subiaco
WA, 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 8090</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jacqueline.curran@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rachelle Kalic</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Roberts Road, Subiaco
WA, 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 7857</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rachelle.Kalic@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rachelle Kalic</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Roberts Road, Subiaco
WA, 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 7857</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rachelle.kalic@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>