<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369895">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001327471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of combined treatment on cervical spine and masticatory muscles on temporomandibular disorders. A pilot study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of combined treatment on cervical spine and masticatory muscles on temporomandibular disorders. A Randomized Controlled Trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym>.</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Temporomandibular disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this trial, patients with Temporomandibular Disorders are randomly assigned to one of four groups (three of them are treatment, and the other one is placebo). The first treatment group receives postero-anterior slow mobilizations in high cervical spine (C2) in four sets of 45 seconds each, with 15 seconds rest in between each set. The second one receives dry-needling in masseter muscle until the patient tolerates or during 60 seconds maximum. The third one receives both treatments. The treatments were administrated by two accredited physiotherapists with 2 and 5 years of experience.
The treatment is based in two sessions spaced two weeks apart. Prior to each treatment session, pain intensity (Visual Analog Scale), pressure sensitivity (with Algometer) and maximum mouth opening (mm interincisor distance) are measured. Furthermore, there is a follow-up assessment, four weeks after last treatment session, with the same variable measurement. To monitor the adherence to the intervention, it is checked at each session that all the patients have attended.

</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator group has the same number of patients and receives the same number of treatment sessions and follow-up assessments. The placebo administrated in this comparator group is fake dry-needling in the masseter muscle during 60 seconds maximum. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is pain assessed by visual analogue scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately prior to first session, at second session (2 weeks after first session), and at third session (one month after second session).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome is mouth opening, measured using measuring tape by treating physiotherapist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately prior to first session, at second session (2 weeks after first session), and at third session (one month after second session).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pressure sensibility, assessed using mechanical algometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately prior to first session, at second session (2 weeks after first session), and at third session (one month after second session).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients diagnosed with temporomandibular disorder.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with presence of other pathologies than musculoskeletal, either genetic (Down syndrome, etc.) or neurological (ICTUS, etc.). Patients that have not been treated by dry needling any time before.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using table created by a computer software (Epidat).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>6/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/07/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>17</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>9/09/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidad Alcala de Henares</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Plaza de San Diego, s/n,28801 Alcala de Henares,Madrid</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidad Alcala de Henares</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Plaza de San Diego, s/n,28801 Alcala de Henares,Madrid</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Spain</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to prove that a combined treatment with postero-anterior mobilisations in the high cervical spine and dry needling in masseter muscles is better than this two therapies on their own in patients with temporomandibular disorders diagnosed. The secondary aims are to improve the pain, the mouth opening and the pressure sensibility.

It is a Randomized Controlled Trial with blinded evaluator in which the study population are adults between 20 and 50 years old. Patients will be divided in four groups, one control and three experimental groups. In the control group fake dry needling will be apply in masseter muscle. In the experimental group 1, the treatment will be postero-anterior mobilisations in high cervical spine. The experimental group 2, will receive dry needling in masseter muscle. And the experimental group 3, will receive both, mobilisations and dry needling, treatments.

The work plan will be distributed in the next way:
First evaluation before the first treatment session.
Second evaluation and second session two weeks later from the first one.
Third and last evaluation. This is a control evaluation one month later than the last treatment session.
In all the evaluation the patients will be identified as a number, so the evaluator will not know which patient belongs to one experimental group and which one to the control group.

After the data collection, these will be analysed by the SPSS 17.0 program.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite de Etica de la Investigacion y de Experimentacion animal de la Universidad Alcala de Henares</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Plaza de San Diego, s/n, 28801 Alcala de Henares, Madrid</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Pilar Moreu Peso</name>
      <address>Plaza de San Diego, s/n,28801 Alcala de Henares,Madrid, University of Alcala de Henares.</address>
      <phone>+34 600 63 23 91</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pilar.moreupeso@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sandra García Valero</name>
      <address>Plaza de San Diego, s/n,28801 Alcala de Henares, University of Alcala de Henares</address>
      <phone>+34 687 72 20 01</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ssandraa_1_@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Guillermo Gil Palop</name>
      <address>Plaza de San Diego, s/n,28801 Alcala de Henares,Madrid, University of Alcala de Henares.</address>
      <phone>+34 651 40 63 99</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>guillegp18@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>