<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370241">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000294459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Safety and efficacy of AKP-11 for atopic dermatitis.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, safety, tolerability and efficacy study of topical AKP-11 administration to participants with atopic dermatitis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1180-2112</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atopic Dermatitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study involves the twice daily topical application of 1 g ointment containing 30 mg of active AKP-11 or matching placebo to  participants with atopic dermatitis for 4 weeks or one week post complete clearance, confirmed by the physician, whichever comes first when the AKP-11 or placebo ointment will be applied twice daily.  The target area of  up to   300 cm2 (~1.5 % of BSA). will be selected by investigator. At every visit, the participant will have to to return used and unused sachets to the study personal for accountability purposes. Participants will be randomized as groups of 2 (AKP-11) and 1 (Placebo). </interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo ointment without active AKP-11.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of 3% AKP-11 ointment. This is assessed by drug related adverse events, physical examination, vital signs, ECG, laboratory assessment (haematology, plasma biochemistry, and urinalysis) and skin irritation assessment, as reported by investigator and by participant in study diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, 8, 15, 22, 28 and End of Study (EOS) visit (Day 7 post last treatment day) </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Local-Investigator Global assessment (L-IGA) from baseline using 6-point scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, 8, 15, 22, 28 and EOS</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Local Eczema Area and Severity Index (L-EASI) score from the baseline, using a 4-point severity scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, 8, 15, 22, 28 and EOS</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Eczema Area and Severity Index (EASI) score from baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 and 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in severity of atopic dermatitis, as assessed by SCORAD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, 8, 15, 22, 28 and EOS</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in pruritus score. The participant diaries will be provided to the participants that include the details how to score pruritus. Participant need to mark a line on a horizontal 10 cm long VAS scale. The study personnel will advise the participants how to mark the VAS scale during the Day 1 visit and ensure the participants are correctly marking VAS scale at every site visit. The participants will refer the table and imagine the intensity of pruritus they experience. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, 8, 22, 28 and EOS</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Males or females aged 18-65 years (inclusive) at the time of screening.
*Individuals diagnosed with atopic dermatitis according to the criteria of Hanifin and Rajka.
*Individuals with mild to moderate disease and equal to 10 % of BSA with atopic dermatitis.
*Participants with L-EASI score of equal to 1 for each of the signs at an appropriate target site.
*Able to provide written informed consent proper to the performance of any study specific procedures.
*Participants with a BMI between 18.0 and 40.0 kg/m2, inclusive.
*Female participants of child-bearing potential with negative pregnancy test at screening and negative urine pregnancy test at check-in (Day 1), AND;
*Agrees to abstinence for the duration of the study and until 4 weeks after dosing with study drug, if this is in line with the usual and preferred lifestyle;
*OR agrees to use condoms plus one other acceptable form of contraception; i.e. intra-uterine device, hormonal contraception (oral, injected or implanted) or a female diaphragm, from screening until 4 weeks after dosing with study drug;
*OR has only same-sex partners, when this is her preferred and usual lifestyle;
*OR has a vasectomized partner, which should be the sole partner for that participant.
*Male participants with female partners of child-bearing potential must agree abstinence or to use condoms plus partner use of an acceptable contraceptive (intrauterine device, hormonal contraception such as oral, injected or implanted; or male condom plus female diaphragm or cervical cap) for the duration of the study and until 4 weeks after dosing with study drug.
* Negative test results for Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV), Hepatitis B and Hepatitis C at the time of screening.
*Negative drug screening test (drugs of abuse; Creatinine control, testing for amphetamines, barbiturates, cocaine, opiates, cannabinoids and benzodiazepines) result (urine test) at the time of screening.
*Participants who are willing and able to comply with all study assessments and adhere to the protocol schedule.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Participants with any skin condition other than atopic dermatitis in particular cutaneous infections, significant sun damage or an inherited skin disorder that in the opinion of the Investigator could interfere with the evaluation of the trial medication.
*History of allergy and/ or hypersensitivity to any of the stated ingredients of the formulations.
*Participants who have smoked more than 10 cigarettes a day in the last 12 months.
*Treatment with any of the following within 4 weeks prior to the commencement of study treatment and for the duration of the study: systemic retinoids; immunosuppressant agents (e.g. methotrexate, cyclosporine, azathioprine, thioguanine prednisone, prednisolone, hydroxyurea or mycophenolate mofetil); phototherapy or photochemotherapy; high potency topical corticosteroids; alternative medicine treatments; or sun exposure or tanning bed use, or any other therapy that in the opinion of the investigator could modify disease activity.
*Topical treatment within 2 weeks prior to commencement of study treatment and for the duration of the study, including: moderate potency topical corticosteroids; topical retinoids; or keratolytics, coal tar and dithranol or any other topical that in the opinion of the investigator could modify disease activity.
*Have received any investigational research agent or therapeutic biologic within 30 days or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to the first dose of Investigational Product.
*Have received an investigational vaccine within 6 months, a live attenuated vaccine within 60 days or a registered vaccine within 30 days prior to the first dose of the Investigational Product.
*Have evidence of drug or alcohol abuse within 6 months prior to screening visit (i.e., more than fourteen units of alcohol per week [1 Unit = 150 ml of wine 360 ml of beer, or 45 ml of 40% alcohol]).
*Have clinical signs of active infection and/or a temperature of above 38.0 degrees of C at the time of screening. Study entry may be deferred at the discretion of the Principal Investigator.
*Anticipate surgery within the trial period or history of major surgery within 3 months of screening.
*A depot injection or an implant of any drug within 3 months prior to administration of study treatment, with the exception of a contraceptive implant.
*Participants who are unable to sign consent or unable to return for all scheduled study visits.
*Evidence of current or previous clinically significant neurological, endocrinal, cardiovascular, pulmonary, haematological, malignant, immunologic, psychiatric metabolic or other uncontrolled systemic disease, or finding of the medical examination (including vital signs and ECG), including any other condition that in the opinion of the investigator, would compromise the safety of the participant or interfere with assessment of endpoints or unsuitable for enrollment or impact on the quality of the data.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>21</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>8</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>15/01/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Skin and Cancer Foundation (Westmead) Day Procedure Centre - Westmead</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Akaal Pharma PTY LTD</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Room 301 E&amp;F
Thomas Cherry Building
Chemistry Department
La Trobe University,
Bundoora, VIC 3086</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Akaal Pharma PTY LTD</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Room 301 E&amp;F
Thomas Cherry Building
Chemistry Department
La Trobe University,
Bundoora, VIC 3086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a Phase I study to determine the safety, tolerability and efficacy of topical doses of AKP-11 when administered to participants with atopic dermatitis. AKP-11 is a Sphingosine-1-phosphate receptor 1 (S1P1) agonist, developed by Akaal Pharma PTY LTD.  AKP-11 targets the immune activity, inhibits the over-expression of pro-inflammatory cytokines and factors including the inflammation. AKP-11 has been tested in several immune/ inflammatory diseases including psoriasis patients in order to establish its efficacy. The twice daily topical application of 1 g ointment containing 30 mg AKP-11 or matching placebo in up to 21 participants. Participants will be randomized as groups of 2 (AKP-11) and 1 (Placebo). The dosing is proposed for up to 28 days or one week post complete clearance, confirmed by the physician, whichever comes first. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Rd
Eastwood SA 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015-10-711</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Foley</name>
      <address>Skin &amp; Cancer Foundation
Level 1, 80 Drummond Street
Carlton VIC 3053</address>
      <phone>+61396239400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pfoley@skincancer.asn.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Foley</name>
      <address>Skin &amp; Cancer Foundation
Level 1, 80 Drummond Street
Carlton VIC 3053
</address>
      <phone>+61396239400</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pfoley@skincancer.asn.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gurmit Gill</name>
      <address>Akaal Pharma PTY LTD
Room 301 E&amp;F
Thomas Cherry Building
Chemistry Department
La Trobe University,
Bundoora, VIC 3086</address>
      <phone>+61394792584</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gurmit.gill@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gurmit Gill</name>
      <address>Akaal Pharma PTY LTD
Room 301 E&amp;F
Thomas Cherry Building
Chemistry Department
La Trobe University,
Bundoora, VIC 3086</address>
      <phone>+61394792584</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gurmit.gill@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>