<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366282">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000519651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of different types of food consumption on the incidence of type 2 diabetes in both normal weight and overweight/obese participants with no diabetes.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of a healthy diet and an unhealthy diet on insulin sensitivity in both normal weight and overweight/obese participants with no diabetes: a randomised crossover study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nill</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Normal glucose levels and prediabetes such as IGT and IFG</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>insulin resistance</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight /obesity </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is a randomized cross-over trial with two different diets: one is a dietary pattern with high red meat and processed meat and refined grains and the other with legumes, nuts, whole grains and dairy products. This study will run for at least 10 weeks and 2 days with 8 visits. The intervention will consist of two 4 week weight stable diet periods with a minimum of 2-week washout period on a usual diet in between.
Participants will be asked to fill out a 3-day weighed food record every 2 weeks and daily checklists with food consumed. Participants will be asked to follow specific instructions on diet. 
The two diets will be designed for individuals depending on their weight and activity levels. The dietary design of this project has been virtually run by foodworks 7 based on Australian dietary habits. 
The dietary cluster with red and processed meat and refined grains includes 200-300g red meat, more than 50g processed meat (ham, bacon and sausage) and 4-6 serves refined grains (bread, rice, noodle and pasta) based on volunteers weights. One to two serves vegetables/day, 1-2 serves fruits/day and a minimal amount of dairy products (e.g. 1-2 teaspoons of milk). Two hundred to three hundred gram of potatoes, 1 serve of jam or marmalade, 3-9 serves of oil or spread, and 3-4 serves of indulgence food (in place of refined grains or potato) were recommended for additional energy intake in accordance with volunteers weights.
In the dietary cluster high in nuts, legumes, whole grains and dairy products, participants will consume 4 serves of dairy products/day, 60-90 g unsalted nuts/day, 3-4 serves whole grains/day in the forms of breads, rice and pasta, 1-2serves fruits and 1-2 serves vegetables/day. 70-150 g chicken or fish (or other seafood) or 150-225 g cooked legumes based on the volunteers weight will be eaten alternatively each day. Two to seven serves of oil or spread and 1 serve of jam or marmalade were advised for additional energy intake in accordance with volunteers weights. 
Participants will be provided with kitchen scales. Participants will be asked to submit a 3-day weighed food record and daily checklists at visit 2, 3, 6 and 7. Participants will be required to have a 12 hour fast before each visit. Weight measurement and blood sampling will be performed during the course of this study.
Blood samplings by MTT (meal tolerance test) and LDIGIT (low dose insulin and glucose infusion test) will be performed at the end of each diet. 
In terms of MTT, participants will be asked to consume a sandwich within 10 min. Blood samples will be taken at -5, 0, 10, 20, 30, 40, 50, 60, 75, 90, 120, 150, and 180 min.
On the other day, LDIGIT will be administered over 150 min after a 12h overnight fast. 19 blood samples will be collected over 150 min. Blood samples will be retained for measurements of insulin, C-peptide and glucose.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Diet high in red meat, processed meat and refined grains is comparator.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>insulin sensitivity using LDIGIT (low dose insulin and glucose infusion test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 1: after first 4- week dietary intervention; Timepoint 2: after second 4- week dietary intervention
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lipid profiles will be measured by Konelab.


</outcome>
      <timepoint>It is a single timepoint at 10 weeks and 2days. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We will measure CRP by Konelab</outcome>
      <timepoint>It is a single timepoint at 10 weeks and 2 days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. People in BMI ranges of 18.50 to 45 
2. Aged over 18 years
3. Normal glucose tolerance or impaired glucose tolerance
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Diagnosed diabetes
2.Drugs that influence glucose metabolism (e.g. Metformin)
3.Pregnant or breastfeeding
4.History of metabolic illness such as kidney or liver diseases
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Flyers will be posted around the Universtiy and on the public boards.Contact information will be provided on the flyers, so participants will call or email the researchers if they are interested in learning more. Anyone that contacts the researchers about the study will be given an information sheet outlining the project and if they are interested in participating, they will be screened to see if they meet the inclusion or exclusion criteria. 
Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation was performed via an online random number generator (www.randomization.com) by a researcher who was not involved in this study.  </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>25 participants in each group would give 80% power (P&lt;0.05) to assess insulin sensitivity for overweight participants with either NGT or IGT using LDIGIT (Mean= 11.8 and 8.9; SD=5.19). 30 participants in each group will be recruited considering a 20% dropout rate.

reference 
Piatti, P., et al., The continuous low dose insulin and glucose infusion test: a simplified and accurate method for the evaluation of insulin sensitivity and insulin secretion in population studies. The Journal of clinical endocrinology and metabolism, 1995. 80(1): p. 34-40.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>23/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>51</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>14/08/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of south Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of South Australia 
City East Campus 
GPO Box 2471 
Adelaide SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of South Austraila </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of South Australia 
City East Campus  
GPO Box 2471 
Adelaide SA 5001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>1. Hypothesis 
We hypothesise that red and processed meat and refined grains negatively affect insulin sensitivity or insulin secretion, compared with dairy products, legumes, nuts and whole grains.
2.Aims
If a dietary pattern rich in nuts, legumes, whole grains and dairy products improves insulin sensitivity, this study will strongly support the recommendation of this diet for people with no diabetes. 
If a dietary pattern high in red, processed meat and refined grains affects negatively insulin sensitivity, this outcome will provide a convincing rationale in reducing the amount of intake of red, processed meat and refined grains for those with insulin resistance. 
This study will provide clarification on dietary influences on insulin sensitivity and contribute to lowering risks of developing type 2 diabetes by changing the dietary patterns.
3. Primary and secondary endpoints
The primary endpoint of this study is to assess insulin sensitivity and the secondary endpoint is to analyse the biomarkers of insulin resistance.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Uni SA HREC (Human Research Ethics Committee)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Innovation Services 
University of South Australia
General Purpose Building
Mawson Lakes Campus
Mawson Lakes Boulevard
Mawson Lakes, SA, 5095 
Australia

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0000032778</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366282-Human Ethics Application.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Yoona Kim</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy and Medical Sciences                     
Division of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
City East Campus, North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000 
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1025</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kimyy031@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Yoona Kim</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy and Medical Sciences                     
Division of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
City East Campus, North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000 
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1025</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kimyy031@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter clifton </name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy and Medical Sciences                     
Division of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
City East Campus, North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000 
</address>
      <phone> +61 8 8302 1357</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Peter.Clifton@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Yoona Kim </name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy and Medical Sciences                     
Division of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
City East Campus, North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000 
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1025</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kimyy031@mymail.unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>