<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83495">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/01/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/01/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000069257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Optimising cefepime dosing in intensive care:  the pharmacokinetics of extended (prolonged) infusions.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In intensive care patients with sepsis, are extended (prolonged) infusions of cefepime, compared to conventional intermittent dosing, more effective in achieving and maintaining plasma concentrations above pharmacodynamic breakpoints?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>intensive care sepsis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>extended (prolonged) intravenous infusion of cefepime 1g over 6 hours every 12 hours for first 3 days of therapy</interventions>
    <comparator>2 comparator arms.
1. cefepime at 1g infused intravenously over 5 minutes every 12 hours for first 3 days of therapy
2. 2g infused intravenously over 5 minutes every 12 hours for first 3 days of therapy</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>percentage of dosing interval above pharmacodynamic breakpoint during the first 12 hours of treatment determined via limited sampling of cefepime concentrations to facilitate pharmacokinetic modelling</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12 hours from start of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>percentage of dosing interval above pharmacodynamic breakpoint from 48 to 60 hours of treatment determined via limited sampling of cefepime concentrations to facilitate pharmacokinetic modelling</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 72 hours from the start of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>limited sampling of cefepime concentrations along with pharmacokinetic modelling will be used to determine the full pharmacokinetic profile for cefepime in intensive care patients with sepsis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Limited sampling will occur on days 1 and 3 at time = 0, 5 minutes, 30 minutes, 3 hours, 6 hours, 8 hours 10 hours and 12 hours after the start of the cefepime infusion.  Pharmacokinetic modelling will be completed at the end of the first 3 days of treatment (ie 72 hours after the first dose of cefepime).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of administration of extended (prolonged) infusions of cefepime in the medical / surgical intensive care setting by the monitoring by health care professionals of the success in administering the infusions and survey by the researchers of the intravenous lines and other infusions administered during the study period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily during the 3 day study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>daily monitoring during the study period by health care professionsals of significant clinical outcomes (duration of mechnical ventilation, length of intensive care unit and hospital stay) , and any possible relation to the use of extended (prolonged) infusions of cefepime which may be used to inform the design of future studies of extended infusions</outcome>
      <timepoint>hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>An adult intensive care patient who: Has been prescribed cefepime according to The Alfred Intensive Care Unit (ICU) Antibiotic Guidelines (ie. after 7 days of hospital admission and requiring empiric or directed anti-microbial treatment); Is likely to remain in ICU for at least three days from enrolment; Has an arterial line already in situ for blood sampling.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Any documented allergy or adverse reaction to cefepime or other cephalosporin antibiotic or significant / serious adverse reaction to other beta-lactam or monobactam antibiotics which would normally preclude the prescribing of cefepime according to the Alfred ICU Antibiotic Guidelines.
2. Moderate to severe renal impairment (calculated estimated glomular filtration ratre (eGRF) &lt;30mL/min at enrolment) or need for continous renal replacement therapy or intermittent heamodialysis.
3. Patients with significant burns (ie. greater than 15% body surface area)
4. Patients with extracorporeal circuits (eg. extracorporeal membranous oxygenation, ventricular assist devices)
5. All transplant patients including solid organ and bone marrow transplants
6. Pregnancy
7. Inclusion in other study protocols which preclude enrolment in this study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sequentially numbered sealed envelopes will be prepared and used to randomise patients at enrolment.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated randomisation table prepared by a statistician will be used.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics / pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/02/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Alfred</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Commercial Rd
Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Alfred Research Trusts</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Alfred and Baker IDI (International Diabetes Institute) Heart and Diabetes Institute Research Office
The Alfred
Commercial Rd 
Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Pharmacy Department</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Alfred
Commercial Rd
Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Monash University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>381 Royal Pde
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cefepime is a broad spectrum antibiotic used as part of the Alfred Intensive Care Unit (ICU) antibiotic guidelines at a dose of 1g every 12 hours in combination with other agents, higher doses are used (eg 2g every 12 hours) in many international centres. Conventional administration is via short infusion over a few minutes. However the antibacterial effect is dependent on adequate drug concentrations being maintained over most of the period between doses.  Extended infusions have been shown in computer modelling to achieve this for cefepime. Clinically, extended infusions have been shown in intensive care patients to be more effective for other antibiotics of similar class to cefepime.
This study will be a randomised controlled trial in intensive care patients which aims to compare the pharmacokinetic profile (blood concentrations of the drug over time) of conventional administration of cefepime over a few minutes at the dose of 1g every 12 hours (the dose routinely used in The Alfred ICU) and the higher dose of 2g every 12 hours against an extended infusion of 1g given over 6 hours every 12 hours.
Cefepime blood concentration will be obtained from analysis of blood samples taken at predetermined time points over two 12 hour periods on Day 1 and Day 3 (steady state) of therapy.  This will allow determination of the pharmacokinetic profile of cefepime in intensive care patients for each of the three dosing regimens. Comparison of these profiles will provide evidence of any advantage of extended infusions in intensive care patients leading to larger scale clinical investigations of this administration method.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred
Commercial Rd
Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/12/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>328/08</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Bianca Levkovich</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Department
The Alfred
Commercial Rd
Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2061</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.levkovich@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Bianca Levkovich</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Department
The Alfred
Commercial Rd
Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2061</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.levkovich@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Bianca Levkovich</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Department
The Alfred
Commercial Rd
Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2061</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.levkovich@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>