<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308026">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000466246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomized controlled trial comparing controlled oxygen therapy versus high flow oxygen therapy for acute myocardial infarctions in the pre-hospital setting</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized controlled trial assessing resolution of chest pain in patients with acute myocardial infarction who are treated with controlled oxygen therapy versus high flow oxygen therapy in the pre-hospital setting</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Myocardial Infarction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: controlled oxygen therapy to maintain oxygen saturations between 92-96%
Control: 8-15 L/min oxygen via non-rebreather mask 

Time frame: for the duration of the ambulance transport to hospital</interventions>
    <comparator>High Flow oxygen therapy- provide high concentration of oxygen 8-15 L/min by Non re-breather mask for the duration of the transport by ambulance.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality, death in hospital post treatment by ambulance offerers for acute exacerbation of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (AECOPD), or death during the care of ambulance officers</outcome>
      <timepoint>Death during treatment of patient by paramedics or during hospital stay after transport by ambulance and treated for an acute myocardial infarction (AMI), during this episode only</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to resolution of chest pain this will be assessed during the transport and treatement of the patient. The paramedics will assess by asking the patient to rate their pain on a scale of 0-10 and it will be recorded in the electronic reporting system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time to resolution of chest pain after intitation of treatment and transport by ambulance for an acute myocardial infarction (AMI), during this episode only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of Hospital Stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>after treatment for AMI by ambulance officers the length of hospital stay during this admission measured in days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>"vital signs" Blood pressure, respiratory rate, heart rate, oxygen saturation. The values will be taken by paramedics and recorded into the electronic reporting system</outcome>
      <timepoint>after treatment for AMI during transport to hospital monitoring vital signs every 10-15 minutes and measured for the duration of care by ambulance officers. Monitoring will stop once the patient has been handed over to the Emergency Department staff.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The study population will be patients attended by the Tasmanian Ambulance Service in the Launceston region with a complaint of non-traumatic chest pain and clinical features and history consistent with acute coronary syndrome and coronary heart disease (CHD). Cases will be considered for inclusion if they meet the following criteria:

1.	Age over 18 years; and
2.	Complaint of chest pain, pressure or tightness; and/or 
3.	Risk factor of acute coronary syndrome and CHD (include: hypertension, diabetes, dyslipodemia, age, sex, family history, smoking history and history of CHD); and/or
4.	Ischaemic changes on electrocardiogram (ECG); and
5.	Transported to the Launceston General Hospital by Tasmanian Ambulance Service.

Eligible cases will be further defined by diagnosis of AMI, made by independent cardiologists, based on patient records (ECG and history), lab results (troponin, creatinine kinase (CK)) and/or evidence from coronary angiography.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Cases will be excluded if no recordings of oxygen saturations are available.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Random concealed evelopes containing cards with treatement allocation which will be drawn after assessment of patient and decided they meet the inclusion criteria</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Menizes Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Menzies Research Institute Private Bag 23, Hobart, TAS
7001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Clifford Craig Medical Research Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Clifford Craig Medical Research Trust
5th Floor, Launceston General Hospital, Charles Street
Launceston  Tasmania  7250</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will advance our understanding of the appropriate management of patients suffering AMI by quantifying the ability of controlled oxygen therapy to reduce adverse outcomes. Our findings will inform the development of guidelines for the local and international use of oxygen therapy in the treatment of AMI, with the potential to modify current practice. The findings of this study with directly benefit the Tasmanian community by improving health outcomes for AMI patients and reducing the overall burden of coronary heart disease in Tasmania.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>National Ethics Application Form (NEAF)- Tasmania Health and Medical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee Administration University of Tasmania Office of Research Services Private Bag 01 Hobart Tasmania 7001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/06/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>H0010676</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/06/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Michael Austin</name>
      <address>Menzies Research Institute 
Private Bag 23
Hobart TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>+61 404667762</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maaustin@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Michael Austin</name>
      <address>Menzies Research Institute 
Private Bag 23
Hobart TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>61 3 6226 7757</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maaustin@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Michael Austin</name>
      <address>Menzies Research Institute 
Private Bag 23
Hobart TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>+61 404667762</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>maaustin@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>