<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347584">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/10/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/10/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001070921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Optimising the residential and community aged care workforce: The evidence-based development of clinical leadership in middle managers in aged care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of the Clinical Leadership in Aged Care (CLiAC) program for residential and community aged care middle managers on the care work environment, care quality, staff turnover, stress/burnout, job satisfaction, and cost benefit, compared with a no program control group (NP)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1123-2305</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Clinical leadership in aged care</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>CLiAC has been developed based on the aged care-specific clinical leadership qualities framework (ACLQF) and informed by key principles of the content and evaluation of the Clinical Excellence Commission Clinical Leadership (CEC-CL) program. CLiAC aims to achieve safe, high-quality person-centred and evidence-based care by assisting care managers to develop effective team relationships and consumer/client-centred leadership strategies that enable them to deal with the day-to-day realities of care service. 
CLiAC will be a structured program and delivered to middle managers from 6 residential aged care facilities and 6 community aged care services (intervention group) over 12 months by a program facilitator who will be mentored by an expert facilitator. 
The core topics will be covered in 4 modules via 10 full day workshops, combined with action learning, case scenarios, one-on-one interactions with a program facilitator, and individual practice improvement projects and process evaluation including 360-degree review.</interventions>
    <comparator>A no program control (NP) group will receive no special intervention or education. The NP group will continue usual care and practice for the duration of the study.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Work environment for aged care staff as assessed using a Work Environment Scale-R subscales and Multi-factor Leadership Questionnaire (MLQ)-S (for staff)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 1.5 years after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Care quality and safety for aged care recipients as assessed using clinical indicators (unplanned hospital admission, fall with injury, unintentional weight loss &gt;2kgs, new pressure areas, new urinary tract infection) and a Person-centred Care Assessment Tool (P-CAT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, and at 9 months and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Staff turnover rates</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, and at 9 months and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost benefits in terms of cost of retaining and recruiting aged care staff, as well as cost of care to aged care service providers</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, and at 9 months and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>aged care managers' knowledge and skills in leadership and management as assessed using a modified NHS Leadership Centre Evaluation Questionnaire,  Multi-factor Leadership Questionnaire (MLQ)-M (for managers) and Approaches to Dementia Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 9 months and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>aged care staff intention to stay and intention to leave as assessed using Workforce Dynamics Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, and at 9 months and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>stress levels in aged care staff as assessed using Workforce Dynamics Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, and at 9 months and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>job satisfaction for aged care staff as assessed using Workforce Dynamics Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, and at 9 months and 18 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Site Inclusion Criteria:
Receive principal support for the study from the Executive Care Manager (ECM) or Community Care Manager (CCM).
ECMs or CCMs agreement that middle manager from their facility will not receive the intervention (CLiAC) during the study if they are randomly allocated to the non-intervention group. 
Middle Manager/Care Staff Inclusion Criteria: 
Currently work in a middle management or in a direct care role for the participating aged care organisation.
Have been employed by the participating organisation for a minimum of six months.
For community aged care services staff be involved in the delivery of extended aged care at home (EACH), EACH-D (dementia), and community aged care packages (CACP).
Consent to participate in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Sites which are currently (or in the near future) undergoing major management/structural changes.
Middle Manager/Care Staff Exclusion Criteria: 
Staff involved in non direct care roles (e.g. administration, maintenance)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involved contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who was at central administration site. 

The lead CI (JEON) was invited to explain the study and its processes to senior managers of residential and community aged care services at one of the participating aged care organisation quarterly meetings. The senior managers had the opportunity to ask questions and clarify any issues at the meetings, and then pass this information to their staff and middle managers. 

Initial site selection (site as unit of randomisation): according to the site eligibility criteria described earlier, the research team was advised of all potential eligible sites for the study by the participating aged care organisation central executive management. 

Recruitment of managers to participate in the Clinical Leadership in Aged Care (CLiAC) program: 1) An invitation letter was sent to all senior and middle managers of eligible sites. All potential participants agreed to inclusion on the basis that they may not receive the intervention during the study, but if they were randomly allocated to the non-intervention group, they would have the option of being offered the intervention once the project is completed.  2) All sites that met the eligibility criteria were approached and invited to participate in random order until 12 Residential Aged Care Facilities and 12 Community Aged Care Services had agreed to participate. For this, sites were stratified by type (RACF or CACS) and randomly permuted within each stratum using software available at www.randomization.com.  3) Once the researchers had established the research sites (where middle managers had agreed to participate in the clinical leadership program), restricted randomisation was used to balance the groups. The intervention is being conducted as part of the participating organisation’s leadership development initiative, but the CIs and senior executives of the participating organisation have agreed that there will be no coercion imposed on the managers and the managers will need to volunteer to participate in the intervention and subsequent data collections. 

Recruitment of Managers in the Survey:  All managers from both intervention and non-intervention sites will be invited to participate in the survey.  Return of their questionnaire will be considered as consent (implied consent).
Recruitment of care staff in the Survey: An invitation letter and a set of questionnaires will be sent to all eligible staff of the participating sites from the research team. Return of their questionnaire will be considered as consent (implied consent).  The participants will be asked to return their completed questionnaire in the stamped return addressed envelope provided with the documentation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Sites were stratified by type of aged care (residential vs. community aged care). Within each stratum, restricted randomisation was used to balance the groups by: size of the service (number of clients), span of control (staff and management ratio) and geographical location (rural vs. urban). This was done using a program in Gauss supplied by Professor Larry Moulton of Johns Hopkins University, co-author of the textbook ‘Cluster Randomised Trials’.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Cluster randomised trial, randomised by site.

Apart from the managers receiving the clinical leadership program intervention (CLiAC), participating staff from all residential and community care sites will be blind to intervention allocation, however, due to the nature of the intervention maintaining blindness may not be feasible. To maximise blindness participating managers will be asked not to discuss their training with their work teams.
Research team members assessing the outcomes (assessor) and analysing the results/data (data analyst) will be blind to allocation of the intervention.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/08/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Yun-Hee Jeon</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney Nursing School, Rm A5.13, Lv 5 M02, 88 Mallett Street, Camperdown, NSW, 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 11 Lancaster Place Majura Park, ACT, 2609</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Baptist Community Services NSW &amp; ACT</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>28A Cambridge St, Epping, NSW, 2121</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Baptist Community Services NSW &amp; ACT</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 655, Epping, NSW, 2121</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Hal Kendig</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Sydney, CERA Building 18 Concord Hospital, Concord, NSW 2139.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Judy Simpson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Sydney, A27 Edward Ford Building, NSW, 2006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Lynn Chenoweth</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Technology Sydney, Faculty of Nursing, Midwifery and Health, PO Box 123, Broadway, NSW, 2007</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Strong, effective clinical leadership is critical in improving healthcare workforce retention and care quality, and reducing associated costs. Yet little evidence exists about the best ways to enable middle managers of aged care to develop clinical leadership skills, critical to the effective delivery of quality care. The trial is part of a larger study which has two aims: 1) to develop and promote evidence-based tools for improving leadership in the sector including a clinical leadership qualities framework (ACLQF) and a clinical and managerial leadership program in aged care (CLiAC); 2) and using a cluster randomised controlled design, to determine the feasibility and the effectiveness of CLiAC in improving workforce recruitment and retention and care safety and quality, which have not been previously researched in the aged care sector. Hypotheses include: the intervention group will have the following significant benefits over the non-intervention group.
HP1  enhanced work environment for aged care staff 
HP2  improved care quality and safety for aged care recipients
HP3  reduced aged care staff turnover rates
HP4  reduced aged care staff absenteeism 
HP5  improved aged care staff intention to stay and decreased intention to leave
HP6  reduced stress levels in aged care staff
HP7  increased job satisfaction for aged care staff
HP8  reduced cost of retaining and recruiting aged care staff, as well as cost of care
HP9  improved aged care managers knowledge and skills in leadership and management</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, Jane Foss Russell Building G02, University of Sydney NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/01/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Database No. 13405</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Baptist Community Services (BCS) Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 655, Epping, NSW, 2121</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/01/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00432</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Yun-Hee Jeon</name>
      <address>Sydney Nursing School, Rm A5.13, Lv 5 M02, 88 Mallett Street, Camperdown, NSW, Australia  2050</address>
      <phone>61, 2, 9351 0674</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Yun-hee.jeon@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Yun-Hee Jeon</name>
      <address>Sydney Nursing School, Rm A5.13, Lv 5 M02, 88 Mallett Street, Camperdown, NSW, Australia  2050</address>
      <phone>61, 2, 9351 0674</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Yun-hee.jeon@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Yun-Hee Jeon</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>Yun-hee.jeon@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Yun-Hee Jeon</name>
      <address>Sydney Nursing School, The University of Sydney, 88 Mallett Street, Camperdown, NSW, Australia 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93510674</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yun-hee.jeon@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>