<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362808">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000795897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomized controlled trial comparing the effectiveness of intranasal ketamine and fentanyl in the relief of moderate to severe pain in children with limb injuries.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized controlled trial comparing the effectiveness of intranasal ketamine and fentanyl in the relief of moderate to severe pain in children with limb injuries.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PiCHForK Trial : Pain in Children: Fentanyl or Ketamine</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>analgesic effectiveness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>limb injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>intranasal ketamine 1mg/kg as a single dose

plus

10mg/kg oral ibuprofen</interventions>
    <comparator>intranasal fentanyl 1.5 micrograms/kg as a single dose

plus

10mg/kg oral ibuprofen</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mean reduction in pain scores on visual analogue pain scale in children over 6 yo and Biere Faces pain scale (modified) in children under 6 yo</outcome>
      <timepoint>t=30 minutes</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mean reduction in pain scores on visual analogue pain scale in children over 6 yo and Biere Faces pain scale (modified) in children under 6 yo</outcome>
      <timepoint>t=15 minutes and t=60 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage responding to each description of change in pain severity (a lot better, a little better, the same, a little worse, a lot worse)</outcome>
      <timepoint>t=15, 30 and 60 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage requiring any rescue-analgesia as additional dose of intranasal fentanyl or intravenous opioid at any time point during the hour-long observation period</outcome>
      <timepoint>t=15, 30 and 60 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage responding to each description of satisfaction with amount of analgesia experienced (satisfied, not satisfied, uncertain)</outcome>
      <timepoint>t=15, 30 and 60 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse event profile, specifically including:
i) Observed level of sedation using the University of Michigan Sedation Score (anxious/restless/both, cooperative/ orientated/ tranquil, respond to commands, brisk response to stimulus, sluggish response to stimulus, no response to stimulus).

ii) Self-reported or parent/guardian opinion on level of sedation

iii) Local adverse effects: presence of nasal irritation, bleeding or any local effects reported by the patient.

iv) Systemic adverse effects: changes in vital signs (tachycardia, hyper/hypotension), hallucinations (visual or other).

v) Suspected allergic reaction (incl type)

vi) Any other</outcome>
      <timepoint>t= 15, 30 and 60 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children aged three to 13 years and under 50kg body weight

Musculoskeletal injury to upper and/or lower limbs

Visual analogue pain score greater than or equal to 6/10 on the standard 11-point verbal rating scale (0 = none, 10 = worst pain imaginable) and patient would normally be considered for intranasal fentanyl administration.

Use of simple analgesia such as paracetamol or ibuprofen or inhalational methoxyflurane during ambulance transport are not exclusion criteria</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>13</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability to gain informed consent from parent or guardian

Prior administration of parenteral or intranasal analgesics (morphine, fentanyl)

Prior administration of oral opioid analgesia (oxycodone, codeine)

Allergy to ketamine, fentanyl, or ibuprofen

Aberrant nasal anatomy

Acute or chronic nasal problems or nasal trauma that may preclude adequate administration or absorption of intranasal medication.

Presence of multiple trauma or injuries.

Sustained a head injury with loss of consciousness.

Presence of cognitive impairment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>In general, patients who are eligible for this study are triaged as Australasian Triage Scale (ATS) Category 2 because it is felt that they need analgesia within 10 minutes.

The ED triage nurse will notify the nominated Paediatric ED ‘Cat 2 doctor’ in the usual way. (Note: At the study ED, both the Cat 2 doctor and the ED Consultant In Charge (CIC) receive a pager notification of the arrival of a Category 2 patient (with whatever diagnosis), and so are usually aware of such patients prior to their reaching an ED cubicle.

The Cat 2 doctor will perform a rapid assessment of the patient in the usual way, which during the study period will include consideration of the study inclusion and exclusion criteria. 

Obtaining a verbal numerical rating of pain severity is standard in this setting. 

If the patient is eligible and the Cat 2 doctor or CIC believe that the time involved in patient recruitment will not have an adverse effect on either that patient’s management or the concurrent work of the ED, then either of these doctors or another delegate may broach study participation with the patient and their parent/guardian.  

Initially, verbal consent for the administration of ketamine or fentanyl as a pain reliever will be sought from the parent/guardian by reading a pre-prepared information sheet describing the study. 

This will be done to prevent delays to analgesia and the increased distress that are likely to occur in the recruitment of study subjects when a complete written PICF must be read and completed by the patient’s parent/guardian prior to the administration of analgesia. A similar approach to consent has been approved for our previous dose-finding studies of ketamine in children and adults. 

Given that ketamine and fentanyl have both been shown to provide significant analgesia by the intranasal route in un-blinded studies we feel it is not unethical to gain initial verbal consent.

Oral ibuprofen (10mg/kg) will then be administered within the first 15 minutes of intranasal injection of the study drug in a weight-based dose appropriate for each child unless these drugs have already been given in the past 3 hours.

Written consent will be obtained once the printed PICF is given to the parent/guardian after analgesia has been ordered and administered, for the data collection, analysis and storage of pain scores, adverse events and other clinical data. 

When the patient parent/guardian’s initial verbal consent is obtained, the attending doctor will calculate the appropriate dosage of Ketamine/Fentanyl from the chart attached to the data collection form and chart this for administration via the intranasal route. 

The drug will be pre-prepared by the clinical trials pharmacist in pre-packaged blinded 2 ml syringes. The syringes will be block randomised at the time of preparation in the pharmacy department and then placed in the locked ED scheduled drug cupboard for use. The syringes will be taken from the cupboard in sequential order The volume to be administered will be calculated from the dosing table. 

The syringe will contain 1.5 ml. This volume will be reduced to the appropriate total volume determined from the dosing table. Half of this final volume will be introduced into each nares by an atomizer device fitted to the end of the syringe. (NB. Staff are familiar with this equipment due to the common use of intranasal fentanyl for paediatric analgesia).

The patient (or if they are not able, their parent/guardian) will be asked to complete the baseline pain severity ratings (T0) and then the drug will be administered and signed for on the medication chart. As early as possible, the attending doctor will complete the baseline demographic information.</concealment>
    <sequence>Block Randomisation undertaken by the clinical trials pharmacists at Monash Medical Centre</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Compare change in VAS ratings at primary end point T30 and secondary endpoints T15, T60 to pre-treatment pain rating T0</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/09/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/11/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Southern Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd,
Clayton, Vic, 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Jack Brockhoff Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
150 Queen Street
Melbourne
Victoria 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Monash University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Southern Clinical School
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd,
Clayton, Vic, 3168</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Control of moderate to severe pain in children following limb injury is a significant challenge in the emergency department. Intranasal administration of fentanyl is commonly used to reduce pain in this group. Ketamine, is a commonly used drug for procedural sedation in the ED. It has recently been shown to also provide good analgesia in doses that do not produce sedation and can also be administered intranasally (IN). An observational dose-confirmation, first time in ED, study was recently undertaken in the paediatric emergency department of Monash Medical Centre revealing that IN ketamine provided pain relief comparable to that reported in observational studies where IN fentanyl was used in children with limb injuries. The observationa study suggests that IN ketamine may be an alterantive pain reliver in children with moderate to severe pain. However, neither ketamine or fentanyl have been assessed in a blinded fashion in treating pain in children.
We aim to compare the effectiveness, side effects and satisfaction of IN ketamine to IN fentanyl in a randomised controlled double-blind fashion in children presenting to the ED with moderate to severe pain and limb injuries.
The results of this study will help confirm the effectiveness of both pain relievers and ascertain whether IN ketamine can be used in place of fentanyl in this patient group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health HREC-B</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Leve4,
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd,
Clayton, Vic, 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/08/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Andis Graudins</name>
      <address>Dept of Emergency Medicine
135 Dandenong Hospital, 
David Street,
Dandenong, Victoria, 3175</address>
      <phone>+61395943193</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andis.graudins@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Andis Graudins</name>
      <address>Dept of Emergency Medicine
135 Dandenong Hospital, 
David Street,
Dandenong, Victoria, 3175</address>
      <phone>+61395943193</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andis.graudins@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Andis Graudins</name>
      <address>Dept of Emergency Medicine
135 Dandenong Hospital, 
David Street,
Dandenong, Victoria, 3175</address>
      <phone>+61395943193</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andis.graudins@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andis Graudins</name>
      <address>Dept of Emergency Medicine
135 Dandenong Hospital, 
David Street,
Dandenong, Victoria, 3175</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9554 9340</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andis.graudins@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>