<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373854">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001501336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Study of Pirfenidone Solution for Inhalation in Healthy Volunteers, Smokers or Former Smokers with Decreased Lung function, and Patients with Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis (IPF) to determine pharmacokinetics, as well as the safety and tolerability in volunteers with a history of smoking with decreased lung function and IPF patients. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1 Study of AP01 (Aerodone, Pirfenidone Solution for Inhalation) Delivered via the PARI eFlow® Nebulizer System in Healthy Volunteers, Smokers or Former Smokers with Decreased Lung Function, and Patients with Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis  (IPF) to determine pharmacokinetics, as well as the safety and tolerability in volunteers with a history of smoking with decreased lung function and IPF patients. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1203-8329 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Sponsor protocol number: AP01-001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Drug: Inhaled Pirfenidone: Cohorts 1, 2 and 3, except those receiving placebo, will receive a single ascending dose, (25, 50, and 100 mg dose of pirfenidone, respectively).  Cohorts 4 - 6, except those assigned to placebo in Cohort 5, will receive a single dose (25, 50,or 100 mg pirfenidone) of the maximum tolerated dose from the first three cohorts.  
Drug: Salbutamol:  Cohorts 1-3: If forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) in two or more subjects in any ascending dose cohort falls by greater than 10% at 15 minutes, all subsequent subjects will be pretreated with salbutamol.   Otherwise, Cohort 4 will not receive pretreatment with salbutamol; Cohort 5 and Cohort 6 subjects with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) or with a smoking history will receive pretreatment with 2 puffs (200µg) of salbutamol metered dose inhaler device within 30 minutes to inhalation of study drug. 
 Subjects will be trained to used the nebulizer upon admission to the Phase 1 facility.  This single dose investigational product administration will be overseen by personnel at the Phase 1 facility.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Drug: Inhaled Placebo: Those assigned to placebo will receive a single dose of placebo.  Placebo contains 5 mMol citrate buffer, 150 mMol NaCl, 0.225 mMol sodium saccharine and water, pH 6.0, filled to 9.0 mL</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate the safety and tolerability of inhaled pirfenidone as measured by adverse events related to investigational product, lab parameters, Spirometry before and after drug administration (Cohort 4 excluded), Oximetry before and after drug administration, cardiac monitoring during bronchoscopy (Cohort 4 only)
 </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-dose on Day 1
Upon Discharge on Day 2
At Follow-Up on Day 5, 6, or 7
 </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine systemic and urine pharmacokinetics (PK) for each dose using Maximum Concentration (Cmax), Time to Peak Concentration (Tmax) and Area Under the Concentration  Time Curve from Time 0 to 24 Hours Post Dose (AUC(0-24) ).  All PK parameters will be summarized using descriptive statistics and presented by time point. All PK parameters will be presented for individual subjects in data listings.
No PK data will be compiled for the placebo subjects.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Analysis of pirfenidone plasma concentrations prior to and at 10 minutes, 30 minutes, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 24 hours post-dose.  Analysis of pirfenidone urine concentrations prior to and 0-6, 6-12, and 12-24 hours post-dose.  Analysis of pirfenidone amounts in bronchoalveolar lavage fluid between 20 - 45 minutes post-dose (Cohort 4 only)
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of Aerodone in normal healthy volunteers (NHV).  Tolerability of dose will be assessed by the Principal Investigator by reviewing adverse events, change in FEV1 and oximetry to determine either continuation of the cohort or dose escalation, respectively.  A safety committee will be available to review the data for determination of cohort continuation and escalation, if needed.  Potential dose limiting events are 1) Possible or probably drug related moderate or severe adverse event 2) Saturated Oxygen (SaO2) &lt; 80% post dose, 3)  IPF cohort only: SaO2 decrease &gt; 10% from baseline (subjects may be on supplemental O2), or 4) FEV1 decrease of &gt; 15% and symptomatic occurring after pretreatment with Salbutamol  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-dose on Day 1
Upon Discharge on Day 2
At Follow-Up on Day 5, 6, or 7
 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Males or females 18 to 55 years 
2.	Female subjects must be:
	of non child-bearing potential [surgically sterilised or postmenopausal (12 months with no menses without alternative medical cause)] OR
	not pregnant, breast feeding or planning to become pregnant AND willing to comply with the medically acceptable contraceptive requirements of the study from Screening to at least 30 days after the last Investigational Medicinal Product (IMP) administration.
3.	Must be able to communicate with site personnel and to understand and voluntarily sign the Informed Consent Form.
Additional Inclusion Criterion for Cohort 5
4.	Current or past smokers with &gt; 20 pack year history of smoking and decreased lung function (50%&lt; FEV1&lt;80% predicted)
Additional Inclusion Criteria for Cohort 6
5.	Diagnosis of IPF by American Thoracic Society (ATS) 2011 criteria
6.	Males or females 18 to 70 years
7.	For at least 2 subjects, &gt; 20 pack year history of smoking
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	History of previous allergy or sensitivity to pirfenidone. 
2.	Use of oral pirfenidone within 2 days prior to admission to Phase 1 facility.
3.	History of reactive airways disease (such as asthma or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), cystic fibrosis, or bronchiectasis (Cohorts 1-4 only). Cohort 5 will exclude cystic fibrosis and bronchiectasis but will allow a history of COPD and Asthma.
4.	Human Immunodeficiency Virus Positive Result (HIV+).
5.	Active Hepatitis B or C.
6.	Cigarette/e-Cigarette smoking or use of other nicotine or tobacco containing products within seven days prior to study drug administration (Cohorts 1-4 only). 
7.	Positive for drugs of abuse or alcohol use at screening or admission to Phase 1 facility.  A breathalyzer test will be used to screen for the presence of alcohol. A urine standard panel will be used to test for the following substances (with repeat testing for confirmation, as needed) (Cohorts 1-5 only):
	 Opiates
	 Methadone
	 Cocaine
	Tetrahydrocannabinol
	Benzodiazepines
	Amphetamines / Methamphetamines
	Barbiturates
	3,4-methylenedioxy-methamphetamine
	Phencyclidine
8.	Participation in a clinical study with administration of an investigational drug product within the previous 30 days, or five half-lives (T1/2) of the previously administered investigational product.
9.	Donation of blood or significant blood loss within the 8 weeks prior to admission to Phase 1 facility.
10.	Donation of plasma within the week prior to admission to Phase 1 facility.
11.	Any other condition which in the view of the Investigator is likely to interfere with the study or put the subject at risk.
12.	Pregnant or nursing.
13.	Use of any medication in the opinion of the Principal Investigator that that might interact with study medication or may lead to abnormal chemistry of hematology tests.
14.	Clinically significant abnormality in the opinion of the Principal Investigator in baseline hematology or chemistry tests.

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>44</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Nucleus Network - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Avalyn Pharma Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 19 HWT Tower 40 City Road Southbank VIC 3006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Avalyn Pharma Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 19 HWT Tower 40 City Road Southbank VIC 3006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A Phase 1, Randomized, Double-Blinded Study of AP01 (Aerodone, Pirfenidone Solution for Inhalation) Delivered via the PARI eFlow Nebulizer System in Healthy Volunteers, Smokers or Former Smokers with Decreased Lung function, and Patients with Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis to determine the Pharmacokinetics and Maximum Tolerated Dose, as well as the Safety and Tolerability in IPF patients</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital 
55 Commercial Rd, 
Melbourne VIC 3004
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/10/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jason Lickliter</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network, Level 5, Burnet Building, AMREP Precinct, 89 Commerical Rd, Melbourne, VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 8960</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>J.Lickliter@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bruce Montgomery</name>
      <address>Avalyn Pharma Pty Ltd, Level 19 HWT Tower 40 City Road Southbank VIC 3006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9869 5922</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bmontgomery@avalynpharma.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bruce Montgomery</name>
      <address>Avalyn Pharma Pty Ltd., Level 19 HWT Tower 40 City Road Southbank VIC 3006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9869 5922</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bmontgomery@avalynpharma.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>
      </name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>