<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367568">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000263594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Bone Density Analysis of Rigid vs Elastic Uncemented Acetabular Cups in Patients with Symptomatic Arthritis of the Hip.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>DEXA Analysis of Conventional Rigid vs. Elastic Uncemented Acetabular Cups in Patients with Symptomatic Arthritis of the Hip.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1164-9901</utrn>
    <trialacronym>DEXA Rigid vs. Elastic Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Symptomatic arthritis of hip</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>RM Pressfit Acetabular Cup.  The cup is a cementless monoblock press-fit acetabular cup and it is manufactured from UHMWPE, which is stabilised with Vitamin E.  The outer surface of the polyethylene is coated with titanium particles for bony in-growth.
This device has no metal shell, and is designed to be flexible in the acetabular bone, unlike a conventional uncemented acetabular cup.
A standard total hip replacement will be performed to implant the device, according to the individual surgeons normal practice.</interventions>
    <comparator>Rigid Uncemented Acetabular Cup.  The cup is a conventional uncemented acetabular cup with a metal shell and polyethylene liner.
A standard total hip replacement will be performed to implant the device, according to the individual surgeons normal practice.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate the acetabular bone stock when using a RM Pressfit Cup compared with a conventional rigid uncemented acetabular cup as assessed by DEXA analysis.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate the acetabular bone stock when using a RM Pressfit Cup compared with a conventional rigid uncemented acetabular cup as assessed by DEXA analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine whether the RM Pressfit Vitamys Cup performs as well as conventional acetabular cups with regards to function using the Oxford Hip Score. Average scores will be compared between the RM Pressfit Cup group and the comparison group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine whether the RM Pressfit Vitamys Cup performs as well as conventional acetabular cups with regards to quality-of-life using the Short Form 36 (SF-36) and the Assessment of Quality of Life (AQoL-6D). Average scores for each assessment will be compared between the RM Pressfit Cup group and the comparison group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients with symptomatic arthritis who are candidates for a primary total hip replacement with an uncemented or cemented femoral stem as determined jointly by the surgeon and the patient.
2. Patients suitable for an uncemented acetabular component
3. Patients who understand the conditions of the study and are willing to participate for the length of the prescribed follow-up
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients who have had previous contralateral hip replacement surgery
2. Pregnant women or those seeking to become pregnant
3. Patients with a history of active infection
4. Patients with conditions or medications associated with osteoporosis or osteopenia ie: bisphosphonates, Protos, steroids and previous acetabular surgery on the affected side.
5. Patients who have severe arthritis of contralateral hip
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients who conform to the inclusion/exclusion criteria will be invited to join the study.  If they agree, then a consent form will be signed and the treatment group will be randomised via central randomisation software. The patient will not be informed of which study group they have been assigned to prior to surgery.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation of equal allocations to each group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants are randomised between the two study groups to receive either the test or control devices.  Recruitment and randomisation continue until the sample size is complete.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The study has adequate power to determine if the bone density behind the Elastic Cup is maintained compared with the control group.
To estimate the sample group size the following parameters
were set:
1.  Level of significance: a or p=0.05, 2 sided
2.  Power level: 95%

Using a sample size formula to calculate the average for two groups; the sample size was calculated at 58 patients. This means that 58 patients per group are required to detect a 20% difference with a 95% confidence.

Allowing for a 25% withdrawal or loss to follow-up this will give 72 patients per group.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>144</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Epworth Richmond - Richmond</hospital>
    <postcode>3121 - Richmond</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mathys Orthopaedics Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Unit 6
1517 Chaplin Drive
Lane Cove West
NSW 2066</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mathys Orthopaedics Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 6
1517 Chaplin Drive
Lane Cove West
NSW 2066
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This clinical study is a prospective, randomised, multi-centre study that will enrol 144 patients over a 12-month recruitment period between three surgeons and three centres.
The objective of the study is to investigate if the Mathys RM Pressfit Cementless Cup maintains acetabular bone stock by reducing the effects of stress shielding when compared with a conventional rigid cementless acetabular cup.  This study also aims to demonstrate safety, and equivalent clinical outcomes to standard care.  
The RM Pressfit Cementless cup is designed to have a modulus of elasticity that is similar to bone, and therefore it may be possible to transfer physiological loads through the cup and prevent the bone behind the cup from resorbing due to stress shielding.
The control group for this study will be a standard hip replacement with a conventional rigid cementless acetabular cup.
Standard, functional parameters will be assessed pre-operatively, and post-operatively at 6 weeks, 6 months, 12 months, 2 years and 5 years.
Antero-posterior and lateral radiographs will be analysed at 6 weeks, 1 year and 5 years to assess femoral stem and acetabular cup orientation. DEXA (measures bone density) scans will be assessed pre-operatively at 6 weeks, 6 months, 12 months, 2 years and 5 years to measure acetabular bone density, with the aim of showing preservation of bone behind the RM Pressfit Cup when compared to a conventional rigid cup.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Epworth HealthCare Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>89 Bridge Road
Richmond
VIC 3121</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>56512</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/10/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St John of God Health Care Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>12 Salvado Road
Subiaco
WA 6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>571</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard de Steiger</name>
      <address>Orthopaedic Surgeon
26 Erin Street
Richmond 
VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9429 5580</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.desteiger@epworth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jenny Burke</name>
      <address>NeoSurgical Pty Ltd
17 Macarthur Avenue
Pagewood
NSW 2035</address>
      <phone>+61 0488 240471</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennyburke@neosurgical.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jenny Burke</name>
      <address>NeoSurgical Pty Ltd
17 Macarthur Avenue
Pagewood
NSW 2035</address>
      <phone>+61 0488 240471</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennyburke@neosurgical.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jenny Burke</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>