<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371683">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001471471p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Whole body vibration training in Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy (DMD)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Whole-body vibration training as a therapy to improve mobility, muscle and bone health in children and adolescents with Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Duchenne muscular dystrophy
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Neurodegenerative diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment
Whole Body Vibration Training (WBVT) will be performed on the Galileo Basic vibration plate (Novotec Medical, Pforzheim, Germany). Each session will consist of three 3-minute bouts of training, interspersed with a 3-minute rest. Sessions will be performed four times a week, over a 20- week period (T1  T2). Participants will start with sessions of three 1-minute bouts at 12 Hz, and both intensity and duration will be gradually increased according to the response of each individual. However, by the end of week 4, all participants should be training at the prescribed protocol of 3 sets of 3 minutes at 20 Hz and 1 mm amplitude, 4 times a week. Training intensity will be maintained at 20 Hz for the remainder of the intervention. This training protocol is a well validated clinical paradigm used in previous published literature.
Participants will stand barefoot on the plate. An adjustable metal frame will initially be used with all participants until they build up confidence and are able to safely support themselves during the vibration training. For participants with poor balance, the frame will be maintained at all times to safely regain balance when necessary. Training sessions will be performed at home. An experienced exercise physiologist and/or a specialist physiotherapist from the research team will supervise the participants performing training at home or school once a week, in order to monitor progress and provide feedback/support. It is the participant's personal preference whether the training will be at home or school. Parents/caregivers will provide ongoing supervision of home sessions. Participants will be asked to maintain a training diary to monitor compliance. Data recorded will include the date, intensity and duration of training, as well as any comments regarding adverse events, tiredness, or pain.
We will provide participants with a Fitbit to monitor activity levels and resting heart rate.
</interventions>
    <comparator>This study will have a single intervention group, comparing baseline (T0), a control period of 20 weeks (T1), and post-treatment outcomes (T2).During the lead in period of 20 weeks (T0  T1) patients will continue their usual activity levels and standard care. This control period will allow for better assessment of efficacy.  All participants will undergo 20 weeks of WBVT between T1 and T2. This study design effectively allows for the participants to act as their own controls with an initial 20 week observation period. Due to the small numbers of children with DMD, a randomised control trial design is not feasible. A cross-over design is also inappropriate, as the effects of WBVT are likely to be long-standing (weeks to months). 
Any patients unable to travel to Auckland for the full assessments, who would like to participate, will be included as a control group with assessments at T0 and T2.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in function and mobility as assessed by the 6 minute walk test
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline (T0), after 20 weeks control period (T1) and after 20 weeks intervention (T2).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in bone health/osteoporosis (composite) measured with comparison of bone mineral density through the DEXA and pQCT scans. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline (T0), after 20 weeks control period (T1) and after 20 weeks intervention (T2).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Confirm safety with regular checks of creatinine kinase levels by serum assay,  We will also check blood tests for bone and muscle turnover (eg. bone-specific alkaline phosphatase, serum osteocalcin, parathyroid hormone, calcium, phosphate, tumour necrosis factor alpha). Symptomatology will be documented in the patient diaries,</outcome>
      <timepoint>Creatine kinase serum assay will by done at baseline (T0), monthly during the 20 week control period (T1), weekly for the first 4 weeks of the intervention, then monthly for the remainder of the intervention (T2) period, ie. 5 months total.
Other blood tests will be done at baseline (T0), after 20 weeks control period (T1) and after 20 weeks intervention (T2).
Patient diaries will be assessed weekly by the research assistant or exercise physiologist, parents can also ring for advice if any concerns arise.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be aged 8- 18 years and have a genetically confirmed diagnosis of Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy.

Only participants with mild to moderate mobility will be recruited, i.e. those who are able to:
 i) stand on the vibration platform for the duration of treatment sessions, and
 ii) undergo the clinical and functional assessments necessary to evaluate treatment outcomes. 
Mobility would be GMFCS Level I to Level IV, and patients would need to be able to complete a 6MWT without the use of a wheelchair (but may use a walking aid).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria include:
1) A bone fracture within 8 weeks of enrolment;
2) Acute thrombosis, tendinitis, nephrolithiasis, discopathy or arthritis;
3) History of another illness or findings on physical examination, which in the opinion of the investigators would prevent the patient from completing the study;
4) Use for greater than or equal to 30 days of medication that might interfere with study results and assessments within 3 months of enrolment (e.g. anabolic agents);
5) Patients who have started bisphosphonate treatment within 12 months of the intervention.
6) Vertebral compression of Genant grade 3 or greater;
7) Vitamin D deficiency at screening (serum 25-hydroxyvitamin D concentrations &lt;50nmol/l); note that if a potential participant is deficient and management of low vitamin D is possible to bring levels above 50 nmol/l, the individual can become eligible.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>N/A</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/05/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Liggins Institute at the University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>85 Park Road, Grafton, Auckand, 1023
Private Bag 92019 Auckland Mail Centre
Auckland, 1142, New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Starship Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Starship Foundation P O Box 9389 New Market, Auckland 1149 New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Neuromuscular Research Foundation Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 12063, Penrose
Auckland, 1642

419A Church Street East, Penrose
Auckland, 1061</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Neurological Foundation of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>66 Grafton Road, Grafton, Auckland
PO Box 110022, Auckland City Hospital, Auckland 1148</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy (DMD) is one of the most common genetic disorders, affecting 1 in 3,600 live male births. Affected patients develop relentlessly progressive muscle degeneration and weakness from 4-5 years of age, and typically lose the ability to walk before 13 years of age. There are no therapies to improve muscle mass and function while maintaining or improving bone health. In addition, patients are on high dose steroids which further reduce bone strength. We aim to investigate the effects of 20 weeks of whole-body vibration training on mobility, muscle mass and function and bone health in 20 children and adolescents with DMD. We also aim to confirm safety and establish efficacy of this novel therapeutic approach. Participants will undergo comprehensive clinical assessments at baseline and after the treatment period. This novel therapy is non-invasive, simple, and potentially could help these boys stay out of a wheelchair for longer, and improve their quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HDEC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371683-WBVT STUDY PROTOCOL.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371683-WBVT PIS and consent.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Hofman</name>
      <address>Liggins Institute
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Grafton
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 6453</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.hofman@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa Power</name>
      <address>Liggins Institute
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Grafton
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737599 ext 86098</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lpower@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa Power</name>
      <address>Liggins Institute
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Grafton
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737599 ext 86098</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lpower@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>