<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369990">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000095460p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Continouous versus Single-injection Interscalene block for minor Shoulder surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Continuous versus Single Shot regional block in shoulder surgery       </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Shoulder musculoskeletal pathology
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Regional anaesthesia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To compare two different forms of delivery of regional anaesthesia during shoulder surgery
The continuous block uses 20ml of 0.5% ropivacaine as a bolus through a catheter prior to general anaesthesia, after a surgical duration of average 90 minutes, the block is administered post operatively with continuous infusion of 0.2% ropivacaine at 2 ml/h with patient-controlled bolus of 5 ml hourly for five days post surgery. 
The patient press a button on the pump to administer 5ml of ropivacaine when they experience pain, this is in addition to the base rate of 2ml/hr. The patient can not have another 5ml additional bolus until an hour later for safety reason. This is common administration for all currently available regional block pain pump.
The anaesthetist places the block using ultrasound guidance aiming at the region around brachial plexus between the neck and the clavicle. The success of the block is checked with a cold object (e.g ice cube) after patient is awake after surgery.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive a bolus of 20ml of 0.5% ropivacaine through a catheter immediately prior to general anaesthesia followed by continuous infusion of normal saline at 2ml/h with patient-controlled bolus of 5ml saline hourly for five days post surgery. The anaesthetist administers the block with ultraound guidance at the brachial plexus between the neck and the clavicle. Again this is checked with patient's sensation to cold after procedure.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>subjective pain score VAS</outcome>
      <timepoint>day 7 post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>patient will record the use of pain medications on daily basis </outcome>
      <timepoint>first week post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>length of hospital stay via hospital record</outcome>
      <timepoint>from end of surgery to discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the patient will record when they first request the use of pain medication to control pain after surgery</outcome>
      <timepoint>between end of the surgery and the first time the patient experience pain and request pain medications after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>total hours of sleep with self reported sleep diary</outcome>
      <timepoint>first week post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>complications such as infection at the injection site, hypersthesia at the particular dermatome from the block, or persistent weakness of the particular myotome from the block
The adverse event are assessed by self report of symptoms in pain diary</outcome>
      <timepoint>daily assessment of adverse events on diary until 7 days post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients undergoing minor shoulder surgery in wellington catchment area</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>14</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Unwilling to consent  those unwilling to consent to participation in the study cannot be included due to ethical reasons.
2. Major shoulder surgery  those who are undergoing major shoulder surgery with surgical incision of more than five centimetres were excluded such as arthroplasty surgery or open shoulder stabilisation procedures. These were generally more painful with prolonged recovery.
3. Complex regional pain syndrome  those who have existing complex regional pain syndrome or previous hyper sensitivity to pain were likely to have significant difficulties with pain management after surgery.
4. Contraindications to interscalene regional block  those who have absolute contraindications to regional block are excluded, such as severe allergic reaction to local anaesthetic agent or contralateral phrenic nerve dysfunction.
5. Failed regional block  those who have severe pain immediately after surgery with clinical evidence of normal sensation of the intended block region were excluded.  Normal sensation indicates the regional block may not been placed around the targeted nerve.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>allocation options will be consealed in identical opaque envelops. These will be stored in a secure location and only opened while patient is in theatre preparing to undergo anaesthesia.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Pre study power analysis was undertaken based on a previous study. We estimated average pain score of 3 and standard deviation of 3 in the continuous block group at day 7. In order to detect a clinical significant pain score difference (&gt;3) with a 90% study power, a minimum of 44 patients are required.  We aim to recruit an overall of 50 patients with 25 patients of each study arm.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/05/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>wellington hospital orthopaedic department</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Riddiford St, Newtown, Wellington 6021</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>wellington hospital research fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Riddiford St, Newtown, Wellington 6021</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Minor shoulder surgery is a commonly performed surgical procedure in New Zealand.  This includes various forms of mini-open and arthroscopic procedures such as acromial spur removal, rotator cuff repair, excision of distal clavicle, and shoulder stabilisation. Patients undergoing these procedures frequently report pain in the immediate post operative recovery period. 
Without proper pain management, complications can occur such as excessive analgesia usage, complex regional pain and delayed rehabilitation. These problems consequently lead to patients dissatisfaction and disability, unnecessary hospital admissions, and sometimes further surgery.
The addition of a regional interscalene block to the standard general anaesthesia helps to significantly reduce pain in the first week after rotator cuff surgery. There are two alternative methods of delivery of the regional block. A single shot injection block was performed by the anaesthetist by placing local anaesthetic agent around the interscalene region prior to surgery. Alternatively a continuous block utilises a pump delivering five days of the same local anaesthetic agent to the same region. Both blocks are commonly practiced in New Zealand, however the effectiveness has not been clearly distinguished in all minor shoulder surgery procedures. 
This study aim to investigate the difference between these two blocks in terms of patients pain management during the first week after surgery.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability ethics committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington 6145
New Zealand</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Justin Chou</name>
      <address>Wellington Hospital Orthopaedic Department
Riddiford St, Newtown, Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 385 5999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>choch550@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Justin Chou</name>
      <address>Wellington Hospital Orthopaedic Department
Riddiford St, Newtown, Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 385 5999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>choch550@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Justin Chou</name>
      <address>Wellington Hospital Orthopaedic Department
Riddiford St, Newtown, Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 385 5999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>choch550@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Justin Chou</name>
      <address>Riddiford St, Newtown, Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 04 385 5999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>choch550@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>