<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343399">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000951954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Sino-Swiss Internet-based intervention for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder project</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of an internet-based intervention on symptoms of Posttraumatic Stress Disorder in Chinese trauma survivors</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1123-8904</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Posttraumatic Stress Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Internet-based intervention is to be used with a multimodal program My trauma recovery, which provides education information about Posttraumatic Stress Disorder and helps users to increase their coping skills and self-efficacy through interactive exercises with feedbacks. The intervention lasts four weeks. Participants are required to use the program at least three times per week with a minimum usage time of 30 minutes per time. The program will provide all participants usage information, including login and logout time, time spent on each module and so on.</interventions>
    <comparator>The scientific goal is to conduct a comprehensive randomized-controlled trial of internet-based treatment of PTSD for Chinese patients. Half of the sample will be randomly allocated to a group starting treatment immediately (after satisfying the intake criteria) and which lasts for four weeks. The second half of the sample will serve as a waiting list control group, starting treatment after a waiting period of, at minimum, four weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms of Posttraumatic Stress Disorder as assessed by Posttraumatic Diagnostic Scale (PDS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before the intervention, at the end of intervention, and 3 months following the completion of intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social functional impairment as assessed by Functional Impairment questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before the intervention, at the end of intervention, and 3 months following the completion of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Trauma events: experienced at least one trauma event (e.g., death or threat to life, assault, or humiliation) during the past five years;
Trauma Timing: 3 months - 5 years;
Trauma symptoms screening: at least 4 symptoms using Trauma Screening Questionnaire</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Age: younger than 18 years;
Competency of Chinese language: bad reading and aural comprehension;
Internet access time: less than 360 minutes in four weeks;
Acute psychosis screening: clinical rating using Psychosescreening;
Substance abuse and intoxication screening: clinical rating using The CAGE Questionnaire</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants make first the trauma symptoms screening by telephone. Those who pass the screening procedure are then allocated to the intervention group or the waiting group by randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table containing number 1 to 90 created by computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sino-Swiss Science and Technology Cooperation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>International Institutional Affairs (IIA)
ETH Zurich, HG F 11
Raemistrasse 101
CH-8092 Zurich</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Switzerland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sino-Swiss Science and Technology Cooperation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>International Institutional Affairs (IIA)
ETH Zurich, HG F 11
Raemistrasse 101
CH-8092 Zurich</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Zurich</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Psychopathology &amp; Clinical Intervention University of Zurich 
Binzmuehlestr. 14/17
CH-8050 Zurich</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Switzerland</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to develop, implement and evaluate a self-sustained virtual out-door clinic for traumatized patients (http://mandarin.mytraumarecovery.com). The virtual treatment center for posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD) applies the multimodal program My trauma recovery as the main technological tool. Its modules focus on social support, cognitive restructuring (self talk), relaxation, coping, trigger recognition, and recognition of the need for further professional help. It contains various technological advantages, such as progress charts and interactive tools. 
The scientific goal is to conduct a comprehensive randomized-controlled trial of internet-based treatment of PTSD for Chinese patients. Half of the sample will be randomly allocated to a group starting treatment immediately (after satisfying the intake criteria) which lasts for four weeks. The second half of the sample will serve as a wait list control group, starting treatment after a waiting period of, at minimum, four weeks. Follow-up assessments will be conducted at the end of treatment and 3 months following the completion of treatment. It is expected that the Internet-based intervention reduce significantly participants distress of Posttraumatic Stress Disorder.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://mandarin.mytraumarecovery.com</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Wang, Z., Tang, S., Wang, J. &amp; Maercker, A. (2012). Foundations and future application of internet-based interventions for PTSD in PR China. International Journal of Electronic Healthcare, 7(1), 19-35.
Wang, Z., Wang, J. &amp; Maercker, A. (submitted). Traumatized users adherence to Internet-based interventions in an randomized controlled trial. Journal of Mental Health.
Wang, Z., Wang, J. &amp; Maercker, A. (in preparation). Chinese My Trauma Recovery: An Internet randomized controlled trial for traumatized persons.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research ethics board in School of Psychology, Beijing Normal University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>No. 19, XinJieKouWai St., HaiDian District, Beijing 100875, China</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/10/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/09/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andreas MAERCKER</name>
      <address>Department of Psychopathology &amp; Clinical Intervention,
University of Zurich, 
Binzmuehlestr. 14/17, 
CH-8050 Zurich</address>
      <phone>+41 (0)44 635 73 10</phone>
      <fax>+41 (0)44 635 73 19</fax>
      <email>maercker@psychologie.uzh.ch</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Zhiyun WANG</name>
      <address>School of Law, Tsinghua University, 
No. 30, Shuangqing Road, HaiDian District, Beijing 100086, China</address>
      <phone>+86 158 1012 0837</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>z.wang@psychologie.uzh.ch</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Zhiyun WANG</name>
      <address>School of Law, Tsinghua University, 
No. 30, Shuangqing Road, HaiDian District, Beijing 100086, China</address>
      <phone>+86 158 1012 0837</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>z.wang@psychologie.uzh.ch</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>