<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372802">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000754347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Influence of Different Breathing Modes on Oxygenation in a Lung Ventilation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Pressure-Controlled Ventilation-Volume Guaranteed Versus Volume-Controlled Respiratory Modes on Respiratory Dynamics and Oxygenation in One-Lung Ventilation: A Prospective, Randomized-Controlled Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1195-9172</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>One lung ventilation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Hypoxemia may develop in some patients, although one-lung ventilation (OLV) can be safely implemented to expand the field of vision and to facilitate surgical manipulation during lung surgeries. The main cause of hypoxemia is pulmonary shunt due to a single non-ventilated lung. Volume-controlled ventilation (VCV) is usually used as a mechanical ventilation modes, when OLV is implemented. Increased airway pressures in the ventilated lung cause the blood flow to be directed to the non-ventilated lung and the rate of pulmonary shunts further increases, thereby, leading to a deepening of hypoxemia. On the other hand, pressure-controlled ventilation-volume guaranteed (PC-VG) ventilation mode is used as a preventive ventilatory strategy during acute lung injury (ALI) and acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), and prevents uncontrolled increase in the alveolar pressure. Several studies comparing PC-VG with VCV have demonstrated that PC mode reduces the airway pressure and improves the partial arterial oxygen pressure (PaO2), particularly in patients with low preoperative forced vital capacity (FVC) values. In addition, the peak airway pressure (Ppeak) has been shown to decrease, while PaO2 increases due to decreased inspiratory current in the PC mode during ALI and ARDS. Therefore, the PC mode has been suggested to be an alternative ventilation mode to avoid high airway pressures during OLV In pressure-controlled ventilation-volume guaranteed (PC-VG) mode, 

The patients were provided with mechanical ventilatory support (Datex-Ohmeda Avance Anesthesia Machine, GE Healthcare, Madison WI USA) at a tidal volume of 7 mL/kg with 4 PEEP support to achieve an inspiration/expiration ratio of 1:2 and 50% FiO2.. During One lung ventilation (OLV), the tidal volumes of patients were reduced to 4 mL/kg and the respiratory frequency was increased up to 18-20. In the case of intraoperative hypoxia (Patients will be evaluated by the same consultant anaesthetist), certain maneuvers were performed for patient optimization including re-adjustment of tidal volume, increasing oxygen ratio, increasing PEEP, oxygen insufflation in non-ventilated lungs, fiberoptic confirmation of location of the intubation tube, and intermittent two-lung ventilation. The patients in PC-VG mode will monitored using the same mechanical ventilation mode from induction of anaesthesia to end of procedure.</interventions>
    <comparator>In Volume-controlled ventilation mode, the patients were provided with mechanical ventilatory support (Datex-Ohmeda Avance Anesthesia Machine, GE Healthcare, Madison WI USA) at a tidal volume of 7 mL/kg with 4 PEEP support to achieve an inspiration/expiration ratio of 1:2 and 50% FiO2. During OLV, the tidal volumes of patients were reduced to 4 mL/kg and the respiratory frequency was increased up to 18-20. The patients in VG mode will monitored using the same mechanical ventilation mode from induction of anaesthesia to end of procedure.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effect of pressure-controlled ventilation-volume guaranteed on arterial blood gas values
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (post intubation), and 15 and 60 mins of OLV, at 15 mins of TLV after lobectomy, and postoperative 6th and 24th-hour (arterial blood gas analysis will be used)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>peak inspiratory pressure (PIP)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (post intubation), 15th and 60th min OLV, and 15 min after TLV following lobectomy were recorded. 
(Airway pressure monitoring, Datex-Ohmeda Avance Anesthesia Machine, GE Healthcare, Madison WI USA)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>hemodynamic parameters (Mean arterial pressure, heart rate, CVP)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, and 15 and 60 mins of OLV, at 15 mins of TLV after lobectomy, and postoperative 6th and 24th-hour (invasive arterial pressure, central venous pressure, pulse oximetry, ECG on hemodynamic monitor)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>complications in one lung ventilation: Complications were defined as follows;
1. Cardiac complications: Postoperative myocardial infarction, atrial or ventricular arrhythmias damaging hemodynamics, 
2. Respiratory complications: Evaluated as Pneumonia, reintubation, tracheotomy, PaO2 values under 60%, PaCO2 values over 45 mmHg, Acute respiratory deficiency syndrome (ARDS); 
3. Cerebrovascular Events: Stroke, temporal ischemic attack, cerebral hemorrhage, infarct;
4. Renal Dysfunction: 0,5 mg dl-2 increase in creatinine when compared to basal values or 50% decrease in the calculated clearance rate or a need for renal replacement treatment/dialysis;
5. Gastrointestinal Complications: Ileus, abdominal distension, mesenteric ischemia, 
6. Hematologic Complications: Massive transfusion, thrombocytopenia, hemolysis, disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)
7. Infection and Sepsis: Proven infection and accompanying systemic inflammatory response syndrome.
8. Multiple Organ Dysfunction (MODS): Dysfunction of two or more organs 
9. Need for Reoperation: A need for revision due to bleeding or for any other reason 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post treatment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Lung lobectomy patients (Only lung lobectomy under one lung ventilation)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients were excluded if they had renal, cardiac, hepatic impairment; a body mass index greater than 30 kg/m2, and defined as less than 50% of the predicted values of forced expiratory volume in 1 second and forced vital capacity.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis was performed using the SPSS version 21.0 software (IBM Corp., Armonk, NY, USA) data were expressed in mean±standard deviation (SD), mean, and percentage (%). Normal distribution of data was analyzed using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. The chi-square and Fisher Exact tests were used for categorical variables, whereas the independent-samples t-test and Mann-Whitney U test were used for quantitative variables. A p value of &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>25/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>28/02/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>100</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>10/03/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cengiz sahutoglu</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ege Universitesi Tip Fakultesi Anesteziyoloji ve Reanimasyon Anabilim Dali 35100, Bornova/Izmir</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cengiz Sahutoglu</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ege Universitesi Tip Fakultesi Anesteziyoloji ve Reanimasyon Anabilim Dali 35100, Bornova/Izmir</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study was to investigate the effects of pressure-controlled ventilation-volume guaranteed (PC-VG) and volume-controlled ventilation (VCV) mode on respiratory parameters (intraoperative and postoperative) and complications in patients with one-lung ventilation (OLV) who underwent lobectomy. 
This prospective, randomized-controlled study included a total of 80 patients who underwent one-lung ventilation and lobectomy between July 2016 and February 2017. The patients were randomly divided into two groups as Group 1 (PC-VG) and Group 2 (VCV). Data including demographic characteristics of the patients, intraoperative mechanical ventilation parameters, intraoperative and postoperative oxygenation parameters, and complications were recorded. Two ventilation modes were compared.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ege University School of Medicine Clinical Research Ethical Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ege University, Faculty of Medicine. Department of Medical Ethics &amp; History of Medicine 35100, Bornova/ Izmir</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16-7/35</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cengiz Sahutoglu</name>
      <address>Ege Universitesi Tip Fakultesi Anesteziyoloji ve Reanimasyon Anabilim Dali 35100, Bornova/Izmir</address>
      <phone>+902323902143</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cengiz.sahutoglu@ege.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cengiz Sahutoglu</name>
      <address>Ege Universitesi Tip Fakultesi Anesteziyoloji ve Reanimasyon Anabilim Dali 35100, Bornova/Izmir</address>
      <phone>+902323902143</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cengiz.sahutoglu@ege.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cengiz Sahutoglu</name>
      <address>Ege Universitesi Tip Fakultesi Anesteziyoloji ve Reanimasyon Anabilim Dali 35100, Bornova/Izmir</address>
      <phone>+902323902143</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cengiz.sahutoglu@ege.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cengiz Sahutoglu</name>
      <address>Ege Universitesi Tip Fakultesi Anesteziyoloji ve Reanimasyon Anabilim Dali 35100, Bornova/Izmir</address>
      <phone>+902323902143</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cengiz.sahutoglu@ege.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>