<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364025">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000407796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An open trial of telephone and internet-delivered psychological assessment and treatment to determine the benefits of the MindSpot Clinic for Australians with symptoms of anxiety and depression</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open trial of telephone and internet-delivered psychological assessment and treatment to determine the benefits of the MindSpot Clinic for Australians aged 18 years+ with symptoms of anxiety and depression</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym>None</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is an open trial of a new national mental health service that provides telephone and internet assessment and treatment of Australians with anxiety or depression.

In this open trial patients will complete structured assessments of anxiety and depression. Those who elect to participate in treatment will complete telephone or internet-delivered treatment course for their primary concern. Four different treatment courses are available targeting different symptoms: 1) Anxiety and low mood in individuals aged 18-65 years; 2) Anxiety and low mood in individuals aged 60+ years; 3) Obsessive compulsive disorder; 4) Post-traumatic stress disorder. 

Each treatment course is administered over 8 weeks. Each course teaches participants how to manage symptoms of anxiety, stress and/or low mood. 

Each treatment course comprises 4-5 lessons which are provided online, electronically, or sent via post. Mode of administration is based on participant preference. Lessons describe evidence-based cognitive behavioural and interpersonal therapy strategies for managing cognitive, behavioural, and physical symptoms of anxiety and low mood. One lesson will be completed every 1 to 3 weeks. Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to read. Participants will also have access to summaries of each lesson, and will read anonymous stories about other people with anxiety and low mood, taking a further 20 minutes per week. All participants will also receive 10-20 automatic emails to promote adherence and engagement, and at least weekly written or telephone contact from a therapist at the MindSpot Clinic. Adherence will be monitored by measures of participant activity including logins and materials accessed.

Study questionnaires will be administered at assessment (when participants initially apply to join a course), pre-intervention (immediately prior to the course), post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention. These will take about 20-30 minutes to complete. Additionally, there will be a brief 5 minute questionnaire at the start of each week of the Course.</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of psychological distress is measured by the Kessler 10-item (K-10) scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at assessment (when participants initially apply to join a course), pre-intervention (immediately prior to the course), post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention. The pre-intervention time-point may occur up several days or weeks after the assessment time-point.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms and severity of depression is measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at assessment, pre-intervention, at the beginning of each week of the Course, post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms of anxiety are measured by the Generalised Anxiety Disorder 7 Item Scale (GAD-7).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at assessment, pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Work and social adjustment status is measured by the Work and Social Adjustment Scale (WSAS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms and severity of obsessive compulsive disorder are measured by the Yale Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale - Self Report (YBOCS-SR).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at assessment, pre-intervention, mid-intervention, post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms and severity of post-traumatic stress disorder are measured by the PTSD Checklist (PCL).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at assessment, pre-intervention, mid-intervention, post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. 18+ years of age
2. Provides informed consent
3. Resident of Australia
4. Presenting problem are symptoms of an anxiety disorder or depressive disorder</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Presenting problem not anxiety or depression
2. Receiving psychological therapy for target symptoms at same time as the present trial</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will contact the MindSpot Clinic, read about the study, and will decide whether or not to provide Informed Consent.

Those who provide Informed Consent will complete a telephone or online assessment that comprises questionnaires of symptoms of depression and anxiety, the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 Item and Generalised Anxiety Disorder-7 item questionnaires, respectively. Potential participants will also be asked to complete demographic questionnaires. 

Potential participants will be informed about MindSpot Clinic Treatment Courses and will decide whether or not to participate. Participants who meet eligibility criteria will be given access codes to begin the intervention.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Because of the observational nature of the aims of this study, formal analyses of sample size have not been conducted. However, it is anticipated consecutive cohorts of 100-200 participants will be analysed, for purposes of exploring changes in effectiveness as the service develops.

Analyses will be conducted using parametric techniques and intention-to-treat and completer models, and will include tests of clinically significant change.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>19/04/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Macquarie University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Balaclava Road
North Ryde NSW 2109</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Mental Health Promotion Section
Mental Health Early Intervention and Prevention Branch
MDP 602
GPO Box 9848
Canberra
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Macquarie University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Balaclava Road
North Ryde NSW 2109</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study evaluates the short and medium term efficacy of assessment and treatment at the MindSpot Clinic in Australians aged 18+ with symptoms of anxiety or low mood.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.mindspot.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Dear BF, Titov N, Schwencke G, Andrews G, Johnston L, Craske MG, McEvoy P. (2011). An open trial of a brief transdiagnostic treatment for anxiety and depression. Behaviour Research and Therapy 49:830-837.

Johnston L, Titov N, Andrews G, Spence J, Dear BF. (2011). A randomized controlled trial of a transdiagnostic Internet-delivered treatment for anxiety disorders. PLoS ONE, 6(11): e28079. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0028079.

Titov N, Dear BF, Schwencke G, Andrews G, Johnston L, Craske M, McEvoy P. (2011). Transdiagnostic Internet treatment of anxiety and depression: A randomised controlled trial. Behaviour Research and Therapy 49:441-452.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Macquarie University
North Ryde
NSW 2109</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5201200912</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>C3A 724
Macquarie University
North Ryde
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98509901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>C3A 724
Macquarie University
North Ryde
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98509901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>C3A 724
Macquarie University
North Ryde
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98509901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>C3A 724
Macquarie University
North Ryde
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98509901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>