<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365521">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000032651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of the AMBU Aura-i and LMA Supreme supraglottic airway devices in spontaneously breathing anaesthetised patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study comparing the clinical performance and insertion parameters of the AMBU Aura-i and LMA Supreme supraglottic airway devices in spontaneously breathing anaesthetised females undergoing minor gynaeocological procedures.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Performance of airway device</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Spontaneously breathing anaesthetised females undergoing minor gynaeocological procedures</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>After induction of a standard general anaesthetic, the supraglottic airway (Ambu aura-i) was inserted into the patient's mouth and insertion parameters recorded. The amount of the air needed to inflate the cuff was measured. 

The duration required to insert the airway device will be timed from when the device enters the patient's mouth till the appearance of the first square end-tidal carbon dioxide (ETCO2) trace, therefore denoting successful establishment of effective ventilation.

Insertion parameters to be recorded are the device's ease of insertion, number of insertion attempts, oropharyngeal leak pressure, fibreoptic position, and haemodynamic response. These were recorded by an unblinded observer who was not involved in the study.</interventions>
    <comparator>In the comparator group, participants will be inserted with the LMA Supreme airway device. The procedure of insertion is the same as for the intervention group. The amount of the air needed to inflate the cuff was measured. The duration required to insert the airway device will be timed from the when the device enters the patient's mouth till the appearance of the first square end-tidal carbon dioxide (ETCO2) trace, therefore denoting successful establishment of effective ventilation. Insertion parameters to be recorded are the device's ease of insertion, number of insertion attempts, oropharyngeal leak pressure, fibreoptic position, and haemodynamic response. These were recorded by an unblinded observer who was not involved in the study.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The time taken to establish effective ventilation.This is the interval from when the Ambu Aura-i or LMA Supreme entered the mouth to the first capnograph trace.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the Ambu Aura-i or LMA Supreme airway device has been inserted into the participant's mouth.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ease of insertion of airway device assessed at point of airway device insertion on a 5 point scale (1= easy, 2 = not so easy, 3 = difficult, 4= very difficult, 5= impossible.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At point of of airway device insertion during procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oropharyngeal leak pressure (OLP)- as measured by closing the adjustable pressure limiting (APL) valve with a fresh gas flow of 3 L min-1, noting the airway pressure at equilibrium on manometer or when there was an audible air leak from the throat.</outcome>
      <timepoint>OLP assessed after airway device inserted into participant's mouth.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The fiberoptic view of the glottis; scored as follows: 0 = failure to function with no vocal cords (VC) seen, 1 = VC not seen but function adequate, 2= VC plus anterior epiglottis seen, 3= VC plus posterior epiglottis seen, 4 = only VC seen.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fibreoptic view assessed after insertion of airway device into participant's mouth.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Haemodynamic response eg.Blood pressure and heart rate as measured every minute for the first five minutes from induction of anaesthesia. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood pressure and heart rate as measured every minute for the first five minutes from induction of anaesthesia. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of visible blood on device.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The airway device is inspected for presence of visible blood upon its removal from participant's mouth at the end of srgery. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative sore throat ( by direct questioning of participants)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed in the PACU (post anaesthesia care unit) forty- five minutes after surgery by an independent observer.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dysphonia  (by direct questioning of participants)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed in the PACU (post anaesthesia care unit) forty- five minutes after surgery by an independent observer.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dysphagia (by direct questioning of participants)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed in the PACU (post anaesthesia care unit) forty- five minutes after surgery by an independent observer.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>One hundred ASA I- II patients scheduled for elective minor gynaecological and breast procedures in our women's hospital</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>ASA physical status III or IV; BMI equal to and greater than 40 kg/m2, those with predicted difficult airway; high risk of regurgitation or aspiration; and respiratory tract pathology (including preoperative sore throat).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible participants were interviewed and invited to participate. Sealed, opaque envelopes concealed the group allocation.  </concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated random number table.  </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome tested was time to LMA insertion.  Sample size was based on earlier studies of AMBU LMA insertion in non-paralysed, anaesthetized patients . Prospective power analysis showed that a sample size of 50 patients per group would be required to detect a 30% difference in the primary outcome at a significance level of 5% and power of 80%. 

The following tests were used to compare the data between the two groups: Students t-test for parametric data, patient demographics and time to insertion; Mann-Whitney U-test for Mallampati grading, ease of insertion, number of attempts;  chi  square / Fishers exact test for comparison of proportions. All statistical analyses was performed using SPSS 16.0 (IBM) software. A p value of less than or equal to 0.05 was considered significant.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/05/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>14/09/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Wendy H.L. Teoh</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>KK Womens and Childrens Hospital,
100 Bukit Timah Road, Singapore 229899.
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Singapore</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This trial compared the clinical performance of two supraglottic airway devices (the Ambu Aura-I and LMA Supreme) in 100 spontaneously breathing females undergoing minor surgery under general anaesthesia. Our primary outcome measure was time taken to achieve effective ventilation. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Singhealth Centralised Institutional Review Board D</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Singapore Health Services Pte Ltd,
31 Third Hospital Avenue,
#03-03 Bowyer Block C,
Singapore 168753.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/05/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CIRB 2012-256-D</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/03/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Singapore</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wendy H.L. Teoh</name>
      <address>Department of Womens Anaesthesia, 
KK Womens and Childrens Hospital,
100 Bukit Timah Road
Singapore 229899
</address>
      <phone>+65- 63941081</phone>
      <fax>+65- 62912661</fax>
      <email>teohwendy@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wendy H.L. Teoh</name>
      <address>Department of Womens Anaesthesia, 
KK Womens and Childrens Hospital,
100 Bukit Timah Road
Singapore 229899</address>
      <phone>+65- 63941081</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>teohwendy@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wendy H.L. Teoh</name>
      <address>Department of Womens Anaesthesia, 
KK Womens and Childrens Hospital,
100 Bukit Timah Road
Singapore 229899</address>
      <phone>+65- 63941081</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>teohwendy@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>