<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372499">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000485336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised trial to evaluate the effect of an education program on the physical activity of University female staff aged 50 years and over</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised trial to evaluate the effect of an education program on the physical activity of University female staff aged 50 years and over</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Physical inactivity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>After gaining informed consent, eligible participants will complete a baseline survey of their current physical activity level and wear an Actigraph accelerometer for 7 days, issued by the research assistant. Participants randomised to the intervention group will attend a one-hour workshop, held at the University of Sydney. 
The workshop will be delivered by one of the investigators (CS, AT, CC, LH or RS), who are also University academic staff members and registered Physiotherapists. Information will be given about the importance of physical activity for maximising physical and mental health and preventing disability in women and to provide information about existing opportunities to participate in and enhance physical activity participation. Speakers at the workshop will include current and retired University staff who manage to fit physical activity into their busy lives and experience the benefits. The COM-B behaviour change framework, which focuses on capability opportunity and motivation, will be used to guide the design of the intervention. Workshop materials will be made freely available at the completion of the workshop. Existing physical activity opportunities that will be referred to include the a) on-campus activities and facilities b) the Active and Healthy website, a freely-available database of physical activity opportunities for the over 50s run by the NSW Ministry of health c) the Get Healthy coaching service run by the NSW Ministry of health and d) the Global Corporate Challenge supported by the University. 
An email list and on-line discussion group will be set up for those who wish to remain in contact. Workshop participants will also be offered the use of a pedometer or internet-connected activity tracker (Fitbit) for the duration of the study (3 months), to provide motivation and feedback to increase activity levels. Participants will be re-evaluated by survey and Actigraph accelerometer 3 months after the workshop, and will be asked about their goals attained, and which additional activities and support approaches were undertaken.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomised to the control group will be allocated to a waiting list and receive access to the intervention after the 3-month follow-up period.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of people achieving an average of at least 10,000 daily steps, measured objectively with an Actigraph accelerometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Actigraph measures collected over 7 consecutive days at baseline, and 3 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) the proportion of people achieving adequate physical activity levels as recommended by national physical activity guidelines, measured using an Actigraph accelerometer; </outcome>
      <timepoint>Actigraph measures collected over 7 consecutive days at baseline, and 3 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2) the average total number of hours of physical activity per week as measured by the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ); </outcome>
      <timepoint>Participant survey at baseline, and 3 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3) change in perceived benefits of and barriers to exercise participation, as measured by the Exercise Benefits and Barriers Scale; 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participant survey at baseline, and 3 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4) physical functioning as measured by the function component of the Late Life Function and Disability Instrument (LLFDI); 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participant survey at baseline, and 3 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5) mood as measured with the positive and negative subscales of the Positive and Negative Affect Schedule (PANAS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participant survey at baseline, and 3 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible participants will be aged 50 years and over and female and be staff of The University of Sydney.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a) have insufficient English language skills to fully participate in the program;
b) have a medical condition that precludes participation in regular physical activity;
c) are already sufficiently active in accordance with the Australian Physical Activity guidelines.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>For eligible people who consent to participate in the study, a baseline assessment will be conducted. At the end of the assessment group allocation will be determined using concealed allocation. Concealed allocation will be achieved by the randomisation schedule being embedded in a secure online database (REDCap). </concealment>
    <sequence>A variable block randomisation schedule will be prepared from a computer-generated list of random numbers by a researcher not involved in the recruitment of participants in the trial. The randomisation schedule will incorporate stratification for University campus.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data analysis will be blinded, by intention-to-treat and guided by a detailed statistical analysis plan. Analysis and interpretation (also performed blinded) on the primary and key secondary outcomes will be conducted by the research team. A p-value of &lt; 0.05 will be considered statistically significant. A full Statistical Analysis Plan will be devised by the lead investigator prior to completion of recruitment.
Odds ratios will be calculated to assess the effect of group allocation on the dichotomously-scored primary outcome (proportion of people achieving 10,000 steps/ day) and secondary outcome (proportion of people achieving physical activity in accordance with national guidelines). General linear models will assess the effect of group allocation on the continuously-scored secondary outcomes (weekly hours of physical activity, function and mood), adjusting for baseline scores.
A total of 50 participants per group (i.e. 100 participants) will provide 80% power to detect 30% more people in the intervention group reaching the recommended 10,000 steps/ day than the control group. This calculation assumed a proportion of 27% compliance with the 10,000 steps/ day activity level in the control group, dropout rate of 15% and alpha of 5%. The estimates of mean proportion of people achieving 10,000 steps/ day activity level was taken from the baseline results of the University of Sydney staff participating in the Global Corporate Challenge, Analyses will be pre-planned, conducted while masked to group allocation and will use an intention-to-treat approach. Analyses will be conducted using the Stata 13 software package.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>25/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>60</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>25/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2006 - The University Of Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>1825 - Lidcombe</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>School of Public Health, The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Sydney
NSW  2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The study is being funded through a Healthy Sydney University seed funding grant.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Level 3, Margaret Telfer (K07) and Level 4 The Quadrangle (A14) L4.05 
The University of Sydney 
NSW 2006
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Faculty of Health Sciences, The University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
PO Box 170,
Lidcombe, NSW, 1825 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Healthy Sydney University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 3, Margaret Telfer (K07) and Level 4 The Quadrangle (A14) L4.05 
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006

</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This randomised waiting list controlled trial aims to test the impact of an intervention designed to enhance ongoing physical activity participation in women aged over 50.
100 female University staff aged 50 years and older will be recruited via University newsletters and websites. Exclusion criteria are limited English skills, a medical condition precluding participation in regular exercise, or currently meeting physical activity guidelines.
Upon giving informed consent participants will complete a baseline survey on physical activity knowledge, attitudes and behaviour, physical functioning and mood. Current physical activity level will be measured with an accelerometer, worn on the hip for 7 consecutive days to determine the average daily step count. 
Participants will then be randomised to attend a workshop immediately, or after 3 months. At 3 months post randomisation, similar surveys and wearing the accelerometer will be repeated.
The intervention will be a one-hour workshop to give information about the importance of physical activity for maximising physical and mental health and preventing disability in women, and to provide information about existing opportunities to participate in and enhance physical activity. 
An email list and on-line discussion group will be set up for those wishing to remain in contact. Workshop materials will be made freely available at the completion of the project, and participants will also be offered the use of a pedometer or internet-connected activity tracker (Fitbit) for the duration of the study, to provide motivation and feedback to increase activity levels.
Participants randomised to the control group will be allocated to a waiting list and receive access to the intervention after the 3-month follow-up period.
The primary outcome will be the proportion of people achieving an average of at least 10,000 daily steps, measured with an accelerometer.
The secondary outcomes will be the proportion of people achieving adequate physical activity levels as recommended by national physical activity guidelines, average total number of hours of physical activity per week, change in perceived benefits of and barriers to exercise participation, physical functioning, mood. 
Analyses will be pre-planned, conducted while masked to group allocation and will use an intention-to-treat approach.
50 participants per group (i.e. 100 participants) will provide 80% power to detect 30% more people in the intervention group reaching the recommended 10,000 steps/day than the control group. This calculation assumed a proportion of 27% compliance with the 10,000 steps/day activity level in the control group, 15% dropout rate and 5% alpha. 
This sample size is also expected to be sufficient to detect between-group differences in the order of 10-15% for the secondary outcome measures.
If shown to be effective, this study is an approach that could be implemented more broadly to increase the population health impact.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics and Research Integrity
 Margaret Telfer Building (K07)
 University of Sydney
 NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Cathie Sherrington</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61418225929</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathie.sherrington@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Cathie Sherrington</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61418225929</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathie.sherrington@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Cathie Sherrington</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61418225929</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathie.sherrington@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Cathie Sherrington</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61418225929</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathie.sherrington@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>