<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83821">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/04/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000321246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of reducing dietary salt intake on the way blood vessels work</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of modification of dietary salt intake on endothelial function in human subjects with and without the metabolic syndrome</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metabolic syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Endothelial function</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In a randomised cross-over fashion, participants will follow a reduced salt diet (6g salt/day, 100mmol Na/day) for 6 weeks and a usual salt diet (10g salt/day, 166 Na/day) for 6 weeks. The higher salt diet will be achieved by the addition of 6 tablets a day containing a small amount (10mmol sodium each) to the reduced salt diet. There will be no wash-out period between interventions. Participants will attend 2 half hour education sessions with the dietitian at Visit 1 &amp; Visit 2 during the first week of the study and will attend another 2 half hour education sessions at Visit 3 &amp; Visit 4 at week 6. Dietitian instruction will cover how to follow a reduced salt diet and participants will receive extensive education about the salt content of foods, label reading and example meal recipes to aid compliance with the diet. Compliance with diets will be measured by 24hour urinary sodium excretion at baseline, day 2, week 6, 2 days after week six and week 12. Trial managers will also collect tablets at the end of the normal salt diet periods as another measure of compliance.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a cross over study so each participant acts as their own control</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in endothelial function as measured by flow-mediated dilatation (FMD)</outcome>
      <timepoint>FMD is measured at each of the following time points: Baseline (start of the intervention), 2 days after baseline, week6, 2 days after week 6 and at week 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vascular compliance measured by pulse wave velocity (PWV) and augmentation index (AI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>PWV &amp; AI is measured at each of the following time points: Baseline (start of  the intervention), 2 days after baseline, week6, 2 days after week 6 and at week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting venous blood samples will be used to measure plasma nitrate/nitrites which will be analysed using a colorimetric assay and plasma asymmetric dimethylarginine (ADMA) will be measured using high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nitric oxide bioavilabitly will be measured at Baseline (start of the intervention), 2 days after baseline, week6, 2 days after week 6 and at week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vasoactive hormones including renin and aldosterone will be measured from blood samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>Vasoactive hormones will be measured at Baseline (start of the intervention), 2 days after baseline, week6, 2 days after week 6 and at week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood samples will be taken to measure the concentrations of (i) soluble adhesion molecules which are primarily derived from the endothelium, Inter-Cellular Adhesion Molecule 1 (ICAM-1), Vascular cell adhesion molecule 1 (VCAM-1), E &amp; P-selectin and endothelin-1 (ET-1), (ii) inflammatory markers, (iii) molecules involved in the fibrinolytic pathway; tissue plasminogen activator (tPA) &amp; Plasminogen activator inhibitor-1 (PAI-1) released from the endothelium</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood markers of endothelial function will be measured at each of the following time points: Baseline (start of  the intervention), 2 days after baseline, week6, 2 days after week 6 and at week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Weight stable individuals with systolic blood pressure between 120-139mmHg and diastolic blood pressure between 80-89mmHg. Those with and without the metabolic syndrome (defined as waist circumference &gt;94cm for men and &gt;80cm for women plus two of the following: fasting triglycerides (TG) = to or &gt; 1.7mmol/L, high density lipoprotein (HDL) cholesterol&lt;1.03 (men) or 1.29 (women), fasting glucose 5.6-6.9mmol/L) will be eligible to participate in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous cardiovascular disease, treated hypertension, significant weight loss (&gt;5% body weight) in the previous 6months, use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs, known metabolic disease such as liver or kidney disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation of treatment order will be done by a third person independant to the study. Subjects will be provided with salth tablets for the normal salt diet period. There is no placebo, therefore participants will not be blinded to the salt intervention.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation sequence will be generated using Clinstat software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The participants will not be blinded to diet intervention as they are to be educated about how to follow a reduced salt diet. Participants will be given salt tablets for the normal salt intervention so therefore will not be blinded to the intervention. Persons performing outcome measures will be blinded to treatment allocation</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>CSIRO Human Nutrition</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO) Human Nutrition PO Box 10041 Adelaide BC SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO) Human Nutrition PO Box 10041 Adelaide BC SA 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cardiovascular disease is a major disease burden, accounting for over 45% of all deaths. Obesity, and its consequences, the metabolic syndrome and type 2 diabetes increase the risk of heart disease potentially leading to early death or disability. Reducing dietary salt is a neglected, valuable intervention with the potential to reduce cardiovascular events. The primary aim of the study is to determine, in a 12 week study the effect of a reduced salt diet (6g salt/day, 100mmol Na/day) compared to a usual salt diet (10g salt/day, 166mmolNa/day) on blood vessel function, as assessed by the ultrasound measurement of blood flow in overweight people with and without the metabolic syndrome who are at increased risk of heart disease. The expected outcomes are that a lower salt intake will have a beneficial effect on the way blood vessels work and reduce an individuals risk for heart attack. The results will support moves to reduce salt in the food supply thereby reducing heart disease risk in the general community as well as in individuals at higher risk. Data from this study will provided a very strong incentive to reduce dietary salt.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CSIRO Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>CSIRO Human Nutrition
Gate 13 Kintore Avenue
Adelaide SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09/09</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jennifer Keogh</name>
      <address>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO) Human Nutrition PO Box 10041 Adelaide BC SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8907</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8303 8899</fax>
      <email>jennifer.keogh@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jennifer Keogh</name>
      <address>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (CSIRO) Human Nutrition PO Box 10041 Adelaide BC SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8907</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8303 8899</fax>
      <email>jennifer.keogh@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>