<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320787">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/11/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001004055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and safety of Methotrexate injections into the eye for inflammatory diseases of the eye.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective, Phase II , non-randomised interventional case series of the safety and efficacy of the use of intra-vitreal methotrexate in the treatment of macular oedema secondary to uveitis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>HREC 09/907H</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Visual loss due to macular oedema secondary to uveitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Single Intraviteal methotrexate injection 400mcg/0.1ml; repeated monthly as required</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Best corrected Snellan Visual Acuity at baseline (pre treatment) and at 3 monthly timepoints over a maximum of 12 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks post injection for 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Central Macular thickness as measured on OCT at baseline and at 3 monthly intervals over 12 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks post injection for 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Uveitic activity as per the Standardised Uveitis Nomenclature (SUN) criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 weeks post injection for 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i)	Over 18 years of age
(ii)	Active non-infectious intermediate, posterior or panuveitis, defined as vitreal cell, vitreal haze, inflammatory debris and/or active chorioretinal lesions of a degree for which systemic or intravitreal corticosteroid treatment is indicated that has either been unresponsive to standard treatment (including intravitreal triamcinolone) or where further local steroid treatment is relatively contraindicated (e.g. pre-existing glaucoma or steroid responder), OR
(iii)	Uveitic cystoid macular oedema in one or both eyes that has either been unresponsive to standard treatment (including intravitreal triamcinolone) or where further local steroid treatment is relatively contraindicated (e.g. pre-existing glaucoma or steroid responder) 
(iv)	Best corrected visual acuity in the affected eye(s)  = 6/12 or worse
(v)	Subjects must have signed the informed consent form</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i)	Loss of vision due to other causes (e.g. myopic macular degeneration)
(ii)	Significant macular ischaemia (as determined on Fundus Fluorescein angiography)
(iii)	Known allergies to methotrexate 
(iv)	Active ocular infection (eg. Conjunctivitis, keratitis)
(v)	Intercurrent severe disease such as septicaemia
(vi)	History of other systemic disease(s) that, in the opinion of the investigator, may render the subject at a high risk for treatment complications
(vii)	Any condition which would affect follow-up or photographic documentation (e.g. geographical, psycho-social, media opacities) 
(viii)	Unwillingness or inability to give informed consent
(ix)	Under age 18
(x)	Pregnant or lactating women
(xi)	Premenopausal women of child bearing potential not using adequate contraception. Adequate contraception includes the use of one or more of the following: surgical sterilisation (tubal ligation), hormonal sterilisation (implant, patch or oral), and double barrier methods (any double combination of: an intrauterine device (IUD), condom with spermicidal gel, diaphragm, sponge, cervical cap). Reliable contraception must be maintained throughout the study and for 30 days after methotrexate discontinuation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants would be recruited from subjects known to have active non-infectious intermediate, posterior or panuveitis; or uveitic macular oedema involving the fovea in one or both eyes. These patients will be outpatients recruited from the Ocular Immunology Clinic of the Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/11/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/11/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2011</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/09/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>32 Gisborne Street
East Melbourne,
Victoria 3002</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>32 Gisborne Street
East Melbourne,
Victoria 3002</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Centre for Eye Research, University of Melbourne</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>32 Gisborne Street
East Melbourne,
Victoria 3002</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Uveitis is a term that refers to inflammatory diseases of the eye. Uveitis accounts for about 10% of the legal blindness in developed countries such as Australia and the United States and is roughly comparable to diabetes in terms of years of visual loss.

The most severe forms of uveitis have the highest risk of vision loss. One of the common causes of vision loss in uveitis is swelling of the central retina, or macular oedema. This is due to the abnormal leakage of fluid from blood vessels within the retina as a result of uncontrolled inflammation.

Standard treatments for severe uveitis and associated complications like macular oedema include systemic medication or injections of long acting steroid into, or around the eye. Systemic treatments include steroid tablets or low doses of drugs that are also used in chemotherapy like cyclophosphamide or cyclosporine. These systemic treatments have significant associated side effects and therefore are not ideal, particularly in people who only have uveitis in one eye.

Injections of a long acting steroid (triamcinolone) directly into the eye (intra-vitreally) is another established treatment modality for some types of uveitis and blinding complications like uveitic macular oedema, particularly in those with uveitis in only one eye. However, there are known side effects of this treatment such as cataract, glaucoma, infection (endophthalmitis) and retinal detatchment. Of these, cataract and glaucoma are by far the most common and, unlike the other complications, are the direct result of the effect of triamcinolone on the eye, rather than being a complication of the injection procedure.

Although the visual loss from cataract may be reversed with cataract surgery, visual loss from glaucoma can only be halted with available treatments and not reversed. Therefore patients who have glaucoma, or are known to develop raised intraocular pressures in response to steroid treatment (such as triamcinolone), are not offered this treatment, thereby limiting the available options for the management of their uveitis and/or uveitic macular oedema.

Methotrexate is a drug that has been used in chemotherapy but also in low doses to control inflammatory diseases like rheumatoid arthritis in both adults and children. More recently, it has also been used as an injection intravitreally to treat both ocular lymphoma as well as uveitis and uveitic macular oedema.

Preliminary studies using methotrexate intravitreally as treatment for severe forms of uveitis and associated sight threatening complications like macular oedema appear promising, without the side effects known to be associated with steroid treatment such as cataract and glaucoma.

We therefore have 2 specific aims: 
Aim 1: To prospectively evaluate the efficacy of intavitreal methotrexate in the treatment of active intermediate, posterior or panuveitis
Aim 2: To prospectively evaluate the efficacy of intravitreal methotrexate in the treatment of uveitic macular oedema</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Results presented at the Melbourne Ophthalmic Alumni Meeting, Melbourne, Victoria, June 2011</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>32 Gisborne Street
East Melbourne,
Victoria 3002</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/09/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09/907H</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lyndell Lim</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Research Australia,
Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital,
Locked Bag 8,
East Melbourne,
Victoria, 8002</address>
      <phone>+613 9929 8759</phone>
      <fax>+613 9929 8030</fax>
      <email>limllp@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lyndell Lim</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Research Australia,
Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital,
Locked Bag 8,
East Melbourne,
Victoria, 8002</address>
      <phone>+613 9929 8759</phone>
      <fax>+613 9929 8030</fax>
      <email>limllp@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lyndell Lim</name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Research Australia,
Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital,
Locked Bag 8,
East Melbourne,
Victoria, 8002</address>
      <phone>+613 9929 8759</phone>
      <fax>+613 9929 8030</fax>
      <email>limllp@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Lyndell Lim </name>
      <address>Centre for Eye Research Australia, Royal Victorian Eye and Ear Hospital, Locked Bag 8, East Melbourne, Victoria, 8002</address>
      <phone>+61399298759</phone>
      <fax>+61399298030</fax>
      <email>limllp@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>