<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363814">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000291785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of exercise on hunger, antropyloroduodenal motility, and gut hormones</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of exercise on hunger, antropyloroduodenal motility, and gut hormones in healthy male volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>N/A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Physiological study to investigate the effects of exercise on hunger, antropyloroduodenal motility, and gut hormones in healthy volunteers.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions> Sixteen (BMI 19-25 kg/m2) healthy subjects, aged between 18 - 35 years, will be recruited.  All subjects will be required to be weight-stable at study entry, as determined by their self-reported weight in the preceding 3 months, and will be required to maintain their normal physical activity over the course of the study.
Each subject will be studied on three occasions, separated by at least 3 (and up to 7) days.  Each visit will be either sedentary or involve exercise on a treadmill at one of two intensities (35 and 70% VO2max) for 60 minutes, with the three interventions administered in a counter-balanced order, by administering the various procedures in different sequences.  On each occasion antropyloroduodenal motility, plasma CCK, ghrelin, GLP-1, and PYY concentrations, appetite perceptions, energy intake and energy expenditure will be measured. 
Peak aerobic capacity of each subject will be determined within a week before the start of the study using a screening treadmill test (GXT), which will be supervised by a medical doctor in the Department of Medicine.  This test involves collection of ventilatory and respirometric measurements from the subject during progressive increases in speed (0.8 km/h/2 min) while walking/running on a level treadmill.  During the GXT, subjects will be monitored with a Polar a 12-lead electrocardiogram will be performed, and blood pressure will also be monitored.  The subjects will also wear the SenseWear bands to provide a direct comparison with the VO2 max test..  During this screening test, as well as at intervals during the study, subjects will breathe through a mouthpiece equipped with a two-way valve. This protocol is well established and commonly used in exercise studies (62).  Peak oxygen consumption (VO2peak) will be measured from expired gases that are continuously sampled from a mixing-chamber and analyzed for gas flow and for oxygen (O2) and carbon dioxide (CO2) concentrations by a metabolic cart (VO2000, Medgraphics, St. Paul, MN, USA).  Heart rate will be monitored with a Polar® heart rate strap and watch. </interventions>
    <comparator>Sedentary
Participants will be required to remain lying down during the sedentary study for 60 minutes. Measurements will be made at the same time points as for the exercise interventions. On this occasion antropyloroduodenal motility, plasma CCK, ghrelin, GLP-1, and PYY concentrations, appetite perceptions, energy intake and energy expenditure will be measured. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Antropyloroduodenal motility (number of antral, duodenal and isolated pyloric pressure waves, and basal pyloric pressure)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Using a manometric assembly and catheter, antropyloroduodenal pressures will be monitored from intubation until 120 minutes.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma concentrations of gastrointestinal hormones (e.g. CCK, GLP-1, PPY, and ghrelin, and other novel gut peptides that may become of interest over the course of the study)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Gut hormone release will be assessed by enzyme linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) or radioimmuno assay (RIA) from blood samples taken at t= -15, 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90, 105, 120 &amp; 150 minutes.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Appetite ratings using a visual analogue scale (VAS) which include hunger, fullness, desire to eat, and amount of food desired to eat and macronutrient and total energy intake at the buffet meal. </outcome>
      <timepoint>VAS questionnaires are taken at t= -15, 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90, 105, 120 &amp; 150 minutes. The buffet meal will be presented at t=120 minutes and the subject will be allowed to freely consume food until comfortably full for 30 minutes (until t= 150 minutes).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vital signs (heart rate, blood pressure, and energy expenditure)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Sensewear bands will be worn to assess energy expenditure and will occur for 15 minutes upon the subjects arrival at the laboratory and during the 60-min exercise or sedentary period. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Sixteen (BMI 19-25 kg/m2) healthy subjects, aged between 18 - 35 years, will be recruited.  All subjects will be required to be weight-stable (i.e. &lt; 5 % fluctuation in their body weight) at study entry, as determined by their self-reported weight in the preceding 3 months, and will be required to maintain their normal physical activity over the course of the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>19</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Each subject will be questioned prior to the study to exclude:
-	significant GI symptoms, disease or surgery 
-	use of prescribed or non-prescribed medications (including vitamins and herbal supplements) which may affect energy metabolism, GI function, body weight or appetite (e.g. domperidone and cisapride, anticholinergic drugs (eg atropine), metoclopramide, erythromycin, hyoscine, orlistat, green tea extracts, Astragalus, St Johns Wort etc.)
-	lactose intolerance or other food allergy(s) 
-	current gallbladder or pancreatic disease
-	diabetes mellitus 
-	epilepsy
-	cardiovascular or respiratory diseases
-	any other illnesses as assessed by the investigator (including chronic illnesses not explicitly listed above)
-	high performance athletes
-	current intake of &gt; 2 standard drinks on &gt; 5 days per week
-	current smokers of cigarettes/cigars/marijuana
-	current intake of any illicit substance
-	restrained eaters (score &gt; 12 on the three factor eating questionnaire)
-	experience of claustrophobia in confined spaces
-	inability to tolerate nasoduodenal tube
-	inability to comprehend study protocol</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Volunteers are asked to visit the clinic for a 30 minute screening visit. A questionnaire is is answered by the volunteer, based on the inclusion/exclusion criteria and eligibility is determined. A signed consent form is obtained. 
Peak aerobic capacity of each subject will be determined within a week before the start of the study using a screening treadmill test (GXT).  This test involves collection of ventilatory and respirometric measurements from the subject during progressive increases in speed (0.8 km/h/2 min) while walking/running on a level treadmill.  During the GXT, subjects will be monitored with a Polar a 12-lead electrocardiogram will be performed, and blood pressure will also be monitored. 
Eligible volunteers are assigned a subject number and randomised into a treatment for each study visit, using a randomisation table created on an excel spreadsheet. Randomisation involved contacting the holder (study assistant) of the randomisation table to inform them of the next subjects details and study dates. The unblinded assistant is therefore responsible for allocating random treatment to the subject.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation table was generated using Microsoft Office Excel</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Christine Feinle-Bisset</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6 Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Road
Adelaide SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Discipline of Medicine, University of Adelaide</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 6 Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Road
Adelaide SA 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Elizabeth Wuorinen</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 6 Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Road
Adelaide SA 5000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to evaluate hunger, energy intake, antropyloroduodenal motility, and plasma concentrations of the gut hormones, ghrelin, cholecystokinin (CCK), peptide YY3-36 (PYY3-36), and glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1), in response to exercise of two intensities, 35% and 70% of peak oxygen consumption (VO2), and a no-exercise control condition, in healthy, lean young men. 
Each subject will be studied on three occasions.  Each visit will be either sedentary or involve exercise at one of two intensities (35 and 70% VO2max) for 60 minutes, with the three interventions administered in a counter-balanced order.  On each occasion antropyloroduodenal motility, plasma CCK, ghrelin, GLP-1, and PYY3-36 concentrations, appetite perceptions, energy intake and energy expenditure will be measured.  Peak aerobic capacity of each subject will be determined within a week before the start of the study using a screening treadmill test.  During this screening test, as well as at intervals during the study, subjects will breathe through a mouthpiece equipped with a two-way valve. VO2max will be measured from expired gases that are continuously sampled by a metabolic cart. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, Hanson Institute
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/03/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>130218</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/01/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine Feinle-Bisset</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine
university of Adelaide
Level 6 Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Road
Adelaide SA 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5247</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.feinle@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine Feinle-Bisset</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine
university of Adelaide
Level 6 Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Road
Adelaide SA 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5247</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.feinle@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine Feinle-Bisset</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine
university of Adelaide
Level 6 Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Road
Adelaide SA 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5247</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.feinle@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Nicole Isaacs</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine
university of Adelaide
Level 6 Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Road
Adelaide SA 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 4130</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicole.isaacs@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>