<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82739">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/05/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/08/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000397314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Multi-National Open-Label Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy of Tocilizumab versus Tocilizumab plus Non-biologic disease modifying antirheumatic drugs in Patients with Active Rheumatoid Arthritis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Multi-National Open-Label Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability and Efficacy of Tocilizumab versus Tocilizumab plus Non-biologic disease modifying antirheumatic drugs in Patients with Active Rheumatoid Arthritis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>MA21573, Issuing authority: Roche Products Pty Ltd</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Active moderate to severe Rheumatoid Arthritis (RA)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Rheumatoid arthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Tocilizumab 8mg/kg intra venously (IV), 60-minute infusion period, every 4 weeks for a total of 6 infusions</interventions>
    <comparator>Background non-biologic disease modifying antirheumatic drugs (DMARDs).
The dosing of concomitant background non-biologic DMARD therapy will be  the investigator's decision and these should be maintained at a stable dose throughout the study (from screening to Wk 24). Patients would remain on the DMARD therapy they were on, prior to study start. The group of patients who are on background DMARDs would also receive Tocilizumab 8mg/kg intra venously (IV), 60-minute infusion period, every 4 weeks for a total of 6 infusions. Some of the background DMARDs that patients might be using are: azathioprine, cyclosporine, penicillamine and hydroxychloroquine etc.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>tolerability.Tests: laboratory assessments such as Haematology, blood chemistry &amp; lipid panel. Patients will also be asked to complete quality of life questionnaires at every visit. Additionally, clinical assessments will be performed at every visit such as joint count.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be assessed at every study visit from screening, again at baseline (which is up to 28 days later), at Wk4, Wk8, Wk12, Wk16, Wk 20 and at Wk 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety will be assessed through standard adverse event (AE) reporting. Adverse events (AEs) of special interest: lipid evaluations, major adverse cardiac events, strokes, infections, neutrophil count and raised transaminases.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at every visit (Wk4, Wk8, Wk12, Wk16, Wk 20 and at Wk 24)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy which will be measured as follows:
1. the number &amp; percentage of patients achieving a clinically meaningful improvement in DAS28 (Disease activity score 28) (reduction of at least 1.2 units) at every visit and time to clinically meaningful improvement in DAS28 (Disease activity score 28)
2. number and percentage of patients achieving low disease activity (DAS28&lt;3.2) (Disease activity score 28)
3. Number and percentage of patients achieving remission (DAS28&lt;2.6) (Disease activity score 28)
4. Disease activity as measured by DAS28 (Disease activity score 28)
5.Number and percentage of patients achieving ACR (American College of Rheumatology)20, ACR(American College of Rheumatology)50, ACR(American College of Rheumatology)70 and ACR(American College of Rheumatology)90 response
6. Time to achievement of a clinically meaninful  improvement in DAS 28 (Disease activity score 28) in time to ACR(American College of Rheumatology)20, ACR(American College of Rheumatology)50, ACR(American College of Rheumatology)70 and ACR(American College of Rheumatology)90 response
7. Mean change from baseline in individual parameters of ACR (American College of Rheumatology) core data set 
8. CRP (C-reactive protein) &amp; ESR (Erythrocyte sedimentation rate)
9.Improvement in physical functioning as measured using the HAQ (Health assessment questionnaire) 
10.Improvement in SF-36 (Medical outcomes study short form health survey) score
11.Reduction in fatigue as measured using the Fatigue VAS (Visual analogue scale)
12.Change from baseline in individual parameters of ACR(American College of Rheumatology) core data set
13.Changes in physical function status at week 24 and over time as measured by the HAQ (health assessment questionnaire)
14.Proportion of patients achieving clinically meaningful HAQ (health assessment questionnaire) response, defined as an improvement of at least 0.22 units from baseline in the HAQ (health assessment questionnaire) disability index
15. Changes in patients' fatigue as assessed using the FACIT (Functional assessment of chronic illness therapy)-Fatigue score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Efficacy will be measured at every visit Wk4, Wk8, Wk12, Wk16, Wk 20 and at Wk 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.Male or non-pregnant, non-nursing female
2.&gt;/-18 years of age
3.Diagnosis of moderate to severe active RA (DAS28&gt;/-3.2) of &gt;/- 6months duration
4.Receiving treatment on an outpatient basis
5.Patients on &gt;/-1 non-biologic DMARDs at a stable dose for a period &lt;/-8 weeks prior to treatment (Day1)
6. Patients with an inadequate clinical response to a stable dose of non-biologic DMARD or anti-TNF therapy
7.If patients are receiving an oral corticosteroid, the dose must have been stable for at least 25 out of 28 days prior to treatment (Day1)
8.Able and willing to give written informed consent and comply with the requirements of the study protocol</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>N/A</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Major surgery (incl joint surgery) within 8weeks prior to screening or planned major surgery within 6months following randomisation
2.Rheumatic autoimmune disease other than RA (rheumatoid arthritis), including systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), mixed connective tissue disease (MCTD), scleroderma, polymyositis, or significant systemic involvement secondary to RA(rheumatoid arthritis) (e.g.vasculitis, pulmonary fibrosis or Felty's syndrome)
Patient with interstitial pulmonary fibrosis and still able to tolerate MTX (methotrexate) therapy are permitted
Sjorgen's Syndrome with RA (rheumatoid arthritis) is permitted
3. Functional Clas IV as defined by the ACR (American College of Rheumatology) Classification of Functional Status in RA (rheumatoid arthritis) (largely or wholly incapacitated with patient bedridden or confined to wheel chair, permitting little or no self-care)
4.Prior history of or current inflammatory joint disease other than RA (rheumatoid arthritis) (e.g. gout, reactive arthritis, psoriatic arthritis, seronegative spondyloarthropaty, Lyme disease)
5.Treatment with any investigational agent within 4weeks (or 5 half-lives of investigational agent, whichever is longer) before screening.
6.Previous treatment with any cell-depleting therapies, including investigational agents (e.g. CAMPATH, anti-CD4, anti-CD5, anti-CD3, anti-CD19 and anti-CD20)
7.Previous treatment with abatacept
8.Treatment with IV gamma globulin, plasmapheresis or Prosorba column within 6months before baseline
9.Intraarticular or parenteral corticosteroids within 6weeks prior to baseline
10.Immunization with a live/attenuated vaccine within 4weeks prior to baseline
11.Previous treatment with TCZ (Tocilizumab) (an exception to this criterion may be granted for single-dose exposure upon application to the sponsor on a case by case basis)
12.Any previous treatment with alkylating agents, such as cyclophosphamide or chlorambucil, or with total lymphoid irradiation
13.Serum creatinine &gt;142</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/07/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3065</postcode>
    <postcode>2600</postcode>
    <postcode>4870</postcode>
    <postcode>3220</postcode>
    <postcode>5041</postcode>
    <postcode>2194</postcode>
    <postcode>3168</postcode>
    <postcode>2450</postcode>
    <postcode>2217</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Austria</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Finland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Greece</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Roche Products Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>4-10 Inman Road
Dee Why
NSW 2099</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Roche Products Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>4-10 Inman Road
Dee Why
NSW 2099</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This phase IIIb study will include adult patients, 18 years or older,body weight 150kg or less, with moderate to severe active rheumatoid arthritis (RA) of duration 6 months or more, who are inadequate responders to DMARDs or anti-TNF therapies. The primary objective is to assess the safety and tolerability of tocilizumab (TCZ) monotherapy or in combination with non-biologic disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs (DMARDs). The secondary objectives is to assess the efficacy of TCZ monotherapy or in combination with non-biologic DMARDs. The study is designed so that patients would be on the study for 24 weeks, receiving 6 x 60min infusions of TCZ every 4 weeks. AEs and other safety variables will be analyzed using descriptive statistics. Safety and study data will be collected on an electronic CRF.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/05/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christelle van Niekerk</name>
      <address>4-10 Inman Road
Dee Why
NSW 2099</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9454 9368</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9982 5269</fax>
      <email>christelle.van_niekerk@roche.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christelle van Niekerk</name>
      <address>Roche Pty Ltd
4-10 Inman Road
Dee Why
NSW 2099</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9454 9368</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9982 5269</fax>
      <email>christelle.van_niekerk@roche.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christelle van Niekerk</name>
      <address>4-10 Inman Road
Dee Why
NSW 2099</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9454 9368</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9982 5269</fax>
      <email>christelle.van_niekerk@roche.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>