<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="783">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/11/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000738628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>CGMS04</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A  randomized study comparing Diamicron MR and Amaryl  once daily in people with well-controlled Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus whose current therapy includes sulphonylurea therapy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This 31 week study is a single centre, randomised parallel group comparison with a crossover of treatment at 12 weeks. The study will consist of a 6 week run-in period of a stable dose of Diamicron equivelant to the previous sulphonylurea dose.(Table 4)  Followed by a 12 week period to either Diamicron MR or Amaryl  once daily in random order. (Table 3)

During the Diamicron run-in phase and  prior to randomisation to either Diamicron MR or Amaryl, the patients will be fitted with the Minimed Continuous Glucose Monitor and instructed in the appropriate care and calibration procedure. Continuous monitoring will take place for three days. 

Prior to crossover of treatment at 12 weeks and prior to completion of the study at 28 weeks, the Continuous Glucose Monitor will be re-fitted for 3 days monitoring of interstitial glucose values.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>None</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1 To determine the number of hypoglycaemic events related to time of day e.g. nocturnal hypoglycaemia.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. To determine the number and extent of post prandial glycaemic excursions, greater than 8.0mmol/L and 10.0mmol/L</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3.To determine the incremental change of prandial glucose levels  of greater than or equal to 2.2.mmol/L.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4. To determine the number of hypoglycaemic events (i.e. a blood glucose reading of &lt;2.8mmol/L) in total over the monitoring period, either symptomatic or asymptomatic, and the number of events per patient. (a hypoglycaemic event will be defined as 3 consecutive CGMS readings ie. of 15 minutes duration below 2.8mmol/L)</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5. To determine the number of borderline hypoglycaemic events (i.e. a blood glucose â¿¥ 2.8mmol/L and &lt;3.6mmol/L) in total over the monitoring period either symptomatic or asymptomatic, and the number of events per patient. (a hypoglycaemic event will be defined as 3 consecutive CGMS readings ie. of 15 minutes duration between 2.8 and 3.6mmol/L)</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6. The average of the daily fasting blood glucose readings for 3 days prior to a study visit.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. HbA1c</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Fasting plasma glucose</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3.  Mean blood glucose levels, (2am - 4am) and (4am- 6am).</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4.  The 8am interstitial glucose level by the CGMS.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5.  Sulphonylurea levels</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients who have been informed of the study procedure and have given written informed consent. 2. Unequivocal diagnosis of Type 2 diabetes mellitus. 3. Glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA1c) 7.5%. 4. Currently regularly taking any sulphonylurea drug. May also be on one or more additional oral antidiabetic medications other than repaglinide. 5. Oral antidiabetic medication dose stable for at least 8 weeks.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Type 1 diabetes mellitus. 2. Unstable diabetes mellitus. 3. Myocardial infarction, transient ischaemic attacks or stroke in the last 6 months. 4. Symptomatic heart failure. 5. Diastolic blood pressure 100mmHg despite drug treatment. 6. Severe hepatic insufficiency. ALT 2.5 times the upper limit of the reference range. 7.  Severe renal insufficiency. Serum creatinine 135­mol/L. 8. Haemoglobinopathy or haemoglobin 10.5g/dl9. Malignant disease in the previous 10 years (except basal cell carcinoma). 10. Conditions which may affect blood glucose levels including: 11. Recent surgery (within the last 6 weeks) or surgery scheduled during the study period. 12. Systemic or generalised infections (bacterial, viral or fungal), including intercurrent illnesses in the last 6 weeks. 13. Concomitant glucocorticoid drug therapy. 14. Cushing's or Addisons disease. 15. Patients known to be immunocompromised  (e.g., lymphoma, AIDS). 16. Known hypersensitivity to glucose oxygenase, the enzyme contained in the monitor probe. 17. Concomitant insulin therapy. 18. hypersensitivity to gliclazide, glimepiride or other suphonylureas. 19. Miconazole treatment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>To ensure the investigator is blinded to the treatment allocation for each participant, the study co-ordinator will down load the data from the CGMS. Data from each participant will be downloaded at the visits but will not be anlysed until the completion of the patients participation in the trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will be randomised using a randomisation list created by a table of random numbers. 50% will be assigned to Treatment A and the other 50% will be assigned Treatment B.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sydney Diabetes Clinical Research Unit</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sydney Diabetes Clinical Research Unit, Royal North Shore Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Louise Hay</name>
      <address>Sydney Diabetes Clinical Research Unit
Royal North Shore Hospital
Level 3
Main Block
St Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99266820</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 94395181</fax>
      <email>lhay@nsccahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Louise Hay</name>
      <address>Sydney Diabetes Clinical Research Unit
Royal North Shore Hospital
Level 3
Main Block
St Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99266820</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 94395181</fax>
      <email>lhay@nsccahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>