<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369777">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000226404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparision of Intraoperative Epidural Analgesia and Intraoperative Periarticular Injection on Pain Control After Total Knee Arthroplasty</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparision of Intraoperative Epidural Analgesia (with morphine) and Intraoperative Periarticular Injection (bupivacaine, epinephrine, dexmedetomidine, magnesium sulfate, prednisolone, morphine) on  Pain Control After Total Knee Arthroplasty
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>postoperative analgesia after total knee arthroplasty</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study interventions were epidural analgesia and periarticular injection. All patients will routinely receive a combined epidural spinal anesthesia. While the patients were in sitting position, appropriate site cleaning was performed and epidural catheter was inserted through the L3-L4 or L4-L5 intervertebral disc spaces using the 18G Tuohy needle. Next, differential spinal block was applied with the 27G Quincke spinal needle through the same disc space. 15mg 0.5% bupivacaine was administered into subarachnoid space. The operation was started when the spinal block reached the suitable level. During the operation, the patients were given oxygen through the Vent mask at a rate of 2 lt /min.
In the Group I (Control group= epidural analgesia group): before wound closure, 3mg morphine sulfate + 7ml saline is administered through epidural catheter in all patients.
In the Group II (periarticular injection group): a 100 ml coctail (0.5% bupivacaine (20 ml), 1 mg/ml of epinephrine (0.6 ml), 100 microgr/ ml of dexmedetomidine (1 ml), 8.4% magnesium sulfate (4ml), 10 mg/ml prednisolone (4 ml), 10 mg/ml morphine (0.5 ml) and 69.9 ml normal saline solution) will be prepared in two 50 ml syringes. This cocktail was administered periarticular injection before wound closure.
The surgical technique and postoperative analgesia protocol were identical in both groups. The patients received patient-controlled epidural analgesia (PCEA) with 110 ml normal saline + 500 microg fentanyl + 200 mg 0.5% bupivacaine for postoperative pain management (bolus dose: 10 ml, lockout period: 20 minutes,without loading dose). All patients received epidural analgesia via the same type of PCA (Patient Controlled Analgesia) device.
The primary outcome is a visual analog scale (VAS) pain score 72 hours after surgery and analgesic consumption. The total amount of analgesics, VAS scores and discharge time was recorded. .In all patients, the epidural catheters were withdrawn at the end of the postoperative 72th hour and 12 hours after the last dose of LMWH (Low Molecular Weight Heparin).</interventions>
    <comparator>comparator / control treatment

Group I (epidural analgesia group) is the control group: receiving  3mg morphine sulfate+ 7ml saline is administered epidural before wound closure.

Group II  (periarticular injection group ): receiving a 100 ml coctail (  0.5% bupivacaine (20 ml), 1 mg/ml of epinephrine (0.6 ml), 100 microgr/ ml of dexmedetomidine (1 ml),  8.4% magnesium sulfate (4 ml), 10 mg/ml prednisolone (4 ml), 10 mg/ml morphine (0.5 ml)  and 69.9 ml normal saline solution) will be prepared in two 50 ml syringes. This cocktail was administered periarticular injection.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>whether epidural morphine or periarticular multimodal drug injection provides better pain control

The primary outcome is a visual analog scale (VAS) pain score 72 hours after surgery </outcome>
      <timepoint>72 hours post surgery
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is a analgesic consumption 72 hours after surgery  


Datas of analgesic agent consumption are assessed by review of medical records. Analgesic consumption will be calculated by the total amount of analgesic agents spent on Patient-controlled epidural analgesia (PCEA)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>72 hours post surgery  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>adverse events (itching, allergies, nausea, vomiting, urinary retention, constipation, respiratory depression, bradycardia, hypotension, dizziness i.e.)

Adverse events were recorded. If adverse events were  recognized, They were evaluated according to Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTC-AE) ver. 4.0.

This adverse events listed are assessed as recorded by treating clinician in the medical records

</outcome>
      <timepoint>72 hours post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria> Patients undergoing unilateral total knee arthroplasty as a result of osteoarthritis will be recruited.
Patients will be eligible for inclusion if they are aged greater  18 years, undergoing unilateral total knee arthroplasty as a result of primary osteoarthritis of the knee, can understand and comply with the study protocol, 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- allergy to any drugs used in this study
-  previous knee surgery
- bilateral total knee arthroplasty
- severe liver or renal insufficiency
- history of stroke or coronary heart disease
- cognitive impairment
- contraindication for regional anesthesia
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>6/01/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>128</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>80</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>3/06/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Bursa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Namik Sahin</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital
Orthopaedic Surgery
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/Bursa</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Namik Sahin</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital
Orthopaedic Surgery
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/Bursa</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Derya Karasu</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital Clinic of Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/ Bursa
Turkey</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Turkey</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>BACKGROUND: Multimodal analgesia is achieved by the combined use of analgesic agents acting on different parts of the pain pathway. Our aim is to compare effects of epidural analgesia and periarticular injection on the postoperative pain for 48 hours after total knee arthroplasty (TKA) and on the early functional outcomes.
METHODS: Eighty patients with unilateral TKA were included in this study. Patients were treated with epidural morphine in Group E (n = 40) and with periarticular injection (100 ml cocktail solutions: bupivacaine, adrenaline, dexmedetomidine, magnesium sulfate, methylprednisolone, morphine and normal saline) in Group P (n = 40). All patients received postoperative analgesia with an epidural patient-controlled device and useage of bupivacaine + fentanyl was recorded for 48 hours. The maximum range of motion (ROM), visual analog scale (VAS), dynamic visual analog scale (DVAS), and complications were assessed.
RESULTS: 24 and 27 patients were analyzed statistically in Group P and Group E, respectively. Lower VAS and DVAS scores at 48 hours, lower amount of consumed analgesics at 24th and 48th hours, higher ROM values at 2nd and 3rd day and more nausea, vomiting and itching at 12th and 24th hours were observed significantly in Group P.
CONCLUSION: Periarticular injection with multimodal drugs in TKA was found superior to epidural analgesia in our study because of lower VAS-DVAS score, less analgesic consumption, fewer side effects,  and more ROM.  

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital 
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/ Bursa
Turkey</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014/23-04</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/12/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Derya Karasu</name>
      <address>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital Clinic of Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/ Bursa</address>
      <phone>+905057281175</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drderyatopuz@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Namik Sahin</name>
      <address>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital 
Orthopaedic Surgery
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/ Bursa</address>
      <phone>+905057281175</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drderyatopuz@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Derya Karasu</name>
      <address>Bursa Yuksek Ihtisas Training and Education Hospital Clinic of Anesthesiology and Reanimation
Mimar Sinan Neighborhood/ Emniyet Street/ 16310 Yildirim/ Bursa</address>
      <phone>+905057281175</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drderyatopuz@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>