<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336741">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000529943</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A multifaceted intervention to facilitate health professional's use of evidence based medicine: an evaluator-blinded randomised controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of providing Evidence Based Medicine training with workplace supports for changing the clinical decision making skills of health professionals who work with people with Cerebral Palsy: An evaluator blinded randomised controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1121-0924</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cerebral palsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The multifaceted intervention included a 3 day workshop, and workplace supports intranet resource summarising research evidence and mentoring. The 3-day workshop used the interface of the intranet resource and real clinical examples to educate participants about how to apply research findings to their day to day work.  The first 2-days of the workshop were held on consecutive days, with day-3 of the workshop being 8-weeks later.  This enabled participants to practice skills that they learned on day-1 and day-2, and to prepare a case study to present in small groups on day-3.  The workshop part of the intervention was 8-weeks in duration.  The intranet resource synthesized the latest Cerebral Palsy research and presented using a traffic light system corresponding to evidence levels.  It also included clinical decision making tools, information about assessment and prognosis related to Cerebral Palsy.  The intranet resource was available from the day of the first workshop, and access to it was available to any employee at the Cerebral Palsy Alliance at any time.  Managers and clinical seniors provided mentoring to support the use and implementation of the intranet resource and information from the workshops.  Managers and clinical seniors attended training and preparation for this via regular meetings for one-year prior to the workshops being conducted.  This mentoring was offered to participants from the first day of the workshop.  It is ongoing, mandatory and is provided via regular sessions with each health professional.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group attended a 3-day workshop about practitioner-patient communication and coaching skills (i.e. a non-EBM educational workshop).  The mentoring provided was the same level and conditions provided for the experimental group, however the focus of the mentoring was communication and coaching.  The control group were not informed about the intranet resource directly, however as it was available on the employer's intranet service, they did have access to it.  For this reason, the intranet resource was not placed on the home page of the intranet.  After the 8-week trial period, the intranet resource was moved to a highly accessible place to ensure ease of use.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self and peer reported change in evidence-based medicine (EBM) implementation behaviour.  A panel of experts familiar with the EBM skills of study participants developed a 25-question evaluation form using the Goal Attainment Scaling (GAS)(Kiresuk &amp; Sherman, 1968). GAS is a psychometrically sound outcome measurement tool, designed to evaluate whether pre-established goals have been attained. Raw goal scores were converted to t-scores, enabling inferential statistical analysis of continuous data.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks after baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self and peer reported EBM attitudes - measured by Evidence-Based Practice Attitude Scale (subsets 3 and 4) (Aarons 2004).</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks after baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EBM knowledge - measured by open-ended questions with pre-defined answers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks after baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Qualified allied health professional
2. Currently employed by the Cerebral Palsy Alliance
3. Role providing direct client services to people with Cerebral Palsy
4. Informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Health professional without university qualifications
2. Qualified health professional who is not regularly providing direct client services (eg. manager)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All allied health professionals working for The Cerebral Palsy Alliance were invited to participate in the research study. Potential participants for the study received information packages via email.  This information package outlined the study design and aims and detailed what participation in the study would involve.  Potential participants were encouraged to email any questions that they may have had to the researchers.  At the beginning of the first day of continuing education workshops both the experimental and control groups were given the opportunity to ask additional questions about the research study.  Those who elected to enroll in the study signed a consent form and placed it in an opaque envelope. From this point, participants assigned themselves a codename and all evaluation forms were place in an opaque envelope and submitted to the investigator.  The investigator who decided whether a participant was eligible was blinded to group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Group randomisation according to geographically distinct worksites was conducted via a random number generator on MS Excel prior to enrollment of participants.  Group randomisation and randomising prior to enrolling participants was necessary for pragmatic reasons.  Group randomisation also reduced potential contamination if staff members at the same worksite were randomised to different groups.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>130</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lanie Campbell (PhD student)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>25 Oxford Street,
Rozelle NSW 2039</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lanie Campbell</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>25 Oxford Street,
Rozelle NSW 2039</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Cerebral Palsy Alliance</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 189,
Brookvale NSW 2100</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to find out if an educational package was effective or not.  The educational package was a multifaceted approach and included a 3-day workshop, a new intranet site and mentoring.  The aim was to improve the way that health professionals apply the latest research in Cerebral Palsy in their day to day work, with the ultimate goal to improve the outcomes for people with Cerebral Palsy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>National Health and Medical Research Council Human Research Ethics Committee at The Spastic Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 189,
Brookvale NSW 2100</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/05/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/05/2009</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lanie Campbell</name>
      <address>25 Oxford Street,
Rozelle NSW 2039</address>
      <phone>61 0425201694</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>campbell.lanie@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lanie Campbell</name>
      <address>25 Oxford Street,
Rozelle NSW 2039</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 0425201694</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>campbell.lanie@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lanie Campbell</name>
      <address>25 Oxford Street,
Rozelle NSW 2039</address>
      <phone>61 0425201694</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>campbell.lanie@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>