<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335902">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/08/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/08/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000715077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Motivational Interviewing Stroke Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Motivational interviews for secondary stroke prevention: A randomised clinical Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1116-7462</utrn>
    <trialacronym>MIST</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Health Research Council of New Zealand Ref. number 10/458</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Motivational interviewing (MI) is a structured, patient-focused, and cost-effective intervention designed to motivate patients to adhere to medication and life-style change recommendations. The MI group will have 4 interviews with trained research nurses. The initial interview will be in-person with patient &amp; family caregivers the day before hospital discharge. Remaining interviews will be done via telephone at 3, 6, and 9 months. Interviews will take up to 1 hr. The intervention will be standardised and sessions will be monitored via standard MI coding, with detailed instructions to guide sessions and ensure consistency across research nurses. Though this study examines the impact of MI on individuals post-stroke, recommendations for lifestyle/medication change often fail without support from significant others. Thus, caregivers will be invited to attend the initial session, but this will not be required. Caregiver attendance will be recorded.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care. Participants in the usual care group will receive standard care determined by their treating physicians, which doesnt typically include MI. In some cases, ad hoc individual therapy may address adherence/non-adherence (e.g., discussing diet with nutritionists). Participation in such therapy will be identified and recorded at follow-up assessments.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>adherence to medication and lifestyle changes recommended by treating physicians at and after hospital discharge in stroke patients 12 months post-randomisation, indicated by change in systolic blood pressure (BP) and low-density cholesterol (LDL) levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 12 months post-randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(1) to examine change in systolic BP levels at 3, 6 and 9 months follow-up, and LDL-cholesterol levels at 6 months follow-up</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 3, 6 and 9 months post-randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(2) self-reported adherence (self-reported use of anti-platelet, statin and BP lowering therapy as prescribed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 3, 6 and 9 months post-randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(3) self-reported barriers to adherence</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 3, 6 and 9 months post-randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(4) cardiovascular events (new stroke or coronary heart disease, both fatal and non-fatal). This outcome will be assessed by means of questionnaire and extraction of data from medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 3, 6 and 9 months post-randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(5)  quality of life as measured by the Short Form 36 (SF-36) questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 3, 6 and 9 months post-randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(6) change in other lipid fractions high-density cholesterol, total cholesterol, triglycerides. This outcome will be assessed by means of blood test and extraction of relevant data from medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months post-randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(7) healthcare resource consumption and cost-effectiveness. The resourse consumption will be estimated from the investigators' point of view. Costs will assessed by means of questionnaires and data from medical records (health service databases) and will include all rehabilitative and medical services, General Medical Service benefit (or other Primary Health Organisation reimbursement), private prescription charges, co-payments, costs for hospitalisations, and resource utilisation costs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after randomisation. The resource consumption will be estimated by means of questionnaire and extraction of relevant data from medical records and health services databases.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) First-ever stroke (excluding subarachnoid haemorrhage) 
(2) discharged from hospital
(3) consented to participate in the trial</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals will be excluded if they: (a) have significant impairments precluding participation (e.g., aphasia, psychiatric conditions or cognitive impairment [defined as Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) &lt;23]); (b) are unable to converse in English, which would impact assessment and intervention delivery; (c) cannot give informed consent; (e) are known to have another condition likely to impact their participation in the trial (e.g., life-threatening condition other than cardiovascular disease); (d) receiving psychiatric or clinical psychology treatment that can contaminate the study intervention; or (e) are likely to move out of the study area after discharge.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation will be concealed via an on-line Internet randomisation service.</concealment>
    <sequence>A stratified minimization randomization algorithm will be used to balance possible prognostic factors (ie, age [10 year bands], stroke severity [Barthel Index =18, &gt;18], sex, and ethnicity [European, non-European]) across the two groups.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>All analyses will use intention-to-treat principles with generalised linear mixed models allowing analyses of different types of data across several time points. The trial is 80% powered to detect a 30% relative improvement in adherence (e.g., from 50% to 65% at 1 year).</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>604</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AUT University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>AUT North Shore Campus
90 Akoranga Dr
Northcote 0627
Auckland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3
Stanley Street
Auckland 1010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Auckland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Private bag 92019
Auckland</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of this trial is to evaluate if motivational interviews (MI) promote adherence to recommended life-style changes and secondary prevention strategies to reduce stroke re-occurrence as compared with usual care. We hypothesise that community-based secondary stroke prevention via MI will effectively improve adherence to medications and life-style changes recommended by treating physicians at and after hospital discharge during the first 12 months after the initial stroke.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Region X Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>3rd Floor, Unisys Building,
650 Great South Road,
Penrose
Auckland</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/08/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Valery Feigin</name>
      <address>National Institute for Stroke &amp; Applied Neurosciences
AUT University
AUT North Shore Campus
AA254, 90 Akoranga Dr
Northcote 0627
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9166</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 921 9620</fax>
      <email>valery.feigin@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Valery Feigin</name>
      <address>National Institute for Stroke &amp; Applied Neurosciences
AUT University
AUT North Shore Campus
AA254, 90 Akoranga Dr
Northcote 0627
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9166</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 921 9620</fax>
      <email>valery.feigin@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Valery Feigin</name>
      <address>National Institute for Stroke &amp; Applied Neurosciences
AUT University
AUT North Shore Campus
AA254, 90 Akoranga Dr
Northcote 0627
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9166</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 921 9620</fax>
      <email>valery.feigin@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>