<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83250">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/10/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/02/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000104257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of bisphosphonate therapy in osteonecrosis of the hip.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to study the effectiveness of potent bisphosphonate (Zoledronic Acid) therapy in patients with early osteonecrosis of the hip.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>BONES</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>BONES Study</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>osteonecrosis of the hip</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>collapse femoral head</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomised to one of two groups, the intervention (zoledronic acid infusion) and control group (placebo infusion). Participants will have a 66% chance of being in the intervention group and a 33% chance of being in the control group. Subjects in the intervention group will be given 5mg Zoledronic acid (via infusion) annually for 3 doses, this means one dose a year for 3 years. Patients with low serum 25OH vitamin D will be supplemented before zoledronate administration.</interventions>
    <comparator>Subjects in the control group will receive a placebo injection (5mg saline solution) for a similar period.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome of this project will be the number of patients progressing to stage III or IV on the Association Research Circulation Osseous (ARCO) scale on imaging (Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)) at 12 months and with an X-ray at 36 months, including the number of patients requiring surgical intervention on the affected hip.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at 12 months and 36 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes on MRI including: size of lesion and bone oedema, measured at baseline and 12 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability evaluation, The Harris Hip Score (HHS) evaluated by the Rheumatologist or Orthopaedic surgeon, is a multidimensional observational assessment which contains eight items representing pain, walking function, activities of daily living, and range of motion of the hip joint. Final score ranges from 100 (no disability) to 0 (maximum disability). The HHS is an accepted test as it can detect small changes in hip function</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 12 months and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life. Questionnaires will be used to assess quality of life (AQoL and SF36). The AQoL consists of 5 dimensions, each of which has 3 items. The SF-36 is a short-form health survey which yields an 8-scale profile of functional health and well-being scores as well as psychometrically-based physical and mental health summary measures and a preference-based health utility index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 12 months and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse effects. Adverse effects of the treatment zoledronic acid will be obtained through open-ended questions in the questionnaire and confirmed by a checklist. A special focus will include dental side effects. All serious adverse events and pregnancies that arise during the conduct of the trial will be reported by the investigator sponsor to Novartis within 24 hours of awareness, irrespective of causality. Follow-up information related to serious adverse events and pregnancies will also be reported within 24 hours of awareness.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 12 months and 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Direct health care costs including; visits to a health care providers, prescriptions and over the counter medication, hospitalization and interventions. Data on direct health care costs including; visits to a health care providers, prescriptions and over the counter medication, hospitalization and interventions will be collected using monthly diaries. Participants will be requested to update these diaries and return when participants attend for 12, 24 and 36 monthly follow up. Participants will be required to also include data on indirect costs due to days off work or from usual activities.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>symptoms of pain and disability in at least one hip joint and/or positive MRI findings stage I or II on the ARCO classification</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous hip joint surgery on the affected hip and/or severe pain and disability at rest if treating clinician has recommended surgery and/or Radiographic or MRI findings suggestive for stage III and IV on the ARCO classification</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants who meet the eligibility criteria will be identified by their treating Rheumatologists or Orthopaedic surgeons, followed by a screening assessment conducted by the study research staff. If suitable, participants will be invited to join the study. Prior to treatment, the study research staff will perform a baseline assessment including demographic details, age, sex, duration of symptoms, medical history including prior surgery, trauma and medication use and known risk factors for osteonecrosis. Eligible participants will be allocated their treatment according to a computer-generated table of random numbers created by the study biostatistician to balance for age, sex and 2 stages of MRI severity. Treatments will then be dispensed by participating hospital pharmacies with active and placebo tablets and infusions prepared in identical packaging to maintain blinding.</concealment>
    <sequence>computer-generated table of random numbers created by the study biostatistician</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney/ Northern Clinical School</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal North Shore Hospital
Pacific Highway
St Leonards 2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Novartis</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>54 Waterloo Road
North Ryde NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Osteonecrosis of the hip is an important cause of musculoskeletal disability and finding therapeutic solutions has proven to be challenging. Osteonecrosis means death of bone which can occur from the loss of the blood supply or some other means. Although any age group may develop osteonecrosis, most patients are between 20 and 50 years old. The most common risk factor is a history of high steroid treatment for some medical condition. The next most common associated condition is a history of high alcohol use. There are some cases of osteonecrosis that occur in patients that are otherwise completely healthy with no detectable risk factors.
In the earliest stage of the disease, x-rays appear normal and the diagnosis is made using MRI. The advanced stages of osteonecrosis begin when the dead bone starts to fail mechanically through a process of microfractures of the bone. As the disease progresses, the surace begins to collapse until, finally the integrity of the joint is destroyed. A wide range of surgical treatments with variable success rates have been proposed for the treatment of the osteonecrosis to preserve joint integrity, including core decompression, whereby the venous hypertension that ensues is lessened and revascularisation may be induced leading to bone repair. Nonsurgical treatment options are limited and usually result in a poor prognosis. Early stage disease can be treated with protected weight bearing and physiotherapy, however some studies have shown protected weight bearing to be associated with a greater than 85% rate of femoral head collapse. Unfortunately most studies indicate that the risk for disease progression is greater with nonsurgical treatment than with surgical intervention. There are no esthablished pharmaceuticals for the prevention of treatment of osteonecrosis. Evidence is increasing that the nitrogen containing bisphosphonates may be beneficial in the treatment of osteonecrosis. One bisphosphonates (alendronate) has been evaluated in 60 patients diagnosed with osteonecrosis of the hip. Recent clinical studies have shown very promising results. All patients had symptomatic improvement after one year. Although the follow up time ranged from 3 months to 5 years, only 6 patients progressed to the point of needing surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Harbour Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office, Level 13, Kolling Building, Royal North Shore Hospital, Reserve Road, St Leonards, NSW, 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/10/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0806-124M</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lyn March</name>
      <address>Department of Rheumatology
Clinical Administration 7C
Royal North Shore Hospital
Reserve Road
ST LEONARDS NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9463 1890</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lyn.march@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Monique Macara</name>
      <address>Department of Rheumatology
Clinical Administration 7C
Royal North Shore Hospital
Reserve Road
ST LEONARDS NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9463 1888</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>monique.macara@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Monique Macara</name>
      <address>Department of Rheumatology
Clinical Administration 7C
Royal North Shore Hospital
Reserve Road
ST LEONARDS NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9463 1888</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>monique.macara@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lyn March</name>
      <address>Department of Rheumatology
Clinical Administration 7C
Royal North Shore Hospital
Reserve Road
ST LEONARDS NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9463 1890</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9463 1077</fax>
      <email>lyn.march@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>