<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363304">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001251819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of protein/fibre drinks on glucose control in people with type 2 diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of protein/fibre drinks on blood glucose control in people with type 2 diabetes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1137-2983</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PROGRESS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This trial aims to show that a drink containing protein and a mix of protein and soluble fibre (guar) slows starch hydrolysis and absorption of glucose. The study consists of 2 phases: acute and chronic. Acute study: Participants will attend the research centre at 9am on 5 consecutive weekdays (Mon - Fri), having fasted overnight for 12 hours. On the first test day a continuous glucose monitor will be inserted. It will remain in place for 7 full days and calibrated daily using fingerprick glucoses 4 times/day. On each test day participants will be fed a morning meal consisting of either: (i) 4 slices of white bread with no spreads; (ii) 2 slices (women) or 3 slices (men) of white bread with jam and margarine; (iii) cereal with milk. Tea or coffee with optional sugar and/milk is optional for breakfasts (ii) and (iii). All participants will have each breakfast option twice over the course of 6 consecutive days such that the final meal test will be completed at home unsupervised (food supplied). For each breakfast type (i.e. (i), (ii) or (iii)) on one of the two occasions the breakfast will be preceeded by 150ml of water (control) and on the other occasion preceeded by a 150ml drink containing 20g protein plus 5 g guar (treatment). The drink (control or treatment) will be taken 15 minutes before consuming the breakfast. As such, the 2 occasions for each breakfast type will be conducted in a crossover fashion on two consecutive days with no washout period between the treatment and control occasion for a given type of breakfast. The tests will be performed with 70 volunteers, with randomisation to the order that the treatment or control is given for each type of breakfast meal. Participants are required to keep a log of medication, physical activity and carbohydrate foods consumed during the 7 day period. However, on the last day of wearing the continuous glucose monitor (Sunday) participants can elect not to fill out logs and can eat their normal breakfast. The monitor is removed on the next day (Monday). Participants over the age of 55 will also be given the option to remain in the clinic for 3 hours post-meal on any two days (of the same type of breakfast meal) to have their blood pressure monitored using an ambulatory blood pressure monitor. Chronic study: Following on from the acute study, 140 participants will be randomised to receive the control (no shake mixture provided) or treatment (shake mixture provided) in either the first period (0-3 months) or second period (3-6 months). The treatment group only will be provided with the treatment drink (shake powder) to take home and self-administer with water on a daily basis 15 minutes before breakfast for 6 months. To ensure the shake is effective in the short term in a given participant, participants for the chronic study will first be tested on two consecutive days using breakfast option (i) above and randomised in a crossover fashion on two consecutive days (i.e. no wahout) such that they will receive the treatment (shake) or control (water) 15 minutes prior to the breakfast meal each once on one of the two days. Post-prandial blood glucose levels will once again be measured with a continuous monitor that will be worn for 48 hours. Participants may be enrolled in the acute or chronic study, or both. Participants who have already completed the acute study and shown a good response will not need to undergo the meal test for the chronic study.</interventions>
    <comparator>For the acute study (and for the meal test for the chronic study): 150 ml of water will be given as a control prior to the breakfast in place of the treatment drink. For the chronic study: participants will be randomised to receive the control (no shake mixture provided) or treatment (shake mixture provided) in either the first period (0-3 months) or second period (3-6 months).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute study: Mean reduction in post-prandial blood glucose levels (mmol) measured using a continuous glucose monitor worn by the participant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within the 24 h following morning test meal during intervention period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Chronic study: Mean reduction in HbA1c (%) measured using fasting venous blood samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 individual time points: baseline, 3 months and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean increase or decrease in systolic and diastolic blood pressure (mmHg) measured using an ambulatory blood pressure monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within the 3 hours following the breakfast meal during the intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosed with type 2 diabetes
On oral hypoglycemic medication or no medication for diabetes
HbA1c reading of &gt;7.0% within the last 6 months</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Taking insulin
Pregnant or lactating women
Previous bariatric surgery</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Both the researcher who determined if the subject was eligible for inclusion in the trial, and the subject, were not aware if the subject would be allocated to the treatment or the control on a given day (acute study) or to the treatment or control group (chronic study). Allocation was centrally performed by computer software.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Note: For the chronic study, the control and treatment groups will be run in parallel, not as a crossover.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/12/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/03/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>210</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Omniblend</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>4 - 8 Capital Link Drive
Campbellfield, VIC 3061</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Commercialisation Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5
111 Bourke St
Melbourne 
VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Baker IDI Heart &amp; Diabetes Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>75 Commercial Rd
Prahran 
VIC 3181</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to test the ability of a high protein / high soluble fibre drink to reduce the rise in blood glucose levels in people with type 2 diabetes following a high carbohydrate meal when taken 15 minutes before that meal, and subsequently show that daily supplementation of the drink can reduce blood glucose levels in the long term (3 - 6 months).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ground Floor, Linay Pavilion, 
The Alfred Hospital, 
Commercial Road,
Melbourne. 
VIC 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/12/0416</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Clifton</name>
      <address>GPO Box 664 Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61884629702</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.clifton@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Clifton</name>
      <address>GPO Box 664 Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61884629702</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.clifton@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Leah Coles</name>
      <address>Baker IDI 
Level 4
99 Commercial Rd
Prahran 3181</address>
      <phone>+61385321855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>leah.coles@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Clifton</name>
      <address>P5-16 Playford Building
University of South Australia, City East Campus
70 North Terrace, 
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61884629702</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.clifton@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>