<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370851">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000913471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of acupuncture on capillary refill time (CTR)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of performing acupuncture at specific acupoints on capillary refill time in healthy adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1183-9585</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>capillary refill time</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We will perform acupuncture on bilateral KI3, LI4 and ST36 acupoints in 60 healthy volunteers. KI3 locates on the medial aspect of the foot, posterior to the medial malleolus, in the depression between the tip of the medial malleolus and tendo calcaneus. LI4 locates on the dorsum of the hand, between the 1st and 2nd metacarpal bones, in the middle of the 2nd metacarpal bone on the radial side. ST36 locates on the anterior aspect of the lower leg, 3 cun below ST 35, one finger-breadth (middle finger) from the anterior crest of the tibia. Only one acupoint (bilateral) will be performed at one time with total two needles for each intervention, thus one subject will receive acupuncture for three times with each treatments separated at least 2 days. Needles will remain in place for 30 minutes for each intervention. Two Taiwan trained and licensed acupuncturists with a median of
15 years of experience will apply the needle. </interventions>
    <comparator>We will compare the effect of performing acupuncture between KI3, LI4 and ST36.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>capillary refill time (CRT)
It will be measured by holding a hand higher than heart-level and pressing the fingernail until it turns white, then taking note of the time needed for the color to return once pressure is released.
Two measurements will be taken for a mean to avoid bias. </outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after acupuncture intervention, and again 30 min later after removal of needle</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quantitative CRT  (Q-CRT)
We use Laser Doppler blood flow monitor (moorVMS-LDF1, Moor Instruments Ltd, United Kingdom) measure tissue perfusion, blood cell concentration, backscattered light. Then left index will be compressed by a pressure-adjustable finger cuff for 20 seconds to induce temporary ischemia and then be released. We defined Q-CRT as a time from the time of pressure release  to the time the tissue perfusion achieve the maximal level.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after acupuncture intervention, and again 30 min later after removal of needle</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>radial arterial pulse waves
A pulse spectrum analyzer (SKYLARK PDS-2010 Pulse Analysis System) will be used to measure radial arterial pulse waves of subjects. Original data will be transformed to frequency spectrum by Fourier transformation. The relative strength of each harmonic wave will be calculated</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after acupuncture intervention, and again 30 min later after removal of needle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>measure blood pressure by using digital sphygmomanometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after acupuncture intervention, and again 30 min later after removal of needle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>measure heart rate by using digital sphygmomanometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after acupuncture intervention, and again 30 min later after removal of needle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>measure core body temperature by using tympanic digital thermometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after acupuncture intervention, and again 30 min later after removal of needle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>measure oxygen saturation by using pulse oximetry</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and after acupuncture intervention, and again 30 min later after removal of needle</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>subjects scheduled for acupuncture treatment in our clinic of acupuncture department</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>subjects enrolled into other clinical trials, have infection disease or use antibiotics in recent two weeks, have impaired renal or liver function, an initial body temperature more than 38.0 degrees Celsius or less than 36.0 degrees Celsius, a known history of alcohol or substance abuse</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>We will compare the data before and after acupuncture intervention by using paired t- test, the data between the different acupoints by using t- test and ANOVA test.
In preliminary study, we measured the CRT before and after acupuncture intervention on KI3 for 3 subjects. According to the mean difference and standard deviation of difference (0.81+/-0.14), a power calculation (a = 0.05 and beta =0.2) indicated the sample size required is 3.
In our design, the total sample size is 60, and it is far more than the estimated sample size.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <state>Taoyuan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bo-Yan Yeh</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of acupuncture and traumatology, Taoyuan Chang Gung memorial Hospital, No.123, Dinghu Rd., Guishan Dist., Taoyuan City 333, Taiwan (R.O.C.)
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Taoyuan Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Chang Gung memorial Hospital, No.123, Dinghu Rd., Guishan Dist., Taoyuan City 333.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Yu-Sheng Chen</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of acupuncture and traumatology, Taoyuan Chang Gung memorial Hospital, No.123, Dinghu Rd., Guishan Dist., Taoyuan City 333, Taiwan (R.O.C.)</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Pulse examination, that reveals information about qi and blood circulation of the human body, is a very important diagnostic tool in Traditional Chinese Medicine. According to Shanghan Lun (Treatise on Cold Damage Diseases), a hard press to the bone (hence have the pulse diminish) followed by a very slight lifting to detect the presence and quickness of a re-pulsation or refilling, a manipulation called examining the root, is to evaluate the original (Shao Yin) qi. Based on clinical observation, performing acupuncture on specific acupoints could recover the root of pulse toward normal, and it is regarded working through deploying body qi to Shao Yin area to restore inner energy. Therefore, acupuncture physician would adjust qi and blood circulation depending on this thinking process. This model is reasonable, but the problem is physicians fingers lacks objective parameters to quantify the pulse.
Capillary refill time (CRT), determined by applying pressure on a finger and measuring the time until perfusion returns, is a simple bedside tool for assessing the circulation status. Prolonged CRT has been shown to be an early marker of inadequate tissue perfusion in acute circulatory shock. Interestingly, this maneuver has similar manipulation with examining the root of pulse but different on the site performed and in the parameter measured. Therefore, we designed this trial to evaluate whether acupuncture intervention could change CRT.
60 subjects will be enrolled into this trial. We measure CRT, Q-CRT, radial arterial pulse waves, blood pressure, heart rate, core body temperature, oxygen saturation before and after acupuncture intervention, and again 30 min later after removal of needle. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> Chang Gung Memorial Hospital Institutional Review Board </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Chang Gung memorial Hospital, No.123, Dinghu Rd., Guishan Dist., Taoyuan City 333, Taiwan (R.O.C.)</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>104-5687C</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bo-Yan Yeh</name>
      <address>Department of acupuncture and traumatology, Taoyuan Chang Gung memorial Hospital, No.123, Dinghu Rd., Guishan Dist., Taoyuan City 333, Taiwan (R.O.C.)
</address>
      <phone>+886-3-3196200 ext. 2613</phone>
      <fax>+886-3-3298995</fax>
      <email>cypressrock@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bo-Yan Yeh</name>
      <address>Department of acupuncture and traumatology, Taoyuan Chang Gung memorial Hospital, No.123, Dinghu Rd., Guishan Dist., Taoyuan City 333, Taiwan (R.O.C.)
</address>
      <phone>+886-3-3196200 ext. 2613</phone>
      <fax>+886-3-3298995</fax>
      <email>cypressrock@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bo-Yan Yeh</name>
      <address>Department of acupuncture and traumatology, Taoyuan Chang Gung memorial Hospital, No.123, Dinghu Rd., Guishan Dist., Taoyuan City 333, Taiwan (R.O.C.)
</address>
      <phone>+886-3-3196200 ext. 2613</phone>
      <fax>+886-3-3298995</fax>
      <email>cypressrock@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bo-Yan Yeh</name>
      <address>Department of acupuncture and traumatology, Taoyuan Chang Gung memorial Hospital, No.123, Dinghu Rd., Guishan Dist., Taoyuan City 333, Taiwan (R.O.C.)
</address>
      <phone>+886-3-3196200 ext. 2613</phone>
      <fax>+886-3-3298995</fax>
      <email>cypressrock@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>