<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368370">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000258459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Mindfulness-Based Program for Depression and Anxiety: a pilot trial of an online intervention</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Pilot Trial evaluating the impact of mindfulness-enhanced internet-delivered cognitive behavioural therapy (MEiCBT) on symptoms of depression and anxiety</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Major Depressive Disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Generalized Anxiety Disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Social Anxiety Disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Panic Disorder with or without Agoraphobia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obsessive Compulsive Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The internet-delivered Mindfulness-Based Program comprises 7 lessons completed over 14 weeks. It includes all treatment components typically seen in face-to-face cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT), as well as a number of formal and informal mindfulness exercises (including guided mindfulness meditations (provided on a CD) and written instruction for using mindfulness in daily life). One lesson will be released every 7 days (it will become available after the preceding lesson has been completed, with a minimum of 5 days between lessons), with each participant taking between one and two weeks to each lesson (14 weeks in total). Each lesson will take approximately 30-40 minutes to complete. Participants will have access to summaries of each lesson, homework exercises, extra resources, for each lesson. Participants are advised to spend at least 3-4 hours per week working through the lesson material, revisiting the content and homework tasks/ practicing the skills. Clinician guidance will be provided in the form of email or phone contact from the clinician (registered clinical psychologist) after completion of the first two lessons, then as required. The participant is able to email or phone the clinician at any point during the trial. The participant completes a measure of psychological distress before each lesson and if their scores increase by one or more standard deviations, the clinician is automatically alerted and initiates contact with the participant by phone or email. This mode of contact is dependent on what is clinically indicated in terms of the participant's distress score and or what the participant may have communicated (in the form of phone or email contact) to the clinician. The mode of contact (email or phone or both) therefore is dependent on the clinician's clinical judgement of the situation in hand.
Strategies used to improved adherence to intervention protocols and procedures for monitoring adherence include: automated email reminders, monitoring the downloading of homework, collection of data on how long participants spent reading lessons and practicing skills.</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A This is an uncontrolled pre-post study design. </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in depression symptoms (according to mean scores on the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (before Lesson 5), one week post-treatment - either one week after the participant has completed the 7 lessons (as they may have completed one lesson per week of the program) or one week after the 14 weeks, and at 3-month post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in anxiety symptoms according to mean scores on the Generalised Anxiety Disorder 7-item scale (GAD-7).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (before Lesson 5), one week post-treatment - either one week after the participant has completed the 7 lessons (as they may have completed one lesson per week of the program) or one week after the 14 weeks, and at 3-month post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in psychological distress according to mean scores on the Kessler-10 (K10).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (before Lesson 5), one week post-treatment - either one week after the participant has completed the 7 lessons (as they may have completed one lesson per week of the program) or one week after the 14 weeks, and at 3-month post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in in functional impairment and disability according to mean scores on the World Health Organisation Disability Assessment Schedule (WHODAS-II).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (before Lesson 5), one week post-treatment - either one week after the participant has completed the 7 lessons (as they may have completed one lesson per week of the program) or one week after the 14 weeks, and at 3-month post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in worry frequency according to mean scores on the Penn State Worry Questionnaire (PSWQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (before Lesson 5), one week post-treatment - either one week after the participant has completed the 7 lessons (as they may have completed one lesson per week of the program) or one week after the 14 weeks, and at 3-month post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in rumination frequency according to mean scores on the Ruminative Responses Scale (RRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (before Lesson 5), one week post-treatment - either one week after the participant has completed the 7 lessons (as they may have completed one lesson per week of the program) or one week after the 14 weeks, and at 3-month post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reductions in experiential avoidance according to the Brief Experiential Avoidance Questionnaire (BEAQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (before Lesson 5), one week post-treatment - either one week after the participant has completed the 7 lessons (as they may have completed one lesson per week of the program) or one week after the 14 weeks, and at 3-month post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in in emotion regulation according to mean scores on the Difficulties with Emotion Regulation Scale (DERS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (before Lesson 5), one week post-treatment - either one week after the participant has completed the 7 lessons (as they may have completed one lesson per week of the program) or one week after the 14 weeks, and at 3-month post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in mindfulness according to mean scores on the Five-Factor Mindfulness Questionnaire (FFMQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (before Lesson 5), one week post-treatment - either one week after the participant has completed the 7 lessons (as they may have completed one lesson per week of the program) or one week after the 14 weeks, and at 3-month post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in well-being according to mean scores on the Warwick-Edinburgh Mental Well-Being Scale (WEMWBS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (before Lesson 5), one week post-treatment - either one week after the participant has completed the 7 lessons (as they may have completed one lesson per week of the program) or one week after the 14 weeks, and at 3-month post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment Satisfaction according to the scores on the Treatment Satisfaction
Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>one week post-treatment - either one week after the participant has completed the 7 lessons (as they may have completed one lesson per week of the program) or one week after the 14 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in severity of social anxiety according to mean scores on the Mini Social Phobia Inventory (mini-SPIN). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (before Lesson 5), one week post-treatment - either one week after the participant has completed the 7 lessons (as they may have completed one lesson per week of the program) or one week after the 14 weeks, and at 3-month post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in the severity of panic disorder symptoms according to mean scores on the Panic Disorder Severity Scale (PDSS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (before Lesson 5), one week post-treatment - either one week after the participant has completed the 7 lessons (as they may have completed one lesson per week of the program) or one week after the 14 weeks, and at 3-month post-treatment (week 24)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Self-identified as suffering from depression and/or anxiety.
* Meet criteria for either Major Depressive Disprder (MDD), Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD), Social Phobia (SP), Panic Disorder (PD), Agoraphobia (AG), or Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder (OCD) according to the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview Version 5.0.0 (MINI)
* Australian resident status
* At least 18 years of age
* Access to a computer, printer, and the internet
* If taking medication, must have been taking the same dose for at least 1 month and not intend to change that dose during the course of the program.
* Prepared to provide name, phone number, and address, and to provide the name and phone number of a local general practitioner.
* Willing to provide informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Does not meet diagnostic criteria for an anxiety or depressive disorder.
- Currently experiencing severe depression symptoms (score of 23 or above on the PHQ-9).
- Regularly using illicit drugs or regularly consuming more than three standard drinks per day
- Current regular use of benzodiazepines
- Current use of atypical anti-psychotics
- Currently experiencing a psychotic mental illness or bipolar disorder
- Completed an online program for depresison and/or anxiety in the past year
- Severe symptoms of suicidal ideation (defined as responding 3 to the PHQ-9 question 9 item that assesses the frequency of suicidal ideation over the past fortnight).
-Those scoring 1 or 2 on the Patient Health Questionnaire_9 Item (PHQ-9) item 9 will require risk assessment with the responsible clinician before being admitted into the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants apply online, followed by a telephone interview to confirm diagnosis via the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview Version 5.0.0 (MINI) a structured clinical interview.</concealment>
    <sequence>This is a non-randomised study. All participants that meet criteria for entry into the study who also provide informed consent will be allocated to the intervention (MEiCBT) group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A pre-to-post-treatment improvement of effect size (ES) 1.0 is expected for the treatment group on the primary depression and anxiety measures.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>5/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>9/03/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>27</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>20/11/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria Street, Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The project aims to explore the efficacy, acceptability and feasibility of an internet-delivered mindfulness-enhanced cognitive behavioural therapy (MEiCBT) program for depression and anxiety. 

Up to 30 people with elevated depression and/or anxiety will be assigned to the active treatment group. The treatment group will commence the Mindfulness-Based Program for Depression and Anxiety immediately. 

The efficacy of the program will be determined by comparing the depression and/or anxiety symptom levels before and after treatment, and at 3 month follow-up.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Follow-up continuing, no data analysis or publication write up until after completion of follow-ups.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincent's Hospital
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/06/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/SVH/170</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/05/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression, St Vincent's Hospital, Level 4 O'Brien Centre, 390 Victoria St Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1405</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Natalie Kladnitski</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression, St Vincent's Hospital, Level 4 O'Brien Centre,  390 Victoria St Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1437</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Natalie.Kladnitski@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Natalie Kladnitski</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression, St Vincent's Hospital, Level 4 O'Brien Centre, 390 Victoria St Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1437</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Natalie.Kladnitski@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Natalie Kladnitski</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression, St Vincent's Hospital, Level 4 O'Brien Centre,  390 Victoria St Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1437</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Natalie.Kladnitski@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>