<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81952">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/04/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/04/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000199415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Cardiac Complications Of Clozapine Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Identifying Early Subtle Changes In Cardiac Function That Precede Overt Dysfunction In Schizophrenic Patients Taking Clozapine</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CCC</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Schizophrenia / schizoaffective disorder patients on clozapine medical therapy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>An ongoing observational study over clozapine treatment duration. Clozapine is used to treat patients with schizophrenia who do not respond to commonly used antipsychotic medicines. Clozapine has proved to be very effective and has been shown to reduce the high rate of suicide in these patients. While generally temporary and not life-threatening, a few side effects can be fatal. In particular, inflammation and reduced contraction (dysfunction) of the heart muscle have been documented with clozapine use. This study will attempt to identify early subtle changes in heart function that precede overt dysfunction in patients taking clozapine. Such patients displaying early signs during can then be identified and managed appropriately. The study is for the duration of the participants receiving Clozapine treatment until the treatment is ceased due to patient non-compliance, adverse effect, death, or other at the discretion of the treating physician.</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator.</comparator>
    <control />
    <interventioncode>None</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Development of echocardiographic and/or electrocardiographic abnormalities of the myocardium</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 1, 2, 3, 4, 24 and 52, and every 6 months thereafter following clozapine initiation, until treatment is ceased due to patient non-compliance, adverse effect, death, or other at the discretion of the treating physician </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in circulating marker of myocardial damage (troponin I or T)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 1, 2, 3, 4, 24 and 52, and every 6 months thereafter following clozapine initiation, until treatment is ceased due to patient non-compliance, adverse effect, death, or other at the discretion of the treating physician </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in circulating marker of myocardial stretch (NT-BNP)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 4 and 24 following clozapine initiation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation of primary outcome measures with clinical events, in particular, deterioration in clinical status or the development of asymptomatic left ventricular dysfunction, myocarditis or cardiomyopathy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 1, 2, 3, 4, 24 and 52, and every 6 months thereafter following Clozapine initiation, until treatment is ceased due to patient non-compliance, adverse effect, death, or other at the discretion of the treating physician.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients with schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder who are commencing clozapine therapy as inpatients or outpatients through the Eastern Health Adult Mental Health Program.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous history of cardiac disease including heart failure, ischemic heart disease, cardiomyopathy and hemochromatosis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Cardiology, Eastern Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Eastern Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Department of Psychiatry, Eastern Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Almost one third of patients with schizophrenia do not respond to commonly used antipsychotic medicines.  For up to 60% of these patients, the novel antipsychotic medicine clozapine can be very effective and has been shown to reduce the high rate of suicide in these patients.  While generally temporary and not life-threatening, a few side effects can be fatal.  In particular, inflammation and reduced contraction (dysfunction) of the heart muscle have been documented with clozapine use (up to 8.5% of patients).  The cause of the heart problems following clozapine use is not known, and there is a need to identify patients at greater risk of developing these side effects during treatment.      

The current study will observe about 40 adult patients each year with schizophrenia starting clozapine therapy through the Eastern Health Adult Mental Health Program.  As is standard care for this group of patients, assessments of heart function will be performed prior to, and at regular intervals from 1 to 6 months, and each 6 months thereafter, for the duration of treatment.  We hypothesise that this study will identify early subtle changes in heart function that precede overt dysfunction in patients taking clozapine.  Such patients displaying early signs during can then be identified and managed appropriately.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Adult Mental Health Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Rachel Denver</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiology
Box Hill Hospital
Level 2
Nelson Road
Box Hill VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 98954830</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 98954834</fax>
      <email>rachel.denver@boxhill.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Louise Roberts</name>
      <address>4th Floor
Clive Ward Building
16 Arnold Street
Box Hill VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 88923662</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 88923659</fax>
      <email>louise.roberts@easternhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>