<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320940">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/12/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609001080213</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of Eutectic Mixture of Lidocaine and Prilocaine (EMLA) cream as a primary dressing for painful chronic leg ulcers: A pilot study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of Eutectic Mixture of Lidocaine and Prilocaine (EMLA) cream as a primary dressing for the reduction in wound related pain associated with chronic leg ulcers: A pilot study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Reduction of pain in lower leg ulcers.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The participants will be randomized to receive EMLA 5% to their painful chronic lower leg ulcers daily as a primary dressing daily for a total of 12 weeks. The dose is 1gm per 10 sq cms. This topical cream will be applied to the wound bed by the participating community clinic nurses</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will receive receive dressings deemed appropriate by the nurse at each required clinic visit. Visits to the clinic by the control group  will be determined by the clinical presentation of the wound. Visits could be daily up to weekly.  The dressing choices will reflect usual care options and will include primary dressings such as: alginate, hydrofibre, hydrogel.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The reduction of wound related pain of chronic leg ulcers. Patients will keep a Daily Pain Diary (American geriatrics Society, 2002) for the duration of the study to record their wound-related pain and the measures taken to treat it. This diary includes the Numerical Rating Scale (NRS) which allows patients to describe the intensity of their discomfort in numbers ranging from 0 to 10 (where 0 = no pain and 10 = worst possible pain). Patients will complete the Pain Diary daily, when pain is at its best, when pain is at its worst, and when analgesics are taken.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured daily for 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The reduction of analgesic requirements.
Details of analgesic requirements include the type of analgesic, dose, frequency and their pain rating one hour after. Pain Diaries will be returned in a sealed envelope to the Nurse Practitioner/Research Assistant weekly at the patient?s clinic appointment. 
At each dressing change, the clinic nurse will assess the patient?s pain using the Wound-related Pain at Dressing Change Assessment Tool</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured daily for 12 weeeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To improve the quality of life for patients with painful chronic leg ulcers.3. Patients will be asked to complete the Cardiff Wound Impact Schedule (Price &amp; Harding 2004), a validated questionnaire to assess health-related quality of life in patients with chronic wounds of the lower limb. Sub-scales include Physical Symptoms and Daily Living; Social Life; and Well-being.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 2,4 and 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To improve the healing rates of painful chronic leg ulcers. Digital Photography - All wounds will be digitally photographed and then the wound size calculated at each time point. Clinic nurses trained in wound photography will take the photographs at the patient?s clinic visit. Photographs will be recorded using the Central Coast Community Nursing Integrated Clinical Information System (ICIS) database. ICIS includes a wound measurement tool which has the capacity to trace the wound circumference and calculate the surface area hence calculating the wound size. Assessment of wound photographs will be undertaken by a trained individual who is blinded to the subjects? group assignment.
The Leg Ulcer Measurement Tool (LUMT) (Woodbury et al 2004) is a validated tool designed to detect changes in appearance of lower extremity ulcers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 2,4,8,12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patient has one or more chronic lower leg ulcer(s) of at least 6 weeks duration and up to 100cm2 in size in total.

Patients with low to moderate wound exudate.
Numerical Rating Scale pain score = 4 at assessment and/or within the previous week.

Patients currently requiring oral analgesics due to previously reported wound-related pain. 
Patients have the capacity to consent to participation.
Patients have the capacity to attend the Community Nursing Procedure clinics.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients scheduled for leg amputation.

History of peripheral sensory neuropathy of the feet. 

Patients that have had or require the use of EMLA cream for debridement of the wound bed within the previous 4 weeks.

Patients with suspected wound malignancy or pyoderma gangrenosum, confirmed by biopsy.

Patients with diagnosed localized or spreading clinical wound infection. 

End stage palliative care patients.

Allergy to EMLA cream and/or history of local anesthetic drug sensitivity

A history of congenital or idiopathic methemoglobinemia

Patients on Class III anti-arrhythmic drugs. 

Severe hepatic disease.

Pregnant and/or lactating women.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients who meet the study inclusion criteria will be recruited from five Community Nursing Procedure clinics in the Central Coast health Service and by referral from collaborating vascular surgeons from their ulcer clinics.  Patients with chronic lower leg ulcers of varying aetiology will be eligible for enrollment eg. venous, arterial or mixed ulceration.
Allocation of treatment will be computer generated randon envelops.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated random numbers</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/01/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Northern Sydney Central Coast Health Central Coast Community Nursing Service</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Central Coast Community Nursing Service
Wyong Community Health Centre
38A Pacific Hwy
Wyong NSW 2259</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NSW Department of Health Nursing &amp; Midwifery Office</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>73 Miller St North Sydney NSW 2060.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Northern Sydney Central Coast Health Department of Primary and COmmunity Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Gosford Hospital
PO Box 361 
Gosford. NSW 2250</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aims of this study will address the following hypotheses, that: 

The daily topical application of EMLA cream to the wound bed reduces pain levels for patients with a chronic leg ulcer.
Improvement in pain levels will be associated with reduced need for oral analgesia, particularly opiates.
Topical application of EMLA cream to the wound bed decreases healing time for chronic leg ulcers
Improvement in leg ulcer pain and/or wound healing will be associated with gains in health-related quality of life. 


Hypothesis
Our hypothesis is that the daily topical application of EMLA 5% cream to the wound bed of painful chronic leg ulcers as the primary dressing, will reduce wound-related pain and analgesic requirements, and improve the quality of life for patients with painful chronic leg ulcers. The secondary outcome measure is decreased wound healing times. As the primary outcome measure is pain reduction, this study will investigate painful chronic leg ulcers of varying aetiology, including venous, arterial and/or mixed ulceration.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/11/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anne Purcell</name>
      <address>Central Coast Community Nursing Service
Wyong Community Health Center
38A Pacific Hwy
Wyong NSW 2259</address>
      <phone>+61 414192868</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>apurcell@nsccahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anne Purcell</name>
      <address>Central Coast Community Nursing Service
Wyong Community Health Center
38A Pacific Hwy
Wyong NSW 2259</address>
      <phone>+61 414192868</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>apurcell@nsccahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anne Purcell</name>
      <address>Central Coast Community Nursing Service
Wyong Community Health Center
38A Pacific Hwy
Wyong NSW 2259</address>
      <phone>+61 414192868</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>apurcell@nsccahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>