<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335002">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/01/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/01/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000063011</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A  Comparison of Liver Function After Hepatectomy in Cirrhotic Patients Between Isoflurane Inhaled and Propofol Intravenous in Anesthesia with Epidural Block</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective randomized controlled trial to compare postoperative liver functions, cytokines and complications between isoflurane inhaled and propofol intravenous anesthesia in cirrhotic patients undergoing hepatectomy for hepatic carcinoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hepatic carcinoma resection among cirrhotic patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Liver</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>a) 1-1.5 minimum alveolar concentration (MAC) of isoflurane 1.15-1.75 % , the individual patient's dose is based on the clinical variables;
b) anaesthic administered from 30 minutes before commencement of surgery until completion of surgery (100-200 minutes in total)
c) the mode of administration: inhalation via tracheal tubing.</interventions>
    <comparator>a) Target controled infusing(TCI) of propofol concentration of 3-6 ug.ml-1, the individual patient's dose is also based on the clinical variables
b) anaesthic administered from 30 minutes before commencement of surgery until completion of surgery (100-200 minutes in total)
c) the mode of administration:intravenous infusion</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative liver fuctions and hepatocyte injury defined by peak alanine-aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate-aminotransferase (AST) levels in blood analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>On operation day,postoperative day 1,3,7</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum Cytokine Tumor Necrosis Factor-a (TNFa) and Interleukin-1(IL1) levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>On operation day,postoperative day 1,3,7</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative recovery: Hospital stay and  Complications (eg. incidence rate (%) of hemorrhage,bile leak,wound infection,pleural effusion,hepatic decompensation,infective complications in each group, and postoperative complications were
assessed by  treatment-oriented complication score.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Entire Hospitalization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Elective liver resection
2. American Society of  Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status II-III patients
3. Primary liver cancer patients who had history of hepatitis B related cirrhosis 
4. undergoing combined general and epidural anesthesia</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Contradictions of epidural puncture including coagulate disorder (prothrombin time (PT) longer than 15 sec or/and blood platelets count less than 10,000)
2.Tumor size too large or small ( longitude of tumor was beyond 3-8 cm) or estimated blood loss was large than 1000 cc.
3.Individuals in whom the regional block failed and surgery was performed under general anesthesia alone were also withdrawn from the study.
4.Indivduals fail to be performed Pringers maneuver due to technologic problem.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>60 ASA physical status II–III patients who underwent hepatectomy surgery for resection the hepatic neoplasms who had history of hepatitis B related cirrhosis under combined general and epidural anesthesia were enrolled  after signed an approved informed consent. 
Sequentially-Numbered, Opaque, Sealed Envelopes (SNOSE) were used as allocation concealment method.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization was based on computer-generated codes that were maintained in opaque envelopes until the anesthesia began</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Shanghai</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Shanghai Rising-Star Program (No 08QA14007)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Shanghai Committee of Science and Technology
200 People Avenue
Shanghai,200003, China</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Shanghai Rising-Star Program (No 08QA14007)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Shanghai Committee of Science and Technology
200 People Avenue
Shanghai,200003, China</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Liver resection may require hepatic inflow occlusion (Pringles maneuver) to diminish intraoperative blood loss, thus may result in transient ischemia followed by reperfusion, which may initiate liver injury and lead to postoperative liver dysfunction. Many protective strategies against ischemia reperfusion (IR) injury in the liver have been proposed, including surgical interventions, use of pharmacologic agents, or gene therapy, however, none of these methods has found its way into routine clinical practice. Therefore, therapeutic strategies to prevent liver tissue damage after IR have become the focus of extensive research efforts.
Recently, accumulating evidence suggests volatile anesthetics can attenuate liver IR injury through a mechanism of inducing some endogenous protective molecules such as heme-oxygenase (HO) enzyme system or hypoxia induced factor (HIF) etc, which suggest volatile anesthetics concerning pharmacological pretreatment would most likely be a hopeful way to prolonger the patients endurance to hepatic IR. Unfortunately, most of isoflurane hepatoprotection evidences and related mechanisms were based on the result of animal studies, as isoflurane are most clinically used anesthetic during liver resection worldwide. 
Since Pringles maneuver are commonly applied by most of surgeons in our center which also cause an inevitable liver damage perioperatively, therefore providing us an ideal clinic model of hepatic IR injury. In order to test our hypothesis that using volatile anesthetics isoflurane can attenuate live IR injury rather than intravenous propofol in hepatectomy patients. We designed this clinical randomized comparative study to observer hepatectomy patients postoperative outcome especially liver function recovery when they received isofluare inhaled anesthesia or propofol injection respectively. We also compared serum proinflammatory factor and liver histiopathologic changes between 2 groups.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Review Board of the 3rd affiliated hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>225 #  Changhai Road
the 3rd affiliated hospital,
the Second Military Medical University,
Shanghai,200438,China</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/10/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ZD2008008-Y1</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/08/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof. Wei-feng Yu M.D. Ph.D.</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia &amp; Intensive Care
the 3rd Affiliated Hospital
the 2nd Military Medical University
225# Shanghai Road,
Shanghai,200438,China</address>
      <phone>+8621-81875231</phone>
      <fax>+8621-81875231</fax>
      <email>ywf808@sohu.com</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Liqun Yang M.D.</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia &amp; Intensive Care
the 3rd Affiliated Hospital
the 2nd Military Medical University
225# Shanghai Road,
Shanghai,200438,China</address>
      <phone>+8621-81875235</phone>
      <fax>+8621-81875231</fax>
      <email>lqyang72721@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Liqun Yang M.D.</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia &amp; Intensive Care
the 3rd Affiliated Hospital
the 2nd Military Medical University
225# Shanghai Road,
Shanghai,200438,China</address>
      <phone>+8621-81875231</phone>
      <fax>+8621-81875231</fax>
      <email>lqyang72721@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>