<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364419">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000884707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Optimising rehabilitation outcomes in frail older adults: effects of increasing the amount of physical activity</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does increasing the amount of physical activity in frail older adults during hospital-based rehabilitation improve mobility outcomes when compared to usual care.  </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1144-5714 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>THE MOVE TRIAL</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Frailty</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In addition to usual care provided by a multidisciplinary rehabilitation team, the intervention group will receive a protocol-specified intervention focused on increasing the amount of time spent standing and walking. This will be delivered as extra sessions on weekdays (1-2 sessions per day, approximate total 30 mins) and weekend days (1-2 sessions, approximate total 45 mins) for the duration of their rehabilitation stay. The intervention will be provided by a trial physiotherapist and or allied health assistant and tailored for each participant. Intervention adherence will be monitored using staff recordings of the amount of time participants spend performing various activities during each session.   Lightweight wristwatch-sized accelerometers will be used to monitor activity of each participant over a 5 day period during their rehabilitation admission.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive usual care, provided by a multidisciplinary team (including physiotherapy, occupational therapy, medical, nursing and other allied health input as indicated).  In addition, to control for the extra physical activity that the experimental group receives, participants in the control group shall have additional social and recreational activities according to their interests, as well as upper limb exercises that have minimal impact on mobility. These will be undertaken with the participant either sitting in a chair or resting in bed. Overall extra contact time will be matched for intervention and control groups. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility - Gait Speed measured with the 6 metre walk test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge from inpatient rehabilitation.    </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility - Functional Gait Speed measured with the Timed Up and Go Test (TUG).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Admission, Discharge and at 6 months post discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility - Functional Mobility measured with the De Morton Mobility Index (DEMMI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Admission, Discharge and at 6 months post discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional Level - measured using the Mobility and Locomotion subsections of the FIM (Functional Independence Measure).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Admission, Discharge and at 6 months post discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life - measured using the EuroQol Health Questionnaire (EQ5D) and the EQ-Visual Analogue Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Admission, Discharge and at 6 months post discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls - measured using a monthly calendar during the 6 month period from discharge to follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge - 6 months post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility - Gait Speed measured with the 6 metre walk test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All adverse events during the intervention and 6 month follow-up periods. These include falls, unplanned re-admission to an acute service during rehabilitation or within 6 months post discharge and mortality. Falls will be defined using the WHO 2011 definition. Falls during the intervention period (i.e. during hospitalisation) will be obtained from hospital records of falls.  Falls post discharge will be obtained via falls calendars.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Admission - 6 months post discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness and cost utility
The main output of interest is incremental cost-effectiveness ratios in terms of net costs per unit of health gain. Net costs will comprise the costs of enhanced physical activity program minus costs saved from the reduction in downstream health services utilization. Health gains can be measured in a variety of ways. For the current study, in addition to clinical outcomes, we shall estimate years of life gained and quality-adjusted life years (QALYs) gained. Both shall be enabled by the collection of time-to-outcome data and the latter also by collection of the EuroQoL Quality of Life data. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 month post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i) over 60 years of age
(ii) a goal of admission is to improve weight-bearing mobility or improve walking as determined by either the admission referral or the treating therapist.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) specific medical restrictions that limit mobilisation (e.g. non weight bearing)
(ii) already enrolled in a different RCT
(iii) primary reason for admission is to await a residential care placement
(iv) previously enrolled in the current trial
(v) primary reason for admission is for carer training</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited from rehabilitation and Geriatric Evaluation and Management wards. Consent will be obtained from the participant or next of kin if the participant is unable to give consent due to cognitive impairment, within 48 hours of admission to the ward.

Participants will be individually randomised to an intervention group (enhanced physical activity) or a control group (usual care) according to a computer generated randomisation procedure performed by a third party.  Randomisiation will occur after baseline assessment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be stratified by functional level (ambulant/ non ambulant) and site.  A randomisation table will be created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Baseline data will be examined to ensure that the control group and the intervention group are comparable using descriptive statistics. Between group differences in terms of the primary outcome variable (gait speed) will be assessed using a 0.05 level of significance. 
Pilot data has shown the median gait speed of people discharged from rehabilitation is .46 m/s, sd = .18m/sec.  Sample size estimation was based on the intervention group acheiving an increase of .1m/sec, which has been previously reported to be the  minimally clinically important difference for gait speed in older adults. Assuming two groups of equal size and using the conventional settings of two tailed significance threshold alpha of .05 and power to yield a statistically significant result of 90%, a sample size of 69 people in each group is required. Allowing for 14% of participants to be unable to complete the walk test on discharge, and a 25% dropout, an estimated total of 198 participants are required.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/01/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/04/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>198</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>198</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital - Heidelberg West</hospital>
    <hospital>Kingston Centre - Cheltenham</hospital>
    <postcode>3081 - Heidelberg Rgh</postcode>
    <postcode>3192 - Cheltenham</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>La Trobe University
Melbourne Victoria 3086
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council
Project Grant - ID1042680</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital, Austin Health, PO Box 5444, Heidelberg West, VIC 3081</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The Kingston Centre</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The Kingston Centre, Southern Health, Warrigal Road, Cheltenham, VIC 3192</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main aim of this study is to investigate whether increasing the amount of physical activity results in better
mobility outcomes in frail, older people. This study will be performed during hospital based rehabilitation and will be
compared to mobility outcomes resulting from usual care. A second aim is to investigate whether this physical activity intervention results in improvements in quality of life. Finally we plan to investigate whether increasing the
amount of physical activity during rehabilitation is cost effective.
Participants will be recruited from two Victorian hospitals which offer inpatient rehabilitation to older adults. Older
people receiving inpatient rehabilitation will be randomly assigned to an intervention group or a control group. The
intervention group will receive extra physical activity on weekdays and weekends while the control group will receive
additional social interaction. Both groups will be assessed at baseline, discharge from hospital and at 6 months.
The primary outcome for this study is gait speed, as measured by the 6 metre walk test. Other outcomes relating to mobility, function and quality of life will also be assessed. At the end of the study a health economic analysis will be performed to assess whether the extra physical activity provided was cost effective, all factors considered.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>La Trobe University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Secretary, La Trobe University Human Ethics Committee Research and Graduate Studies Office Level 2, 
David Myers Building 
La Trobe University 
BUNDOORA VIC 3086
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12-122</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress> Research Ethics
    Office for Research
    Level 6 HSB Austin Health
    PO Box 5555
    Heidelberg
    Victoria
    Australia, 3084

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H2013/05042</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health Human Research Ethics Committee B</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Directorate 
Level 4, Main Block, 
Monash Medical Centre 
246 Clayton Road 
CLAYTON VIC 3168
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Melbourne Behavioural &amp; Social Sciences Human Ethics SubCommittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Melbourne Research Office 
The University of Melbourne 
MELBOURNE VIC 3010
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University of Technology Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research and Development
Curtin University 
GPO Box U 1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Meg Morris</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health
Faculty of Health Sciences
La Trobe University
Bundoora
Victoria, 3086.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94796080</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9479 5768</fax>
      <email>m.morris@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joanne Wittwer</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Faculty of Health Sciences
La Trobe University
Bundoora
Victoria, 3086.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94795808</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>J.Wittwer@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cathy Said</name>
      <address>Austin Health, 
PO Box 5444, 
Heidelberg West, 
VIC 3081</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 2055</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathy.said@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joanne Wittwer</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Faculty of Health Sciences
La Trobe University
Victoria, 3086.</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94795808</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>J.Wittwer@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>