<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363079">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001036808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The impact of energy or traffic light labelling on parent and
child fast food selection</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An investigation into the impact of energy or traffic light labelling on parent and child fast food selection as measured by intentional energy purchases from hypothetical fast food menus</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Child and adult intended energy consumption</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study protocol required participants to complete two scripted telephone surveys conducted by a trained research assistant. A baseline survey conducted during June and July 2011 collected demographic and health behaviour data from parents and a child aged three to 12 years in their household.  Where parents had more than one child from age three to 12, the child with the most recent birthday was selected. Following completion of the baseline survey, participants were randomly allocated to one of three groups using a random number function embedded in the computer assisted telephone interviewing  software in a 1:1:1 ratio without stratification. Based on group allocation, participants in this study were posted one of three hypothetical fast food menus. Menus were comprised of items selected from a variety of common fast food outlets in Australia. Generic descriptive names were provided for each food item to reduce any pre-conceived beliefs about existing branded fast food products. Groups were as follows

Group 1. Standard fast food menu (control). All items in this menu were included in subsequent menus. The standard menu contained 36 food and beverage items, including healthier options.

Group 2. Standard menu with energy labelling. This menu was identical to that provided to Group 1, with the addition of energy content information being displayed next to each menu item. Energy content was displayed in kilojoules (kJ). 

Group 3. Standard menu with traffic light (sign-post) labelling. The menu items were identical to that provided to Groups 1 and 2, with the addition of a single coloured symbol (traffic light) placed next to each menu item. The single coloured symbol of red, amber, or green reflected the saturated fat, sugar, salt and energy content of each menu product adapted from criteria developed for school canteens in Australia

Energy content, volume measures and pricing were sourced from the Australian websites of fast food outlets from which the menu items had been sourced.

Participants answered a series of questions about these menus in the follow up survey, which was conducted on average 17 days after the completion of the baseline survey. The follow up interview contained questions about purchase intentions, awareness of labelling information and attitudes towards fast foods.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group recieved a standard fast food menu. All items in this menu were included in menus for other groups. The standard menu contained 36 food and beverage items, including healthier options. All menu items were grouped into three categories: beverages, main menu items and dessert items. Menu items as well as a description of the items ingredients were presented in a standard order on each menu. 

The menu included volume measures for beverages (millilitres) and unit price sourced from existing fast food chain websites. This menu did not contain information regarding energy content, or any other indication of the nutritional value of each product.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total energy of intended purchase</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calculated based on responses to follow-up telephone interview</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Awareness and use of labelling information. This was assessed by asking participants whether they noticed any nutritional information on the menu, and if so, whether this information influenced their purchase for themselves, or for their children.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calculated based on responses to follow-up telephone interview</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>English speaking parents of children aged between three and 12 years residing in the Hunter New England region of New South Wales, Australia, were eligible for participation in the current study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants were recruited from an existing research cohort of parents established as part of a random household child health telephone survey. A research assistant telephoned randomly selected parents from the research cohort, assessed eligibility and invited study participation. They subsequently completed the baseline survey.

Following completion of the baseline survey, participants were randomly allocated to one of three groups. Participants were unaware of their group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants were randomly allocated to one of three groups using a random number function embedded in the computer assisted telephone interviewing  software in a 1:1:1 ratio without stratification</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>294</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Pennie Gibbins</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>c/o HNEPH
Locked Bag 10
WALLSEND NSW 2287</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Newcastle</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Hunter New England Population Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Locked Bag 10
WALLSEND NSW 2287</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Luke Wolfenden</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>c/o HNEPH
Locked Bag 10
WALLSEND NSW 2287</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Kathy Chapman</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 572
Kings Cross NSW 1340</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Clare Hughes</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 572
Kings Cross NSW 1340</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Lyndal Wellard</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 572
Kings Cross NSW 1340</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Labelling of food from fast food restaurants has been suggested as one strategy to reduce energy consumption and contribute to reductions in population obesity prevalence. The aim of this study was to examine the effects of two different types of menu labelling techniques (energy and traffic light labelling) on the intended food purchases of children and adults. We are unaware of any past research that directly compares these menu labelling techniques, so our purpose was to determine whether people ordered foods with less total energy content when given a menu with either energy or traffic light labels.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag No. 1
New Lambton NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/09/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06/07/26/4.04</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pennie Dodds</name>
      <address>c/o Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
WALLSEND NSW 2287</address>
      <phone>+612 49246235</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pennie.dodds@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pennie Dodds</name>
      <address>c/o Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
WALLSEND NSW 2287</address>
      <phone>+612 49246235</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pennie.dodds@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Pennie Dodds</name>
      <address>c/o Hunter New England Population Health
Locked Bag 10
WALLSEND NSW 2287</address>
      <phone>+612 49246235</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pennie.dodds@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>