<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365928">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000388617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Rhinovirus Study : A bedroom heating intervention to reduce rhinovirus infection in children.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised placebo controlled trial of the effect of heating children's bedrooms for an 8-week period over the colder months of the year on preventing rhinovirus caused colds and reducing symptom severity as measured by parental reported cold symptoms and nasal swabs for determining levels of rhinovirus in the nose.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U111-1136-4538</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prevention of rhinovirus cold infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants are randomly assigned to one of two different interventions - either a 10 minute ultraviolet light (UV) treatment of the walls and surfaces of the childs bedroom; or a heater is placed in the childs bedroom for an 8-week period (in April to November), and set to come on at night time to keep the ambient air temperature at 18-22 degrees C.  The heaters have thermostat control.</interventions>
    <comparator>The UV light intervention group will act as the placebo control for this RCT because although UV light is a valid method for denaturing viruses and rendering them non-infectious, it is unlikely that the one time application of this treatment at the beginning of the 8 week study period will effectively prevent exposure to viruses in a child's bedroom throughout the entire 8 week study duration. We will therefore disregard the first week's cold symptom data and use data from the second week onwards to act as the control data for this study. We therefore consider the UV group a sham treatment group (placebo) and it will act as the control group for this study. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in cold symptoms as recorded in cold symptom diaries in the heating intervention group compared to the placebo group. The parent or guardian will fill in the cold symptom diaries for the child participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Symptom diaries are collected for 8 weeks from the first visit. The first week of data will be discarded during data analysis, and the subsequent 7 weeks of data will be used to give an average cold symptom score per day. We will compare the mean of the average cold symptom scores per day in the intervention group and the control group. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fewer rhinovirus positive nasal swabs in the heating group compared to the placebo group in the swab taken at the end of the 8 week intervention period. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Nasal swabs will be taken at the beginning and the end of the 8 week intervention period from all participants. Parents will also swab their children's noses when they exhibit symptoms of a cold. One swab will be taken per cold but if the cold lasts more than seven days, another swab will be taken at the start of the next seven days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lower rhinovirus levels in nasal swabs in the heating group compared to the UV (placebo) group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nasal swabs will be taken at the beginning and the end of the 8 week intervention period from all participants. Parents will also swab their children's noses when they exhibit symptoms of a cold. One swab will be taken per cold but if the cold lasts more than seven days, another swab will be taken at the start of the next seven days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>At least one cold infection reported in the previous 12 months.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>5</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Child lives in more than one house. Child regularly sleeps more than 1 full night per week or more than 2 hours per night) in more than one bedroom. Child's bedroom is heated to 20C for more than 12 hours per day.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Our previous HRC programme He Kainga Oranga/ Community Housing and Health Intervention Research Programme HOME Study examined the influence of housing factors and visible household mould on the development of first onset wheezing. We are approaching this group of participants again to see if they are interested in participating in the Rhinovirus Study. We aim to recruit 300 children in total. If we are not able to achieve this number from the HOME Study invitees, we will recruit the additional participants from the community. After screening the participant and determining that they are eligible, the researcher will assign them to either the heating or UV (placebo) intervention groups using a computer generated randomisation programme. The researchers do not know in advance which group the participant will be assigned to, so in this way, allocation to the study groups is concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Sequence generation will occur by using a randomisation table created by computer software and applied at the time of enrolment.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Power, sampling and analysis: The primary outcome will be the total cold symptom score from the childs symptom diary, excluding week 1. As the symptom scores are  recorded daily per child, a generalised hierarchical linear model, will be used to allow for repeated measures in the data. The primary analysis will therefore be the effect of assignment to the intervention group from hierarchical linear model with total cold symptoms per day as the outcome and each child as a repeated measure with an adjustment for season. 

Power: Assuming that the mean of childrens mean symptoms score will reduced by 0.75 and that the standard deviation of the children mean symptom score will be 2 after adjusting for season, the study will have 80% power.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>10/06/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/10/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>20/08/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Julian Crane</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Medicine and Health Sciences
University of Otago Wellington
23a Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington
New Zealand 6021</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council (NZ)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3, Pro CARE Building, Grafton Mews
110 Stanley Street
Auckland 1010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a randomised control trial (RCT) to investigate whether heating the ambient air in children's bedrooms to at least 18C overnight for an eight week period during the colder months of the year will significantly reduce the number cold symptoms they get due to rhinovirus infection compared to the number of cold symptoms experienced by children in the placebo group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No.1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Julian Crane</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Wellington
23a Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+6449185258</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julian.crane@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Julian Crane</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Wellington
23a Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+6449185258</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julian.crane@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Julian Crane</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Wellington
23a Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+6449185258</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julian.crane@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>