<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364218">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000569707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>In Vivo Arthroscopic Temperatures: Comparison between Two Types of Radiofrequency Ablation Systems</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In individuals undergoing shoulder, hip and knee arthroscopy, how does the use of ArthroCare 'Coblation technology' ablation system compare to the regular diathermy ablation system effect in the intra-articular fluid temperatures during arthroscopy?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Australia Online Forms for Research AU/1/F58217</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Shoulder Arthroscopy
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Rotator cuff injury
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Subacromial impingement/bursitis
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>acromioclavicular joint osteoarthritis
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>shoulder instability/labral tear</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Knee Arthrosopcy
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>ACL injury
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hip arthroscopy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Femoral Acetabular impingement and labral tear</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>One group will comprise of patients undergoing arthroscopy using the ArthroCare ablation system ('Coblation') which uses radiofrequency energy to excite electrodes in the surrounding saline solution to produce a charged plasma gas that breaks down molecular bonds in tissue. Coblation system uses radiofrequency that range from 100-500 kHz. The duration of the surgery is very variable depending on the type of surgery and severity of condition.</interventions>
    <comparator>This group will comprise of patients undergoing arthroscopy using the Stryker ablation system which uses radiofrequency energy to create heat at the tip of the wand to ablate the targeted tissue. The radiofrequency output waveform is set at 200kHz. Again, the duration of surgery is highly variable.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intra-articular fluid temperature</outcome>
      <timepoint>During arthroscopic surgery:
 - measurements will be recorded intra-operatively via use of independent sterile temperature probe</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of surgery</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calculated intra-operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Clinically indicated for shoulder arthrosopcy:
- rotator cuff repair
- sub-acromial decompression, acromioplasty
- acromioclavicular joint excision
- shoulder stabilisation or labral repair
2) Clinically indicated for knee arthroscopy
- ACL reconstruction
3) Hip arhtroscopy for femoral acetabular impingement</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>&lt;18 years of age
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be identified from those referred to participating orthopaedic surgeons for treatment of their knee or shoulder condition as per the inclusion criteria. Participants will be give a verbal and written explanation of the trial and written informed consent will be obtained. Participants will be randomised to the two groups.</concealment>
    <sequence>Online random number generator. Blinded allocation. Concealment will be achieved via central randomisation computer.</sequence>
    <masking />
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Mater Hospital Pimlico - Pimlico</hospital>
    <postcode>4812 - Pimlico</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>ORIQL (Orthopaedic Research Institute of Queensland)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suite 3 Level 2
Mater Medical Centre
21-29 Fulham Rd 
Pimlico 4812 Qld</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Orthopaedic Research Institute (ORIQL)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 3 Level 2
Mater Medical Centre
21-29 Fulham Rd 
Pimlico 4812 Qld</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Radiofrequency ablation is a commonly utilized tool in arthroscopic orthopaedic surgery primarily in joints such as shoulders and knees. It allows accurate debridement of soft tissues and control of bleeding.  Use of radiofrequency ablation wands produces heat either directly or as a by-product. Studies have shown that if these temperatures exceed a certain threshold, (commonly known to be 45 degrees Celcius), the risk of injury to surrounding tissues within the joint is increases. We will be comparing two types of radiofrequency ablation systems that are very widely used today in arthroscopic surgery. One system, such as the Striker SERFAS Energy probe, uses radiofrequency energy to generate heat at the tip of the instrument. This heat is used to ablate or remove unwanted or damaged tissues and may also be used to coagulate vessels to control bleeding. The other system, such as that used in the Arthrocare RF wands, uses 'coblation' technology. This technology differs in that it uses radiofrequency energy to produce a controlled non-heat driven process where it excites electrodes within the surrounding saline solution to create a charged plasma gas that breaks up molecular bonds within tissue. Heat in this system, is produced as a by-product, and as claimed by its manufacturers, at much lower temperatures.

In this study we will be comparing the temperatures established in arthroscopic surgery to determine the risk of injury to surrounding tissues using both these two systems. We will be recruiting 80 patients undergoing arthroscopic knee or shoulder surgery for a variety of conditions. The patients will be randomised to the ablation system and temperatures will be continuously monitored and recorded using an independent digital temperature probe. The probe will be placed in the same location within the joint in all patients through a small key-hole incision. The duration of surgery will also be recorded. Many variable can affect the fluid temperatures and these incluced, baseline infused fluid temperature, flow rate, and number of ports. We will not be regulating these variables in order to create a more natural clinical scenario which will in turn produce results that are more relevant to the common orthopaedic surgeon. 

Results will be analysed to determine the average and maximum temperatures reached in both systems, and in different types of surgeries (e.g. rotator cuff repair, sub-acromial decompression and acromioplasty, and stabilisation in shoulders, and ACL reconstruction in knees). Statistical analyses will be used to determine if there are any statistically significant differences in results using the two types of ablation systems and whether in fact using the Arthrocare charged plasma 'coblation' process will produce lower and potentially safer temperatures.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Hospital Townsville Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mater Hospital Townsville
21-37 Fulham Rd 
Pimlico QLD 4810</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MHS20130806-02</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Wilkinson</name>
      <address>The Orthopaedic Research Institute of Queensland Suite 3 Level 2 Mater Medical Centre 21-29 Fulham Rd Pimlico 4812 Qld</address>
      <phone>+61747553564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>research_coordinator@oriql.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrea Grant</name>
      <address>The Orthopaedic Research Institute of Queensland Suite 3 Level 2 Mater Medical Centre 21-29 Fulham Rd Pimlico 4812 Qld</address>
      <phone>+61413685331</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>research_coordinator@oriql.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Wilkinson</name>
      <address>The Orthopaedic Research Institute of Queensland Suite 3 Level 2 Mater Medical Centre 21-29 Fulham Rd Pimlico 4812 Qld</address>
      <phone>+61747799902</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>research_coordinator@oriql.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Andrea Grant</name>
      <address>The Orthopaedic Research Institute of Queensland Suite 3 Level 2 Mater Medical Centre 21-29 Fulham Rd Pimlico 4812 Qld</address>
      <phone>+61747553564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>research_coordinator@oriql.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>