<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82598">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/02/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/02/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000082303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Doxorubicin Transdrug® in Advanced Hepatocellular Carcinoma.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the efficacy and tolerance of Hepatic Intrarterial-Injection of Doxorubicin Transdrug® in Advanced Hepatocellular Carcinoma, to that of standard care. A Randomized, Multicentre Phase 2-3 Study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DOTAHCC1</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>HepatoCellular Carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Liver</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Hepatic Intrarterial-Injection of Doxorubicin Transdrug® at 30mg/m2. 3 courses, one course every 28 days.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment
This includes Embolisation, Transarterial Chemoembolisation (TACE), Hepatic Intra-Arterial chemotherapy with or without Lipiodol®, Lipiocis®, Intravenous Chemotherapy and best supportive care (pain and symptoms management). Each hospital has their own procedures for each of these treatments, however, typically you will receive the treatment on one day and have a follow-up visit 4-6 weeks later. Treatment may then need to be repeated depending on disease progression.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of patients free of local progression at 3 months after randomisation (treatment group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of patients free of local progression at 3 months after randomisation (control group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison between the treated and control groups: progression free survival, overall survival, objective response rate, tolerance and quality of life</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every three months for 12 months and survivial until death.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the pharmacokinetic profile of Doxorubicin Transdrug.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Detemrined at the end of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC); Multinodular hepatocellular carcinoma more than one lesion) regardless of the number of lesions, but involves less than 50% of the liver mass; Child-Pugh score A (assessment of the prognosis of chronic liver disease, mainly cirrhosis); Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) greater than or equal to 50% as determined by echocardiography/cardiac ultrasound (the amount of blood pumped out of a ventricle with each heart beat); Adequate pulmonary function; Platelets greater than or equal to 75 x 109L; Absolute neutrophil count (white blood cells)greater than or equal to 1,0 x 109L; Aspartate transaminase (AST) and/or Alanine transaminase (ALT) less than or equal to  5 times upper limit of normal (liver enzymes, determine the health of the liver); Prothrombin time ratio greater than 60% and Factor V greater than 60% (measure of blood clotting ability).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Blood clots in the main blood vessels of the liver;
Risk for oesophageal bleeding; 
Hepatocellular carcinoma developed on transplanted liver;
Presence of extra-hepatic metastases (cancer outside liver);
Patients able to benefit from hepatic transplantation, surgical resection, pure alcogol injection into tumour or radiofrequency ablation (tumour mass is heated by radiofrequency to a point where the cells die); 
Patient having undergone a 450 mg/m² cumulated dose of doxorubicin; 
Prior chemotherapy, transarterial chemoembolisation (TACE), embolisation, radiation therapy for hepatocellular carcinoma regardless of the time elapsed before the enrolment; 
Patients who have benefited from surgical resection or percutaneous  (alcohol and/or radiofrequency) treatment in the month preceding the enrolment; 
Patients currently being treated with immunosuppressor agent (medication to suppress the immune system) and/or an anticoagulant (medication to thin your blood) that cannot be stopped; 
Presence of cardiac abnormalities; 
Patient with a life expectancy of less than 3 months;
Pregnant or breast-feeding women; Patients with mental deficiency preventing proper understanding of trial protocol requirements.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients who meet the inclusion/exclusion criteria can be randomised into the trial.  The Investigator connects to the International Drug Development Institute web-based randomization tool to randomize the patient. Patients will be centrally randomised into two treatment groups with a ratio of 2:1 using study centre, performance status (ECOG score) and the CLIP score as stratification factors. The system will generate  a unique Patient ID and assign a treatment group. A patient randomization confirmation in pdf format is sent to the investigator, that pharmacist and the Sponsor.</concealment>
    <sequence>The Investigator connects to the International Drug Development Institute web-based randomization tool to randomize the patient. Patients will be centrally randomised into two treatment groups with a ratio of 2:1 using study centre, Performance status (ECOG score) and the CLIP score as stratification factors.  The dynamic minimization will use a stochastic treatment allocation algorithm based on the variance method.  The system will generate  a unique Patient ID and assign a treatment group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2217</postcode>
    <postcode>3084</postcode>
    <postcode>3004</postcode>
    <postcode>3050</postcode>
    <postcode>6160</postcode>
    <postcode>6009</postcode>
    <postcode>5000</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>ORION Clinical Services (Australia) Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suite 115, 45 Glenferrie Road
MALVERN, VIC,  3144</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>BioAlliance Pharma</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>49 boulevard du General Martial Valin (1st floor), 75015 Paris, France</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>France</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>BioAlliance Pharma</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>49 boulevard du General Martial Valin (1st floor), 75015 Paris, France</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>France</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of the trial is to compare the efficacy (based on time to progression of tumour) and tolerance of Hepatic Intra-Arterial injection of Doxorubicin Transdrug® every 4 weeks, up to 3 courses with control standard treatment according to each centres usual practice (including TACE). This is an open label, multicentre, randomized in two parallel groups, Phase 2-3 study. The trial is designed to be performed in two successive parts, Phase 2 and Phase 3. At the end of the Phase 2, the efficacy of Doxorubicin Transdrug® will be evaluated based on the rate of patient free of local progression 3 months after randomisation. If more than 66% of patients treated with Doxorubicin Transdrug® are free of local progression, the study will be pursued and patients included in the Phase 2 study will automatically be followed and analyzed in the Phase 3 study.  A total of 200 patients will be accrued of whom 50 patients will be accrued for the Phase 2.
	
	Patients satisfying inclusion and exclusion criteria will be centrally randomised to one of two treatments groups. Group A: Patients will receive a course of hepatic intra-arterial Doxorubicin Transdrug® on Day1. The treatment will be repeated every 4 weeks or until D90 (i.e. 3 months after randomization) for a total of 3 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.  Group B: Patients will receive treatment according to each centres usual practice (including TACE), treatment will be repeated until D90 (i.e. 3 months after randomization) in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.  Patients are followed every 3 months for one year.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/02/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anna Tippett</name>
      <address>Level 1, 141 Osborne Street
South Yarra, Vic, 3141</address>
      <phone>03 9279 3947</phone>
      <fax>03 9867 1086</fax>
      <email>anna.tippett@orioncro.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anna Tippett</name>
      <address>Level 1, 141 Osborne Street
South Yarra, Vic, 3141</address>
      <phone>03 9279 3947</phone>
      <fax>03 9867 1086</fax>
      <email>anna.tippett@orioncro.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anna Tippett</name>
      <address>Level 1, 141 Osborne Street
South Yarra, Vic, 3141</address>
      <phone>03 9279 3947</phone>
      <fax>03 9867 1086</fax>
      <email>anna.tippett@orioncro.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>