<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343227">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000897965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Tetherx Natural Vascular Scaffolding (NVS) Procedure for Treating Patients with Atherosclerosis of the Femoropopliteal Artery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>This is a prospective, single-center, first-in-man, proof-of-concept study to be conducted at Auckland City Hospital, Auckland, New Zealand to evaluate the safety and performance of the Tetherx NVS System in subjects with femoropopliteal atherosclerosis, Rutherford category 2-4.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1123-0317</utrn>
    <trialacronym>RESTORE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Symptoms of claudication or ischemic rest pain (Rutherford category 2, 3, or 4) with suspected atherosclerosis in either the superficial femoral artery or the proximal popliteal artery (above the knee articulation).</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The use of the NVS balloon catheter in clinical practice is the same as other percutaneous transluminal angioplasty (PTA) balloon catheters used to perform balloon angioplasty.

The steps of the NVS procedure include:

1) Inflate both occlusion balloons so that the treatment zone (length of the artery between both occlusion balloons) is isolated.  Keep the occlusion balloons inflated for the duration of the procedure.

2) Inject the NVS Solution - which is a polyethylene-glycol (PEG)-based, aqueous solution - in between the 2 inflated occlusion balloons.  This will enable the NVS solution to diffuse into the vessel wall.  The duration to let the NVS Solution diffuse into the vessel wall is 5 minutes.

3) Inflate the balloon in between the 2 occlusion balloons; this is the Treatment Zone Balloon.  Keep the Treatment Zone Balloon inflated for the duration of the light activation (see step below - i.e. 60 seconds).

4) Activate the light fiber that runs through the catheter so that blue light (light with wavelength of 444-457nm) activates the NVS Solution; the duration to activate the light fiber is 60 seconds.

Note that the lumen in the catheter that the light fiber is in has a saline drip attached to it which enables a constant flow of saline to mitigate any risk of heat transferring from the light fiber to the catheter lumen, balloon or vessel.

5) Deflate the Occlusion Balloons and the Treatment Zone Balloons and remove the NVS Delivery Catheter.

The NVS Treatment is now complete.  The duration of the procedure is between 8-10 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>- The method and tecnique for inflating the Occlusion Balloons is similar to inflating a percutaneous transluminal angioplasty (PTA) balloon; this includes inflating the balloon with a mixture of contrast media and saline such that the inflated balloon can be verified angiographically.  The duration of inflation is 8-10 minutes; this is longer than the 3-5 minutes that a PTA balloon is inflated for

- The method and technique for inflating the Treatment Zone Balloon - is the same as stated above for the Occlusion Balloons; the duration that the Treatment Zone Balloon is inflated for (60 seconds) is less than the inflation time for a PTA balloon (3-5 minutes).

- The method and technique for injecting the NVS Solution is the same as injecting contrast media and saline through the catheter; e.g. a 5cc or 10cc syringe is used to do so.

- The method and technique for activating the light fiber includes turning on the blue light source that the light fiber is attached to; after 60 seconds, the blue light source is turned off

- The method and technique for providing a cooling flush though the catheter lumen that the light fiber is in includes attaching the tubing that extends from a saline bag to the catheter itself.  

The Historical control group is sourced from a peer-review scientific journal (Catheterization and Cardiovascular Interventions) from 2007, Volume 69, pages 910-919.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety as determined by either angiographic criteria or duplex ultrasonography criteria in the presence of return of symptoms (an increase in the Rutherford Classification by greater than 1 category) and/or decline in rest Ankle Brachial Indices from the post-procedure baseline value.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the procedure and immediately following the procedure (acute) and 30 days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Freedom from index limb amputation; method of assessment is clinical assessments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the procedure and immediately following the procedure (acute) and 30 days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Freedom from clinically-driven target lesion revascularization (TLR); method of assessment is clinical assessments and Duplex Doppler Ultrasound.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the procedure and immediately following the procedure (acute) and 30 days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy as determined by a Duplex Ultrasound (DUS) Peak systolic velocity ratio (PSVR) and freedom from clinically-driven target lesion revascularization. Clinically-driven is defined as either a PSVR greater than or equal to 2.5 or visually estimated angiographic percent DS greater than 70% and one of the following:  an increase in the Rutherford Classification by greater than 1 category from the 30 day post-intervention Rutherford Classification and/or a decline in rest Ankle Brachial Index (ABI) of greater than 0.15 from post-procedure baseline value</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post intervention at 30 days, 6 months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Freedom from clinically-driven target lesion revascularization (TLR).  Method of assessment is Duplex Doppler Ultrasound.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>I1	Age &gt; 18 years and &lt; 85 years 
I2	Subject or subjects legal representative have been informed of the nature of the study, agrees to participate and has signed an EC approved consent form
I3	Female subjects of childbearing potential have a negative pregnancy test at 7 days before the procedure and are willing to use a reliable method of birth control for the duration of study participation
I4	Subject understands the duration of the study and its follow up visit requirements
I5	Subject has documented claudication or ischemic rest pain in the target limb prior to the study procedure with documented Rutherford category 2, 3, or 4
I6	Subject is able to walk unassisted
I7	Subject has a documented resting ABI &lt; 0.9 or a toe brachial index (TBI) performed (if ABI non-diagnostic) prior to enrollment</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>I1	Life expectancy &lt; 12 months (in the Investigators opinion)
I2	Debilitating cerebrovascular accident (CVA) or ST Segment Myocardial Infarction (STEMI) within the 3 months prior to enrollment
I3	Administration of local systemic thrombolytics for acute limb ischemia (ALI) within the previous 30 days 
I4	Known allergies or sensitivities to heparin, aspirin, other anti-coagulant/antiplatelet therapies, and/or the NVS vascular polyethylene glycol (PEG) solution
I5	Allergy to contrast media that cannot be adequately pre-treated prior to procedure
I6	Chronic renal insufficiency with serum creatinine &gt; 2.5 mg/dL 
I7	Untreatable bleeding diatheses, hypercoagulable state, thrombocytopenia, and/or other bleeding disorder unresponsive to or not improved by blood transfusion
I8	Systemic infection present or suspected
I9	Enrolled in another investigational device, drug, or biologic study in which the subject has not completed the follow-up requirements 
I10	There is an additional planned percutaneous intervention (cardiac/peripheral) &lt; 30 days following the study procedure
I11	Subject is breast-feeding or plans to become pregnant during the follow-up period
I12	Previous lower limb amputation, excluding toe amputations</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Up to 30 subjects presenting with symptoms of claudication or ischemic rest pain (Rutherford category 2, 3, or 4) with suspected atherosclerosis in either the superficial femoral artery or the proximal popliteal artery (above the knee articulation) will be consented and screened for potential enrollment.</concealment>
    <sequence>The patients will not be randomised.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>None</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 0</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/07/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Tetherx, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>41 Darlene Drive
Southborough, MA 01772</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Avera Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>23rd Avenue
Sioux Falls, SD 57015</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United States of America</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>None</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>None</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>None</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the acute and post-procedural safety through 12 months of the Tetherx NVS therapy in the treatment of superficial femoral or proximal popliteal atherosclerotic disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern X Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Northern X Regional Ethics Committee
C/o Ministry of Health
3rd Floor, Unisys Building
650 Great South Road, Penrose
Private Bag 92-522 Wellesley St.
Auckland
1023</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/03/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michele Lucey</name>
      <address>128 Blye Hill Landing
Newbury, NH 03255</address>
      <phone>1+603 763 3455</phone>
      <fax>1+603 763 3456</fax>
      <email>lucey_m@msn.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chris D. Pierson</name>
      <address>41 Darlene Drive
Southborough, MA 01772</address>
      <phone>1+508 308 7845</phone>
      <fax>1+508 820 0818</fax>
      <email>cpierson@tetherx.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chris Pierson</name>
      <address>41 Darlene Drive
Southborough, MA 01772</address>
      <phone>1+508 308 7845</phone>
      <fax>1+508 820 0818</fax>
      <email>cpierson@tetherx.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>