<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367445">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/11/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001234606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Silver dressings and the diabetic foot</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessing the potential for silver dressings to enhance healing of diabetes-related foot ulcers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1164-1857 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetic foot ulcers</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A total of two hundred diabetic foot wounds will be randomised 1:1 to receive either (i) a silver impregnated wound dressing in combination with a foam dressing (Acticoat flex and Mepilex or Zetuvit) or (ii) similar silver free control dressing (Duoderm, Aquacel or Intrasite conformable with Mepilex or Zetuvit).  The intervention is a topical wound dressing and will be changed twice per week. Treatment will continue until wound closure of maximum of 12 weeks.  All other treatments will be equal between groups.</interventions>
    <comparator>One hundred individuals with receive a silver free control dressing (Duoderm, Aquacel or Intrasite conformable with Mepilex or Zetuvit). The control dressing is a topical wound dressing and will be changed twice per week. Treatment will continue until wound closure of maximum of 12 weeks.All other treatments will be equal between groups.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The study aims to determine if a silver impregnated wound dressing leads to improvement in wound healing rate when compared to a similar silver free control dressing, when managing individuals with diabetes related foot ulcers. 

Wound size will be determined by measuring the longest wound length and then the width of a line that runs perpendicular to longest length. Participants will be monitored for wound healing (time to complete healing and time for 50% wound reduction).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants wil be assessed for signs of wound infection and need and duration of antibiotic therapy, with a comparison being made between the cohort of individuals receiving a silver based dressing and those receiving a similar silver free dressing. This is a composite secondary outcome.

Infection will be defined as being present, for the purposes of this study, if there is evidence of (1) purulent discharge or (2) two or more of redness, pain/tenderness, swelling or warmth. The use of any antibiotics and their duration will be record for all subjects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will need to have a confirmed diagnosis of diabetes and an ulcer distal to the level of the ankle.  The ulcer will be of less than 6 weeks duration at the time of recruitment and participants will be 18 years or older. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals who are pregnant, who have an allergy to silver, Mepilex or Zetuvit, wounds with tendons or underlying osteomyelitis and individuals with a life expectancy of less than 12 weeks will be excluded from the study.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Consecutive individuals managed by the Diabetic Foot Unit / Podiatry Department at The Royal Melbourne Hospital, including the units inpatient and ambulatory care programs, will be invited to participate in this randomised study.  Once an individual is identified as being suitable for participating in the study, a blinded researcher holding the allocation schedule with be contacted by phone in order to acquire the allocation to either receive treatmet with the silver dressing or non silver dressing.

All participants will receive standard care, including wound debridement, antibiotics in the setting of infection, revascularisation in the setting of peripheral arterial disease and maximisation of sugar control.  The only variation to care will be the randomisation of participants to have wounds managed with a dressing that contains silver versus a similar dressing that is silver free. 

As individuals may have more than one ulcer, affecting one or both feet, total numbers of wounds will be recruited for, rather than total number of individuals.  It is planned that a total of 200 wounds will be recruited (with a maximum possible number of participants being 200). Wounds will be randomised 1:1 to receive either (i) a silver impregnated wound dressing in combination with a foam dressing (Acticoat flex and Mepilex or Zetuvit) or (ii) similar silver free control dressing (Duoderm, Aquacel or Intrasite conformable with Mepilex or Zetuvit). Recruited individuals will be randomised to receive one of the two dressing options for a total of 12 weeks, until they heal or the wound characteristics are such that these dressings can no longer be safely applied, whichever occurs first. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated randomisation process will be developed to randomised wounds 1:1 to receive either the silver dressing plan or non-silver dressing plan. However, as the presence of infection and peripheral arterial disease (PAD) are independent risk factors for non-healing, these factors will be controlled for during randomisation.  Wounds will be assessed at recruitment and defined as being: no infection and no PAD, no infection with PAD, infection without PAD and infection with PAD.  PAD will be defined as a toe pressure less than 60mmHg while the absence of PAD defined as a toe pressure equal or greater to 60mmHg.  Infection will be defined as the presence of purulent discharge or 2 or more of redness, pain/tenderness, swelling, and warmth.  Once recruited, a wound will be randomised to receive either the silver or non-silver based dressing, unless an identical wound type has already been recruited and randomised.  In this situation, in order to ensure that equal numbers of wounds with the four different wound characteristics are equally randomised to receive silver and non-silver based dressings, the newly recruited wound will receive the opposite dressing type to that which has already been recruited. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is a pilot study to assess the non-inferiority of non-silver dressings to achieve timely wound healing as compared to using a silver based wound dressing. At the end of the study, statistical analysis will be performed on the number of wounds achieving wound closure, the percentage closure from baseline of all wounds, and the number of wounds becoming infected and requiring antibiotics during the study period.  Results will be analysed and compared between wounds receiving silver impregnated dressings as compared to those receiving standard silver free dressings.  Analysis will also be made between wounds free of infection at baseline receiving the two treatment options as compared to infected wounds at baseline receiving the two treatment arms. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3050 - Royal Melbourne Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Royal Melbourne Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Royal Melbourne Hosptial
Grattan St
Parkville, Victoria
Australia, 3050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Diabetic Foot Unit</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St,
Parkville, Melbourne
Australia, 3050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To determine if a silver impregnated wound dressing has any clinical benefit over using a similar silver free control dressing, when managing individuals with diabetes-related foot ulcers. Wound healing rates, signs of infection, and need and duration of antibiotic therapy will be compared between the cohort of individuals receiving a silver based dressing and those receiving a similar silver free dressing. 

Outcomes will also be assessed regarding any clinical benefit in using a silver impregnated wound dressing as compared to a similar silver free control dressing on wounds that are both (1) clinically infected (purulent discharge or 2 or more of redness, pain/tenderness, swelling, warmth) at the outset as well as (2) those that have no signs of infection. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St
Parkville, Victoria
Australia, 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014.089</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Wraight</name>
      <address>Department of Diabetes and Endocrinology
4 West
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St 
Parkville, Victoria, 3050</address>
      <phone>+61409427943</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.wraight@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Wraight</name>
      <address>Department of Diabetes and Endocrinology
4 West
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St 
Parkville, Victoria, 3050</address>
      <phone>+61409427943</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.wraight@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Wraight</name>
      <address>Department of Diabetes and Endocrinology
4 West
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St 
Parkville, Victoria, 3050</address>
      <phone>+61409427943</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.wraight@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Wraight</name>
      <address>Department of Diabetes and Endocrinology
4 West
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St 
Parkville, 3050</address>
      <phone>+61409427943</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.wraight@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>