<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363399">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/12/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000003774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Looking at the safety of primaquine when given by mouth once a week for 8 weeks to Cambodian patients with vivax malaria. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessing the safety of weekly administered primaquine in vivax malaria infected Cambodians. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Vivax malaria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Oral primaquine at a dose of 0.75 mg/kg given once per week for 8 weeks AND 

Oral dihydroartemisinin piperaquine given once per day for 3 days according to the maufacturer's dosing instructions.  

This regimen will be given to patients with vivax malaria and G6PD deficiency. </interventions>
    <comparator>Oral primaquine at a dose of 0.75 mg/kg given once per week for 8 weeks AND 

Oral dihydroartemisinin piperaquine given once per day for 3 days according to the maufacturer's dosing instructions.  

This regimen will be given to patients with vivax malaria but without G6PD deficiency. This is the control group. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportions of patients who complete 8 weeks of primaquine; that is, patients who are not withdrawn from the study because of primaquine induced haematological toxicity. This is defined as: 

1. Fall in baseline Hb &gt;25% by D7

2. Development of severe anaemia by D7, defined as a Hb &lt; 7 g/dL for all ages 

3. Haemoglobinuria for 2 days, defined as a urine colour &gt;=8 based on a urine colour chart (Hillmen, Hall et al. 2004)

4. Development of metHaemoglobinaemia &gt; 20%

5. Increase in baseline creatinine &gt; 50% with evidence of acute haemolytic anaemia      </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 56</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine risk factors (e.g. age, sex, G6PD activity, level of parasitaemia) for primaquine related toxicity by logistic regression

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 56</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hb dynamics over 8 weeks by measuring the Hb concentration at each time point and seing how these concnetrations change over time 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 56</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of protocol defined adverse events e.g. abdominal pain, vomiting, any skin rashes. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 56</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sensitivity, specificity, positive &amp; negative predictive values of the G6PD rapid test vs. quantitative G6PD assay + G6PD PCR </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male or non pregnant females aged &gt; 1 year

Weight &gt;= 10 kg

Presentation with: (i) acute (within 10 days), symptomatic (i.e. history of fever), uncomplicated, Plasmodium vivax mono- or mixed infection, AND (ii) vivax asexual parasitaemia = 200 &amp; &lt; 200,000 parasites/microL 

Written informed consent provided by the volunteer. Witnessed consent is permitted, if the individual cannot write.  

Able and willing to participate based on information given to the volunteer

Not currently taking any prescribed, over the counter or herbal drugs that could cause haemolysis in G6PD deficiency </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Hb &lt; 8 g/dL for a patients of all ages

Have any malaria danger signs: unable to swallow because of vomiting, &gt;=2 convulsions within previous 24 hours, reduced level of consciousness, unable to sit or walk unaided. 

Any clinically significant disease requiring treatment or further investigation

Pregnant, planning to become pregnant   

Breast feeding

For a G6PD deficient child under 5  living more than 25 km from the research site

Allergic to primaquine or DHA-PP known to have had a clinically significant, contraindicating adverse reaction to either drug

Having taken part in research involving an investigational drug within the past 8 weeks.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients with fever who attend the local clinic will be managed according to local practice. This usually involves either the preparation of a blood film or use of a rapid test or both tests to determine if the patient has malaria. Prestudy training will be given on slide preparation. 

If a subject has vivax malaria, he or she will be asked if they would like to be part of a research study. If the answer is yes, a copy of the consent form in Khmer will be given to them to read or the consent form will be read to them. A trained study nurse may assist the research physicians in the consent process. Any questions that may arise will be answered by one of the study doctors. 
If the potential study subjects / guardians are happy to join the study, they will be asked to sign the consent form. A screening number will be assigned to them starting at SC001 and will also have a code for the study site. 

After the consent form has been signed, all mandated study investigations to determine eligibility to the study will be performed. Patients found to be eligible will then be allocated a study number. </concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Risk/proportional data - These data will be compared by chi squared or Fishers exact test, as appropriate. The primary endpoint will also be analysed using simple proportions and Kaplan Meier survival method; the survival curves compared using the log rank test. The risk difference and attributable risk in unacceptable haematological toxicity will be calculated.    

Continuous data - These data will be summarised by medians (ranges) and means (standard deviations), as appropriate, and will include the haematological and biochemical parameters. Between group means/mean changes analyses will be unpaired t test,  or the non parametric tests, as appropriate. Changes relative to baseline will be by paired test or ranksum test, as appropriate. 

Exploratory, simple regression analyses will be done to determine relationships e.g. between G6PD enzyme activity and free Hb concentrations, metHb concentrations &amp; degree of haemolysis.

Risk factors for haemolysis - These will be assessed in a logistic regression model.    

Time to event - The time for the Hb to return to baseline will be determined by KM survival analysis; time curves will be compared by the log rank test. 

Test characteristics - The sensitivity, specificity, positive &amp; negative predictive values of the G6PD rapid test vs. quantitative G6PD assay + G6PD PCR will be calculated. 

The positive predictive values for clinically significant haemolysis of the rapid test and qualitative G6PD test will also be determined.  
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <state>Pailin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Center for Parasitology, Entomology &amp; Malaria Control</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>372 Monivong Boulevard
Phnom Penh</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Cambodia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>World Health Organisation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Avenue Appia 20
1211 Geneva </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Primaquine is a drug that is used to kill malaria parasites that sleep in the liver. Plasmodium vivax and plasmodium ovale are the scientific names of the malaria species that can sleep in the liver. The species These sleeping forms of malaria can wake up and enter the blood where they will cause another bout of malaria. 

Primaquine is not widely used because it can cause red cells on the blood to break open if they are short of an enzyme  called glucose 6 phosphate dehydrogenase, G6PD for short. 

With little or no G6PD, the red cell cannot produce certain substances to protect itself when it is under stress from certain drugs like primaquine and also fava beans.

G6PD deficiency is common in many parts of the world, especially where there is malaria. There are tests that can be used to see if someone is G6PD deficient but many countries do not use them because of cost and the logistical challenges involved. As a result primaquine is not used because of the risk of causing harm to patinets due to the red cells breaking apart is too high. 

Our research project will look closely at the risk of effects of red cells breaking apart by giving G6PD deficient patients and seeing what happens. We will monitor the patients very closely and have developed a good safety net to detect any health problems quickly.

The results of this research will provide useful information for the Ministries of Health that are trying to control malaria. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>National Ethics Committee for Health Research</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health,
2 Boulevard Km Yl Sung
Phnom Penh</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>39</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/03/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Cambodia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>WHO WPRO Ethics Review Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>P.O. Box 2932, 
1000 Manila</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012.5.CAM.01.MVP</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/05/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Philippines</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kheng Sim</name>
      <address>National Center for Parasitology, 
Entomology and Malaria Control,
372 Monivog Boulevard,
Phnom Penh. 
</address>
      <phone>+85512307068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khengsim@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kheng Sim</name>
      <address>National Center for Parasitology, 
Entomology and Malaria Control,
372 Monivog Boulevard,
Phnom Penh. 
</address>
      <phone>+85512307068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khengsim@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kheng Sim</name>
      <address>National Center for Parasitology, 
Entomology and Malaria Control,
372 Monivog Boulevard,
Phnom Penh. 
</address>
      <phone>+85512307068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khengsim@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bob Taylor</name>
      <address>National Center for Parasitology, 
Entomology and Malaria Control,
372 Monivog Boulevard,
Phnom Penh. 
</address>
      <phone>+855979588068</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>wallybobby1@yahoo.co.uk</email>
      <country>Cambodia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>