<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368522">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000644561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Accelerated versus conservative rehabilitation following rotator cuff surgery to repair full-thickness tears: Clinical outcomes and recovery of muscle function.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Accelerated versus conservative rehabilitation following rotator cuff surgery to repair full-thickness tears: Clinical outcomes and recovery of muscle function.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Rotator cuff tear</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a prospective RCT investigating two different post-operative rehabilitation interventions and, therefore, all patients who are undergoing arthroscopic rotator cuff repair will be invited to participate in this trial. Participants will be invited to be part of the study after consultation with the surgeon having confirmed a full-thickness tear of the supraspinatus via clinical examination and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), and being scheduled for surgery. At this time, the Patient Information Sheet and a verbal summary of the study and patient expectations, with particular reference to the two different rehabilitation pathways, will be presented to the patients. Patients willing to participate will then complete the Patient Consent Form and will then be randomised to one of the two rehabilitation arms of the study: conservative (CR) or accelerated (AR) rehabilitation. 

Patients allocated to the AR group will be required to attend an initial education session for 1 hour, 1-2 weeks post-surgery with an Accredited Exercise Physiologist (AEP) for instructions on their post-operative exercise regime, including any contraindications and an outline on progressions from passive exercises, through to active strengthening exercises. Patients will commence post-operative rehabilitation immediately following hospital discharge, receiving passive range of motion exercises from week 1 post-surgery, progressing to active-assisted ROM from week 4, strengthening from week 8, up until weeks 12-16 post surgery. 

Rehabilitation from weeks 1  4 will be initially self-managed by the patient after the initial education session. Self-managed exercises will involve undertaking prescribed exercises lasting approximately 20 to 30 minutes, 3 times per day, and will be developed and monitored via an online home-exercise software platform (Physitrack). Physitrack involves video-based demonstrations of exercise technique and dosage, and allows the therapist to monitor daily adherence and patient-reported pain, with the software allowing direct access to the therapist via email and text message in case of a problem or adverse event. At week 4, a 1 hour one-on-one session with an AEP will take place to ensure all exercises are being performed soundly, and to prescribe the active-assisted ROM exercises. From week 4 to 7, patients will again be self-managed, with the program on Physitrack updated to incorporate more active exercises. This will involve exercises for 20 to 30 minutes, 3 times per day.

From the 8-week mark, patients will be required to commit to exercise rehabilitation twice per week for 6 weeks lasting approximately an hour, along with daily home exercises which will again be delivered and monitored via Physitrack. Rehabilitation commencing at this point will involve controlled strengthening exercise of the rotator cuff and scapula muscles delivered one-on-one by an experienced AEP, and cardiovascular exercise for general conditioning. Patients will be provided with a training kit consisting of Therabands and other simple equipment found in most homes to complete the prescribed exercises. Hard copies of the patient information sheet and exercise program will also be provided. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment will consist of conservative, post-operative rehabilitation 

Patients allocated to this group will also be required to attend an initial education session for 1 hour, 1-2 weeks post-surgery with an AEP for instructions on their post-operative exercise regime, including any contraindications and an outline on progressions from passive exercises, through to active strengthening exercises. They will be required to wear an immobilisation sling for 6 weeks, and perform minimal activities of daily living. From 6 weeks post-surgery, patients will begin to undertake ROM exercises, including active-assisted exercises. Strengthening exercises will commence from 12 weeks post-surgery. 

From weeks 6 to 11, patients will be self-managed, required to undertake the prescribed exercises independently at home for approximately 20 to 30 minutes, three times per day. Competency and ongoing instruction in undertaking home exercises will be determined by the treating therapist, and will be developed and monitored via an online home-exercise software platform (Physitrack). Physitrack involves video-based demonstrations of exercise technique and dosage, and allows the therapist to monitor daily adherence and patient-reported pain, with the software allowing direct access to the therapist via email and text message in case of a problem or adverse event.

At the 12-week mark, patients will be required to commit to exercise rehabilitation twice per week for 6 weeks lasting approximately one hour, along with daily home exercises which will again be delivered and monitored via Physitrack. Rehabilitation commencing at this point will involve controlled strengthening exercise of the rotator cuff and scapula muscles delivered one-on-one by an experienced Accredited Exercise Physiologist. Patients will be provided with a training kit consisting of Therabands and other simple equipment found in most homes to complete the prescribed exercises. Hard copies of the patient information sheet and exercise program will also be provided.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxford Shoulder Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6, 12, 26 and 52 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Constant Score </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6, 12, 26 and 52 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Simple Shoulder Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6, 12, 26 and 52 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Shoulder Activity Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6, 12, 26 and 52 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EuroQoL 5 Dimensions Questionnaire </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6, 12, 26 and 52 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male or female, between 35 and 75 years

Have been diagnosed with a full-thickness tear of the supraspinatus that is deemed repairable by the surgeon.

Have failed conservative treatment (physiotherapy and corticosteroid injection) prior to surgery.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Have supraspinatus tears &gt; 2cm, or a partial thickness tears.

Present with rotator cuff tears secondary to significant trauma (fracture, dislocation etc).

Have received non-surgical treatment in the rotator cuff within the three months prior to surgery, including corticosteroid injection and platelet rich plasma (PRP) injections.

Present with pre-existing conditions associated with upper extremity pain, including arthritis, ongoing infection, carpal tunnel syndrome, cervical neuropathy or other nerve pathology.

Are likely to have problems with follow-up (i.e. patients with no fixed address, report a plan to move out of town, or intellectually challenged patients without adequate support network).

Do not read and speak English.

The individual is unable or unwilling to follow the designated post-operative rehabilitation protocol.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a prospective RCT investigating two different post-operative rehabilitation interventions and, therefore, all patients who are undergoing arthroscopic rotator cuff repair with Mr Allan Wang (AW) will be invited to participate in this trial. Participants will be invited to be part of the study after consultation with the surgeon (AW), having confirmed a full-thickness tear of the supraspinatus via clinical examination and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), and being scheduled for surgery. At this time, the Patient Information Sheet and a verbal summary of the study and patient expectations, with particular reference to the two different rehabilitation pathways, will be presented to the patients. Patients willing to participate will then complete the Patient Consent Form, and will then be randomised to one of the two rehabilitation arms of the study: conservative (CR) or accelerated (AR) rehabilitation.

Allocation is concealed, and involves contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is locate at an independent office “off-site”.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by a random number generator on Microsoft Excel.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size Calculation

A power analysis using G power software was performed to calculate the sample size required for this study. Assuming a 5% significance level and a power of 0.8, the minimal clinical important difference of 10.4 points between groups on the Constant Score and standard deviations from previous study, generated a sample size of 72 patients (36 per group). 


Statistical analysis will be performed using SPSS software (SPSS, Version 11.5, SPSS Inc., USA). A series of repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) will be used to investigate primary and secondary clinical outcome measures between the two rehabilitation groups at baseline, and at 6 weeks and 3, 6, and 12 months post-surgery. Where a significant interaction effect is found, post-hoc independent t-tests will be used to determine time-points at which the two groups differ. Statistical significance will be determined at p = 0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St John of God Hospital, Subiaco - Subiaco</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Sport Science, Exercise and Health (M408)
The University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley Perth
Western Australia 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Western Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Sport Science, Exercise and Health (M408)
The University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley Perth
Western Australia 6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>St John of God Hospital Subiaco Clinic</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>302/25 McCourt Street, Subiaco WA 6008</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Rotator cuff tears may affect one or more of the tendons of the four rotator cuff muscles in your shoulder, principally the supraspinatus. These tears cause significant pain and restricted movement of the arm, affecting the ability to perform daily activities, participate in sport and exercise, and the ability to work. Arthroscopic rotator cuff repair is the most popular surgical treatment for rotator cuff pathology. While surgery is considered an effective treatment, high failure rates and recurrent tears are common, especially degenerative tears, which are frequently observed in the older population. 

Post-operative rehabilitation is a critical part of the treatment following rotator cuff repair. Specific exercises to improve mobility and strength of the rotator cuff are commonly prescribed after repair. However, the role of post-surgical immobilisation, the amount of load that can be safely borne by the repair site throughout the early post-operative stages, and when and how to safely graduate this progressive load through rehabilitation, is currently unclear.  

Traditionally, repairs have been managed with passive range of motion followed by delayed active motion and, finally, strengthening exercises. However, as the incidence of repair failures grew, it has been suggested that overly aggressive rehabilitation and excessive loading at the healing repair site may play a role. Subsequently, delayed rehabilitation involving an early period of immobilization (arm in a sling) has become common practice. The rationale behind a delayed rehabilitation program stems from concerns that early repair site loading may negatively affect tendon healing, and that the repair site requires suitable time to heal without aggravation via loading. 

However, improvements in surgical techniques and current evidence and expert opinion suggesting that this period of immobilisation is too conservative and may potentially increase the risk of post-operative shoulder stiffness and a delayed return of shoulder muscle function, have allowed the possibility of an early, controlled post-operative treatment protocol. We hypothesise that a structured, accelerated post-operative rehabilitation program designed to safely return patients to work and sport faster, will improve patient based outcome scores and accelerate recovery of muscle function compared to a conservative regime, without risk to the repaired shoulder. 

This is a prospective randomised controlled trial (RCT), which seeks to investigate the benefit of an accelerated post-operative rehabilitation program after your rotator cuff repair surgery. This will be evaluated via validated questionnaires about your pain and function, clinical scores looking at your strength, mobility and function, as well as the time taken to return to work/sport, overall satisfaction and re-injury rate. This information will be of benefit to you in your return to full function, as well as other patients who require such treatment in the future.    
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC) University of Western Australia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Office (M459)
The University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley Perth
Western Australia 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St John of God Health Care (SJGHC) Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St John of God Health Care Human Research Ethics Committee
Level 3, St John of God House
177-179 Cambridge Street
Wembley  WA 6014</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368522-Research Plan Study 3.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368522-Participant Information Sheet Study 3.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368522-Table 2.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Peter Edwards</name>
      <address>The School of Sport Science, Exercise and Health (M408), The University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, Perth, Western Australia 6009</address>
      <phone>+61422370913</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.edwards@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Peter Edwards</name>
      <address>The School of Sport Science, Exercise and Health (M408), The University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, Perth, Western Australia 6009</address>
      <phone>+61422370913</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.edwards@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Peter Edwards</name>
      <address>The School of Sport Science, Exercise and Health (M408), The University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, Perth, Western Australia 6009</address>
      <phone>+61422370913</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.edwards@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Peter Edwards</name>
      <address>The School of Sport Science, Exercise and Health (M408), The University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, Perth, Western Australia 6009</address>
      <phone>+61422370913</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.edwards@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>