<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371596">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001576415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Sacral neuromodulation for the treatment of detrusor hyperreflexia with impaired contractility (DHIC)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Sacral neuromodulation for the treatment of detrusor hyperreflexia with impaired contractility (DHIC)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1188-3249 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>SDOIC Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Detrusor overactivty and impaired bladder contraction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Detrusor hyperactivity with impaired contractility (DHIC) is a common clinical entity that is poorly understood, under-recognized, and difficult to effectively manage. It is a condition in which patients unexpectedly display detrusor overactivity (DO) during storage, yet are unable to mount a sufficient detrusor contraction during voiding to completely empty the bladder. It is theorised that SNM would potentially treat both aspects of DHIC, the DO and poorly contractile bladder. Currently, there are no studies evaluating the efficacy of SNM for DHIC. In this study, we aim to evaluate the efficacy of SNM for treating DHIC.
Patients with urodynamically proven DHIC will undergo a two stage surgical procedure performed under general anaesthesia (GA) and then local anaesthesia with sedation. The 1st stage procedure will involve a tined lead insertion into the S3 foramina and corresponding nerve root. This procedure is performed with the patient in the prone position and under GA. This tined lead is connected to an external battery and a trial of SNS.
Patients are trialled for 2 weeks (occasionally 3 weeks).  Patients stay on the same program for the trial duration, unless their response is lower than a 50% improvement in symptoms. Symptom parameters are measured using a Patient Management Worksheet.  For patients with DHIC we initially generally leave them on one program for at least 5 days. At this point if their symptoms have not improved we then consider changing their program.    Patients can change their own program during the trial and after consultation. Patients document symptom control for each program. The duration of each programming session will be approximately 20 minutes. The programming will be done by a specialist representative from Medtronic who has specialist training in SNS programming and the senior author of the study.

During a trial, patients can access 3 programs stored in their SNS controller. Patients are usually given C1, C2, &amp; C3 or C2, C3 &amp; C4 depending on motor response in theatre, amplitude limit and patient comfort. 

Different controller program specifications
C1: Electrode combination 0-/3+, Time 210 micro seconds, Frequency 25 Hz	
C2: Electrode combination 1-/3+, Time 210 micro seconds, Frequency 25 Hz
C3: Electrode combination 2-/0+, Time 210 micro seconds, Frequency 25 Hz
C4: Electrode combination 3-/0+, Time 210 micro seconds, Frequency 25 Hz
C5: Electrode combination ,1-/3+, Time 210 micro seconds, Frequency 25 Hz
C6: Electrode combination 1-,2-/3+ 2, Time 210 micro seconds, Frequency 25 Hz
C6: Electrode combination -,3-/0+, Time 210 micro seconds, Frequency 25 Hz

Thus settings be a will adjusted on a case-by-case basis to provide optimal patient symptom relief, minimize patient discomfort, and maximize neurostimulator battery life. Patients that report an improvement of greater than 50% in urgency, urge incontinence, and frequency will be offered a stage 2 procedure. The stage 2 procedure is performed in the lateral position under sedation. If the patient has had an adequate response that the implantable battery is placed in a tissue pocket in the buttock. The duration of SNS is indefinite if the patient has a good response. Adherence to the desired treatment and device function will be check by 6 month interrogation of the Medtronic sacral nerve stimulator.
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patients that underwent a stage 2 procedure and had a implantable battery placed will be followed up for improvement in there lower urinary tract symptoms. 

Treatment response will be assessed by  nternational Consultation on Incontinence Modular Questionnaire on overactive bladder (ICIQ-OAB), </outcome>
      <timepoint>These indices will be recorded at baseline, two weeks post first stage  2 procedure, and at  3 months, 6 months and 12 months post procedure to assess treatment response. Success will defined as greater than 50% symptom improvement in urgency, urge incontinence, and frequency,</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patients will also examined for improvements in voiding. Median voided volumes, median post void residual volumes (PVR) by clean intermittent catheterization (CIC) will be examined</outcome>
      <timepoint>These indices will be recorded at baseline, two weeks post first stage  2 procedure, and at  3 months, 6 months and 12 months post procedure to assess treatment response. Success will defined as greater than 50% reduction in PVR,</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient experience and response to treatment will be patient Global Impression of Improvement (PGI-I).</outcome>
      <timepoint>These indices will be recorded at baseline, two weeks post first stage  2 procedure, and at  3 months, 6 months and 12 months post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients with urodynamically proven DHIC are included in study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with evidence bladder outlet (BOO), pelvic organ prolapse, stress urinary incontinence, and neurogenic bladder are excluded</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Pending</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>6/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Epworth Richmond - Richmond</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3121 - Richmond</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Johan Gani</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Melbourne Bladder clinic
49 Erin Street 
Richmond
Victoria 3121</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dr Johan Gani</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Melbourne Bladder clinic
49 Erin Street 
Richmond
Victoria 3121</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Detrusor hyperactivity with impaired contractility (DHIC) is a common clinical entity that is poorly understood, under-recognized, and difficult to effectively manage. It is a condition in which patients unexpectedly display detrusor overactivity (DO) during storage, yet are unable to mount a sufficient detrusor contraction during voiding to completely empty the bladder. It was first described by Resnick in 1987, as the second most common cause of urinary incontinence in institutionalized elderly people. Although initially described in frail institutionalized elderly, DHIC has been increasingly recognized as a cause of lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) in elderly patients . DHIC was identified as the principal dysfunction in up to 8-18% of elderly patients referred for urodynamic studies, furthermore DHIC was more commonly seen in men. 

There is no defined treatment algorithm for patients with DHIC, but typically, patients have been treated based on the severity of their particular symptoms. Sacral neuromodulation (SNM) is currently approved as a treatment for both idiopathic DO, and non-obstructive urinary retention independently. It is theorised that SNM would potentially treat both aspects of DHIC, the DO and poorly contractile bladder. Currently, there are no studies evaluating the efficacy of SNM for DHIC. In this study, we aim to evaluate the efficacy of SNM for treating DHIC.
 </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Johan Gani</name>
      <address>Melbourne Bladder Clinic
49 Erin Street 
Richmond
Victoria 3121 
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9428 2232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>derek.hennessey@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Derek Hennessey</name>
      <address>Austin Health
Department of Urology
145 Studley Road
 Heidelberg 
Victoria 3084
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5000 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>derek.hennessey@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Derek Hennessey</name>
      <address>Austin Health
Department of Urology
145 Studley Road
 Heidelberg 
Victoria 3084
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5000 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>derek.hennessey@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Derek Hennessey</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>