<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365343">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001284752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of individual imagery based cognitive-behavioural therapy for clinical perfectionism</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In adults with clinical perfectionism, does a single individual imagery cognitive-behavioural therapy session reduce clinical perfectionism and related psychological symptoms when compared to individual cognitive therapy and relaxation?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Clinical perfectionism
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Intrusive/distressing mental imagery</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression symptoms</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety symptoms</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There are two separate intervention groups 
Intervention group 1: 
Individual imagery rescripting based cognitive behavioural therapy for clinical perfectionism. In this intervention participants receive 1 x 2 hour sessions of individual therapy, where they explore and manipulate distressing mental imagery related to clinical perfectionism. The strategies are derived from the book Oxford guide to imagery in cognitive therapy (Hackmann, Bennett-Levy, &amp; Holmes, 2011)

Intervention group 2:
Individual cognitive restructuring based cognitive behavioural therapy for clinical perfectionism. In this intervention participants receive 1 x 2 hour sessions of individual therapy, where they explore distressing mental imagery related to clinical perfectionism and use cognitive disputations to re-evaluate their appraisal of the images. The strategies are derived from the book Overcoming Perfectionism (Shafran, Egan, &amp; Wade, 2010)</interventions>
    <comparator>Individual relaxation session for clinical perfectionism. In this control group participants receive 1 x 2 hour sessions of relaxation, where they explore distressing mental imagery related to clinical perfectionism and learn relaxation techniques to reduce stress experienced. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Perfectionism score as assessed by the Clinical Perfectionism Questionnaire (Fairburn, Cooper, &amp; Shafran, 2003)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, immediately after the intervention, and at 1 week, 1 month, and 3 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Personal Standards, Concern over Mistakes, Doubts about Actions, Parental Expectations, Parental Criticism, and Organisation as assessed by Frost Multidimensional Perfectionism Scale (Frost, Marten, Lahart, &amp; Rosenblate, 1990)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, immediately after the intervention, and at 1 week, 1 month, and 3 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression score as assessed by the Depression, Anxiety and Distress Scale-21 (DASS-21; Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, immediately after the intervention, and at 1 week, 1 month, and 3 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety score as assessed by the Depression, Anxiety and Distress Scale-21 (DASS-21; Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, immediately after the intervention, and at 1 week, 1 month, and 3 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stress score as assessed by the Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale-21 (DASS-21; Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, immediately after the intervention, and at 1 week, 1 month, and 3 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression score as assessed by the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI; Beck, Steer, &amp; Garbin, 1988).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, immediately after the intervention, and at 1 week, 1 month, and 3 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>State Anxiety questions from State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI; Spielberger, Gorsuch, &amp; Lushene, 1970). </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, immediately after the intervention, and at 1 week, 1 month, and 3 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Repetitive negative thinking score as assessed by the repetitive negative thinking - short scale (RNT-10; McEvoy, Mahoney, &amp; Moulds, 2010)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, immediately after the intervention, and at 1 week, 1 month, and 3 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Imagery Interview Questionnaire which has 7 questions assessing Image intensity, Image Distress, Difficulty Dismissing Imagery, Impact of Imagery, and Imagery Frequency (Lee, Roberts-Collins, Coughtrey, Phillips, &amp; Shafran, 2011).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, immediately after the intervention, and at 1 week, 1 month, and 3 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Future oriented imagery scores as assessed by the Impact of Future Events (IFES; Deeprose &amp; Holmes, 2010)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, immediately after the intervention, and at 1 week, 1 month, and 3 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Interpretation task which is developed for specifically examining interpretation bias in participants with perfectionism. Based on work by Yiend, Savulich, Coughtrey, &amp; Shafran (2011). Consisting of 40 items designed to explore perfectionist interpretations of three line passages that depict a scenario where a protagonist falls just short of reaching perfection. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive Dot-Probe Task designed to measure attention to failure, achievement or neutral stimuli. Based on work by Grafton, Watkins, &amp; Macleod (2012); Posner, Snyder, &amp; Davidson (1980).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Imagery interview is a semi-structured interview that examines intrusive mental thoughts, images and associated sensations related to a specific memory (Lee, Roberts-Collins, Coughtrey, Phillips, &amp; Shafran, 2011).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 18 years or older. Not have undergone specific treatment for perfectionism prior to starting the study. Have met or currently meet a diagnosis of an Axis I disorder. They must have been stable on any anti-depressant medication/s for a minimum of two months prior to commencement of the study, and be willing to remain on the same medication for the duration of the study (if applicable). Clinical levels of perfectionism as defined by a score of 24.7 or greater on the Concern Over Mistakes Scale (Frost et al., 1990)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Moderate to severe suicidality section of the MINI (Sheehan et al., 1998a). Meeting the DSM-IV-TR (American Psychiatric Association, 2000) criteria for psychosis. Meeting the DSM-IV-TR (American Psychiatric Association, 2000) criteria for alcohol/substance dependence. Adults who wish to receive treatment for perfectionism prior to commencement or duration of the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Individuals interested in the study who telephone the Curtin University Psychology and Speech Clinic will be emailed or posted the Concern over Mistakes subscale of the Frost Multi-dimensional Perfectionism Scale (Frost et al., 1990), an information sheet about the study and a consent form.Participants who score at 24.7 + on the Concern Over Mistakes subscale (i.e., have clinical levels of perfectionism) and consent to the study will be telephone- screened by Joel Howell to assess their eligibility. Ineligible participants will be referred to external services. The telephone screening will involve administering the MINI-screen (Sheehan &amp; Lecrubier, 2006), the MINI modules corresponding to the exclusion criteria (Sheehan et al., 1998) and asking questions corresponding to the inclusion criteria. Ineligible individuals will be referred to external services. At this point the researcher has no knowledge of the condition that a participant will be in. Eligible individuals will be advised on the telephone that they will have a baseline assessment in a few days and that only after they have had this baseline assessment, they will be
randomly allocated to either be in the intervention condition or the waitlist control condition. Eligible individuals then have their baseline assessment, where they will be administered a battery of assessment measures. At this point the researcher still does not know which condition the participant will be allocated to. The researcher will then use Saghaei’s (2004) Random Allocation computer software version 1.0 to randomly allocate participants to conditions. It is only after this random allocation has occurred that the researcher becomes aware which condition the participant has been allocated to.</concealment>
    <sequence>A simple random allocation procedure will be employed to randomly allocate participants to conditions. The researcher will use Saghaei’s (2004) Random Allocation software version 1.0, which generates randomised number lists. This software allows the number of individuals per group and the number of groups to be accounted for in the system to enable equal group sizes (Steele &amp; Wade, 2008).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Previous research on single session imagery rescripting in disorders (Nilsson et al., 2012; Wild &amp; Clark, 2011) has yielded a large effect size (Cohen, 1992). The current study will plan to detect a Group x time interaction, therefore to detect a small-moderate effect size (f = .2), there needs to be 15 participants in each treatment group condition (N = 45) (power = .80, alpha = .05). This is because there is still limited research on imagery rescripting, and no research has examined imagery rescripting for perfectionism related imagery. By planning for a conservative effect size, any interactions and effects from the treatment that may not have been captured in previous literature can be observed.

The intervention data is best analysed using mixed effects linear regression model (Bryk &amp; Raudenbush, 1987). This analysis will analyse the data within a hierarchical data structure, in which time is nested within the participant. This will be implemented through SPSSs Generalised Linear Mixed Models (GLMM; SPSS version 19) procedure. GLMM does not rely on participants providing data at both pre- and post-test; GLMM uses all the data present at each assessment point thereby reducing the impact of subject attrition on statistical power. Moreover, GLMM is robust to unequal group sizes. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Senior Lecturer Dr. Sarah Egan, Principal investigator of the study</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth Western Australia 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kent Street, Bentley,
Perth Western Australia. 6102.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Rebecca Anderson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth Western Australia 6845</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project will primarily examine whether an individual mental imagery based treatment for distressing mental images related to clinical perfectionism is better than receiving a standard cognitive treatment technique or relaxation techniques in 
a) reducing individuals' levels of clinical perfectionism, 
b) reducing the impact and distress caused by negative mental imagery and,
c) reducing their symptoms of anxiety, depression, and/or eating concerns and 
It is predicted that the mental imagery individual treatment will lead to greater reductions in clinical perfectionism, greater reductions in imagery distress, frequency, and intensity experienced, and psychological symptoms compared
to the standard cognitive disputation technique and relaxation. Additionally this project will examine whether individual mental imagery psychological treatment for clinical perfectionism produces treatment-related change in each individual and whether this is clinically significant.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kent Street, Bentley,
Perth Western Australia 6102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR88/2012</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Egan</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 2367</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Egan@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Joel Howell</name>
      <address>Curtin University Psychology and Speech Clinic, Kent Street, Bentley, Western Australia 6102.</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92663436</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>joel.howell@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Egan</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 2367</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Egan@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Joel Howell</name>
      <address>Curtin University Psychology and Speech Clinic, Kent Street, Bentley, Western Australia 6102.</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92663436</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>