<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363190">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001147875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Caregiver Intervention and Support for carers of people with brain tumours.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of a supportive educational intervention for caregivers of patients with high grade glioma (HGG).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1136-3146</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Care-IS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Experience of Caregiving</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Quality of life of caregivers</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety and Depression amongst caregivers</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Preparedness to care</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Competency to care</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Caregiver strain</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Unmet needs of caregivers of brain tumour patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Intervention is a supportive educational intervention for caregivers. It will be in four parts and delivered in a sequential manner:
1. An initial telephone assessment of current unmet needs of the caregiver by research nurse.  This should take 20 minutes.
2. 7-14 days later there will be a single home visit where the research nurse will provide support and education around the issues that have arisen in the telephone assessment and baseline survey of unmet need. The research nurse will also deliver the information folder specified below. It is expected that these home visits may take 60-90 minutes.
3. Caregivers will be given a tabbed supportive and educational information resource file which is specifically tailored for the caregiver as appropriate for their identified unmet needs. New information will be provided to the caregiver to place in the folder if new unmet needs are identified.
4. Ongoing monthly telephone support and assessment of new needs as they arise. These will commence a month after the delivery of the intervention. These telephone assesments should take about 10 minutes unless prolonged by the participants.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive current usual care which is information that is currently freely available and some access to a cancer nurse coordinator with no specific tailoring or extra support.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Experience of caregiving (as measured on the either the preparedness to care, caregiver competence or caregiver strain index - whichever is identified as being most informative in the pilot study). The other tools will be relegated to secondary outcomes if they are feasible.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: baseline, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months for full assessment Monthly assessment of health care utilisation will be carried out over the telephone</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver Quality of life - cancer scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver Unmet Needs ( Partner and Caregiver Supportive Care Needs Scale or Brain Tumour Specific Supportive Care needs for Carers survey - whichever is identified in the pilot as being most informative)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver anxiety and Depression (Hospital anxiety and depression scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Distress thermometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health care utilisation checklist</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly  for 12 months in the monthly nurse led phone assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EQ-5D 3L as measured by care-reciepient once at baseline and proxy measures collected at all time points</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be self rated once by the care-recipient at baseline.
The caregiver will provide ongoing proxy ratings  at baseline, 6 weeks post intervention and at 3, 6, and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Karnofsky score as rated by nurse and caregiver</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly  for 12 months in the monthly nurse led phone assessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General Health Questionnaire (GHQ-12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 6 weeks, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Primary caregivers of patients with High Grade Glioma
Aged 18 and over
Fully competent, independent individuals with no mental, cognitive or functional disability and willing to comply with study guidelines.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>No concealment procedures. 
All participants are informed upfront that this is a randomised trial.
Participants will be identified by clinical staff at neurosurgical, radiation oncology and medical oncology outpatient departments while treating the care-receiver with chemoradiotherapy for high grade glioma. Potential participants will be provided with an information brochure.

Randomisation will take place at the School of Nursing, Midwifery and Paramedicine  at Curtin University. Randomisation will be stratified by site. Participants will be informed once randomised. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a computer sequence generation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/01/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/01/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>123</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>St John of God Hospital, Subiaco - Subiaco</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>The Chris O’Brien Lifehouse - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987, Perth, WA 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hospital Avenue
Nedlands 6009
Western Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Cancer Council of WA</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>15 Bedbrook Place, Shenton Park WA 6008, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked Bag 3, STRAWBERRY HILLS NSW 2012</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname />
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Faculty of Health Sciences, Curtin University, GPO Box U1987, Perth, WA, 6845</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>High grade glioma (HGG) is a term used to encompass grade III anaplastic astrocytomas, oligodendrogliomas and glioblastoma multiforme. This is a rapidly terminal, progressive, and significantly debilitating group of diseases which robs patients of function, cognition, and personality, making this a highly distressing disease for patients, families and carers. In addition to the general cancer related caregiving issues, the impact of the disease on the patients ability to function leads to reduced quality of life, increased stress and carer burden for their caregiver . The diagnosis of a brain tumour is particularly stressful for carers because the prognosis is dire and life expectancy short. These carers report increased stress and distress levels and decreased quality of life compared to carers of patients with cancers with a good prognosis. There are more than 200 problems and burdens identified by caregivers, which fall under several categories including: physical health problems, social problems and information needs, emotional problems and burdens related to responsibilities and impact on daily life.
Psychosocial interventions for caregivers in a range of situations have been developed with various aims including improving caregiver understanding and ability to care, self-efficacy, quality of life, stress reduction, and improving communication and relationships in the family. There is a paucity of information regarding the role or effect of interventions addressing the unmet needs of caregivers of patients with HGG.
Thus far this group has carried out two investigations into the experience and needs of patients with HGG and their caregivers. The first was a qualitative study of the needs of patients with HGG and their caregivers. Caregivers described a time of rapid change and a steep learning curve where they struggled with caring for partners with major disabilities and not knowing where to seek additional support or assistance (Halkett et al. 2010; McConigley et al. 2010). The second was a quantitative study (SCGH HREC 2006-146) which examined the experiences of 100 patient-carer dyads at three time points during the disease trajectory: during combined chemoradiotherapy, and 3 and 6 months later. 31% of caregivers reported moderate distress (DT score 5-6) and 31% reported extreme distress (score 7-10). Caregivers also
reported significantly more distress than patients (mean 5.1 vs. 4.1; paired t test p=0.01). Caregiver distress was associated with higher scores on the general health questionnaire (r=0.61, p&lt;0.001). The top 5 moderate/high caregiver unmet needs were: 1. accessing prognostic information; 2. accessing financial support and government benefits; 3. accessible hospital parking; 4. impact of caring on usual life; and 5. reducing stress in the patients life. These preliminary results will be presented in a poster at COSA in November 2012.
The development of our intervention is based on our preliminary data and the identification of several key components including the caregivers preparedness to care, sense of control, competence, self-efficacy, anxiety, depression and distress, social support, information, a sense of reward, meaningfulness, positive emotions, optimism, respite and relationship with the care-receiver. Our intervention is currently in the development phase and is aimed to cover all these areas. We are seeking support and advice regarding the development of the intervention from a variety of sources including medical oncologists, neurosurgeons, radiation oncologists, palliative care physicians, psychologists, social workers, nurses, experienced representatives from Carers WA and COGNO, as well as consumer representatives. The purpose of this project is to determine the feasibility and efficacy of this supportive-educational intervention for caregivers of patients with HGG.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Halkett, G. K. B., Lobb EA, Miller L, Shaw T, Moorin R, Long A, King A, Clarke J, Fewster S, Nowak AK. (2017) Feasibility Testing and Refinement of a Supportive Educational Intervention for Carers of Patients with High-Grade Glioma - a Pilot Study. J Cancer Educ. 2017 Feb 11. doi: 10.1007/s13187-017-1175-x. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>HREC SCGH
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands
WA 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013-172</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St John of God Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>12 Salvado Road 
Subiaco
Western Australia 6904</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>671</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/01/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room G71 East Wing
Edmund Blacket Building
Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC ref no:16/105 (HREC/16/POW/219)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prof Anna Nowak</name>
      <address>Department of Medical Oncology
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital 
Locked Bag 2012
Nedlands 
WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 1222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N/A</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ms Jenny Clarke</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences, Curtin University, GPO Box U1987, Perth, WA, 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 1757</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jenny.clarke@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Georgia Halkett</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences, Curtin University, GPO Box U1987, Perth, WA, 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 1762</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.halkett@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Georgia Halkett</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences, Curtin University, GPO Box U1987, Perth, WA, 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 1762</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.halkett@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>