<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320657">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/09/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/10/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000879268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study of the acute and chronic cognitive, neurocognitive and blood flow effects of polyphenols in middle aged volunteers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study of the acute and chronic cognitive, neurocognitive and blood flow effects of polyphenols in middle aged volunteers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive function</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular function</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Neuro-cognitive function</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>20 grams of dry blended chocolate drink mix will be administered in 200mL of water once daily for a total of 4 weeks.
 Participants will be allocated to receive one of the following treatments:
- Treatment 1 - polyphenol-free dark chocolate containing &lt;.5mg total flavanols
- Treatment 2 - standard dark chocolate containing 200mg total flavanols
- Treatment 3 - Acticoa dark chocolate containing 460mg total flavanols
This is both an acute and chronic study. On the first testing day, participants will undergo baseline testing and will then be administered one treatment. The acute effects will be tested 1 hour post dose. The chronic effects will be tested 4 weeks after consuming treatment once daily for 4 weeks. Participants will come for their testing session not having consumed their treatment for the day to measure the chronic effects. Baseline tests will reveal any chronic effects. Following this (on the same day), they will consume their last treatment and the acute/chronic effects will be measured.</interventions>
    <comparator>- Treatment 1 - polyphenol-free dark chocolate</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive performance measured using Cognitive Drug Research (CDR) computerised cognitive battery</outcome>
      <timepoint>ACUTE: 1 hour, 2.5 hours and 4 hours post dose

CHRONIC: 4 weeks after consuming chocolate treatment each day for 4 weeks

CHRONIC/ACUTE: 1 hour, 2.5 hours and 4 hours post dose on second visit (4 weeks after consumption)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiovascular function measured using Transcranial Doppler (TCD) ultrasound to measure blood flow in the middle cerebral artery and common corotid artery and the Sphygmocor (arterial stiffness) system</outcome>
      <timepoint>ACUTE: 2 hours post dose 
CHRONIC: 4 weeks after consuming chocolate treatment each day for 4 weeks
CHRONIC/ACUTE: 2 hours post dose on second visit (4 weeks after consumption)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neuro-cognitive performance using Steady State Topography (SST)</outcome>
      <timepoint>CHRONIC: 4 weeks (after consuming chocolate treatment each day for 4 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- non smoker 
- aged between 40 and 65 years 
- no history of anxiety, depression, psychiatric disorders or epilepsy 
- not taking any medication, herbal extracts, vitamin supplements or illicit drugs
- no health conditions that would effect food metabolism including the following: food allergies, kidney disease, liver disease and/or gastrointestinal diseases (e.g Irritable bowel syndrome, celiac disease, peptic ulcers)
- not pregnant or breast feeding.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- smoker
- history of anxiety, depression, psychiatric disorders or epilepsy 
- taking any medication, herbal extracts, vitamin supplements or illicit drugs
- health conditions that would effect food metabolism including the following: food allergies, kidney disease, liver disease and/or gastrointestinal diseases (e.g Irritable bowel syndrome, peptic ulcers)  
- pregnant or breast feeding. 
- Free from epilepsy and have no history of epilepsy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants responded to ads via community bulletin boards and local papers. Once they passed a phone screen, they came in for a practice session where they were introduced to the tests and informed consent was obtained. They were randomly allocated to a treatment group. The person who determined if a subject was eligible for inclusion in the trial was unaware, when this decision was made, to which group the subject would be allocated. Allocation was concealed by central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>A disinterested third party generated the randomisation list using a computerised random number sequence generator. Participants were allocated to receive 1 of 3 treatments.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, within-subjects design</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Barry Callebaut</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Aalstersestraat 122
B-9280 Lebbeke</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Belgium</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Barry Callebaut</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Aalstersestraat 122
B-9280 Lebbeke</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Belgium</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim for the current trial is to understand how polyphenols affect cognition, brain functioning and blood flow for both acute and chronic doses. We wish to explore the acute (single dose) and four-week (28 doses) neuro-cognitive effects of polyphenols in 72 healthy middle aged volunteers. The cognitive effects will be assessed using the CDR computerised cognitive assessment system and the neurophysiological effects will be measured using high spatial resolution electrical brain recordings measures by the Steady State Topography technique (SST) which has been pioneered at the Brain Sciences Institute and used in over 50 published studies. The cardiovascular effects will be measured using Transcranail Doppler Ultrasound to measure blood flow and the sphygmocor system to measure arterial stiffness</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Swinburne Univeristy Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 218
Hawthorn VIC 3122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>0708/156</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof Con Stough</name>
      <address>400 Burwood Rd
Hawthorn VIC 3122</address>
      <phone>613 9214 8167</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cstough@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof Con Stough</name>
      <address>400 Burwood Rd
Hawthorn VIC 3122</address>
      <phone>613 9214 8167</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cstough@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marni Kras</name>
      <address>400 Burwood Rd
Hawthorn VIC 3122</address>
      <phone>613 9214 5094</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mkras@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>