<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370972">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000867493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of 16-week Bikram yoga program on heart rate variability and cardiovascular disease risk factors in sedentary, stressed adults.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial examining the effects of a 16-week Bikram yoga program on high frequency heart rate variability (HRV), additional HRV outcomes, and cardiovascular disease risk factors in sedentary, stressed adults compared to a no-treatment control group.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Men and women aged between 18-64 were randomised into either the treatment group (yoga classes) or no-treatment control group. All participants were assessed at baseline (week 0) and completion (week 17) of the trial and were monitored weekly throughout the trial to record changes to lifestyle and/or health status. Baseline and completion assessments each included a 1.5 hour visit with the primary researcher to collect anthropometric, haemodynamic, fitness and psychological data, and a visit to a Capital Pathology collection centre in Canberra for a blood test. Participants were also required to complete a 7-day food diary prior to and after the trial to control for major changes to diet over the course of the trial.
Participants randomised to the treatment group were required to attend between 3 and 5 90-minute Bikram yoga classes per week for 16 weeks (participant could choose exact number of classes between 3-5 each week). Bikram yoga is a form of hatha yoga that takes place in a heated environment  (40 degrees celsius, 38-40% humidity). The sequence of postures is the same every class and the class is led with an instructional dialogue. The classes were held at two Bikram yoga centres in the Australian Capital Territory. Participants attended classes with the current members of both studios and classes were taught by certified Bikram yoga instructors. All sessions were supervised. Participants were required to sign in for every class (attendance data was collected electronically).</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomised to the control group continued with their current lifestyle for the duration of the trial. Upon completion they were given a 10-class pass to use at either of the two centres partaking in the trial. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>High frequency heart rate variability (HF HRV).HF HRV was assessed using ECG data produced by the SphygmoCor equipment and software (SphygmoCor, AtCor Medical Pty, Sydney, Australia).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0) and after the 16-week intervention at completion (week 17)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Additional frequency and time domains of HRV - low frequency HRV, LF:HF, total power, and RMSSD, SDNN, triangular index, pNN50. These measures were also assessed using the SphygmoCor system (SphygmoCor, Atcor Medical Pty, Sydney, Australia).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0) and after the 16-week intervention at completion (week 17)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total cholesterol
Fasting bloods were collected by Capital Pathology (accredited by NATA, facility number 3448)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (week 0) and after the 16-week intervention (week 17)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HDL
Fasting bloods were collected by Capital Pathology (accredited by NATA, facility number 3448)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0) and at completion after the 16-week intervention (week 17)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LDL
Fasting bloods were collected by Capital Pathology (accredited by NATA, facility number 3448)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0) and at completion after 16-week intervention (week 17)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting blood glucose
Fasting bloods were collected by Capital Pathology (accredited by NATA, facility number 3448)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0) and at completion after the 16-week intervention (week 17)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>C-reactive protein
Fasting bloods were collected by Capital Pathology (accredited by NATA, facility number 3448)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0) and at completion after the 16-week intervention (week 17)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body fat percentage
Body composition data was collected at University of Canberra using DEXA technology (GE Lunar Prodigy)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0) and at completion after the 16-week intervention (week 17)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference
Measured using soft  tape measure according to American College of Sports Medicine guidelines.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0) and at completion after the 16-week intervention (week 17)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiorespiratory fitness
VO2 was estimated from a sub maximal, modified Bruce treadmill protocol</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0) and at completion after the 16-week intervention (week 17)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived stress (measured by 10-item Perceived Stress Scale)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), midpoint (week 8) and at completion after the 16-week intervention (week 17)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life (measured by SF-36 questionnaire )</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), midpoint (week 8) and at completion after the 16-week intervention (week 17)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy (General Self Efficacy and Exercise Self Efficacy questionnaires)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0), midpoint (week 8) and at completion after the 16-week intervention (week 17)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Augmentation Index
Measured using SphygmoCor system with tonometer (SphygmoCor, Atcor Medical, Sydney, Australia)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (week 0) and at completion after the 16-week intervention (week 17)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult (&gt;18 years); sedentary (&lt;150min of continuous moderate-intensity exercise per week for at least 6 months); a score &gt;7 on the stress component of the 21-item depression-anxiety-stress scale (DASS-21); waist circumference as a risk factor  greater than 80cm (women) and greater than 94cm (men), able to attend 3-5 Bikram yoga classes per week for 16 weeks; no acute or chronic medical conditions which would make Bikram yoga potentially hazardous or primary outcomes impossible to assess (according to ACSM risk stratification guidelines); ability to communicate in English; willingness and cognitive ability to provide written informed consent to participate in the trial; access to internet and email.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Currently active; participation in Bikram yoga in the last 6 months or at any point consistently for &gt;2 years; diagnosed chronic diseases (cardiovascular disease, blood pressure &gt;140/90, uncontrolled diabetes or hyperlipidaemia); pregnancy; pacemaker.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>An investigator not involved in testing or the delivery of the intervention prepared the randomisation assignments, sealed them in opaque envelopes, and labeled them according to stratification in the order that they were to be handed out.  Group assignments were delivered to participants in person in the sealed, opaque envelopes upon the completion of baseline testing. Participant opened envelope and showed primary researcher the assignment and then their group assignment was recorded.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants were randomised via a computer-generated list (www.randomization.com) stratified by sex and age (&lt;50yr; &gt;50yr).  </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data derived from an HRV and aerobic exercise intervention in an apparently healthy adult cohort was used to compute statistical power a priori using the non-commercial statistical power analysis program G*Power. With an alpha level of 0.05, approximately 56 participants (28 per group) were required to provide 80% power to detect a statistically significant difference between groups. Recruitment was inflated to 68 participants to enable a 20% participant attrition rate.
All analyses were carried out using SPSS (IBM, Registered Trademark, Version 23). Primary analysis was via intention-to-treat with all participants included regardless of dropout or level of adherence.  Missing data at week 17 was imputed using the last observation carry forward method.  Outcomes data is presented as the mean +/- standard deviation with effect size and 95% confidence intervals.  Baseline characteristics were compared using t-tests and non-normally distributed data was transformed (Ln) prior to analysis with parametric methods.  Chi square tests were used to assess normality of non-continuous, descriptive variables at baseline.  Changes over time in all continuous outcome variables and covariates were determined by analysis of covariance (ANCOVA). Categorical variables will be analysed using logistic regression models.  Linear and multivariate regression analyses will be used to analyse associations between variables of interest.  A p value of &lt;0.05 is considered indicative of statistical significance.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>68</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>63</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/06/2015</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>4/01/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Miss Zoe Hewett</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Science and Health
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South NSW 2751</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Western Sydney University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Western Sydney University
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bikram Yoga Canberra</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>6/56 Hoskins Street
Mitchell ACT
2911</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bikram Yoga Kingston</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>27-29 Eyre St
Kingston ACT
2604</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Capital Pathology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 20
Woden ACT
2605</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Western Sydney University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South NSW 2751</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this parallel-arm RCT was to investigate the effects of a 16-week Bikram yoga program on the high frequency (HF) component of HRV and secondary related outcomes (i.e., additional HRV measures, anthopometric, haemodynamic, haematological, and psychological measures) in a population of sedentary, stressed adults. We hypothesised that engaging in 16 weeks of Bikram yoga, 3-5 times per week, would improve HF HRV, secondary measures of HRV, and associated CVD risk factors when compared with a no-treatment control group.
Participants were recruited via word of mouth, flyers, and social media and were screened via email/phone/in person for eligibility to participate. Sixty-three participants were enrolled in the trial with 34 in the control group and 29 in the experimental group. The experimental group was required to attend 3-5 Bikram yoga classes each week for 16 weeks, whereas the control group was asked to continue with their current lifestyle. Both groups were asked not to change their diet and exercise habits (aside from the intervention) throughout the trial period. Baseline measures and completion measures were assessed at week 0 and week 17 respectively. Body composition, waist circumference, HRV, blood pressure and psychological  questionnaires were done at a 1.5 hour appointment at University of Canberra with the primary investigator. Blood tests were done at various Capital Pathology collection centres in Canberra. Both testing sessions took place in a fasted state in the morning and were done on separate days to one another.
All participants were followed up with weekly via email/phone/in person to record changes in health status or lifestyle throughout the trial. Upon completion of the trial, participants had the option to fill out an exit survey to gain a better understanding of their experience as a participant.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Sydney University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked bag 1797
Penrith NSW
2751 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H10549</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Canberra Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Services Office
Locked Bag 1
University of Canberra
ACT 2601</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/06/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H10549 14/009174</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Zoe Hewett</name>
      <address>School of Science and Health
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South 2751
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61421786333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>13521266@student.westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Zoe Hewett</name>
      <address>School of Science and Health
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South 2751
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61421786333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>13521266@student.westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Zoe Hewett</name>
      <address>School of Science and Health
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South 2751
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61421786333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>13521266@student.westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Zoe Hewett</name>
      <address>School of Science and Health
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South 2751
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61421786333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>13521266@student.westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>