<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372070">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000059369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pregabalin for acute whiplash</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Targeting pro-nociceptive mechanisms to prevent chronic pain after whiplash injury - a randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Whiplash Injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will be provided with an advice booklet Whiplash Injury Recovery: A Self Help Guide (2nd edition) published by the Motor Accident Insurance Commission (MAIC), Qld. It provides information about whiplash; assurance about prognosis; advice to stay active and resume working as well as information on correct posture; pictorial descriptions of specific exercises for the neck and upper limbs and information on resuming functional daily activities. This second edition of the booklet was written based on consumer and health care professional feedback via focus groups. The booklet is based on the recommendations of the current Australian Guidelines for Whiplash Management.
 
Patients randomized to the experimental arm of the study will receive 1 pregabalin capsule (75 mg) orally twice daily with the first dose taken before discharge during the initial ED presentation. Patients will continue on this dose for 3 days after which time the dose could be titrated to 150mg twice daily if the previous dose is well tolerated. The dose could be further increased to 300 mg twice daily after the second week if 150 mg twice daily is well tolerated. The dose will be reduced to the previously tolerated level if the higher dose is not well tolerated after 3 days. The study medication will be continued for 28 days, after which a dose of 300 mg twice daily will be weaned to 150 mg twice daily for 3 days and then 75 mg twice daily for 3 days, a dose of 150 mg twice daily will be weaned to 75 mg twice daily for 6 days and a dose of 75 mg twice daily continued for 6 days. Dose de-escalation in lower maximum tolerated doses will use proportionately lower doses over the same time schedule.  The dose escalation/reduction regimen for our trial has been used in previous pregabalin trials. All patients will be asked to continue taking the medicines (active or placebo) for a period of 28 days with a subsequent 6 days of weaning. The prescription of pregabalin in this way is standard clinical practice.
Adherence will be measured by self-report in patient diaries and pill counts.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients in the control group will also receive the information booklet described above. A placebo will be administered as a control and this will be compared to the pregabalin drug administration.. Both drugs and administration regimes will be identical to ensure blinding. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neck pain intensity at 3 months post randomisation from baseline between the treatment groups. Neck pain intensity is measured on the continuous numeric rating scale (NRS) of 0 to 10, and will represent the patient's self-report of average pain intensity during last 24 hours.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Neck pain intensity will be assessed at 3 months post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.	Neck pain intensity (NRS 24 hours) at 6-and 12-month follow-up from baseline between the treatment groups;
</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 month and 12 month followup</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Neck Disability Index (NDI) scores 3,  -6 and 12-months from baseline, compared between the treatments </outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6 months and 12 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Pain Catastrophising Scale (PCS) scores at follow-up from baseline, compared between treatments</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the 5-week, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month follow ups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Between treatment differences in Posttraumatic Stress Diagnostic Scale (PDS) symptom score, measured during follow-up</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the 5-week, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month follow ups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Between treatment differences in Depression, Anxiety &amp; Stress scale (DASS), measured during follow-up</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the 5-week, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month follow ups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generic measure of health status scores (SF-12) during follow-up between the treatment groups</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the 5-week, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month follow ups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of proportion of patients who lodge a compensation claim during follow-up, between the treatment groups. This will be self-reported on the followup questionnaires</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the 5-week, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month follow ups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of doses of break through medication. Self reported by the patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the 5-week, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month follow ups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of pronociception - conditioned pain modulation. 
This will be measured via the change in pressure pain threshold measured in the neck (C5/6) and  lower limb (Tibialis Anterior) after immersion of the upper limb in cold water.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the 5-week, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month follow ups. Post randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of pronociception - temporal summation. This will be measured as the change in reported pain after repeated stimulation (X10 repetitions, performed 1 sec apart) with a weighted blunt probe over the C5/6 spinous process and tibialis anterior muscle.  Temporal summation is defined as the difference in pain ratings between the application of the 10th repetition and the 1st repetition.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the 5-week, 3-month, 6-month, 12-month follow ups. Post-randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Individuals with Grade II WAD and within 12 hours of injury. 
2. Experiencing at least moderate pain (VAS&gt;=5/10) on first measurement by ambulance or on arrival in ED. 
3. Age 18-65 years
4. Proficient in written and spoken English
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Known or suspected serious spinal pathology (e.g. metastatic disease of the spine); 
2. Confirmed fracture or dislocation at time of injury (WAD IV); 
3. WAD III (neurological compromise eg decreased reflexes, muscle power); 
4. Previous whiplash injury or neck pain condition requiring treatment; 
5. Patient Health Questionnaire-2 score of 3 or more
6. Patients using gabapentin/pregabalin; 
7. Patients with known peripheral neuropathy; 
8. Known hypersensitivity to pregabalin use (hives, blisters, rash, dyspnea and wheezing); 
9. History of renal insufficiency; liver disease?
10. Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding;
11. History of psychiatric illness or substance abuse; 
12. Inability to speak and write in English (participants will be required to complete questionnaires written in English only).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All analyses will be conducted on an intention to treat basis and by a statistician blinded to group allocation. The primary outcome of change in neck pain intensity at 3 months from baseline will be compared between the treatment groups using standard analysis of variance technique, and the 95% confidence intervals of changes between the groups will be presented. Analyses of data from earlier studies and our simulation studies suggest approximate normality of the distribution of change in intensity score. Missing data will be examined for its randomness and addressed with multiple imputations, if required.  

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Gold Coast University Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Menzies Health Institute of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>G40 Griffith Health Centre, Level 8.86
Gold Coast campus
Griffith University QLD 4222</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC Centre of Research Excellence in Road Traffic Injury Recovery</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421 Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Menzies Health Institute of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>G40 Griffith Health Centre, Level 8.86
Gold Coast campus
Griffith University QLD 4222</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of this study is to conduct a randomised controlled trial examining the effectiveness of pregabalin to prevent chronic pain following whiplash injury in at-risk individuals. The secondary aims are to: 1) Investigate the effectiveness of pregabalin to decrease disability, depression, posttraumatic stress symptoms, pain catastrophizing and measures of pro-nociception and 2) To conduct an economic evaluation of the pregabalin intervention. 
We hypothesise that pregabalin used in acute whiplash injury will prevent or modulate pro-nociceptive mechanisms and improve health outcomes for this treatment resistant condition. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Gold Coast Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee (HRECs)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 Hospital Boulevard
Southport QLD 4215</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QGC/296</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michele Sterling </name>
      <address>Recover Injury Research Centre
Griffith University 
Gold Coast Campus
Parklands Drive
Southport QLD 4222
</address>
      <phone>61 488 196 862 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.sterling@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jane Nikles</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health Sciences
Griffith University Logan campus
University Drive
Meadowbrook QLD 4131</address>
      <phone>61 408 599 033</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.nikles@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jane Nikles</name>
      <address>School of Allied Health Sciences
Griffith University Logan campus
University Drive
Meadowbrook QLD 4131</address>
      <phone>61 408 599 033</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.nikles@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>