<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364431">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000689774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised double blinded controlled pilot trial investigating the effect dietary nitrate in the treatment of acute decompensated heart failure.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised double blinded controlled pilot trial investigating the effect dietary nitrate in the treatment of acute decompensated heart failure.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIl</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The dietary nitrate will be in the form of a commercially available beetroot supplement manufactured from organic beetroot by James White Drinks (UK). It is a 70ml preparation that contains 0.4g of dietary nitrate. The researchers have no financial relationship with James White Drinks.

For this study the investigational product and placebo control will be sourced directly from the manufacturer in the UK.

Study Frequency - 5 days of treatment, once daily for 5 days 
 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo

The placebo control is also manufactured by the same company and is a nitrate depleted version and is indistinguishable from the nitrate containing preparation</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary hypothesis in this study is that dietary nitrate supplementation will improve vascular function in ADHF patients.

Assessment of outcome - improvement in symptoms via KCCQ, Endopat tool  to assess vascular function, </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 5</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary end point is overall treatment success . This composite parameter has been widely used in HF trials. Outcomes are defined as treatment success, treatment failure, or no change in the patients condition. Success is defined as patient-reported moderate or marked improvement in dyspnoea at 5 days, in the absence of any criterion for failure. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 5</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age  18-75 years 
Acute decompensated HF requiring hospitalization (at the discretion of the treating physician), reflected by clinical signs or symptoms of peripheral or pulmonary congestion 
NYHAC III or IV
And LVEF less than 40% (either previously documented or documented at admission)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Age between 18, and 75
Hypotension (BP less than 90)
inotropic therapy
anticipated need for LVAD or ECMO within 48 hrs
endotracheal intubation/ventilation
cardiac or other solid organ transplantation
STEMI at presentation
suspected sepsis
arrhyhthmia as a primary cause for ADHF
Allergy to Beetroot
Pregnancy
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based upon our data and the above hypothesis, with power 80% and the null hypothesis set for rejection at p less than 0.05 we calculate that we require n equals 13 per group. Based on our previous experience we anticipate a drop-out rate of up to 50% per group due to a variety of factors (eg conversion to inotropic therapy, patient withdrawal, loss to follow up, unplanned discharge) hence we request approval of a total of 40 patients. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/01/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>7/01/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>1</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Alfred Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road, Heart Centre, Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Alfred Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The trial will invite patients at the Alfred Hospital, Melbourne, Victoria presenting with acute decompensated heart failure to participate in a study of a dietary supplement (Beetroot extract - Dietary Nitrate) within 48 hours of their hospital admission. 
Heart failure is a condition where the heart fails to provide enough blood pumping power for the needs of normal body function. At times the condition may worsen significantly leading to fluid retention, low blood pressure, kidney failure and breathlessness, which usually each requires hospitalization. Currently there are limited treatment options available for these patients and there is a high risk of further hospitalization or death in subsequent months after the patients admission to hospital.
In this study we propose to study the effects of dietary nitrate in th patients described above. There is a growing body of evidence that dietary nitrate in the form of concentrated beetroot supplementation has beneficial cardiovascular effects including lowering blood pressure and enhances exercise performance during sub-maximal exercise. Forty patients will be invited to participate in the trial. After obtaining informed consent, twenty patients will be randomly assigned to treatment with oral Dietary Nitrate (70ml concentrated beetroot juice, manufactured by James White UK) or nitrate depleted placebo once daily for five days. This is in addition to any other medication prescribed by their treating doctor. 
At enrolment the patients will be educated and counselled about the trial and the intervention medication. Various parameters will be monitored on a daily basis, including objective and subjective symptom review, observations, blood vessel function, weight, kidney function, and medication requirement. Blood samples will also be taken and stored for analysis. We will contact the patient by telephone after 30 days to ask about their health.
The primary objective of the trial is to see whether the administration of dietary nitrate will improve blood vessel function and overall treatment outcomes.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Research &amp; Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>194/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/06/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Kaye</name>
      <address>The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 3263</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.kaye@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joshua Martin</name>
      <address>The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2948</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.martin@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joshua Martin</name>
      <address>The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2948</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.martin@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Vivian Mak</name>
      <address>The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria 3004, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2948</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 2162</fax>
      <email>v.mak@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>