<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370469">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000533392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>What brain waves indicate conscious response during anaesthesia?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Electroencephalographic markers of behavioural responsiveness during anaesthesia in adults undergoing airway surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1181-5561 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>EMBRACE  (Electroencephaolgraphic Markers of Behavioural Responsiveness during Anaesthesia: Consciousness Explored)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anaesthesia
Awareness</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Level of consciousness will be assessed using the behavioural response to the command ((patient name, if you can hear me, squeeze my hand)
The exposures will be slow intravenous induction of general anaesthesia, and then the steps involved in the airway surgery surgery itself, and then emergence from anaesthesia.
Behavioural responses will be checked at regular intervals throughout anaesthetic induction, surgery and emergence in conjunction with continuous multichannel EEG recording </interventions>
    <comparator>N/A</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EEG markers.  Corresponding multichannel EEG epochs will be analysed for spectral measures, connectivity measures, entropy and other putative markers of consciousness/unconsciousness</outcome>
      <timepoint>EEG recordings will be continuous from induction of anaesthesia to emergence from anaesthesia.  Specific epochs of interest will include:  
Loss of consciousness
Surgical stimulation
Episodes of spontaneous movement
Return of consciousness 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite autonomic responses (heart rate variability (from continuous ECG recordings) and galvanic skin responses (continuous sensor))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuous monitoring from induction of anaesthesia to emergence from anaesthesia</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Behavioural response to verbal command by an observer ('X (patient's name), if you can hear me, squeeze my hand') assessed by observer noting whether or not their hand was squeezed</outcome>
      <timepoint>Verbal commands will be given throughout the induction of anaesthesia (every 30 seconds), maintenance(every 5 minutes) and emergence of anaesthesia (every 30 seconds).  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reflex motor responses to painful stimuli</outcome>
      <timepoint>There will be continuous observation for movements which could occur following any painful stimulus; an observer will record the time and a description of any movements observed
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults undergoing airway surgery at Waikato Hospital</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability to provide informed consent
Inability to follow commands appropriately preoperatively</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Analysis will be done using MATLAB software.  We shall be testing temporal and spatial EEG changes across transitions of responsiveness.  We shall be making within and between individual comparisons to determine the most sensitive and specific EEG markers of unresponsiveness.
The number of participants required was calculated using findings from a volunteer study to guide the required sample size to achieve 80% power with alpha type 1 error risk 0.05 for paired t-test comparisons of a EEG coherence measure across transitions of consciousness.  We increased sample size over and above the minimum suggested by these calculations to account for a more heterogeneous study population and less tightly controlled anaesthetic regime</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>11/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Waikato</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Waikato Hospital Dept of Anaesthesia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Selwyn Street and Pembroke Street, Waikato Hospital, Hamilton 3204</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Waikato Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Selwyn Street and Pembroke Street, Waikato Hospital, Hamilton 3204</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian and New Zealand College of Anaesthetists</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>630 St Kilda Rd., Melbourne VIC 3004, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim
To evaluate electroencephalographic (EEG) markers of behavioural responsiveness during anaesthesia, providing insights into the mechanisms of loss and return of behavioural responsiveness during anaesthesia induction, noxious stimulation and emergence from anaesthesia

Significance
Awareness under anaesthesia is a rare but important complication of anaesthesia associated with significant negative psychological sequelae.  The incidence of awareness with recall is well established at approximately 1 case per 1000 anaesthetic events.  The ability of currently used depth of anaesthesia monitors to prevent awareness with recall is contentious, and whilst processed values correlate well with pharmacological levels or effect site concentrations of anaesthetic agents, their ability to detect behavioural responsiveness during anaesthesia as revealed by isolated forearm testing is poor. This is perhaps due to their reliance upon frontal EEG measurement and analysis. 

Recent studies in healthy volunteers using functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) and multichannel EEG have identified key changes in regions of the cortex associated with loss of behavioural responsiveness during anaesthesia. In particular there is growing evidence that a key marker of consciousness is the electroencephalographic connectivity between frontal and parietal regions of the brain.

Hypothesis
Loss of fronto-parietal connectivity as measured from the EEG results in loss of behavioural responsiveness to command during anaesthesia. Return of behavioural responsiveness during noxious stimulation or emergence from anaesthesia requires return of fronto-parietal connectivity. 

Objectives
1.	To evaluate multichannel EEG markers of behavioural responsiveness to command
2.	To evaluate multichannel EEG markers of spontaneous motor response to noxious stimuli
3.	To explore the relationships between cortical arousal and autonomic nervous system responses

Methods 
Prospective observational cohort study of 60 patients undergoing microlaryngoscopy and airway surgery.  Key features will be a slow controlled induction of anaesthesia to maintain spontaneous ventilation.  Multichannel EEG and haemodynamic recordings will be taken continuously.  Behavioural responsiveness will be checked by command at multiple time points during induction, emergence and during noxious stimuli. Spontaneous motor responses will also be recorded.  The EEG recordings will be analysed using MATLAB software including spectral analysis, entropy and connectivity measures and relationships between EEG markers and behavioural responsiveness and non-responsiveness will be assessed using appropriate statistical tests.
 
Benefits
Ultimately we hope our findings will contribute to the development of improved depth of anaesthesia monitoring.  We will obtain a rich dataset which can be further analysed to gain insights into mechanism of anaesthesia, interactions between hypnotic and analgesic agents and relationships between cortical arousals, EEG patterns and autonomic responses in the presence and absence of verbal and noxious stimuli. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health and Disabilty Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Health and Disability Ethics Committees
Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/STH/134</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amy Gaskell</name>
      <address>Dept of Anaesthesia
Waikato Hospital 
Private Bag 3200
Corner Pembroke Selwyn St
Hamilton
3204</address>
      <phone>+64 78398899</phone>
      <fax>+64 7 8398761</fax>
      <email>amy.gaskell@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amy Gaskell</name>
      <address>Dept of Anaesthesia
Waikato Hospital 
Private Bag 3200
Corner Pembroke Selwyn St
Hamilton
3204</address>
      <phone>+64 78398899</phone>
      <fax>+64 7 8398761</fax>
      <email>amy.gaskell@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amy Gaskell</name>
      <address>Dept of Anaesthesia
Waikato Hospital 
Private Bag 3200
Corner Pembroke Selwyn St
Hamilton</address>
      <phone>+64 7 8398899</phone>
      <fax>+64 7 8398761</fax>
      <email>amy.gaskell@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amy Gaskell</name>
      <address>Dept of Anaesthesia
Waikato Hospital 
Private Bag 3200
Corner Pembroke Selwyn St
Hamilton</address>
      <phone>+64 7 8398899</phone>
      <fax>+64 7 8398761</fax>
      <email>amy.gaskell@waikatodhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>