<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372717">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000562370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A comparison of arterial and blood gas analyses in sleep studies</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Gas Analysis in Sleep study: a comparison of arterial and blood gas analyses in sleep study participants</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1195-2949</utrn>
    <trialacronym>GAS Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hypoventilation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A venous blood gas will be taken as paired with each arterial blood gas (generally two per patient in a one night sleep study at the commencement and end of the study). Transcutaneous measurements of CO2, if taken as part of the sleep study, will also be recorded, along with the time between blood samples and relevant personal information.
The venous and arterial blood tests will be taken by nursing staff, sleep scientists and occasionally doctors where appropriate.</interventions>
    <comparator>The study compares the values obtained from venous and arterial blood gas measurements and non-invasive percutaneous measurements. Each patient provides both "treatment" and "control" data.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between arterial and venous blood gas carbon dioxide tensions in terms of absolute and relative bias (a composite outcome). This is assessed statistically by comparing the values from arterial and venous blood gases.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time blood gases would otherwise be taken for the sleep study, which is generally at the start of the study (before sleep) and the end of the study (upon waking in the morning).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between arterial and venous blood gas carbon dioxide tensions in terms of a Bland-Altman plot and 95% limits of agreement. This is assessed statistically by comparing the values from arterial and venous blood gases.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time blood gases would otherwise be taken for the sleep study, which is generally at the start of the study (before sleep) and the end of the study (upon waking in the morning).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of the difference of (percutaneous carbon dioxide vs venous carbon dioxide measurements) and (percutaneous carbon dioxide vs arterial carbon dioxide measurements)  as a single endpoint. This is assessed statistically by comparing the values from arterial and venous blood gases and the percutaneous carbon dioxide measurement recorded at the time of taking the blood gases.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time blood gases would otherwise be taken for the sleep study, which is generally at the start of the study (before sleep) and the end of the study (upon waking in the morning).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Data modelling to illustrate any evident consistent relationships between venous and ABG pCO2 when measured twice in the same patient over the course of the sleep study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time blood gases would otherwise be taken for the sleep study, which is generally at the start of the study (before sleep) and the end of the study (upon waking in the morning).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Data modelling to illustrate how the pvCO2-paCO2 relationship is affected by pH, haemoglobin, oxygen saturation, bicarbonate or a combination of these.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time blood gases would otherwise be taken for the sleep study, which is generally at the start of the study (before sleep) and the end of the study (upon waking in the morning).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between arterial and venous blood gas pH in terms of a Bland-Altman plot and 95% limits of agreement. This is assessed statistically by comparing the values from arterial and venous blood gases.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time blood gases would otherwise be taken for the sleep study, which is generally at the start of the study (before sleep) and the end of the study (upon waking in the morning).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between arterial and venous blood gas pH in terms of absolute and relative bias (a composite outcome). This is assessed statistically by comparing the values from arterial and venous blood gases.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time blood gases would otherwise be taken for the sleep study, which is generally at the start of the study (before sleep) and the end of the study (upon waking in the morning).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients having a diagnostic, continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) or ventilation sleep study which includes arterial blood gas analysis.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy, inability to consent, outside age group</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The trial is randomised only as to the order of ABG and VBG collection, but participants are not randomised to a control group [there was no option above]. Patients will be allocated by sealed-envelope selection. Envelopes will be opaque and shuffled as well as is practicable.</concealment>
    <sequence>Envelopes will be opaque and shuffled as well as is practicable.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Blinding will not be practicible.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Mean age and the percentage of tests from males will be reported.
Tests will be done for normality of data distribution. (eg. gladder in Stata)
Repeated-measures ANCOVA will be used for the primary analysis of pvCO2-paCO2 controlling for within-subject correlation against the hypothesized 0mmHg and forms the basis for the sample size calculation above.
Linear regression will provide the absolute and relative bias of pvCO2 vs paCO2, reporting the constant and gradient of the derived equation and the r2 value. Similar statistics can be performed for the relationship between (paCO2 vs ptCO2) and (pvCO2 vs ptCO2).
Collected data is to be used to test equation/s for estimating paCO2 from pvCO2 and other data collected in this study (in particular the pulse oximetry reading). Multivariate linear regressions with co-variates be used to explore the hypothesis of the impact of variables [saO2  svO2] and [saO2  svO2]*Hb on the degree of difference in paCO2 and estimated values.
A Bland-Altman bias plot, linear regression/ MANCOVA, 95% limits of agreement, F-tests of co-variates and a comparison of correlation coefficients (using Fishers z transformation and its variants such as corcor in Stata) will be used to test differences between true and estimated values of paCO2.
Similar statistics will be performed for pH, bicarbonate and base-excess where appropriate.
A pre-specified subgroup of patients with a pCO2 &gt;60mmHg may be expanded upon.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>7/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>8/07/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg VIC 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Austin Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg VIC 3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Institute for Breathing and Sleep</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg VIC 3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Institute for Breathing and Sleep</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg VIC 3084</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients having sleep/CPAP/ventilation (SCV) studies for chronic respiratory failure often require arterial blood to be taken for measurement of blood oxygen, pH and carbon dioxide measurement - so called arterial blood gases (ABGs). These measurements are used to assist in 
1.	identifying inadequate breathing
2.	determining need for assisted ventilation in patients with known or possible ventilatory disorders (eg chronic respiratory or neuromuscular disease or reduced ventilatory capacity associated with obesity ( obesity hypoventilation syndrome) .
3.	providing information to assist in modification of ventilator settings in such patients. 
An arterial blood sample is somewhat more difficult to obtain and generally believed to be more painful than a venous sample (venous blood gases (VBGs)), but there is currently no evidence that VBGs can adequately replace the role of ABGs in this setting.
The project will involve taking a venous blood sample for VBGs at the same time as the standard arterial blood sample (for ABGs) from patients already having SCV studies already including ABGs. The results from the arterial and venous samples will be compared. The study will involve an additional paired blood test for each ABG (estimated two per patient), during the same visit and should take minimal extra time (estimated 10 minutes total). At the end of the study we will compare the ABG and VBG measurements to see if we can use venous gases as a reliable alternative to ABGs in future. The data may also be used to see if we can use an equation to better approximate the arterial values from VBGs and if there is a consistent relationship between VBGs and transcutaneous measurements (across skin) of carbon dioxide, which are already being measured.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg VIC 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/03/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/Austin/441</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine McDonald</name>
      <address>Austin Health
145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61394965000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.mcdonald@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine McDonald</name>
      <address>Austin Health
145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61394965000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.mcdonald@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Steven Lindstrom</name>
      <address>Austin Health
145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg VIC 3084</address>
      <phone>+61394965000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drsjlindstrom@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>