<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370591">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000560493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing the clinical efficacy of internet-delivered cognitive behavioural therapy for perinatal anxiety and depression to treatment as usual.
Study 1: The Perinatal MUMentum Program: Pregnancy Course</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing the clinical efficacy of internet-delivered cognitive behavioural therapy for perinatal anxiety and depression to treatment as usual.
Study 1: The Perinatal MUMentum Program: Pregnancy Course</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety during pregnancy
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression during pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is a randomised controlled trial comparing the clinical efficacy of an internet-based cognitive behavioural therapy (iCBT) program for maternal anxiety and/or depression during pregnancy versus treatment as usual (TAU) control.  Individuals will apply for Study 1 if they are currently pregnant (&lt;30 weeks). Participants will be randomly allocated to Group 1 or Group 2, Group 1 will receive a 4-week intervention program (The Perinatal MUMentum Program: Pregnancy Course), while Group 2 will participate in a 9-week waiting period before gaining access to the program.

Group 1: The internet-based intervention program for Study 1 consists of a 3-lesson iCBT pregnancy course. The course is completed over a 4-week period, with one lesson released per week (7 days) for the first 3 weeks. The course describes the experiences of two fictional female characters who learn to recognise and manage their symptoms of anxiety and depression by using cognitive and behavioural skills and principles. Each lesson will take approximately 45-60 minutes to complete and contains an illustrated lesson, a lesson summary with practical exercises and activities, and extra resources. Participants are encouraged to spend 3-4 hours per week reviewing the lesson content and implementing the practical skills and exercises. Participants are not required to complete all components of the lesson at once, but are required to view the illustrated lesson online and download the lesson summary in order to proceed with the program. There is a 5-day waiting period between lessons to ensure participants spend enough time completing each lesson before moving on. Adherence and time spent per lesson is monitored by computer software, with automated emails sent to participants if they have not accessed or completed the lesson. Automated notification emails are also sent to participants when the next lesson is available (5 days after completion of previous lesson).</interventions>
    <comparator>All participants randomised to the control group (TAU) will receive usual care with their GP or perinatal health practitioner. Over the 9-week waiting period, participants will be required to complete 3 sets of online questionnaires, which enquire about their mental health (e.g. anxiety, depression, stress etc.). At conclusion of the 9-week waiting period, participants will be offered access to the Perinatal MUMentum Program via a secure website (which includes both the pregnancy and postpartum course materials and resources).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety severity: Change in scores from baseline on the Generalised Anxiety Disorder 7-point scale (GAD-7).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-treatment (Week 5)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression severity: Change in scores from baseline on the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-treatment (Week 5)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pathological worry severity: Changes in scores from baseline on the Penn State Worry Questionnaire (PSWQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-treatment (Week 5); 1-month follow-up; 12-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perinatal anxiety: Changes in scores from baseline on the Perinatal Anxiety Screening Scale (PASS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-treatment (Week 5); 1-month follow-up; 12-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perinatal depression: Changes in scores from baseline on the Edinburgh Postnatal Depression Scale (EPDS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-treatment (Week 5); 1-month follow-up; 12-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General psychological distress severity: Changes in scores from baseline on the Kessler 10-item scale (K-10).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-treatment (Week 5); 1-month follow-up; 12-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant satisfaction with the intervention program on the Credibility/Expectancy Questionnaire (CEQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-treatment (Week 5); 1-month follow-up; 12-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional impairment/disability: Changes in scores from baseline on the World Health Organization Disability Assessment Schedule 2.0 (WHODAS-II).

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-treatment (Week 5); 1-month follow-up; 12-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety severity: Change in scores from baseline on the Generalised Anxiety Disorder 7-point scale (GAD-7).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-month follow-up; 12-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression severity: Change in scores from baseline on the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-month follow-up; 12-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women who are currently pregnant (&lt;30 weeks) and whose online self-report questionnaire scores indicate a clinical level of anxiety (GAD-7 &gt;9) and/or depression (PHQ-9 &gt;9) will be included in this study. Participants must also:
- Live in Australia
- 18 years of age or older
- Fluent in written and spoken English
- Have a computer with internet access, up to date browser, and printer
- Willing to provide the name and contact details of their general practitioner 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if they do not live in Australia, are under 18 years of age at application, are not fluent in written and spoken English, and do not have a computer with internet access, up to date browser, and printer.

Participants who self-report a diagnosis of a psychotic mental illness (Bipolar, Schizophrenia), substance abuse or dependence, severe depression (PHQ-9 score of &gt;23), or current suicidality will also be excluded. 

Women who are more than 30 weeks pregnant will be excluded, as will participants that report a medically high-risk pregnancy. Participants that do not provide their GP contact details at application will also be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomly allocated online by computer generated software to either Group 1 or Group 2. Allocation will be generated  through the use of computer software by an independent member of the research team, and will be concealed from the study investigators, with the number sequence uploaded by an independent IT staff member.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation sequence will be generated via www.random.org</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation: A pre-to-post-treatment improvement of effect size (ES) 1.0 is expected for the iCBT treatment group on the primary measures (PHQ-9; GAD-7). This group is also expected to improve more than the treatment as usual (TAU) control group by an ES of 0.8. Assuming an ES &gt; 0.8, power at 80%, and alpha set at .05, a sample size of 25 per group is needed to detect a between-groups effect size difference of 0.8. A sample of N=80 will allow for attrition. 

Analysis Plan: All analyses will be undertaken using intention to treat mixed model and linear analyses. Relationships between observations at different occasions will be modelled with the appropriate covariance matrix. Planned contrasts will be used to compare changes between pre-treatment and post-treatment, and 1-month and 12-month follow-ups. Planned pairwise comparisons will be used to compare between-groups at post-treatment, and follow-up and effect sizes will be calculated (Hedges g) to measure the size of the between-groups difference on primary and secondary outcome measures.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/09/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hospital for Women - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst 
NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>HCF Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 4242
Sydney NSW 2001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Anxiety and depression are common in the perinatal period (i.e. during pregnancy and the first year after childbirth). Postnatal depression and anxiety disorders affect around 15% of women, with up to 45% of cases beginning in pregnancy (e.g., Austin et al., 2010). 

Early evidence shows that iCBT is effective for reducing postnatal depression, anxiety, general distress and parental distress  (Danaher et al., 2013; Pugh, Hadjistavropoulos, &amp; Dirkse, in press). Tailored iCBT programs are needed to provide women in the perinatal period with practical coping skills to manage depression and anxiety symptoms, as well as deal with the unique difficulties they may face which can impact on depression and anxiety (e.g. complications during pregnancy and/or delivery, body image, difficulty breastfeeding, an unsettled baby, and unrealistic expectations about motherhood).

The primary purpose of this trial is to evaluate the clinical efficacy of a newly developed internet-delivered cognitive behaviour therapy (iCBT) program, the  Perinatal MUMentum Program. This iCBT program has been tailored to maternal anxiety and depression experienced during the perinatal period. The MUMentum Program consists of two 3-lesson courses: Pregnancy and Postpartum. The courses can be completed separately or in conjunction with each other and have been designed in consideration of several key issues experienced during the perinatal period when seeking and completing treatment, including a lack of time, fatigue, and stigma.

The main hypotheses to be tested for Study 1 (Pregnancy Course) are as follows:
1.	Internet cognitive behavioural therapy delivered during pregnancy will  significantly reduce symptoms of anxiety, depression, distress and disability. 
2.	Internet cognitive behavioural therapy delivered during pregnancy will be significantly more effective than the control group at reducing symptoms of anxiety, depression, distress and disability.

It is hoped that the findings of this trial will provide further information regarding the efficacy and acceptability of the Perinatal MUMentum Program in reducing maternal anxiety and depression experienced during the perinatal period.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.virtualclinic.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil as yet</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital HREC (EC00140)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincent's Hospital Research Office
Level 6, de Lacy Building
390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/SVH/63</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370591-Letter - HREC FINAL approval at HREC Exec meeting 19 04 2016 OOS - 16 046.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression (CRUfAD)
4, The O'Brien Centre, St Vincent's Hospital, 394-404 Victoria St, Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1400</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Siobhan Loughnan</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression (CRUfAD)
4, The O'Brien Centre, St Vincent's Hospital, 394-404 Victoria St, Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1434</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>Siobhan.Loughnan@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Siobhan Loughnan</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression (CRUfAD)
4, The O'Brien Centre, St Vincent's Hospital, 394-404 Victoria St, Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1434</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>Siobhan.Loughnan@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Siobhan Loughnan</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression (CRUfAD)
4, The O'Brien Centre, St Vincent's Hospital, 394-404 Victoria St, Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1434</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>Siobhan.Loughnan@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>