<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81891">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/03/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/03/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000162415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Specialised nutrition in head and neck cancer surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised Phase I/II trial to investigate the effects of immune-modulating nutritional supplements provided perioperatively to non-malnourished patients undergoing surgery for head and neck cancer on postoperative immune status and inflammation.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients with cancer of the oral cavity, pharynx or larynx.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Head and neck</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Three-arm study:

IMPACT group receives 5 days standard ORAL IMPACT (Novartis, 3 sachets/d, each sachet of 74g contains 3.8g arginine, 0.4 g nucleotides, 1.0 g eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) and docosahexaenoic acid (DHA)) preoperatively and standard enteral IMPACT postoperatively commencing as soon as possible, within clinical guidelines, after surgery up to full caloric requirements for 5 days.
Glutamine group receives 5 days oral lutamine (30g/d, Glutaminox, Oxford Nutrition) preoperatively and glutamine enriched (30g/d) standard enteral feed postoperatively commencing as soon as possible, within clinical guidelines, after surgery up to full caloric requirements for 5 days.
.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group receives standard nutritional therapy, typically no preoperative nutritional supplements and standard postoperative enteral feed. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative immune and inflammatory status which includes C-reactive protein, total lymphocytes, CD3, CD4, CD8, immunoglobulin G (IgG), immunoglobulin M (IgM), immunoglobulin (IgA), tumor necrosis factor-alpha (TNF-alpha) and interleukin-6 (IL-6).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on postoperative days 1, 3, 5 and 7</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative infectious complications </outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the first 30 postoperative days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in total body protein </outcome>
      <timepoint>From baseline to postoperative day 10.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Scheduled for radical resection of cancers of the oral cavity, pharynx and larynx.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded if pregnant, diabetic, on immunosuppressants, have had previous wide-field radical radiotherapy for head and neck cancer, or have greater than 10% weight loss.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is by sequentially numbered sealed envelope.</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation with randomisation sequence generated by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/03/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Mark Izzard</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Otolaryngology, Auckland City Hospital, Private Bag 92024, Auckland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Greenlane Research and Education Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level3, Auckland City Hospital</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Lindsay Plank</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Surgery, University of Auckland, Private Bag 92019, Auckland</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a study of specialised nutrition in people having surgery for head and neck cancer.

Who is it for?
You can join this study if you are undergoing major surgery for head and neck cancer and your doctor thinks you are not malnourished. 

Trial details
Participants will be randomly divided into three groups. The different groups receive either:
 preoperatively 5 days of oral IMPACT solution and postoperatively IMPACT enteral feeding. (IMPACT contains a number of supplements that may help the immune system.)
 preoperatively 5 days of oral glutamine supplements and postoperative glutamine enteral feeding. (Glutamine may help the immune system.)
 standard nutritional supplementation which usually involves no preoperative supplements and standard postoperative enteral feeding.

The study looks at the effects of the different regimes. In particular it investigates postoperative immune and inflammatory status measured by blood tests on Days 1, 3, 5 and 7 after surgery.  

Standard postoperative care for people undergoing major surgery for head and neck cancer includes intensive nursing and medical care and enteral nutritional support. The trial includes different types of supplements which try and help the immune system. One of the trials uses the supplement IMPACT which contains a number of different supplements and the other uses glutamine.  The supplements are given orally before the surgery and enterally after the surgery. The blood test results will provide the foundation for a larger scale study with infectious complications and nutritional status as major endpoints.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Auckland City Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/02/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTY/0610/094.</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Mark Izzard</name>
      <address>Department of Otolaryngology
Auckland City Hospital
Private Bag 92024
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 6309943 ext 4388</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marki@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Lindsay Plank</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery
University of Auckland
Auckland Hospital Support Building
Park Road
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3074935</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.plank@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>