<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366426">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000598684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Sequentially applied transcranial magnetic stimulation in the treatment of obsessive compulsive disorder</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Do patients with obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD) who receive active, sequentially applied transcranial magnetic stimulation experience reductions in obsessive and compulsive symptoms over and above patients who receive sham stimulation. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1157-4271</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obsessive compulsive disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients with OCD will receive 15 daily sessions (Monday to Friday) of repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation over three weeks. Repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation will be administered using a Magstim Rapidstim system with a 70mm, figure of eight air cooled coil applied to three brain regions sequentially. A fitted cap based on the accepted 10-20 electroencephalography system will be used to identify the three brain regions. The cap will be centred using several landmarks including the distance between the left and right ears (inter-aural distance) and between the bridge of the brow and protrusion in the back of the head (nasion to inion). As the cap is pre-marked, we will be stimulating the left orbitofrontal cortex at coordinate Fp1 using low frequency parameters of 1 Hz using 80% of active motor threshold for 10 minutes (600 pulses), the right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex at the coordinate F4 using high frequency parameters of 10hz for 5 seconds, with an inter-train interval of 25 seconds for 10 minutes (20 trains in total) using 110% of resting motor threshold and the supplementary motor area which will be defined as 15% of the distance between the nasion and inion anterior to the centre point using low frequency parameters of 1Hz at 110% of resting motor threshold for 10 minutes. Overall, patients will be required to attend 40 minute sessions which includes treatment administration and set-up. </interventions>
    <comparator>Sham repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation will be applied to the left orbitofrontal cortex, the right dorsolateral prefrontal cortex and supplementary motor area sequentially using the same coordinates outlined above. Sham treatment will be administered using a Magstim 70mm, figure of eight, air cooled sham coil that is identical to the look, sound and percussion of the real 70mm coil. However, the sham coil does not have any conducting material and does not induce or stimulate the brain.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient symptom severity will be measured using the Yale-Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale (YBOCS). </outcome>
      <timepoint>The YBOCS will be administered at four time points including baseline measures to be taken at the beginning of the trial, at the end of the final session and after one week and one month thereafter. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient negative affective symptoms will be measured using the Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scales (DASS). </outcome>
      <timepoint>The DASS will be administered at four time points including baseline measures to be taken at the beginning of the study, at the end of the final session, then after one week and one month thereafter. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient neurocognitive functioning will be measured using the Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery (CANTAB). </outcome>
      <timepoint>The CANTAB will be administered at four time points including baseline measures to be taken at the beginning  of the trial, at the end of the final session, then after one week and 1 month thereafter. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient verbal fluency will be measured using the Delis-Kaplin Executive Function System (D-KEFS) verbal fluency form. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The D-KEFS will be administered at four time points including baseline measures to be taken at the beginning  of the trial, at the end of the final session, then after one week and 1 month thereafter. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Intelligence Quotient will be estimated using the Test of Premorbid Functioning. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The Test of Premorbid Functioning will be administered at four time points including baseline measures to be taken at the beginning  of the trial, at the end of the final session, then after one week and 1 month thereafter. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with a primary diagnosis of OCD according to the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders IV-Test Revision (2000) criteria. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients are to be excluded if they have metal implants in or around the head, implanted pace maker or pace maker like devices, metal clips or shrapnel inside the head, if the patient has a past history of epilepsy/seizures, pregnant females and patients who have concurrent psychotic symptoms. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment will be achieved by having an independent researcher not affiliated with the proposed study generate a random allocation sequence matched to a unique patient identifier (e.g. the patient’s ID code). Allocation to the control or experimental group will involve contacting the independent researcher who is ‘off site’ for a unique patient identifier. As the unique patient identifier will already be generated by the independent researcher, the researchers involved in the actual conduct of the study will not be able to influence patient group allocations. Moreover, researchers involved in the study will not be privy to the generated list.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a computer program. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Previous TMS clinical trials in OCD patients have shown that magnetic stimulation induces low to moderate effects. With this assumption, an a priori power analysis using the power analysis program G*power (Faul, Erdfelder, Lang &amp; Buchner, 2007) indicated that in order to detect small effect sizes (0.40), with power (1-beta) set at 0.80 and a = 0.05 (two-tailed), a total of 100 patients in the control and experimental group would be required. The sample size of 30 patients was selected due to the potential difficulty in recruiting from a vulnerable population, the novelty of the protocol, and the resources available to the researchers. As the study is longitudinal in nature and involves comparing two groups, we will submit our data to repeated measures analysis of variance, if statistically appropriate, to determine whether there are group differences between patient symptomology and neurocognitive functioning.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3125 - Burwood</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deakin University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>221 Burwood Highway, Burwood VIC, 3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Deakin University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC, 3125</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to evaluate the effectiveness of a brain stimulation technique referred to as transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) in treating obsessive compulsive disorder (OCD). Thirty OCD patients will allocated to either the control or experimental condition and receive TMS once daily for three weeks (Monday to Friday). Patients will then be followed up at two times points; after one week and four weeks post-treatment. The treatment protocol will consist of identifying and stimulating three brain regions which have been shown to be involved in OCD. Each region will be stimulated for 10 minutes using TMS parameters developed within well-established safety guidelines. We will measure the primary and secondary symptoms that patients experience and also measure their ability to perform computerised and pen and paper tasks. It is hypothesised that patients who undergo active treatment will experience a reduction in their OCD symptoms when compared to patients in the control condition.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Office, Deakin Research Integrity, Deakin University, 221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC, 3125</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/02/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00213</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Linda Byrne </name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92446424</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 92446858</fax>
      <email>linda.byrne@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Linda Byrne</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92446424</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 92446858</fax>
      <email>linda.byrne@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alan Pearce</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92517224</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 92446858</fax>
      <email>alan.pearce@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Michael Do</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</address>
      <phone />
      <fax>+61 3 92446858</fax>
      <email>m.do@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>