<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320956">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/12/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/01/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000001099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Daily disposable trial:Prospective, open label, randomised, cross-over clinical trial to evaluate the performance of Focus (registered trademark) 1-2 Week, Focus(registered trademark) Monthly and FreshLook (registered trademark) Handling Tint contact lenses on a daily wear, daily disposable wear schedule in neophyte and experienced East Asian wearers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective, open label, randomised, cross-over clinical trial to evaluate the performance of Focus (registered trademark) 1-2 Week, Focus (registered trademark) Monthly and FreshLook(registered trademark) Handling Tint contact lenses on a daily wear, daily disposable wear schedule in neophyte and experienced East Asian wearers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Evaluation of the vision, fitting characteristics, ocular and subjective responses of commercially available lenses made from Vifilcon A (Focus 1-2 Week, Focus Monthly) and Phemfilcon A (Freshlook Handling Tint).</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Prospective, open label, randomised, crossover trial to assess the performance of contact lenses made from vifilcon A and phemfilcon A when worn for 1 month each over a 3 month period (with 1 day washout between switching lenses) on a daily wear, daily disposable schedule.</interventions>
    <comparator>Acrive control - crossover study</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the best performing lens in terms of clinical (vision, fitting characteristics, ocular responses) and subjective responses. Clinical responses will be assessed with medical equipment (vision chart and biomicroscope) and subjective responses with questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1, 2 and 3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Be able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent;
-Be at least 18 years old;
-Be of East Asian ethnicity (either Japanese, Chinese, Taiwanese or Korean);
-Be willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the investigator;
-Have ocular health findings considered to be normal and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses; 
-Have vision correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses;
-Be experienced or may be inexperienced at wearing contact lenses.
-Have a current spectacle correction.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including keratoconus and herpes keratitis) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses;
-Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves disease, and auto-immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjögrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosis. Conditions such as systemic hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants;
-An active corneal infection or any active ocular disease that would affect wearing of contact lenses;
-Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication up to 12 weeks prior to and during the trial;
-Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications or participation in any clinical trial which may alter normal ocular findings/are known to affect a participants ocular health/physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse manner or risk providing a false positive. 
N.B. Systemic antihistamines are allowed on an as needed basis, provided they are not used prophylactically during the trial;  
-Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial;
-Previous corneal refractive surgery;
-Contraindications to contact lens wear;
-Contact lens wear within 1 calendar day of initial lens fitting (washout period to be performed post enrolment if necessary) 
-Allergy or intolerance to topical anaesthetics</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be randomly allocated (allocation concealment performed by central randomisation by computer) to wear  each lens type (Focus 1-2 week, Focus Monthly and Freshlook Handling tint) for 1 month each over a 3 month period. The person who determined if a subject was eligible for inclusion in the trial was unaware as to which group the subject would be allocated.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation list (which will be generated by computer) will be generated based on a crossover design where each subject receives all the study products.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/01/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>CIBA VISION</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>11460 Johns Creek Parkway
Duluth, GA 30097-1556</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>CIBA VISION</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>11460 Johns Creek Parkway
Duluth, GA 30097-1556</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To evaluate the clinical performance and subjective responses of commercially available Focus (registered trademark) 1-2 Week, Focus (registered trademark) Monthly and FreshLook (registered trademark) Handling Tint lenses in a sample of East Asian population when the lenses are worn on a daily wear, daily disposal schedule.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Vision Cooperative Research Centre (CRC) and Institute for Eye Research Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14, Barker Street, The University of New South Wales | SYDNEY NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/12/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>09/33</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Percy Lazon</name>
      <address>Institute for Eye Research
Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street, 
UNSW Sydney  NSW  2052</address>
      <phone>+6193857516</phone>
      <fax>+6193857401</fax>
      <email>p.lazon@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jerome Ozkan</name>
      <address>Institute for Eye Research
Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street, 
UNSW Sydney  NSW  2052</address>
      <phone>+6193857516</phone>
      <fax>+6193857401</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jerome Ozkan</name>
      <address>Institute for Eye Research
Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street, 
UNSW Sydney  NSW  2052</address>
      <phone>+6193857516</phone>
      <fax>+6193857401</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>