<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373100">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000912381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating the effectiveness of mind-body skills training based on yoga techniques in children on the Autism Spectrum </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized trial of the effectiveness of yoga-based mind-body skills training on self-regulation, anxiety, emotion and body awareness, and sleep in children on the autism spectrum</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1197-3065</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autistic spectrum disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The research study proposes a  Randomised Controlled Trial (RCT) to assess the efficacy of a yoga-based mind-body skills training program with approximately 30 children on the Autism Spectrum (ASD) in the intervention condition and 30 children with ASD in the wait-list control condition along with one of their parents/caregivers.

The training will be run in a group format and contain 5 parent-child dyads in each group. Participants will be matched per gender given the gender-specific differences observed in children with ASD and will be randomly assigned using a computer-generated method to either the yoga-based mind-body skills training group or the wait-list control group. The participants in the intervention condition will take part in the 6-session yoga-based mind-body skills training program called "The Incredible Explorers." The program will be delivered once per week for 6 consecutive weeks at the School of Psychology, University of Queensland. Each session will be delivered face-to-face and run for around 45 minutes. Each 45-minutes session will be divided into two parts. In the first part, both parents and the children will participate and practice gentle breath-centered movements. The lead researcher and two other facilitators will deliver the program. In the second part, the parents and the children will split up into two separate groups. Whilst the children learn mindful exercises through games and activities in the children-only group with two facilitators, the parents will discuss any process issues and learn different ways to support their children with the practice outside the sessions. This group will be facilitated by the lead researcher, Radhika Tanksale. 

At the end of each session, home tasks and home practice will be encouraged. The parents will be provided with a checklist to mark off the days the tasks were practised by the children during the week and will be reviewed in the next session. This checklist will assist to monitor the adherence to the intervention. A register of attendance at each session will also be maintained. 

The participants in the wait-list group will wait for 12 weeks before commencing the program. This is to ensure that a controlled comparison can be done at pre, post, and 6-week follow-up. 

The exercises included in the program will be simple, gentle, breath-centered mindful movement practices. The purpose of the exercises is not to improve strength, flexibility, and balance or increase heart rate, rather improve mindful attention through gentle movements. The mind-body practices will include breathing practices, mindfulness or meditation, and relaxation practices. Participants will be taught to pay mindful attention to their breath, their sensations, their feelings, and their thoughts that arise in the moment, without judgement.  Examples of the some of the exercises include paying mindful attention to walking, standing tall like a mountain and being aware of the different sensations they notice with their feet touching the ground, noticing how their belly rises and falls with each breath, as well as progressive muscle relaxation. The mindfulness-based activities in the child-only group will include activities such as mindful listening of the sound of a bell. 

Separate manuals for both facilitators and participants will be created to ensure consistency. Psychology interns, who will assist the lead researcher, Ms Radhika Tanksale in delivering the program will be recruited and trained in a half-day workshop and supervised by the researcher prior to the commencement of the RCT. 

Assessments will be done at three different points for the intervention condition, Time 1 or pre or baseline, Time 2 or post-6-week intervention program, Time 3 or 6-week after the completion of the intervention program or follow-up and four times for the wait-list control condition Time 1,2,3 and at the end of the 6-week intervention ( time 4). The lead researcher will be supervised by Associate Professor Kate Sofronoff and Dr Jeanie Sheffield. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>30 children on the autism spectrum will comprise the wait-list control group. The wait-list control group will receive the skills training 12 weeks after the intervention group commence with the program. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Behaviour Rating Inventory of Executive Function-Second Edition (BRIEF-2; Gioia, Isquith, Guy, &amp; Kenworthy, 2000) (Parent form)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline or pre-assessment (Time 1), Post-6 week intervention program (Time 2), and at 6-weeks after the completion of the intervention program or Follow-up (Time 3) for the intervention group. 

Time 1, 2, 3 and Post-6 week intervention program (Time 4) for the wait-list control group. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety Scale for Children- Autism Spectrum Disorder Parent and Child version (ASC-ASD-P/C; Rodgers et al., 2016) (Parent and children forms)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline or pre-assessment (Time 1), Post-6 week intervention program (Time 2), and at 6-weeks after the completion of the intervention program or Follow-up (Time 3) for the intervention group. 

Time 1, 2, 3 and Post-6 week intervention program (Time 4) for the wait-list control group. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child Emotion Awareness Questionnaire (EAQ-30). (Rieffe, Oosterveld, Miers, Meerum Terwogt, &amp; Ly, 2008). (Child-form)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline or pre-assessment (Time 1), Post-6 week intervention program (Time 2), and at 6-weeks after the completion of the intervention program or Follow-up (Time 3) for the intervention group. 

Time 1, 2, 3 and Post-6 week intervention program (Time 4) for the wait-list control group. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Childrens Sleep Habits Questionnaire (CSHQ; Owens, Spirito, &amp; McGuinn, 2000) (Primary Outcome) (Parent-form)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline or pre-assessment (Time 1), Post-6 week intervention program (Time 2), and at 6-weeks after the completion of the intervention program or Follow-up (Time 3) for the intervention group. 

Time 1, 2, 3 and Post-6 week intervention program (Time 4) for the wait-list control group. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Computerised Go- No/Go test to assess sustained attention and inhibitory control. (Primary Outcome) (Children only)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline or pre-assessment (Time 1), Post-6 week intervention program (Time 2), and at 6-weeks after the completion of the intervention program or Follow-up (Time 3) for the intervention group. 

Time 1, 2, 3 and Post-6 week intervention program (Time 4) for the wait-list control group. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Goal Attainment Scale: The goal attainment scaling will be based on the guidelines by McDougall and King, 2007. One goal will be identified by the parents for their child before the training program begins. The scale will assess whether the child has attained the goal desired or identify any observed changes at the completion of the program (Time 2) and the 6-week follow up (Time 3). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-Intervention (Time 2) and 6 weeks follow-up (Time 3) for the intervention group and Post-Intervention (Time 4) for the wait-list control group. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Program satisfaction questionnaires created specifically for this program (Parent and child) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-intervention (Time 2 for intervention group and Time-4 for wait-list control group). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A computerised Flanker test to assess selective attention and response inhibition. (Primary outcome) (Child only)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline or pre-assessment (Time 1), Post-6 week intervention program (Time 2), and at 6-weeks after the completion of the intervention program or Follow-up (Time 3) for the intervention group. 

Time 1, 2, 3 and Post-6 week intervention program (Time 4) for the wait-list control group.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The study will include children with a diagnosis of Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD) given by a Paediatrician, Psychiatrist, Clinical Psychologist, or Psychologist as per the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual, 5th Edition (DSM 5) or with a diagnosis of Aspergers Syndrome, High-Functioning Autism or PDD-NOS made prior to 2013 as per the DSM-IV. A confirmation of the diagnosis will be requested from the parents by asking them for the name of the person who diagnosed their child, the qualifications of the person, and the date or year when the diagnosis was given. 60 children, 8-12 years of age, and who are verbally fluent will be included in the study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No formal diagnosis of ASD and with pre-verbal or phrase-like speech.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>A mixed design will be used, with groups as the between-subjects variable and time as the within-subjects variable. Both the intervention group and the wait-list control group will receive the same mind-body skills training program. However, the wait-list group will have to wait for 12 weeks before they receive the intervention. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A Repeated Measures statistical method will be used for analysis. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>19/10/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>8/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4072 - University Of Queensland</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Radhika Tanksale </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology
McElwain Building
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>School of Psychology, University of Queensland </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Psychology
McElwain Building
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The present study will assess whether for children on the autism spectrum, teaching them the new skills to practice gentle breath-centered movement practices and mindful attention training based on the principles of yoga, will influence and promote their self-regulation of behavior, emotions, improve their cognitive control of executive functions, their emotion and body awareness, and benefit sleep, in those children with parent-identified sleep difficulties in the initial assessment. The study will explore the benefits of active involvement of parents in sessions, assess whether psychologists, with little or no experience in yoga, can deliver the modified, age-appropriate, user-friendly, and simple yoga-based exercises effectively as a training tool. It will examine whether a modified and manualized yoga skills training program is suitable and effective for this population and their parents and whether it can be used as an adjunct to existing treatment. 60 children on the autism spectrum between the ages of 8-12 years will be randomly assigned to either an intervention group or a wait-list control group. The intervention group will receive the 6-week yoga-based intervention program delivered once per week/6weeks. The intervention program will be delivered face-to-face by the lead researcher and two other facilitators. The wait-list control group will wait for 12 weeks before receiving the intervention. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>School of Psychology, Ethics Review Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>School of Psychology
McElwain Building
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>17-PSYCH-PHD-21-JMC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/04/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Radhika Tanksale</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
McElwain Building
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61452506282</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.tanksale@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Radhika Tanksale</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
McElwain Building
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61452506282</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.tanksale@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Radhika Tanksale</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
McElwain Building
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61452506282</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.tanksale@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Radhika Tanksale</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
McElwain Building
The University of Queensland
St Lucia, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61452506282</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.tanksale@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>