<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336143">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000704998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of "Anxiety Online": A public online mental health service</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of clinical severity and psychological distress following use of Anxiety Online: A virtual psychology clinic for adults with anxiety disorders or subclinical symptoms</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>anxiety disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Online treatment programs for each of the anxiety disorders: Generalised Anxiety Disorder, Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder, Panic Disorder, Post Traumatic Stress Disorder and Social Anxiety Disorder. Participants choose whether to do an online program on their own or with email assistance from a psychologist. Programs are based on cognitive behaviour therapy techniques and contain 12 multi-media enriched modules with homework exercises designed to be completed over 12 weeks. It is anticipated that participants will spent about 40 minutes a week reading through the online module and completing associated offline exercises.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group is being used. Participants are given treatment options based on their completion of a comprehensive online assessment (e-PASS). Comparisons are being made for fully automated self-help and therapist versions of each of the anxiety disorder treatment programs. The therapist-assisted version involves receiving an email from a psychologist or provisional psychologist under supervision each week over the 12 week treatment period.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety disorders (Generalised Anxiety Disorder, Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder, Panic Disorder with or without agoraphobia, Post Traumatic Stress Disorder, Social Anxiety Disorder) clinical severity ratings, as measured by online assessment (e-PASS) based on DSM-IV criteria and currently undergoing validity testing</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-program, post-program (week 12) then annually from 1-year post-program through to 5-years post-program</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress, as measured by the Kessler-6</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-program, post-program (week 12) then annually from 1-year post-program through to 5-years post-program</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>depression, as measured by online assessment (e-PASS) based on DSM-IV criteria and currently undergoing validity testing</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-program, post-program (week 12) then annually from 1-year post-program through to 5-years post-program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>eating disorders (anorexia nervosa, bulimia nervosa, binge eating disorder), as measured by online assessment (e-PASS) based on DSM-IV criteria and currently undergoing validity testing</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-program, post-program (week 12) then annually from 1-year post-program through to 5-years post-program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Somatoform disorders (somatisation, body dysmorphic disorder), as measured by online assessment (e-PASS) based on DSM-IV criteria and currently undergoing validity testing</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-program, post-program (week 12) then annually from 1-year post-program through to 5-years post-program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>pathological gambling, as measured by online assessment (e-PASS) based on DSM-IV criteria and currently undergoing validity testing</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-program, post-program (week 12) then annually from 1-year post-program through to 5-years post-program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleeping disorders (insomnia, hypersomnia), as measured by online assessment (e-PASS) based on DSM-IV criteria and currently undergoing validity testing</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-program, post-program (week 12) then annually from 1-year post-program through to 5-years post-program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>dependence disorders (alcohol dependence and substance dependence), as measured by online assessment (e-PASS) based on DSM-IV criteria and currently undergoing validity testing</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-program, post-program (week 12) then annually from 1-year post-program through to 5-years post-program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life rating, as measured by Likert-type scale within an online assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-program, post-program (week 12) then annually from 1-year post-program through to 5-years post-program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Confidence in managing mental health, as measured by a Likert-type scale within an online assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-program, post-program (week 12) then annually from 1-year post-program through to 5-years post-program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Likert scale-based questions (largely self-developed) are used to measure treatment satisfaction and self-perceived improvement, as well as open-ended questions regarding the best and worst aspects of the program and how the program could be improved.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-program (week 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Client's perceptions of the helpfulness of their relationship with their therapist - as measured by the Working Alliance Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-program (week 12) for those consumers accessing therapist-assisted programs</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of mental health disorder diagnoses, as measured by the number of diagnoses on a person's online assessment (e-PASS report)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-program, post-program (week 12) than annually from 1-year post-program through to 5-years post-program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>18 years or older
For the therapist-assisted programs, Australian resident (people residing outside of Australia can only undertake the fully automated self-help programs)
Internet access</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Under 18
No internet access
For the therapist-assisted programs (but not the fully automated self-help programs), not an Australian resident</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants receive different online treatment programs depending on their e-PASS results and personal choice as to which online program to complete. They complete programs at different time points as registration is open continuously.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/10/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National eTherapy Centre and BPsyC eTherapy Research Unit, Swinburne University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Mail H29, PO Box 218, Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Health and Ageing</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 9848
Canberra, ACT, 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project is examining the user-experience and evaluating Anxiety Online, an internet-based treatment clinic for consumers with anxiety symptoms and disorders. Consumers can complete a comprehensive psychological assessment (e-PASS), following which they receive a report which provides them with details as to the type and severity of their anxiety and other mental health problems and appropriate treatment recommendations. If they show symptoms of anxiety consumers have the option of completing a treatment program on their own or with email assistance from a therapist. Programs are available for generalised anxiety disorder, obsessive-compulsive disorder, panic disorder, with or without agoraphobia, post traumatic stress disorder and social anxiety disorder. Consumers are asked to complete e-PASS post-program (week 12) and invited to complete it yearly from 1-year post-program through to 5-year post-program. It is expected that at post-program consumers will show a reduction in the severity of their anxiety symptoms, K-6 scores and total number of clinical diagnoses/symptoms. In addition, it is expected that quality of life and confidence in managing one's own mental health care will increase at post-program.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.anxietyonline.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Klein, B. (2010). Anxiety Online Evaluation Report. Commissioned research report submitted to the Federal Department of Health and Ageing.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Swinburne University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Swinburne Research, Swinburne University, Mail H68, PO Box 218, Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/10/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2009/261</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/10/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Britt Klein</name>
      <address>BPsyC eTherapy Research Unit and National eTherapy Centre, Faculty of Life and Social Sciences, Swinburne University of Technology, Mail H29, PO Box 218, Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9214 8851</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bklein@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Britt Klein</name>
      <address>BPsyC eTherapy Research Unit and National eTherapy Centre, Faculty of Life and Social Sciences, Swinburne University of Technology, Mail H29, PO Box 218, Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9214 8851</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bklein@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jo Abbott</name>
      <address>BPsyC eTherapy Research Unit and National eTherapy Centre, Faculty of Life and Social Sciences, Swinburne University of Technology, Mail H29, PO Box 218, Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9214 5866</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jmabbott@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>