<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368200">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000325505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Researching Effective Approaches to Cleaning in Hospitals</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In 11 major public and private Australian hospitals, what is the effect of an environmental cleaning bundle intervention on healthcare associated infections (HAIs) and on health care costs?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U-1111-1167-7862</utrn>
    <trialacronym>REACH </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Healthcare associated infections</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Implementation of a cleaning bundle intervention, consisting of 5 interdependent components (training, audit, communication, product and technique), in 11 hospitals for randomly allocated time periods between 20 weeks and 50 weeks.
Interdependent bundle components are each tailored to meet the site context. 

TRAINING
The study team will deliver tailored training activities (reflecting the educational needs identified at each site during the control period through the environmental services pre- intervention surveys):
- at the commencement of the intervention phase for all environmental services staff with a role in environmental cleaning
- as part of induction for new environmental services staff with a role in environmental cleaning
- and as required throughout the intervention phase. 

Content of the introductory training activity (1-2 hour face-face session for environmental services staff) in week 1 of the intervention period will minimally include: the bundle components, clearly defined roles and responsibilities for environmental cleaning at the site and the impact of environmental cleaning on HAI.

Additional training sessions will continue throughout the intervention period as required by the site and provide responsive feedback from the bundle audit activities. Training will articulate with existing education events and timings in trial sites as much as possible, including induction for environmental services staff, team meetings and annual training updates.

TECHNIQUE
All environmental services staff at each site will follow an established cleaning technique throughout the intervention period when completing a daily clean or discharge clean. 
It will be communicated to environmental services staff through the training and through availability of posters, fact sheets and tip sheets/ cards (e.g on the cleaning trolley). 

PRODUCT
Each trial site will have existing supply arrangements for environmental cleaning product, including cleaning equipment. To promote cost-effectiveness and ensure feasibility the product component will be clarified with each site to ensure the product component: 
-	minimally includes the use of disinfectant for all discharge cleans and for daily cleans of high risk/contact precaution rooms. To ensure organic matter is removed effectively either a 2 in 1 detergent and disinfectant product or a 2-step process will be used
-	minimally includes the use of point of care wipes for medical equipment 
-	is Therapeutic Good Administration approved for that use and setting 
-	adheres to manufacturers instructions for use 
-	is compatible with other product or application materials (e.g. microfiber cloths) in use
-	ensures effective cleaning technique is used. 
All environmental services staff with a role in environmental cleaning at the trial site will use this product component throughout the intervention period. 

AUDIT
In this cleaning bundle the DAZO fluorescent marker system will be used monthly in the control and intervention periods as an audit tool by the study team or trained members of the site team at each trial site. DAZO® Fluorescent Marking Gel and UV Light system dries on surfaces following application and resists dry abrasion, but is removed with standard cleaning. The locations of the gel dots will be consistent with the Centers for Disease Prevention and Control Environmental Cleaning Checklist in two different bed and bathroom areas in the Intensive Care Unit and in at least 50% of the hospital trial site wards. 

In 3 hospital sites the study team will use ATP luminometry bi-monthly in the same ward sites as the fluorescent markers to audit bio burden of the frequent touch surfaces post daily or discharge clean. The 3 hospitals will be located in either South East Queensland or at an investigator affiliated site due to equipment limitations. 

COMMUNICATION
The communication component of the bundle will be implemented by the study and site teams, throughout the intervention period. Communication activities will focus on:
-	maintaining a positive feedback loop to all staff about the audit results
-	the role of the multidisciplinary team in preventing HAI 
-	creation of a culture of hygiene through hospital wide promotional activities to raise the profile and importance of cleaning in reducing infections and support a culture shift in the perception of environmental services staff
-	daily contact between cleaning staff and ward leaders or managers
-	supporting the participation of cleaning staff on relevant clinical governance committees.

Site adherence with the bundle components will be monitored by the study team through fortnightly site contact and the review of audit results. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The study design is a stepped wedge: each hospital acts as its own control for 8 weeks prior to commencing the intervention.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The (whole of hospital) combined number of healthcare associated Staphylococcus Aureus Bacteremia (SAB) infections, healthcare associated Clostridium Difficule infections (CDI) and positive clinical isolates of Vancomycin Resistant Enterococci (VRE) at each trial site. This is assessed through whole of hospital infection data and reports about these 3 HAIs, along with antimicrobial prescribing data  (including antimicrobial agent, daily drug does and occupied bed days) and hand hygiene compliance data, supplied to the project team by the trial site team. Antimicrobial prescribing and hand hygiene rates may impact HAI rates, This data on healthcare associated infections is routinely collected by the trial site for ongoing surveillance.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>HAI rates, antimicrobial prescribing data, and hand hygiene compliance data will be collected from 1 May 2015 to end of intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in costs associated with implementing the bundle relative to changes in health benefits (incremental cost effectiveness ratio). This is assessed by identifying the number and unit cost of resources  used in implementing the bundle (including staff, training, cleaning product) and the opportunity cost of infection (treatment costs, bed days lost) quality adjusted life years (QALY) calculations.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (control period) and monthly during intervention period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number (and %) of ultraviolet gel dots removed correctly following routine hospital cleaning. 
The gel dots  will be applied in frequent touch points (as per the Centers for Disease Prevention and Control Environmental Cleaning Checklist)  post daily clean in two different bed and bathroom areas in the  Intensive Care Unit and in at least 50% of the hospital trial site wards. Wards will be chosen that reflect the National Health Performance Authority (NHPA) risk factors for patient vulnerability: immunosuppressed patients and patients admitted with a risk of infection.  

Following cleaning the next day,  the sites will be checked using the UV light pen, which will (literally) show if the gel dot remains after the cleaning. The outcome measure will be cleaning success, as number of dots removed divided by the total number of dots placed. All results will be recorded using the iCombat application at the time of data collection.  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (control period) and monthly during intervention period. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adenosine Tri Phosphate (ATP) bio luminescence (levels of organic matter) in relative light units post cleaning in 3 trial site hospitals.
This will be assessed using an ATP luminometer swabbing sytem in seven frequent touch sites from the checklist used for the UV dots audits in the same bed/bathroom locations in the same wards,  bi-monthly to coincide with the  UV gel dots audits. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (control period) and two monthly during intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in staff knowledge and attitudes around environmental cleaning. This will be assessed by pre- and post intervention surveys of the environmental services staff and through discussion groups and interviews of environmental services staff with a role in environmental cleaning, pre- and post intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (control period) and post intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in number (and %) of screening isolates for Methicillin Resistant Staphylococcus Aureus (MRSA). 
This is assessed through whole of hospital infection data and reports, supplied to the project team by the trial site team, where this data on MRSA screening isolates is already collected by the trial site for ongoing surveillance.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (control period) and monthly during intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in number (and %) of clinical isolates of multi-resistant organisms 
This is assessed through whole of hospital infection data and reports, supplied to the project team by the trial site team, where this data on multi resistant organisms is already collected by the trial site for ongoing surveillance.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (control period) and monthly during intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in patient perceptions of hospital cleanliness.

This data set is collated from existing hospital-based and approved  survey processes and data, supplied to the study team by the trial site team. It could be ward/unit specific or a whole of hospital  data set as per what is collected by the hospital as their usual procedure. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and if available during intervention period (existing data set)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in costs associate with implementing the cleaning bundle</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (control period) and monthly during intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in quality adjusted life years associated with implementing the bundle</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (control period) and monthly during the intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Acute hospitals that:
- have an intensive care unit accredited for advanced clinician training by the College of Intensive Care Medicine 
- public hospitals - classified by the National Health Performance Authority (NHPA) as a major hospital' 
- private hospitals  over 200 in-patient beds
- have an established healthcare associated infection (HAI) surveillance program in place that collects data on SAB infections, CDI and VRE infections.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Hospitals that do not meet all of the inclusion criteria.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>Randomisation for the study will be performed through the simple  computerised allocation of hospital identifiers (letters A to K).  Trial sites will be randomly allocated to these identifiers and the intervention timing once 11 sites have been enrolled.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Stepped wedge trial: each hospital receives the intervention with length of the intervention randomly allocated to one of 11 time points between 20 and 50 weeks.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size:
Eleven hospitals with a pre-intervention infection rate (a combination of SAB, CDI and VRE) of 5 per 10,000 patient days will give us 86% power to detect a 20% post-intervention reduction in infection risk. This is based on a two-sided 5% significance level, a within-hospital correlation in infection rates of 0.3 and the stepped intervention timings between 20 and 50 weeks.
Analysis:
The Objective 1 primary outcome of infection rates will be analysed using Poisson regression with the   infection counts as the dependent variable and the weekly number of patient days as the denominator. The key independent variable will be the intervention. The model will include a linear term for time to control for any long term patterns in infection rate, and analysed using a generalised linear mixed model (GLMM).

The Objective 1 secondary outcome of success or failure of environmental cleaning as measured by removal of UV gel dots will be examined using a similar GLMM but assuming a binomial response.

The Objective 1 secondary outcome of ATP assays will be quantified and expressed as relative light units, then analysed and correlated with the secondary outcome data (ultraviolet dots). 

The Objective 1 outcome of changes in staff knowledge and attitudes around environmental cleaning will be analysed by reviewing the outcomes of pre and post intervention surveys and interviews.

For the Objective 2 primary outcome of cost effectiveness, the incremental cost effectiveness ratio at the hospital level, will be estimated by summing intervention costs and deducting cost savings from reduced lengths of stay and use of health care resources that arise from reduced incidences of infection.

The secondary outcome of changes to costs will be estimates by the extra staff time spent, costs of cleaning products, invisible gels, UV lamps and pathology costs. The changes to health benefits will be estimated in quality adjusted life years using  the number of life years saved from reduced infection outcomes, the expected duration of life (had infection not occurred) based on age and co-morbidities.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/11/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>26/02/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>29/04/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>11</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>11</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/09/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box 2434
Brisbane, QLD 4001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland University of Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 2434
Brisbane, QLD 4001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Wesley Medical Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 499
Toowong QLD 4066</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Kimberley-Clark Australia Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>52 Alfred Street 
Milsons Point NSW 2061
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Wesley St. Andrew's Research Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 499
Toowong QLD 4066</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Avondale College of Higher Education</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Avondale College of Higher Education, 185 Fox Valley Road, 
Wahroonga
NSW, 2076.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Australian Catholic University Limited</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 968, North Sydney NSW 2059</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Western Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>35 Stirling Highway, Crawley WA 6009</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Whiteley Corporation Pty Ltd</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 1076
North Sydney NSW 2059
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ecolab Pty Ltd</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO Box 383
Nrth Ryde BC 1670 NSW</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Healthcare associated infections (HAI) are a major cause of avoidable costs, morbidity and deaths among hospital patients.  In Australia 200,000 cases of HAI arise each year and 1.9 million hospital bed days are diverted to treat them. Reducing important HAI requires multiple evidence-based approaches. This study will evaluate the effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of improving environmental cleaning, using an evidence-based bundle, to reduce HAI.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://reach.cre-rhai.org.au/index.html</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Hall L, Farrington A, Mitchell BG, Barnett AG, Halton K, Allen M, Page K, Gardner A, Havers S, Bailey E, Dancer S, Riley TV, Gericke CA, Paterson DL, Graves N. Researching effective approaches to cleaning in hospitals: protocol of the REACH study, a multi-site stepped-wedge randomised trial. Implementation Science. 2016;11(1):1-10.
DOI: 10.1186/s13012-016-0406-6 
URL: http://www.implementationscience.com/content/11/1/44

Presentations
Mitchell, B on behalf of the REACH Project team. The effectiveness of cleaning bundles. Infection Prevention Society Conference. 27/09/2016.			

Poster presentations
Farrington A, Allen M, Hall L, on behalf of the REACH Project team. Implementing a national infection prevention trial with iPARIHS.  Australasian Implementation Conference. 06/10/2016. 

Farrington A, Allen M, Hall L, Mitchell B on behalf of the REACH Project team. Evaluating a process of change in hospital environmental cleaning  the role of logic models. Australian College for Infection Prevention and Control Conference. 20/11/2016.

Farrington A, Allen M, Hall L, Mitchell B on behalf of the REACH Project team. Environmental cleaning research: Participating in the REACH study.  Australian College for Infection Prevention and Control Conference. 20/11/2016. 
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UnitingCare Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 499  Toowong  QLD  4066</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1413</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland University of Technology Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box 2434
Brisbane, QLD 4001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec> 1400000828 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Health and Aged Care Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>48 Montpelier Rd
Bowen Hills QLD 4006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC15/13</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7 Block 7
Butterfield St
Herston QLD 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/QRBW/463</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Barwon Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Bellerine St
Geelong VIC 3220</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/159</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lookout Rd
New Lambton NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LNR/15/HNE/527</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tasmanian Health and Medical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>301 Sandy Bay Road
Sandy Bay TAS 7005</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0015519</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>185 Cooper St
Epping VIC 3076</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LR 03.2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2
5 Arnold St
Box Hill VIC 3128</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LR05/2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Flats F6/F8
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/01/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>470.15 - HREC/15/SAC/457</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Metropolitan Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2, Southern Research Facility (Perkins Building) 
Fiona Stanley Hospital,
102-118 Murdoch Drive, 
MURDOCH WA 6150</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-057</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Graves</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
GPO Box 2434
Brisbane QLD 4001</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 3814</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.graves@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alison Farrington</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
GPO Box 2434
Brisbane QLD 4001</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 6132</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.farrington@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alison Farrington</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
GPO Box 2434
Brisbane QLD 4001</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 6132</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.farrington@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alison Farrington</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
GPO Box 2434
Brisbane QLD 4001</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 6132</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.farrington@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>