<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365055">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001082796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An investigation of the efficacy of a motherhood decision aid for women with epilepsy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An investigation of whether receiving a motherhood decision aid improves pregnancy knowledge and decisional self-efficacy, and reduces decisional conflict in women with epilepsy who are contemplating pregnancy, compared to not receiving a motherhood decision aid.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>epilepsy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epilepsy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>About the Intervention:
The intervention is a Decision Aid, which is an evidence-based tool designed to prepare patients to make specific and deliberate choices regarding their health care. The Decision Aid developed for this study is an online 50-page booklet in PDF format, developed especially for women with epilepsy according to the quality criteria outlined by the International Patient Decision Aids Standards Collaboration (IPDAS, Elwyn et al., 2006). The current Decision Aid describes the options available regarding whether or not to have a child (e.g., have children, not have children, have only 1 child, have multiple children), as well as describing the benefits and risks of these options, according to the available research on pregnancy and epilepsy. The Decision Aid is designed to help inform women with epilepsy of the relevant research and help them to consider what values are important to them using written exercises included throughout the resource. Decision aids are designed to supplement, not replace, clinician's counselling about health care options, and this is explained in the present Decision Aid.

Mode of Administration and Duration: 
Participants who are randomly allocated to the group which receives the online Decision Aid (the intervention group) will be asked to read it all the way through. Participants in this group will receive the Decision Aid via email after completing some online questionnaires. It is estimated that reading the Decision Aid would take 1- 2 hours, depending on a participant's speed of reading. This group will also receive a phone call from a member of the research team to check that they have received the Decision Aid and to talk about the information and clarify anything that is unclear. The telephone conversation will take no more than 20 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment: women in this group do not receive the Decision Aid until after the study is completed. 

Participants who are randomly allocated to the control group will not receive the Decision Aid immediately. Once their involvement in the study is over (approximately two weeks after first participating in the study), they will be sent a copy of the Decision Aid via email for their information.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knowledge levels: assessed by mean scores (% correct answers) on a Knowledge Questionnaire containing 15 multiple-choice items which assess participants' knowledge about a range of epilepsy and pregnancy-related issues that are addressed in the Decision Aid. In the absence of an existing tool for women with epilepsy regarding pregnancy and child rearing, this questionnaire was developed by the researchers. It was based on the format of a knowledge questionnaire used in the only other published validation study of a motherhood Decision Aid for women with a chronic disabling medical condition (Multiple Sclerosis) (Prunty et al., 2008).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and two weeks post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decisional self-efficacy: assessed by mean scores on the Decision Self-Efficacy Scale (O'Connor, 1995a). This scale determines the level of self-confidence and belief that participants have in their own ability to make a decision.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and two weeks post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decisional conflict: assessed by mean scores on the Decision Conflict Scale 4th Edition (O'Connor, 1995b). This instrument evaluates patients decisions regarding a range of healthcare decisions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and two weeks post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression: assessed by mean scores on the Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D; Radloff, 1977). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and two weeks post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety: assessed by the mean scores on the Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD)-7 Scale (Spitzer, Kroenke, &amp; Williams, 2006). There are currently no instruments specifically validated for assessing anxiety disorders in people with epilepsy. The GAD-7 has been shown to be a reliable and valid self-report anxiety measure for anxiety in the general population  (Lowe et al. 2008) and in primary care patients (Spitzer, Kroenke &amp; Williams, 2006). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and two weeks post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women with a diagnosis of epilepsy who are of childbearing age (18-45 years) who are undecided about whether or not to have children (or more children). Women must be proficient in the English language. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants with a level of cognitive impairment that prevents them from being able to read the whole Decision Aid. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Once participants have completed the baseline questionnaires online and their responses indicate their eligibility for the study, participants will be randomly allocated by the researcher (Amanda McGrath) to either the intervention group (those receiving the Decision Aid at the start) or the control group (those who do not receive the Decision Aid until after the study is completed). Allocation will be concealed until the time of each participant's allocation using sequential sealed opaque envelopes. Participants will then be sent an email from Ms McGrath, notifying them to which group they have been randomly allocated and the next steps for the study. </concealment>
    <sequence>A list of participant numbers will be linked in advance to a series of random numbers 1-2. The sequence of random numbers will be generated through randomizer.com and concealed until after the assessment.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>As a large-scale randomised control trial is beyond the scope of this research project, a pilot study is planned. In their validation study of a motherhood decision aid for women with Multiple Sclerosis, Prunty et al. (2008) found that their decision aid had large effects on knowledge (ES = 0.89) and decisional conflict (ES=0.72) and a moderate effect on decisional self-efficacy (ES=0.51). According to G-power, based on these effect sizes, we would need 13 participants per group to get an effect on knowledge, 18 for decisional conflict and 33 for self-efficacy, with 80% power and an alpha of 0.05. Hence, the study will aim for 33 participants per group (i.e., N = 66). Eligible women will be those diagnosed with epilepsy between the ages of 18 to 45, who are currently undecided about motherhood.

Baseline differences between the intervention and control group will be calculated using parametric (for continuous variables) and non-parametric (for dichotomous variables) t-tests to identify covariates. A series of (group: intervention vs. no intervention) x 2 (time: pre vs. post) mixed model ANCOVAs will be conducted using statistical software, to determine the effectiveness of the intervention. 
 </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/09/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>13/11/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>66</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress> The University of Sydney 
NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The study is being conducted in fulfilment of the requirements for a Master of Science degree at the University of Sydney, as undertaken by one of the researchers, Amanda McGrath. 

No monetary funding has been received or is planned for this study.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Amanda McGrath
Brennan McCallum Building (A18) 
The University of Sydney 
NSW 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to test the efficacy of a decision-making tool, called a Decision Aid, for women with epilepsy who are in the process of deciding whether or not to have a child. 

It is hypothesised that women with epilepsy who receive the Decision Aid will report increased knowledge about pregnancy; reduced decisional conflict and increased decisional self-efficacy regarding their decision compared to women who do not receive the Decision Aid. In accordance with previous research, the Decision Aid is not expected to affect depression, anxiety or the direction of a woman's decision. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics
Margaret Telfer K07
University of Sydney NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013/791</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Louise Sharpe</name>
      <address>Brennan McCallum Building (A18)
The University of Sydney 
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 4558</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 7328</fax>
      <email>louise.sharpe@sydney.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda McGrath</name>
      <address>Brennan McCallum Building (A18)
The University of Sydney 
NSW 2006 </address>
      <phone>+61 410 477 935</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ahig9515@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda McGrath</name>
      <address>Brennan McCallum Building (A18)
The University of Sydney 
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 410 477 935</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ahig9515@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Amanda McGrath</name>
      <address>Brennan McCallum Building (A18)
The University of Sydney 
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 410 477 935</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ahig9515@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>