<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366660">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000795695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of  chiropractic  care  on  synchronised pelvic floor muscle contraction </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of chiropractic care compared to passive movement on pelvic floor muscle function in women with non-synchronised pelvic floor muscle contractions</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U111111571251</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non-synchronised pelvic floor muscle contractions</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Individuals who are identified as having non-synchronous pelvic floor muscle contraction during the baseline/control session will be assessed a second time within one month of the initial assessment. At the second assessment all measures will be recorded before and after lumbopelvic chiropractic adjustments. The order of the various measures will be pseudo-randomised (e.g. order of assessment of maximal voluntary contractions, submaximal contractions and voluntary coughs). No control setup will be performed during the second assessment as control data will be available from the first assessment. All of the spinal adjustments to be carried out in this study will be high-velocity, low-amplitude thrusts to the spine. This is a standard adjustment technique used by manipulative physicians, physiotherapists, and chiropractors. The mechanical properties of this type of CNS perturbation have been investigated; and although the actual force applied to the subject's spine depends on the therapist, the patient, and the spinal location of the adjustment, the general shape of the force-time history of spinal adjustments is very consistent (Hessell, Herzog, Conway, &amp; McEwen, 1990) and the duration of the thrust is always less than 200 milliseconds (for review see Herzog, 1996).The high-velocity type of adjustment was chosen specifically because previous research (Herzog, Conway, Zhang, Gail, &amp; Guimaraes, 1995) has shown that reflex EMG activation observed after adjustments only occurred after high-velocity, low-amplitude adjustments (as compared with lower-velocity mobilizations). This adjustment technique has also been previously used in studies that have investigated neurophysiological effects of spinal adjustments (for review see Haavik &amp; Murphy, 2012).

After each individual segmental adjustment the spine will be re-checked in order to determine if the subsequent levels identified as subluxated still require an adjustment. The levels of the spine adjusted for each subject will be recorded in an experimental log book. 

The adjustment intervention will take approximately 5 minutes and will be administered once.</interventions>
    <comparator>We will assess the effects of positioning a subject in a side-posture position as done during a spinal adjustment. This movement will consist of the same type of side posture set-up that a chiropractor positions a patient in prior to the delivery of the adjustive thrust. No thrust will be applied to the spine during this control movement. This control movement is not intended as a sham manipulation, but rather as a control for the potential physiological changes that could occur when lying on the adjustment bench, and the touch of the chiropractor. The subject will be positioned in the lateral decubitus  position, as will  be done for the adjustment intervention. The free superior leg will also be flexed at the knee and the pelvis so as to flex the lumbar spine. The pisiform bone of the clinicians inferior (in relation to the subjects head) hand will contact any lumbar spinal segment over the spinous process, or the PSIS of the sacroiliac joint. However, no thrust will be applied. One session will be required which will take approximately 5 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Commercially available intra-vaginal EMG probes (Sugar International, Auriol, France) will be used to detect contraction onset times from the left and right side of the deep pelvic floor muscles to be compared with the superficial ones. The EMG signals will be amplified with a band pass filter of 10 to 500 Hz. Data will be sampled by the 14 bit analog-to-digital converter at a rate of 1,000 samples per second, stored on a computer.


Recording will be made of voluntary and involuntary pelvic floor muscle activity before, during and/or after several tasks, manoeuvres and movements including maximum voluntary contractions (MVCs) of their pelvic floor muscles, maximal intra-abdominal pressure (IAP) efforts (i.e. Valsalva manoeuvres), and voluntary coughs. The outcome of interest is the synchronisation of pelvic floor muscle contractions. 

Individuals who are identified as having non-synchronous pelvic floor muscle contraction using the above protocol will be assessed a second time within one month of the initial assessment using the same protocol as above. At the second assessment all measures will be recorded before and after lumbopelvic adjustments. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and post a single intervention session</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>None</outcome>
      <timepoint>None</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Women aged 18-55 with non-synchronised pelvic floor muscle contractions, as observed during ultrasound examination,
* A body mass index of less than 25 kg/m2 to achieve reliable EMG recordings
* Normal perineal sensibility 
* Detectable non-synchronised pelvic floor muscle contractions, as observed during electromyography (EMG) examination.
(Participants in this trial will be included whether they are pregnant or not)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Any history of pelvic floor dysfunction, stress incontinence, pelvic organ prolapse, pelvic floor muscle avulsions, etc.
* Women with vaginal, urethral or bladder infection,
* Significant back pain in the last 3 months
* Known neurological diseases
* If currently taking antidepressant, analgesic or sedative medication.
* Known contraindication to receiving chiropractic adjustments. This includes a history of recent trauma, or known conditions such as inflammatory or infectious arthropathies, or bone malignancies.
* Previous adverse reactions to spinal adjustments
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Volunteers will be recruited into the trial and recordings will be made of voluntary and involuntary pelvic floor muscle activity before, during and/or after several tasks, manoeuvres and movements. If non-synchronsied muscle activity is observed a second assessment will take place that involves a chiropractic intervention pre and post the pelvic floor muscle function assessment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Basic science trial. Non-random allocation will be used. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To assess the effects of chiropractic adjustments on the dependent variables a multifactorial repeated measures ANOVA will be used for each of the dependent measures (contraction of left vs right pelvic floor muscles and deep vs superficial pelvic floor muscles), with TIME (pre and post intervention measures) and INTERVENTION (Chiro vs control intervention) as factors. A priori pairwise comparisons of the pre and post intervention data will be carried out when an interactive effect is significant. All statistical analysis will be carried out using IBM SPSS Statistics Version 21.0.0.0 software (IBM Corp, Armonk, NY). Significance will be set at P = .05.

Based on previous research we expect an effect size of 0.8. Power calculations suggest that to detect an anticipated effect size of 0.8 (estimates have been based on previous research) with an alpha of 0.05 and a power of 0.8, 15 subjects will be required to participate in the intervention arm of this study. Previous studies have revealed that between 14-20% of subjects considered to be normal exhibit non-synchronous patterns of pelvic muscle contraction. We therefore anticipate that we will need to screen 90 subjects to identify the 15 subjects required to participate in this study.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/08/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/04/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>New Zealand College of Chiropractic</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>6 Harrison Road
Ellerslie
Auckland 1060
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Spinal Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 1047. Springwood QLD 4127</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project will investigate whether adjusting lumbopelvic vertebral subluxations alters pelvic floor muscle function
using a novel multiarray
surface electrode vaginal probe. Pelvic floor muscles are fundamental in the birth process,
mainly during the pushing stage of labour. They normally contract in a synchronised coordinated fashion. However,
nonsynchronised
pelvic floor muscle contractions are often detected and this is thought to be the cause of pelvic
floor dysfunction such as urinary incontinence. If spinal adjustments are able to improve pelvic floor muscle function
then this could have important benefits for both delivery and pelvic floor health. Spinal adjustments are known to
improve the timing and ability to contract the deep abdominal muscles. Since the pelvic floor muscles work together
with the abdominal muscles, it is possible that adjustments will also be able to improve the timing and the
synchronization of the pelvic floor muscles.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Health and Disability Ethics Committees
Ministry of Health
C/- MEDSAFE, Level 6, Deloitte House
10 Brandon Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/06/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/NTA/75</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/05/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Heidi Haavik</name>
      <address>New Zealand College of Chiropractic
6 Harrison Road
Ellerslie
Auckland 1060</address>
      <phone>+6495266789</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>heidi.haavik@nzchiro.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Heidi Haavik</name>
      <address>New Zealand College of Chiropractic
6 Harrison Road
Ellerslie
Auckland 1060</address>
      <phone>+6495266789</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>heidi.haavik@nzchiro.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Heidi Haavik</name>
      <address>New Zealand College of Chiropractic
6 Harrison Road
Ellerslie
Auckland 1060</address>
      <phone>+6495266789</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>heidi.haavik@nzchiro.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Holt</name>
      <address>New Zealand College of Chiropractic
6 Harrison Road
Ellerslie
Auckland 1060</address>
      <phone>+6495266789</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kelly.holt@nzchiro.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>