<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372670">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000665336p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Impact of clinical pharmacist medication review on appropriate prescribing in elderly patients: A randomized, controlled trial
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Impact of clinical pharmacist medication review on appropriate prescribing as measured by Medication Appropriateness Index in elderly patients: A randomized, controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1194-9579 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>inappropriate prescribing</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients with chronic disease have regular visit to their physician in the Specialist Out-patient Clinic (SOPC) for follow-up. 
For the intervention group, clinical pharmacist with 5 years of clinical experience will perform medication chart review prior to the next SOPC follow-up, The review includes assessing the appropriateness of each of the regular medications based on laboratory findings, medication lists, consultation and discharge notes, procedures and test results. Face-to-face interview (lasts for around 30-45 mins) will then be conducted with patients on the day prior to the SOPC follow-up. Clinical pharmacists will assess drug use history, identify drug-related problems and provide drug therapy interventions through written pharmacist note to physicians during the SOPC follow-up, based on the medication chart review and the above pharmaceutical assessments. Immediately after the SOPC follow up, clinical pharmacist will provide education (which lasts  about 15 minutes) on drug-related problem identified before the visit, reinforce physicians instruction, and encourage drug compliance using written patient educational leaflets. Phone follow follow-up will be conducted 1 month after the pharmacist intervention. 
Written patient education leaflets were published by the Central Pharmacy Office, Hong Kong Hospital Authority.</interventions>
    <comparator>For patient randomzied to control group, they will attend the medical follow-up as usual and receive usual care, in which patients would have visit their physicians during the Specalist Out-patient Clinic (SOPC) and with their medication dispensed in the Out-patient pharmacy as usual. No pharmacist medication review will be performed, and no pharmacist interview with patients for the contro group. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medication Appropriateness Index (MAI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured at baseline and at 1 month post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in number of drugs prescribed to each participant
assessed by review of medical record</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 1 month post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Potentially Inappropriate Medications (PIMs) identified by Screening Tool of Older Persons Prescription (STOPP)
by review of medical record</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 1 month post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Potential Prescription Omission (PPOs) identified by the Screening Tool to Alert Doctors to the Right Treatment (START)
by review of medical record</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 1 month post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in total number of drug related problems
by review of medical record
</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 1 month post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of pharmacist intervention made 
assessed by review of medical record</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>30 day-unplanned hospital admission
by review of medical record
</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>30 day- AED visit
by review of medical record
</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medication adherence measured by Morisky Score (MMAS-4)
by interview with patient
</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 1 month post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction will be assessed by four questions from the Health Care Attitude Questionnaire at the end of study, which will be rated by a 5-point Likert scales
by interview with patient</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of pharmacist intervention that is followed by physician
by review of medical record</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria> Patients are eligible for the study if they 1) attend medical follow up in Specialized Out-patient Clinic (SOPC) of the Department of Medicine, 2) are 65 years or older, 3) have hyper-polypharmacy (defined as 10 or more regular drugs and 4) agree to provide oral informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria> 1) patients who are cognitively impaired (defined as a clinical diagnosis of dementia or mild cognitive impairment and/or not communicable and do not have care-givers, 2)patients who had received pharmacist medication review within six months prior to randomization. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>central randomization by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>randomized using computer generated number</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size calculation is based on previous study showing clinical pharmacist significantly reduced inappropriate prescribing. A sample size of 100 per arm is required to provide a 80% power using a two sided alpha-level of 0.05 to detect a mean difference in MAI of 0.4 between the intervention group and control group. Sample size is made up to 120 per arm to account for drop out. 
For baseline characteristic, Wilcoxon rank sum test will be used for ordinal variables, and chi-square test will be used for categorical variables. Difference in MAI between the intervention group and control group will be compared by Students t-test.For other secondary outcome measurement with ordinal variables, Wilcoxon rank sum test will be used, and chi-square test for categorical variables. In all cases, 2-tailed P values of &lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital
3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan, HK</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital
3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan, HK</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Hong Kong</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study aims to evaluate the impact of clinical pharmacist medication review to improve appropriate prescribing as demonstrated by Medication Appropriateness Index (MAI) in comparison to standard care.
This is a prospective randomized controlled trial, which will be conducted in Specialized Out-patient Clinic (SOPC) of the Department of Medicine in Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital.
For the intervention group, medication chart review and corresponding written recommendation will be performed by clinical pharmacists for all randomized patients. Medication chart review includes assessing the appropriateness of each of the regular medications based on laboratory findings, medication lists, consultation and discharge notes, procedures and test results. Face-to-face interview will be conducted with patients prior to the SOPC follow-up. Clinical pharmacists will assess drug use history, identify drug-related problems and provide drug therapy interventions through written pharmacist note to physicians during the SOPC follow-up, based on the medication chart review and the above pharmaceutical assessments. After the SOPC follow up, clinical pharmacist will provide education on drug-related problem identified before the visit, reinforce physicians instruction, and encourage drug compliance using written patient educational leaflets. Phone follow follow-up will be conducted 1months after the SOPC visit. 
For patients randomized to the SOC group, they will attend the medical follow-up as usual and receive usual care
All patients will be followed up for 1 months post-SOPC visit. Data collection will be conducted at baseline and1monthafter the SOPC visit.
Primary outcome of the study is Medication Appropriateness Index (MAI)5, which will be measured at baseline (prior to physician visit), and at 1 month post SOPD follow-up.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HKEC Ethics Comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital
3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan, HK</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/04/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372670-Study proposal2017.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Heidi Chan</name>
      <address>Pharmacy, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital
3Lok Man Road, Chai Wan, HK</address>
      <phone>+852-64601008</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cyh123@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Heidi Chan</name>
      <address>Pharmacy, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital
3Lok Man Road, Chai Wan, HK</address>
      <phone>+852-64601008</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cyh123@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Heidi Chan</name>
      <address>Pharmacy, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital
3Lok Man Road, Chai Wan, HK</address>
      <phone>+852-64601008</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cyh123@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Heidi Chan</name>
      <address>Pharmacy, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital
3Lok Man Road, Chai Wan, HK</address>
      <phone>+852-64601008</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cyh123@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>