<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373437">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001236381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of low dialysate sodium on interdialytic weight gain (IDWG) and hypertension in patients undergoing chronic intermittent haemodialysis  a prospective study in The Townsville Hospital and the North Ward haemodialysis units
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of low dialysate sodium on interdialytic weight gain (IDWG) and hypertension in patients undergoing chronic intermittent haemodialysis  a prospective study in The Townsville Hospital and the North Ward haemodialysis units
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Renal failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention phase:  alteration of sodium bath concentration in dialyser from 140mEq/L to 136mEq/L

-Participants will be provided an information sheet explaining the intervention and purpose of the study
-Dialysis nurses  (competent to deliver a dialysis service) will alter settings on the machine to allow change in sodium bath.  Participants will otherwise undergo their normal dialysis treatment in the unit.
-Delivery of the intervention will take place at each dialysis session.
- The intervention will be performed at each dialysis session (three sessions per week) for a total of 8 weeks
- Initially the bath concentration will be decreased from 140mEq/l to 138mEq/l for 1 week (three treatment sessions) and then to 136mEq/l for the remainder of the data collection period
- The intervention will occur within the haemodialysis unit (Townsville Hospital; North Ward Satellite Clinic)

The intervention will be applied to all eligible participants
Participants will need to attend their usual planned haemodialysis treatment to receive the intervention.
Adherence:
-Dialysis nurses routinely call patients when they do not attend their planned haemodialysis treatment; social workers provide assistance for community-based transport for those who require it;
2.  The 8 week control period will be performed prior to the 8 week intervention period for every participant.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Active Control:  sodium bath concentration in dialyser remains at 140mEq/L

-Participants will be provided an information sheet explaining the intervention and purpose of the study
-Dialysis nurses  (competent to deliver a dialysis service) will not change the usual sodium bath.  Participants will undergo their normal dialysis treatment in the unit.
-Delivery of the intervention will take place at each dialysis session.
- The control phase will be performed at each dialysis session (three sessions per week) for a total of 8 weeks
- Sodium bath concentration remains unchanged for an 8 week period of observation
- The control phase will occur within the haemodialysis unit (Townsville Hospital; North Ward Satellite Clinic)

All eligible participants will undergo a 8 week period of observation with the usual dialysis regime
Participants will need to attend their usual planned haemodialysis treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with a reduction in interdialytic weight gain of at least 0.5kg after reduction in dialysate sodium (by 4mEq/L); assessed by weighing participant pre and post dialysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks following intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with reduction in interdialytic hypertension of at least 10mmHg (systolic blood pressure), assessed by sphygomanometer prior to commencing dialysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of  number of hypotensive events (interdialytic and postdialytic); defined as SBP &lt;100mmHg, per week; assessed by sphygomanometer during and immediately following dialysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of post dialysis cramping (number of episodes per week), assessed by patient self-report</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of intra- and post dialysis events of nausea (events per week), assessed by patient self-report</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of headache during or following dialysis (episodes per week); assessed by patient self-report</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients aged between 18 and 90 years
2. Patients on maintenance haemodialysis for at least 6 months
3. Patients with significant IDWG (2 kilogram or more) with or without associated uncontrolled hypertension
4. Patients who are medically stable with no other acute issues that can affect the study outcome 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients who have cardiac failure and cardiovascular compromise 
2. Patients who are admitted to hospital for acute illness
3. Patients who are hyponatraemic (sodium &lt;135)
3. Patients prone for hypotension
4. Patients who are pregnant
5. Patients who are homeless
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>If the true difference in the experimental and control means is 0.6, the study will need 44 subjects to be able to reject the null hypothesis that the population means of the experimental and control groups are equal with probability (power) 0.8. The Type I error probability associated with this test of this null hypothesis is 0.05 (Sample size calculated using openepi version 3. The mean weight gain and SD for sample size calculations were based on the study by Mendoza JM, et al. Effect of Lowering Dialysate Sodium Concentration on Interdialytic Weight Gain and Blood Pressure in Patients undergoing Thrice-weekly In-Centre Nocturnal Hemodialysis: A Quality Improvement Study). 

Continuous variables will be tested for normality. Based on the outcome of the test parametric students T test or non-parametric Mann-Whitney test will be carried out to determine the significant differences in weight gain. Paired tests will be carried out to determine differences in weight gain among the patients during and after the treatment. Categorical data will be analysed using the Chi-squared analysis. Bivariate analysis would be performed for determining the confounding factors. Where appropriate multivariate tests will be carried out, a p value &lt; 0.05 will be considered statistically significant.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>2/02/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/03/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Townsville Hospital - Douglas</hospital>
    <postcode>4814 - Douglas</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Townsville Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>100 Angus Smith Drive
Douglas, QLD 4810</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Townsville Hospital </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Renal Medicine
100 Angus Smith Drive
Douglas QLD 4810</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Purpose of the research
Significant weight gain and poorly controlled blood pressure are commonly seen in patients with end stage renal disease on intermittent hemodialysis. There is evidence that these complications are due to not enough salt being removed from the body during hemodialysis. The hemodialysis machine currently uses a standard strength of sodium during each hemodialysis session. If this concentration is reduced, this may improve blood pressure control and decrease the amount of weight gained between dialysis sessions. The reason we are doing this research is to find out if the low sodium fluid is better than the regular concentration that is currently being used.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Townsville Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethcis Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>100 Angus Smith Drive
Douglas, QLD 4810

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QTHS/200</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373437-Informed Consent V1.4 11-05-17.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373437-16QTHS200_4 Approved.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373437-ResearchProtocolV1.411052017.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catherine Wilkinson</name>
      <address>The Townsville Hospital
100 Angus Smith Drive
Douglas QLD 4810
</address>
      <phone>+617 44331111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.wilkinson@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catherine Wilkinson</name>
      <address>The Townsville Hospital
100 Angus Smith Drive
Douglas QLD 4810</address>
      <phone>+61 7 4433 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.wilkinson@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catherine Wilkinson</name>
      <address>The Townsville Hospital
100 Angus Smith Drive
Douglas QLD 4810</address>
      <phone>+61 7 44331111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.wilkinson@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Catherine Wilkinson</name>
      <address>The Townsville Hospital
100 Angus Smith Drive
Douglas QLD 4810</address>
      <phone>+61 7 4433 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>catherine.wilkinson@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>