<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1119">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/02/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/02/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000074594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An oral killed Non-typeable Haemophilus influenzae vaccine for preventing episodes of acute bronchitis in patients with moderate to severe airways disease: Safety and efficacy study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A multi-centre, double blind, placebo controlled, prospective study to assess safety and efficacy of orally administered killed whole cell nontypeable Haemophilus influenzae (NTHi) HI-1-164 in preventing episodes of acute bronchitis in patients with moderate to severe airway disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Hunter Immunology Ltd Protocol HI-H002</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute bronchitis in moderate to severe airway disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects will be randomly allocated to active tablets each containing 45mg HI-1-164-AS (inactivated non-typeable Haemophilus influenzae).                                                                           Study medication (2 tablets) will be taken on days 1,2,3, 29,30,31, 57, 58,59.                                                                                                                                                                           The live phase of the study will be of 8 months duration (March-October).</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo tablets containing excipients only. Placebo (2 tablets) will be taken on days 1,2,3, 29,30,31, 57, 58,59. The live phase of the study will be of 8 months duration (March-October).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of episodes of acute bronchitis during the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of subjects experiencing an episode of acute bronchitis during the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The duration of episodes of acute bronchitis during the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of courses of antibiotics taken for treatment of acute episodes of bronchitis during the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>NTHi-specific antibody</outcome>
      <timepoint>At beginning and end of study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharyngeal colonisation with H. influenzae </outcome>
      <timepoint>Gargles collected at each of the monthly visits (7-9 visits depending on date of registration).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of H. influenzae, M. catarrhalis, S. pneumoniae and Pseudomonas spp in sputum </outcome>
      <timepoint>Sputum collected at each of the monthly visits (7-9 visits depending on date of registration), and also at times of acute excerbations.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of episodes of acute bronchitis.  It was planned that the analysis of the severity of episodes of acute bronchitis was to be based on the respiratory questionnaires completed by the patients at the time of each episode. However, insufficient respiratory questionnaires were completed during the study to allow for analysis of the data collected. In accordance with recent draft guidance for industry for developing drugs for treatment of COPD issued by FDA in November 2007, assessment of modification or prevention of exacerbations of disease can include severity of exacerbations as a primary efficacy endpoint. This can be based on worsening in symptoms requiring changes in treatment or requiring urgent treatment or hospitalisation. On a post hoc basis, rates of hospitalisation, corticosteroid use and a review of the medications used to treat the episodes of acute bronchitis were all analysed as measures of severity of episodes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Severity of episodes was measured at each of the monthly visits (7-9 visits depending on time of registration).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety parameters.  This outcome was measured by biochemistry and haematology profiling on bloods collected at visits 1, 3 and final visit, and also via adverse event data collected by patient verbatim at each visit. Examples of adverse events include cough, hypertension, headache (these events were not related to investigational product).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Bloods for safety profiling were collected at visits 1, 3 and final visit; adverse event data was collected at every visit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Moderate to severe airway disease (FEV1 less than or equal to 50% of predicted value); at least two episodes of acute bronchitis in each of the past two years; no medical or social reason for being unable to comply with study requirements; willingness and availability to give informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known current infection (except bronchitis); taking of antibiotics within 4 weeks prior to visit 1; participation in a clinical trial of any vaccine or immune stimulating product (except probiotics) in the past 12 months (unless known to have received placebo treatment only); participation in a clinical trial apart from that described above, in the past 3 months); pregnant, breast-feeding, or women with child-bearing potential without an effective form of contraception; any significant medical disorder which would preclude evaluation of the patient's condition (except COPD); any subject likely to withdraw or not comply with the study protocol; any other medical reason for which the investigator feels a patient should not be included.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Interested persons were provided with an Information Statement and Consent Form to read. An appointment was then made for the first visit where an informed consent discussion occurred and consent was obtained. Participants were allocated a Subject number &amp; Randomisation number. The randomisation code was held in a sealed envelope at each study site - only randomisation code envelopes specific to that site was forwarded to the site.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation code was generated using MS Excel. Restriction method: block randomisation, issued in blocks of six to ensure equal distribution between groups if maximum number of participants were recruited.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/03/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>124</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>6009</postcode>
    <postcode>2300</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hunter Immunology Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suite 209-210, 18 Rodborough Road,
Frenchs Forest NSW 2086</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hunter Immunology Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 209-210, 18 Rodborough Road,
Frenchs Forest NSW 2086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This aim of this study is to determine whether an oral vaccine against non-typeable Haemophilus influenzae will reduce the number of episodes of acute bronchitis experienced by people with moderate to severe airway disease</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hollywood Private Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Avenue, 
Nedlands, Western Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/12/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HPH206</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/11/2005</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emeritus Professor Robert Clancy</name>
      <address>Hunter Immnology Ltd,
David Maddison Building Level 4,
Cnr King and Watt Sts,
Newcastle NSW 2300</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4913 8135</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4913 8998</fax>
      <email>Robert.Clancy@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emeritus Professor Robert Clancy</name>
      <address>Hunter Immnology Ltd,
David Maddison Building Level 4,
Cnr King and Watt Sts,
Newcastle NSW 2300</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4913 8135</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4913 8998</fax>
      <email>Robert.Clancy@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>