<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370212">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000290493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pelvic floor assessment in post-partum women</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Symptomatic and physiological consequences of obstetric anal sphincter injury in post-partum females</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Fecal incontinence in post-partum women</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obstetric anal sphincter injury syndrome (OASIS)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will be asked to complete a follow up questionnaire. 
Anorectal manometry and anorectal ultrasound is to be performed on patient who are consenting to a repeat study using our standard protocol. 
(1) Anorectal manometry. This involves insertion of a thin catheter into your rectum (back passage) while you are lying on your left side on a bed. Pressure measurements are then obtained while you squeeze your anal muscles, while you cough and when you bear down or strain. In addition, a small balloon will be inflated inside your rectum and you will be asked to rate the sensations felt at that time. Lastly, you will be requested to try to expel the balloon over a private toilet and  (2) Anorectal ultrasound. This involves insertion of an anorectal ultrasound probe into your rectum (back passage) while you are lying on your left side on a bed. Imaging is obtained assessing for your anal sphincters. Both procedures are performed by a physician or a nurse specialist and will be done discretely and with consideration for your privacy at all times. The procedures can cause minor discomfort, but this will be minimised by careful technique. Overall the appointment time is approximately 60 minutes. 
The patients invited to participate in this study have previously attended our neurogastroenterology unit for testing between 2001 and 2015. Our follow-up data will consequently offer a follow-up period between 1-15 years. 
For ARM testing, the testing protocol is identical to the testing protocol the patients have previously undergone in our Unit. For the anorectal ultrasound, as not all patients have performed this study previously in our Unit, our protocol might be slightly different then the procedure they had previously undergone. Nevertheless, the protocol follows international standards and should be much similiar. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control groups</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The development of faecal incontinence in previously asymptomatic post-obstetric women with anal sphincter tear. This will be assessed by long term follow up Faecal incontinence severity index (FISI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients selected have already completed an anorectal study within our unit at the request of their obstetrician/physician/surgeon between 2001 and 2015. They are invited to complete a follow-up study (identical protocol) to compare data/outcome for this study, hence the follow-up period is anywhere between 1 to 15 years. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The time-related changes in anorectal physiology following OASIS. This will be assessed by the comparing the anorectal physiology parameters (anal pressures) after childbirth to long-term repeated testing. </outcome>
      <timepoint>1-15 years following initial assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Single component outcome of subsequent birth history(inclduing repeat OASIS) following previous OASIS. This will be assessed by follow up questionnaires specifically designed for the study and access to ObstetriX to obtain the mode and complications of subsequent deliveries. </outcome>
      <timepoint>1-15 years following initial assessment </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in quality of life following OASIS. This will be assessed by QOL of life questionnaires (SF36, VAS scores)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-15 years following initial assessment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Outcome in sexual function as assessed by the Sexual Function for Women with: POP, Urinary Incontinence and/or Fecal Incontinence questionnaire. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-15 years following initial assessment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Post-partum females referred to the Neurogastroenterology Unit for anorectal manometry between 1.1.2001 and 1.1.2016

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The only exclusion criterion for the study includes patients with a history of psychological illness or condition such as to interfere with the patients ability to understand the requirements of the study. 

Only for patients who agree to undergo repeat physiological testing, exclusion criteria include:
1.	Women lactating or pregnant.
2.	Patients with significant anorectal disease precluding the insertion of an anorectal tube or ultrasound probe. 
3.	Latex allergy
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>We will review 300 patients overall, so that we can realistically obtain the 150 patients  required to reach statistical power. 

9.1	Sample Size Estimation
Aim 1: For quantitative measures a sample of n=144 would provide statistical power of 0.8 and the 0.05 (two-tailed) level of statistical significance for a Cohens d effect size of 0.5 (moderate effect size). For qualitative measures a sample of n=92 would provide statistical power of 0.8 and the 0.05 (two-tailed) level of statistical significance for an odds ratio of 2.0 from a baseline probability of 0.3 (overall Fecal Incontinence rate in this group is approximately 1/3).
Aim 2: In aim 2, based entire on unconditional logistic regression (see below), there is an additional consideration of correlation between potential predictors. Defining the minimum clinically important effect size as an odds ratio of 2.0 and assuming a baseline rate of 15%, to allow for a correlation between any predictor and other predictors of 0.3 increases the required sample size from 92 to 149.

Based on this consideration of samples size per aim the expected available sample size (n=150) should exceed the required sample size for all statistical analyses.


9.2	Statistical Analysis Plan 
Aim 1: Among women who have undergone Anorectal manometry those who develop Fecal Incontinence will be compared with those who have not developed Fecal Incontinence with respect to quantitative parameters using the Mann-Whitney test and with respect to qualitative parameters via the Pearson Chi-Square test. A nonparametric approach will be adopted due to the expected non-Normal distribution of a number of the quantitative parameters. Identification of statistically independent discriminators of women who develop Fecal Incontinence from those who do not will be via backward elimination within unconditional logistic regression.
Aim 2: All quantitative and qualitative measures utilised in aims 1  which were recorded at the time of OASIS (Obstetric anal sphincter injury syndrome)  will be considered as potentially predictive of the development of subsequent pelvic floor complications. The probability of development of pelvic floor complications will be modelled using unconditional logistic regression with predictive variables selected by backward elimination to ensure the full covariance structure of the predictors is taken into account. To protect against the over-optimism phenomenon to which model selection procedures are prone the selection process will itself be bootstrapped (2000 replications) and only predictive measures that are selected in at least 50% of bootstrap samples will be considered in the final predictive model.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>15</followup>
    <followuptype>Years</followuptype>
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - Royal North Shore Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Allison Malcolm </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal North Shore Hospital
Neurogastroenterology Unit
Reserve Road
St-Leonards, NSW 2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dr Allison Malcolm Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal North Shore Hospital
Reserve Road
St-Leonards, NSW 2065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>n/a</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>n/a</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obstetric anal sphincter injury syndrome (OASIS) is a common occurrence in females after childbirth, and is an established risk factor for faecal incontinence (FI). Risk factors for OASIS include increased maternal age, high birth-weight and co-morbidities such as diabetes. As each of these elements is on the rise, the likelihood is that the frequency of OASIS will increase, and along with it, the possible increased burden FI. However, its association with the development of FI remains poorly understood and the obstetrics recommendation following OASIS (C-section vs vaginal delivery) on subsequent pregnancies is highly variable and debated in the literature.  

We aim to assess the anorectal physiology effect of OASIS, as well as its impact on the patient (Sexual health, quality of life, urinary and faecal incontinence) to first obtain a better understanding of OASIS. We will then compare the data of patients who develop FI (symptomatic) to those who do not (asymptomatic) in an effort to better understand OASIS and its link to FI.  Lastly, we aim to collect long term follow up data on patients in order to assess for the subsequent development of FI and other pelvic floor problems. This will enable us to build a prediction model to assist in clarifying the obstetricians practice and recommendations for future pregnancies in women with OASIS and/or FI. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Kolling building, level 13
Royal North Shore Hospital
Reserve Road
St-Leonards, NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/HAWKE/486</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Allison Malcolm</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital
Neurogastroenterology Unit
Reserve Road
St-Leonards, NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61(0)294632450</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amalcolm@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Allison Malcolm</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital
Neurogastroenterology Unit
Reserve Road
St-Leonards, NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61(0)294632450</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amalcolm@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Allison Malcolm</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital
Neurogastroenterology Unit
Reserve Road
St-Leonards, NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61(0)294632450</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amalcolm@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yoav Mazor</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital
Neurogastroenterology Unit
St-Leonards, NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61(0)294632450</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yoavmazor@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>