<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83571">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/02/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/04/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000166279</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised control trial of an internet-based outpatient cardiac rehabilitation program</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The efficacy of an internet-mediated cardiac rehabilitation program in increasing health-related phsycial activity participation in a sample of Phase II cardiac rehab patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>eOCR</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cardiac rehabiliations</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The project involves the assessment of an electronic Outpatient Cardiac Rehabilitation (eOCR) platform, which was designed and developed by the research team at CQUniversity with the assistance of cardiac rehabilitation professionals. The platform is an internet-based educational content management system that provides the online cardiac case manager with the ability to deliver interactive outpatient education, track patient progress by means of an online patient self-monitoring system and interact with the patient and/or their selected significant others within the security-protected web-based platform. The patient view of the eOCR site includes a patient dashboard which is specifically tailored by the case manager for the participant to collect, track and display important health and behavioural measures. The site contains a library comprised of readings drawn from existing best practice guidelines and the My Heart My Life publication by the Heart Foundation and a workbook that provides interactive educational activities relating to behavioral self management developed by the researchers in previous studies. The site also includes a variety of communication tools aimed at allowing patients to interact with their cardiac case manager, other patients and/or significant others that the patient has invited to take part (the support people are provided with their own login and home pages). Communication tools include email, discussion boards, and an integrated Voice over Internet Protocol (VoIP) programming link (Skype). The site also maintains records of the patients contact details and those of significant others as well as emergency contact details and protocols. The online cardiac case manager has a separate content/patient management structure, which allows them to track the progress in terms of readings, educational activities and patient self-report data for one or more patients concurrently. The case manager can also interact with the patients under their guidance by way of site email, discussion or VoIP. The current study assesses the efficacy of the use of the platform in the reduction of subsequent cardiovascular risk compared to individuals who undertake regular care. Participants progress at their own rate through a 12-week educational program</interventions>
    <comparator>The overall study population is drawn from individuals who decline participation in existing conventional face-to-face cardiac rehabilitation. The control group are individuals in the no treatment group who receive no other concurrent support. The control group will be assessed at baseline and 12 weeks post-baseline, at the same timepoints as the intervention group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure is the risk of recurrent coronary heart disease as assessed by the Framingham Risk Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and completion of intervention (12 weeks)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional Capacity measured by the Duke Activity Status Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and completion of intervention (12 weeks)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The key inclusion criteria are: eligibility for phase II cardiac rehabilitation program, living in an area serviced by broadband internet service provider and meeting American College of Sports Medicine (ACSM) guidelines for inclusion in physical activity/exercise</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>individuals who fail to meet ACSM exercise guidelines, patients with imparied ventricular function, patients with heart failure or controlled cardiac failure,arrythmisas, pacemaker, hostory of cariac arrest, preinz metal angina, uncontrolled diabetes</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>MBF Foundation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>50 Bridge St
Sydney NSW 2000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medical Benefits Fund (MBF) Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50 Bridge St
Sydney NSW 2000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Rockhampton Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Canning Street ROCKHAMPTON QLD 4700</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The overall objective of the project is to complete a randomised control trial to test the effectiveness and efficacy of an internet-based (electronic) outpatient cardiac rehabilitation program. Phase II outpatient cardiac rehabilitation patients who choose not to complete a face to face program will be invited to participate in the study. Patients willing and eligible for the study will have their baseline data collected and will then be randomised into either a 'Control' (or usual care) group or the 'Intervention' group. Control participants will undertake their intended usual care with no contact with the research team until follow-up. The Intervention participants will be provided with a laptop and internet connection (if necessary) for the period of the intervention. Participants will be encouraged to access the online program with monitoring via the online program by a cardiac rehabilitation case manager.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>CQUniversity, Bruce Highway, 
Rockhampton, QLD 4702</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/02/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof. Kerry Mummery</name>
      <address>Institute of Health and Social Science Research, CQUniversity Australia
Bruce Highway, Rockhampton, QLD, 4702</address>
      <phone>+61 7 4930 6749</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.mummery@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mrs. Anetta VanItallie</name>
      <address>Institute of Health and Social Science Research, CQUniversity Australia, Bruce Highway, 
Rockhampton, QLD, 4702</address>
      <phone>+61 7 4923 2171</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.vanitallie@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof. Kerry Mummery</name>
      <address>Institute of Health and Social Science Research, CQUniversity Australia
Bruce Hwy, Rockhampton, QLD, 4702</address>
      <phone>+61 7 4930 6749</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.mummery@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>