<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372659">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001205325p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prevent Second Stroke (P2S): A randomised controlled trial of stroke survivors testing an online program to improve quality of life. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Healthy living after stroke: An online intervention for improving stroke
survivor health behaviours and quality of life</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Nicotine Addiction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Poor diet quality</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Alcohol consumption</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical inactivity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Individuals in the intervention group will receive access to an online program called Prevent Second Stroke (P2S). Individuals will be advised to access the program at least once a week, with a training video on how to use the program presented to the individual on first use. Individuals will have access to the online program for 12 weeks, and will be able to access 24 hours a day, 7 days a week during that time.
P2S contains evidence-base techniques and information in six core modules: 1) Blood Pressure, 2) Smoking, 3) Alcohol, 4) Activity, 5) Nutrition, and 6) Feelings and Mood available as icons across the top of the screen, along with Home and My Progress icons. Each health risk behaviour module commences with 2-3 brief questions regarding the topic of interest (e.g., Blood Pressure: their last blood pressure reading and when they were last screened; Smoking: smoking status, how many cigarettes per day, interest in quitting) in order to provide tailored information to the user. Each module will take approximately 20-30 minutes to complete. Participants will be asked to set a specific goal at the end of each module and will be provided with information and advice on how to achieve the goal. The information contained in each module is in the form of videos and text based information. Individuals will also be provided with other useful website links to more information. The advice in each module is tailored to accommodate stroke-related symptoms. 
Timing data will be collected from the online platform which hosts the program regarding the time spent on program modules. Fortnightly texts and emails will be sent to prompt program access. At present there are no plans to have a member of the research team checking fidelity or adherence to the program, with no plans at present made to analyse timing data.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomised to the minimal ethical care control group will receive a letter with the web addresses of readily available, generic online health programs designed for the general population (e.g., Department of Health Quit Now; Eat for Health sites; the MOODGym site).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life (EuroQuol-5 Dimensions [EQ-5D-5L])</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost-effectiveness (Client Service Receipt Inventory [CSRI])</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression and anxiety levels (Patient Health Questionnaire for Depression and Anxiety [PHQ-4])</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical functioning and independent living (Activities of Daily Living [ADL]
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Smoking status (Heaviness of Smoking Index (HSI))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol consumption (Alcohol Use Disorders. Identification Test  Consumption [AUDIT-C])</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diet quality (Australian Recommended Food Score [ARFS])</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity (Godin Leisure Time Exercise Questionnaire [GTLEQ])</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Instrumental Activities of Daily Living [IADL] scales)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 &amp; 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>hospital re-admission for all causes (using medical records data)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1)	admitted to an Australian Stroke Clinical Registry (AuSCR) hospital for first episode of care for acute stroke or other indexed stroke event (ischaemic, haemorrhagic, TIA, or undetermined types of stroke will be included) at 6  36 months post stroke;
2)	sufficiently fluent in English; and 
3)	sufficiently fluent in internet use via a home device (e.g. computer or tablet device) or willing to use public internet services (e.g. public library).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1)	been admitted with a subsequent stroke event (second to the indexed stroke event) or documented evidence of a previous stroke; or
2)	experienced disability at a level that may limit their use of the program (determined using a score of &gt;2 in the modified Rankin Score.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A computer random number generator embedded in the computer assisted telephone interview (CATI) software will be used to allocate study participants to either receive the intervention or standard care, once all baseline questions have been answered. </concealment>
    <sequence>Individuals will be randomised in permuted blocks of randomly varying size (e.g. 4 and 6), stratified by state (New South Wales, Queensland, Western Australia and Victoria/Tasmania), and type of stroke (ischaemic, haemorrhagic, TIA). The block size will be masked from all except the statistician. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The distribution of all variables will be checked for normality, with non-parametric statistics used when appropriate. The age and gender of participants will be compared to that of the non-responders (AuSCR database) to investigate the representativeness of the study sample.
A full Statistical Analysis Plan will be written prior to the completion of data collection.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>530</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/03/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1 University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of the trial is to examine, using a randomised controlled trial, the effectiveness of an online healthy recovery intervention program (Prevent 2nd Stroke[P2S]) in improving health-related quality of life amongst stroke survivors at 6 months follow-up. Stroke survivors will be recruited from the The Australian Stroke Clinical Registry (AuSCR) database which contains the contact information of individuals who have had a stoke or TIA (indexed stroke event). Individuals assigned to the intervention group will receive 12 weeks access to the P2S program which they are able to to use to help improve their health behaviours and health outcomes. 
P2S is an online health behaviour change program containing six modules: 1) Blood Pressure, 2) Smoking, 3) Alcohol, 4) Activity, 5) Nutrition, and 6) Feelings and Mood. The program is interactive and tailored to accommodate stroke-related symptoms. Goals and progress will be monitored and graphed and will be available to the user in a My Progress section of the program.
at 6 and 12 months follow-up, health-related quality of life will be determined, as too will be:
a)	depression and anxiety levels; 
b)	self-reported physical functioning and independent living; 
c)	four health risk behaviours (smoking cessation, reduction in alcohol use, diet quality, and increase in moderate physical activity), and; 
d)	hospital admission for recurrent stroke, myocardial infarction and all causes 

Cost-effectiveness of the intervention will also be determined at 6 and 12 months. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle Human Ethics Comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 University Drive 
Callaghan NSW 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Billie Bonevski</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle
1 University Drive 
Callaghan NSW 
Australia 
2308</address>
      <phone>+61 240 335 710</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>billie.bonevski@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Olivia Wynne</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle
1 University Drive 
Callaghan NSW 
Australia 
2308</address>
      <phone>+61 240 335 705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>olivia.wynne@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Olivia Wynne</name>
      <address>The University of Newcastle
1 University Drive 
Callaghan NSW 
Australia 
2308</address>
      <phone>+61 240 335 705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>olivia.wynne@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>