<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364787">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/12/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001348741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel group, ascending multiple dose study to evaluate the tolerability of Manuka Honey with Honey CycloPowerTM chewable tablets taken daily by healthy subjects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel , ascending multiple dose study to evaluate the tolerability of Manuka Honey with Honey CycloPowerTM chewable tablets taken daily by healthy subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1146-9102</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gastro-intestinal effect </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Oral health and wellness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Gastro-intestinal wellness</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The purpose of this study is to evaluate safety and tolerability following the oral administration (sucking) of Manuka Honey with Cyclopower a day for 2 weeks.  Cohort 1 will take 800mg (1 chewable tablet); Cohort 2 will take 1600mgs (2 tablets); cohort 3 will take 2400mgs (3 chewable tablets); cohort 4 will take 3200mgs (4 tablets); cohort 5 will take  4000mgs (5 tablets) and cohort 6 will take 4,800mg (6 chewable tablets), each cohort takes this amount daily in single or divided doses for 2 weeks (3 tablets 1x3 times daily; 4 tablets 2x2 daily; 5 tablets 2x2 plus 1x1 daily; 6 tablets 2x3 daily) . An exploratory assessment will also be completed to assess the potential benefits on oral health via saliva pH measurement.  All unused tablets will be returned.</interventions>
    <comparator>There is a placebo arm to this trial made up largely of maltodextrin and sorbitol, which will be administered at the same time as the active treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of a range of doses of Honey Cyclopower chewable tablets in healthy subjects taken orally (sucked) daily for 2 weeks.  Mouth swabs will be taken for saliva testing and patients will be required to report any adverse effects including nausea and loose stools.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the effect of the study treatment on saliva pH after rinsing the mouth with a 10% sucrose solution</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Healthy subjects age 18 to 45 years of age inclusive, and in good health as determined by past medical history, physical examination, vital signs at screening.
2. Subjects must be non-smoking (no use of tobacco products in the previous 3 months).
3. Subjects must have had no active dental caries within the last 2 years of screening and be willing to avoid intake of food or beverages for at least 1 hour (for the collection of saliva samples) at randomisation and at the final visit.
4. Subjects must have a body mass index (BMI) within the range of 18 to 29 kg/m2 inclusive at screening. 
5. Subjects of childbearing potential must be using an acceptable method of contraception for the duration of the study.
6. Subjects must be able to communicate well with the investigator, to understand and comply with the requirements of the study and understand and sign the written informed consent.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. A past medical history of clinically significant disease or abnormality. 
2. Known allergy to any bee products or Honey Cyclopower
3. Known allergies or intolerance to fibre-based products
4. Known allergies or intolerance to xylitol or other ingredients in the study treatment
5. Use of any prescription drugs within 7 days prior to initial dosing in this study, other than occasional use of analgesics (less than 3 days in any 7-day period) and/ or hormonal contraceptives
6. Use of any recreational drugs in last 7 days prior to initial dosing in this study
7. Significant illness within two (2) weeks prior to initial dosing in this study.
8. Randomisation in a previous study evaluating Manuka Honey with CycloPower within 6 months of initial dosing in this study.
9. Dosing of a study drug in any clinical investigation within 30 days prior to initial dosing in this study.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The investigator must ensure that all subjects being considered for the study meet the following inclusion and exclusion criteria. Deviation from any entry criterion excludes a subject from enrolment into the study.

Each subject in the study is uniquely identified by a subject number. When the subject has signed the informed consent form, the investigator or his/her staff will assign the subject number for the subject. Informed consent must be obtained before any testing is performed to determine a subject’s eligibility. Any subjects who are screened but do not meet the entry criteria will be allocated a 900 series number. The first screen failure subject will be assigned the number 901, the second 902 etc.
Randomisation and groups selection occurs with the use of a computer software programme and subjects and their specimens are only identifiable by the number that is then allocated to them - identifying data will be held at the head office of Manuka Health NZ Ltd by Dr Mandy Suddes who can then identify the participant should medical treatment be warranted for an adverse event.  Dr Suddes will not be involved in any part of the trial that involves contact with participants.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be generated by computer software programme.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multiple ascending dose </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The data will be analysed by Manuka Health New Zealand Ltd. or designee.  The decision regarding required participant numbers, sample sizes and consequent statistical analyses are decided by registered statistician Hans Hockey (in conjunction with the Manuka Health team)who works via the University of Waikato.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/09/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>20/12/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>48</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Manuka Health NZ</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>34 Hannigan Drive
Mt Wellington
Auckland 1072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Manuka Health NZ
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>34 Hannigan Drive
Mt Wellington
Auckland 1072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Waiariki Institute of Technology</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Mokoioa Drive
Rotorua 3015</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, parallel-group, multiple ascending dose study in healthy volunteers. Each subject will participate in one of 4 cohorts. Eligible subjects will receive a total daily dose (either as a single dose, twice daily or three (3) times a day) of Honey Cyclopower chewable tablets at 800mg to 4,800mg total daily dose, or the matching placebo. In each cohort, 8 subjects will receive Honey Cyclopower while 4 will receive matched placebo. 

The study will consist of a screening visit (Day -7 to -3), treatment period (Days 1 to 14) after which the final End of Study assessments will be completed. Once randomised, subjects will be given sufficient supplies for 7 days of treatment. After 7 days subjects will then return to the clinic where the subject will be assessed for safety and dosing compliance. Safety assessments will include physical examinations, vital signs, concomitant medications, adverse event and serious adverse event monitoring. If the tolerability is deemed acceptable, a second week of study treatment will be dispensed.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Waiariki Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mokoia Drive
Rotorua 3015</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lynne Chepulis</name>
      <address>C/o Waiariki Institute of Technology
Mokoia Drive
Rotorua 3015</address>
      <phone>+64226753353</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lynne.chepulis@waiariki.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Evelyn Francis</name>
      <address>Waikato District Health Board
36 Pearsons Avenue
Claudelands
Hamilton 3214</address>
      <phone>+640213882474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gypsy.francis@yahoo.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Evelyn Francis</name>
      <address>Waikato District Health Board
36 Pearsons Avenue
Claudelands
Hamilton 3214</address>
      <phone>+640213882474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gypsy.francis@yahoo.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Evelyn Francis</name>
      <address>36 Pearsons Avenue
Claudelands
Hamilton</address>
      <phone>+640213882474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gypsy.francis@yahoo.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>