<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371442">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001266459p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Microdrop administration of phenylephrine and cyclopentolate in neonates (MAPC-N)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Testing a lower than standard dose of phenylephrine and cyclopentolate in neonates requiring pupil dilation for routine retinopathy of prematurity screening and red reflex testing.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1187-0769 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>MAPC-N</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Retinopathy of prematurity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomised to receive either a combination of;
1.	One combination microdrop (7 microlitre) of both phenylephrine 1% and cyclopentolate 0.2% to both eyes.  Participants will have one to three doses administered depending on pupil dilation.
2.	One combination microdrop (7 microlitre) of both phenylephrine 0.5% and cyclopentolate 0.1% to both eyes.  Participants will have one to two doses administered depending on pupil dilation.  If a third dose is required, it will be one combination microdrop (7 microlitre) of both phenylephrine 1% and cyclopentolate 0.2%

To develop an eye colour chart to determine light iris vs dark iris.

</interventions>
    <comparator>Control treatment is one combination microdrop (7 microlitre) of both phenylephrine 1% and cyclopentolate 0.2% to both eyes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To identify whether phenylephrine 1% or 0.5% and cyclopentolate 0.2% or 0.1% in a 7 microlitre volume will achieve adequate pupil dilation (&gt;5 mm) for retinal examination in premature neonates.  Pupil dilation will be measured using two pupilometers; Colvard pupilometer and a Neuroptics pupilometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pupil measurements will be taken from both eyes at baseline, 20 minute, 45 minute, 90 minute and 120 minute intervals.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To describe the time-course of physiological markers of systemic absorption following eye drop administration (blood pressure).

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood pressure will be taken at baseline, then six hourly post mydriatic dosing for 24 hours. Manual blood pressure will be measured using a Phillips monitor.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if eye pigmentation (light or dark) is a potential covariate for phenylephrine and cyclopentolate induced pupil dilation.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pupil measurements will be taken from both eyes at baseline, 20 minute, 45 minute, 90 minute and 120 minute intervals.  Pupil measurement will be measured with both a Colvard pupilometer and a Neuroptics pupilometer.  

Eye pigmentation will be determined by comparing neonatal eye colour to a colour chart (dark eye colour vs light eye colour).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To describe the time-course of physiological markers of systemic absorption following eye drop administration (heart rate).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Heart rate will be continuously measured for 24 hours prior and 24 hours post eye drop installation. Heart rate will be measured using a Phillips monitor.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To describe the time-course of physiological markers of systemic absorption following eye drop administration (feed intolerance).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Feed intolerance will be reviewed by retrospectively reviewing feed volumes and spills, on either the category 4 or 5 observation chart, for 24 hours prior and 24 hours post eye drop installation.  Medical notes will be reviewed for 7 days post eye drop installation to monitor for diagnosis of necrotising enterocolitis.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All neonates that meet the Dunedin Hospital, Neonatal Intensive Care Unit (NICU) retinopathy of prematurity (ROP) screening criteria. 

All infants who require pupil dilation for red reflex testing.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Weeks</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>4</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any neonate with ROP greater than stage 2.
Any neonate with an ocular medical condition.
If the staff member who administered the eye drop was unsure if the microdrop reached the eye, then the neonate will be excluded from the trial, in accordance with the per-protocol study design.
Any neonate whom phenylephrine and/or cyclopentolate is contraindicated.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive statistics for use in sample size calculations
Mean (SD) within-person dilation pre-treatment between eyes.
For those that have repeat measures: Mean (SD) within-person dilation pre-treatment, between visits for each eye.
Mean (SD) post-treatment dilation for each treatment
Mean (SD) within-person dilation post-treatment (difference between treatments). (calculated for: (a) only first visit data and (b) all data including repeats).
Pearsons correlation coefficients for all within-person comparisons.
Proportion that sufficiently dilated for each treatment.
Range of dilation (mm) measured for sufficient and not sufficient.
Proportion of eyes/infants that had to be excluded because drop application was not successful.
Inter-observer reliability:
Inter-observer reliability assessed with intraclass correlation coefficient.
Mean (SD) difference between two measures by different observers (within-person mean. calculated, including repeats; then calculate the mean (SD) of the within-person means).
Data will be displayed visually where appropriate (histograms, scatter-plots, bar-graphs).
Statistical Analysis
Due to sample size, statistical tests in a pilot study are to be applied and interpreted with caution.
Was dilation different between treatments?
Paired and unpaired t-test for difference between treatments.
Was the proportion with sufficient dilation different between treatments?
McNemars test and Fishers exact test for analysis of sufficient dilation between treatments.
Was dilation different by demographics?
Using control data (current treatment) determine if pre- and post-treatment dilations are different by: gender; ethnicity; and iris colour, grade of ROP and level of respiratory support. Use unpaired t-tests for dilation measures and Fishers Exact test for sufficient dilation. Descriptive statistics (mean, SD and proportions) will be calculated for each of the groups.
Pupil diameter measurements
Correlations will be used for test-retest reliability of pupil diameter measurements and relative validity between measurement methods.
Ambient light measurements
Correlation between pre treatment dilation and ambient light.  Difference in ambient light between those that sufficiently dilate and those that didnt.  Use unpaired t-test for analysis.
Describe the time course physiological markers
Systolic and diastolic blood pressure and heart rate results will be anaylsed using summary measures of hourly mean and peak results.
Feed intolerance will be commented on using summary measures and descriptive statements.
TEAE results will be commented on using descriptive statements.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Dunedin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Pharmacy and Department of Medicine (Womens and Childrens)
18 Frederick St
Dunedin
9054</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Pharmacy and Department of Medicine (Womens and Childrens)
18 Frederick St
Dunedin
9054</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dunedin Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>201 Great King St
Dunedin
9054</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Phenylephrine and cyclopentolate are two medicines that are currently used at Dunedin Hospital during retinopathy of prematurity screening (eye checks).  The two medicines are used to dilate the pupil so the retina can be viewed.  Both of these medicines have been associated with harmful side effects such as necrotising enterocolitis, can cause reflux, feed intolerance, increase in blood pressure (which can increase the risk of intraventricular haemorrhage), increase in heart rate and there are case reports of seizures. One of the ways side effects can be reduced, is to reduce the amount of medication administered (i.e. reduce the dose).

It is known from published papers that small doses of these two medicines are likely to be effective in dilating pupils.  What is unknown is if even smaller doses are effective, and this is what this study will compare  standard eye drop doses to half the usual dose.

The hope of the researchers, is that results from this study will suggest if using an even lower dose of phenylephrine and cyclopentolate will be effective in dilating neonatal pupils, with minimal side effects.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>n/a</trialwebsite>
    <publication>n/a</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>n/a</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health Research South</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Dunedin Hospital
201 Great King St
Dunedin
9054</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371442-0. MAPC-N Study Protocol.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371442-6. MAPC-N consent form.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371442-5. MAPC-N Whanau Patient Information Form_V2.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Lisa Kremer</name>
      <address>University of Otago
School of Pharmacy
Adams Building
18 Frederick St
Dunedin
9054</address>
      <phone>+6421973255</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.kremer@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Lisa Kremer</name>
      <address>University of Otago
School of Pharmacy
Adams Building
18 Frederick St
Dunedin
9054</address>
      <phone>+6421973255</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.kremer@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Lisa Kremer</name>
      <address>University of Otago
School of Pharmacy
Adams Building
18 Frederick St
Dunedin
9054</address>
      <phone>+6421973255</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.kremer@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Lisa Kremer</name>
      <address>University of Otago
School of Pharmacy
Adams Building
18 Frederick St
Dunedin
9054</address>
      <phone>+6421973255</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.kremer@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>