<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370638">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000598482p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The relative efficacy of cognitive bias modification for interpretation or attention in social anxiety </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The relative efficacy of cognitive bias modification for interpretation or attention in social anxiety </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>n/a</utrn>
    <trialacronym>n/a</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>social anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We will compare three active treatments: cognitive bias modification for attention (CBM-A), cognitive bias modification for interpretation (CBM-I) and a combined arm (i.e. CBM-AI). All treatments are given on one single occasion and matched for time. The tasks take approximately 20-30 minutes. All are administered on a computer.

Cognitive bias modification of interpretation trains participants to interpret ambiguous sentences in a neutral manner by giving feedback that the sentences are not associated with a word that has salience for social threat. 496 trials are presented.

Cognitive bias modification for attention involves implicitly training participants to attend to a non-threatening word by presenting word pairs (threat/neutral pairs) and consistently replacing the neutral (rather than threatening word) with a probe, Participants must identify the probe via key press as quickly as possible. There will be 640 trials.

CBM-AI: combines both and in order to match the length of the intervention, the number of trials of each of the interventions is halved. </interventions>
    <comparator>A placebo group will be included that uses the same experimental stimuli as CBM-A and CBM-I, except that in CBM-A there is no contingency between the probe and the target; and in CBM-I there is no feedback. Hence participants receive the same stimuli but without any attempt to modify the biases of attention or interpretation.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average score on Social Anxiety Response Scale to assess social anxiety.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after CBM</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average score on Social Anxiety Response Scale to assess social anxiety.</outcome>
      <timepoint>immediately following the post-social stress task. The social stress task asks participants to describe in a group for five minutes why they are a good person</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attention Bias will  be assessed using the dot-probe task (same task as for CBM-A), however, in test trials the probe will occur as often replacing the neutral as the threat word. An attentional bias is inferred when participants respond more quickly to trials where the probe replaces the threat word than the neutral word.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The test is part of the CBM protocol and therefore occurs both immediately before and after the CBM training phase. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>interpretation bias: Interpretation bias is assessed using the same task as is used to train interpretation. However, in test trials different stimuli are used and no feedback is given. An interpretation bias is inferred on the basis of how many threat-related interpretations the participant completes. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The test is part of the CBM protocol and therefore occurs both immediately before and after the CBM training phase. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Coding. The videotapes of the social interaction task will be recorded and scored by a researcher who is blind to the group allocation. They will be coded, for amount of time (in minutes) that each person spoke for; and ratings of confidence and nervousness. </outcome>
      <timepoint>During the five minute social interaction task (after training)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>We will recruit participants who score one standard deviation above the average on the Social Interaction Anxiety Scale. Participants will be first year Psychology undergraduate students at the University of Sydney. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>17</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Low levels of social anxiety</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Particpiants will be tested in groups of four. Groups of the numbers 1,2,3,4 will be developed, where the order randomly determined using randomizer.org. These numbers will then be placed in opaque envelopes on cards and the cards will be handed out to participants in the order of arrival. The card will let the participant know which computer they should sit at. Each computer will have a different variant of the task, consistent with the allocated condition, but the experimenter will not know which computer holds which task and therefore will remain blind. </concealment>
    <sequence>randomizer, org will be used to generate sequences of 1-4, as described above. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a 3 (time: pre-training; post-training and post-social stressor) 2 (CBM-A or not) x 2 (CBM-I or not) design, whereby four groups are created: CBM-A; CBM-I; CBM-AI and placebo.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We will conduct a 3 (time) x 2 (CBM-A) x 2 CBM-I ANOVAs for the primary outcome of SARS. For the secondary outcomes of interpretation and attention biases, we will conduct a 2 (time) x 2 (CBM-A) x 2 (CBM-I) ANOVAs and 2 (CBM-A) x 2(CBM-I) ANOVAs will be conducted to examine ratings generated by the coding of videotapes. On the basis of previous studies, we anticipate a moderate effect size, according to G-power to achieve 80% power with a p = 0.05, we require 30 participants per group.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/08/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2006 - The University Of Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Brennan MacCallum Building A18
The University of Sydney 
Camperdown  NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Brennan MacCallum Building A18
The University of Sydney 
Camperdown  NSW 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will examine the relative efficacy of two variants of cognitive bias modification. these are two implicit training tasks (administered by computer), which train interpretation bias and attention bias. These two variants of CBM will be compared to each and then a combined version and a placebo group will also be included. The participants will complete the relevant training prior to a five minute social interaction task where they will be asked to describe why they are a good person. This will be videotaped. We predict that CBM-A will affect the social anxiety reported during the interaction task (rated immediately after the task), whereas CBM-I will affect the anxiety levels immediately after training. Further, we predict that the combined group will have improved outcomes overall (i.e. we predict an interaction effect between CBM-A and CBM-I.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>n/a</trialwebsite>
    <publication>n/a</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Jane Foss Russell Building
The University of Sydney
Camperdown NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Louise Sharpe</name>
      <address>Brennan MacCallum Building A18
The University of Sydney 
Camperdown  NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61293514558</phone>
      <fax>+61293517328</fax>
      <email>louise.sharpe@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Louise Sharpe</name>
      <address>Brennan MacCallum Building A18
The University of Sydney 2006</address>
      <phone>+61293514558</phone>
      <fax>+61293517328</fax>
      <email>louise.sharpe@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Louise Sharpe</name>
      <address>Brennan MacCallum Building A18
The University of Sydney 2006</address>
      <phone>+61293514558</phone>
      <fax>+6193517328</fax>
      <email>louise.sharpe@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Louise Sharpe</name>
      <address>Brennan MacCallum Building A18
The University of Sydney 2006</address>
      <phone>61293514558</phone>
      <fax>61293517328</fax>
      <email>louise.sharpe@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>