<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83786">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/04/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000429257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Probiotic treatment for the prevention of antibiotic-associated diarrhea in geriatric patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Probiotics (Lactobacillus casei Shirota strain, Yakult) for the prevention of antibiotic-associated diarrhea in geriatric patients admitted to subacute units.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>diarrhea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Administration of 65mL probiotic drink containing Lactobacillus casei Shirota strain twice a day everyday during the participant's admission (average length of stay is 25days).</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo- same 65mL drink without the active probiotic strain administered twice a day everyday during their admission (average length of admission is 25 days).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diarrhea defined as three or more bowel motions of type 6 or 7 consistency as defined by the Bristol Stool Chart during a 24 hr period for 2 consecutive days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the participant's admission to the subacute ward their bowel motions will be recorded at least three times a day (once each nursing shift). The bowel chart will be audited on multiple occasions during their admission and all documented bowel motions will be reviewed.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>n/a</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All consented participants admitted to a subacute 'geriatric evaluation and management' bed at St Vincent's and St George's hospital during the trial period.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>105</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria includes participants who have had recent bowel surgery, history of an artificial heart valve or rheumatic heart disease, previous infective endocarditis, artificial feeding via a nasogastric tube, severe life threatening illness, immunosuppression or intolerance to cow milk protein and citrus intolerance.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/08/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>350</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3065</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>41 Victoria Parade 
Fitzroy 
Victoria
3065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Health, Victoria</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>41 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy 
Victoria
3065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>n/a</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>n/a</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We plan a randomised controlled double blinded trial to answer the question; does the regular use of a commercially available probiotic (Yakult) reduce the incidence and duration of diarrhea amongst geriatric inpatients (people aged =65yo)?  The study population is all patients admitted to the sub-acute wards of St Vincents Hospital and St Georges Hospital during the period of the study. Recent antibiotic use in the last 2-8 weeks can commonly cause the complication of diarrhea.  This can extend inpatient stay by 3-7 days, increase morbidity including dehydration and deconditioning due to illness, increase mortality by 2-3 times and cause hospital outbreaks of diarrhea in the general hospitalised population.  The geriatric population admitted to subacute wards are frailer and have multiple co-morbidities. They have a higher incidence of recent antibiotic use and increased risk of complications developing secondary to diarrhea.

All patients admitted to the subacute wards who meet the inclusion criteria will be invited to participate.  They will be encouraged to drink the 65ml milk product twice a day which will be randomised as to whether it contains the probiotic.  Basic demographic data will be collected from the patient chart including age, gender, medical co-morbidities, recent antibiotic use, and current medications. The patient bowel charts will be monitored to ascertain the incidence of diarrhea.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research and Grants Unit
St Vincent's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>41 Victoria Parade
Fitzroy Victoria 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/06/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC-A 048/09</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/04/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kelly Wright</name>
      <address>c/- Geriatric Department
St George's Hospital 
283 Cotham Rd
Kew 
Victoria 3101</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83451212</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8345 1449</fax>
      <email>kelly.j.wright@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kelly Wright</name>
      <address>c/-Geriatric Department
St George's Hospital
283 Cotham Rd 
Kew 
Victoria 3101</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 83451212</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kelly.j.wright@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>