<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81729">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/12/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/01/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000007437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Supermarket Healthy Options Project :  Strategies to Promote Healthier Food Purchases : A Supermarket Intervention Trial.  The Effect of tailored nutrition education and price discounts on the nutrient content of supermarket foods purchased by main household shoppers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Supermarket Healthy Options Project :  Strategies to Promote Healthier Food Purchases : A Supermarket Intervention Trial.  The Effect of tailored nutrition education and price discounts on the nutrient content of supermarket foods purchased by main household shoppers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SHOP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>HRC</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Nutrition-related disease
Healthier food purchases</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1. Price Discounts on Healthy Food: participants allocated to the price discounts group received a list of 'healthier' foods that were eligible for a 12.5% discount. The list was sent by mail monthly during the six month intervention period. Discounts were electronically loaded onto participants Shop N Go cards so that when they purchased discounted foods at participating supermarkets, the discount was automatically applied at point of sale. 2. Culturally Appropriate Tailored Nutrition Education: promoted and supported the purchase of 'healthier' food options.  Education was targeted by ethnicity and tailored by usual food purchases. Participants were sent seven nutrition education packages by mail over the six month intervention period (weeks 1, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20 and 24). Each package focused on a staple food category. 3. Price discounts plus tailored nutrition education.</interventions>
    <comparator>4.  Control (no intervention)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in percent energy from saturated fat of supermarket food purchases at completion of the six-month trial intervention phase.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months post intervention (9 months into the trial following 3 months of baseline data collection)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in saturated fat at 12 months post-randomisation</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post-randomisation (15 months at trial conclusion following 3 months of baseline data collection, 6 months of trial intervention, and 6 months of follow-up)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in other key nutrients - total fat (percentage energy), protein (percentage energy), carbohydrate (percentage energy), energy density (MJ/kg), sodium (mg/MJ), and sugars (g/MJ) at six and 12 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months post intervention (at 9 and 15 months respectively, following 3 months baseline data collection)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in quantities of healthier foods purchased (by weight) of all healthier foods, cereal and cereal products, fats and oils, fruit and vegetables, meat and alternatives, and milk and milk products, at six and 12 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months post intervention (at 9 and 15 months respectively, following 3 months baseline data collection)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) primary household food shopper, (2) shop regularly at one of the eight participating PAK n SAVE stores in the Wellington region (where a regular shopper is defined as one that shops at least once every 2 weeks and spends a minimum of $150 per month), (3) registered users of Shop n Go (self-scanning) system, or willing to sign up to the system for the period of the study, (4) able to give written informed consent to participate in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) another member of the household is already included in the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Web-based central randomisation system</concealment>
    <sequence>JAVA software used to generate the study randomisation sequence.  Minimization for ethnicity and household income using pre-set allocation probabilities</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington region</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Clinical Trials Research Unit, University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 4, School of Population Health,
Tamaki Campus
University of Auckland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Grafton Mews
Grafton
Auckland, New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Research Fellow is supported by a Heart Foundation of New Zealand postgraduate scholarship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>9 Kalmia Street
Ellerslie
Auckland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Te Hotu Manawa Maori</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>72 Dominion Road
Mt Eden
Auckland</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Pacific Heartbeat</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>c/- The Heart Foundation of New Zealand
9 Kalmia Street
Ellerslie
Auckland</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Foodstuffs Wellington Co-operative Society Ltd</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>57 Kiln Street
Silverstream, Upper Hutt
Wellington</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Unhealthy diet plays a role in 11,000 deaths every year in New Zealand and healthier diets are important in preventing common diseases including heart disease, stroke, cancer, and diabetes. Most of our food is bought at supermarkets so choosing healthier foods at supermarkets is likely to have important health benefits. The Supermarket Healthy Options Project (SHOP) assessed two ways of promoting healthier food purchases in supermarkets: price discounts and tailored nutrition education. 1,104 PAK n SAVE customers were randomised to one of four groups: (1) price discounts on specified 'healthier' food products, (2) culturally appropriate tailored nutrition education based on usual supermarket food purchases, (3) both price discounts and tailored education, and (4) control (no intervention). Effects on shopping habits were measured using individulised barcode scanner data. This research provides important information about two promising ways to improve our populations diet.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>KRUSE, K., BLAKELY, T., EYLES, H.C.  'Lessons learned from co-ordinating a group health education workshop for Pacific people', Health Promotion Journal of Australia, 19, (3), p232-232, 2008

EYLES, H.C., NI MHURCHU, C., WHAREMATE, L., FUNAKI, M. and 2 others 'Developing Nutrition Education Resources for a Multi-ethnic Population in New Zealand', Health Education Research, 2009, 24 (4), p558-574, doi: 10.1093/her/cyn057  

NI MHURCHU, C., BLAKELY, T., FUNAKI-TAHIFOTE, M., MCKERCHAR, C. and 3 others. Inclusion of indigenous and ethnic minority populations in intervention trials:  challenges and strategies in a New Zealand supermarket study.  Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health, 2009, doi:10.1136/jech.2008.081109   

EYLES, H.C., JIANG, Y., NI MHURCHU, C.  'Use of household supermarket sales data to estimate nutrient intakes: a comparison with repeat 24-hour dietary recalls', Journal of the American Dietetic Association, In press, 2009  

EYLES, H.C., NI MHURCHU, C. 'Does tailoring matter? A systematic review of the long-term effectiveness of tailored nutrition education for adults, including priority population groups', Review in Nutrition Reviews, 67 (8), p464-480, 2009 doi:10.1111/j.1753-4887.2009.00219.x  

EYLES, H.C., NI MHURCHU, C., RODGERS, A.  'Using electronic sales data to tailor nutrition education resources for an ethnically diverse population of supermarket shoppers: Developing the methodology'., Journal of Human Nutrition and Dietetics, In press, 2009

NI MHURCHU, C., BLAKELY, T., JIANG, Y., EYLES, H.C., and 3 others 'Effects of price discounts and tailored nutrition education on supermarket food purchases:  A randomised, controlled trial (Submitted)</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Wellington-University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/12/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2006/4602</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Cliona Ni Mhurchu</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Research Unit University of Auckland Private Bag 92019 Auckland
and
MRC Human Nutrition Research
Cambridge
United Kindom</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 ext 84494</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 373 1710</fax>
      <email>c.nimhurchu@ctru.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Cliona Ni Mhurchu</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Research Unit
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 48650</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 373 1710</fax>
      <email>s.chua@ctru.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Helen Eyles</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Research Unit University of Auckland Private Bag 92019 Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 ext 84658</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>regtrials@ctru.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>