<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371636">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001455459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Open-label Extension Study of ZYN002 (transdermal gel) in Patients with Partial Onset Seizures</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Open Label Extension Study to ZYN2-CL-03 to Assess the Long Term Safety and Efficacy of ZYN002 Administered as a Transdermal Gel to Patients with Partial Onset Seizures (STAR 2)
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>STAR2</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Zynerba  ZYN2-CL-004
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Epilepsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epilepsy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>ZYN002 will be administered as a transdermal gel for 12 months with all patients starting at ZYN002 - CBD 195 mg every 12 hours (390 mg daily), with the option to reduce to ZYN002 - CBD 97.5 mg every 12 hours (195 mg daily) as determined by the investigator.
After the Month 12 visit, or the last visit if the patient terminates early from the study, patients will have a two-week taper period.  Patients will have their dose reduced by 50% at week 53 and another 50% at week 54 and then treatment will be discontinued.
ZYN002 gel will be applied to the skin of both the right and left shoulder and/or upper arms.
Participants will bring used and unused sachets to each visit for site to check treatment compliance.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the long term safety and tolerability of ZYN002 in partial onset (focal) seizures in adult epilepsy patients over a 12-month treatment period. 
Assessed by: physical exams, neurological exams, examination of skin, vital signs, ECGs, clinical laboratory
tests e.g. haematology, chemistry, urinalysis, pregnancy test (when applicable), assessing suicide risk and adverse event (AE) monitoring.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety and tolerability will be assessed at every study visit from Day 1 to End of study visit (Week 2 and Months 1, 2, 3, 6, 9 and 12 and End of Study)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the long term efficacy of ZYN002 in partial onset (focal) seizures in adult epilepsy patients over a 12-month treatment period.
Assessed by: monitoring seizure frequency and type in daily diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Investigator will review daily diary at each study visit (Week 2 and Months 1, 2, 3, 6, 9 and 12)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Must have completed 12 weeks of the ZYN2-CL-03 protocol, with greater than 95% compliance with study drug application and daily seizure and skin check diaries. 
2.	Patient agrees to abide by all study restrictions and comply with all study procedures.
3.	Patient must be adequately informed of the nature and risks of the study and give written informed consent on Day 1.
4.	In the Investigators opinion, the patient is reliable and is willing and able to comply with all protocol requirements and procedures.
5.	Females of child-bearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test at Day 1 and at Months 1, 2, 3, 6, 9 and 12 and End of Study.  Females of child-bearing potential and male patients with a partner of child-bearing potential must continue to use an acceptable method of contraception until at least 3 months after the last dose of study drug.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Patient is receiving any investigational drugs or using any experimental devices.
2.	Patient has an ongoing serious adverse event (SAE) or has experienced a SAE in ZYN3-CL-03 that in the opinion of the investigator should exclude them from participation.
3.	Patient has been less than 95% compliant with study medication in ZYN2-CL-03.
4.	Patient demonstrates behavior indicating unreliability or inability to comply with the requirements of the protocol. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable as this is not a randomized trial</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The safety and efficacy variables will be summarized descriptively for all patients in the open label extension study and also by the following dosing cohorts listed below which are based on the randomized treatment (total daily dose) received in the double-blind study (Placebo, ZYN002-195 mg, ZYN002-390 mg) and the initial treatment received (total daily dose) in the open-label extension study (ZYN002-390 mg). The dosing cohorts will be identified as: Placebo/390 mg, 195 mg/390 mg and 390 mg/390 mg, where the treatments are a double blind (DB) treatment dose (total daily dose)/initial open label treatment dose (total daily dose).

The pharmacokinetic variables for anti-epileptic drugs (AEDs) and CBD will be summarized descriptively for all patients in the open label extension study.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>4/07/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>171</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/07/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Private Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>University of Sunshine Coast Health Clinics - Sippy Downs</hospital>
    <postcode>3050 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
    <postcode>4556 - Sippy Downs</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland, Wellington, Waikato and Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Zynerba Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>At the office of PriceWaterhouseCoopers, 2 Riverside Quay, Southbank VIC, 3006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Zynerba Pharmaceuticals Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>80 West Lancaster Avenue
Suite 300
Devon, PA 19333</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Novotech (Australia) Pty Limited</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 3, 235 Pyrmont St
Pyrmont NSW 2009</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is an open-label extension study to Protocol ZYN2-CL-03 (STAR1). The study aims to evaluate the long term effectiveness, safety, tolerability and blood levels of twice daily ZYN002 in addition to regular seizure medication for 12 months in up to 180 adults with partial onset seizures (POS) who have participated in study ZYN2-CL-03. This will be done by analysing a daily seizure and skin irritation diary, drug levels in the blood at various
times following drug administration, and side effects. Skin at the application sites will be checked to see if there is any irritation or reactions present after applications.

Who is if for? You may be eligible to join this study if have completed the 12 weeks of study treatment on protocol ZYN2-CL-03. 

Study details: All participants will administer ZYN002 transdermal gel twice daily for 12 months. 

What does study participation involve? Eligible patients can immediately transition after completing day 84 (at Week 12) of the double-blind study, ZYN2-CL-03, to the open label study, ZYN2-CL-004.. All participants in this extension study will receive active ZYN002. This could be the first time a participant receives ZYN002, depending on which treatment they received in the previous study (ZYN2-CL-03).
After pre-dosing procedures are completed, patients will start study medication (Day 1). The first dose of study drug will be applied by the patient at this visit. Patients will be required to visit the clinic at Week 2 and Months 1, 2, 3, 6, 9 and 12 and End of Study to have study procedures completed.
Participants will continue to record their seizure frequency and type in their daily diary.
At the clinic visits the following procedures will occur:  blood sampling; review of daily diary, medications, adverse events and skin irritation; measurement of blood pressure, heart rate, breathing rate and temperature ; suicide risk; and possibly, a brief physical and neurological exam, pregnancy tests (females only, if applicable) and an ECG. Participants withhold their morning application until after blood sample collection at these visits. Additional out-patient visits may be required if there is skin irritation present at the application site.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Level 6 East
300 Grattan Street
Parkville 3050 Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Terence O’Brien</name>
      <address>The Royal Melbourne Hospital
300 Grattan Street
Parkville 3050 Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 5490</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 1863</fax>
      <email>obrientj@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Carol O'Neill</name>
      <address>Zynerba Pharmaceuticals, Inc.
80 West Lancaster Avenue
Devon, PA 19333</address>
      <phone>+1 484 581 7481</phone>
      <fax>-</fax>
      <email>oneillc@zynerba.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Donna Gutterman</name>
      <address>Zynerba Pharmaceuticals, Inc.
80 West Lancaster Avenue
Devon, PA 19333</address>
      <phone>+1 484 581 7481</phone>
      <fax>-</fax>
      <email>guttermand@zynerba.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kim Wong</name>
      <address>Novotech (Australia) Pty Limited
Level 3, 235 Pyrmont St
Pyrmont NSW 2009</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8569 1400</phone>
      <fax>+61 85691498</fax>
      <email>rog@novotech-cro.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>