<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368537">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000990527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The community-based physical activity study for adults with type 2 diabetes, at high risk of Type 2 diabetes or overweight /obese.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Integrating Smartphone Technology, Social Support and the Outdoor Physical Environment to Promote Physical Activity among Adults diagnosed with Type 2 Diabetes, at High Risk of Type 2 Diabetes or Overweight /Obese: The Pilot Randomised Controlled Trial of the eCoFit.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes


</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>High risk of Type 2 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical inactivity </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this pilot randomized controlled trial is to develop, implement and evaluate a community-based physical activity intervention to improve aerobic and muscular fitness among adults diagnosed with Type 2 Diabetes, at high risk of Type 2 Diabetes or overweight /obese.

The 20-week multi-component intervention integrates the outdoor physical environment and smartphone application (App) technology. The intervention components include:

1) Five 90 minute group sessions which includes a 60 minute group outdoor training session with a qualified personal trainer and a 30 minute cognitive mentoring session with a clinical psychologist. Weeks 1 - 10; 1 session every 2 weeks.
a) Group outdoor training sessions with a qualified personal trainer: Participants will be educated on and participate in sessions using the outdoor physical environment (e.g. parks, benches) to increase aerobic and resistance training physical activity. The sessions involve 50% of aerobic training and 50% of resistance training [moderate-to-vigorous intensity (equal to or greater than 3 METs)].
b) Cognitive group mentoring sessions with a clinical psychologist: Participants will be educated on strategies to overcome barriers, increase their motivation for and adherence to physical activity.

Adherence to sessions will be monitored using a log of session attendance for each session.

2) "eCoFit Smartphone App". Weeks 1 to 20. The App, which will be specifically tailored to the study location, will include:
a) A description of where and how to use the outdoor physical environment to be more physically active. It includes pictures and instructions regarding how to use the outdoor physical environment (e.g., park benches) to perform various aerobic and resistance training exercises;
b) A standardized eCoFit Challenge in locations in the Newcastle Region, which involves a combination of 3km of aerobic activity and 2 sets of 6 resistance training activities. Participants will be able to see a map of the course indicating what activities are performed where and how to perform the exercises correctly on the course. It also has the option to select the level of difficulty (6 levels). The App will track the time it took participants to complete the eCoFit Challenge course and provides participants with a results table and progress chart;
c) Indoor Challenges which are resistance and aerobic training sessions that participants can complete at home with no equipment to provide an option for inclement weather (i.e., rain or heat).
d) A function to set weekly physical activity goals and self-monitor their progress;
e) FitMind Challenges which involve short tasks to increase motivation, overcome barriers and develop positive physical activity behaviours; and
f) Links to social media.

Participants will have unlimited access to all of App`s features. It is recommended that participants do at least 3 "eCoFit Challenges" per week.

The primary and secondary timepoint of the study is 10-weeks and 20-weeks respectively.</interventions>
    <comparator>Wait-list control. Participants in the control group will receive standard treatment (i.e. follow their T2D management procedures as specified by their GP) during the intervention period and will receive the intervention after the 20-week follow-up assessments. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Aerobic fitness: assessed using the single stage submaximal treadmill walking test (Ebbeling et al., 1991).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lower body muscular strength: assessed using the chair stand test (Rikli &amp; Jones, 2013).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity: objectively measured physical activity will be assessed using pedometers (7 consecutive days wear time) and self-reported aerobic and resistance training physical activity will be assessed using specific items from the Godin Leisure-Time Exercise Questionnaire (Godin &amp; Shephard, 1985).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Upper body muscular strength: assessed using the arm curl test (Rikli &amp; Jones, 2013).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional mobility: assessed using the Timed Up and Go test (Podsiadlo &amp; Richardson, 1991).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index: weight and height will be measured using a portable digital scale and stadiometer. Body mass index will be determined using the standard method (weight [kg] / height [m]2).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference: measured using a non-extensible steel tape.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure: measured using a standard sphygmomanometer with brachial cuff.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stages of behavior change, using a validated algorithm assessing stages of the Transtheoretical Model (TTM) to determine the Health Action Process Approach Model (HAPA) stages</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intention, assessed using a validated  measure the Health Action Process Approach Model (HAPA; Schwarzer, 2007)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Implementation intention assessed using a validated  measure of the Social Cognitive Theory (SCT; Bandura 1997)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy a validated measure of the SCT (Bandura, 1997), Theory of Planned Behaviour (Ajzen, 1991), TTM (Prochaska, 1992);</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motivational Self-Efficacy assessed using a validated measure of the HAPA (Schwarzer, 2007)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recovery Self-Efficacy assessed using a validated measure of the HAPA (Schwarzer, 2007)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Outcome expectancies assessed using a validated measure of the SCT (Bandura, 1997) and HAPA (Schwarzer, 2007)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Risk Perception assessed using a validated measure of the PMT (Rogers, 1983) and HAPA (Schwarzer, 2007)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived Environment assessed using Perceived Environment 7 item scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health survey, measured using SF-12 (RAND-12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health outcome, measured using EQ-5D</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Support assessed using Social Support 2 item scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived insufficient sleep assessed using item from the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System (BRFSS) survey. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sedentary behavior, assessed using 1 item from the 45 and UP Study Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nature relatedness measured by validated short-form version of the nature relatedness scale (NR-6)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The rate of Depression using the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The rate of Anxiety, using the Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-item (GAD-7)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Implicit attitude toward physical activity, using modified version of the Implicit Association Test (IAT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible participants will be18 to 75 years of age; diagnosed with Type 2 Diabetes (HbA1c greater than 7.0) or at high risk of Type 2 Diabetes (equal to or greater than 12 points on the AUSDRISK (Australian Government, 2010)) or overweight or obese (BMI equal to or greater than 25 and less than 40 kg/m2); not currently meeting the Australian physical activity guidelines as assessed by the Godin Leisure-Time Exercise Questionnaire (Godin &amp; Shephard, 1985); passed the Adult Pre-exercise Screening System (Exercise and Sports Science Australia, 2011 or permission from GP); and own a smartphone.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if they have a medical condition that might be adversely affected by increasing their physical activity as determined by the Adult Pre-exercise Screening System (Exercise and Sports Science Australia, 2011) or their GP; currently participating in an alternative physical activity program; intending to participate in other physical activity programs during the study period; or not available for assessment sessions</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/06/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/06/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>7/07/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>10/07/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>84</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>20/12/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hunter Medical Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1 Kookaburra Circuit
New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hunter Medical Research Institute </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 Kookaburra Circuit
New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Newcastle</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this randomised controlled trial is to develop, implement and evaluate a community-based intervention to promote physical activity among adults diagnosed with Type 2 Diabetes, at high risk of Type 2 Diabetes or overweight /obese. The 20-week intervention will include five sessions with a qualified personal trainer and a smartphone App. Aerobic fitness, muscular strength, physical activity, functional mobility, BMI, waist circumference, blood pressure, and cognitive variables will be assessed. Assessment will be conducted at baseline, 10-weeks and 20-weeks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Wilczynska M, Lubans DR, Cohen KE, Smith JJ, Robards SL, Plotnikoff RC. Rationale and study protocol for the eCoFit randomized controlled trial: Integrating smartphone technology, social support and the outdoor physical environment to improve health-related fitness among adults at risk of, or diagnosed with, Type 2 Diabetes. . Contemp Clin Trials. 2016;49:116-125.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Newcastle Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Newcastle
Callaghan NSW 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/05/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ronald Plotnikoff</name>
      <address>Priority Research Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition
University of Newcastle
University Drive Callaghan NSW 2308
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 4465</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ron.plotnikoff@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ronald Plotnikoff</name>
      <address>Priority Research Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition
University of Newcastle
University Drive Callaghan NSW 2308
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 4465</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ron.plotnikoff@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ronald Plotnikoff</name>
      <address>Priority Research Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition
University of Newcastle
University Drive Callaghan NSW 2308
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 4465</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ron.plotnikoff@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ronald Plotnikoff</name>
      <address>Priority Research Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition
University of Newcastle
University Drive Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 4465</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ron.plotnikoff@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>