<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372754">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000566336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Frusemide and Diamox Evaluation in ICU (FADE ICU) Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot comparative evaluation of the haemodynamic and electrolyte effects of Frusemide and Acetazolamide in critically ill patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The FADE ICU Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Kidney disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A single 500 milligram (mg) intravenous dose of Acetazolamide will be administered by an intensive care nurse following the prescription by the patient's treating intensive care doctor</interventions>
    <comparator>A single 40 milligram (mg) intravenous dose of Frusemide will be administered by an intensive care nurse following the prescription by the patient's treating intensive care doctor</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urine volume</outcome>
      <timepoint>Volume of urine documented in the six hour period from the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Systolic blood pressure change as assessed by intra-arterial blood pressure monitoring.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Systolic blood pressure recorded every 5 minutes for the six hour period from the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate change as assessed via continous electrocardiographic monitoring </outcome>
      <timepoint>Heart rate recorded every 5 minutes for the six hour period from the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum sodium (Na+) as measured via blood sample analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in serum sodium levels from immediately prior to the diuretic being administered compared with at six hours following the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in urinary sodium (Na+) as measured via urine sample analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in urinary sodium levels from immediately prior to the diuretic being administered compared with at six hours following the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Central venous pressure change as assessed via invasive central venous catheter monitoring.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hourly for the first 6 hours after the administration of the diuretic as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean arterial blood pressure as assessed by intra-arterial blood pressure monitoring.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Mean arterial blood pressure recorded every 5 minutes for the six hour period from the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum creatinine </outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in serum creatinine levels from immediately prior to the diuretic being administered compared with at six hours following the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urinary creatinine clearance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in urinary creatinine levels from immediately prior to the diuretic being administered compared with at six hours following the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum potassium (K+) as measured via blood sample analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in serum potassium levels from immediately prior to the diuretic being administered compared with at six hours following the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum calcium (Ca++) as measured via blood sample analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in serum calcium levels from immediately prior to the diuretic being administered compared with at six hours following the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum magnesium (Mg+) as measured via blood sample analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in serum magnesium levels from immediately prior to the diuretic being administered compared with at six hours following the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in urinary potassium (K+) as measured via urine sample analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in urinary potassium levels from immediately prior to the diuretic being administered compared with at six hours following the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in urinary calcium (Ca++) as measured via urine sample analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in urinary calcium levels from immediately prior to the diuretic being administered compared with at six hours following the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in urinary magnesium (Mg+) as measured  via urine sample analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in urinary magnesium levels from immediately prior to the diuretic being administered compared with at six hours following the diuretic being administered as recorded in the patient's medical record.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urinary oxygenation value</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in urinary oxygenation value from the time of the insertion of the urinary oximetry probe and immediately prior to and six hours post diuretic administration as well as until it's removal in association with the routine insertion and use of a urinary catheter in critically ill patients admitted to the intensive care unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Admission to the Austin Hospital ICU 
Age 18 years or greater
An attending physicians decision to administer a diuretic
An anticipated ICU length of stay of &gt;24 hours after frusemide administration 
Patients with existing intra-arterial cannulae or central venous catheters for blood sampling, and indwelling urinary catheters. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with known allergy to frusemide or acetazolamide or other sulphonamides.
Known existing end stage renal failure
Long-standing use of diuretic therapy
Dose of different diuretic in the preceding 12 hours.
Significant pre-existing acid-base disturbance at time of enrolment (pH &lt; 7.30 or &gt; 7.50)
Patient receiving continuous renal-replacement therapy
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Variables will be assessed for normality and log-transformed if appropriate.  Baseline comparisons will be performed using Fishers exact tests and reported as n (%). Continuous normally distributed variables will be compared using Student t-tests and reported as means (standard deviation), while non-normally distributed data will be compared using Wilcoxon rank-sum tests and reported as medians [interquartile range].
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/08/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
Victoria 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Austin Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Rinaldo Bellomo</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg VIC 3084</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The use of diuretics in critically ill patients is widespread. Indications include the management of volume overload, maintenance of acid-base balance and potassium homeostasis. Commonly used diuretics include frusemide and acetazolamide. Despite the common use of these drugs there is no high quality evidence available comparing the effect of these drugs on the haemodynamic status and metabolic status of critically ill patients. 

We aim to evaluate the comparative effect of a standard dose of intravenous frusemide vs a standard dose of acetazolamide in critically ill patients. We plan to enrol a total of twenty-four patients in whom a decision has been made to administer a diuretic.  These twenty-four patients will then be randomly assigned to receive a single dose of either frusemide of acetazolamide.  To understand the effect of the diuretic administration, we will retrieve routinely recorded patient demographic data, haemodynamic data (such as blood pressure, heart rate, central venous pressure and cardiac output), data from the arterial blood gas samples (serum creatinine, sodium and potassium) as well as urine from the patients existing indwelling urinary catheter.

The results of this study will provide insight into the effects of these two diuretics on electrolyte imbalances and the haemodynamic status of critically ill patients.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>145 Studley Road
Heidelberg 
Victoria 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/03/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/17/Austin/75</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372754-20170302 HREC17Austin75 Mar 17 (FULL ETHICS APPROVAL).pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372754-20170630 HREC17austin75 July 17 (Ethics PA and PICF's).pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rinaldo Bellomo</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
Victoria 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5992</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>rinaldo.bellomo@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Glenn Eastwood</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
Victoria 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 4835</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>glenn.eastwood@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rinaldo Bellomo</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
Victoria 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 4835</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 3932</fax>
      <email>rinaldo.bellomo@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Glenn Eastwood</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
Victoria 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 4835</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 5992</fax>
      <email>glenn.eastwood@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>