<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365684">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000112662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Helping Older Patients with End-stage kidney disease: survival, symptom control and quality of life without dialysis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Experiences of Palliative Nephrology and Pre-Dialysis Clinics (EXPAND): survival, symptom control and quality of life of patients not planned for dialysis who are receiving renal supportive care.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>EXPAND: HOPE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>End stage kidney disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We sought to learn prospectively the likely survival of patients not planned for dialysis and whether or not they could be provided with reasonable quality of life and control of their symptoms.
This prospective observational study was over 4 years.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator being studied are the outcomes of patients attending the Renal Supportive Care (RSC) clinic.
These outcomes will be compared to the patients attending standard renal clinics (Pre-Dialysis clinic).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Survival - time to death, or renal replacement therapy 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored over the 4 year study period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maintenance or improvement of symptoms. Symptoms were assessed using the Memorial Symptom Assessment Scale (MSAS-SF), a validated tool for assessing patients symptoms, as well as by using the POS-S (renal) survey for those patient in the Renal Supportive Care non-dialysis group. Symptoms were assessed as both the number of symptoms and the total symptom score.
Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) was repeated each 6 months along with repeat assessment of symptom burden by the MSAS-SF survey tool.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored over the 4 year study period and recorded at 6 monthly intervals for each patient.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maintenance or improvement of quality of life.
Quality of life was assessed using the Short Form-36 (SF-36). Estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) was repeated each 6 months along with repeat assessment of quality of life by the SF-36 survey tool.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored over the 4 year study period and recorded at 6 monthly intervals for each patient.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcomes included hospitalisations. This involves data linkage to patient medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored over the 4 year study period for each patient</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria were patients referred to either pre-dialysis clinic or the Renal Supportive Care clinic over 18 years with ability to provide informed consent. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Excluded were those patients planned for pre-emptive transplantation and patients who moved out of the area.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The number of participants needed to achieve the study objectives was based on patients attending the clinics within the 4 year study period. All patients, who consented, were included if they satisfied the inclusion criteria during this period.
Comparison of continuous variables between groups was done using Student's t-tests or Mann-Whitney tests as appropriate. Comparison of categorical variables between groups was done using Chi-square testing. Survival was estimated by the Kaplan-Meier technique from the initial visit to the relevant clinic and from the time eGFR fell below 15ml/min. Factors influencing survival were determined by multivariable logistic regression analysis. Factors tested in the univariable analysis included age, weight, eGFR at initial visit, BMI, Haemoglobin, serum albumin, Calcium, Phosphate, PTH, gender, diabetes, dementia, co-morbidities, smoking and nutritional status. All factors significant on univariable analysis were tested by step-wise multivariable analysis. Change in symptoms or QOL over time were categorized into "stable", "improved" or "worse". Chi-square testing was used to compare the change in symptoms and QOL between groups. Analysis was by intention to treat and level of significance was 0.05. Analyses were undertaken using SAS statistical software version 9.2.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/03/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/03/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2009</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>27/03/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>480</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St George Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Renal Department
50 Montgomery St
Kogarah
NSW 2217</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Amgen Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 7
123 Epping Rd
North Ryde
NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Amgen Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 7
123 Epping Rd
North Ryde
NSW 2113</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A combined palliative and nephrology, Renal Supportive Care clinic was established in March 2009. This research aims to describe the impact of a specialised palliative nephrology service on outcomes and will put this in context by also describing outcomes of patients who are managed in standard renal clinics (pre-dialysis clinic).
The data collected is collected as part of standard medical care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Presentation title: Non-dialysis management in the elderly: survival, symptom control and quality of life
Presenter: Professor Mark Brown
Conference: American Society of Nephrology (ASN), Kidney Week 2013, November 2013</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>The number of participants needed to achieve the study objectives was determined by how many patients attended the clinics during the 4 year study period. 
There were no statistical assumptions or any sample size calculations prior to commencing the study, therefore the number was determined by the number of clinic patients.

The data collection period commenced 3/3/2009, which was when the Renal Supportive Care clinic commenced. The decision to monitor and assess the outcomes of the clinic and compare them to the standard renal clinics was made in September 2010. The study was approved and the study was initially a retrospective observational study, then became a prospective study to capture patients attending the clinics until the conclusion of the study period in March 2013.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District- Northern Sector (SESLHD-NS) Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Office 
South Eastern Sydney Local Health District 
Prince of Wales Hospital
G71 East Wing, Edmund Blacket Building
Cnr High &amp; Avoca Streets
Randwick
NSW 2031

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/STG/121</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/09/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Brown</name>
      <address>Renal Department
St George Hospital
50 Montgomery St
Kogarah
NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+610291132622</phone>
      <fax>+610295538192</fax>
      <email>mbrown@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Brown</name>
      <address>Renal Department
St George Hospital
50 Montgomery St
Kogarah
NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+610291132622</phone>
      <fax>+610295538192</fax>
      <email>mbrown@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Gemma Collett</name>
      <address>Renal Department
St George Hospital
50 Montgomery St
Kogarah
NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+610291132854</phone>
      <fax>+610291132684</fax>
      <email>gemma.collett@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Gemma Collett</name>
      <address>Renal Department
St George Hospital
50 Montgomery St
Kogarah
NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+610291132854</phone>
      <fax>+610291132684</fax>
      <email>gemma.collett@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>