<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335011">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/12/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000022965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The use of Near-Infrared Spectroscopy to assist in the diagnosis of Compartment Syndrome in paediatrics</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The use of Near-Infrared Spectroscopy to assist in the diagnosis of Compartment Syndrome in paediatrics</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1113-2639</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>compartment syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>complications of fractures</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Observation of tissue oxygenation levels using near infrared spectroscopy.
Near infrared spectroscopy is a completely non-invasive optical method that utilizes near infrared light to ascertain the average oxygen saturation of haemoglobin in a region of tissue. The method is closely related to standard plethysmographic oxygen saturation measurement(SpO2), and is currently used in cardiac surgery to measure brain tissue oxygenation during cardiopulmonary bypass, and in intensive care. It is also used in sports science to study real-time muscle oxygen kinetics, and is being investigated in a variety of areas.
Group 1 involves patients presenting with grade 3 supracondylar fractures. NIRS monitoring of the injured and uninjured sides is commenced at the end of surgery for up to 48 hours or discharge, in addition to standard post operative monitoring(pain scores, range of motion, swelling). 
Group 2 involves patients presenting with suspected compartment syndrome. In these patients a single discrete 2 minute NIRS measurement is made immediately prior to surgery, co-temporaneously with invasive compartment pressure measurement. At surgical fasciotomy, the muscle is assessed for signs of compartment syndrome(swelling, colour, response to stimulation)
The current planned duration is 1 year, with group 1 recruitment of 30 and group 2 recruitment of 10.</interventions>
    <comparator>clinical indicators of compartment sydnrome
compartment pressures. A standard assessment includes pain scores, range of motion, pain during active and passive movement, and manual assessment of muscle compartment swelling. Both NIRs and clinical indicators are used on all patients.
As mentioned above there are 2 groups, one with supracondylar fractures and the other with suspected compartment syndrome.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tissue oxygenation level</outcome>
      <timepoint>From time of operative fixation until hospital discharge in group 1, measured continuously at a 2 second sampling rate, for up to 48 hours or discharge.

At time of surgical intervention for fasciotomy for group 2, as a discrete measurement taken over 2 minutes at a 2 second sampling rate.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>number of group 1 patients developing compartment syndrome. Clinical assessment, described before, is used to detect the development of compartment sydnrome. If suspected, muscle compartment pressures are measured usign an invasive device(Stryker pressure monitor), and fasciotomy is performed, at which time the muscle is directly inspected for colour, swelling and response to stimulation, allowing a definitive diagnosis of compartment syndrome to be made.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuous clinical observation for up to 48 hours post fixation or dischaege from hospital.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Grade 3 supracondylar fracture for group 1
Clinically suspected compartment syndrome for group 2</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>volar forearm skin damage preventing probe attachment
Jaundice</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/02/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/11/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>29</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/11/2011</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Children's Hospital at Westmead</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hawkesbury Road
Westmead
2145
NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Children's Hospital at Westmead Volunteer fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hawkesbury road
Westmead
2145
NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Compartment syndrome occurs when swelling in a muscle interferes with the blood supply to that muscle. The syndrome happens most often in fractures, and after bone operations, and can lead to damage to the muscle and nerves of the limb affected. We are interested in using a new technology that is designed to look at the blood oxygen levels in tissue (in this case muscle). The technology uses probes attached to a machine. The probes are placed on the skin, and shine light into the muscle. The light is not damaging to the tissue. We would like to know more about the oxygen levels of muscles in compartment syndrome in children.
All children 0 to 18 years of age can participate. They cannot participate if they have jaundice, or broken skin where the probes may be placed. 
For those presenting with suspected compartment syndrome, when the child comes to theatre, once they are asleep, we will place a probe on the skin over the muscle. We will do this on the affected and the unaffected side. We will also do a standard compartment pressure measurement simultaneously. The probe will be left on for 2 minutes in theatre, and then removed. 
For those presenting with a supracondylar fracture, the probes will be placed on the injured, and uninjured sides and left on for 48 hours or until hospital discharge. 

The monitor has not yet been shown to help in this problem, and we will not use the values to alter treatment in any way. We hope that the results of this study will help us to detect compartment syndrome early on, and allow quicker treatment, in those children who develop it.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Children's Hospital at Westmead HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hawkesbury road
Westmead
2145
NSW</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/02/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/CHW/117</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Justin Skowno</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatric Anaesthesia
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Hawkesbury Road
Westmead
2145</address>
      <phone>+61298450000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>justins@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Justin Skowno</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatric Anaesthesia
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Hawkesbury Road
Westmead
2145
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61298450000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>justins@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Justin Skowno</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatric Anaesthesia
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Hawkesbury Road
Westmead
2145</address>
      <phone>+61298450000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>justins@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Justin Skowno</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, The Children's Hospital at Westmead, Hawkesbury Road, Westmead, 2145, New South Wales, Australia.</address>
      <phone>+61298450000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>justin.skowno@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>