<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373705">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001401347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Probiotics for newborn babies with surgical conditions of the gut</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Probiotic supplementation in neonates with major gastrointestinal surgical conditions: A Pilot Randomized Double Blind Placebo Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PRINS Trial (Probiotics In Neonatal Surgery)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Major congenital gastrointestinal anomalies</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: Mixture of 3 strains (B. breve M-16V, B. longum subsp. infantis M-63 and B. longum subsp. longum BB536 (1×109 Colony Forming Units of each strain per 1 g sachet: Probiotic group). 
Supplementation protocol: As soon as possible after admission, enrolled neonates will be supplemented with freshly reconstituted contents of the allocated sachets every day, and continued until discharge. 
Reconstitution of the dry powder in the sachets will be done using sterile water for injection or breast milk. Care will be taken during reconstitution to reduce the risk of cross contamination by adhering to strict hand hygiene. The dose will be 3×109 CFU/day ( i.e. 3 billion organisms per day) in 1.5 ml of the reconstituted solution, given as a single daily dose via the orogastric/nasogastric feeding tube or orally. Supplementation will be continued until discharge from the neonatal unit. The principal investigator will monitor the medication charts of study infants to ensure adherence to the intervention.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo: Dextrin. The contents of the sachet will be diluted in 1.5 ml of the reconstituted solution and given as a single daily dose via the orogastric/nasogastric feeding tube or orally. Supplementation will be continued until discharge from the neonatal unit.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcomes: Gut microbiota (using 16 s r RNA Pyrosequencing studies for phylogenic profiling) on the stool samples </outcome>
      <timepoint>a. as soon as possible after admission, b) Between D12-14 of life, and c) Between D19-21, if the infant is still in the neonatal unit. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stool Short Chain Fatty Acids (SCFA) assay using gas chromatography</outcome>
      <timepoint>stool samples for SCFA are collected a. as soon as possible after admission, b) Between D12-14 of life, and c) Between D19-21, if the infant is still in the neonatal unit.  
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood culture positive sepsis</outcome>
      <timepoint>During initial hospitalisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of antibiotic therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>During initial hospitalisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of hospital stay (days)</outcome>
      <timepoint>During initial hospitalisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time (days) to achieve full enteral feeds of 120 ml/kg/day. </outcome>
      <timepoint>During initial hospitalisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) Neonates (&gt;=35 weeks gestation) with the following major congenital gastrointestinal anomalies: Intestinal Atresia (duodenal, jejunal, ileal or colonic), Intestinal Malrotation,  Tracheo-Oesophageal fistula, Oesphageal atresia, Gastroschisis, Exompholos, Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia, Meconium ileus or peritonitis requiring laparotomy, Hirschsprung Disease, Anal atresia, Impeforate anus, Short Bowel Syndrome, and any surgical condition needing the creation of small or large intestinal stoma (eg severe meconium ileus, micro-colon).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Days</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>4</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) Non gastrointestinal surgical conditions. (2) Neonates born at &lt;35 weeks' gestation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment will be optimized by using pharmacy controlled allocation. </concealment>
    <sequence>Group assignment will be allocated by a computer generated randomization sequence in randomly ordered block sizes of 2 and 4. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Continuous variables will be compared using the t test for normally distributed data and Wilcoxon rank sum test for skewed data. Categorical variables will be compared using the fishers exact test. Logistic regression analysis will be used for analysis of binary outcomes (primary outcome of interest) to derive Relative Risk and 95% confidence intervals. Linear regression analysis will be used for continuous outcomes to derive regression coefficients and respective confidence intervals. A p value of &lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/01/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <hospital>Perth Children's Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco East</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Broadway Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1 Roberts Road, Subiaco, Western Australia, 6008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Centre for Neonatal Research and Education, University of Western Australia </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>374 Bagot Road, King Edward Memorial Hospital for Women, Subiaco, Western Australia, 6008</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Perth Children's Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Hospital Avenue, Nedlands, WA, 6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Newborn babies with serious surgical conditions of the gut are admitted to intensive care units, undergo surgery, and receive intravenous drips and strong antibiotics. The administration of breast milk is often delayed in these infants. All these factors interfere with the normal development of healthy bacteria in their intestines and enhance the proliferation of harmful bacteria. Such an imbalance between healthy and unhealthy bacteria in the gut can be harmful to the health and well-being of these babies. In this study, we plan to give healthy bacteria called probiotics orally for 30 surgical newborn babies and placebo for 30 surgical newborn babies to see if probiotics help improve their intestinal bacteria and overall health. The results of this study will help us design a much larger study in the future. If that larger study confirms the benefits, probiotics will then be used routinely for all newborn babies with surgical conditions of the gut.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Child and Adolescent Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children, Subiaco, Western Australia, 6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016086EP</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Shripada Rao</name>
      <address>Neonatal Intensive Care Unit, Princess Margaret Hospital for Children, Roberts Road, Subiaco, WA, 6008, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61893408672</phone>
      <fax>+61893407852</fax>
      <email>shripada.rao@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Shripada Rao</name>
      <address>Neonatal Intensive Care Unit, Princess Margaret Hospital for Children, Roberts Road, Subiaco, WA, 6008, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61893408672</phone>
      <fax>+61893407852</fax>
      <email>shripada.rao@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Shripada Rao</name>
      <address>Neonatal Intensive Care Unit, Princess Margaret Hospital for Children, Roberts Road, Subiaco, WA, 6008, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61893408672</phone>
      <fax>+6193407852</fax>
      <email>shripada.rao@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Shripada Rao</name>
      <address>Neonatal Intensive Care Unit, Princess Margaret Hospital for Children, Roberts Road, Subiaco, WA, 6008, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61893408672</phone>
      <fax>+61893407852</fax>
      <email>shripada.rao@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>