<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362079">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000197831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of intermittent dieting on weight loss in overweight and obese females</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of intermittent energy restriction compared to continuous energy restriction on weight loss in healthy overweight to obese females</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>overweight</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Volunteers will be assigned to one of two groups for an 8-week study.  One group will diet continuously while the other will diet intermittently:  1 week dieting with an energy intake of no more than 5.5Mj, 1 week not dieting (no energy restriction), throughout the 8 weeks.  Instruction in how to achieve the energy level of 5.5 MJ will be given at the beginning of the study and dietary advise will be given at every other week for 8 weeks. The continuous dieting group will be instructed in how to achieve the 5.5MJ and reinforcement will be given at fortnightly visits for 8 weeks. A food frequency questionnaire will be completed and dietary education will be delivered in a group session at UniSA at the beginning of the study and each volunteer will be weighed and measured privately every two weeks.  The first visit will take approximately an hour; follow up visits will be shorter.  A 1-year follow up visit will also be held to assess the long term effect.</interventions>
    <comparator>The level of energy restricted diet will give 5500 kJ/day. Total Wellbeing Diet book will be used. 
The volunteers will be instructed to consume a 5.5MJ diet for the duration of the study in the continuous energy restricted group. In the intermittent energy restricted group volunteers will be instructed in consuming a 5.5MJ diet in alternate weeks, starting the week of commencement. In the following week the volunteers will consume their usual diet.
The TWD book will be given to all volunteers. The system will be explained and example diet plan handed out.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight loss will be assessed using digital weighting scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>eight weeks and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist to hip circumference</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline eight weeks and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women over age 18
Body mass index (BMI)  &gt;27 kg/m2 
No concomitant serious illness</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion: Previous surgery for weight reduction
Pregnant or breast feeding women
Alcohol intake in excess of 5 standard drinks per day
Participation in other ongoing trials aiming at altering energy or macronutrient intake</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be divided into groups according to BMI and age.

Participants will be randomized using the minimization method, sealed envolopes containing the diet allocation will be used</concealment>
    <sequence>Dynamic randomization using minimization</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>To show if intermittent dieting is as or more effective in producing weight loss compared to continuous dieting</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/02/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO BOX 2471, Adelaide SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of South Australia, School of Pharmacy and Medical Sciences</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 2471, Adelaide, SA 5001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Overweight and obesity is a major health problem increasing the risk of several lifestyle diseases including type 2 diabetes, cardiovascular disease and certain forms of cancers and effective strategies for weight loss are needed.  A number of studies have shown equal effect on weight loss when using intermittent fasting (fasting 24h followed by 24h ad libitum eating) vs. continuous dieting. Preliminary data has suggested that an intermittent diet strategy using an energy restricted diet, in line with the continuous diet, instead of fasting produces greater weight loss compared to continuous dieting; but this has been investigated only in men. This research will look into the effect of intermittent dieting vs. continuous dieting in a cohort of overweight and obese women
Aim: 
To investigate the effect on weight loss of an intermittent energy restriction compared to a continuous energy restriction, in healthy overweight to obese participants.
Hypothesis:
An intermittent energy restriction will result in greater weight loss.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Ethics Commitee of University of South Australia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of South Australia, GPO Box 2471, Adelaide SA 5001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0000027538</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ass Professor Dr. Jennifer Keogh</name>
      <address>University of South Australia, GPO Box 2471, Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2579</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennifer.keogh@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ass Professor Dr. Jennifer Keogh</name>
      <address>University of South Australia, GPO Box 2471, Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2579</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennifer.keogh@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Eva Pedersen</name>
      <address>University of South Australia, GPO Box 2471, Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1015</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eva.pedersen@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>