<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335762">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/07/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/07/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000618055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Simple, safe and economical: In patients with continent catheterizable ileal pouch after cystectomy, sterile solution for rinsing of pouches can safely be replaced by tap water</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessment of intermittent rinsing of pouches with sterile sodium chloride (NaCl) 0.9% solution or tap water in patients with continent catheterizable ileal pouch after cystectomy in terms of incidence of nitrite-positive days and urinary tract infections, quality of life and costs in a cross-over study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1116-3127</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Continent catheterizable ileal pouches</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Urinary tract infection</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Bladder cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bladder - transitional cell cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients with continent catheterizable ileal pouch are prospectively randomized in a two-arm crossover study. One study arm is "aseptic intermittent self catheterisation (ISC) and rinsing with sodium bicarbonate (NaCl) 0.9% solution". This study arm lasts 90 days. Every morning a dipstick urine test is done by the patient to check nitrite in urine. After that, the umbilicus is cleaned with aseptic solution. Then the pouch is catheterized with a sterile single-use catheter. After catheterizing, the poch is rinced with 3 times 60 milliliters of sterile NaCl 0.9% solution. In case of nitrite-negativity, the same procedure is repeated next morning. In case of nitrite-positivity, the same procedure is repeated at the next catheterization 4 hours later. The entire procedure takes about 15 minutes. In monthly intervals urine cultures are collected. In case of symptomatic urinary tract infection (UTI) an antibiotic therapy is prescribed. Evaluation of quality of life and costs by questionnaire.
There is washout period is one day between the two study arms of the cross-over study.</interventions>
    <comparator>The other study arm is "hygienic ISC and rinsing with tap water". This study arm lasts 90 days. Every morning a dipstick urine test is done by the patient to check nitrite in urine. After that, the umbilicus is cleaned with tap water. Then the pouch is catheterized with a clean single-use catheter. After catheterizing, the poch is rinced with 3 times 60 milliliters of tap water. In case of nitrite-negativity, the same procedure is repeated next morning. In case of nitrite-positivity, the same procedure is repeated at the next catheterization 4 hours later. The entire procedure takes about 15 minutes. In monthly intervals urine cultures are collected. In case of symptomatic urinary tract infection (UTI) an antibiotic therapy is prescribed. Evaluation of quality of life and costs by questionnaire.
After the end of the second study arm the study is finished, no further follow-up.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The amount of nitrite-positive urine study days. Every study day with at least one nitrite-positive urine dipstick test is counted as "nitrite-positive". A study day with a negative nitrite-test in the morning is negative.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and then daily until the end of study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>urinary tranct infection by urine culture</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and then monthly until the end of study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quality of life by questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline and 3 and 6 months after beginning of the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>costs per month of the used material of each patient are evaluated. costs include catheters, syringes, rinsing solution, aseptic solution. Not included are costs for tap water, shipment of the material and waste disposal.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at the end of the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The amount and the duration of every prescribed antibiotic treatments for a symptomatic urinary tract infection (UTI) is evalutated. A symptomatic UTI is defined as a nitrite-positive urine dipstick with fever and/or abdominal pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at the end of the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Continent catheterizable ileal pouch since 2 weeks or more</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Chronical urinary tract infection</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>26</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Urology, Inselspital Bern</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Anna Seiler-Haus
Inselspital
CH-3010 Bern</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Switzerland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Urology, Inselspital Bern</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Anna Seiler-Haus
Inselspital
CH-3010 Bern</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Continent catheterizable ileal pouches must be regularly rinsed to reduce the risk of urinary tract infections (UTI). The aim of this study is to compare the standard method of "aseptic ISC and rinsing with NaCl 0.9% solution" to "hygienic ISC and rinsing with tap water" to assess whether UTI rate, quality of life (QoL), and costs differ. The hypothesis is a lower UTI rate, better QoL and lower costs with the method with tap water.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Kantonale Ethikkommission Bern (KEK)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Postfach 56
CH-3010 Bern</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/10/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Switzerland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Frederic Birkhaeuser</name>
      <address>Department of Urology
Inselspital 
Anna Seiler-Haus
CH-3010 Bern</address>
      <phone>+41 31 632 36 41</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>frederic.birkhaeuser@insel.ch</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Frederic Birkhaeuser</name>
      <address>Department of Urology
Inselspital 
Anna Seiler-Haus
CH-3010 Bern</address>
      <phone>+41 31 632 36 41</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>frederic.birkhaeuser@insel.ch</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Frederic Birkhaeuser</name>
      <address>Department of Urology
Inselspital 
Anna Seiler-Haus
CH-3010 Bern</address>
      <phone>+41 31 632 36 41</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>frederic.birkhaeuser@insel.ch</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>