<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365385">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000016639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can interventions that aim to promote physical activity and prevent falls be combined successfully to improve mobility and independence in older age?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>What is the effect of a physical activity promotion and fall prevention intervention compared to an advice brochure on physical activity participation, mobility goal attainment and falls in older, community-dwelling adults?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Falls</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical activity participation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention aims to increase physical activity participation and reduce risk of falling. It involves a fall risk assessment, tailored fall prevention and physical activity counselling using health coaching and a pedometer-based intervention enhanced with a web-interface (using the "fitbit") to provide feedback and encouragement. The intervention components mentioned above will be delivered by the research physiotherapist  during one home visit, lasting approximately two hours. Participants will be encouraged to wear the pedometer during waking hours on a daily basis for the whole six months to record their daily steps and provide feedback and motivation to increase their physical activity participation. An ultimate goal of undertaking 10,000 steps/ day will be the target. The "fitbit" enhanced pedometer is designed to wirelessly synchronise with computer software to download stored physical activity information and participants will be encouraged to synchronise and download their data on a weekly basis or more often if they desire to. During the implementation of the intervention participants will be taught how to use the "fitbit" device and the associated internet-based feedback and monitoring technology. The research team will have access to all intervention participants "fitbit" data and will monitor individual adherence with the intervention. People who have not downloaded their "fitbit" data in the past week will be contacted to enquire about any problems encountered with the pedometer and to encourage compliance with the intervention protocol.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive the Staying Active and On Your Feet booklet developed by the NSW Ministry of Health and will be advised to continue their usual activities including any health service contact so will not be disadvantaged by being in the study. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity participation, assessed over a 7-day period using the Actigraph accelerometer </outcome>
      <timepoint>Six and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility goal attainment will be assessed using the Goal Attainment Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Six and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of people meeting physical activity guidelines of 150 minutes per week of moderate to vigorous physical activity (from the Actigraph) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Six and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life will be assessed with the EQ-5D.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Six and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fear of falling will be assessed using the short-form Falls Efficacy Scale International </outcome>
      <timepoint>Six and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood will be assessed with the positive sub-scale of the Positive and Negative Affect Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility disability will be assessed using the Late Life Function and Disability Index </outcome>
      <timepoint>Six and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls- recorded with monthly postal calendars</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-aged 60+
-living at home
-regular (weekly) use of a computer or internet-connected tablet device
-leaves the house regularly (at least once per week) without physical assistance from another person. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>being house-bound -cognitive impairment (a diagnosis of dementia or a Memory Impairment Screen score of less than 5) -insufficient English language skills to fully participate in the program -an inability to leave the house without physical assistance from another person -a progressive neurological disease (e.g., Parkinsons disease) -a medical condition precluding exercise (e.g., unstable cardiac disease) -or if they already meet the Australian Physical Activity Guidelines for older adults (operationalised as 30 minutes of moderate intensity physical activity 5 days a week assessed using the Incidental and Planned Exercise Questionnaire and they have had a falls risk assessment in the past year and subsequently implemented fall prevention strategies as a result of the risk assessment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Informed consent
Baseline measurement
Central randomisation by an investigator not involved in recruitment</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>General linear models will be used to assess the effect of group allocation on the continuously-scored primary (average physical activity counts per minute) and secondary outcome measures (quality of life, fear of falling, mood, mobility disability, community participation), after adjusting for baseline scores. Between-group differences in goal attainment (primary outcome) will be analysed with ordinal regression. The number of falls per person-year will be analysed using negative binomial regression models to estimate the between-group difference in fall rates after one year (secondary outcome). Modified Poisson regression models will be used to compare groups on dichotomous outcome measures (proportion of fallers, proportion meeting physical activity guidelines). 

A total of 130 participants (65 per group) will provide 80% power to detect a 15% between-group difference in the primary physical activity outcome (i.e., a between-group difference of 35 mean counts per minute during wear time, standard deviation of 91), a dropout rate of 15% and alpha of 5%. The estimates of mean accelerometer counts per minute for this calculation were taken from the 263 community dwelling USA-based women aged 65 and older in a large sample of accelerometer data. We took a conservative approach and estimated the proportion of dropouts at 15% although our previous trials have had lower dropout rates. These calculations were undertaken in Stata 12 using the sampsi command, assuming a 0.7 correlation between measures and assuming a post-test between-group comparison that adjusted for baseline scores. 

A sample size of 130 will also provide 80% power to detect a clinically meaningful 20% between-group difference in goal attainment scores. The sample size will also be sufficient to detect between-group differences in the order of 10-15% for the secondary outcome measures.


</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/01/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/01/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>13/08/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>130</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>131</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/08/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The George Institute for Global Health
PO Box M201 Missenden Rd 
NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Marrickville Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2-14 Fisher St, PO Box 14 Petersham NSW 2049</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Research bequest</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>not applicable</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This trial aims to establish the impact of a physical activity and fall prevention intervention compared to an advice brochure on physical activity levels, mobility goal attainment, fall rates, mobility disability, quality of life, fear of falling, mood and community participation in community-dwelling older people. 
We hypothesise that at the end of the 12 month follow-up period, intervention participants will be more physically active, have fewer falls and improve on measures of mobility goal attainment, mobility disability, quality of life, fear of falling, mood and community participation compared to control group participants.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Sydney HREC. 
The University of Sydney. NSW. 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013/789</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anne Tiedemann</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health, PO Box M201 Missenden Rd, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61280524393</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>atiedemann@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anne Tiedemann</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health, PO Box M201 Missenden Rd, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61280524393</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>atiedemann@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anne Tiedemann</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health, PO Box M201 Missenden Rd, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61280524393</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>atiedemann@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anne Tiedemann</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health, PO Box M201 Missenden Rd, NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61280524393</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>atiedemann@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>