<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368627">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000604505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomized Controlled Trial of Self-regulated Constraint-induced Movement Therapy to promote functional regain in Subacute Stroke Patients </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized Controlled Trial of Self-regulated Constraint-induced Movement Therapy as compared with conventional occupational therapy to promote functional regain in Subacute Stroke Patients </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1166-8303</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Subacute stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Self-regulated constraint-induced movement therapy (SR-CIMT) - participants' non-hemiplegic arm was restrained in a mitt for 4 hours every day, 2 weeks, 5 days a week (therapy days) (CIMT) (the same CIMT protocol as in the CIMT group described under 'comparator/control treatment'); participants were taught using the self-regulation (SR) strategy to relearn the tasks; SR strategy involved participants self-reflecting on their abilities and deficits in performing the tasks, identifying problems and solutions in achieving the most independence in the tasks, and then actually carrying out the tasks. There were 10 tasks to practice in total, they included fold laundry, put clothes on hanger, brush teeth, dress upper garment, dress lower garment in week one; and use telephone, prepare a cup of tea, sweep floor, wash towel, wash dishes in week two.

In the 4 hours when the participants had their non-hemiplegic arm in the restrain, they received  one hour therapist-guided training using SR strategy on task relearning as described above. Therefore, all participants received 10 one-hour therapist-guided training sessions (daily on weekdays, total two weeks). The intervention was delivered by occupational therapist. For the rest of the 3 hours in the restrain, the participants' wearing of the restrain was monitored by the nursing staff in the ward.</interventions>
    <comparator>1. Control intervention - conventional occupational therapy involving therapist to demonstrate the adapted task performance followed by patients practice under supervision. They practised the same 10 tasks as in the SR-CIMT group described above. They received training for 2 weeks, 5 days a week (therapy days), the same as in the SR-CIMT and CIMT groups.

2. Constraint-induced movement therapy (CIMT) - non-hemiplegic arm was restrained in a mitt for 4 hours every day, 2 weeks, 5 days a week (therapy days); therapist provided demonstration on the adapted task performance with one arm (the side of participants' hemiplegic arm), and participants to practice the tasks with the unrestrained hemiplegic arm under supervision. They practised the same 10 tasks as in the SR-CIMT and control groups.

The same as the experimental intervention group (SR-CIMT), in the 4 hours when the participants had their non-hemiplegic arm in the restrain, they received  one hour therapist-guided training using the strategy on task relearning as described above. Therefore, all participants received 10 one-hour therapist-guided training sessions (daily on weekdays, total two weeks). The intervention was delivered by occupational therapist. For the rest of the 3 hours in the restrain, the participants' wearing of the restrain was monitored by the nursing staff in the ward.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lawton Instrumental Activities of Daily Living Scale (Lawton IADL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, after the intervention and at one month after intervention completed</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Action Research Arm Test (ARAT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, after the intervention and at one month after intervention completed</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fugl Meyer Assessment (FMA), upper extremity motor subsection</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, after the intervention and at one month after intervention completed</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motor Activity Log - 28 (MAL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, after the intervention and at one month after intervention completed</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients receiving in-patient rehabilitation post-stroke were recruited from a rehabilitation hospital. 

Patients were eligible if they:
(1) had sustained an ischemic type stroke with lesion in the primary or motor cortical areas resulting in hemiplegia, 
(2) had stroke onset of less than 3 months, 
(3) were aged above 60, 
(4) had 10 degree active extension in metacarpophalangeal joint and interphalangeal joint, 20 degree active extension of wrist joint.  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) had excessive spasticity in the affected limb, as defined by a score of 2 or more on the Modified Ashworth Scale, 
(2) had excessive pain in the affected limb, as defined by a score 4 or more using a Visual Analog Scale, 
(3) had a score below 19 on the Mini-Mental Status Examination (MMSE), and 
(4) had diagnosed of depression according to DSM-IV criteria.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible patients were randomized by drawing lots using three sealed opaque envelopes (for the three intervention groups). The randomization was conducted by a blinded researcher who was not involved in delivering the interventions or study measures. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by drawing lots using three sealed opaque envelopes (for the three intervention groups)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Using PASS 13 software, based on the parameters used for ANOVA tests, and with reference to the results obtained from the previous CIMT study, the total sample size of 20 in each group would give a power of 80%, an alpha value of 0.05 and effect size of 0.50. 

Differences among the three groups in demographic variables were assessed using analysis of variance (ANOVA) and chi square test; and in study measures at baseline were assessed using the Kruskal-Wallis test. For changes in the study measures among baseline, after intervention and one month after the intervention completed in each group, Friedman test was used. Differences in the gains across the study measures, before and after intervention, among the three groups were measured using the Kruskai-Wallis test. Mann-Whitney U test was used to further test the differences, if any, between any of the two groups. Significance level was set at a 2-tailed P&lt;0.050 for all comparisons.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>10/09/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>12/10/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>81</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>Hong Kong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University
11 Yuk Choi Rd
Hung Hom
Kowloon
Hong Kong</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University
11 Yuk Choi Rd
Hung Hom
Kowloon
Hong Kong</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Hong Kong</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Western Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Western Sydney
Campbelltown Campus
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Western Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Western Sydney
Campbelltown Campus
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Emerging research suggests the use of self-regulation (SR) strategies at improving functional regain in patients with brain injury. SR is proposed to produce an added effect to the effective constraint-induced movement therapy (CIMT). This study aimed to examine the efficacy of a self-regulated CIMT program (SR-CIMT) for function regain of patients with sub-acute stroke.
It was hypothesized that participants receiving the combined treatment (SR and CIMT) would have a better functional regain.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Lam, K., Liu, K., Leung, T., Sum, C., Yue, A. &amp; Mok, V. (2013, 24-26 July). The effectiveness of self-regulated constraint-induced movement therapy for functional regain for people with sub-acute stroke: A randomized controlled trial. Australian Occupational Therapy Journal, 110.

Leung, T., Liu, K.P.Y., Sum, C., Mok, V. &amp; Lum, C. (2010). Self-regulation constraint-induced movement therapy programme for people with sub-acute stroke. Hong Kong Hospital Authority Rehabilitation Symposium.

Leung, T., Liu, K.P.Y., Sum, C., Mok, V. &amp; Lum, C. (2010). Self-regulation constraint-induced movement therapy programme for people with sub-acute stroke. Hong Kong Journal of Occupational Therapy,19, A8.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University
11 Yuk Choi Rd
Hung Hom
Kowloon
Hong Kong</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/11/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NA</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Joint the Chinese University of Hong Kong - New Territories East Cluster Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flate 3C, Block B
Staff Quarters
Prince of Wales Hospital
Shatin 
Hong Kong</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/05/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CRE-2008.192-T</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>New Territories West Cluster Clinical and Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Tuen Mun Hospital
Tsing Chung Kwun Road
Tuen Mun
Hong Kong</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/08/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NA</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368627-PolyU ethicsapprovalletter_extend to 31Dec2010.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368627-Ethics approval.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368627-TMH cluster ethics approval.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Karen Liu</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney
Campbelltown Campus
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 46203432</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.liu@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Karen Liu</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney
Campbelltown Campus
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 46203432</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.liu@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Karen Liu</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney
Campbelltown Campus
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 46203432</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.liu@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Karen Liu</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>