<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367425">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/12/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001294640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Coronary Artery calcium score: Use to Guide management of Hereditary Coronary Artery Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Study of intermediate risk subjects with a family history of coronary artery disease to identify whether  management based on coronary calcium scoring vs usual care leads to reduction of coronary plaque volume progression and adverse cardiovascular events </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CAUGHT-CAD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary artery disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A computed tomography (CT) scan is a 30 min assessment obtained at baseline and 3 year follow-up.
This is an Xray picture undertaken by lying in a computed tomography (CT) scanner. The coronary calcium score is obtained by automatic measurement of the density and extent of Xray findings caused by calcium. A CT coronary angiogram is obtained at the same time.
The coronary calcium score is used to identify subjects with early coronary artery disease. Those randomized to the treatment arm will be started on oral atovastatin 40 mg/d for the duration of the trial. Intolerance of this dose will lead to down-titration to atovastatin 20mg. If still intolerant, rosuvastatin 10 mg/d or pravastatin 40mg will be tried. If the subject remains intolerant, statin will be stopped but the subject will remain in the trial for intention to treat analysis.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care (lifestyle and risk factor modification). These subjects will have CT scans but the results will not be used to guide management.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in coronary plaque volume is measured by comparison of baseline and 3 year CT coronary angiograms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost-effectiveness of CCS in subjects with a CAD family history (based on management costs vs coronary events) in the Australian setting</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to therapy, assessed by drug tablet return and results of laboratory tests</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Asymptomatic subjects age 40-70y 
- Family history of CAD involving an index patient &lt;60y (1st degree) or &lt;50y (2nd degree) 
- Not already on statins
- Total cholesterol &lt; 6.5 mmol/L and LDL cholestrerol &lt;5 mmol/L
- CAD 5-year risk (Australian risk calculator) 2.5-15% </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Symptomatic coronary, cerebrovascular, or peripheral vascular disease
- Intolerance of statins or already on statins
- Pre-existing muscle disease (eg polymyositis, fibromyalgia) 
- Atrial fibrillation
- Chronic kidney disease on haemodialysis 
- Inability to provide informed consent
- Major systemic illness eg malignancy, rheumatoid arthritis
- Women of child bearing potential
- Poorly controlled hypertension: SBP&gt; 200 and or DBP &gt; 100
- Severe psychiatric disorder (eg bipolar depression; psychosis)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation (by computer access to central administration site) before scanning to coronary calcium-guided (CCS) vs usual care. Usual care = calcium score not given to patient or clinician.
Allocation concealment to core lab reading coronary plaque volumes (PROBE design)
</concealment>
    <sequence>
Update
 Computerised protocol with a 1:1 ratio of CCS reporting to usual care. We will block-randomise for the six participating centres and randomisation will be stratified according to risk level (low or intermediate CCS). </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We have powered this study for a delta plaque volume of 20 mm3, which is more conservative than Budoff et al (decrease of 47+/-72 mm3 vs 14+/-77 in control, p&lt;0.001). We have therefore determined that 638 patients will need to undergo serial imaging to have 80% power to detect a difference between the groups of 20 mm3, with a standard deviation of 90 mm3 (two-sided p=0.05). Assuming that 15% of subjects will drop out or not have evaluable imaging at both time points, 734 subjects will be randomised over the 1st 18 months of the study, to provide a minimum 3 year follow-up. 

All data will be pooled and summarised with respect to demographic and baseline characteristics. Exploratory data analyses will be performed using descriptive statistics. 
The primary analysis will compare the 3-year coronary plaque volume in CCS-guided and usual care subjects. We will use linear regression to correct for coincidental between-group differences despite randomisation, and to obtain the effect size of CCS-based management, independent of age, sex and baseline risk. The same methods will be used for the secondary end-points. The primary analysis will be on grounds of intention-to-treat (ITT), ie. inclusion of all patients having taken part in baseline and final evaluation. We will also perform a per-protocol analysis.

Events are expected to be very rare. Nonetheless, differences between groups with respect to the number and/or timing of events will be assessed using survival curves for all-cause and event-free survival. Cox-Proportional Hazards Models will be used to examine the independent effect of treatment and risk factors on outcomes. 

Analyses with be performed or supervised by a CI-biostatistician.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/12/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>734</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Ipswich Hospital - Ipswich</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
    <postcode>6000 - Perth</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>4305 - Ipswich</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - St Kilda Road Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Baker-IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>75 Commercial Road, Melbourne Vic 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke Street, Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The proposed study will be the first randomized controlled trial (RCT) of the use of CCS, and will be targeted to 40-70 year old 1st degree relatives of patients with CAD onset &lt;60 years old, or 2nd degree relatives of patients with onset &lt;50 years old. Control patients will undergo standard risk scoring but have blinded CCS results. In the intervention arm, treatment will be initiated based on CCS, applying the new ACC/AHA prevention guidelines. At three years, the effectiveness of intervention will be assessed on change in plaque volume at CT coronary angiography (CTCA), the extent of which has been strongly linked to outcome. The results will provide high-level evidence to inform the guidelines regarding the place of CTCA in risk assessment, specifically in patients with a family history of premature CAD. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (Tasmania)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Unit
Office of Research Services
University of Tasmania
Private Bag 1
Hobart TAS 7001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0014081</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Thomas Marwick</name>
      <address>Baker-IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute, 75 Commercial Road, Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tom.marwick@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Thomas Marwick</name>
      <address>Baker-IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute, 75 Commercial Road, Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tom.marwick@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Thomas Marwick</name>
      <address>Baker-IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute, 75 Commercial Road, Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1550</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tom.marwick@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>