<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336530">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/03/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000283976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Analysis of the effectiveness of the pilates method on stress urinary incontinence</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Analysis of the effectiveness of the pilates method on stress urinary incontinence</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1119-4438</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>There's no other number</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stress urinary incontinence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>kinesiotherapy 
Exercise 1 - Patient will begin with 5 minutes of global stretching of the upper and lower limb.
Exercise 2 - The patient will sit on the ball (Bobath) will be held  and mobility pelvic movements (exercises anteversion / retroversion, lateral inclination).
Exercise 3 - Hundred (Hundred) - Starting Position: Patient supine, hip and knee flexed 90 degress, the scapula stabilized, arms at your sides and palms facing down. Exercise: patient inhales, the expiration patient flex the head and upper body, stabilizing the shoulder blades and tightening the abdominal muscles and the perineum ("Hold Your Wee") and extend the knees. Inspiring, returning to its initial position. 
Exercise 4 - Double leg stretch (Double Leg Stretch) - Starting Position: Patient supine, hip and knee flexed at 90 degrees, bring your hands on your ankles. Will flex the trunk and maintaining the elongated head and feet in tip. Exercise: A patient inspires, the patient expired contract the abdomen and the perineum muscle and spreading her legs and arms outstretched to take the head. Inspiring, returning to its initial position 
Exercise 5 - Bearing partial back (Half roll back) - Starting Position: Patient seated, knees bent, feet parallel, about the column bent knees, arms extended and stabilized scapula. Exercise: A patient inspires, the patient expired contracts abdomen and perineum muscle and starts rolling back and can continue while maintaining lumbar flexion and feet on the mat. Inhale, returning to its initial position. 
Exercise 6 - Preparing for the bridge (Shoulder Bridge Prep) - Starting Position: Patient supine, knees bent and parallel to the line of hip, scapula stabilized, arms at your sides and palms facing down. Exercise: A patient inspires, the patient expired contracts abdomen and perineum muscle, lift your pelvis up vertebra by vertebra, extending the column. Inhale, returning to its initial position. 
Exercise 7 - Kick Series IV (Side Kick Series IV) - Starting position: lying on its side on the outstretched arm (serving as the headrest), neutral spine and pelvis, scapula stabilized, and one arm resting on the mat. Top leg bent forward with the other foot and lower leg perform adduction, standing on tip. Exercise: inspiration, during expiration the patient contracts the abdominal muscles and perineum, leading to the leg from the bottom up (adduction), inhale back to the starting position. 
Exercise 8 - Coordination (Coordination) - Starting Position: Patient supine, hip flexed at 45 degrees, the scapula stabilized, arms above your head holding the ball Bobath. Exercise: inspiration, during expiration the patient will contract the abdomen and perineum muscle, flexing the hip and take the ball to the ankle, holding the ball with the medial malleolus. Inhale back to center position. 
Exercise 9 - Circle of the hip (Hip Circles) - starting position: The patient sits on the buttocks, arms extended and resting on the floor, bend the trunk and then bend your legs at 90 degrees to the trunk. 
Exercise: Breathe in, hold on expiration circles with the legs. 
Exercise 10 - Corkscrew (Corkscrew) 
Starting Position: Patient supine, hip flexed at 45 degrees, the scapula stabilized, arms along the body. Exercise: inspiration, during expiration the patient contracts the abdominal muscles and the perineum, held circular motion with both legs at the same time. 
All exercises were performed individually by the same physiotherapist three times a week (Monday, Wednesday and Friday), with 1 hour per session for 3 months. All exercises are performed with 10 repetitions of each exercise lasting 1 hour</interventions>
    <comparator>Compared before and after treatment</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urogynecological assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Urogynecology evaluation contained the data: age, chief complaint, disease history and physical examination. Physical examination was used vaginal cones to determine the degree of perineal muscle strength. The vaginal cones are used in number of five weighing 25g to 65g. The cone weighed a 25g, 35g cone weighing two, three cone weighed 45g, four cone weighed 55g; Cone five weighed 65g. 
Procedure: 
To determine the degree of muscle strength of the perineum, the patient was instructed to enter each cone in the canal, one at a time and perform 10 steps, and perform 10 squat jumps 10 times and that this cone was inserted into the vagina could not out, indicating that the patient can sustain the cone with the muscles of the perineum. The procedure started with 25gr cone, then get up to 35g to 65g cone. 
For the degree of muscle strength "0" indicates that the patient could not sustain the cone 25g 
For the degree of muscle strength "1" indicates that the patient could sustain the cone 25g 
For the degree of muscle strength "2" indicates that the patient could sustain the cone 35g 
For the degree of muscle strength "3" indicates that the patient could sustain the cone 45g 
For the degree of muscle strength "4" indicates that the patient could sustain the cone 55g 
For the degree of muscle strength "5" indicates that the patient could sustain the cone 65g 
The evaluation was performed in the pre-treatment and three months after treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Assessment Questionnaire Quality of Life "King's Health Questionnaire (KHQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>King's Health Questionnaire (KHQ) is composed of 21 questions divided into eight areas: 
1 - perception generates health, 
2 - impact of urinary incontinence, 
3 - limitations of daily activities, 
4 - physical limitations, 
5 - social limitations, 
6 - personal relationships, 
7 - emotions, 
8 - sleep / disposal. Each response is referred to a value (0 = no / not sure; 1 = little / rarely, 2 = average / sometimes, 3 = very much / always). 
Scores range from 0 to 100 and the higher the score, the greater the impact on quality of life
Was assessed at pre-treatment and three months after treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>included in the study a female patient aged 47 years with a clinical diagnosis of stress urinary incontinence and physical therapy for pelvic floor muscle weakness with power equal to and above 3.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with urgent urinary incontinence, stress urinary incontinence due to insufficiency insfecteriana, incontinent women, patients with cognitive and neurological injuries that deny patients sign an informed consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/10/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>MG</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Pouso Alegre</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Andreia Maria Silva</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>R Benjamin Constant 93
City: Alfenas
State: MG
CEP: 37130-000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University Vale to sapucai</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Av Alfredo custodio de paula 320
City: Pouso Alegre
State: MG
CEP: 37550-000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University Vale to Sapucai</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Av Alfredo Custodio de Paula 320
City: Pouso Alegre
State: MG
CEP: 37550-000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Objective: To examine the effectiveness of Pilates in rehabilitation in women with stress urinary incontinence. Materials and methods: After approval by the ethics committee on research under No. 1482/10, the study included one female patient aged 47 years with a clinical diagnosis of stress urinary incontinence and physical therapy for pelvic floor muscle weakness with Power equal 3 and above. Evaluation was performed by Urogynecology Checklist and a questionnaire to evaluate Quality of Life "King's Health Questionnaire. The protocol was performed three times per week (2, 4 and 6), lasting 1 hour per session for 3 months. Statistical analysis Mean and standard deviation. Results: At baseline and final respectively obtained the percentage of 60% and 100% of muscle strength and the King's Health Questionnaire quality of life gained 32 points respectively (68%) and 20 points (80%). Conclusion: The Pilates method associated with the treatment of urinary incontinence was effective, promoting better quality of life and strength of pelvic floor muscles. Larger samples are suggested to achieve a more effective completion of the technique.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee in Research UNIVAS</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Av Pref. Tuany Toledo 470 Fatima
City: Pouso Alegre
State: MG
CEP: 37550-000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1482/2010</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/08/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andreia Maria Silva</name>
      <address>R Benjamin Constant 93
City: Alfenas
State: MG
CEP: 37130-000</address>
      <phone>55(35)3291-1486</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andreiamarias@bol.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andreia Maria Silva</name>
      <address>R Benjamin Constant 93
City: Alfenas
State: MG
CEP: 37130-000</address>
      <phone>55(35)3291-1486</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andreiamarias@bol.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andreia Maria Silva</name>
      <address>R Benjamin Constant 93
City: Alfenas
State: MG
CEP: 37130-000</address>
      <phone>55(35)3291-1486</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andreiamarias@bol.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>