<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372726">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000592347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>CXCR4 PET/CT for Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma (HNSCC) staging.     </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Pilot Study of CXCR4 PET for nodal staging of resectable mucosal head and neck Squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC), including correlation with histopathology immunohistochemistry, sputum and Circulating Tumour Cells.                          </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Head and neck</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study intervention is the addition of PET/MR, a PET/CT image using a CXCR4 tracer (68Ga-CPCR4-2) and an additional FDG PET/CT scan. We would also take saliva and blood samples. The scans and samples will be taken within 36 hours of each-other and be at least 4.5 hours apart. It is standard for biopsy samples to be taken during surgery, but in addition their location would be recorded. Tissue will be obtained from the surgical procedure.  There will be no impact on usual patient care. Participants will also receive MR contrast agent so as to obtain a standard of care MRI acquisition during the PET/MR scan; in some cases, where participants have had a prior MRI scan, the use of MR contrast agent will be an additional intervention.

Blood samples
Before imaging begins, a blood sample will be taken by injecting a needle into a vein and letting a small amount of blood pool into a collection tube. Three tubes of blood will be taken but from the same needle.

Session 1a: 68Ga-Pentixafor -PET/MR
After emptying your bladder, a qualified Nuclear Medicine Technologist will ask you to lie on the scanner bed. They will insert a tube into your vein and inject a radioactive substance called 68Ga-Pentixafor as well as MRI Contrast. The scan involves lying flat with knees supported and arms resting by your side. Only your head/neck will be scanned. The scan time for the PET/CT will be approximately 70 minutes. During this time the MR part of the scanner will make buzzing or knocking noises as it generates different kinds of images.

Session 1b: 68Ga-Pentixafor-PET/CT
You will be asked empty your bladder again and walk to the PET/CT scanner in the room next door. After lying down you will be scanned from head to mid-chest. This scan will last approximately 20 minutes.

After the first imaging session and having a drink of water and something to eat, you will be asked to not eat or drink anything but water (drinking water is encouraged) for the four hours prior to the next scan.

Saliva samples
Approximately one hour after eating and drinking you will be asked to provide three saliva samples. The three saliva samples will take some time to obtain because a different method will be used each time: 
1. Once after waiting for saliva to build up in the mouth, 
2. Once after having had a lemon sweet, and
3. Once after rinsing with mouthwash.

After the saliva samples have been taken, you will then be asked to continue to avoid eating, but encouraged to drink water.

Session 2: FDG-PET/CT
Four hours after eating, a qualified Nuclear Medicine Technologist will ask you empty your bladder and to lie on the scanner bed. They will insert a tube into your vein and inject a radioactive substance called FDG. The scan involves lying flat with knees supported and arms resting by your sides. For approximately the first 60 minutes only your head will be scanned. In the second part of the scan, you will be scanned from head to mid-chest. This will take approximately another 15 minutes. 

After the examination is completed, you will be able to eat and drink normally.

Scanning sessions can be performed on two separate days if required but both scanning sessions need to be performed within 36 hours of the first scan starting. 

A nuclear medicine physician will for interpreting the results.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will receive standard of care diagnostic scanning as per the Head and Neck Multidisciplinary Team requirements.  
FDG-PET Scan will act as the comparator as this is the current Standard of Care in this population.

A qualified nuclear medicine technologist will be responsible of administering the tracers and performing the scans and a qualified nuclear medicine physician will interpret the results.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CXCR4 receptor expression in Oral cavity SCC and other head and neck mucosal subsites (eg larynx and hypopharynx) assessed by FDG PET/CT scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Diagnosis</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CXCR4 receptor expression in Oral cavity SCC and other head and neck mucosal subsites (eg larynx and hypopharynx) assessed by PET MRI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Diagnosis</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Utilise measurements of salivary miRNA expression levels. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Diagnosis</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of performing simultaneous PET/MR, assessed by proportion of enrolled participants completing the protocol, and by semi-structured interviews with treating clinicians.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Diagnosis</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The relationship between tumoural CXCR4 expression and established novel markers of immune cell infiltration and function will be assessed as an exploratory endpoint.

Tests relating to exploratory endpoints of immune correlates of CXCR4 expression will be performed primarily at QIMR Berghofer:
* Flow cytometry will be performed on fresh tumour tissue to quantify protein expression indicating presence of
* Immune cell subsets of interest including T cells (TCRBeta/CD3), T cell subsets (CD4/8, FoxP3), NK cells (CD56 and others), others (e.g. CD11b)
* Immune modifiers (which may include T-cell immune checkpoints and other markers such as PD-1/PD-L1, CTLA-4, TIGIT, CD96/CD155) and markers of function (which may include IFN, IL-2, Granzyme B and others)
* CXCR4 expression on tumour-infiltrating immune cells and tumour/stroma tissue
* Standard assays of immune cell function employing in-vitro techniques such as mixed lymphocyte reaction, T cell stimulation, treatment with monoclonal antibodies

All immunological studies are being performed in the lab of Prof Mark Smyth (Team Head, Immunology in Cancer and Infection, QIMRB), and may be shared with scientific collaborators after HREC review. These results are not relevant to the treatment of the patient and do not need to be communicated with the treatment physicians. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Diagnosis</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Circulating tumour cell levels, assessed by serum assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Diagnosis</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria	 	 	 	
1.	Biopsy proven mucosal head and neck SCC suitable for upfront surgery with planned neck dissection.
2.	Age 18 years and over.
3.	Written informed consent
4.	All women of childbearing age must have a pregnancy test before enrolment
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria 	 	 	
1.	Patients with head and neck cancers other than SCC
2.	Patients unable to undergo a PET scan for any reason, in the opinion of the investigator.
3.	Patients allergic to FDG
4.	Pregnant or breastfeeding
5.	Diabetic
6.	Prior exposure to a CTLA-4 inhibitor (e.g. ipilimumab, tremelimumab), PD-1 inhibitor (e.g. nivolumab, pembrolizumab), PD-L1 inhibitor (e.g. MEDI-4736), PD-L2 inhibitor or any or any other antibody or drug specifically targeting T-cell costimulation or immune checkpoint pathways.
7.	A condition requiring systemic treatment with either corticosteroids (&gt; 10 mg daily prednisone equivalents) or other immunosuppressive medications within 14 days of study commencement. Inhaled or topical steroids and adrenal replacement doses &gt; 10 mg daily prednisone equivalents are permitted in the absence of active autoimmune disease.
8.	Standard MRI exclusion criteria and claustrophobia
9.	Patients with a history of psychological illness or condition such as to interfere with the patients ability to understand the requirements of the study.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Metro North Hospital and Health Service
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston QLD 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Herston Imaging Research Facility Seed Funding</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Metro North Hospital and Health Service
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street 
Herston QLD 4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to evaluate the use of an investigative imaging technique, known as CXCR4 positron emission tomography (PET), for disease staging in patients with resectable mucosal head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC).

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above, and have biopsy proven mucosal head and neck SCC suitable for upfront surgery with planned neck dissection.

Study details
Prior to resection and in addition to our usual standard of care assessments, all participants in this study will be imaged with PET/CT and PET/MRI with a CXCR4 tracer (68Ga-CPCR4-2) and have blood and saliva collected.  




</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7 Block 7
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Herston Road 
Herston QLD 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lizbeth Kenny</name>
      <address>Cancer Care Services 
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lizbeth.kenny@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jacqui Keller</name>
      <address>Cancer Care Services
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jacqui.keller@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lizbeth Kenny</name>
      <address>Cancer Care Services
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street 
Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lizbeth.kenny@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>