<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1341">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/01/2003</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/01/2003</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000264583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised controlled trial to see if Continuous Positive Airways Pressure will reduce the number of infants transferred from Special Care Nurseries to Intensive care Nurseries.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised controlled trial of headbox oxygen versus Continuous Positive Airways Pressure (CPAP) to reduce up-transfer of infants with respiratory distress in non-teritary hospitals.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Bubbles for Babies</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Perinatal Trials Registry: PTR401</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Babies born with respiratory distress in non-tertiary centres.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention is CPAP at 5cms of water. Provided using Hudson Nasal prongs connected to an underwater seal. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group receives standard of care treatment for respiratory distress.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be transfer or treatment failure, as determined by the following criteria:
1. HeadBoxOxygen (HBO) only. HBO will be considered to have failed if =60% oxygen is required to maintain a saturation of =94%, and if this requirement persists for more than one hour. (75% of the participating paediatricians would definitely transfer an infant requiring &gt; 60% oxygen.).
2. CPAP only. CPAP will be considered to have failed if =50% oxygen is required to maintain a saturation of =94%, and if this requirement persists for more than one hour. As agreed with representatives of NICUs that use CPAP as frontline treatment, and in keeping with the principle that babies in CPAP who are in the same amount of oxygen as babies in a headbox are more unwell.
3. Both groups. The persistence of a CO2 level of &gt; 60 on two successive gasses at least 1 hour apart. (75% of the participating paediatricians would definitely transfer an infant with a CO2 of &gt; 60%).
4. Both groups. The persistence of a pH level of &lt; 7.25 on two successive gasses at least 1 hour apart. (75% of the participating paediatricians would definitely transfer an infant with a pH level of &lt; 7.25).
5. Both groups. Transfer may be arranged prior to meeting these criteria for any baby if so decided through consultation between the support hospital and the attending paediatrician. The justification for doing so will be clearly documented.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Length of time needing oxygen. The duration of respiratory support in air (i.e., without supplementary oxygen) will also be measured.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Length of time in oxygen will be measured in hours. This will commence from the moment of treatment commencement post-randomisation. If oxygen is recommenced during the initial stay, or if an infant is up-transferred to a NICU, this time will be added.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Length of stay. Length of stay to discharge home will be calculated for all babies. This will include up-transfers and any down-transfers until the infant is discharged home.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3. Parental stress. A questionnaire used to identify levels of stress.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4. Pneumothorax. All pneumothoraxes will be identified whether requiring a chest drain or not. The final diagnosis of a pneumothorax will be determined by radiologist.   </outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5. Morbidity and mortality data will be collected on all babies. The following indicators will be used as a measure of morbidity: 1. Requirement of oxygen at 28 days of age. 2. Mortality 3. Intraventricular haemorrhage. Head ultra sound will be obtained on babies where clinically indicated by the paediatrician. Any other side effects, such as ulceration of the nares, will be recorded but not included as part of this outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6. Nurse workload will be measured for all babies whether randomised to HBO or CPAP.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. dagnosed with respiratory distress. Defined as al least one of the following: recession, grunt, nasal flare, or tachypnoea (respiratory rate &gt;60/minute)2. Who require &gt;30% oxygen to maintain SaO2 or&gt; or = 94% over a period of &gt;30minutes.3. Babies aged less than 24 hours</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Not stated</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>31</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Infants &lt; 31wks gestation. 2. Infants &lt;1200 grams. Corresponds to the 10th percentile for 31 weeks gestation. 3. Apgar score = 3 at 5minutes of age. Used as an arbitrary and de-facto indicator of possible perinatal asphyxia.4. Cardiac cause of respiratory distress. 5. Any infant who is perceived by their paediatrician to need NICU care. This out clause will provide an added safety mechanism and will cover infants with, for example, congenital anomalies. Potential implications for generalisability will be assessed by recording non-identifying details of all infants excluded for this reason, along with the reason for transfer.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone.</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation according to gestational age and centre of birth.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/08/2002</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Adam Buckmaster</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Financial Markets Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many babies are born with respiratory distress and require care in a Special Care Nursery (SCN). Whilts most of these babies get better with oxygen and other routine supports a number have to be transferred to a Neonatal Intensive Care Unit (NICU). Such a transfer has a major impact on the health of the baby and on the family unit and incurs a significant cost.
Continuous Positive Airways Pressure (CPAP) is used to treat infants with respiratory distress in Australian NICUs. This proposal seeks to compare, by randomised trial, nasal CPAP to head box oxygen in SCN, as means of early treatment of respiratory distress. The study is designed to be able to detect a 50% reduction in the number of babies meeting criteria that would ordinarily result in transfer to NICUs.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Coast Area Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>01/38</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Gold Coast Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>200306</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>6651</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Sydney Area health service HS/TG</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2002/5/3.3 (1365)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South western Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>AHS 04/034</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Health service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>01/133</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Illawarra Helath Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>HE02/024</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms J. Foster</name>
      <address>NSW Pregnancy and Newborn Services Network
University of Sydney, NSW</address>
      <phone>(02) 93518749</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jfoster@perinatal.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms J. Foster</name>
      <address>NSW Pregnancy and Newborn Services Network
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>(02) 93518749</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jfoster@perinatal.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>