<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372594">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000630314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of motor imagery after total knee arthroplasty: pilot study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of motor imagery after total knee arthroplasty on knee pain and function: pilot study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>total knee arthroplasty</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Knee osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim is to demonstrate the efficacy of the motor imagery technique in combination with conventional physiotherapy versus the effectiveness of conventional physiotherapy only in patients undergoing total knee arthroplasty due to osteoarthrosis.

For this, both therapies will be compared. Patients participating in the study will be randomized into two groups:
-Group A: conventional physiotherapy.
- Group B: conventional physiotherapy implemented with motor imagery.

Therefore the only difference between the two groups will be the motor imagery, our objective to study.
The Motor Imagery is a representation of movement technique's, process during which an individual mentally simulates a movement the action without its actual execution.
The process is carried out as follows:
- Observation of movement in another person.
- Observation of movement in the non-operated lower limb.
- Imagination of the realization of movement in the non-operated lower limb.
- Imagination of movement in the operated lower limb.
- Realization of the movement.
This process has been implemented in the protocol of therapeutic exercises of habitual physiotherapy, that is, motor imagery will be ustilised for each exercise performed during sessions, always guided by the physiotherapist.
Autonomous follow-up of therapy will be recommended in both groups.

For this study we will need two physical therapists with more than 5 years of experience: physiotherapist 1 or evaluator who will be the one who will perform the data collection and physiotherapist 2 or executor of the intervention. The evaluating physiotherapist will be blinded to the intervention and the physiotherapist who executes the intervention will be blinded to the measurements.

 It will be held individually in your hospital room starting the second day after surgery. 
Patients in both groups will perform an individual physical therapy session a day for a total of 5 sessions of 30 minutes each session. 

Before to data collection, the patient information sheet will be provided along with informed consent for signature.</interventions>
    <comparator>An active control will be used; The control group will be treated as is usually done in the hospital unit, following the steps of the clinical guide for knee arthroplasties.

As in the case of intervention, the treatment will be 5 sessions daily, 30 minutes each, performed individually.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effectiveness of motor imagery after total knee arthroplasty on knee functional capacity assessed using the WOMAC questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at days 3 and 5 post-surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee pain intensity as assessed using the Visual Analogue Scale (VAS).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and after 5 days of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perception of pain threshold measured with a pressure algometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and after 5 days of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Joint amplitude variation of the knee assessed through clinical goniometric measures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at days 1 and 5 post-surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- To undergo total knee arthroplasty due to osteoarthrosis.
- Age between 60 and 85 years.
- Signature of informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Diagnosis of neurological pathology.
- Diagnosis of psychiatric or developmental disorders.
- Uncompensated and / or uncontrolled cardiac pathology.
- Severe respiratory pathology
- Acute fracture.
- Cognitive impairment.
- Infectious, febrile or uncompensated tension (hypo / hypertension).
- Alterations that prevent the understanding by the patient of the slogans of the proposed treatment.
- Any other alteration that contraindicates the intervention of the physiotherapist during the development of the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size consisted of a total of 30 subjects, operated on total knee arthroplasty of the traumatology department of the Hospital 12 de Octubre, by means of consecutive sampling. In the scientific literature consulted, we have not exploited the evidence that compares the two interventions used in this study, therefore, by carrying out a previous study to know an approximation of the differences that can be found if they existed. For this reason, it is not possible to estimate the change that can be considered as significant to perform the calculation of the sample size and to be performed first in a study in order to carry out the calculation.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>10/04/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>26/05/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/05/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidad Complutense de Madrid</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>
Universidad Complutense de Madrid. Facultad de enfermeria, fisioterapia y podologia.
 Plaza de Ramon y Cajal, s/n, 28040 Madrid</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidad Complutense de Madrid</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Universidad Complutense de Madrid. 
Facultad de enfermeria, fisioterapia y podologia.
 Plaza de Ramon y Cajal, s/n, 28040 Madrid</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Spain</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The increase in life expectancy in Spain translates into a progressive aging of the population and thus an increase in chronic degenerative joint pathologies such as knee osteoarthrosis, with arthroplasty being the treatment of choice for advanced phases in patients Who have severe pain and disability, and have not benefited from conservative therapy.

Relatively recent evidence suggests that motion-representation techniques may be effective in reducing pain, increasing joint amplitude, and improving the functionality of patients following knee arthroplasty. Motor Imagery (MI) is a technique of motion representation, a process during which an individual mentally simulates a movement or action without its execution, activating the same neural networks that are involved in the real movements, thus improving performance and training new motor skills.

In order to corroborate the effectiveness of MI, a clinical trial pilot study will be conducted with patients aged 60-85 years undergoing total knee arthroplasty. They will be divided into two groups: a first group that will be treated with conventional physiotherapy implemented with MI and a second group where only conventional physiotherapy will be used with blind evaluation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ethics committee of the Hospital 12 October, Madrid</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Avd. de Cordoba s/n 28041, Madrid
Centro de Actividades ambulatorias, bloque D, planta 6a</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>17/072</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Spain</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Maria Briones Cantero</name>
      <address>Indalecio Fernandez 5B, 2B, cp 28041 Madrid.

Hospital Universitario 12 de Octubre, Avd de Cordoba s/n cp 28041</address>
      <phone>+34 913908000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marbri02@ucm.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Maria Briones</name>
      <address>Indalecio Fernandez 5B, 2B, cp 28041 Madrid.

Hospital Universitario 12 de Octubre, Avd de Cordoba s/n cp 28041</address>
      <phone>+34 917792072</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marbri02@ucm.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Maria Briones</name>
      <address>Indalecio Fernandez 5B, 2B, cp 28041 Madrid.

Hospital Universitario 12 de Octubre, Avd de Cordoba s/n cp 28041</address>
      <phone>+34 635470458</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marbri02@ucm.es</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>