<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="27">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/07/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/07/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000019606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A comparison of two models of spirometry in general practice in the identification and prevention of COPD.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A cluster randomised crossover study comparing the efficacy of two models of spirometry provision in general practice on the identification and prevention of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in smokers and ex-smokers over 35 years.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MYLF STUDY</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>New secondary ID. Please modify.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1.Trained nurse provision of spirometry to people aged over 35 at risk of COPD in general practice using a portable electronic spirometer.</interventions>
    <comparator>2. Usual care in practices supplied with a portable electronic spirometer</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of spirometry tests in a six month period.  Acceptability of spirometry to patients and GPs experiences of spirometry provision.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of spirometry in a six month period.  Acceptability of spirometry to patients and GPs experiences of spirometry provision.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Costs of spirometry in a six month period.  Acceptability of spirometry to patients and GPs experiences of spirometry provision.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>New diagnoses of COPD</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post spirometry</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in intention to quit smoking in current smokers with normal or abnormal lung function.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post spirometry</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Smokers and ex-smokers</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable to perform spirometry manoeuvres</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Third party code generation by random numbers</concealment>
    <sequence>Cluster randomisation at practice level, stratification by socio-economc status and geography. Random sequence generation by coin toss.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Longitudinal follow up of current smokers in intervention 1 arm for smoking cessation and intention to quit smoking (stage of change)</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Richard Wood-Baker</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Respiratory Medicine,
Royal Hobart Hospital,
GPO Box 1061L
Hobart, Tasmania, 7001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Tasmania</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Tasmania, 
PO Box 252-34
Hobart Tasmania 7001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>none</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To increase recognition of airflow obstruction in primary care, two models of spirometry delivery in a target group at risk of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) were compared in a  qualitative/quantitative cluster randomised study in eight practices over 6 months; opportunistic spirometry by visiting trained nurses (TN) and optimised usual care (UC). In the eligible target population of smokers and ex-smokers aged over 35 years, 531/904 (59%) patients underwent spirometry in the TN model and 87/ 1130 (8%) patients in the UC model (p,0.0001). ATS spirometry standards for acceptability and reproducibility were met by 76% and 44% of tests in the TN and UC models, respectively (p,0.0001). GPs valued high quality spirometry and increased testing of patients at risk of COPD in the TN model. They identified limitations, including the need for better systematic follow-up of abnormal spirometry and support with interpretation, which may explain persisting underdiagnosis of COPD in practice records. Conclusions: Although opportunistic testing by visiting trained nurses substantially increased and improved spirometry performance compared with usual care, translating increased detection of airflow obstruction into diagnosis of COPD requires further support.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1.	Walters JA, Hansen E, Johns D, Blizzard L, Walters E, Wood-Baker R. A mixed methods study to compare models of spirometry delivery in primary care for patients at risk of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease. Thorax. 2008;63:408-14.
2.	Walters JA, Hansen E, Walters EH, Wood Baker R. Under-diagnosis of Chronic obstructive Pulmonary Disease: a qualitative study in primary care. Respir Med. 2008;102(5):738-43.
3.	Walters J, Johns DP, Blizzard L, Walters EH, Wood-Baker R. Effects of 
4.	feedback on spirometry in primary care on motivation for smoking cessation. Journal of Smoking Cessation. 2009;4(1):34-41.
5.	Walters J, Wood-Baker R, Walls J, Johns D. Stability of the EasyOne ultrasonic spirometer for use in general practice. Respirology. 2006;11(3):306-10.
6.	Walters JA, Hansen E, Mudge P, Johns DP, Walters EH, Wood-Baker R. Barriers to the use of spirometry in general practice. Aust Fam Physician. 2005;34(3):201-3.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Julia Walters</name>
      <address>Menzies Research Institute Tasmania
MS1 UTAS, 17 Liverpool Street,
Private Bag 23, Hobart TAS 7000</address>
      <phone>+61 03 6226 4798</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Julia.Walters@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Julia Walters</name>
      <address>Menzies Research Institute Tasmania
University of Tasmania,
MS1 UTAS, 17 Liverpool Street,
Private Bag 23, Hobart TAS 7000</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62264798</phone>
      <fax>+61 03 6226 7704</fax>
      <email>jaew@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>