<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365184">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001178730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Treating Comorbid Insomnia with Obstructive sleep Apnoea (COMISA) Study: A new treatment strategy for patients with combined insomnia and sleep apnoea.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Treating Comorbid Insomnia with Obstructive Sleep Apnoea (COMISA): A randomised controlled trial evaluating the effectiveness of a new treatment strategy incorporating Cognitive Behaviour Therapy for Insomnia (CBTi) plus treatment as usual for patients with combined insomnia and sleep apnoea </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1149-4230</utrn>
    <trialacronym>COMISA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Insomnia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnoea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is Cognitive Behaviour Therapy for Insomnia (CBTi) plus Treatment As Usual (TAU) for Obstructive Sleep Apnoea. 
Four 1 hour CBTi sessions will occur at weekly intervals in a face-to-face group session of 2 or more participants (depending on recruitment numbers) before starting on Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) therapy at home for 6 months. 
CBTi Session 1: Sleep education - Bedtime Restriction therapy. CBTi Session 2: Misperceptions of sleep - Polysomnograph (PSG) Feedback. CBTi Session 3: Hyperarousal and Anxiety in Insomnia. CBTi Session 4: Review and Relapse Prevention. 
Participants will be asked to keep four 1-week sleep diaries and a record of their thoughts and feelings on sleep. 
Participants receiving CBTi will given a CBTi  Participant Manual which explains the process of sleep and some of the factors which can cause and maintain insomnia and effective treatment and strategies for insomnia. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive Treatment as Usual (CPAP therapy at home for 6 months) for Obstructive Sleep Apnoea only. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CPAP Adherence - the average hours/night of machine use at therapeutic pressure recorded over 6 months. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 3 months and 6 months after start of CBTi.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insomnia - Sleep efficiency measured by home Polysomnography (PSG) at baseline, 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 6 weeks and 6 months.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of the impact of sleep disorders on daily functioning and quality of life as assessed by the Functional Outcomes of Sleep Questionnaire (FOSQ). </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after start of CBTi.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of the perceptions and distress relating to insomnia and impact on the quality of life as measured by the Insomnia Severity Scale (ISI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 4 weeks, 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after start of CBTi. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A self report measure designed to evaluate sleep related cognitions that play a role in perpetuating insomnia as measured by the Dysfunctions Beliefs and Attitudes about Sleep (DBAS-16).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after start of CBTi. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of daytime fatigue associated with insomnia utilising the Flinders Fatigue Scale (FFS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after start of CBTi. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daytime Feelings and Functioning Scale (DFFS) that assesses the frequency of specific daytime deficits commonly reported in insomnia </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after start of CBTi. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health status score, and a preference score that will allow computation of utilities for the estimation of quality adjusted life years (QALYs) within cost effectiveness analysis as measured by the Assessment of Quality of Life Index (AQoL).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after start of CBTi. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A standardised measure of health status at 5 levels of severity in each of the 5 dimensions as measured by the European Quality of Life (EQ-5D-5L) questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after start of CBTi. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Productivity Cost Questionnaire (iMTA PCQ) measures and subsequently values indirect costs arising outside the scope of the healthcare system, also known as productivity costs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 6 weeks, 3 months and 6 months after start of CBTi. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age greater than or equal to18 years of age up to and including 75 years of age. 2. An apnoea/hypopnoea index (AHI) greater than 15 events per hour of sleep by polysomnography (PSG) with clinical diagnosis of OSA confirmed by treating consultant respiratory physician. 3. Recommended by treating sleep physician for CPAP treatment. 4. A diagnosis of Insomnia to ICSD-2 criteria, Insomnia Severity Index Score greater than 13. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Severe daytime sleepiness, or other reason, which in the opinion of the treating physician would cause undue risk to the patients safety during the CBTi treatment period while awaiting CPAP treatment. 
2. Any other sleep disorder (eg REM behaviour disorder, severe restless legs syndrome) which in the opinion of the treating physician is the dominant sleep diagnosis and which requires immediate treatment.   Patients with other medical or psychiatric conditions (e.g. depression &amp; anxiety) will not be excluded, but diagnoses recorded from the patients file for reporting and analysis purposes.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be provided by an independent central allocation service (Pharmacy Department, Repatriation General Hospital) to ensure concealment, documentation and integrity. </concealment>
    <sequence>A minimisation program will stratify treatment allocation by site, severity of insomnia (ISI score &gt; and &lt; 22) and OSA (AHI &gt; and &lt; 30).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All analyses will be conducted on an intention to treat basis, and the trial conducted according to CONSORT guidelines. Missing data will be imputed using multiple imputations. 
All calculations assume an overall Type 1 error rate of 0.05% and a Type 2 error rate of 20%. A total sample of 126 participants (63 per group) provides 80% power to detect an improvement of 1.25 hrs per night in CPAP adherence, based on standard deviations for CPAP use in TAU groups of approximately 2.5 hrs/night. 
Enrollment of 140 participants allows the completion of an adequately powered per protocol analysis assuming a 10% attrition rate, and increases power in the primary ITT analysis to 85%. 
A greater than 1.25 hrs/night in CPAP adherence is expected after CBTi because of increases in sleep efficiency (ie sleep time) and greater overall CPAP treatment acceptance and tolerance; the consensus amongst the participating sleep physicians is that a change of less than 1.25 hrs/night is unlikely to be clinically significant. 
A 5% change in PSG-derived sleep efficiency is considered clinically significant and the minimum expected from other CBTi trials. The sample of 140 provides 80% power to detect this difference assuming a standard deviation in the order of 7.5. For ISI there is 80% power to detect difference of 3.4 ISI units groups (moderate clinical change in ISI is approx 8.5), assuming a standard deviation in the order of 5.
The sample size gives 80% power to detect a change of 8.6 FOSQ units ( typical moderate change is approx 12 units) assuming a standard deviation of change of 18.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>29/04/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>140</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>145</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>13/01/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>Repatriation Hospital - Daw Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <postcode>5041 - Daw Park</postcode>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Doug McEvoy</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health
Repatriation General Hospital - Block C
Daws Road
Daw Park SA 5041</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>1. To conduct a randomized controlled trial of Cognitive Behaviour Therapy for insomnia (CBTi) in patients with co-morbid Obstructive sleep Apnoea (OSA) and insomnia to establish whether CBTi therapy improves Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) adherence and sleep-related patient outcomes.
2. To explore whether insomnia and OSA are causally inter-related.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.adelaidesleephealth.org.au/</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flinders Medical Centre
The Flats G5  Rooms 3 and 4
Flinders Drive,
Bedford Park
SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>428.12</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/11/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland University of Technology Research Ethics Unit</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4 
88 Musk Avenue 
Kelvin Grove  
Queensland 4059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1300000302</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Doug McEvoy</name>
      <address>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health
Repatriation General Hospital - Block C
Daws Road
Daw Park
SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751187</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82776890</fax>
      <email>doug.mcevoy@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mandy O'Grady</name>
      <address>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health
Repatriation General Hospital - Block C
Daws Road
Daw Park
SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751301</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82776890</fax>
      <email>amanda.o'grady@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Doug McEvoy</name>
      <address>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health
Repatriation General Hospital - Block C
Daws Road
Daw Park
SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751187</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82776890</fax>
      <email>doug.mcevoy@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mandy O'Grady</name>
      <address>Adelaide Institute for Sleep Health
Repatriation General Hospital - Block C
Daws Road
Daw Park
SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751301</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82776890</fax>
      <email>amanda.o'grady@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>