<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83617">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/02/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000437268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of a self-paced intervention to increase distance walked and decrease admissions to hospital in people with heart failure</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of a modified, self-administered six minute walk test to improve health related outcomes in people with symptomatic heart failure</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will undergo baseline assessment including a standardised six munite walk test, heart rate assessment, blood pressure measurement and questionnaires to assess functional status and self-efficacy. All participants will receive an information session from a cardiac nurse identifying the importance of self-management. They will also be given an action plan and the National Heart Foundation Consumer Resource Guide, which are part of the routine care provided by the Area Health Service. Both the intervention and control groups will receive monthly telephone follow-up for six months.  Participants in the intervention group will undertake The Home-Heart-Walk program. This  is a self-administered, modified six minute walkexercise activity. Participants will be instructed to undertake the Home-Heart-Walk at least weekly for six months at their own home, using the provided "home kit", that includes a 5-metres long rope, a digital count down timer, a lap counter and a study diary. 
To undertake the Home-Heart-Walk participants will be instructed to walk alongside the 5-metre rope (marked in 1-metre gradations with the numbers 0-5) on a flat, hard surface, free of obstacles while trying to cover as much distance as possible in 6 minutes. Stopping and resting will be allowed during the walk. Encouragement will not be used during the walk. Participants will also use the lap counter to count how many full laps they have walked. At the end of the 6 minutes, participants will be asked to record how many full laps they have walked, and at which number they stopped at the end of the walk. This is to allow calculation of the distance walked during the 6 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group: standard heart failure management and monthly telephone follow-up for six months (regarding self-management in the context of participant's condition) standard heart failure management from Area Health Service includes home visits and telephone follow-up. The frequency and length of home visits and telephone follow-up is determined by individuals clinical needs.
Participants from both groups will undertake baseline assessment, including the six-minute walk Test and receive an information session from a cardiac nurse identifying the importance of self-management. They will also be given an action plan and the National Heart Foundation Consumer Resource Guide, which are part of the routine care provided by the Area Health Service..</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient perceived health related quality of life measured by the Medical Outcomes Study Short Form 36</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Distance walked on a standard 6 minute walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Enropean Heart Failure self-care Behaviour Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity level measured by the National Physical Activity Prescription Scale which is a self-administered test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bandura's Exercise Self-efficacy Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Minnesota Living with Heart Failure Questionnaire will assess the impact of heart failure on health related quality of life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major acute cardiovascular events (MACE) includes death, non-fatal acute myocardial infarction and acute coronary syndrome events as well as planned and unplanned revascularisation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 month and 6 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All cause hospitalisation</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Hospitalised for heart failure within the previous 6 months. 
New York Heart Association-Functional Calss II or III</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unstable angina pectoris.
Recent unexplained syncope.
Failure to give informed consent.
Resting heart rate greater than 120.
Inability to perform the six minute walk test (6MWT) (e.g. severe arthritis)
Significant cognitive impairment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Research personnel will fax the newly recurited participant's name and date of birth, from the recuritement site, to an administrative officer at the Centre for Cardiovascular and Chronic Care, for randomisation.These codes will be stored securely in the Centre for Cardiovascular and Chronic Care and accessible by an office manager who is not involved in conduct of the trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a computer generated sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>166</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2010</postcode>
    <postcode>2770</postcode>
    <postcode>2148</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>39 Regent Street
Chippendale
NSW 2008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Health and Ageing</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Primary &amp; Ambulatory Care Division, Department of Health, GPO Box 9848 Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>St Vincents Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Victoria Street Darlinghurst NSW 2010</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronic heart failure is a common and debilitating condition and most commonly occurs in the elderly. Although physical activity is part of recommended self-management plans, older, community dwelling individuals find this challenging. We have developed a program, based on the well-validated six minute walk test, which not only provides the structure and motivation for the individual to undertake physical activity but also generates a measurement that can be used by patients and clinicians alike to monitor their functional status. In addition, this model of intervention will provide structured telephone follow-up to promote adherence to the treatment principles. This study will use a randomized controlled trail design to test if the Home-Heart-Walk program can improve self-management through increasing the participants self-efficacy for physical activity and their functional status and health related quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>390 Victoria St 
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/09/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/08/0077</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Patricia Davidson</name>
      <address>Centre for Cardiovascular and Chronic Care, Curtin University
39 Regent Street, 
Chippendate, 
NSW 2008</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83997831</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 83997834</fax>
      <email>p.davidson@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Patricia Davidson</name>
      <address>Centre for Cardiovascular and Chronic Care, Curtin University
39 Regent Street, 
Chippendate, 
NSW 2008</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83997831</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 83997834</fax>
      <email>p.davidson@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Patricia Davidson</name>
      <address>Centre for Cardiovascular and Chronic Care
Curtin University
39 Regent street
Chippendale
NSW 2008</address>
      <phone>+61 2 83997831</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 83997834</fax>
      <email>p.davidson@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>