<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365349">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001313729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The ASPREE NEURO study: Does daily, low dose aspirin in adults aged 70 years and over affect age related changes in brain small blood vessels seen on MRI over time, and do these changes improve prediction of stroke risk or cognitive decline?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The ASPREE NEURO study: Does daily, low dose aspirin in adults aged 70 years and over affect age related changes in brain small blood vessels seen on MRI over time, and do these changes improve prediction of stroke risk or cognitive decline?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1150-6183</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ASPREE NEURO Sub-study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral Microhaemorrhage (CMH)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>White matter Hyperintensity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive Decline</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is a sub-study of the Aspirin in Reducing Events in the Elderly study (ASPREE, ClinicalTrials.gov identifier NCT01038583, website www.aspree.org). ASPREE is a double blinded, randomised controlled trial of low dose aspirin, 100mg oral tablets versus placebo, taken daily for a mean of five years in healthy participants aged 70 and over, followed over a mean of five years for the primary outcomes of dementia-free survival and disability-free survival. It is a primary prevention study. 

The ASPREE NEURO substudy will involve a subset of newly enrolling participants in the parent ASPREE study based in Melbourne. At the ASPREE randomisation visit ASPREE participants will be given information on the ASPREE NEURO substudy and will later be screened for any contraindication to MRI. 

Participants will undergo a non contrast 3 Tesla brain MRI early after entry into the ASPREE study, and again at year 3. The MRI study will include T1 and T2 weighted images, diffusion weighted imaging and SWI. 

Participants will now also be invited to undergo an additional non contrast 3 Tesla Brain MRI, utilising the same MRI protocol, 1 year after their baseline image. </interventions>
    <comparator>The constituents of the placebo tablets are: calcium hydrogen phosphate dehydrate, cellulose (microcrystalline), citric acid anhydrous, lactose monohydrate, magnesium stearate, maize starch and silica (colloidal anhydrous).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Cerebral microhaemorrhage on brain MRI</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Haemorrhagic and ischaemic stroke. This is an outcome measured through the parent ASPREE study. The diagnosis of stroke is confirmed by review of medical records and adjudicated by a stroke endpoint adjudication committee.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Volume of white matter hyperintensity on brain MRI</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive Function as measured through the parent ASPREE study. This outcome is assessed using the Modified Minimental State Test (3MS), Hopkins Verbal Learning Test (HVLT), Symbol Digit Modalities Test (SDMT), Controlled Oral Word Association Test (COWAT), Stroop and Colour Trails</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of cerebral microhaemorrhages on brain MRI </outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Enrolling into the ASPREE study in Melbourne
Aged 70 and over
Able and willing to provide informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>70</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria for ASPREE: History of diagnosed cardiovascular event, including MI and stroke, atrial fibrillation, serious intercurrent illness likely to cause death within 5 years, cognitive impairment or dementia, disability, anaemia, a current or recurrent condition with a high risk of major bleeding, absolute contradindication or allergy to aspirin.

Additional exclusion criteria for this study: Any contraindication to MRI scanning (e.g. implanted pacemaker, presence of metal in eye, claustrophobia, cerebral aneurysm clip).  
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrollment into the parent study ASPREE is through general practitioner co-investigators. Informed consent for participation in ASPREE is obtained by ASPREE research staff. Enrollment into the ASPREE NEURO study takes place at the second baseline ASPREE visit, after randomisation but prior to initiation of study medication of either aspirin or placebo in ASPREE. 

Randomisation takes place through the parent ASPREE study. All staff remain blinded to treatment allocation through the randomisation procedure.

The randomisation list is generated by an independent statistician using the STATA "ralloc" procedure with randomisation stratified for site and age (&lt;80 yrs and &gt;80yrs). </concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation list is generated by an independent statistician using the STATA "ralloc" procedure with randomsiation stratified for site and age (&lt;80 yrs and &gt;80 yrs). </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Power calculations for the ASPREE NEURO study have been based on ensuring a sufficient number of subjects to test the primary hypothesis that the number of cerebral microhaemorrhage (CMH) in the aspirin treated group at 3 year follow-up will be greater than the number of CMH in the placebo treated group. 

Sample size calculations are based on our pilot study data in which the standard deviation for the number of CMH was found to be approximately 1.5 units. Therefore, 235 subjects per group will enable a 95% power to detect a difference equal to one third of a standard deviation with a two sided p-value of 0.05. While the standard deviation in the number of CMH at 3 years is unknown, it is anticipated to be higher than at 12 months. Based on an estimated standard deviation of 2, a total of 504 subjects (252 per group) will enable an 80% power to detect a difference equal to one quarter of a standard deviation with a two sided p-value of 0.05. In anticipation that the distribution for the number of CMH will not follow a normal distribution, these numbers have been inflated by 15% in accordance with Lehmann and further inflated by 5% to account for dropout, loss to follow-up or cross-over. 

With 606 subjects, this study will have &gt;95% power to detect a difference between low dose aspirin and placebo in the average number of CMH at 12 months equal to one half of one unit of CMH, with a two sided p-value of 0.05 and &gt;80% power to detect the same difference after 3 years. A difference of this magnitude is perceived to be of clinical importance.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>6/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>6/01/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>559</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>6/01/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3800 - Monash University</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wellington Road,
Clayton,
Victoria, 3800</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Wellington Road,
Clayton,
Victoria, 3800</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Changes to the small cerebral blood vessels are commonly obeserved on brain MRIs of the elderly. Two common changes observed are cerebral microhaemorrhages (CMH), which have been reported in 10-60% of healthy elderly subjects, and areas of white matter hyperintensity (WHI). The clinical significance of CMH remains uncertain, though there is a possibility they could predipose to later, clinically overt, haemorrhages.

There have been mixed reports, derived from cross-sectional and longitudinal studies, on whether long-term low-dose aspirin increases the risk of CMH but this has not been evaluated in the context of a clinical trial.

This study will investigate whether daily low dose aspirin increases the number of CMH after one and three years, as measured on brain MRI, as well as determine whether daily low dose aspirin changes the volume of WHI over the same time period, whether the presence of CMH on MRI at baseline is associated with subsequent incidence of ischaemic and haemorrhagic stroke and cognitive decline, and will also correlate imaging biomarkers measured with MRI with cognitive and clinical outcomes over three years. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.aspree.org/AUS/aspree-content/aspree-sub-studies/ASPREE-NEURO.aspx</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Ward SA, Raniga P, Ferris NJ, Woods RL, Storey E, Bailey MJ, Brodtmann A,
Yates PA, Donnan GA, Trevaks RE, Wolfe R, Egan GF, McNeil JJ; (Joint Senior
authorship); on behalf of the ASPREE investigator group.. ASPREE-NEURO study
protocol: A randomized controlled trial to determine the effect of low-dose
aspirin on cerebral microbleeds, white matter hyperintensities, cognition, and
stroke in the healthy elderly. Int J Stroke. 2016 Sep 15. pii: 1747493016669848. 
[Epub ahead of print] PubMed PMID: 27634976.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash University
Level 1, Building 3e, Clayton Campus
Wellington Rd
Clayton VIC 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec> CF12/2271 – 2012001223</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John McNeil</name>
      <address>Department of Epidemiology and Preventive Medicine
School of Public Health
Monash University
Level 6, The Alfred Centre
Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria, 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 03 99030565</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john.mcneil@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Robyn Woods</name>
      <address>ASPREE National Coordinating Centre
Ground Floor
Burnet Building
89 Commercial Rd
Melbourne, Victoria 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 03 99030345</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robyn.woods@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Robyn Woods</name>
      <address>ASPREE National Coordinating Centre
Ground Floor
Burnet Building
89 Commercial Rd
Melbourne, Victoria 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 03 99030345</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robyn.woods@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stephanie Ward</name>
      <address>ASPREE National Coordinating Centre
Ground Floor
Burnet Building
89 Commercial Rd
Melbourne, Victoria 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 03 99030345</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stephanie.ward@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>