<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364422">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000984796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The relative efficacy of codeine 60mg four times daily in improving analgesia for patients following mandibular third molar surgery when augmented to paracetamol 1000mg four times daily and ibuprofen 400mg three times daily: a pilot, double-blind randomized control trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients who have had mandibular wisdom teeth surgically removed, does the addition of codeine 60mg four times daily to paracetamol 1000mg four times daily and ibuprofen 400mg three times daily, compared to paracetamol 1000mg four times daily and ibuprofen 400mg three times daily alone, improve pain relief?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1142-1254</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Postoperative pain following mandibular third molar surgery.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention group: 
paracetamol 1000mg four times daily (qid) + ibuprofen 400mg three times daily (tds) + codeine phosphate 60mg qid.
Mode of administration is oral. 
Duration of intervention is 48 hours following surgery.
Participants will be asked regarding their adherence to the prescribed drug regime as part of the post-operative questionnaire on day 3 following surgery.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group: 
paracetamol 1000mg qid + ibuprofen 400mg tds + placebo.
Mode of administration is oral. 
Duration of intervention is 48 hours following surgery.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of pain.  Measured using:
1) a visual analogue scale (VAS);
2) by means of a participant questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each participant records their pain level on a VAS immediately before surgery, shortly after surgery (prior to leaving hospital), and then following surgery every 3 hours for the first 48 hours during awake hours.  Each participant also fills out a questionnaire regarding level of pain prior to surgery and also on day 3 following surgery.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The patient must be aged 17 years or over. 
There will be no discrimination (e.g. gender; race; ethnicity).  Moreover, non-English speaking people will not be excluded; an accredited interpreter will be employed per required need.
Patient participation is entirely voluntary.
Patients must have been seen by a consultant oral and maxillofacial surgeon at the    
University of Otago, or by one of their oral and maxillofacial surgery trainees, and be 
deemed appropriate for participation in the present study by this clinician.
The patient must legitimately require at least the removal of one or both of their mandibular third molars.
Expected bone removal for extraction of the mandibular third molar(s).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>17</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients under 17 years of age are not eligible for participation in this research project.  This is to provide a safeguard around the level of drug doses used.

The patient must not have any of the following conditions or reasons which contraindicate or caution the use of paracetamol, ibuprofen, or codeine, as described in the latest edition of MIMS New Ethicals:
Anyone who needs to drive a motor vehicle or operate machinery within the 48 hour period following surgery   
NSAID-sensitive asthma 
Active gastrointestinal bleeding or ulceration 
Bleeding disorder 
Patients on anticoagulants P
Renal impairment 
Hepatic impairment 
Cardiovascular disease 
Systemic lupus erythematosus 
Patients on hepatic enzyme inducers (e.g. certain anticonvulsants) 
Pregnancy and lactation 
Respiratory depression; COPD 
Raised intracranial pressure 
Alcoholism 
Opioid addiction 
Patients on CNS depressants 
G-6-PD deficiency 
Hypersensitivity to morphine 

Furthermore, the patient must not have any of the following conditions or reasons which contraindicate or caution the use of midazolam or dexamethasone, as described in the latest edition of MIMS New Ethicals:
Hypersensitivity to benzodiazepines 
Myasthenia gravis 
Glaucoma 
Systemic viral, bacterial, or fungal infection 
Osteoporosis 
Psychosis 

Finally, the patient must not have a contraindication to either intravenous sedation or general anaesthetic.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will enrol at the School of Dentistry via routine enrolment procedures in order to receive treatment.  Subjects who choose to participate in the study are seen in the Department of Oral Diagnostic and Surgical Sciences and enrol in the study by filling out a written consent form.
Allocation concealment procedures is by sealed opaque envelopes.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation). </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Data upon which to undertake a power analysis are scarce.  However, for an anticipated effect size of 0.5, an a value of 0.05 and a power of 0.8 to detect a difference, the estimated number per group is 51. 
That is, 102 human subjects divided into two groups:
	Control group:	 	51 participants
	Intervention group:  	51 participants
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>102</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Head of the Department of Oral Diagnostic and Surgical Sciences </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Dentistry, University of Otago, PO Box 647, Dunedin 9054.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Oral Diagnostic and Surgical Sciences, of the School of Dentistry, at the University of Otago. </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Faculty of Dentistry, University of Otago, PO Box 647, Dunedin 9054, New Zealand.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Health Research South (University of Otago)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Health Research South
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The proposed study aims to determine whether codeine pain relief medication is necessary in addition to paracetamol and ibuprofen pain relief medications following wisdom teeth surgery.  This study, therefore, may prove beneficial to dentists, oral surgeons, and oral-and-maxillofacial surgeons, and ultimately to their patients, in regard to postoperative pain management for wisdom teeth surgery.  For example, if the proposed study demonstrates that codeine is not a statistically significant supplement to the paracetamol ibuprofen combination for adequate pain relief following wisdom teeth surgery, then patients may benefit by not being unnecessarily subjected to the risk of greater side effects associated with codeine.  Conversely, the study may find that codeine is indeed statistically significant, thereby providing clinicians with scientific evidence that in order to attain adequate pain relief after wisdom teeth surgery it is advisable to add codeine to the paracetamol ibuprofen regime.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/STH/35</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room: G22  Clocktower Building
University of Otago
Dunedin 9054</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/080</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Rohana De Silva</name>
      <address>Department of Oral Diagnostic and Surgical Sciences
Faculty of Dentistry
PO Box 647
University of Otago
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7036</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rohana.kumara@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Rohana De Silva</name>
      <address>Department of Oral Diagnostic and Surgical Sciences
Faculty of Dentistry
PO Box 647
University of Otago
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7036</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rohana.kumara@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Rohana De Silva</name>
      <address>Department of Oral Diagnostic and Surgical Sciences
Faculty of Dentistry
PO Box 647
University of Otago
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7036</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rohana.kumara@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>