<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366920">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000912684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Establishing a dose of exercise tolerated by stroke survivors with walking impairment: A phase 1 dose-escalation trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Maximum dose of exercise tolerated by stroke survivors with walking impairment, after a 12 week multimodal exercise program.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Walking impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study intervention was a 12 week multimodal exercise program, three sessions each week. Sessions were individual run by a rehabilitation physiotherapist at the participating hospital. The first 4 weeks were 360 min per week, next 4 weeks 420 min per week, last 4 weeks (dose Maximization) was guided by cumulative 3+3 dose escalation design aiming to go up to 750 min per week. A description and examples of the types of exercises are;

Endurance training was delivered using a combination of cycling, treadmill and over-ground walking. Endurance training time was planned to progress by 5-15% every week. We aimed for a moderate level of training intensity, with the Borg Rate of Perceived Exertion (RPE) =11. Most endurance activities used steady state training, with interval training added for variety and when RPE levels dropped below 11. Planned interval training included a variety of regimes with a set time at a higher effort (on) followed by low effort recovery (off), e.g., 4 minutes on:2 minutes off, 3 minutes on:3 minutes off.

Progressive Resistance Training (PRT) followed a standardized format. Five lower limb strengthening exercises, with free weights or pin-loaded machine weights, were tailored to each participant. Exercises included single or double leg press, calf press, hip abduction, hip extension, hamstring curls and quadriceps over fulcrum. Variation in the weight, number of sets, repetitions and speed of contractions were modified to vary the training stimulus. Amount of weight was increased if the target repetition maximum was achieved. During the Dose-maximization phase participants performed HVPRT, which involves rapid concentric, followed by slower eccentric, muscle contractions.
Task-related practice was integral to the program, with emphasis on activities that challenged balance and community walking ability. Stepping and walking progressions included obstacle clearance of the lead and trail legs, variable surfaces, gradients, speed and direction changes, external perturbations, changing environmental demands and dual tasks.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The amount of exercise (as measured in total number of minutes) participants were able to complete per week during the Dose-maximization phase without reaching the dose limiting criteria (DLT). DLT thresholds were: (1) failure to complete more than 20% of prescribed weekly exercise dose due to pain, fatigue or effort required  (e.g., if the weekly dose was 540 minutes, &gt;432 minutes must be completed), and (2) the after effects of exercise resulted in the participant being unable to perform usual activities of daily living. This was established by a single question each training day. </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of 12 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Six minute walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of 12 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>four square step test</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of 12 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Timed up and go test</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of the 12 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged at least 18 years with impaired balance, limited community walking and considered at risk of falls. They must at discharge from our hospital also meet the following criteria: (1) walking less than 250 metres for the Six Minute Walk Test, (2) taking at least 15 seconds (or unable) to complete the Four Square Step Test, (3) cognitively able to follow an exercise program (equal to a score of 4 on the FIM19 problem solving, memory and comprehension items), (4) living at home, and (5) between 1 to 5 years post-stroke.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>To be eligible, written medical clearance to participate in an exercise program was required.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/09/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>9</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Florey Institute of Neuroscience and Mental Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>245 Burgundy st Heidelberg, VIC 3089</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Stroke Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 7, 461 Bourke Street
Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Stroke survivors with poor balance and walking impairments have low activity levels and are at risk of falls. Targeted exercise can improve mobility.
However, the absence of dose-finding studies may explain the limited effects of exercise delivered in many trials. In this dose-escalation study, we tested the feasibility of using dose-escalation methods, common in Phase 1 pharmaceutical trials, to determine the maximum tolerable dose of exercise in chronic stroke survivors with substantial mobility impairment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Austin Health
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg
Victoria
Australia, 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H2013/04973</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Julie Bernhardt</name>
      <address>Florey Institute of Neuroscience and Mental Health
Melbourne Brain Center
245 Burgundy st Heidelberg
Victoria, 3089</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 7072</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.bernhardt@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Wayne Dite</name>
      <address>Royal Talbot Rehabilitation Centre
1 Yarra Boulevard
Kew
Victoria
Australia 3101</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9490 7500</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Wayne.DITE@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Julie Bernhardt</name>
      <address>Florey Institute of Neuroscience and Mental Health
Melbourne Brain Centre
245 Burgundy st Heidelberg, VIC, 3089</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 7072</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.bernhardt@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Audrey Raffelt</name>
      <address>Florey Institute of Neuroscience and Mental Health
Melbourne Brain Centre
245 Burgundy st Heidelberg, VIC, 3089</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90357267</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>audrey.raffelt@florey.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>