<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367174">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001132639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A phase II study for treatment of proteinuria in patients currently on irbesartan therapy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open label, Phase II dose escalation and expansion study to evaluate the safety and efficacy of propagermanium (PPG) added to stable angiotensin receptor blocker therapy (irbesartan) for the treatment of patients with proteinuria</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1162-3355</utrn>
    <trialacronym>DMX-200</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Proteinuria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is propagermanium, which is an oral capsule taken once daily. Participants must be taking irbesartan.  There are two parts to the trial Part A (dose escalation) and Part B (dose expansion phase). Patients completing Part A may enter Part B after a 3 month wash out period. New patients are also eligible for Part B.

Duration of exposure in Part A (dose escalation):
In Part A, each patient receives increasing doses every 4 weeks (30mg, 60mg, 90mg, 150mg, 240mg per day) until normalisation of proteinuria. Once proteinuria is within the normal range the current dose becomes that patients final dose, and the patient will remain on their final dose for up to a further 8 weeks. The exposure period ranges from 84 days (if proteinuria is normalised at 30mg) though to 168 days (if a patient is escalated through all doses to the maximal dose).  Additionally, there is a screening period ranging from 14 to 42 days and a follow-up period of 28 days where the participant is not exposed to propagermanium.

Duration of exposure in Part B (dose expansion):
In Part B the duration of exposure is 84 days. The dose in part B is chosen by principle investigators as the clinically significant dose. To aid with the dose choice, the statistician will provide the PIs with the average dose required to achieve normalised proteinuria in part A.  Additionally, there is a screening period ranging from 14 to 42 days and a follow-up period of 28 days where the participant is not exposed to propagermanium.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the safety and tolerability of propagermanium when added to standard irbesartan treatment in patients with proteinuria as assessed by laboratory evaluations, physical examinations and the incidence and severity of AEs throughout the study. Known/possible adverse events for irbesartan and propgermanium include vertigo, loss of strength, fatigue, skin rash, itchiness and loss of appetite for food (common) high blood potassium levels, jaundice, muscle and joint pain (infrequent) and abnormalities in liver and renal function tests (rare). Patients will be assessed by telephone each week they don't visit the clincic for general health and well being. At each visit (every 4 weeks) the patients will have a physical examination for the following body symptoms: General Appearance, Respiratory, Skin  (inc. rashes), Cardiovascular, Eyes, Abdomen/ Gastrointestinal, Ears/Nose/ Throat, Musculoskeletal, Head and Neck /Thyroid, Extremities.  Physical measurements will include blood pressure (BP), electrocardiogram (ECG), temperature, height, weight, and respiratory rates. The BP, ECG, thermometer, and scales are calibrated automated digital devices. The panel of evaluations  from blood and urine samples which will be taken at each visit are:
 1. Liver Function and Enzymes:  AST, ALT, GGT, LDH, Alkaline phosphatase, Total Bilirubin, Total protein, Albumin
2. Electrolytes: sodium, potassium, calcium, phosphate, chloride, bicarbonate, magnesium 
3. Metabolic &amp; Lipids:   HbA1c
4. Renal function: creatinine, BUN, uric acid, eGFR, cystatin C.
5. Haematology: Haemoglobin, Haematocrit, Red cell count, Mean Cell volume, White cell count, platelet count
Mid Stream Urine samples:
1. Chemical examination: pH: Protein: Glucose: Ketones: Blood: Leukocyte Esterase: Nitrite: Bilirubin:
2. The microscopic examination Red Blood Cells: White Blood Cells: Epithelial Cells: Casts: Bacteria: Crystals
24-hour urine samples:
1. Quantification of protein and albumin  calculation of PCR and ACR
2. Urinary Biomarkers:  Urinary albumin excretion, Urinary protein excretion, urinary PCR, MCP-1, IL-6, IL-8, TGF-beta, CTGF fibrotic growth factor, NGAL. 
The test results and observations on examination will be used by the clinician to determine the safety of the therapy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>In both part A and part B, physical examination and laboratory variables are measured each visit whilst they are in the study. The participants general well-being is measured weekly, either at during a study visit or via the telephone. 

For part A the duration is dependent on time each participant requires to reach their final dose, with all participants starting on 30mg with incremental increase each month to a maximum dose of 240mg (study period range 98 to 224days). In part B the participants will be in the trial for a total of 126 days (assuming the minimum screening time).
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the effects of propagermanium on urinary protein biomarkers when added to standard irbesartan in patients with proteinuria, as assessed by measurement of change in urine protein/creatinine ratio (PCR), albumin excretion, urine protein excretion, and albumin creatinine ration (ACR).</outcome>
      <timepoint>The participant will have blood and urine tests to measure protein biomarkers every 28 days whilst they are in the trial. For part A the duration is dependent on time each participant requires to reach their final dose, with all participants starting on 30mg with incremental increase each month to a maximum dose of 240mg (study period range 98 to 224days). In part B the participants will be in the trial for a total of 126 days (assuming the minimum 14 days screening).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the effects of propagermanium on urinary biomarkers of inflammation when added to standard irbesartan in patients with proteinuria. The biomarkers measured are MCP-1, IL-6, IL-8, TGF-beta, CTGF fibrotic growth factor and NGAL.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The participant will have urine tests to measure biomarkers of inflammation every 28 days whilst they are in the trial. For part A the duration is dependent on time each participant requires to reach their final dose, with all participants starting on 30mg with incremental increase each month to a maximum dose of 240mg (study period range 98 to 224days). In part B the participants will be in the trial for a total of 126 days (assuming the minimum 14 days screening).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the effects of propagermanium on serum biomarkers when added to standard irbesartan in patients with proteinuria as assessed by measurement of serum creatinine.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The participant will have blood tests to measure serum creatinine every 28 days whilst they are in the trial. For part A the duration is dependent on time each participant requires to reach their final dose, with all participants starting on 30mg with incremental increase each month to a maximum dose of 240mg (study period range 98 to 224days). In part B the participants will be in the trial for a total of 126 days (assuming the minimum 14 days screening).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the effects of propagermanium on plasma concentration of irbesartan, when added to standard irbesartan in patients with proteinuria as assessed by measurement of plasma levels of PPG and Irbesartan at a single collection time point every 4 weeks throughout the trial.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The participant will have blood tests to measure the concentration of PPG and irbesartan in the plasma every 28 days whilst they are in the trial. For part A the duration is dependent on time each participant requires to reach their final dose, with all participants starting on 30mg with incremental increase each month to a maximum dose of 240mg (study period range 98 to 224days). In part B the participants will be in the trial for a total of 126 days (assuming the minimum 14 days screening).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Capable of providing informed consent.
Women of child bearing potential or men of reproductive potential must be using adequate birth control measures.
Previously diagnosed with protein in the urine and have a protein/creatinine ratio (PCR) of greater than 50 (mg/mmol) based on 24 hour urine collection.
Patients with a defined level of kidney function as follows:
- serum creatinine 115 to 291 micromol/L inclusive for women
- serum creatinine 132 to 309 micromol/L inclusive for men
- or estimated GFR 20-60
Taking stable irbesartan with BP in range of 110/70 to 150/95 mmHg. (Stable is defined as taking the same dose of IRB for at least 90 days prior to baseline). 
Liver function tests less than or equal to 2X upper limit of normal
Patients taking a diuretic must be on a stable dose for at least 2 months.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Rapidly progressing proteinuria (rapidly progressing is defined as a trebling of proteinuria over the preceding 3 month period)
Recent gastrointestinal bleeding
Heart disease that is not considered stable
Acute kidney injury within the 3 months before screening
Are receiving any ACE inhibitor, NSAID therapy or spironolactone
Have uncontrolled blood pressure
Required to take drugs that change the immune system (immunosupressants)
HIV infection
Viral Hepatitis B or C, liver infection, liver cirrhosis or any clinically significant liver damage. (Liver function tests &gt; 2X ULN)
Cancer within 3 years (excluding non melanoma skin cancer) or high risk of developing cancer
Major surgery within 3 months of screening or planned during the study period.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed, all patients fall within the intention to treat group</concealment>
    <sequence>no randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>In Part A each patient has the dose escalated until normalisation of their proteinuria is determined. That patient is then continued on the same dose for up to 8 weeks.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is an exploratory open label, non-randomised observational pharmacological study and as such formal sample size calculations have not been conducted. The total number of up to 60 patients is considered a suitable size to characterise the effect of the drug on reduction in proteinuria.
The analysis sets will be (1) Intent to treat population, (2) Safety population and (3) Efficacy Population. Demographic and Baseline variables will be described by statistical characteristics. Descriptive analyses will be presented for the intention-to-treat population, safety and efficacy population. Primary safety variables will be extent of exposure, adverse events and clinical laboratory evaluations.The study endpoints will be described using statistical characteristics. Categorical data will be described by frequency and percentage; Continuous data will be described by mean, standard deviation, minimum, 1st quartile, median, 3rd quartile and maximum. Also the number of missing and non-missing values will be given.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Reservoir Private Hospital Day Procedure Centre - Reservoir</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill Central</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Royal Melbourne Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>3073 - Reservoir</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dimerix Bioscience Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suite 5, 95 Hay St, Subiaco WA 6008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dimerix Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 5, 95 Hay St, Subiaco WA 6008</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is to investigate the safety and tolerability of propagermanium on patients exhibiting proteinuria and who are already taking standard irbesartan therapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Austin Hospital
145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg
Victoria 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/Austin/296</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Power</name>
      <address>Nephrology
Austin Health
Austin Hospital
145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg
Victoria 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 5634</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 5123</fax>
      <email>David.POWER@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James Williams</name>
      <address>Dimerix Bioscience Limited
PO Box 24231
Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 409 050 519</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>james@dimerix.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James Williams</name>
      <address>Dimerix Bioscience Limited
PO Box 24231
Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 409 050 519</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>james@dimerix.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kathy Harrison</name>
      <address>Dimerix Bioscience Pty Ltd PO Box 24231 Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 419 359 149</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kathy.harrison@dimerix.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>