<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363765">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000245796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Self-management and Multiple Sclerosis: The impact of a community-based exercise and education program</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot randomised controlled trial investigating the effectiveness and feasibility of a self-management community group program (MANAGE) for improving mobility in Multiple Sclerosis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1139-8360</utrn>
    <trialacronym>MANAGE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention participants will attend a 12 week program twice a week, consisting of twice weekly group exercise (60 minutes duration each) and once weekly education sessions (60 minutes duration) for six weeks, based at the Physiotherapy Department. Their exercise program will be individually-tailored after a physiotherapy assessment. In week 7 participants will complete their twice weekly group exercise sessions at a community gym. In week 8 participants will be accompanied to a local community exercise option, chosen in the first 6 weeks, with a hospital based health professional. They will be supported to attend this option for a minimum of once weekly for the remainder of the program (weeks 9-12) with support from hospital and trained community exercise location staff. The education sessions will cover principles of self-management, redefining problems,  goal setting, facilitators to exercise, solutions to exercise barriers, strategies to manage fatigue &amp; exercise, and community resources. The education sessions will be facilitated by a physiotherapist and an exercise physiologist in a group setting with 6 participants. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be a waitlist control group. They will continue with no treatment and will attend assessment sessions only. This group will be offered the opportunity to participate in a program after study completion.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking speed as measured with then 10 metre walk test with a minimal detectable change of 0.1 metres per second.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 24 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking endurance as measured with the 6 minute walk test </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 24 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Standing balance as measured with the functional reach test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 24 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue as measured by the Fatigue Severity Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 24 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Broad impact of Multiple Sclerosis as measured by the Multiple Sclerosis Impact Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 24 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived benefits and barriers to exercise as measured by the Exercise Benefits and Barriers Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 weeks, 12 weeks, 24 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity levels via self-report for the week prior to assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 24 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Multiple Sclerosis diagnosed by medical practitioner, Extended Disability Status Scale (EDSS) 0-6.5 (i.e. at a minimum be able to walk 20m with bilateral support), reside within RMH RPC Community Therapy Service catchment area, and currently not receiving or wait-listed for outpatient therapy.

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Medically unstable (e.g. unstable cardiovascular disease or uncontrolled seizures) or other medical condition that would preclude participation in the program or confound results of the trial (e.g. severe arthritis, amputation or other neurological disorder).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The MS clinic register at the RMH Royal Park Campus will be screened for potential eligible participants. Potential participants will be contacted by telephone utilising a standardised script to ascertain interest in study participation. Informed consent will be obtained from participants at the baseline assessment. Following baseline assessment, participants will be randomly allocated to intervention or usual care group using an electronic randomisation schedule managed by a clinician not involved in the research. Allocation will be concealed from the blinded assessor.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated simple randomisation into intervention or usual care group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Baseline characteristics and feasibility data will be summarised using descriptive statistics and groups will be compared with respect to demographic and prognostic factors using Independent t-tests or Mann-Whitney-U tests. Repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) will be used to compare changes over time and between group comparisons of changes in the primary and secondary outcome measures. Descriptive statistics will be used to summarise the characteristics of any drop outs and to analyse feasibility outcomes. The level of significance will be set at 0.05. Analyses will be on an intention-to-treat basis and results will be reported in accordance with the CONSORT criteria </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/04/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Royal Park campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Melbourne Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Royal Melbourne Hospital  Royal Park Campus, 34-54 Poplar Road, Parkville VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Melbourne Health Research Funding Program</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 6 East, 300 Grattan Street, Parkville VIC 3050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This pilot study will investigate if an exercise and education program is useful to help keep persons with Multiple Sclerosis exercising in the community by themselves.  We hypothesise that the program will improve walking speed and be a feasible and safe program.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Louie, J., Baquie K.A., Offerman J., Bower K.J., Granger C.L., Khan, F. (2015) Maximising abilities, negotiating and generating exercise options (manage) program: a pilot randomised controlled trial in persons with Multiple Sclerosis. Physiotherapy; 101, supplement 1. (02/05/2015)</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Office for Research
Level 6 East, Main Building, 
300 Grattan St, Carlton VIC 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/01/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012.242</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Julie Louie </name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
The Royal Melbourne Hospital  Royal Park Campus
34-54 Poplar Road, Parkville VIC 3052
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83872685</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 83872109</fax>
      <email>julie.louie@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Julie Louie</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
The Royal Melbourne Hospital  Royal Park Campus
34-54 Poplar Road, Parkville VIC 3052
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83872685</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 83872109</fax>
      <email>julie.louie@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Julie Louie</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
The Royal Melbourne Hospital  Royal Park Campus
34-54 Poplar Road, Parkville VIC 3052
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83872685</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 83872109</fax>
      <email>julie.louie@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Julie Louie</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
The Royal Melbourne Hospital  Royal Park Campus
34-54 Poplar Road, Parkville VIC 3052
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83872685</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 83872109</fax>
      <email>julie.louie@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>