<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="883">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/11/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/11/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000751673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Psychological factors and response to medical treatment: Do psychological 
factors determine the outcome in patients with inflammatory bowel disease?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does the disclosure of the inflammatory bowel disease patient's 
psychological status to their physician influences patient's 
responses to the clinical treatment?: The randomized controlled 
trial with Royal Adelaide Hospital gastroenterologists.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>RCT on disclosure of psychological status of IBD patients to doctors</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Inflammatory bowel disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The psychological status of patients assigned to the experimental group will be disclosed to the treating physicians.  However, any patient diagnosed with severe psychological disorder (i.e. psychosis, severe depression) will be reported to his/her doctor irrespective of the 
process of randomisation.

Study will be a randomized controlled trial examining whether disclosure of IBD patients' psychological status to 
their physician influences patients' responses to the clinical treatment. IBD patients will all receive current standard 
medical care. In addition, they will fill in questionnaires measuring their disease activity, quality of life and 
psychological status. Participants with diagnosed psychological disorders detected by the screening instruments 
(HADS, SCL90) will be randomly allocated into one of two groups.  As psychological co-morbidities in patients with IBD are frequently unrecognised in 
standard care settings, and often not specifically treated; this methodology should reveal whether a physician's 
knowledge of the patient's mental health status influences the physician's actions or the patient's response to 
clinical treatment. Study will be prospective with follow-up every 3 months for a year.</interventions>
    <comparator>The psychological status of patients assigned to the control group will not be disclosed to the treating physician. However, any patient diagnosed with severe psychological disorder (i.e. psychosis, severe depression) will be reported to his/her doctor irrespective of the process of randomisation.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be remission of inflammatory bowel disease defined as 3 
weeks of Crohn's disease activity &lt; 150 points (Crohn's Disease Activity Index) or a 
drop in the score of at least 70 points, and ulcerative colitis activity &lt; 2 (Simple 
Clinical Colitis Activity Index) or a drop in the score of at least 3 points. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured each 3 months for a year.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome will be a remission of a psychological disorder and improved quality of life. A score between 0-7 on 
the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) or a drop of one category will be marked as improvement of 
psychological disorders. A change on SCL-90-R will confirm the result on HADS. In general, respondents who score &gt; 11 on 
either subscale of HADS have a probable psychiatric disorder (Zigmond and Snaith 1983).
The change in quality of life will be noted on the SF-12 scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The outcome will be measured each 3 months for a year.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants who visit the Department of Gastroenterology in Royal Adelaide Hospital (RAH) between November 2005 and April 2006 will be recruited consecutively by their doctors from IBD outpatients. Patients will be informed about the research and written consent will be obtained. Inclusion criteria (1)Patients with IBD (Crohn's disease or ulcerative colitis) diagnosed by clinical, endoscopic, histologic and/or radiologic criteria; (2)Patients with sufficient knowledge of English to understand and answer questionnaires;(3)Patients who sign written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Not stated</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1)Patients with insufficient knowledge of English or who are cognitively impaired, as the study requires filling in and understanding questionnaires written in English;(2)Patients who do not give informed consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients with diagnosed psychological disorders will be allocated into two groups. The psychological status of patients assigned to the  experimental group will be randomly disclosed to the treating physicians. The psychological status of patients assigned to the control group will not be disclosed to the treating physician. The psychological status of any patient diagnosed with severe psychological disorder (i.e. psychosis, severe depression) will be reported to his/her doctor irrespective of which experimental group the subject is assigned to. The treatment approach will be at the physicians discretion.</concealment>
    <sequence>Random number tables will be used to generate a randomisation schedule. Allocation to study group will be via a preorganised sequence of sealed envelopes each containing the questionnaires for the next follow-up.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/11/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>65</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Adelaide</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of General Practice and the Department of Psychology, the University of Adelaide, Frome Rd, Adelaide 5001, SA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of General Practice and the Department of Psychology, the University of Adelaide</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Frome Rd, Adelaide 5001, SA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Gastroenterology, Hepatology and General Medicine, the Royal Adelaide Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>North Tce, Adelaide 5000, SA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>North Tce, Adelaide 5000, SA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To discover whether disclosure of the psychological status of inflammatory bowel disease patients to their physicians influences patients responses to treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Mikocka-Walus, A., Turnbull, D., Andrews, J., Moulding, N., Wilson, I., Holtmann, G. (2009). Does doctors knowledge of inflammatory bowel disease patients psychological status affect patients clinical outcomes: A pilot randomised controlled trial. The European Journal of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, 21(4): 484-5</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Commiittee,</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Adelaide Graduate Studies Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Antonina Mikocka-Walus</name>
      <address>University of South Australia, Nursing, GPO Box 2471, Adelaide 5001, SA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83022468</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83022168</fax>
      <email>antonina.mikocka-walus@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Antonina Mikocka-Walus</name>
      <address>University of South Australia, Nursing, GPO Box 2471, Adelaide 5001, SA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83022468</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83022168</fax>
      <email>antonina.mikocka-walus@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Antonina Mikocka-Walus</name>
      <address>University of South Australia, Nursing, GPO Box 2471, Adelaide 5001, SA</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83022468</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>antonina.mikocka-walus@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>