<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363941">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000385741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Radiotherapy and Ipilimumab in Metastatic Melanoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective trial examining safety and biological effects of combining Ipilimumab and radiotherapy in patients with metastatic melanoma.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1141-1952 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>RT and Ipi in Mestatstatic Melanoma</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>BMS ID - CA184-325</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Melanoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This group involves giving 25 Gy of radiotherapy in 5 daily fractions during the first week. Ipilimumab 3mg/kg will be given intravenously commencing on day 1 of radiotherapy and will be administered weeks 1, 4, 7, and 10, for a total of 4 infusions.</interventions>
    <comparator>This group involves giving 25 Gy of radiotherapy in 5 daily fractions during the first week. Ipilimumab 10mg/kg will be given intravenously commencing on day 1 of radiotherapy and will be administered weeks 1, 4, 7, and 10, for a total of 4 infusions.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To establish a toxicity profile for patients receiving Ipilimumab in combination with radiotherapy. This will be assessed by physical examination and symptom recording during treatment and at the end of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the tumour response using CT scans and Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) V1.1</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess for changes in immune response in the tumour lesions and peripheral blood. Pre and Post treatment biomarker levels will be taken from tumour biopsy's and peripheral blood. </outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To document progression free survival using CT scans and follow up appointments with physical exams.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To document overall survival using follow up appointments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.Voluntarily signed and dated institutional ethics committee (IEC) approved informed consent form in accordance with regulatory and institutional guidelines. This must be obtained before performing protocol-related procedures that are not part of standard patient care.
2.Able to comply with visits/procedures required by the protocol
3.Life expectancy of at least 3 months
4.&gt; 18 years of age
5.Good performance status (ECOG 0-1)
6.Histologically proven advanced melanoma stage IIIC or IV 
7.Measurable disease by modified RECIST 1.1 criteria (irradiated index lesion not included in overall response assessment).
8.Index lesion to be irradiated is measurable by RECIST 1.1 criteria
9.Index lesion to be irradiated is amenable to biopsy
10.Adequate hematologic, renal and liver function
11.Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) and men must be using an acceptable method of contraception (using the clinicians discretion) to avoid pregnancy throughout the study and for up to 12 weeks after the last dose in such a manner that the risk of pregnancy is minimized. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Symptomatic brain metastases or those treated &lt; 3 months previously
2.Patients requiring RT to brain, or chest and abdomen where it is expected that viscera will be in field
3.Patients being recommended a higher dose of RT (e.g. 30Gy/10#)
4.Taking immunosuppressive doses of corticosteroids (&gt;5mg of prednisolone or equivalent) or other immunosuppressant medications
5.Previous treatment with Ipilimumab
6.Previous other investigational products within last 4 weeks
7.Uncontrolled infectious diseases (HIV, Hepatitis B etc)
8.Autoimmune disease (including, but not limited to Crohns Disease, Ulcerative Colitis, Rheumatoid Arthritis etc)
9.Prior malignancy in last 5 years, not including basal or squamous cell carcinoma of skin
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>The RT dose will remain constant for each patient (25 Gy in 5 daily fractions) over 1 week. No further RT will be delivered during the 4 infusions of Ipilimumab. 
Two different doses of Ipilimumab will be evaluated.  The initial 15 patients will receive 3 mg/kg dose.  The next 15 patient will receive 10mg/kg dose. Administration of Ipilimumab will include a total of 4 infusions. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Dose Comparison Trial</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>As this is pilot study to identify toxicity and biomarkers which would then be evaluated in larger (appropriated powered) future studies, there are no formal assumptions of statistical power.  The goal of this research is to confirm that systemic Ipilimumab and palliative RT is safe to give concurrently, and to identify biomarkers potentially related to tumour response in each patients tumour and peripheral blood. Therefore pragmatically, the sample size of 30 patients (encompassing two groups of 15 patients each receiving a different dose level of Ipilimumab) was chosen to demonstrate safety and also provide a signal for efficacy, whilst providing a translational component. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/06/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Institute - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St Andrews Place, East Melbourne, VIC, 3002</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bristol Myers Squibb</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 4 Nexus Court, Mulgrave, VIC, 3170</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is examining the safety and biological effects of combining Ipilimumab and radiotherapy in patients with metastatic melanoma. 

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged over 18 years and have been diagnosed with advanced melanoma stage IIIc or IV.

Trial details
All participants in this trial will undergo 5 daily doses of radiotherapy during week 1. They will also receive Ipilimumab at a dose of either 3mg/kg or 10mg/kg at weeks 1, 4, 7, and 10. This drug will be administered intravenously (i.e. directly into the vein) over a period of 90 minutes.

Participants will be reviewed for up to 24 months in order to determine treatment toxicities, tumour response, and immune response.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Andrews Place, East Melbourne, VIC, 3002</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>HREC/13/PMCC/14.</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kathy Pope</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place
East Melbourne
Victoria, 3002</address>
      <phone>61 3 9656 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kathy.pope@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Tina Thorpe</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place
East Melbourne
Victoria, 3002</address>
      <phone>61 3 9656 1521 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tina.thorpe@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kathy Pope</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place
East Melbourne
Victoria, 3002</address>
      <phone>61 3 9656 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kathy.pope@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Tina Thorpe</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place
East Melbourne
Victoria, 3002</address>
      <phone>61 3 9656 1521 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tina.thorpe@ptermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>