<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365999">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000333617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Metabolic handling of dietary protein in critically ill patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of initiating enteral protein feeding on whole-body protein turnover in critically ill patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Critical illness</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Enteral feeding is initiated in critically ill patients. Due to tolerance problems that are common in these patients, a low dose of enteral nutrition is given initially. At an infusion rate of 20 ml/h, nutrient supply is 0.73 g/h casein and 2.73 g/h maltodextrin. Study nutrition contains casein intrinsically labeled with L-[1-13C]-phenylalanine (van Loon, L.J., et al., J Dairy Sci, 2009. 92:4812-22). This allows measurement of the dietary contribution to whole-body protein kinetics. Measurements of whole-body protein kinetics are made before and after six hours of enteral feeding.</interventions>
    <comparator>Parameters of whole-body protein turnover are measured before and after initiation of enteral protein feeding. Patients function as their own controls.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parameters of steady-state whole body protein kinetics are calculated from arterial plasma enrichments of isotope labeled phenylalanine and tyrosine tracers. Tracers are given intravenously and as intrinsically labelled casein via nasogastric tube. Calculations yield values for whole-body protein breakdown and synthesis. The arithmetic difference of breakdown and synthesis is the net protein balance which is the main outcome. The intermediary results are also reported for clarity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and 6 hrs post post initiation of enteral protein feeding</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Splanchnic extraction fraction of phenylalanine from dietary casein is calculated from arterial plasma enrichments of isotope labeled phenylalanine and tyrosine tracers. Tracers are given intravenously and as intrinsically labelled casein via nasogastric tube. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 hrs post initiation of enteral protein feeding</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma amino acid profile</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and 6 hrs post initiation of enteral protein feeding</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>ICU patients who are tracheally intubated or tracheostomized; clinical indication for inititating enteral feeding</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prior enteral feeding; milk protein allergy; ongoing renal replacement therapy or other extracorporeal blood treatment; liver failure; ongoing hemorrhage requiring transfusion; major surgery during the study period; contraindications to enteral feeding via nasogastric tube</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients are recruited from ICU clientele as available</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The study nutrition has not previously been used in the protocol described or a similar protocol. Therefore, healthy volunteers are studied in a pilot phase to establish feasibility of the protocol. This is not a separate study; rather, this part of the study is included in the ethical committee's approval and in the publication.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Values for the primary outcome are compared within-group, before vs. after intervention, appropriately by Wilcoxon matched pairs test. 

For physiological reasons, the secondary outcome "splanchnic extraction fraction of phenylalanine from dietary casein" can only be studied after intervention and results are therefore presented decriptively.

Comparison of results for patients  vs. subjects from the reference (pilot) group is not intended,  because the great differences in physiology preclude a meaningful interpretation.

A sample size calculation is not made, because the effect size is unknown and cannot be estimated from available knowledge. There are no experimental results in comparable patient groups that would allow such a estimation.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>10/12/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>12/01/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Olav Rooyackers</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Karolinska Institutet
Inst. for klinisk vetenskap, intervention och teknik
Enheten for anestesi
Karolinska Universitetssjukhuset, Huddinge, K32
141 86 Stockholm</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Sweden</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Regional Agreement on Medical Training and Clinical Research (ALF) between Stockholm County Council and Karolinska Institutet</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Stockholm County Council
Stockholms lans landsting
Box 22550
104 22 Stockholm
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Sweden</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>European Society of Intensive Care Medicine </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rue Belliard, 19
BE - 1040 Brussels
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Belgium</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Critically ill patients suffer from catabolism, i.e. protein loss, which may contribute to complications such as muscle weakness, protracted ventilator treatment, and delayed recovery. Appropriate feeding may alleviate catabolism, but ideal feeding strategies are controversial, partly because the underlying physiology is poorly understood.

We investigate the effect of protein feeding via nasogastric feeding tube in critically ill patients. Using stable isotope techniques, we measure whether whole-body protein catabolism is improved after initiation of feeding.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Felix Liebau, Jan Wernerman, Luc JC van Loon, and Olav Rooyackers

Effect of initiating enteral protein feeding on whole-body protein turnover in critically ill patients. Am J Clin Nutr. 2015 Mar;101(3):549-57.

doi: 10.3945/ajcn.114.091934. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Regionala etikprovningsnamnden i Stockholm</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Box 289 (Nobels vag 12 A)
171 77  Stockholm
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/12/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2009/1647-31/3</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Sweden</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Olav Rooyackers</name>
      <address>Karolinska Institutet
Inst. for klinisk vetenskap, intervention och teknik
Enheten for anestesi
Karolinska Universitetssjukhuset, Huddinge, K32
141 86 Stockholm</address>
      <phone>+46-8-58580553</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>olav.rooyackers@ki.se</email>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Felix Liebau</name>
      <address>Inst. for klinisk vetenskap, intervention och teknik
Enheten for anestesi
Karolinska Universitetssjukhuset, Huddinge, K32
141 86 Stockholm</address>
      <phone>+46-8-58580553</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>felix.liebau@karolinska.se</email>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Felix Liebau</name>
      <address>Inst. for klinisk vetenskap, intervention och teknik
Enheten for anestesi
Karolinska Universitetssjukhuset, Huddinge, K32
141 86 Stockholm</address>
      <phone>+46-8-58580553</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>felix.liebau@karolinska.se</email>
      <country>Sweden</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Felix Liebau</name>
      <address>Inst. for klinisk vetenskap, intervention och teknik
Enheten for anestesi
Karolinska Universitetssjukhuset, Huddinge, K32
141 86 Stockholm</address>
      <phone>+46-8-58580553</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>felix.liebau@karolinska.se</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>