<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370646">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000599471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of varying dietary protein concentration with carbohydrate versus fat on energy intake in healthy adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Interactions between protein leverage and dietary carbohydrate and fat content in the control of energy intake in humans</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each participant attended four, 4-day periods of in-house dietary manipulation. Participants will be given ad libitum access to diets containing varying protein content (10% and 25%), and the nutrient used to adjust dietary protein concentrations (carbohydrate or fat). The 4 diet treatments will be matched for palatability and energy density. The 4 diet composition will be as follows:  

Fixed fat, variable carbohydrate  
Diet 1: 10% protein, 30% fat and 60% carbohydrate 
Diet 2: 25% protein, 30% fat, 45% carbohydrate

Fixed carbohydrate and variable fat 
Diet 3: 10% protein, 40% fat and 50% carbohydrate
Diet 4: 25% protein, 25% fat and 50% carbohydrate

Participants will be given ad libitum access to study food with no access to other foods during each intervention period. Participants will have free access to a variety of foods all day and can initiate their own meal times. Participants will be asked to leave any uneaten foods and/or empty packages in a designated bag. 

Food intake will be measured by recording the weight of food before and after serving, to the nearest gram. Energy intake will be calculated using the nutritional information for each recipe. The trial will be a randomised cross-over trial, each participant completed each of the four 4-day interventions with at least a one week washout period between interventions.</interventions>
    <comparator>The trial was a randomised crossover trial, each participant was their own control. None of the four diets will act as the comparator/control.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Energy intake (MJ): Participants will be given ad libitum access to study food with no access to other foods during each intervention period. Participants will have free access to a variety of foods all day and could initiate their own meal times. Participants will be asked to leave any uneaten foods and/or empty packages in a designated bag. Food intake will be measured by recording the weight of the food before and after serving to the nearest gram. Total energy intake will then be calculated using the nutritional information for each recipe. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Provided foods will be weighed at the beginning of each day and food intake will be monitored and weighed by the study coordinator every 1-2 hours from 7am until 7pm. Any leftover or empty packages from foods consumed overnight (7pm-7am) will be weighed at 7am the next day. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasted serum levels of glucose</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on the morning of day 1 prior to and on the morning of day 5 following each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasted serum levels of triglycerides</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on the morning of day 1 prior to and on the morning of day 5 following each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasted serum levels of total cholesterol</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on the morning of day 1 prior to and on the morning of day 5 following each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasted serum levels of HDL cholesterol</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on the morning of day 1 prior to and on the morning of day 5 following each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasted serum levels of urea</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on the morning of day 1 prior to and on the morning of day 5 following each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasted serum levels of protein</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on the morning of day 1 prior to and on the morning of day 5 following each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasted serum levels of albumin</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on the morning of day 1 prior to and on the morning of day 5 following each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasted plasma levels of fibroblast growth factor-21</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on the morning of day 1 prior to and on the morning of day 5 following each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>24 hour levels of urinary urea</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured the day prior to and on day 4 of the four interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glucose control measured by continuous Glucose Monitoring System</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured throughout each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep duration measured by Actiwatch</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured throughout each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Levels of activity measured by Actiwatch</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured throughout each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Appetite rating using visual analogue scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Appetite questionnaires were administered hourly from before breakfast until 22:00 on day 4</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Food palatability ratings using visual analogue scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Palatability questionnaires were administered for each food consumed on day 4</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure was measured by Omron Standard Blood Pressure Monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on the morning of day 1 prior to and on the morning of day 5 following each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body weight using a digital scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on the morning of day 1 prior to and on the morning of day 5 following each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference using a tape measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on the morning of day 1 prior to and on the morning of day 5 following each of the four 4-day interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body height using a fixed stadiometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured on day 1 of the first of the four dietary interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Lean (BMI &lt; 25 kg/m2), healthy male and female participants</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy or planning pregnancy, breastfeeding, known diabetes, known unstable or untreated elevated blood pressure or cholesterol, cardiovascular disease, chronic inflammatory conditions, medications that interfere with glucose metabolism, smoking, alcohol consumption above current NHMRC dietary guidelines, allergy or intolerance to any of the intervention foods, irregular eating patterns or eating disorder, following a weight reducing diet. Vegetarians and Vegans will be excluded to aid preparation of covertly manipulated foods. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Each subject was screened to determine eligibility for the study. At this point the trial coordinator was unaware of the sequence of interventions the subject would be allocated. Once it was determined that the participant was eligible to be included in the trial the participant was then randomly allocated an order of intervention. Allocation of order was concealed by randomly selecting a sequence from an envelope. </concealment>
    <sequence>All possible sequences of interventions were printed the same number of times and placed in an envelope prior to the start of the study. The total number of sequences printed exceeded the number of participants that would be required to complete the trial. A sequence was randomly selected from the envelope for each participant. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Within subject design, each participant completed each of the interventions. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The study aims to recruit 30 lean subjects, comprising equal numbers of males and females. The sample size calculation was based on a previous ad libitum study where a 4.5MJ change in energy intake was measured in response to a reduction in percent dietary protein from 15% to 8% with a standard deviation of differences within pairs of approximately 1.2MJ. In order to detect a difference of 0.8MJ with a power of 80%, a significance of &lt;0.05 using a within subjects design, a sample size of 20 will be required. Recruitment of 30 subjects would allow for a dropout of 30%.  

Mixed model linear regression will be used to test for significant effects of the interventions and for differences in the change from baseline between each intervention for measurements taken prior to and following each intervention. Data will be presented as means and standard errors, an a p value of &lt; 0.05 will be accepted as significant. Estimates from the mixed model linear regression will also be presented alongside confidence intervals.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>4/11/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>14/08/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>13</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney, NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke Street, Canberra, ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Alison Gosby</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The University of Sydney, NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Protein intake has remained relatively stable through the development of the obesity epidemic. The protein leverage hypothesis proposes that a separate and dominant appetite for protein drives excess energy intake when dietary protein is diluted by fat and carbohydrate. We have provided convincing evidence that when the percent protein of the diet is reduced from 25% to 10% by increasing percent carbohydrate and keeping fat constant at 30% lean humans respond by increasing total energy intake. Recent data from a rodent dietary model suggests that intake of protein and carbohydrate is regulated (with protein dominating) but intake of fat is not. If dietary fat is not regulated in humans we would predict that the protein leverage effect will be even stronger if protein and fat co-vary in experimental diets and carbohydrate is kept constant at an adequate level. The aim of the study is to test whether converse changes in fat rather than carbohydrate will accentuate the protein leverage effect in covert trials. To do this we will manipulate the protein to energy ratio of the diet by increasing or decreasing the protein content whilst respectively decreasing or increasing the carbohydrate or fat content on 4 occasions for 4-days. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Level 11, KGV Building
Missenden Road
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Camperdown, NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/06/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X11-0139 &amp; HREC/11/RPAH/194</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/05/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370646-X11-0139 approval.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen Simpson</name>
      <address>Charles Perkins Centre, Bldg D17, The University of Sydney, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1613</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stephen.simpson@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Gosby</name>
      <address>Charles Perkins Centre, Bldg D17, The University of Sydney, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.gosby@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Gosby</name>
      <address>Charles Perkins Centre, Bldg D17, The University of Sydney, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.gosby@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Gosby</name>
      <address>Charles Perkins Centre, Bldg D17, The University of Sydney, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.gosby@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>