<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336669">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/03/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000281998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Continued Evaluation of Percutaneous Single Port Access Placement of a Paragastric Implant for the Treatment of Morbid Obesity</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Continued Evaluation of Percutaneous Single Port Access Placement of a Paragastric Implant for the Treatment of Morbid Obesity</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Morbid Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A one-time surgical procedure involving percutaneous, single-port access placement of the PREVAIL(Trademark) Single Port Access Paragastric Implant System. A saline filled silicone implant placed adjacent to the stomach and attached to the anterior abdominal wall.  The approximate duration of the procedure is 30-60 minutes. The implant is indicated for long-term implantation; however, it can be removed by means of a laparoscopic surgical procedure.</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary end point of this study will be the six-month efficacy rate, as measured by average percentage excess weight loss (%EWL), for subjects treated with the PREVAIL Single Port Access Paragastric Implant System.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six months following implantation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluation of the ability to successfully place the Paragastric Implant utilizing the Percutaneous Single Port Access technique. This outcome will be assessed by the successful deployment into the abdominal cavity, attachment to the anterior abdominal wall and inflation of the implant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 (procedure day)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in co-morbidities including:
Type II diabetes mellitis, hypertension, dislipidemia, sleep apnea, coronary heart disease, osteoarthritis, and gall bladder disease. Improvements will be assessed by means of physical examination and clinical pathology.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and six months following implantation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in quality of life measures, as assessed using the following questionnaires:
Three Factor Eating Questionnaire
Beck Depression Inventory
Short Form 36 (SF-36)
Short Musculoskeletal Function Assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and six months following implantation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety will be assessed by the incidence of severe or serious adverse events reported either by the subject or observed by the investigator, relating to the procedure or to the device itself either peri-operatively or in the follow-up period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All events reported that occur anytime from day of procedure through six months following implantation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subjects who would otherwise qualify for bariatric surgery based on BMI and co-morbidity criteria put forth by the National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) and the U.S. National Institutes of Health (NIH), and have presented to the Bariatric Clinic for consideration of weight loss surgery. These patients must have a Body Mass Index (BMI) &gt;40 kg/m2 and&lt;/= 50 kg/m2, or &gt;35 kg/m2 and &lt;40 kg/m2 with one or more significant medical conditions related to obesity (co-morbid conditions of type 2 diabetes, dyslipidemia, hypertension, obstructive sleep apnea, osteoarthritis, coronary heart disease, and gall bladder disease).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subject exhibits psychological or emotional characteristics which, in the opinion of the investigator, makes the subject a poor candidate for Paragastric Implant surgery
Documented history of drug and/or alcohol addiction; 
women of childbearing potential who are not practicing an effective method of birth control or who are pregnant or lactating, or planning to become pregnant within 3 years;
previous upper abdominal surgery that would interfere with placement of the Paragastric Implant; non-ambulatory;
acute or chronic infection (localized or systemic);
history of cancer  or presence of terminal illness with life expectancy &lt; 5 years; 
presence of any of the following medical conditions:
Inflammatory diseases of the gastrointestinal (GI) tract, anomalies of the GI tract, upper GI bleeding conditions, esophageal or gastric disorders, severe cardiopulmonary disease, uncontrolled hypertension, portal hypertension, uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, cirrhosis of the liver, chronic pancreatitis, hiatal hernia, or immunocompromised.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Vibrynt, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>701  Galveston Drive
Redwood City, CA 94063</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Vibrynt, Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>701  Galveston Drive
Redwood City, CA 94063</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The PREVAIL (Trademark)  Single Port Access Paragastric Implant System is a novel approach to the treatment of morbid obesity. The saline-filled Paragastric Implant is placed in a minimally invasive fashion into the abdominal cavity in the space adjacent the stomach, thereby reducing the ability of the stomach to expand and reducing oral intake.  The Paragastric Implant volume can be adjusted by the addition or removal of sterile saline through a subcutaneous port.

This trial is a single-arm, prospective, multi-center study designed to demonstrate the safety and effectiveness of the Vibrynt PREVAIL (Trademark) Paragastric Implant System in the treatment of morbid obesity.  The primary end point of this study will be the six-month efficacy rate, as measured by the average percent excess weight loss for subjects treated with the PREVAIL(Trademark) Single Port Access Paragastric Implant System .  Subjects will be followed for three years for long term safety and efficacy evaluations.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW Grants Management Office
Rupert Myers Building
University of NSW
Randwick, NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/06/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08245</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/03/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>229 Greenhill Road
Dulwich
South Australia 5065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011-03-139</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/03/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rosalea Gunter</name>
      <address>701 Galveston Drive
Redwood City, CA  94063</address>
      <phone>+11-650-362-6139</phone>
      <fax>+11-650-362-6182</fax>
      <email>rgunter@vibrynt.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rosalea Gunter</name>
      <address>701 Galveston Drive
Redwood City, CA  94063</address>
      <phone>+11-650-362-6139</phone>
      <fax>+11-650-362-6182</fax>
      <email>rgunter@vibrynt.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rosalea Gunter</name>
      <address>701 Galveston Drive
Redwood City, CA  94063</address>
      <phone>+11-650-362-6139</phone>
      <fax>+11-650-362-6182</fax>
      <email>rgunter@vibrynt.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>