<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367622">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/12/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000059561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Low dose of oral corticosteroids in the treatment of painful acute otitis externa (swimmer's ear)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of low dose of oral corticosteroids on time to pain resolution, lost hours of normal activity and patient satisfaction in the treatment of painful acute otitis externa (swimmer's ear) in General Practice</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1165-2370 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Project database / registry at College of Medicine and Dentistry at James Cook University. The ID number is: 117331. Registration is available at https://au.researchweb.org/is/jcu/document/117331 (This is not the trial website).</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute otitis externa</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Ear</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other ear disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Capsule with prednisone 10mg to take twice daily (20mg daily) for four days. When symptoms have stopped or 10 days after starting treatment with the study tablet, whichever occurs first, the patients answer a questionnaire. One of the questions are: "How many study tablets did you take?". They can tick 1-2 or 3-4 or 5-6 or 7-8.</interventions>
    <comparator>capsule with Lactose to take twice daily for four days</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time (number of days) to resolution of pain using a previously validated diary (Shikiar R, Halpern MT, McGann M, Palmer CS, Seidlin M. The relation of patient satisfaction with treatment of otitis externa to clinical outcomes: development of an instrument. Clinical therapeutics. 1999;21(6):1091-104.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be measured daily up until a maximum of ten days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lost hours in respect of:
	1) need for bed rest
        2) activity limitation
        3) paid work missed
        4) need for paid child/elder care
Measurements by using a previously validated diary (Shikiar R, Halpern MT, McGann M, Palmer CS, Seidlin M. The relation of patient satisfaction with treatment of otitis externa to clinical outcomes: development of an instrument. Clinical therapeutics. 1999;21(6):1091-104.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be measured daily up until a maximum of ten days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>"Patient satisfaction" concerning:
	1) burning or stinging feeling post administration of topical treatment
	2) itching post administration of topical treatment
	3) time to resolution of pain
	4) time to resolution of itching
	5) time to resolution of swelling
	6) time to resolution of discharge
Measurements by using a previously validated questionnaire (Shikiar R, Halpern MT, McGann M, Palmer CS, Seidlin M. The relation of patient satisfaction with treatment of otitis externa to clinical outcomes: development of an instrument. Clinical therapeutics. 1999;21(6):1091-104.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be measured with a questionnaire when symptoms have resided or after 10 days, whichever occurs first</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of unplanned revisits to a medical practitioner. Unplanned visits will be asked for in a questionnaire designed specifically for this study.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>When symptoms have resided or after 10 days, whichever occurs first.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The need for exclusion from the study due to worsening of symptoms. The need for exclusion will be known from reported adverse events.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patient complete their participation when symptoms have resided or after 10 days, whichever occurs first. Any adverse events during this period must be reported to the study centre.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation between any of the other outcomes and ethnicity. Information about ethnicity is collected using a questionnaire that was designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Ethnicity will be asked for with a questionnaire when symptoms have resided or after 10 days, whichever occurs first using a questionnaire that was designed specifically for this study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>"Patient satisfaction" concerning time to resolution of normal activities. Measurements by using a previously validated questionnaire (Shikiar R, Halpern MT, McGann M, Palmer CS, Seidlin M. The relation of patient satisfaction with treatment of otitis externa to clinical outcomes: development of an instrument. Clinical therapeutics. 1999;21(6):1091-104.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be measured with a questionnaire when symptoms have resided or after 10 days, whichever occurs first.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients diagnosed by their General Practitioner as having acute otitis externa and:
  
a)	Has ear pain where VAS is at least 2.5 cm of maximum 10 cm (anchored as moderate pain).

b)	Will be staying in Australia at least 10 days (not leaving the country within a few days).

c)	Age at least 16 years.

d)	Not being pregnant.

e)	Seems to be cognitively intact.

f)	Speak English well enough to understand instructions and consent form.

g)	Has no large visual impairment that would preclude completion of the patients diary and questionnaire.

h)	Does not have Downs syndrome.

i)	Does not have obvious craniofacial abnormalities.

j)	Does not have diabetes mellitus.

k)	Does not have known immunodeficiency (HIV, Leukemia, etc).

l)	Is not taking immunosuppressant drugs or oral corticosteroids.

m)	Does not have known rupture of the tympanic membrane.

n)	Does not have grommet (tympanostomy tube).

o)	Does not have signs of systemic sepsis (body temperature &gt;38.5 degrees), invasive fungal disease or perichondritis of the pinna.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a) Patients experiencing moderate worsening of pain after taking two or more doses of the study tablets and still have more study tablets to take.

b) Patients experiencing severe worsening of pain while still on the study tablet.

c) Patients experiencing fever &gt;38.5 degrees while still on the study tablet.

d) Other types of adverse events need to be evaluated case by case.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>A series of random numbers generated by "Research Randomizer". These random numbers were transformed to a series of X or Y.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Time to resolution of pain: The VAS in patient diary measuring pain will be used to determine the number of days until pain is almost (=10mm of max 100mm) or completely (0mm of max 100mm) gone. Groups will be compared using log rank test. Cox regression will be used in case baseline differences exist between groups. If ethnicity is of importance it will be a confounding variable in the Cox regression. Furthermore, in that situation sub analysis will be made separately for Indigenous people (although the study is not powered for this sub analysis).
  
Lost hours: Items 16-19 in the patient diary are summed up to a total amount of lost hours per patient in respect of need for bed rest, activity limitation, paid work missed and need for paid child/elder care. Effect size with 95% confidence interval is calculated. Total number of hours in each area will also be compared between groups using Mann-Whitneys test (skewed data). Should baseline differences exist between groups we will investigate using covariance analysis.
  
Satisfaction with symptom resolution: Item 10-16 in the patient satisfaction questionnaire are used. We primarily intend to calculate effect size with 95% confidence interval. Secondly, we will compare groups with Mann-Whitneys test. However, should any baseline differences exist then we will analyse with Logistic regression. In such case the outcome of the item will be dichotomised with the median value as cut off limit and used as dependent variable. Treatment and variables that differ between groups at baseline will be independent variables.
  
Secondary research questions: If oral steroids reduce the need for unplanned revisits or the need for exclusion due to worsening of symptoms will be analysed using Fishers exact test. The importance of ethnicity will be evaluated in the research question time to resolution of symptoms where ethnicity will be a covariate. The question if corticosteroids increase patient satisfaction concerning time to resolution of normal activities will be analysed as the other questions about patient satisfaction with symptom resolution (see above).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>James Cook University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>James Cook University
Cairns Hospital
Box 902
A-Block level 2
Cairns
4870 Queensland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>College of medicine and Dentistry, James Cook University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>James Cook University
Cairns Hospital
Box 902
A-Block level 2
Cairns
4870 Queensland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Otitis externa (swimmers ear) is a frequent problem worldwide, especially in the tropics. The pain and swelling often makes proper topical treatment difficult. This study aims to evaluate the effect of oral corticosteroids (an anti-inflammatory drug) on swimmers ear.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.otitisexterna.net/</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>James Cook University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee
Research Office, Room 128
Faculty Science &amp; Engineering Building (DB17)
James Cook University
Townsville
Queensland, 4811</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>C16</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/09/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367622-C16_Gunnarsson_Approval 3 November 2014_Final.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367622-C16_Gunnarsson_Amendment Approved 16 Dec 2014.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367622-2015-09-08 --- C16_Gunnarsson_Amendment Approved 26 Aug 2015.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367622-2015-10-28 --- C16_Gunnarsson_Amendment Approved 28 Oct 2015.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367622-2015-11-25 --- C16_Gunnarsson_Amendment Approved 25 Nov 2015.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367622-2016-02-08 --- C16_Gunnarsson_Amendment Approved 8 Feb 2016.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367622-2016-03-29 --- Annual report signed by the Dean.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367622-2016-07-05 --- C16_Gunnarsson_Amendment Approved 29 June 2016.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367622-2014-11-28 --- 29 - Project proposal - long version.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ronny Gunnarsson</name>
      <address>James Cook University at Cairns Hospital
Box 902
A-Block level 2
Cairns
Queensland, 4870</address>
      <phone>+61742267391</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ronny.gunnarsson@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ronny Gunnarsson</name>
      <address>James Cook University at Cairns Hospital
Box 902
A-Block level 2
Cairns
Queensland, 4870</address>
      <phone>+61742267391</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ronny.gunnarsson@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ronny Gunnarsson</name>
      <address>James Cook University at Cairns Hospital
Box 902
A-Block level 2
Cairns
Queensland, 4870</address>
      <phone>+61742267391</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ronny.gunnarsson@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ronny Gunnarsson</name>
      <address>James Cook University at Cairns Hospital
Box 902
A-Block level 2
Cairns
Queensland, 4870</address>
      <phone>+61742267391</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ronny.gunnarsson@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>