<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365567">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000437662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of a brief intervention for parents of children aged 3-10 years old who are experiencing sibling conflict</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A 2-hour parenting discussion group on managing fighting and aggression versus care-as-usual for parents of children experiencing sibling conflict in order to decrease sibling conflict, increase sibling warmth and decrease parents' use of ineffective parenting practices</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sibling Conflict</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Agonism</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Arguments</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical Aggression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention consists of one, 2-hour parenting discussion group on Managing Fighting and Aggression, designed to target the direct and indirect pathways of parenting impact on sibling conflict outcomes (i.e., parenting practices, and parenting confidence and stress). The Managing Fighting and Aggression discussion group targets parents of children with sibling conflict and is designed to assist parents in preventing and managing their childrens conflict effectively. The discussion group aims to combine education about conflict management with parenting strategies that will empower parents to ensure their children are implementing prevention and management plans appropriately (using checklists, charts, and diary keeping to track childrens progress). 

Participants will be asked to complete a series of online measures on entry to the trial, four to six weeks later and at a 6-month follow up.</interventions>
    <comparator>Families in care-as-usual will also be assessed on entry to the trial, four to six weeks later and again at six months. During this time, families will continue to undertake whatever practices they were previously using in attempting to manage their childrens conflict. After the 6-month follow-up assessment, families will be offered participation in the intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: improve children's sibling relationships through decreased levels of conflict between siblings.  Measured through the agonism subscale of the Parental Expectations and Perceptions of Children's Sibling Relationship Questionnaire (PEPC-SRQ) (Kramer &amp; Baron, 1995) and the How do you Manage Children's Conflict Measure (Kramer &amp; Washo, 1999).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline, 4 to 6 weeks later, 6 months later</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2: improve children's sibling relationships through increased warmth in the sibling relationship. Measured through the warmth subscale of the PEPC-SRQ (Kramer &amp; Baron, 1995). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline, 4 to 6 weeks later, 6 months later</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 3: decrease parents' use of ineffective parenting practices in managing the sibling relationship. Measured through subscales of the How do you Manage Children's Conflict Measure (Kramer &amp; Washo, 1999).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline, 4 to 6 weeks later, 6 months later</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: lower levels of child behavioural and emotional problems.  Measured through the Child Adjustment and Parent Efficacy Scale (CAPES) (Morawska, Sanders, Haslam, Filus &amp; Fletcher, in press).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline, 4 to 6 weeks later, 6 months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2: increase parents' use of positive strategies in managing their children's behaviour. Measured through the Parenting and Family Adjustment Scale (PAFAS) (Sanders, Morawska, Haslam, Filus &amp; Fletcher, 2014).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Baseline, 4 to 6 weeks later, 6 months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3: increase parents' confidence in improving their children's behaviour. Measured through the Child Adjustment and Parent Efficacy Scale (CAPES) (Morawska, Sanders, Haslam, Filus &amp; Fletcher, in press).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Basline, 4 to 6 weeks later, 6 months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i) presence in the family of at least two children in the 3-10 year old age range with no more than four years separating the two children; (ii) presence of parental concern about sibling conflict; and (iii) an elevated score on the agonism subscale of the PEPC-SRQ (Parental Expectations and Perceptions of Children's Sibling Relationship Questionnaire);</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>10</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) child has a developmental delay or intellectural disability including language and speech impairment; (ii) the parents are currently receiving psychological assistance for their children's behaviour or to deal with their children's behaviour; or (iii) the parents are unable to attend The University of Queensland's St Lucia Campus on four separate occasions for the purpose of participating in the intervention.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Following eligibility screening and completion of the pre-assessment measures, randomisation to condition will occur. Participants will be randomly allocated to either the intervention condition or care-as-usual condition using a computer random number generator. Allocation concealment will involve contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is “off-site” or at a central administration site. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a table created by computer software. Depending on recruitment rates, parents may be randomised in a block sequence (i.e., 15 parents randomised concurrently)  The experimenter will be blind to the process of randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants in the Intervention condition receive the intervention after completing the pre-assessment measures.  Participants in the care-as-usual condition will receive the intervention at the completion of the trial.  </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A power analysis was conducted to determine the required sample size. To detect a medium effect size of .50, with alpha of .05, and power at .80, a minimum of 50 participants per cell is required (N = 100 for the two-group study). 

ANOVA and MANOVA methods will be used to evaluate the data across the timepoints and between the conditions.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/05/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>28/07/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>76</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>22/02/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>John Pickering</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Parenting and Family Support Centre
School of Psychology
The University of Queensland
St Lucia 
Brisbane QLD 4072
AUSTRALIA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Parenting and Family Support Centre
School of Psychology
The University Of Queensland 
St Lucia 
Brisbane QLD 4072
AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Most children born in the Western world have a sibling. Of all the aspects of the sibling relationship, none is potentially more harmful than sibling conflict. Of particular concern, the impact of pervasive sibling conflict is potentially devastating and far reaching for children and their parents social, emotional and behavioural health. This study aims to evaluate the efficacy of a brief, group-based parenting intervention for parents of children experiencing sibling conflict. It is expected that participating in a group based parenting intervention has the potential to reduce rates of sibling conflict, increase warmth in the sibling relationship and lower rates of ineffective and coercive parenting practices.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.exp.psy.uq.edu.au/siblings</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Pickering, J. A. &amp; Sanders, M. R. (2013). Enhancing communities through the design and development of positive parenting interventions. Journal of Applied Research on Children: Informing Policy for Children at Risk.4(2), Article 18. Available at: http://digitalcommons.library.tmc.edu/childrenatrisk/vol4/iss2/18

Pickering, J. A. &amp; Sanders, M. R. (February, 2014).  The Development and Evaluation of a Parenting Intervention for Managing Sibling Conflict. Paper presented at the 2014 Helping Families Change Conference. Sydney, Australia.

Pickering, J. A. &amp; Sanders, M. R. (October, 2013). The Development and Evaluation of a Parenting Intervention for Managing Sibling Conflict. Paper presented at the 2013 Australian Association of Cognitive and Behaviour Therapies. Adelaide, Australia.

Pickering, J. A. &amp; Sanders, M. R. (February, 2013). Consumer Engagement and the Development of Effective Parenting Interventions for Managing Sibling Conflict. Paper presented at the 2013 Helping Families Change Conference. Los Angeles, USA. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Behavioural &amp; Social Sciences Ethical Review Committee (BSSERC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research &amp; Innovation Division
Cumbrae-Stewart Building
The University of Queensland
St Lucia 
Brisbane QLD 4072
AUSTRALIA
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/12/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>John Pickering</name>
      <address>Parenting and Family Support Centre
School of Psychology
The University of Queensland
St Lucia 
Brisbane QLD 4072
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 8743</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.pickering@psy.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>John Pickering</name>
      <address>Parenting and Family Support Centre
School of Psychology
The University of Queensland
St Lucia
Brisbane QLD 4072
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 8743</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.pickering@psy.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>John Pickering</name>
      <address>Parenting and Family Support Centre
School of Psychology
The University of Queensland
St Lucia
Brisbane QLD 4072
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3346 8743</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.pickering@psy.uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Margaret Crane</name>
      <address>Parenting and Family Support Centre School of Psychology The University of Queensland St Lucia Brisbane QLD 4072 AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61733657428</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.crane@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>