<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82050">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/05/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/06/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000295448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Treatment of cutaneous leishmaniasis with meglumine antimoniate and allopurinol.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized controlled trial to evaluate the efficacy and safety of meglumine antimoniate (20mg) versus meglumine antimoniate (10 mg) plus allopurino (20 mg) in patients with cutaneous leishmaniasis to assess the efficacy in terms of healing time and to assess safety in terms of side effects.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cutaneous leishmaniasis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Injection meglumine antimoniate 10 mg/kg/day plus tablet allopurinol 20 mg/kg/day (experimental drug) for a period of 28 days maximum.</interventions>
    <comparator>Injection meglumine antimoniate 20 mg/kg/day (control) for a period of 28 days maximum.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complete reepithelization </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after the beginning of the treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Absence of reactivation and affections of the mucous membrane during the 6 months of the study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The lesion size and induration will be measured every week during the treatment phase (28 days), thereafter once monthly during the follow up phase to assess the increase/decrease in the size of lesions.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incomplete reepithelization</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three months after the beginning of the treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increase in the size of the ulcer by more than 50% in relation to the last clinical evaluation.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reactivation and/or affections of the mucous membranes during the 6 months of the study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Study patients will be evaluated once weekly for ulcer size, induration and mucous membrane involvement, during the treatment period. In the follow up period patients will have monthly visits to record the parameters for 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>2. Cutaneous ulcers, nodules, plaques, of more than two weeks of evolution requiring systemic therapy.283. Positive parasitological diagnosis for cutaneous leishmaniasis.4. Patients that voluntarily accept to participate in the study and sign the informed consent.5. Disposition to be admitted to hospital, if necessary, and to attend all the visits punctually (initial, treatment and follow up).6. Acceptation of not using any other treatment for cutaneous leishmaniasis while in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Pregnant women.2. Presence of any condition or disease that compromises the patient immunologically (i.e. diabetes, cancer, etc.) or, any other, that, based on the judgment of the researcher, could alter the course of cutaneous leishmaniasis.3. Diffuse cutaneous leishmaniasis.4. Visceral leishmaniasis.5. Complete or incomplete treatment with antimony compounds in the last three months.6. Patients with history of hepatic, renal, or cardiovascular disease.7. Mentally or neurologically disabled patients that are considered not fit to approve their participation in the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>numbered containers</concealment>
    <sequence>block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>620</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Amer Ejaz</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>combined military hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>kharian cantonment</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Pakistan</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr SNR Qadir</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: Cutaneous Leishmaniasis is a worldwide disease, endemic in over 88 countries, that has shown an increasing incidence over the last many decades. For the last 60 years antimony compounds are considered the treatment of choice. Though their use is expensive, cumbersome, has many adverse effects and not effective in all patients, the search for a better alternative is still going on. Low dose antimony compounds in combination with several agents have shown promise of reducing adverse effects of antimony compounds without compromising efficacy. Allopurinol is one such agent which though promising lacks randomized, controlled trials to prove efficacy. The main objective of this study is to evaluate low dose sodium stibogluconate in combination with allopurinol and to compare it with high dose sodium stibogluconate in terms of efficacy and adverse effects.
Methods and design: A multi-center randomized, controlled trial including 620 patients from endemic areas for Leishmaniasis in Pakistan will be undertaken to assess the research question. Parasitologically confirmed cutaneous leishmaniasis will be included in the study. After evaluating the inclusion/exclusion criteria patients will be randomized to receive either meglumine antimoniate (20 mg/kg/day/intramuscular, till clinical resolution or a maximum of 28 days) or combination of meglumine antimoniate (10 mg/kg/day intramuscular) and allopurinol (20 mg/kg/day/oral) till clinical resolution or a maximum of 28 days. During treatment patients will be admitted to hospital and monitored daily for the presence of adverse effects. Follow up period will last six months during which patients will visits the research centers for assessment of healing process at monthly intervals.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research and ethics committee, Combined Military Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/05/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RCT/001/2007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Pakistan</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Amer Ejaz</name>
      <address>Combined Military Hospital
Main boulevard
Kharian Cantonment</address>
      <phone>00 92 300 928 7063</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amer_ejaz@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Amer Ejaz</name>
      <address>Combined Military Hospital, Main boulevard, Kharian Cantonment</address>
      <phone>00 92 300 928 7063</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amer_ejaz@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>