<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373044">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000829314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical Trial Evaluation of the Percutaneous 4Tech TriCinch Coil Tricuspid Valve Repair System</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessment of the All Cause Mortality at 30 days for Patients suffering from Tricuspid Regurgitation implanted with the Percutaneous 4Tech TriCinch Coil System </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>functional tricuspid regurgitation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients enrolled in this study with all eligibility criteria confirmed will be implanted with the TriCinch Coil System. This device offers a percutaneous treatment (access through the vein at the groin) to treat the leaking tricuspid valve, without the need for surgical intervention. This procedure is done by an interventional cardiologist or a cardiac surgeon under a general anaesthetic or deep sedation without the need for respiratory assistance and is expected to last 60-90 minutes initially. 
The TriCinch Coil System implantation is as follows: 1) A delivery system that consists of a catheter (a hollow tube) that is attached to a handle is inserted in the patient's body through a vein in the groin. The delivery system contains a small anchor and a stent.  
2) The small anchor is permanently placed in the wall of the tricuspid valve. The anchor is connected to a tensioning band that is connected to a stent at the opposite end. The stent (a mesh-like metal tube that expands, when deployed, to fit the patient's anatomy) is permanently deployed in a large vein called the inferior vena cave (IVC). 
3) Then, the delivery system is removed and the procedure is complete. </interventions>
    <comparator>not applicable</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All-cause mortality of the Per Protocol cohort at 30 days post procedure. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of individual adverse events related to the system or procedure. Adverse Events will be assessed based on the available source documentation. Severity will be assessed per based on ISO 14155 definitions. Serious Adverse Events will be adjudicated by an independent Clinical Events Committee for their relationship to the device and/or the device procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, three (3), six (6), twelve (12) and twenty-four (24) months post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Echocardiographic changes compared to Baseline by means of echocardiographic semi-quantitative and quantitative measures (e.g. TV annular diameter, TV area, vena contracta, PISA EROA, Quantitative EROA, TV Regurgitant Volume, RA, RV, IVC dimensions, TAPSE). The independent Echo core lab measurements will be used to evaluate this secondary endpoint.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, three (3), six (6), twelve (12) and twenty-four (24) months post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional changes as compared to Baseline for New York Heart Association (NYHA) classification, </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, three (3), six (6), twelve (12) and twenty-four (24) months post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of Heart Failure event post-procedure defined as a heart failure hospitalization or a heart failure hospitalization equivalent</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, three (3), six (6), twelve (12) and twenty-four (24) months post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise tolerance (Six Minute Walk Test) </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, three (3), six (6), twelve (12) and twenty-four (24) months post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life evaluation (Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire).</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, three (3), six (6), twelve (12) and twenty-four (24) months post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in peripheral oedema will be evaluated using weight and diuretics dosage as a surrogate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, three (3), six (6), twelve (12) and twenty-four (24) months post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>New onset of Atrial Fibrillation will be evaluated using the ECG collected at each follow-up visit</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, three (3), six (6), twelve (12) and twenty-four (24) months post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in average dosages of concomitant cardiac medications (including diuretics) will be evaluated based on the dosages reported on the medication form at each follow-up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, three (3), six (6), twelve (12) and twenty-four (24) months post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kidney function will be evaluated using the creatinine and creatinine clearance levels (blood tests)</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, three (3), six (6), twelve (12) and twenty-four (24) months post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in NT Pro BNP will be evaluated through blood tests at each follow-up</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, three (3), six (6), twelve (12) and twenty-four (24) months post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Procedure time will be evaluated from first skin incision to skin closure (time)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Radiation dose during the procedure will be evaluated from the X ray machine in the cath lab</outcome>
      <timepoint>Procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Technical success defined as (per MVARC) at post-procedure and 30 days post-procedure: absence of procedural mortality; and successful access, delivery, and retrieval of the device delivery system; and successful deployment and correct positioning of the first intended device; and freedom from emergency surgery or reintervention related to the device or access procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>post-procedure and 30 days post-procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Functional tricuspid regurgitation (FTR) with annular diameter greater or equal 40 mm
2. 18 years old or older
3. Subject has read and signed the informed consent prior to study related procedures.
4. Willing and able to comply with all required follow-up evaluations and assessments.
5. The 'Heart Team' assessment recommends TriCinch Coil Implantation
6. New York Heart Associate Classification greater or equal to II.
7. Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction greater or equal to 30%.
8. Symptomatic despite on optimized medical therapy by the local heart team; at minimum subject on diuretic use
9. Subject has suitable anatomy for investigational device implantation as per imaging requirements </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Currently participating in another investigational drug or device study.
2. Subject with Systolic pulmonary arterial pressure (sPAP) &gt; 60mmHg
3. Subject requiring another cardiac procedure in the framework of the index procedure; subject requiring a percutaneous procedure within 30 days before or after the procedure or a cardiac surgical procedure within 3 months before or after the procedure
4. Moderate or Severe tricuspid valve stenosis
5. Aortic, mitral and/or pulmonic valve stenosis and/or regurgitation more than moderate
6. Intra-cardiac thrombus, mass or vegetation requiring active treatment
7. Implanted inferior vena cava (IVC) filter.
8. Prior tricuspid repair or tricuspid replacement
9. Known allergy to contrast media, silicone, PET, Co-Cr, stainless steel or nitinol
10. History of cardiac transplantation
11. Contraindication to Transthoracic/Transoesophageal Echocardiography (TTE/TOE).
12. Endocarditis or severe infection within 3 months of scheduled implant procedure
13. Myocardial Infarction (MI) or known unstable angina within the 30 days prior to the index procedure
14. Cerebro Vascular Accident within the previous 6 months
15. Hemodynamic instability or on IV inotropes
16. Contraindication to anticoagulant therapy or dual antiplatelet therapy
17. Documented history of bleeding diathesis, hypercoagulable or active peptic ulcer or gastrointestinal bleeding within 3 months of scheduled implant procedure
18. Severe renal impairment or on dialysis
19. Life expectancy less than 12 months.
20. Acute anemia
21. Chronic Oral Steroid Use greater than or equal to 6 months
22. Pregnant or lactating female of childbearing potential with a positive pregnancy test 24 hours before any study-related radiation exposure
23. Pulmonary embolism within the last 6 months
24. Tricuspid Valve Tethering distance &gt; 10 mm
25. Presence of trans-tricuspid pacemaker or defibrillator leads which are determined as immobile or interfering with the procedure, as evaluated by echocardiography.
26. Contra-indicated for blood transfusion or refuses transfusion</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec, British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>4Tech Cardio, Ltd. a wholly owned subsidiary of 4Tech Inc, a Delaware corporation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ballybrit Business Park
Unit 3
Galway, H91DT7C</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Ireland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>4Tech Cardio, Ltd. a wholly owned subsidiary of 4Tech Inc, a Delaware corporation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ballybrit Business Park
Unit 3
Galway, H91DT7C

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Ireland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mobius Medical Pty Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Suite 1002
23 Hunter Street
Sydney NSW 2000
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this clinical study is to evaluate a new, medical device called the TriCinch Coil System. This is an early phase study. This device is designed to treat patients suffering from tricuspid valve disease, It has not been approved by the Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA) as a treatment for tricuspid valve regurgitation in Australia.,
The study is a multi-centre study, which means that up to 20 hospitals may be participating in this study. Implantation of the TriCinch Coil System will be attempted in up to 90 patients in this study.
The goal of this clinical study is to evaluate the safety and performance of the TriCinch Coil System as a new method to treat leaking tricuspid valves which cause regurgitation (backflow of blood). Through the trial, information will be collected about the safety of the device, the success of placing the device, and its ability to reduce tricuspid regurgitation in a less invasive way for patients who have a high risk for undergoing open-heart surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Monash Health Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Health, 246 Clayton Road, Clayton, Victoria, 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/06/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Initial protocol approval</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/04/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Robert Gooley</name>
      <address>Monash Heart, Level 2
246 Clayton Road
Clayton,
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9594 2680</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Robert.Gooley@monashhealth.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Julien Delumeau</name>
      <address>4TECH Cardio Ltd
Ballybrit Business Park
Unit 3
Galway, H91DT7C</address>
      <phone>+33 7 85 10 59 70</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Julien.Delumeau@4tech.ie</email>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Julien Delumeau</name>
      <address>4TECH Cardio Ltd
Ballybrit Business Park
Unit 3
Galway, H91DT7C</address>
      <phone>+33 7 85 10 59 70</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Julien.Delumeau@4tech.ie</email>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Julien Delumeau</name>
      <address>4TECH Cardio Ltd
Ballybrit Business Park
Unit 3
Galway, H91DT7C</address>
      <phone>+33 7 85 10 59 70</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Julien.Delumeau@4tech.ie</email>
      <country>Ireland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>