<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370125">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000238471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot study evaluating the Every Moment program for foster and kinship carers of children with challenging behavioural and/or mental health needs</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot study evaluating the efficacy of the Every Moment program for foster and kinship carers of children with challenging behavioural and/or mental health needs.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>EM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Complex/Developmental Trauma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Foster and kinship carer depression, anxiety and stress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Social, emotional and behavioural difficulties in children in foster and kinship care.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A small sample of carers who meet inclusion criteria are invited to attend 8 x 1.5 hour education and management training sessions focusing on Safety, Trauma, Attachment, Interpersonal Relationships and Skills Building in the context of complex/developmental trauma. The sessions are presented one per week in group format and are convened and run by an Endorsed Clinical Psychologist. Adherence is assessed by a register of attendance. The sessions have been informed by reviews of applicable scientific literature and informed by 8 years of direct experience working and teaching in the areas of child protection and out of home care. Material is conveyed using presentations, participant experience and contribution, video and case scenario material. </interventions>
    <comparator>pilot, no control</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of behavioural difficulties displayed by children in foster and kinship care. 

This will be assessed with the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire, 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at baseline, week 2, week 4, week 6, week 8, and at follow-up at three months. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of social difficulties displayed by children in foster and kinship care. 

This will be assessed with the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire, </outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at baseline, week 2, week 4, week 6, week 8, and at follow-up at three months. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of emotional difficulties displayed by children in foster and kinship care. 

This will be assessed with the Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire, </outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at baseline, week 2, week 4, week 6, week 8, and at follow-up at three months. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcomes of interest are a reduction in depression displayed by foster and kinship carers. 

This will be assessed with the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scales (DASS 21) and the Parent Child Stress Index Short Form (PSI SF) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at baseline, week 2, week 4, week 6, week 8, and at follow-up at three months. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcomes of interest are a reduction in anxiety displayed by foster and kinship carers. 

This will be assessed with the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scales (DASS 21) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at baseline, week 2, week 4, week 6, week 8, and at follow-up at three months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcomes of interest are a reduction in  stress displayed by foster and kinship carers. 

This will be assessed with the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scales (DASS 21) and the Parent Child Stress Index Short Form (PSI SF) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Data will be collected at baseline, week 2, week 4, week 6, week 8, and at follow-up at three months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Foster or kinship carer of child(ren) where the child(ren) are aged 4-17 years, have lived with their current family for at least 6 months, and who reported a Total Difficulties Score on the SDQ equal to or above the "high" ("/low") range.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria in this pilot include:
carer characteristics (significant mental health or substance use concerns, care of child for less than 6 months, inability to communicate in English to a rudimentary level) and
child characteristics (under threshold on psychometric measures: SDQ)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>none</concealment>
    <sequence>none</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>pilot</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>multivariate stats</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>8/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/02/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>6</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>6</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Technology Sudney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 4 Building 7
67 Thomas St
Ultimo NSW 2007 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In 2013-14 18,950 children and young people were in out-of-home care (OOHC) in NSW. 
A substantial proportion of those in foster or kinship care arrangements are, or have been in foster or kinship care arrangements that have broken down. Approximately 60 per cent of those placed in foster care placements are placed with two or more foster families following their removal from their birth parents, a portion were placed with significantly more (FACS, 2013-14).
A significant proportion of children in foster and kinship care arrangements have experienced some form of maltreatment. Reviews differ but some find children in foster care have social and emotional problems at between three and ten times those of children in the general population (Dorsey, Burns, Southerland, Cox, Wagner, &amp; Farmer, 2012).Fisher, Gunnar, Dozier, Bruce  &amp; Pears, 2006; Nilsen, 2007). Their behaviour has significant implications for their social, emotional and academic development, and the stability of their living arrangements (Cook et al, 2005; Nilsen, 2007).
Children who have suffered abuse &amp;/or neglect present with a cluster of symptoms currently known as Complex Trauma (Cook et al, 2005, van der Kolk, Bessel,2005). The outcomes for these children include social, emotional behavioural and cognitive challenges. This is important as childhood behavioural and emotional difficulties are among the best predictors of mental health difficulties in adolescence and adulthood.
Foster and kinship care arrangements provide an immensely important opportunity to change the trajectories of children who have had their development impacted by early maltreatment (Fisher et al, 2006; Nilsen, 2007). Given the emotional and behavioural challenges that children in foster and kinship care can display, this potential can be very difficult and foster and kinship care placements often break down as a result of these pressures (Nilsen, 2007). 
Currently neurodevelopmental science and clinical psychological treatment evidence identifies a range of treatment components that has the potential to both inform foster and kinship carer training and allow foster and kinship carers an opportunity to understand and engage characteristics of presentation of children in their care. UTS: familychildbehaviour has developed Every Moment, an innovative program of trauma informed Foster and Kinship Care for carers looking after children with challenging behavioural &amp;/or mental health needs.
The primary purpose of this study is to evaluate whether the Every Moment program can contribute to reductions in difficulties experienced by foster and kinship carers in looking after children who have experienced early maltreatment and also whether Every Moment can contribute reducing difficulties for children that commonly follow early maltreatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UTS Human Research Ethics Expedited Review Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Technology Sydney
Level 4 Building 7
67 Thomas St
Ultimo NSW 2007

 (PO Box 123)</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>UTS HREC REF NO. 2015000482-23. </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>John McAloon</name>
      <address>University of Technology Sydney
Level 4 Building 7
67 Thomas St
Ultimo NSW 2007 

(PO Box 123)

</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 7240</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john.mcaloon@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>John McAloon</name>
      <address>University of Technology Sydney
Level 4 Building 7
67 Thomas St
Ultimo NSW 2007 

(PO Box 123)</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 7240</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john.mcaloon@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>John McAloon</name>
      <address>University of Technology Sydney
Level 4 Building 7
67 Thomas St
Ultimo NSW 2007 

(PO Box 123)</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 7240</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john.mcaloon@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>John McAloon</name>
      <address>University of Technology Sydney
Level 4 Building 7
67 Thomas St
Ultimo NSW 2007 

(PO Box 123)</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 7240</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john.mcaloon@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>