<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320915">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/12/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/12/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609001066279</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Inhaled mannitol for the clearance of mucus in asthma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Inhaled mannitol for the treatment of mucociliary dysfunction in patients with asthma - Its effect and mechanisms on the clearance of mucus</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study consisted of 5 visits.  The first visit was a screening visit involving assessment of lung function and a bronchial challenge with mannitol after premedication with eformoterol.  Subjects were eligible to proceed to the next visits if they had a fall in forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) less than 15 % from the baseline value. 
 
Visits 2-5 were mucociliary and cough clearance studies using a radioaerosol technique and imaging with a gamma camera in the Departmet of Nuclear Medicine.  The radioaerosol inhaled was sulphur colloid tagged with technetium.  
Mucocilairy and cough clearance was measured over a total of 90 min at baseline (no cough or mannitol) and in response to 2 doses of inhaled dry powder mannitol (240 and 480 mg). Patients were premedicated with eformoterol at all times prior to inhaling mannitol.  The baseline and mannitol visits were randomised. The last visit was a cough control day involving cough but no mannitol.
Cough clearance was assessed by asking the subjects to cough, 30 minutes after mannitol inhalation, 100 times (4 per min) over 30 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>an improvement in mucociliary and cough clearance  of mucus measured with the imaging technique.  Image analysis gives counts over time that are used to calculate clearance of mucus over time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>acute effect of total of 90 min measured in each visit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>acute improvement in the physical properties of sputum as a result of interventions.
Sputum is collected at the beginning (baseline) and end of each visit for the measurement of the physical properties. The physical properties include the solids content, surface tension, rheology and contact angle. An improvement in the physical properties is a significant reduction in the physical properties at the end of each visit compared to the baseline measurements.</outcome>
      <timepoint>over 90 min on each visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>asthma
chronic cough and sputum production</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>17</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>fall in FEV1 greater or equal to 15% in response to mannitol
bronchiectasis based on high resolution computed tomography (HRCT)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>The order of the mucociliary clearance studies at baseline and with the  two doses of mannitol (visits 2-4) were randomised using the randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/02/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Evangelia Daviskas</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Respiratory and Sleep Medicine, 11 West, Building 75, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital Missenden Road, Camperdown, Sydney, NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council 
GPO Box 1421 Camberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Baseline mucociliary and cough clearance is very abnormal in asthmatics with excessive secretions and presenting symptoms of chronic cough and sputum production. Inhaled mannitol markedly improves mucociliary clearance and this effect is dose dependent in the large airways.  Repetitive voluntary coughing following inhalation of mannitol enhances clearance of mucus.  Asthmatics with mucociliary dysfunction, after careful assessement and appropriate premedication may benefit from inhaling mannitol to clear excessive secretions and prevent mucus plug formation in the small airways</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>The effect of mannitol and cough in asthmatics with mucociliary dysfunction (Abstract) to be presented at the Thoracic Society of  Australia and New Zealand Annual Scientific Meeting in Brisbane March 2010</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Review Committee of Sydney South West Area Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Development Office, Building 92, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital Camperdown NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/10/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>07/RPAH/32</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/08/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Evangelia Daviskas</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory and Sleep Medicine, 11 West Building 75, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, Missenden Road, Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61 2 95157410</phone>
      <fax>61 2 95158196</fax>
      <email>daviskas@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Evangelia Daviskas</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory and Sleep Medicine, 11 West Building 75, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, Missenden Road, Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>612 95157410</phone>
      <fax>61 2 95158196</fax>
      <email>daviskas@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Evangelia Daviskas</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory and Sleep Medicine, 11 West Building 75, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, Missenden Road, Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61 2 95157410</phone>
      <fax>61 2 95158196</fax>
      <email>daviskas@ed.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>