<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362814">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000816853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Role of a drug called Montelukast, in acute asthma attack</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial to assess the effects of Oral Montelukast on forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) and peak expiratory flow rate (PEFR) in patients with acute asthma exacerbation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Not applicable</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients in the treatment arm 1 will receive oral montelukast 10 mg first dose in the ER followed by 10 mg oral dose once a day in evening for the duration of stay in the hospital</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients in the treatment arm 2 will get the placebo that will be of the same appearance (color and size) and taste as the trial medication; it will be prepared by the Hilton Pharma after being approved by Ministry of Health (MoH) Pakistan. The first dose to be given in the ER followed by once daily for a period of duration of stay in the hospital</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1:Improvement in FEV1</outcome>
      <timepoint>Bedside spirometry to be done on admission and discharge using PiKo-1 (ATS and EU electronic peak flow monitor, Ferraris Respiratory Europe Ltd., Westford SG13 7NW, UK) software which measures the PEFR and FEV1. The PiKo-1 test to be repeated three times</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2:Improvement in PEFR</outcome>
      <timepoint>Serial peak expiratory flow rate (PEFR) monitoring; 
a baseline PEFR value to be obtained on enrolment, 
then at 30, 60 and 90 minutes from the baseline value, followed by every 12 hours daily until discharge. 
A minimum of 3 readings to be obtained each time before administration of bronchodilator and the best of 3 to be taken as the final value.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1:Development of complications such as respiratory failure, cardiac arrest and/or death</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment of secondary outcomes to be done throughout the duration of hospital stay after initiation of therapy with oral montelukast sodium</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All adults (age 16 and above), presenting to the ER or clinic of Aga Khan University Hospital (AKUH) with acute asthma exacerbation will be eligible for the study. They will be included if they have one or more features suggestive of Acute asthma exacerbation according to GINA Guidelines and are hospitalized

Acute asthma exacerbation is characterized by a progressive increase in shortness of breath, cough, wheezing or chest tightness, and by a decrease in expiratory flow that can be quantified by simple measures of pulmonary function such as PEFR and FEV1. The severity of exacerbations may range from mild to life-threatening.
Hospital admission criteria will be standardized:
a.FEV1 &lt; 70% predicted or PEFR &lt; 300 L/min after receiving initial treatment in the emergency room
b.Respiratory rate &gt; 24 breaths/min
c.No improvement in symptoms like shortness of breath or wheezing</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Under 16 years of age
2.Pregnancy
3.Patients who do not consent to participate
4.History of tobacco use &gt; 10 pack years 
5.Any acute concurrent medical condition like pneumonia, congestive heart failure or pneumothorax on presentation to the ER
6.Concomitant therapy with systemic corticosteroids or le ukotriene modifiers at time of admission
7.FEV1 &gt; 70% predicted or PEFR &gt; 300 L/min
8. Acute respiratory failure requiring mechanical ventilation
9.Patients initially recruited in the study but improved after initial treatment and discharged from the ER</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All adults (age 16 and above) coming to the emergency room or outpatient clinic of Aga Khan University Hospital for acute asthma exacerbation will be evaluated by the on-call Pulmonary resident / Senior medicine resident on Pulmonary rotation

The purpose and methods of the study will be explained to him/her and consent will be obtained in writing. The patient will then be randomly allocated to either treatment group.

The study has two arms:
ARM 1:	Standard therapy + Montelukast
ARM 2:	Standard therapy + Placebo</concealment>
    <sequence>This would be a double-blinded study; neither the patient nor the doctor will know the treatment status of the patient. The AKUH pharmacy will play a pivotal role in randomization of patients. The trial coordinator at AKUH pharmacy will be the key person to maintain randomization and blinding and will be the only one to know the treatment status of the patient. As soon as a patient is enrolled in the trial, a message will be sent to the pharmacy, which will issue a code number and allot the patient to one of the treatment groups.

Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation) was used for randomization and Excel sheet was used to generate random numbers as per sample size</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/02/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <state>Sindh</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hilton Pharma (Pvt.) Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>8th floor,
Prograssive Plaza,
Beaumont road,
Karachi, 75530</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Pakistan</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hilton Pharma (Pvt.) Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>8th floor,
Prograssive Plaza,
Beaumont road,
Karachi, 75530</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Pakistan</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Aga Khan University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Stadium Road, 
P.O. Box 3500
Karachi, 74800</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Pakistan</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A randomized, double blind, placebo-controlled trial was conducted at the Aga Khan University Hospital to assess the efficacy of oral montelukast on patients of 16 years of age and above who were hospitalized with acute asthma exacerbation. The patients were given either montelukast or placebo along with standard therapy throughout the hospital stay for acute asthma. Improvements in clinical parameters along with PEFR and FEV1 were monitored.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>A randomized, double-blind placebo-controlled clinical trial of Oral Montelukast in Acute Asthma Exacerbation, World Asthma Meeting (WAM 2007), Istanbul, Turkey
ABS Zubairi, AS Haque, SJ Hussain, N Salahuddin, JA Khan</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethical Review Committee (ERC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethical Review Committee (ERC)
Aga Khan University 
Stadium Road
P.O. Box 3500
Karachi 74800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/12/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>375-Med/ERC-04</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Pakistan</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ali Bin Sarwar Zubairi</name>
      <address>Section of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine 
Department of Medicine
 Aga Khan University Hospital 
Stadium Road, P.O. Box 3500
Karachi, 74800</address>
      <phone>+92 21 3486 4685</phone>
      <fax>+92 21 3493 4294</fax>
      <email>ali.zubairi@aku.edu</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ali Bin Sarwar Zubairi</name>
      <address>Section of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine 
Department of Medicine
 Aga Khan University Hospital 
Stadium Road, P.O. Box 3500
Karachi, 74800</address>
      <phone>+92 21 3486 4685</phone>
      <fax>+92 21 3493 4294</fax>
      <email>ali.zubairi@aku.edu</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ali Bin Sarwar Zubairi</name>
      <address>Section of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine 
Department of Medicine
Aga Khan University Hospital 
Stadium Road, P.O. Box 3500
Karachi, 74800</address>
      <phone>+92 21 3486 4685</phone>
      <fax>+92 21 3493 4294</fax>
      <email>ali.zubairi@aku.edu</email>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>