<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363456">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000087752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Feasibility of using pedometer-driven walking to promote physical activity, and improve health-related quality of life among meat processing workers: randomized controlled trial. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Feasibility of using pedometer-driven walking to promote physical activity, and improve health-related quality of life among meat processing workers: randomized controlled trial. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Musculoskeletal disorders</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Promoting physical activity and improving health-related quality of life among meat processing workers</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>After randomization all participants will be attended a 30 min education session on the health benefits of being physically active, then participants in the intervention group will be received another 70 min session including 10 min walk efficacy by pedometer, 30 min exercise behaviour change and 30 min about PA booklet.  This session will be based on back 2 activity protocols and conducted by a physiotherapist and student researcher.Participants in the intervention group will use a Yamax Digi-walker W200 pedometer from the beginning of the intervention. They will be instructed on how to wear and use the pedometer (to record steps taken) by doing the following: wear the pedometer at the assigned location over the hip; wear the pedometer during all waking hours (except when bathing, swimming or going to bed at night); reset the pedometer to zero at the beginning of each day, and remove it at the end of each day, record on their step calendar the date, the total number of steps displayed on the pedometer, and the strategies used to increase physical activity that week. Participants will receive weekly e-mail reminders about his or her weeks step-count goal which aimed to gradually increase the level of activities by 5% with an additional increase from previous goal setting to reach at least 10000 steps/day at the end of the 12 week period as weel as information about the importantce of PA for health benefits . The 12 weeks pedometer-driven walking intervention will be used in this study based on self-regulation theory (SRT) and will include goal setting, feedback, educational material, and the use of a step calendar for self-monitoring. Walking will be performed for at least 5 days/week according to evidence based international guidelines that recommend adults to accumulate at least 30 min of moderate intensity activity, on at least 5 days/week, to achieve optimal health benefits Participants in both the walking (intervention) and control groups will also receive standardised educational material that consists of written and graphic information describing the importance of walking as a PA for health benefits and prevention of different diseases. At the completion of the 12 weeks both groups will again use the pedometer for one week to establish a weekly step count for comparison to baseline scores</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomly allocated to the control group will be encouraged to read the educational activity material from the booklet as well as weekly email, and will be asked to record any exercise they perform over the 12 weeks.At the completion of the 12 weeks participants will again wear the pedometer for one week and also one week during week 24 post-intervention to establish a weekly step count for comparison to baseline</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Quality of life will be measured using The Short Form 36 Version2 (SF-36v2) 
 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 12-week, and the follow-up measurement (3 months after the intervention).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity levels PAL will be measured using International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ-Short Form) and pedometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 12-week, and 3 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional capacity will be measured using The Six Minute Walk Test </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 12-week, and 3 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Blood pressure will be measured using Omron MX3 plus Blood Pressure Monitor
 

 </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 12-week, and the follow-up measurement (3 months after the intervention).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Body Mass Index will be calculated as weight divided by height squared</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 12-week, and 3 moths follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional exercise capacity will be measured using the Six Minute Walk Test (6MWT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 12-week, and 3 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>-Body Fat Percentage BF will be measured using Skinfold thickness </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 12-week, and 3 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist Circumference WC will be measured using plastic tape </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 12-week, and 3 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Currently working with Silver Fern Farms (SFF) Company-Balclutha/ Otago male or female aged 18-65 years
 Having a sedentary lifestyle 
Able to walk continuously for at least 10 minutes 
Able to read and sign an informed consent and questionnaires</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion if they participation in PA program during the last 6 months, pregnant women will be also excluded</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will initially be screened for eligibility for entry into the randomized control trial by wearing the pedometer (Yamax Digi-walker SW-200) for 7 consecutive days.  In addition, the ability of the participant to be physically able to participate in walking program will be based on the results of the physical activity readiness questionnaire (PAR-Q)</concealment>
    <sequence>After successfully completing the baseline assessment and signing the informed consent, randomization will be performed by using sealed envelopes to one of two groups. Participants will be invited to choose an envelope each containing the group name and the timetable of the study from a basket containing envelopes a half for the intervention and the other half for the control groups. Researchers and participants will be not be blinded to group allocation. The assessor for outcome measurements will be blinded to group allocation until the final assessment is achieved</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis will be performed using SPSS software 20.0, and will include descriptive data and means, confidence intervals and the standard deviation. 
A repeated-measures two-way analysis of variance ANOVA will be performed to compare between the groups for the primary outcome measurements at different time periods (baseline, 12-week, and 24-week follow-up)</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/01/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>8/03/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>58</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Dunedin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Otago
Clocktower Building
364 Leith Walk
Dunedin, 9016</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Otago
Clocktower Building
364 Leith Walk
Dunedin, 9016</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The meat processing industry is an important component of the New Zealand economy generating approximately 13% of exports and employing about 25000 people. It also has the highest risk of occupational injury and illness in NZ workplace. Physical inactivity and sedentary lifestyle are now known to elevate the risk of health problems such as cardiovascular disease, osteoporosis, depression, and musculoskeletal disorders. While these factors can impact adversely on work productivity and sick leave, they are also known to positively respond to increased physical activity. A healthier, more active work force will likely be associated with reduced sick leave, reduced injury rates and increased productivity, and national and international guidelines recommend that adults accumulate daily at least 30 min of moderate intensity activity, on at least 5 days per week, in order to achieve optimal health benefits.
As one form of physical activity, walking plays an important role in the prevention and management of chronic health disorders and can improve quality of life in the general population, and thus the use of a simple, cheap, performance driven walking intervention may be a significant step towards improving the health and lifestyle of these workers. The aim of this project is to undertake a feasibility study for an eventual randomised clinical trial (RCT) of pedometer-driven walking as an intervention to improve health-related quality of life, and increase physical activity among meat processing workers. This project will also assess the adherence to a 12-week pedometer-driven walking intervention to change sedentary lifestyle habits.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Otago
Clocktower Building
364 Leith Walk
Dunedin, 9016</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Suliman Mansi</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy 
University of Otago 
Level 3 
325 Gt King Street 
Dunedin 9016 
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)3 479 9619</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>almsu521@student.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Suliman</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy 
University of Otago 
Level 3 
325 Gt King Street 
Dunedin 9016 
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)3 479 9619</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>almsu521@student.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Suliman</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy 
University of Otago 
Level 3 
325 Gt King Street 
Dunedin 9016 
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)3 479 9619</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>almsu521@student.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>