<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364597">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001052729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Australia and New Zealand Emergency Department
Airway Registry (ANZEDAR). A multi-centre observational study of the practice of intubation in the Emergency Department (ED)
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective, multicentre, observational study of all patients undergoing endotracheal intubation in the Emergency Department, to evaluate key metrics including indication for intubation, staff seniority, techniques, number of attempts at laryngoscopy required and the rate of intubation manoeuvres and complications.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ANZEDAR</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Head Injury</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Neck or Facial Trauma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Burns/Inhalation
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Drowning</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chest Trauma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Shock due to trauma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Traumatic Cardiac Arrest</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Respiratory Failure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Airway obstruction</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anaphylaxis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac Failure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sepsis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>GI Bleed</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Seizure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stroke/ICH</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Altered mental status not due to overdose</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overdose/Ingestion
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac Arrest</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We will record the indication for intubation, staff seniority, techniques (eg induction drugs or type of laryngoscope, bougie or stylet use), number of attempts at laryngoscopy required and the rate of intubation manoevres and complications. The entire process usually lasts only a few minutes, however complications are relevant if they occur within 10 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Observational study of current practice only</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pooled data will be used for a descriptive study of the practice of intubation in Australasian EDs, with particular emphasis on the following key areas: indication for intubation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over 12 months at each site</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intubation technique (equipment and drugs used)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complications resulting from intubation - including hypoxia (Oxygen saturation &lt;93%), hypotension (requiring fluid bolus or vaso pressor agents), main stem bronchial intubation, airway trauma, vomiting, medication error or equipment failure. These are observed via clinical assessment, routine monitoring of vital signs or on chest Xray (in the case of main stem bronchial intubation). They should occur within 10 minutes of intubation in order to be reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Can ED physicians predict difficulty of laryngoscopy? - one question s was laryngoscopy predicted to be difficult? (Y/N) - this can be compared to grade of view obtained and number of attempts required to intubate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Identify behaviours towards failed intubation at different experience levels  eg SRMO/REG/CMO/Specialist. What do more senior doctors change for repeated attempts, eg technique/ laryngoscope/ patient position for a second attempt, in comparison to more junior staff? </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in rates of complication (as defined in primary outcomes) reference to pre-oxygenation techniques, drugs and patient positioning. </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impact of manual in-line stabilisation/cricoid pressure/bougie on success - do these techniques affect first pass success rate? This will be observed and recorded at the time</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Use of a pre-RSI checklist - this is marked as Y/N on the data form and its use will be compared to incidence of multiple attempts at intubation and the rate of occurrence of complications</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients requiring endotracheal intubation in the ED</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>All patients who are requiring endotracheal intubation in participating EDs over a 12-month period will be enrolled. Experience at three tertiary EDs in Sydney suggests an average rate of 170 per year per ED. This equates to 2.6 intubations per 1000 presentations (actual values = 1.73, 2.33, 3.81). Indications for intubation due to trauma at these hospitals  all major trauma centres  comprised approximately 30% of the total. At an urban district hospital ED in Sydney, 35 intubations were recorded in one year  this institution has an annual census of 24,000. This yields an intubation rate of 1.5 per 1000 presentations.

All data will be entered into Microsoft Excel 2010 (Microsoft, Redmond, WA, USA) and analysed using SPSS PASW version 18.0 (SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). Descriptive statistics will include median and inter- quartile range (IQR from the 25th to the 75th percentile). chi squared test or, as appropriate, exact tests will be used to compare groups of categorical data and to test for trends. Logistic regression analysis using the direct method will be used to calculate the odds of success of intubation on first attempt. For all analyses, actual P-values will be reported and all tests will be two-tailed. Statistically significant differences will be considered at the P &lt; 0.05 level, and 95% confidence intervals (CI) will be presented where possible.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>less than 1 hour</followup>
    <followuptype>Weeks</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/07/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Mona Vale Hospital - Mona Vale</hospital>
    <hospital>Manly Hospital - Manly</hospital>
    <hospital>Orange Health Service - Orange</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Maroondah Hospital - Ringwood East</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Gove District Hospital - Nhulunbuy</hospital>
    <hospital>Liverpool Hospital - Liverpool</hospital>
    <hospital>Broome Hospital - Broome</hospital>
    <hospital>Gladstone Hospital - Gladstone</hospital>
    <hospital>The Townsville Hospital - Douglas</hospital>
    <hospital>Rockingham General Hospital - Cooloongup</hospital>
    <hospital>Fremantle Hospital and Health Service - Fremantle</hospital>
    <hospital>Western Hospital - Footscray</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>Calvary Mater Newcastle - Waratah</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>Cairns Base Hospital - Cairns</hospital>
    <hospital>Wagga Wagga Base Hospital - Wagga Wagga</hospital>
    <hospital>Peel Health Campus - Mandurah</hospital>
    <hospital>Hornsby Ku-ring-gai Hospital - Hornsby</hospital>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Toby Fogg</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal North Shore Hospital, Reserve Road, St Leonards, NSW, 2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Emergency Care Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4, Sage Building, 67 Albert Avenue, 
Chatswood NSW 2067</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Advanced airway management is an accepted core skill of Emergency Physicians in Australasia. Rapid Sequence INtubation (RSI) is, however, a high-risk procedure that has been shown to have an increased rate of severe complications  such as failed intubation, hypoxia, hypotension or surgical airway  when it takes place in the Emergency Department (ED) in comparison to the operating theatre. The recently published Fourth National Audit of Major Complications of Airway Management in the UK reviewed severe complications associated with airway management in the ED. The authors found that a large proportion of events occurred out of hours, without consultant supervision, or without the operators following standard airway management algorithms and failing to plan for failure.

Several studies have been published that describe the performance of intubation in the EDs of North America, UK, Korea and Japan, but to date, only a single centre study has been published from an Australian ED. This study, carried out at the Royal North Shore Hospital, prompted significant changes in the practice of intubation in that ED, along with an increased educational focus on the subject, in order to improve clinical management.

This current project is being led by Dr. Toby Fogg and Dr. John Vassiliadis from the Royal North Shore Hospital ED, as a collaborative research venture with other EDs across Australasia and the Emergency Care Institute in NSW. It is a surveillance study to acquire data on the practice of intubation in the ED in order to improve the quality of care associated with this procedure. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.airwayregistry.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Fogg T, Annesley N, Hitos K, Vassiliadis J. Prospective observational study of the practice of endotracheal intubation in the emergency department of a tertiary hospital in Sydney, Australia. Emergency Medicine Australasia. 2012 Dec 6;24(6):617624.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office Level 13, Kolling Building Royal North Shore Hospital Pacific Highway ST LEONARDS NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LNR/12/HAWKE/306</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Toby Fogg</name>
      <address>Emergency Department,
Royal North Shore Hospital,
Reserve Road,
St Leonards, NSW, 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 7111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tobyfogg@mac.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Toby Fogg</name>
      <address>Emergency Department,
Royal North Shore Hospital,
Reserve Road,
St Leonards, NSW, 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 7111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tobyfogg@mac.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Toby Fogg</name>
      <address>Emergency Department,
Royal North Shore Hospital,
Reserve Road,
St Leonards, NSW, 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 7111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tobyfogg@mac.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>