<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370017">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000151437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase II  study:
Haematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation for highly active
treatment resistant  multiple sclerosis .
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase II  study:
Haematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation for highly active
treatment resistant  multiple sclerosis .
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Relapsing Remitting Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autoimmune diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients are assessed  using inclusion and exclusion criteria, specific for the highly active, treatment resistant  multiple sclerosis  in order to determine whether they are eligible for an Autologous Stem cell transplant. If eligible, all patients are given intravenous Cyclophosphamide 2g/m2 as per standard practice  followed by G-CSF 10mcg/kg for the next 10-12 days until the following Monday when stem cells are collected by taking 150-200mls of blood which is processed in the laboratory. Minimum target CD34+ stem cell collection will be 2 x 10^6/kg.
Patients will be admitted into hospital for their autologous stem cell transplant within 4-8 weeks of stem cell collection based on speed of laboratory processing to produce transplant cells. Patients will then undergo chemo-immunotherapy. 
with BEAM therapy combined with Horse ATG (Atgam). This includes intravenous administration of all the following agents carmustine 300mg/m2 on Day -6; then cytosine arabinoside 200mg/m2 /day and etoposide 200mg/m2 /day on Days -5, -4, -3, -2; then Melfalan 140mg/m2 on Day -1. Reinfusion of stem cells occurs on Day 0. This is followed by intravenous methylprednisolone 5mg/Kg /day and intravenous horse antithymocyte globulin 20mg/Kg /day on Days +1 and +2.

Standard supportive measures including hydration, antiemetics, and antimicrobial prophylaxis are followed as per institutional protocols.</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety, as measured by transplant related mortality (TRM) by day 100. This is defined as death up to 100 days post transplant, not due to the original disease following review of the medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 100 post transplant</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy of HSCT in highly active multiple sclerosis that is refractory to standard therapies. This will be assessed using standardised clinical and laboratory criteria, including MRI and EDSS.</outcome>
      <timepoint> 6months, 12months then yearly up to 5 years post transplant</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adequate organ function as measured by: Cardiac LV Ejection Fraction greater than  45%, total Lung Capacity greater than 60%, Pulmonary artery pressure less than  50mmHg, DLCO greater than or equal to 50%.
Negative serology for HBV, HCV and HIV.
Negative pregnancy test.
Able to provide informed consent and the absence of mental and cognitive deficits which can interfere with the capability of providing the informed consent.
Absence of severe chronic infection.

Specific Inclusion Criteria for multiple sclerosis
Age between 18-55   
EDSS  between 2.5-5.5 
10 years or less since first treated for MS
And meets criteria (below) on both clinical and MRI grounds, for highly active MS within the past 2 years despite ongoing use of a PBS approved therapy 
Clinical
i) a minimum of at least 1 severe relapse  with an increase in EDSS  of 1 (or 0.5 for those with pre relapse EDSS  of 5.5 or above) 	
in motor, cerebellar or brain stem deficit (or documented changes in  neurological examination consistent with these magnitudes) 	
and/or
ii)	incomplete recovery from clinically significant relapses	
	
MRI
i.	at least one  gadolinium-positive (Gd+) lesion of diameter 3 mm or greater on MRI within the past 6 months.
      or 
ii.	accumulation of at least  0.3 T2 lesions/month on two consecutive MRIs 612 months apart.

Previous Treatment with Nataluzimab is allowed but a minimum of 6 months MUST have elapsed since completion of treatment.

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Progressive forms of  multiple sclerosis with no evidence of recent disease activity on MRI.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>open label
</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>15/01/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>145 Studley Road
Heidelberg    Vic  3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Austin Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>145 Studley Road
Heidelberg   Vic 3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/a</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Over  the past 15 years a number of new treatments have proved successful in the treatment of multiple sclerosis. There a remains though a small group of patients who do not respond and who continue to have attacks despite treatment causing   further permanent neurological disability in a cumulative fashion. This disability can take the form of muscle weakness, impairing walking ability, visual loss, impaired balance, bladder and bowel dysfunction  and loss of higher intellectual faculties. Patients with aggressive forms of MS also have a shortened life span as a result of their  disease.
Haematopoietic  stem cell transplantation (HSCT) is a procedure  originally used to treat patients with blood cancers. A high dose of chemotherapy is given which not only kills the malignant cells but also normal healthy bone marrow and blood cells. In order for the patient to survive these cells must be replaced by giving the patient a stem cell infusion following the chemotherapy . The stem cells replenish the bone marrow and a new blood and immune system then grows from it. 
Over the last 15 years, HSCT has become much safer. At the same time, numerous lines of evidence have emerged suggesting that a small number of patients with severe autoimmune diseases such as MS not controlled by other treatments could also respond to treatment with HSCT. This evidence came initially from patients with a co-existent auto-immune disease (AID) including multiple sclerosis (MS) who had chemotherapy for blood tumours. It was observed that not only did their cancers remain in prolonged remission after HSCT but so did the manifestations of their autoimmune disease. 
The procedure requires an initial dose of chemotherapy with a drug called cyclophosphamide to help stem cells to be collected via a vein in the arm. Subsequently the patient is admitted  into hospital tohave high doses of chemotherapy that intensely suppresses the immune system. At this point the stem cells collected at the earlier time point are reinfused through the vein so they can re-grow a new immune system and protect the patient from the toxic effects of the chemotherapy. It takes about 14 days for the new stem cells to grow and then follow up is conducted carefully over several years to see if this method of immunosuppression and immune reconstitution prevents the reemergence of multiple sclerosis. The procedure is not without risk with the major complications of infection and death. Overall the risk of death where the procedure is done for an autoimmune disease is quoted at between 1-5 %.
The Neurology Unit  at Austin Health has conducted trials in MS since 1996 and the  Haematology Unit performs HSCT on a regular basis for patients with blood malignancies. The units morbidity and mortality results for HSCT are on par with the worlds leading hospitals. We intend to explore therapy in patients with an aggressive form of MS and then follow them in a rigorous fashion over 5 years to gauge its effectiveness.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>145 Studley Road
Heidelberg Vic 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard Macdonell</name>
      <address>Austin Health
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg Vic 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 3705</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 2153</fax>
      <email>richard.macdonell@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard Macdonell</name>
      <address>Austin Health
145 Studley Road,
Heidelberg Vic 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 3705</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 2153</fax>
      <email>richard.macdonell@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard Macdonell</name>
      <address>Austin Health
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg  Vic  3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 3705</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 2153</fax>
      <email>richard.macdonell@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard Macdonell</name>
      <address>Austin Health
145 Studley Road
Heidelberg  Vic  3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 3705</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 496 2153</fax>
      <email>richard.macdonell@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>