<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366146">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000423617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to assess a low volume meal test and a very low calorie diet in obese patients with type 2 diabetes, for the future study of bariatric surgery.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study to assess a low volume meal test to assess 
gut peptide physiology, and the tolerability and safety of a short term very low caloric restriction diet in obese patients 
with type 2 diabetes.
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111­-1154­-4243</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>12 participants will be recruited.  The study comprises 2 sub studies (study 1 and study 2) and the same 12 participants will undertake both studies.  For study 1, participants will be asked to attend our research centre on two separate days (within 7 days of eachother) where a liquid meal test will be performed.  This involves the consumption by the participant of a liquid meal (similar to yoghurt in consistency, TWOCAL HN, Abbots nutrition, fat 39.4%, carbohydrate 43%, protein 16.8%, 2 calories/ml) within 10 minutes, and the collection of blood samples immediately before and then at 10,20,30,60,90,120,150, and 180 minutes after the drink is consumed.  The volume of the liquid meal will differ between the 2 days (200ml and 50ml), and participants will be randomised as to which of the liquid meal volumes used in this study they undertake first.  

Study 2 will commence immediately after completion of the second liquid meal test for study 1, and involves participants adhering to a very low calorie diet for 4 days.  Participants will be asked to consume no food or drink (with the exception of water) for the 96 hour period from the consumption of the liquid meal through to 8am on study day 6.  They will be asked to attend our research unit daily during this time (study days 3-6) for an assessment (including a blood test) and the intravenous administration of 2000ml of dextrose solution (providing 340 calories).  At 8am on study day 6 a third liquid meal test will be performed as above before the study is completed.  The volume of the meal on consumed by each participant on study day 6 will be the same as taken on study day 2.  Adherence to the intervention will be monitored through a daily interview and assessment.</interventions>
    <comparator>Study 1 will assess the performance of a low volume meal test against a standard volume (control).  Each participant will undertake both meal tests within a 7 day period, and will thus act as their own controls.  
Study 2 will assess a number of parameters (weight, blood pressure, heart rate, kidney function, etc) for each participant during the period of caloric restriction (days 3-6) and compare these against baseline results for each participant (study day 2).  Each participant will thus act as their control, and each participant will receive the intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect of low volume meal test on gut peptide physiology when compared with standard volume.  Mean hormone level at each time point will be calculated along with the standard deviation and variance.  95% confidence intervals will be calculated.  Mean hormone levels at time point +10 through to +180 minutes will be compared to baseline results using a paired T-test.  Results will be considered statistically significant if the p value is &lt;0.05.  The area under the curve of each hormone at each time point will be calculated along with an assessment of dynamic change (delta).  The standard deviation and variance of these results will be calculated, and a comparison will be made between results at the same time point after the 50 and 200ml liquid meal tests.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week (study day 2)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect of very low calorie diet on physical examination (weight, blood pressure, heart rate)</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days (study day 6)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect of very low calorie diet on blood tests (electrolytes, renal function and hepatic function)</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 days (Study day 6)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. BMI  &gt;35 kg/m2
2. Type 2 diabetes treated with diet or tablets (Metformin and/or a Sulphonylurea) 
3. HbA1c&lt;86 mmol/mol
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Type 1 diabetes
2. Use of Insulin therapy
3. Recent significant weight change (&gt; 5 kg over past 3 months)
4. Previous bariatric surgery
5. Currently pregnant or planning pregnancy within 3 months
6. Significant medical condition which, in the view of study investigators, would make recruitment in study inappropriate.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be identified from diabetes clinics run at Wellington regional hospital.  Information regarding the study will be provided to those who show an interest in participation.  An appointment will then be made for consent to be obtained.  Once this has been confirmed, participants will be randomised to one of two study arms by means of selecting a sealed envelope containing details on allocation. Randomisation will be 1:1.  The 2 arms will differ with respect to which volume liquid meal they undertake at study day 1 and study day 2 (a standard or low volume meal)</concealment>
    <sequence>The sealed envelopes will be prepared in advance by an independent researcher, and both the participant and study investigator will be blinded to contents.  Participants will select an envelope, thus each participant will be randomly allocated to a study arm.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A randomised crossover design will be utilised in this study. Two statistical analyses will be performed on study 1 data.  Firstly, the mean hormone level at each time point will be calculated along with the standard deviation and variance.  95% confidence intervals will be calculated.  Mean hormone levels at time point +10 through to +180 minutes will be compared to baseline results using a paired T-test.  Results will be considered statistically significant if the p value is &lt;0.05.

Secondly, the area under the curve of each hormone at each time point will be calculated along with an assessment of dynamic change (delta).  The standard deviation and variance of these results will be calculated, and a comparison will be made between results at the same time point after the 50 and 200ml liquid meal tests.

For study 2, the mean of each measured parameter from study day 3 through to 6 will be compared against the respective mean from study day 2 (baseline) with the use of a paired T test.  Results that fall above or below reference laboratory/clinical ranges will be noted.

There is no published data on either a low volume meal test or the degree of caloric restriction required to allow sample size calculation.  The role of this pilot study is to assess these tools and allow future study (including of these interventions if required).


</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/05/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Endocrine, diabetes and research centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5 Grace Neill block
Wellington regional hospital
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6011</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Endocrine, diabetes and research centre
Wellington regional hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5 Grace Neill block
Wellington regional hospital
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a study of 2 research tools, the availability of which will allow more detailed studies exploring the mechanism underlying the improvements in diabetes control seen very early after bariatric (weight loss) surgery.  Participants will be asked to undergo 2 liquid meal tests to assess whether a small volume meal test performs as well as a standard volume meal test in the assessment of gut hormones.  Participants will also be calorie restricted for 4 days under supervision.  The degree of calorie restriction is approximately 15% of the recommended daily intake and is comparable to the intake of calories seen within the first 5 days following bariatric surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern B ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
C/- MEDSAFE Level 6, Deloitte House
10 Brandon Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/NTB/35</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jeremy Krebs</name>
      <address>Endocrine, diabetes, and research centre
Level 5 Grace Neill Block
Wellington regional hospital,
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6011</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8062140</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jeremy.krebs@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Carroll</name>
      <address>Endocrine, diabetes, and research centre
Level 5 Grace Neill Block
Wellington regional hospital,
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6011</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8062140</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.carroll@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Carroll</name>
      <address>Endocrine, diabetes, and research centre
Level 5 Grace Neill Block
Wellington regional hospital,
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6011</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8062140</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.carroll@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Carroll</name>
      <address>Endocrine, diabetes, and research centre
Level 5 Grace Neill Block
Wellington regional hospital,
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6011</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8062140</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.carroll@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>