<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="737">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000476639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Individual Medication Effectiveness Tests Comparing Celecoxib (encapsulated Celebrex) with Panadol Extend for Relief of Osteoarthritis.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Individual Medication Effectiveness Tests Comparing Celecoxib (encapsulated Celebrex) with Panadol Extend for Relief of Osteoarthritis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This single patient (n of 1) Individualised Medication Effectiveness Test (IMET) is a randomised, double-blind, cross-over comparison of celecoxib (200mg ro 400mg daily) and Panadol Extend (3990mg paracetamol daily) within an individual patient. The patient will undergo three pairs of treatment periods. The duration of each treatment period will be two weeks (so each pair will be four weeks), making a total of twelve weeks. During one period of each pair the patient will take celecoxib and a Panadol Extend placebo, and during the other period they will take Panadol Extend and a celecoxib placebo. The order of drugs in each cycle will be determined by random allocation. The choice of initial therapy will be balanced in blocks of four, to ensure that equivalent numbers start the IMET on each of the two drugs. Patient and practitioners will be blinded to which treatment the patients are taking. 

The patient will keep careful track of their symptoms by recording them in a special diary. If at any time during the patient feels worse, that treatment period can be terminated, and they can go on to the next treatment period. 

Upon the completion of the study, the timing of each active treatment will be revealed. After looking at the symptom scores recorded on the patient's report and the analysis provided by the IMET Service, the doctor and patient decide together which drug is of greatest benefit. If the patient chooses, they can then continue on that drug, confident that it is the most effective.</interventions>
    <comparator>Panadol Extend Placebo</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Identification of non-responders to chronic therapy through routine Individual Medication Effectiveness Tests (IMETs) can reduce adverse events, unnecessary drug therapy and drug expenditure while maintaining benefits to responders.  Participants will be asked to consent to follow-up of PBS prescribing (via the HIC) and will be contacted regarding their medication regime.  IMETs are resource intensive and their cost effectiveness varies across drugs and patients. This project will evaluate the economic feasibility of routine IMETs. The detailed resource use and outcome data collected nationally will be used to inform: a protocol for cost-effective targeting and administration of such trials; and a business case to inform policy makers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be asked to consent to follow-up of PBS prescribing (via the HIC) and will be contacted regarding their medication regime at 3, 6, 9, and 12 months post-IMET.   </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To facilitate the best outcome for the health needs of patients with certain chronic conditions, by allowing doctors to obtain a deeper understanding of what these health needs are and therefore to prescribe appropriately.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Any adult patient with a clinical diagnosis of osteoarthritis with pain of at least a month's duration, of sufficient severity to warranty consideration of long-term Cox-2 inhibitor or paracetamol use, in the opinion of the attending medical practioner. - Either the attending medical practitioner or the patient is uncertain of the effectiveness of their medication for osteoarthritis.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous sensitivity to cox-2 inhibitors, paracetamol, or aspirin- Any patient with contraindications to prescribing of celecoxib or paracetamol- Presence of concomitant disease which will increase the risk of side-effects- Treatment with corticosteroids by joint injection within the previous two months.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/12/2003</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>59</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Health Ministers' Advisory Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>GlaxoSmithKline</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>United Kingdom</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Michael Yelland</name>
      <address>Department of Primary Health Care
School of Medicine
Griffith University
Logan Campus
University Drive
Meadowbrook QLD 4131</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33821358</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 33821338</fax>
      <email>m.yelland@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Norma McNairn</name>
      <address>Individualised Medication Effectiveness Test (IMET) Service
University of Queensland
Level 2 Edith Cavell Building
Herston QLD 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 33464835</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 33655130</fax>
      <email>n.mcnairn@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>