<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335847">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000834055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Bioequivalence study comparing AndroForte 5 (Registered Trademark (R))  and Testogel (R) 1%</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open-label, phase 2, single centre, randomised, crossover design bioequivalence study of AndroForte (R) 5 Compared With Testogel (R) 1% in Hypogonadal Men</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1116-5976</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Testosterone replacement therapy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypogonadism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>AndroForte 5
white oil-in-water cream containing testosterone 50mg/mL
2ml of cream to be topically applied to torso once daily for 30 days.  
Washout period 7 - 10 days between crossover treatments</interventions>
    <comparator>Testogel 1% is testosterone dissolved in a hydroalcoholic solution.
Each sachet contains 50mg of testosterone (in 5g gel). 
The contents of one sachet to be topically applied to torso once daily for 30 days.  
Washout period 7 - 10 days between crossover treatments.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess Pharmacokinetic (PK) variables: Area under the curve (AUC), Average concentration (Cavg), Maximum plasma concentration (Cmax), Time to maximum plasma concentration (Tmax), % Fluctuation (with and without baseline correction) for AndroForte 5 and Testogel 1% on Day 1 and Day 30 by measuring serum testosterone &amp; dihydrotestosterone.</outcome>
      <timepoint>PK serial sampling will be performed at -15 , -5, 0 min prior and 2, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 12, 16 and 24 hours post administration on Day 1 and 30 of Period I and II of  each treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the bioavailability of AndroForte 5 as compared to Testogel 1%, by measuring serum testosterone levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>PK serial sampling will be performed at -15 , -5, 0 min prior and 2, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 12, 16 and 24 hours post administration on Day 1 and 30 of Period I and II of  each treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the proportion of samples within percentage testosterone target (% T) or outside target blood testosterone range.   Percentage above testosterone  [%AT], percentage below testosterone  [%BT], by measuring serum testosterone levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>PK serial sampling will be performed at -15 , -5, 0 min prior and 2, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 12, 16 and 24 hours post administration on Day 1 and 30 of Period I and II of  each treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the profiles of other reproductive hormones :- changes in blood dihydrotestosterone (DHT), estradiol (E2) and Sex Hormone Binding Globulin (SHBG). Suppression of blood Lutenising Hormone (LH) &amp; Follicile Stimulating Hormone (FSH), by measuring reproductive hormone levels throughout the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>after Day 1, Day 15  and Day 30 of each treatment period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the safety and tolerability of  AndroForte 5.  Safety biochemistry and haematology blood samples will be collected &amp; adverse events will recorded throughout the study.

The most common side effects experienced in 10% of subjects treated with Testogel (R) 1% and AndroForte (R) 5 are:
* Skin reactions at the application site - e.g. irritation, redness, dry or stinging skin 
* Acne
Less common side effects, occurring between 1-10% of subjects treated include: 
Headaches, dizziness, nausea, retention of salt and water, loss of head hair, increased body hair, changes in your mood &amp; deepening of the voice</outcome>
      <timepoint>after Day 1, Day 15  and Day 30 of each treatment period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life (SF-36) and Mood, sexual function (Sexual Desire Inventory (SDI), International Index of Erectile Function (IIEF) assessment.  Participants will complete these questionnaires throughout the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at Day 1 and Day 30 of each treatment period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Established androgen deficiency (primary or secondary)  (including newly diagnosed persons) requiring androgen replacement therapy as determined by current Pharmaceutical Benefit Scheme (PBS) guidelines (laboratory results demonstrating that Australian guidelines have been met must be available for review)
                            Or 
Established androgen deficiency (primary or secondary) and currently receiving androgen replacement therapy (at an equivalent dose as outlined in this protocol) and willing to withdraw from current androgen replacement therapy and observe the necessary washout period prior to entering the study as outlined below: 
	
- 7 days for transdermal testosterone or oral testosterone undecanoate
-  6-12 weeks for intramuscular injections of testosterone esters
-  6 months since last dose for subcutaneous testosterone pellets or testosterone undecanoate</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Untreated obstructive sleep apnoea as determined by the Berlin Sleep Apnoea questionnaire 

* Clinically significant non-malignant disease including, active clinically significant infection (requiring systemic antibiotics), cerebrovascular event or transient ischemic attack within 12 months prior to randomisation or major surgery within 3 months of randomisation

 
* Active cardiac disease defined as one or more of the following  
- New York Heart Association functional classification of heart failure  of greater than or equal to 2 or symptomatic angina
- Uncontrolled arrhythmias, or arrhythmias deemed clinically significant by the investigator
- Myocardial infarction, cardiac stenting or angioplasty in past 6 months 

* Prior history of prostate cancer or other malignancy, which could affect compliance with the protocol or interpretation of study results. Cancer(s) treated with curative intent (including non-melanoma skin cancer) are eligible if disease-free for at least 2 years.

* Any form of respiratory failure requiring oxygen supplementation 


* Evidence of a significant medical illness, abnormal laboratory finding or adverse event from prior androgen replacement therapy that would, in the investigators judgment, make the participant inappropriate for this study 

* Receipt of therapy with another investigational drug within 4 weeks of Day 1 or current enrolment in another clinical trial


* Current smoker or past smoker who has ceased smoking within the past year
 
* Elevated blood pressure (greater than or equal to 140/90mmHg) at screening or a diagnosis of hypertension unless on stable therapy for at least 3 months and currently normotensive


* History of mental illness (requiring ongoing psychotropic medications)

* Active substance abuse 


* Known to be human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or hepatitis B surface antigen positive
 
* Planned elective surgery within 1 month of randomisation or during the study period


* Generalised skin disease on the abdomen that may be affected by or affect testosterone absorption at the site of transdermal absorption  e.g. psoriasis

* Body Mass Index (BMI) of less than 18 kg/m2 or more than 35 kg/m2 as either extreme may result in hypogonadism responsive to normalisation of weight


* Currently on medications, herbal remedies or vitamins/juices (e.g. grapefruit juice) known to 
- Be strong inducers/ inhibitors of Cytochrome 3A4 (CYP 3A4) 
- Affect the production (e.g. opiates, gonadotropin releasing hormone (GnRH) agonists) or action (e.g. spironolactone) of androgens 
- Affect the production of SHBG (e.g. thyroxine, insulin, growth hormone, antiepileptics), unless the dose has been stable for at least 3 months and will remain so.
 
* Dementia or altered cognitive function that would interfere with the participants safety or compliance to the study procedures

* Use of topical salves or topical steroids to abdomen within past 7 days 


* Participants unwilling to adhere to the guidelines in regard to intimate contact post application

* Known allergy to  almonds


* Participants experiencing severe voiding symptoms as identified on the International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS) questionnaire

* Men who are able to father a child who are unwilling to use an acceptable method of contraception during the trial</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is an open study &amp; eligible participants will be randomly assigned the order in which they will receive the 2 treatment options prior to crossing over to the other treatment period. The hospital pharmacist will hold the allocation schedule &amp; dispense according to this schedule.</concealment>
    <sequence>centrally randomisation by computer</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Bio-equivalence</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lawley Pharmaceuticals</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Lawley Phrmaceuticals
Unit 2, 15a Harrogate Street
West Leederville
Perth
Western Australia 
6007</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lawley Pharmaceuticals</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 2, 15a Harrogate Street
West Leederville
Perth
Western Australia 
6007</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study will determine if AndroForte (R) 5 (testosterone cream) is bioequivalent to Testogel (R) 1% (testosterone gel) for the treatment of men with low testosterone levels.  Participants will apply the cream or gel to their torso for 30 days during each treatment period and at the start and finish of each of the treatment periods, participants will provide blood samples at pre-determined time points for the measurement of blood testosterone levels.  This study aims to establish that AndroForte (R) 5 is equally effective as Testogel (R) 1% (considered to be the standard comparator for transdermal testosterone worldwide), in increasing the testosterone levels in men with low testosterone to within the normal circulating range.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide 
SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/08/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Gary Mulholland</name>
      <address>C/O Lawley Pharmaceuticals,
Unit 2, 15a Harrogate Street
West Leederville
Western Australia 
6007</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)421 491 727</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)8 9304 2565</fax>
      <email>gmctcwa@tpg.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michael Buckley</name>
      <address>Lawley Pharmaceuticals
Unit 2, 15a Harrogate Street
West Leederville, WA 6007</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)8 9388 0096</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)8 9388 0098</fax>
      <email>michaelb@lawleypharm.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Gary Mulholland</name>
      <address>C/O Lawley Pharmaceuticals,
Unit 2, 15a Harrogate Street
West Leederville
Western Australia
6007</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)421 491 727</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)8 9304 2565</fax>
      <email>gmctcwa@tpg.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>