<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308322">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/03/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/05/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000358044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Sexually Transmitted Infections (STI) in Remote communities: ImproVed &amp; Enhanced primary health care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Sexually Transmitted Infections (STI) in Remote communities: ImproVed &amp; Enhanced primary health care - A randomised community trial to reduce STIs in remote Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander communities, comparing clinical care enhanced with a Sexual Health Quality Improvement Program with standard clinical care</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>STRIVE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sexually transmitted infections</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sexually transmitted infections</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention, called the Sexual Health Quality Improvement Program will involve the following components: 

1. Development of an action plan including goals and strategies to improve clinical service delivery for diagnosis and management of bacterial STIs to reach best practice targets. STRIVE Coordinators will meet with participating primary health services annually for a day to undertake a site assessment,  develop an Action Plan tailored to the individual service and discuss goals and strategies for the Action Plan. 

2. Six-monthly collaborative feedback meetings to discuss progress on the Action Plan. STRIVE Coordinators will meet with health service management to discuss the Action Plan and progress towards the goals and strategies developed. 

3. Quantitative data reports will be provided to health services every 6 months showing progress towards best practice targets. 

4. Training - STRIVE coordinators will provide staff with training in quality improvement and basic research skills and encourage further training in sexual health. Training requirements will be discussed at the collaborative feedback meetings. 

5. Incentives payments based on progress towards the best practice targets. Opportunities exist for each health service to receive a total incentive payment of between $10,000 and $30,000 per year. Incentives will be calculated from the quantitative reports and will be paid 6 monthly. 

Best practice episodes and targets:

Best practice episodes - 
1. Offer STI screening to sexually active 14 - 34 year olds
2. Treat quickly a) Symptomatic STI infections - treat immediately b) Asymptomatic STI infections - treat within 7 days of the positive result being received from the laboratory
3. Test for re-infection at 3 months. For people with STI infection, follow up and test at 3 months after treatment
4. Contact referral. For people with STI infection, test and treat their partner/s

Best practice targets - 
1. 80% of the resident population aged 16 - 34 tested annually
2. 95% of syndromically diagnosed infections treated immediately
3. 80% of asymptomatic STI infections - treated within 7 days of the positive result being recieved from the laboratory
4. 80% of STI infections - re-tested within 3 months of treatment
5. 50% of STI infections - the named sexual partner/s is documented to be treated within 14 days

The trial is cluster-randomised. The duration of the intervention will depend on when the cluster, in which the health service falls, is randomised. For clusters that are randomised in year 1, the intervention will continue for three years. For clusters randomised in year 2, the intervention will continue for 2 years. For clusters randomised in year 3, the intervention will continue for 1 year.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control trial sites will undergo standard STI care. Standard care is per the following clinical guidelines: For the Northern Territory - CARPA (Central Australian Rural Practitioners Association) Reference Manual 5th Edition, Minymaku Kutju Tjukurpa  Women's Business Manual 4th Edition. For Far North Queensland - The Primary Clinical Care Manual, the Queensland STI Clinical Guidelines, Clinical Practice Guidelines for Sexual and Reproductive Health Nursing Officers. For Western Australia - Guidelines for Managing Sexually Transmitted Infections - The Silver Book. These guidelines include screening, assessment, treatment, management, prevention and reporting recommendations. Clinicians are recommended to follow these guidelines on a case by case basis.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Best practice service delivery involving the diagnosis and treatment of the three STIs (chlamydia, gonorrhoea and trichomonas) in Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander people, defined as: STI testing coverage, STI testing uptake, 3-month test for re-infection, time to treatment interval and named sexual contacts treated. This will be assessed by analysing results from health services' data reports. These data will indicate if health services have achieved the determined best practice service delivery levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Annually and at completion of the trial</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of chlamydia, gonorrhoea or trichomonas among 16-34 year olds. This will be measured using an annual prevalence survey: 50 male and 50 female Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islanders aged 16 - 34 residing in each cluster will be opportunisitically tested when they present at the health service.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Annually and at completion of the trial</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The profile of health services defined as the characteristics of the site, including STI management practices. This will be determined through the initial site assessment process, which will include collection of demographic information and a review of sexual health clinical care. The site assessment results will be analysed to create a de-identified profile of trial clusters.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the completion of the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Barriers and motivators related to the uptake of STI clinical services. This will be assessed through qualitative and quantitative data from the health services and systems assessment questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the completion of the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trial acceptability and transferability to health services staff and stakeholders. This will be assessed through qualitative interviews with key stakeholders and health service management and clinical staff.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the completion of the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Non-trial events that have a potential to impact on the extent of STIs in trial clusters. STRIVE investigators will maintain a log of other sexual health activities occurring during STRIVE and will analyse this in relation to the potential impact on STIs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Communities that meet the following criteria: - Considered remote by the Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS) - With a resident population of at least 100 Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander people aged 16 - 34 years - Community and health services willing and able to provide access to de-identified clinical data - Health services able to sustain data collection, consistent with trial protocol</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>34</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Communities where there is a diverse range of health services that are accessed by Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islanders within the same location</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The trial is cluster randomised using a stepped-wedge design. The unit of randomisation is a geographic cluster. Each cluster includes at least one community and primary health service, and is defined by known social and cultural networks. The randomisation sequence for each trial clusters will be held by the statistician at the National Centre in Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) Epidemiology and Clinical Research. When a trial cluster is ready for randomisation, the STRIVE coordinator will contact the statistician via email and the statistician will then inform the STRIVE coordinator if this clusters will receive the Sexual Health Quality Improvement Program or will be a control cluster.

Randomisation will occur over a period of three years. At the start of each year, seven of the trial clusters will be randomised to the intervention, the following year a further seven will be randomised, and in the third year, the final seven will be randomised such that by the end of the trial, all clusters will have received the intervention.</concealment>
    <sequence>Geographical areas (trial clusters) will be randomised to the intervention or control strategies using a minimisation approach. This will maximise the balance across several baseline variables. These variables will include: - Estimated baseline STI prevalence in each geographical area; - Size - Geographical region - Prevalence The randomisation sequence will be generated at NCHECR once the estimated baseline STI prevalence and testing rates are available</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Community randomised, stepped wedge</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>21</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>UNSW KENSINGTON CAMPUS
The University of New South Wales
SYDNEY
NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Menzies School of Health Research, Charles Darwin University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 41096
Casuarina NT 0811</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Northern Territory (NT) Department of Health</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>87 Mitchell Street
Darwin NT 0800</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Central Australian Aboriginal Congress</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>25 Gap Rd 
Alice Springs NT 0870</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Aboriginal Medical Services Alliance Northern Territory</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Tourism House
43 Mitchell Street
Darwin NT 0800</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Apunipima Cape York Health Council Aboriginal Corporation</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>186 McCoombe Street
Bungalow
Cairns QLD 4870</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Kimberley Aboriginal Medical Services Council</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Corner of Anne and Dora Street
PO Box 1377
Broome WA 6725</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Kimberley Population Health Unit</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Yamamoto House
Napier Terrace
Broome WA 6725</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Government body</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Cape York Health Service District</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Corner Northern and Central Avenue
Rocky Point
Weipa QLD 4874</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of South Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The University of Melbourne</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Melbourne
Victoria 3010</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>STRIVE  Sexually Transmitted infections in Remote communities: ImproVed and enhanced primary health care services is a new trial which aims to reduce levels of STIs in 21 or more participating trial clusters  over a five year period. STRIVE is 5 year project in partnership between the National Centre in HIV Epidemiology and Clinical Research, the Menzies School of Health Research and government and community organisations in NT, WA and QLD. Funding for the trial was awarded by the National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC Project Grant, Application ID: 568806, 2009-2013).

Proposed clusters of communities will be located in the NT, WA and QLD. 

STRIVE will test whether the development and then implementation of a Sexual Health Quality Improvement Program tailored for primary health care centres will improve STI service delivery and assist these services on reaching best practice in STI control.  STRIVE will also provide incentive payments for achieving aspects of best practice in STI care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Australian Aboriginal Health Information Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>189 Royal Street
East Perth WA 6004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/12/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00292</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/11/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cairns Base Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 902
Cairns QLD 4870</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00157</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/11/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Australian Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 4066, Alice Springs, NT 0871</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00155</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/11/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of Northern Territory Department of Health and Families and Menzies School of Health Research</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 41096
CASUARINA NT 0811</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00153</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/11/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Australian Country Health Service Board Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>WA Country Health Service ? Head Office (South West Branch)
1st Floor Bunbury Tower
61 Victoria Street 
BUNBURY WA 6230</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>EC00261</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/04/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales Human Research Ethics Committee (B)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW Research Services
Rupert Myers Building, Level 3
The University of New South Wales  
NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/04/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00153</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/04/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor John Kaldor</name>
      <address>CFI Building, Corner West and Boundary Streets Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 2 9385 0900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jkaldor@kirby.unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr James Ward</name>
      <address>CFI Building, Corner West and Boundary Streets Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 2 9385 0900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jward@kirby.unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms Skye McGregor</name>
      <address>CFI Building, Corner West and Boundary Streets Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 2 9385 0900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>smcgregor@kirby.unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>