<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363093">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000067774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The 'Healthy Dads, Healthy Kids' community effectiveness trial: Evaluation of a community-based healthy lifestyle program for overweight fathers and their children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The 'Healthy Dads, Healthy Kids' community effectiveness trial for overweight fathers and their children in four local government areas of the Hunter Valley Region, NSW, Australia with the primary outcome of reducing body weight in fathers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1135-2156</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>N/A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity treatment/prevention</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is the second phase of a two phase project. Phase 1 (a community RCT) is described in ACTRN12610000608066 http://www.anzctr.org.au/trial_view.aspx?ID=335368 


Phase 2 will follow the same methodology as Phase 1 and will be conducted in 5 Local Government Areas of the Hunter Valley Region, NSW, Australia (Maitland, Singleton, Muswellbrook, Scone, Cessnock).  In short, the duration of the intervention is 8 sessions over 12 weeks. The intervention involves fathers attending eight 90 minute face to face information sessions (including 4 interactive sessions with their children). The program includes: physical activity components; dietary and nutritional information; a self-monitoring component. More specifically program sessions focus on: 1) sustainable weight loss for men; identification of healthy and unhealthy lifestyle behaviours and explanation of the use of role modelling and positive reinforcement; 2) father and child engagement in a variety of physical activities to develop child's confidence and ability in performing various fundamental movement skills; 3) the importance of fathers for children's physical activity levels; strategies for encouraging physical activity in children; 4) another session for father and child engagement in a variety of physical activities; 5) nutritional information to encourage healthy eating for fathers and children; 6) Father and child games and fun physical activities as well as a focus on positive family traditions and rituals 7) sustaining healthy eating patterns for the family; 8) father and child engagement activities and closure.

 Fathers will also receive behavioural procedures over the course of the program via the use of the online website www.calorieking.com.au. The key constructs of social cognitive theory will be operationalised in the sessions (self efficacy, self monitoring, goal setting and social support). 

When translating evidence-based programs into real-world settings, ongoing modifications are required based on the unique characteristics of the settings and populations. Modifications will be made to the program based on both outcome and process evaluation from the community RCT (phase 1) and each subsequent program implementation in 2011 and 2012 and these will be documented. The goal will be to develop a comprehensive model of a real-world intervention for application in communities through updating materials, developing standardized train-the-trainer education and resources and ongoing evaluation of the implementation of the intervention with a final evaluation conducted in 2012/13.</interventions>
    <comparator>The program will be evaluated using a non-randomized, prospective design without a control group.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fathers' body weight (kg) as measured on a set of electonic scales which are regularly checked and calibrated as necessary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference for fathers and children (cm) using non-extensible steel tapes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body Mass Index (BMI) for fathers calculated using the formula: weight in kilograms divided by the square of height in meters. Children's Body Mass Index z-score (BMI-z) will be calculated similarly using standard deviation for children's scores related to age and gender. Children's body weight (kg) will be measured using the same protocol as for the fathers and height of fathers and children will be calculated using a portable stadiometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity of fathers is measured using a modified version of the Godin Leisure-Time Exercise Questionnaire (GLTEQ) and the Children's Leisure Activities Study Survey (CLASS) questionnaire is completed by the father with the eldest child as the reference.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary intake for fathers. A modified version of the Australian Eating Survey relating to 8 key nutritional messages is completed by fathers. This questionnaire is also completed by fathers as proxy for their eldest child.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting strategies: Parental engagement is measured using a modified version of the Parental Engagement survey used in Phase 1. Fathers will complete the questionnaire in reference to their eldest child. Parenting strategies for physical activity and nutrition are measured using a validated questionnaire. Attitudes to rough and tumble play are assessed via a semi-structured interview with a limited number of participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For the questionnaires:  At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up. The semi-structured interview is to occur prior to the baseline assessment in a select number of participants.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sedentary behaviour measured in fathers using the Modified sitting questionnaire and proxy-report for children (completed by fathers) using the Indoor based activites section of the CLASS questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary portion size is reported by fathers using photographs from the Dietary Questionnaire for Epidemiological Studies Version 2</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol Consumption is self reported by fathers using a Modified Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test 2009</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Overweight or obese fathers (BMI over 25kg/m2) of children aged 5-12 years (primary school age).  Medical approval to participate must be obtained when indicated by health screening.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Lack of a medical clearance from treating doctor if the Exercise and Sports Science Australia Adult Pre-Exercise Screening Tool identifies the participant requires a medical clearance prior to undertaking exercise.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will complete a phone eligibility screen with a research assistant and also a pre-exercise screening questionnaire. If a participant meets the eligibility criteria they will be enrolled in the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>n/a</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2320</postcode>
    <postcode>2333</postcode>
    <postcode>2337</postcode>
    <postcode>2336</postcode>
    <postcode>2330</postcode>
    <postcode>2325</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Philip Morgan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Priority Research Centre in Physical Activity and Nutrition
School of Education 
University of Newcastle
University Drive 
Callaghan NSW 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hunter Medical Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hunter Medical Research Institute (HMRI) Clinical Research Centre John Hunter Hospital Lookout Road, New Lambton Postal address: Locked Bag 1 Hunter Region Mail Centre NSW 2310</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is well established that parents of primary school aged children substantially influence the food and physical activity home environment through behaviours, attitudes, feeding styles and role modelling. However, the contribution of fathers influence on childrens physical activity and eating behaviour is often overlooked.The Healthy Dads Healthy Kids (HDHK) project is based on research that shows the eating habits and exercise routine of fathers and father figures influence the ways in which the whole family approaches their health. The program was developed and successfully trialled at the University of Newcastle, with trial results showing that the major aims of HDHK were achieved. These were (i) to help overweight/obese fathers achieve a healthy weight, and (ii) to improve the activity and eating behaviours of their children (using fathers as the key agents of behaviour change). Phase 1 of the HDHK community effectiveness trial (http://www.anzctr.org.au/trial_view.aspx?ID=335368 
) was to evaluate the impact of the program in a community setting  with trained local facilitators, employing a RCT design. The intention of this current project (Phase 2) is to research the effectivenss of the HDHK program on a larger scale community roll-out using a non-randomized, prospective design.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://healthydadshealthykids.com.au/</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Morgan, P.J., Lubans, D.R., Plotnikoff, R.C., Callister, R., Burrows, T., Fletcher, R., Okely, A.D. Young, M., Miller, A., Clay, V. Lloyd, A. &amp; Collins, C.E. (2011). The Healthy Dads, Healthy Kids community effectiveness trial: study protocol of a community-based healthy lifestyle program for fathers and their children, BMC Public Health, 11: 876.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle, Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Services/Research Office

University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan New South Wales 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/04/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2010-0045</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/02/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Philip Morgan</name>
      <address>Priority Research Centre in Physical Activity and Nutrition
School of Education 
University of Newcastle
University Drive 
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 29217265</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 7407</fax>
      <email>philip.morgan@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Philip Morgan</name>
      <address>Priority Research Centre in Physical Activity and Nutrition
School of Education 
University of Newcastle
University Drive 
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 29217265</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 7407</fax>
      <email>philip.morgan@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kristen Saunders</name>
      <address>Priority Research Centre in Physical Activity and Nutrition
School of Education 
University of Newcastle
University Drive 
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49217787</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kristen.saunders@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Philip Morgan</name>
      <address>Priority Research Centre in Physical Activity and Nutrition
School of Education 
University of Newcastle
University Drive 
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 29217265</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 7407</fax>
      <email>philip.morgan@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>