<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373405">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001200370p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>He Pataka Marohi: will provision of cheap or free food increase vegetable and fruit consumption for Maori households</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>a 2x2 randomized trial intervention to investigate the difference in vegetable and fruit consumption between ad libitum (at cost) and ad libitum (free), with or without education in Maori households</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1200-1047 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>nutrition deficiency</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study design follows a four-arm, randomised trial, superiority approach. There are 2 main components:
	Food packages: all groups will be offered weekly fruit (3 serves) and vegetable (6 serves) packages up to the recommended number of servings for the composition of the household. For example:
o	For a family of 2 adults and 3 children, up to 15 serves of fruit and 30 serves of vegetables can be ordered
	Wananga: eight interactive wananga (seminar) will be held, including topics such as, how to cook and prepare provided foods, how to grow foods, sources of cheap or free foods. The wananga will be on average 3 hours long

The food packages will be ordered and delivered every week over 26 weeks. Eight wananga will be held during that 26 weeks, as suitable. 

	Forty households will be randomly assigned to one of four groups. 
	Group 1 will receive the Food Package free; 
	Group 2 will receive the Food package free and wananga; 
	Group 3 can order weekly packs of NZ$5 worth of fruit and vegetables up to the maximum number of packages based on the size of the family.  
	Group 4 can order weekly packs of NZ$5 worth of fruit and vegetables up to the maximum number of packages based on the size of the family and wananga. 

Each week, all participants will be contacted to order food, which will be recorded in a spreadsheet. Each week, a group reminder will be sent each week, in addition to follow up as preferred by the participants. If participants are not responding to contact attempts, a NC (not contactable) will be recorded in the spreadsheet. Every participant will be contacted every week, irrespective of if they responded the previous week. 

A co-ordinator, currently working with Te Wakahuia o Manawatu Trust (TWMT), will be employed to support research work and organise the intervention. The job will include:
	Contacting food providers, sourcing weekly foods, organising pick up, packing and delivery. 
	Organise recruitment
	Provide support with designing research material
	Organise data collection
	Organise wananga
In addition, up to 2 people will be employed to pick up, package, deliver and return weekly foods. 

Food supply
All groups will receive a package of fruit and vegetables over a period of six-months. Each week households will be contacted to order fruit and vegetables. The order will be delivered to the door of each participating household and at the same time food not consumed from the preceding week will be retrieved.
Wananga 
In addition to the supply of food, eight wananga (group education) will be held to provide the following to groups 2 and 4:
-	Recipes for cooking foods
-	Methods for preparing and cooking uncommon, inexpensive foods such as legumes
-	Assistance with setting up a vegetable garden
The wananga will be facilitated by enlisted local experts and will be held in a facility local to participants.


</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 3 can order weekly packs of NZ$5 worth of fruit and vegetables up to the maximum number of packages based on the size of the family</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of vegetable servings consumed. 
Each week participants will order fruit and vegetables, which will be delivered to them in a food container. At the delivery of the order, any fruit or vegetables left over from the previous week, will be collected. 
The servings consumed each week will be calculated: 
Number of servings consumed = number of vegetable servings delivered  number of vegetable servings returned. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weekly, for the duration of the intervention (that is 26 weeks), and analysed after the completion of the intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of fruit servings consumed. 
Each week participants will order fruit and vegetables, which will be delivered to them in a food container. At the delivery of the order, any fruit or vegetables left over from the previous week, will be collected. 
The servings consumed each week will be calculated: 
Number of servings consumed = number of fruit servings delivered  number of fruit servings returned. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weekly, for the duration of the intervention (that is 26 weeks), and analysed after the completion of the intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost of food provision
Each week, the following data will be collected in order to assess the weekly cost of providing foods:
	Hours worked on sourcing, collecting, packaging and delivering foods
	Hours worked on collecting orders
	Cost of communicating to obtain orders
	Number of kilometres driven 
	Cost of purchasing foods
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Collected weekly, and analysed after the completion of the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Semi-structured face-to-face Interviews will be conducted by an independent contracted person, with a subsample of household, to conduct Intervention evaluation, which encompasses:
o	Suitability of intervention
o	Potential improvements to intervention 
o	decisions about consuming fruit and vegetables, in the household
o	interest in future interventions 
o	perspectives of the barriers and facilitators of fruit and vegetable consumption
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The inclusion criteria includes: 
-	Households identifying as Maori 
-	the main participant being minimum 18 years old and have at least one child (less than 18 years of age), living in their household 
-	In Highbury area in Palmerston North, Manawatu, NZ
-	Likely to be able to remain in the study for 6 months  
-	If allocated to the at-cost condition, likely to be able to pay for a $5 pack of food most weeks
-	In high need
o	high need will be established through motivational interviewing technique conducted by recruiter. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Food secure</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation to condition will be concealed from participants at the time they agree to participate. Once a participant has agreed to participate, they will be given a sealed opaque envelop with their allocation. The allocation will be concealed to researchers and intervention staff until the participant opens the envelop. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome of this study will be the product of: 
SerDel (servings delivered)  SerRet (servings retrieved) = SerCon (Servings consumed) 

This outcome variable will be adjusted by number of household members and number of children. 
The primary outcome will be analysed using generalised linear mixed models analysis as the repeated measures design of the study works well within this model.  Randomised and fixed effects will be enacted for this analysis.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Manawatu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Geoff Kira</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Public Health
Massey University
Massey Wellington Campus
Block 4, Level E
Wallace St
Mt Cook
Wellington 6021</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3 - ProCARE Building, Grafton Mews, at 110 Stanley Street (GPS: 50 Grafton Road), Grafton, Auckland 1010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Te Waka Huia a Manawatu Trust</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>56 Pembroke Street
Palmerston North 4412</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Anette Kira</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Pohangina
Manawatu
C/O School of Public Health
Massey University
Massey Wellington Campus
Block 4, Level E
Wallace St
Mt Cook
Wellington 6021</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In developed countries, such as Aotearoa New Zealand (NZ), poverty affects more than 300,000 NZ children and places more than one in five NZ households, and two in five Maori (indigenous NZers) households, at risk of losing their right to food that prevents chronic disease. The NZ Ministry of Health estimates that 8,000-9,000 deaths per year can be attributed to nutrition-related causes. NZ research attempts to address nutrition and food security have limited to retail-based supermarket price discounts or food vouchers which have had nil to poor outcomes for Maori. The primary purpose of this study is to increase fruit and vegetable consumption for Maori people who do not have reliable access to fruit and vegetables. 
Participants will be randomly allocated to one of four groups:
	Group 1 will receive the Food Package free; 
	Group 2 will receive the Food package free and wananga; 
	Group 3 can order weekly packs of NZ$5 worth of fruit and vegetables up to the maximum number of packages based on the size of the family.  
	Group 4 can order weekly packs of NZ$5 worth of fruit and vegetables up to the maximum number of packages based on the size of the family and wananga.
The aims of this proposal are to: 1) Observe household consumption of fruit and vegetables supplied. 2) Measure the difference in consumption between four groups: free food, free food + education, at-cost food, and at-cost food + education.  The hypothesis is that participants in the free food + education group will consume more servings of fruit and vegetables than the other groups. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>133 Molesworth Street
Thorndon
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/09/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Geoff Kira</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
Massey University
Massey Wellington Campus
Block 4, Level E
Wallace St
Mt Cook
Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 979 3974</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.kira@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Geoff Kira</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
Massey University
Massey Wellington Campus
Block 4, Level E
Wallace St
Mt Cook
Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 979 3974</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.kira@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Geoff Kira</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
Massey University
Massey Wellington Campus
Block 4, Level E
Wallace St
Mt Cook
Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 979 3974</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.kira@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Geoff Kira</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
Massey Wellington Campus
Block 4, Level E
Wallace St
Mt Cook
Wellington</address>
      <phone>+64 4 979 3974</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.kira@massey.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>