<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308342">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/08/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/11/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000986279</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomized controlled trial of modes of ventilatory support in preterm babies from point of delivery to the neonatal intensive care unit.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In preterm babies born at the Nepean Hospital less than 30 weeks gestational age and requiring ventilation in the delivery suite, would the use of volume-targeted ventilation as compared to standard intermittent mandatory ventilation from the point of delivery until admission to the neonatal intensive care unit reduce the incidence of hypocarbia in the first 2 days of life?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TARDIS (Targeted Delivery Suite Intervention Study)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Blood carbon dioxide on admission to the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit (NICU)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Blood oxygen level on admission to the NICU</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Oxygen saturation and blood delivery to the brain, as measured by Near Infra-Red Spectroscopy (NIRS)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Development of intra-ventricular haemorrhage and/or periventricular leukomalacia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Presence or absence of cerebral autoregulation as determined by NIRS and its relationship to hypocarbia on arrival in the NICU</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Triggered, volume-targeted mechanical ventilation (for those newborns that require ventilation) from the delivery suite to the neonatal intensive care unit.  Ventilator set to target an exhaled tidal volume of 5 mL/kg with inspiratory pressures automatically adjusted breath-to-breath by the ventilator depending on pulmonary compliance. Cerebral oxygenation monitoring using spatially resolved near infra-red spectroscopy in the first 48 hours of life; ultrasound assessment of cardiac output and presence of a patent ductus arteriosus in the first 48 hours of life.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard non triggered intermittent mandatory ventilation (for those newborns that require ventilation) from the delivery suite to the neonatal intensive care unit. Ventilator set at regular 60 breaths per minute, positive end-expiratory pressure of 5cm, positive inspiratory pressure set by the medical team and based on the newborn's chest movements. Nasal continuous positive airways pressure support for those newborns not requiring active ventilation. Cerebral oxygenation monitoring using spatially resolved near infra-red spectroscopy in the first 48 hours of life; ultrasound assessment of cardiac output and presence of a patent ductus arteriosus in the first 48 hours of life.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>hypocarbia; partial pressure of carbon dioxide in arterial blood (PaCO2) &lt; 30mmHg</outcome>
      <timepoint>on arrival in the neonatal intensive care unit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>hyperoxia; partial pressure of oxygen in arterial blood (PaO2) &gt; 100mmHg</outcome>
      <timepoint>on arrival in the neonatal intensive care unit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>reduced cerebral blood flow as measured by near infra-red spectroscopy</outcome>
      <timepoint>measurement periods of 2 hours' duration; measurements performed as soon as possible after admission to the neonatal intensive care unit, then at the age of 12, 24 and 36 hours of life.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>development of severe (grade 3 or 4) intraventricular haemorrhage as assessed by cranial ultrasound scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>cranial ultrasound scan measurements performed as soon as possible after admission to the neonatal intensive care unit, then at 12, 24 and 36 hours' age, then at chronological age of 1 week and 2 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>development of periventricular leukomalacia as assessed by cranial ultrasound scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>cranial ultrasound scan measurements performed at chronological age of 6 weeks, then again at term corrected age or prior to discharge home.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>death</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 28 days of birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>development of chronic lung disease (requiring oxygen at 36 weeks' corrected gestational age in order to maintain oxygen saturations, as measured by a peripheral transcutaneous oxygen saturation monitor, above 92%)</outcome>
      <timepoint>based on continuous monitoring at 36 weeks' corrected gestational age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>neurodevelopmental disability (graded as mild, moderate or severe) as assessed by a formal Bayley 3 assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at age 1 and 3 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Preterm babies less than 30 weeks gestation at birth</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>23</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Weeks</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>29</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Suspected pulmonary hypoplasia, suspected chromosomal abnormality or a suspected syndrome.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed, numbered opaque envelopes, opened only if the baby requires some form of respiratory support (either intubation or nasal CPAP) the baby is NOT ineligible if he or she does not require respiratory support at the point of delivery.Ventilation in the neonatal intensive care unit (NICU) uses a variety of different modes, all considered to be safe, including volume “targeted” ventilation known as “volume guarantee” or VG on the commonly available Draeger neonatal ventilator. Local (within each hospital) neonatal transport systems, specifically from the delivery suite to the NICU, are not standard and most hospitals will have a standard ventilator capable only of intermittent mandatory ventilation (IMV).All preterm babies less than 32 weeks are assessed at birth regarding their need for respiratory support. Most will need intubation and mechanical ventilation, the standard of care for this is currently to use IMV from the delivery suite to the NICU; a small group of these babies may not require ventilation but will need continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) support. If the newborn baby requires ventilation, as assessed by the medical practitioner on clinical service and independent of the researcher, it will be weighed, intubated as per current practice. During the intubation process, the researcher will open the relevant envelope and thus randomise the newborn to receive either the standard IMV or the triggered VG mode of ventilation, the latter being the interventional mode only as regards transport from the delivery suite to the NICU (as explained above). If the newborn is deemed not to require ventilation, it will receive CPAP but will still be included as a control group within this study.An attempt to obtain consent to enrol each baby will be made prior to the delivery/birth of the newborn. In cases of rapid labour/delivery where consent cannot be obtained before the delivery/birth of the baby, the baby will be initially enrolled and consent will be sought within the next 6 hours, depending on the clinical condition of the mother if the father is not available. Parents will have the right to request withdrawal from the study at any point.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a sequence generated by computer software: Graphpad Statmate. Stratification for 2 groups of gestational ages: (a) 23 weeks (+ 0 days) to 26 weeks (+ 6 days), (b) 27 weeks (+ 0 days) to 29 weeks (+ 6 days)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/11/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Mark Tracy</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>NICU, Nepean Hospital
Derby Street
Kingswood NSW 2747</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nepean Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nepean Hospital
Derby Street
Kingswood, NSW 2747</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Most newborn infants less than 30 weeks' gestational age at birth require either nasal continuous positive airway pressure (nCPAP) or intubation and mechanical ventilation for acute respiratory distress syndrome at the point of delivery, whether in the delivery suite or in the operating theatre.  This is an interventional study looking at whether using a targeted expiratory tidal volume mode of ventilation from the point of delivery until admission in the neonatal intensive care unit may improve a newborn infant's blood gas parameters on arrival in the neonatal intensive care unit. Monitoring and adjusting ventilation to achieve normal arterial carbon dioxide levels is standard practice once the baby is within the neonatal intensive care unit. Current best practice recommends using handbagging ventilation or intermittent mandatory ventilation (IMV); volumes of each breath are not usually measured until the newborn is connected to a ventilator in the neonatal intensive vare unit . The use of an advanced neonatal ventilator which can target set expiratory tidal volumes in the resuscitation, stabilisation and transport of such a premature neonate may allow better arterial blood gases on arrival to the neonatal intensive care unit. Further, the impact of the use of an advanced neonatal ventilator from point of delivery may influence the initial respiratory course as well as the cerebrovascular circulation. This randomised controlled trial (RCT) may demonstrate the value of using an advanced neonatal ventilator in the initial ventilatory management of critically ill newborn babies.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Nepean Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Nepean Hospital Ethics Committee
Nepean Hospital
Derby Street
Kingswood NSW 2747</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/10/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC No: 06/063 TARDIS Study</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Mark Tracy</name>
      <address>NICU, Nepean Hospital
P.O. Box 63
Penrith NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 414324162</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 47342698</fax>
      <email>tracym@wahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Mark Tracy</name>
      <address>NICU, Nepean Hospital
P.O. Box 63
Penrith NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 414324162</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 47342698</fax>
      <email>tracym@wahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>