<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366099">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000739617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>REACT: Reducing anaesthetic complications in children undergoing tonsillectomies</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does inhaled salbutamol decrease the incidence of perioperative respiratory adverse events in children undergoing tonsillectomy (+/- adenoids/grommets) procedures?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>REACT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Respiratory complications under general anaesthetic in children undergoing tonsillectomy (+/- adenoids/grommets) procedures.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will be recruited at the pre anaesthetic visit and randomised to receive either an inhaled placebo or inhaled salbutamol ( 200micrograms ventolin, GSK) via a metered dose inhaler (pMDI) and a spacer. The placebo/salbutamol will be administered in the 60 minutes prior to anaesthesia induction. The attending anaesthetists, the surgeon , anaesthetic technician, the nursing and recovery staff as well as the research staff will be blinded to the group allocation. Only the pharmacy will be unblinded. </interventions>
    <comparator>Inhaled placebo administered via a metered dose inhaler (pMDI) and a spacer in the 60 minutes prior to anaesthesia induction. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of Perioperative respiratory adverse events (PRAE) in children undergoing tonsillectomy receiving either a premedication of inhaled salbutamol or placebo as assessed via clinical assessments. PRAE include Bronchospasm, Laryngospasm, oxygen desaturation, airway obstruction, coughing and stridor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Perioperative period until the patient is discharged from the Post anaesthesia Care Unit (PACU)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome is to reduce costs to the hospital by reducing time spent in the PACU due to PRAE. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Lenght of time spent in PACU measured and recorded on PACU records and study data sheets.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome is to reduce costs to the hospital by reducing the number of unplanned admissions to the hospital due to PRAE. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured in the patients notes in the post operative period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome is to reduce costs to the hospital by reducing the prolonged hospital stays due to PRAE. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured in the post operative period and as per detailed in the patients notes. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>We will study 484 children, aged 0-8 years, undergoing general anaesthesia for elective tonsillectomy (+/- adenoidectomy, +/- grommets).
There will be two patient groups for the study:
Group one: Children 0-6 years old receiving an endotracheal tube (ETT)
Group two: Children 3-8 years old receiving a Laryngeal mask airway (LMA) 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>8</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children receiving a sedating premedication (e.g. midazolam, clonidine) before surgery.
Children with a known difficult airway or thoracic malformation.
Children with a known cardiopulmonary disease:
Uncorrected congenital heart disease
Primary/secondary pulmonary hypertension
Cardiac/thoracic malformations/tumours
Structural lung changes
The above list is a non-exhaustive list. Any other less common cardiopulmonary conditions will be assessed by the anaesthetist in charge and accounted for in the exclusion criteria list.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients will be recruited at the pre-anaesthetic visit. Only patients who meet the inclusion criteria for the study will be enrolled and only after informed consent is given voluntarily by the guardian and by the patient if appropriate. The patients will be randomised by computer generated block randomisation. The next available participant number will be assigned to the patient. The drug randomisation will be performed by pharmacy at Princess Margaret Hospital. The patient will receive the study drug corresponding with his/her Participant Number. The study drug is in boxes with patient numbers detailed on the outside. The participant number will be used to identify the patient for the duration of the study. All staff involved with the care of the patient and the data recording and entering will be blinded to the group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated block randomisation. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary aim of this study is to investigate the difference in prevalence of PRAE between the intervention (salbutamol) and control (placebo) groups. This project will investigate the effects of salbutamol on PRAE, separately for the two different airway devices commonly used, an ETT will be used for 0-6 year old children and an LMA will be used for 3-8 year old children. In our recently completed randomised controlled trial involving tonsillectomy, the prevalence of PRAE was 48.2%. We aim to reduce the prevalence to 24.1% +/- 5%. We conservatively selected the upper limit of prevalence of 29.1% (24.1%+5%) for our power and sample size calculation. For the ETT group (for 0-6 year old children), we need 110 children for the intervention and the control groups, respectively, to detect a decreased prevalence of PRAE by 19% (48.2%-29.1%), with a power of 0.8 and at the significance of 0.05. Likewise for our study purpose in the LMA group (for 3-8 year old children), we need the same number of children (n=110) in the intervention and control groups, respectively. Therefore we require 440 children to take part in this project. Furthermore, based on our previous experience, approximately 10% of the data will not be usable due to changes in clinical requirements for the particular patients or due to patient withdrawal and we thus have to add 10% to our sample size calculation to keep the study appropriately powered. We will therefore recruit 484 patients.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>18/05/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>484</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>484</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>19/05/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Princess Margaret Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Roberts Road
Subiaco
WA 6008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Princess Margaret Hospital Foundation
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>68 Hay street
Subiaco
WA 6008</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Not applicable.</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Despite the development of anaesthesia management guidelines, PRAE remain a major cause of morbidity and mortality during paediatric anaesthesia, accounting for more than three quarters of critical incidents and nearly one third of all perioperative cardiac arrests. 
It is known that the rate of PRAE is approximately 2-folds higher in children undergoing tonsillectomy procedures compared to adults and that the rate of complications is also inversely proportional to age. Younger children are at a higher risk for PRAE compared with older children with a decrease in PRAE of 11% with each yearly increase in age.  
In recent studies and audits in our institution looking at children undergoing tonsillectomies, we found that approximately half the patients suffer from PRAE. Such a high rate of complications inevitably generates a cascade of linked events such as delays in theatre, with the potential for cancellation of other children due to the lack of theatre time and consecutive increases in waitlist time, unplanned hospital admissions, prolonged hospital stay and additional treatment. Even though most PRAE are not associated with long-term sequelae, it also creates more stress for the child and parents. Furthermore, data from closed malpractice claims in the United States of America (USA) show that nearly half of all claims were due to PRAE with higher incidents of death and brain damage as well as higher compensation payments in children as compared with adults. 
The development of preventative strategies, incorporated into an optimised anaesthesia management, would help reduce the occurrence of PRAE and address the previously cited issues. Salbutamol is a commonly used drug in the treatment of asthma which is available as an over the counter medication in Australia. A previous observational trial showed that premedication with inhaled salbutamol reduced the incidence of respiratory adverse events and in particular reduced bronchospasm and persistent cough by up to 50% in children with a recent upper respiratory tract infection. This current study aims to test the efficacy of inhaled salbutamol to prevent PRAE in young children undergoing tonsillectomies, who are at a particularly high risk for PRAE in a randomised controlled setting. The secondary objectives are to reduce the delays in theatre and the time spent in PACU due to PRAE, the number of unplanned admissions, prolonged hospital stays and delays in the waiting lists due to sequelae following PRAE. 

Hypothesis
We hypothesise that, in children undergoing tonsillectomy (+/- adenoidectomy, +/- grommets) procedures, the incidence of overall PRAE will be significantly reduced by the preoperative treatment with inhaled salbutamol as compared with placebo.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Not applicable</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Not applicable</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Roberts Road
Subiaco
WA 6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EP2014042</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Britta Regli-von Ungern-Sternberg  </name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Pain Management Princess Margaret
Hospital for Children Roberts Road Subiaco WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61893408109</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>britta.regli-vonungern@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Britta Regli-von Ungern-Sternberg  </name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Pain Management Princess Margaret
Hospital for Children Roberts Road Subiaco WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61893408109</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>britta.regli-vonungern@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Britta Regli-von Ungern-Sternberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Pain Management Princess Margaret
Hospital for Children Roberts Road Subiaco WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61893408109</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>britta.regli-vonungern@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lliana Slevin</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Pain Management Princess Margaret
Hospital for Children Roberts Road Subiaco WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61893408109</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lliana.slevin@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>