<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362051">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000191897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>E-health behavioural family interaction program for treatment of conduct problems in children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of online-based behavioural family interaction program for treatment of conduct problems in children</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Oppositional Defiant Disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Conduct Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Online behavioural family intervention: Online based behavioural family intervention using the Integrated Family Intervention for Child Conduct Problems (Dadds &amp; Hawes, 2006). This program focuses on managing child aggression, non-compliance and disruptive behaviour. Parents are taught to encourage good behaviour by giving positive reinforcement and rewards, and discourage bad behaviour through the provision of consistent, emotionally neutral punishment. This program has been adapted to an online based program whereby the information is presented in a modules accessed through a virtual clinic with guidance provided on a weekly basis by a clinical psychologist. Each module consists of a short video of a  therapist outlining the strategies and techniques from the program.

Parents after completing pre assessment will be given logins to access a virtual clinic. After they have logged in to the clinic parents will be able to access the modules. After watching the module, parents will be encouraged to implement the techniques discussed, they will also then receive a phone call from a clinical psychologist who will review the material from the module and also answer any questions and problem solve difficulties. After this phone call, the next module in the program will be unlocked for them to view. There is a total of 6 modules in the program. Each module contains video content and also supplemented with written materials.

Duration: Each module goes for between 10-20 minutes and the phone call with the clinician will vary between 45-60 minutes. Each subsequent module in the program is unlocked and able to view after the parents speak to the clinician to review the information presented in the current module. Parents will be required to login to the program on a weekly basis and at the end of the same week they will receive the phone call with the clinician. The program goes in total for 6 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard behaviour family intervention treatment: Parents will receive the behavioural family intervention using the Integrated Family Intervention program. This program focuses on managing child aggression, non-compliance and disruptive behaviour. Parents are taught to encourage good behaviour by giving positive reinforcement and rewards, and discourage bad behaviour through the provision of consistent, emotionally neutral punishment.
This program will be provided by clinical psychologist face to face in weekly sessions. 

Duration: There is a total of 6 weekly sessions over 6 weeks.
Each session will go between 60-90 minutes and content and duration of sessions will match the intervention condition.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome: Levels of disruptive behavior

Levels of disruptive behavior will be assessed in three ways:

1. DSM-IV-TR diagnostic status for Oppositional Defiant Disorder or Conduct Disorder as determined by the Diagnostic Interview Schedule for Children, Adolescents and Parents (DISCAP; Johnson, Barrett, Dadds, Fox, &amp; Shortt, 1999). 

2. Oppositional and conduct symptom severity, also assessed with the DISCAP.

3. Independent observations of disruptive behavior from video recordings of a ten minute free play procedure with parents and child. Videos will be coded using the FOS-VII coding schedule (Pasalich &amp; Dadds, 2009). Videos will be coded for child non-compliance, criticisms, oppositionality, complaints and withdrawal. Both the consistency and intensity of variables are coded, along a 5-point scale ranging from 0 (no occurrence of the behaviour) to 4 (behaviour occurred a lot of the time and/or was of very high intensity).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint:

1. Pre-treatment assessment

2. Immediate post treatment assessment (e.g., within a week of completing treatment)

3. Six month follow up assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental Stress levels 

Level of parental stress will be assessed based on scores on the Parenting Stress Index (Abidin), this scale is designed to measure parenting stress and dysfunctional parenting.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint:

1. Pre-treatment assessment

2. Immediate post treatment assessment (e.g., within a week of completing treatment)

3. Six month follow up assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting Behaviour

Parenting Behaviour will be assessed using the Alabama Parenting Questionnaire (APQ; Shelton, Frick &amp; Wooton, 1196), which has been designed to look at parenting behaviour related to conduct problems.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint:

1. Pre-treatment assessment

2. Immediate post treatment assessment (e.g., within a week of completing treatment)

3. Six month follow up assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental Knowledge of Behaviour Management Principles.

Parent's knowledge of Behaviour Management Principles will be assessed using a questionnaires adapted from O' Dell, Tarler-Benlolo, and Flynn (1979) measure and is designed to assess parental knowledge of behaviour management principles as they complete the program.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint:

After viewing each module or session (control condition) parents will complete a set of 10 questions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Primary DSM-IV-TR diagnosis of ODD or CD
2. Fluency in English

Inclusion Criteria for Parent(s)/Caregivers:

1. Fluency in English</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>11</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Current diagnosis of a psychotic disorder

2. Primary autism

3. Developmental delay (estimated at IQ &lt; 80)

4. Major medical disorder that has significantly interfered with family or school life.

There are no exclusion criteria for parent(s)/caregivers.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Mark Dadds</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Room 526, Griffith Taylor (A19) 
The University of Sydney
 NSW 2006 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 11 Lancaster Place
 Majura Park ACT 2609</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Christina Thai</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Room 104 
Child Behaviour Research Clinic
Mallett Street Campus (M02K)
97 Church Street 
The University of Sydney, Camperdown
 NSW 2006 Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr David Hawes</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Room 440, Brennan MacCallum Building
School of Psychology
The University of Sydney
NSW, 2006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Professor John Brennan</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Sydney Children's Hospital
Mental Health Inpatient Unit
High Street
Randwick NSW 2031</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to investigate the effectiveness of an online based behavioural family interaction program. Behavioural family interaction programs are the treatment of choice for conduct problems in children. However due to issues of 'reach' (i.e geographical) and time restrictions not all families are able to access this treatment. Online based interventions have the potential to overcome these barriers and provide families with better access to treatments that would otherwise be unavailable.  The aim of this current research is to evaluate whether a online based behavioural family interaction can lead to an increase in pro-social behaviour and effectively reduce aggression and anti-social behaviour comparable to standard behavioural family interaction programs which are usually delivered face to face in a clinic setting. 

This online based behaviour family interaction program aims to teach parents to modify unhealthy parenting practices by targeting negative reinforcement contingencies operating in the family. Parents through accessing modules in a virtual clinic and via follow-up phone calls with a clinical psychologist are taught to encourage good behaviour by giving positive reinforcement and rewards, and discourage bad behaviour through the provision of consistent, emotionally neutral punishment.
It is hypothesised that families receiving the online based program will show comparable improvements in levels of disruptive behaviour, decrease in parental stress and improvements in parenting behaviour to those receiving face to face therapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of NSW HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW Research Ethics &amp; Compliance Support
The University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052 Australia
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/09/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/03/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics and Research Integrity
 Margaret Telfer Building (K07)
 University of Sydney
 NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015/822</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Mark Dadds</name>
      <address>Room 526  Griffith Taylor University of Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>61286275873</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mark.dadds@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Christina Thai</name>
      <address>M02k Brain and Mind Centre University of Sydney Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61286275873</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christina.thai@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christina Thai</name>
      <address>M02k Brain and Mind Centre University of Sydney Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>61286275873</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Christina.thai@Sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mark Dadds</name>
      <address>Professor of Psychology
NHMRC Principal Research Fellow
Director, Sydney Child Behaviour Research Clinic

School of Psychology
University of Sydney NSW 2006
</address>
      <phone>+61286275873</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mark.dadds@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>