<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335786">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/08/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/08/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000658011</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison  of peritonsillar
infiltration of ketamine and dexamethason   for postoperative pain
relief in children following  adenotonsillectomy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect  of peritonsillar
infiltration of ketamine and dexamethason   for postoperative pain
relief in children following  adenotonsillectomy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1116-3950</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>'None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>postoperative pain  after tonsillectomy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>One hundred sixtyAmerican Society of Anesthesiologists 
(ASA) I-II children 3-12 were randomized four groups of 40 each. Group P received a local peritonsillar infiltration of 2 ml saline, group D dexamethson (0.2 mg/kg)) , group K ketamine (0.5 mg/kg) and group KD combination of ketamine0.5mg/kg-dexamethason 0.2mg/kg.  All medications were 2 ml in  volume which was applied 1 ml per tonsil 3 min prior to tonsillectomy( all four groups).</interventions>
    <comparator>received a local peritonsillar infiltration of 2 ml saline,</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Modified Hannallah pain scale [observational pain scores (OPS)]</outcome>
      <timepoint>first, 15th, 30th and 60th min postoperatively( After extubation  when the patients were taken to the postanesthesia care unit (PACU).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>time to first demand of analgesia and 24h postoperative analgesic  consumption this outcome will be assessed by Modified Hannallah pain scale [observational pain scores (OPS)] and using a four-point scale: 0 no pain, 1 mild pain, 2 moderate pain, 3 severe pain by questioning their parents .</outcome>
      <timepoint>first, 15th, 30th and 60th  min after exubation (at postanesthesia care unit  [PACU]and 24 h  postoperative(in the ward)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nausea, vomiting  will be assessed  by questioning their parents.</outcome>
      <timepoint>first, 15th, 30th and 60th  min after extubation at postanesthesia care unit    and 24 h  postoperative(in the ward)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>bleeding will be assessed  by questioning their parents.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 h  postoperative(in the ward)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>sedation and Aldrete scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>first, 15th, 30th and 60th  min after extubation at postanesthesia care unit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>family satisfaction  will be assessed  by questioning their parents.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 h  postoperative( in the ward).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>children age 3-12 years ASAI,II  undergoing elective tonsillectomy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>contraindication for  usage of  Ketamine, dexamethason, (upper respiratory tract infection, increase intracranial pressure( ICP), open eye surgery, seizure) ,history of alergy ,chronic usage of   analgesic ,antiemetic ,stroied drugs   before surgery,  history of peritonsillar abscess, , tonsillitis within two weeks, pain before surgery, psychiatric illness, , bleeding disorders and other surgical procedures during the same operation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrollment is decided and permission of the patient is obtained by two of the anesthesiologists during preoperative rounding,.This is a double blinded clinical trial, with blinding of both the patient and the administrating practitioner to the anaesthetic type. Allocation will be managed by a Resident external to the project. The blinding will occur through use of equal amounts of pretreatment drugs (2ml’s) Each syringe will be labeled A ,B,C orD  according to its contents. . The drug syringes are handed over to anesthesiologists blinded to the patient allocation to carry out the induction of anesthesia .All medications were 2 ml in  volume which was applied 1 ml per tonsil 3 min prior to tonsillectomy.At PACU  a nurse who were unaware of the study drug observed the patients.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer-generated table of
numbers guided randomization.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/08/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <state>qazvin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Qazvin University of Medical Science.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Qazvin University of Medical Science. Iran ,qazvin-boulvar bahonar postal code:34188 99578</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Marzieh Beigom Khezri,</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Marzieh Beigom Khezri, , Department of Anesthesiology ,Qazvin University of Medical Science. Iran ,qazvin-boulvar bahonar postal code:34188 99578</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ghods hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>qazvin .boulvar shahid beheshti
postal code:34159-14595</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>fatemeh khalili</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>qazvin .naderi street,postal code
:24137-73691</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Objective:
The immediate postoperative period after tonsillectomy, , is often difficult. These children frequently have severe pain but postoperative airway edema along with increased sensitivity to the respiratory-depressant effects of opioids may result in obstructive symptoms and hypoxemia. Opioid consumption may be reduced by nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs, but these drugs may be associated with increased bleeding after this operation.
Methods: One hundred sixty ASA I-II children 3-12 were randomized four groups of 40 each. Group P received a local peritonsillar infiltration of 2 ml saline, group D dexamethson (0.2 mg/kg)) , group K ketamine (0.5 mg/kg) and group KD combination of ketamine0.5mg/kg dexamethason 0.2mg/kg.  All medications were 2 ml in  volume which was applied 1 ml per tonsil 3 min prior to tonsillectomy. Study drugs were marked only with a coded number label. A computer-generated table of numbers guided randomization. .
 Exclusion criteria were: history of peritonsillar abscess, previous tonsil surgery, tonsillitis within two weeks, pain before surgery, psychiatric illness, asymmetrical tonsils, chronic analgesic usage, bleeding disorders and other surgical procedures during the same operation, Children who received antiemetics, steroids, anti-histaminic, or psychoactive drugs during the week before surgery.  Modified Hannallah pain scale [observational pain scores (OPS)], nausea, vomiting, bleeding, rescue analgesia, sedation and Aldrete scores were recorded at first, 15th, 30th and 60th min postoperatively. Patients were interviewed on the day after surgery to assess the postoperative pain, nightmares, hallucinations, vomiting and bleeding. All the children were  premedicated with midazolam  hydrochloride 0.3 mg/kg)  and fentanyl 1micro g/kg intavenously. Anesthesia was induced with thiopenthal 5mg/kg and atracurium0.3mg/kg. Anesthesia was maintained with isoflurane 1.5% and nitrous oxide 30% in oxygen. The two surgeon used the same dissection and snare technique for all cases and hemostasis done with bipolar cutter. At the end of the surgery neuromuscular blockade was reversed by  neostigmine 0.03 mg/kg) and   atropine 0.01 mg/kg intravenously), anesthesia was discontinued and the tracheal tube removed in the operating room when patients were deep. After extubation the patients were taken to the postanesthesia care unit (PACU) where an nurse who were unaware of the study drug observed the patients. The pain scoring observer nurse in PACU was consistent. Time to awaken (from the end of anesthesia until the patients opened their eyes on command) and time to the first administration of postoperative analgesia were recorded.  Pethidine in a titrated dose (total 1 mg/kg) was administered intravenously for rapid pain relief to patients with a OPS score &gt; 4 or who were crying during two consecutive five minute observation periods until the child was comfortable. Postoperative pain during the first 24 h was assessed using a four-point scale: 0 no pain, 1 mild pain, 2  moderate pain, 3 severe pain by questioning their parents. In the ward the standardized postoperative analgesic technique was with acetaminophen supp (40 mg/kg followed by three doses of 20 mg/kg at 6-hour intervals to be given as needed for pain. Pethidine in a titrated dose (total 1 mg/kg) was administered intravenously for rapid pain relief to patients who had pain scale &gt;3.Any supplementary analgesia , nausea and vomiting, bleeding, sleep disturbance and nightmares that the child might have had as surgery were assessed during a telephone follow up 24 h later. The time needed for first demand of analgesia and analgesic consumption  to reduce the OPS  for resting throat pain to &lt;4   and 24-h pethidine and supp acetaminophen  consumptionwere recored.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>qazvin mediccal science university</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>shahid bahonar,Ave3419759811 Qazvin ,Iran postal code:34197/59811</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/07/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>d/20/1629</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/06/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marzieh Beigom Khezri</name>
      <address>Department of Anesthesiology ,Qazvin University of Medical Science, Iran ,qazvin-boulvar bahonar 
postal code:34188 99578</address>
      <phone>+98-912-3811009</phone>
      <fax>+98-281-2236378</fax>
      <email>mkhezri@qums.ac.ir</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marzieh Beigom Khezri</name>
      <address>Department of Anesthesiology ,Qazvin University of Medical Science, Iran ,qazvin-boulvar bahonar 
postal code:34188 99578</address>
      <phone>+98-912-3811009</phone>
      <fax>+98-281-2236378</fax>
      <email>mkhezri@qums.ac.ir</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>fatemeh khalili</name>
      <address>qazvin ,naderi street
,postalcode :24137-73691</address>
      <phone>+98 912 5826298</phone>
      <fax>+98 281 3344088</fax>
      <email>nasr-1282005@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Iran, Islamic Republic Of</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>