<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362798">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000808842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of Green Tea Polyphenols on Myelodysplastic Syndromes: A Double-Blind Placebo-Controlled Phase II Randomised Clinical Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A phase II double-blind and placebo-controlled randomised clinical trial to determine the efficacy of Green Tea Polyphenols on 200 myelodysplastic syndromes participants</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>GTPs on MDS RCT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is a randomised phase II, 48 weeks clinical trial, with four parallel arms conducted under double-blind and placebo-controlled conditions on 200 MDS participants aged 18 years or more.  The trial will be stratified into 100 patients with lower risk (low and intermediate-1) disease, and 100 with higher risk (intermediate-2 and high) disease, according to the International Prognostic Scoring System.
The conventional treatment for lower risk group will be compound Zaofan pills (CZP), a form of traditional Chinese medicine, 1800mg/d with three meals. For higher risk group the conventional treatment will be the CAG regimen (aclarubicin 10 mg/day, days 1-8; cytosine arabinoside 50 mg/day, days 1-14; G-CSF 300 ug/day, days 1-14), which has been widely used for the treatment of MDS in China and Japan.
Arm 1: Lower risk stratum 50 patients: GTPs capsule 1400mg/d (700mg/capsule, twice per day with morning and evening meals) for 48wks + conventional treatment 
Arm 2: Lower risk stratum 50 patients: Placebo 1400mg/d (700mg/capsule, twice per day with morning and evening meals) for 48wks + conventional treatment 
Arm 3: Higher risk stratum 50 patients: GTPs 1400mg/d (700mg/capsule, twice per day with morning and evening meals) for 48wks+ conventional treatment 
Arm 4: Higher risk stratum 50 patients: Placebo 1400mg/d (700mg/capsule, twice per day with morning and evening meals) for 48wks + conventional treatment</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo control: placebo will be capsules filled with 700mg of GT-colored microcrystalline cellulose.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: Altering the natural history of the disease collected from medical records including peripheral blood tests and bone marrow examinations.
Number of participants with Complete Remission (CR): less than or equal to 5% marrow blasts without evidence of dysplasia and normalisation of peripheral blood counts, including Hb equal to or greater than 11g/dL (not receiving erythropoietin or transfusions), neutrophil count equal to or greater than 1.5x109/L, and platelet count equal to or greater than 100x109/L;
Number of participants with Partial Remission: patients must demonstrate all CR criteria if abnormal before treatment except marrow blasts decrease equal to or greater than 50% compared with pre-treatment levels; or patients may demonstrate a less-advanced MDS disease classification category than prior to treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: at 12, 24, 36 and 48weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2: Hematologic improvement (HI) collected from medical records of peripheral blood tests.
Improvement includes erythroid (HI-E), platelet (HI-P), and neutrophil (HI-N).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: at 12, 24, 36 and 48weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: Overall survival, duration of hospitalization and progression into AML available from medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: at 12, 24, 36 and 48wk after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2: Cytogenetic response collected from medical records of bone marrow examinations.
Major cytogenetic response: disappearance of a cytogenetic abnormality;
Minor cytogenetic response: 50% or more reduction of abnormal metaphases.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: at 12, 24, 36 and 48wk after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3: Quality of life measured by EORTC QLQ-C30 version 3.0.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints: at baseline and at 12, 24, 36 and 48weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Newly diagnosed as MDS by WHO 2008 criteria; Age is 18 years or over; ECOG performance status less than or equal to 2; Protocol defined adequate hepatic and renal function; Willing to refrain from drinking any kind of tea for the duration of the study; Written informed consent; And intending to reside in the state during study period.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Lack of, or withdrawal of, informed consent; Significant hematological co-morbidities, hepatic failure, renal failure or severe cardiovascular disease; Pregnant or positive pregnancy test or child-bearing; Participation in another trial; Or history of any cancer.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Registration: This will be undertaken by the trial coordinator upon referrals from participating clinicians.  It will include obtaining the consent of participants, screening of the patients, provision of information about trial logistics; randomisation, recording of baseline data; and issuing of the first 12-wk supply of treatment capsules from the pharmacy.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will occur through pre-arranged blinded sequences of supplies of treatment capsules collected by the trial coordinator from the Hospital Pharmacy Department.  An allocation and dispensing sequence numbers will be available for the trial participants in a uniform 1:1 allocation ratio, using a fixed Moses-Oakford algorithm and a variable block size.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/12/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Zhejiang Province</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley WA 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Western Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Western Australia, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley WA 6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>School of Population Health , The University of Western Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Population Health, The University of Western Australia, M431, 35 Stirling Highway, Crawley WA 6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The First Affiliated Hospital of College of Medicine, Zhejiang University, P. R. China</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The First Affiliated Hospital of College of Medicine, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, 310003, P. R. China</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>China</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Laboratory evidence and observational epidemiological studies show that GTPs protect against cancer. 
This study aims to assess the efficacy of GTPs in MDS patients by comparing pre-post differences in results of hematological markers of disease activity and quality of life between intervention and placebo patient groups.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Not applicable</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Not applicable</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of The University of Western Australia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Office
Research Services
35 Stirling Highway, Crawley, WA  6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/07/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of College of Medicine, Zhejiang University.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The First Affiliated Hospital of College of Medicine, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou,</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/07/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Min Zhang</name>
      <address>School of Population Health,
The University of Western Australia (M431)
35 Stirling Hwy
CRAWLEY WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 64888175</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 64888188</fax>
      <email>min.zhang@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Min Zhang</name>
      <address>School of Population Health,
The University of Western Australia (M431)
35 Stirling Hwy
CRAWLEY WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 64888175</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 64888188</fax>
      <email>min.zhang@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ping Liu</name>
      <address>School of Population Health,
The University of Western Australia (M431)
35 Stirling Hwy
CRAWLEY WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 64883737</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 64888188</fax>
      <email>ping.liu@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>