<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366375">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000562673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of a high protein preload drink on satiety, food intake, satiety-related hormones and protein metabolites. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a high protein preload drink on satiety, food intake, satiety-related hormones and protein metabolites in healthy normal-weight young adult women. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each participant participated in 3 sessions in total with a minimum of 2 days between each session. Two flavoured milk-based preload drinks differing in carbohydrate and protein were administered 120 min before an ad libitum test meal. A water control was also administered. 

Each subject was provided with a standardised breakfast to consume 3 h before coming to the laboratory and only water is permitted thereafter. Upon arrival at the laboratory, a cannula was placed into a vein in the subject's arm for repeated blood draws. Subject was given a preload drink to consume within 5 min. Subjects completed some questionnaires to assess their feelings of appetite and had 8 blood samples (10 ml each) collected within 120 min. At the end of the 120 min, the cannula was removed and subjects were provided with a hot meal and water to consume until satisfied within 15 min. 

The time involvement for each subject on each session day was at least 170 min and there are 3 sessions, therefore 510 min. 

The 300 ml preload drinks used a sweet flavoured milky solution as a base to which 45 g of either maltodextrin, a carbohydrate with a simple structure or cheese whey protein isolate will be added. All the ingredients in the preload drinks are natural food-grade materials normally consumed in foods. The amount of carbohydrate and protein in 300 ml of the carbohydrate-enriched preload drink was 72 g and 3 g, respectively. The whey protein-enriched preload drink contributed 26 g carbohydrate and 46 g protein per 300 ml drink.  

</interventions>
    <comparator>The control treatment was a water (no energy) preload drink. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subsequent food intake of a hot meal measured using digital scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>120 min after ingestion of the preload drink. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feelings of appetite as assessed using a Visual Analogue Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, immediately after consumption of the preload drink, 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90 and 120 min after finishing the preload drink and 15 and 30 min after consumption of the hot meal. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Circulating plasma levels of satiety-related hormones (glucose, insulin, ghrelin, CCK, GIP, GLP-1, PP and PYY) and protein metabolites (amino acids, urea and ammonia)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, immediately after consumption of the preload drink, and 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90 and 120 min after finishing the preload drink</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>None</outcome>
      <timepoint>None</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women aged 18-40, within a BMI of 19-30 kg/m2 and in good general health. 

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Training athlete, smoker or recreational drug user, vegeratian or vegan, anaemic or suffering from a bleeding or clotting disorder and/or taking medication that affects blood clotting, having a diet-related illness, pregnant or breast-feeding or having a history of menstrual irregularities, an allergy or intolerance to milk or milk-derived products, an aversion to having blood samples taken. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The principal investigator, Dr Sylvia Chungchunlam, carried out the screening process to ensure that potential participants met the selection criteria. 

Subjects were their own control and each treatment was allocated using random numbers in Microsoft Excel. Allocation is not concealed. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/03/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/04/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/03/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Manawatu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Riddet Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Massey University
Private Bag 11-222
Palmerston North 4442</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Riddet Institute, Massey University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Massey University
Private Bag 11-222
Palmerston North 4442</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is widely accepted that protein is the most satiating macronutrient (protein, carbohydrate and fat). The objective of the study is to compare the satiety responses (subsequent food intake, feelings of appetite and circulating concentrations of satiety-related hormones and metabolites) to carbohydrate and protein preloads administered 120 min prior to a test meal in healthy young normal-weight women. A water control was also used. We hypothesise that consumption of the protein preload will result in a reduction in subsequent food intake and rated feelings of appetite and an increase in plasma levels of satiety-related hormones and metabolites. 


  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Massey University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Office
Turitea Campus
Massey University
Private Bag 11-222
Palmerston North 4442

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/07/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HEC: Southern A Application 08/38</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sylvia Chungchunlam</name>
      <address>Riddet Institute
Massey University
Private Bag 11-222
Palmerston North 4442</address>
      <phone>+64210376080</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sylvia.lawrence.17@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sylvia Chungchunlam</name>
      <address>Riddet Institute
Massey University
Private Bag 11-222
Palmerston North 4442</address>
      <phone>+64210376080</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sylvia.lawrence.17@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sylvia Chungchunlam</name>
      <address>Riddet Institute
Massey University
Private Bag 11-222
Palmerston North 4442</address>
      <phone>+64210376080</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sylvia.lawrence.17@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>