<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366582">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000683639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Nortriptyline in knee arthritis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised placebo controlled trial of nortriptyline for pain in knee osteoarthritis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1158-3131</utrn>
    <trialacronym>NortIKA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Nortriptyline as 25mg capsules.  Dose adjusted during 8 week dose-finding period according to participant response from starting dose of 25mg daily to maximum potential dose of 100mg daily.  During the dose-finding period each participant will be contacted fortnightly by the research nurse to make dose adjustments.  This period will then be followed by a 6 week steady dosing period.  Participants will be asked to complete medication diaries to assess adherence.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo capsules containing non-active ingredients only.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference between active treatment and placebo arms in mean pain score at 14 weeks, measured using the WOMAC pain subscale and adjusted for pain score at baseline.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>14 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical function using the WOMAC function subscale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant-rated global assessment using a visual analogue scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in the proportion of participants reporting a treatment effect, defined according to the Osteoarthritis Research Society International set of responder criteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life using the SF36 survey.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant-recorded NSAID and other analgesic use in the final 2 weeks of the study period.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events using the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events. Tricyclic adverse effects will be specifically measured using the Antidepressant Side-Effect Checklist.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>14 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Primary knee OA defined according to American College of Rheumatology (ACR) classification criteria (knee pain plus 3 of: age &gt;50 years, stiffness &lt;30 mins, crepitus, bony tenderness, bony enlargement, no palpable warmth).
2.	 Pain severity of &gt;=20 points on the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities (WOMAC) numerical rating scale (range 0 to 50 points) at the study knee.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>01. Prior joint replacement surgery on the study knee
02. Intra-articular steroid injection within the previous 3 months
03. Secondary OA (OA due to inflammatory arthritis [eg gout, rheumatoid arthritis, juvenile arthritis], septic arthritis or trauma)
04. Known hypersensitivity to nortriptyline or  history of adverse reaction to any tricyclic antidepressant
05. Current use of nortriptyline or other antidepressants, or amiodarone 
06. Within 6 months of myocardial infarction 
07. Heart block
08. Postural hypotension
09. Pregnancy
10. Hyperthyroidism or phaeochromocytoma under current investigation or treatment
11. History of epilepsy or other seizure 
12. History of bipolar disorder or manic episode
13. History of increased intra-ocular pressure or history of angle-closure glaucoma
14. Chronic constipation
15. Urinary retention</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Upon providing informed consent, each participant will be assigned a unique sequentially-numbered study identifier according to the order in which he or she is enrolled in the trial.  The participant will then complete the baseline assessment and anthropometric measures, before the research nurse dispenses the study medication.  The study medication (nortriptyline or identical placebo) will be packaged in identical containers.  Each container will be pre-labelled (by the pharmacist contracted to provide the study medication) with a study identifier according to randomisation schedule. The contracted pharmacist will have no contact with the participants, nor will he be able to influence treatment allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly assigned to receive nortriptyline or placebo at a 1:1 ratio using a computer generated randomisation schedule with permuted blocks of random size.  The randomisation schedule will not be stratified as the risk of important imbalances in prognostic factors is small for a trial of this size. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The minimum important clinical difference for a reduction in pain measure using the WOMAC osteoarthritis index has been determined to be about 10% of the scale maximum, or a total difference of five points on the WOMAC pain numerical rating scale (range 0 to 50).  A sample size of 85 per group will give at least 90% power at a significance level of 0.05 to detect a difference in treatment effect of five points between the nortriptyline and placebo groups. The sample size was calculated using a pooled standard deviation ten points estimated from previous studies, and conservatively assuming no correlation between baseline and follow-up scores. This sample size also allows for detection of the minimum important clinical difference in the proportion of participants responding to treatment according to the OMERACT-OARSI criteria.  The sample size will be inflated to 100 participants per group (200 in total) to account for a possible 15% loss-to-follow-up.

Data analysis will be performed on an intention to treat basis.  All statistical tests will be two-sided and a level of significance (alpha) of = 0.05 set for all confidence intervals and p values. The mean and standard deviation of participants WOMAC pain score at 14 weeks follow-up, and change between baseline and 14 weeks, will be calculated for each treatment group. The primary outcome of the study will be the size of the treatment effect (mean difference in pain between treatment groups at 14 weeks adjusting for differences at baseline), which will be determined using linear regression modelling including treatment group as fixed effect and baseline pain scores as a covariate. A secondary analysis of this primary outcome will be conducted using multivariable linear regression, adjusting for pre-randomisation variables reasonably expected to predict a favourable outcome (duration of disease, medication use at baseline, and use of assistive devices), and participants use of other analgesics (paracetamol, NSAIDs, and opiates) in the 2 final weeks of the study period (weeks 12-14). Secondary continuous outcome measures (WOMAC function and stiffness, patient global assessment, and quality of life measures) will be analysed in a similar manner.

As secondary analysis, patients will be dichotomised according to the OMERACT-OARSI set of responder criteria, defined as a high improvement in pain or function, or a moderate improvement in at least two of pain, function, or patients global assessment.  Incident rates will be calculated for this and other binary outcomes (including use of other pain medications, adverse events, and tricyclic side effects and compared using chi-square or Fisher exact tests. Generalised linear regression models will be used to calculate absolute and relative differences in risk between treatment groups with 95% confidence intervals, adjusting for other variables as appropriate. Self-reported treatment dosage over the past two weeks will be summarised for each follow-up, as will the number of participants discontinuing treatment and reasons for doing so. The incidence of all suspect serious treatment reactions will be presented in line with the CONSORT 2010 recommendations.

Participants who are missing outcome data will be included in the analysis using modern multiple imputation methods. To determine the robustness of results per protocol analysis will be performed, excluding participants with major protocol violations such as cross-over treatments, withdrawals and loss-to-follow-up. The dose-response rate will be investigated by entering final dose achieved as a predictor in regression models.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/02/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Ben Hudson</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of General Practice
University of Otago
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of New Zealand </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 5541, Wellesley Street, Auckland, New Zealand 1141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Osteoarthritis (OA) is a very common and painful condition.  Medicines currently available for treating OA pain are not ideal: they are either inadequately effective or cause unpleasant or dangerous side effects.  Recent research has shown how the brain processes pain in OA and this has opened up the possibility of using different types of medicines for OA pain.  Nortriptyline (an antidepressant) has been used to treat persistent pain in other conditions, and other antidepressants may reduce pain in knee OA.  It is not known whether nortriptyline is useful in this condition.  We plan to test this effect by randomly allocating participants to treatment with nortriptyline or placebo and to measure changes in their pain before and after a period on the medication.  We hope that this will tell us whether nortriptyline will be helpful.  If it is, then we believe that many people may benefit from taking this medicine. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Health and Disability Ethics Committees
Ministry of Health
C/- MEDSAFE, Level 6, Deloitte House
10 Brandon Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/NTA/139</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Hudson</name>
      <address>Department of General Practice
University of Otago
Christchurch
PO Box 4345, Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 27 3481122</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 3643637</fax>
      <email>ben.hudson@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Hudson</name>
      <address>Department of General Practice
University of Otago
Christchurch
PO Box 4345, Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 27 3481122</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 3643637</fax>
      <email>ben.hudson@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Hudson</name>
      <address>Department of General Practice
University of Otago
Christchurch
PO Box 4345, Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 27 3481122</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 3643637</fax>
      <email>ben.hudson@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>