<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362896">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000863831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Changes of total antioxidant capacity and total oxidant status of aqueous humor in different stages of diabetic retinopathy and non-diabetic patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Aqueous humor sampling during cataract surgery in diabetic retinopathy and non-diabetic patients and measuring total antioxidant capacity and total oxidant status of aqeous humor to define early diabetic retinopathy progression.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetic Retinopathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1-Collecting aqueous humor during cataract surgery of diabetic retinopathy patients.
Aqueous humor collected just beginning of cataract surgery. corneal side insicion have been done with MVR knife and 0,1-,0,2 cc aqueous humor aspirated via 26 gauge insulin syringe then cataract surgery continued with the enjection of viscoelastic substance into anterior chamber.


2-Measuring Total antioxidant capacity and total oxidant status in collected aqueous humor.
Aqeous humor immediately stored at -80 celcius and all samples measured  at the same time via Erel method. (at January 2011, one month before end of study)


Measurements of total antioxidant capacity and total oxidant status performed with Erel method. It is a new calorimetric method. This method spectrophotometrically measures changes of oxidant and antioxidant ions present in the sample.</interventions>
    <comparator>1-Collecting aqueous humor during cataract surgery of non-diabetic patients

2-Measuring Total antioxidant capacity and total oxidant status in collected aqueous humor</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1- Total antioxidant status and total oxidant satus of all aqueous humor samples measured.
Measurements of total antioxidant capacity and total oxidant status performed via new calorimetric method known as Erel method.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-At january 2011, at the end of data collection, one month before end of study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1-Measured oxidative and antioxidative stress markers compared with diabetic retinopathy levels.

Statistical analysis was done via SPSS Windows 15.0 program.
Basicly Sperman and Pearson correlation tests were used for analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-at one month after data collection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria included diabetic patients who had diagnosis of senile cataracts. For non-diabetic patients inclusion criteria was presence of cataract.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria included patients who had dense cataract which hinder retinopathy staging,  previous ocular surgery, type 1 diabetes, history of glaucoma, retinal vein occlusion, uveitis, any other posterior segment pathologies.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>110</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ulucanlar eye research and training hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>silahtar caddesi No:2 Gazi/Ankara</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Emrullah Beyazyildiz</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ulucanlar Goz egitim ve arastirma hastanesi No: 59 Ankara</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Numune research and training hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Ulku mahallesi Talatpasa bulvari no:5 Altindag/Ankara</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Turkey</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There are no sensitive markers that can predict or quantify total oxidant status and total antioxidant capacity in DR patients. The lack of reliable biomarkers prevents early, cost-effective measures to target those who might benefit from intensive diabetic therapy. We aimed to observe changes of total oxidant status (TOS) and total antioxidant capacity (TAC) of aqueous humor between stages of diabetic retinopathy patients. If these biomarkers works, it will be very usefull method to detect diabetic retinopathy progression risk.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emrullah Beyazyildiz</name>
      <address>Gazi Mustafa Kemal devlet hastanesi silahtar caddesi no:2 
Gazi Mahallesi/Yenimahalle</address>
      <phone>+905057669783</phone>
      <fax>+903122126675</fax>
      <email>dremrullah@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emrullah Beyazyildiz</name>
      <address>Gazi Mustafa Kemal devlet hastanesi silahtar caddesi no:2 
Gazi Mahallesi/Yenimahalle</address>
      <phone>+905057669783</phone>
      <fax>+903122126675</fax>
      <email>emrllh@yandex.com.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>