<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366275">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001006639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Early access to Vocational Rehabilitation Services for People with Spinal Cord Injury</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An evaluation of early access to vocational rehabilitation services for people with recent spinal cord injury admitted to spinal injury units compared to usual care in improving vocational and psychosocial outcomes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1156-4842 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>In-Voc </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Spinal Cord Injury</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Vocational rehabilitation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Early access to vocational rehabilitation (VR) services in the three spinal cord injury units in New South Wales, Australia will be provided by trained vocational consultants.  

The duration of the intervention is individualised according to the needs and goals of the participants, anywhere around 3 weeks to 3 months.

Contact will be made as early as one week post injury if possible considering medical/psychological stability but may be up to 6 months post injury based on the consultation with the treating health professionals, when the rehabilitation team were in agreement that the person is well enough to be offered the intervention. 

The rehabilitation vocational consultants will engage in a variety of tasks with each client - the frequency and nature of which will be individually tailored to the client's needs, they include; 
1. Engagement in a series of conversations regarding return to work expectations
2. Assisting the inpatient to commence conversations with the pre-injury employer to explore return to work possibilities including conducting work place visits, job analysis and workplace assessments
3. Assisting the inpatient to explore return to work options including providing vocational counseling, job seeking skills training
4. Assisting the in-patient to develop an individual return to work plan
5. Establishing relationships and processes with key stakeholders that will support and facilitate return to work 
6. Ensuring the continuity of appropriate vocational rehabilitation post discharge
  
</interventions>
    <comparator>People with spinal cord injury in similar settings but in different states, Western and South Australia, where VR services are not available during acute and sub acute care will be used as comparators. 
VR services in these states are generally delivered after the patient is discharged from the hospital in the community setting.

This trial essentially compares early provision of VR services vs usual/traditional care.   

An additional strategy due to anticipated difficulty in recruiting controls is to form a historical comparison group using data already available from a previous project, the Spinal Cord Injury Community Participation Project. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Return to work rates (assessed per Australian Bureau of Statistics definition)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12, 24 &amp; 30 months after injury</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General Health and well being measured using SF-36 (The Medical Outcomes Survey Short Form 36) </outcome>
      <timepoint>12, 24 months after injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability measured using FIM (Functional Independence Measure (TM))</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 24 months after injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The level of handicap using CHART (The Craig Handicap Assessment and Reporting Technique) </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 24 months after injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Moorong Self Efficacy Scale to measure self efficacy across a wide range of life domains.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 24 months after injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative experiences of (purposively) selected participants and rehabilitation team members involved in the early intervention program to explore issues such as acceptance, timeliness, appropriateness, role conflict etc .

Assessed by focus group discussions of rehabilitation team members at all 3 sites, key informant interviews of  all the vocational consultants and in-depth semi-structured interviews of purposively selected participants.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months from the time of completion of the early intervention program</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness analysis of the early intervention program using Incremental Cost Effectiveness Ratio (ICER)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Recent spinal cord injury (defined as spinal cord injury in previous 6 months that results in permanent disability)
2. Gives informed consent to participate in the evaluation
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Spinal injuries attributable to progressive or degenerative diseases, congenital conditions, or metastatic lesions

2. No return to work goal as indicated by a total lack of interest in and/or desire to return to work on the part of the participant. Work may be either in a paid or unpaid capacity. Note that students yet to obtain work are included as are participants who wish to return to or commence non paid work eg volunteer work, or as a carer, or to commence or continue a course of study or training that may lead to improved vocational prospects 

3. Considered by the rehabilitation treatment team to be unable to participate due to any medical or psychological reasons, e.g. requiring permanent mechanical ventilation, severe depression or adjustment disorder


</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All eligible persons admitted to the three spinal units in New South Wales, Australia during the study period will be offered the intervention while a similar group of people with spinal cord injury in Western and South Australia where the intervention is not available will be used as control. </concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Prospective cohort study</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The number of participants needed to achieve this study's primary objective was determined based on these assumptions that were based on literature review and clinical reasoning of minimally worthwhile treatment effect:
1. The anticipated return to work rate in the intervention group is around 50% at 12 months
2. The anticipated return to work rate in the control group  is around 20% at 12 months
and assuming two-sided significance level(1-alpha) of 95  and 80% Power with the ratio of sample size, Unexposed/Exposed of 0.5, giving the total sample size of 105 (70 intervention and 35 control). 
However given the anticipated 60% rate of participation (20% declining and 20% with no return to work expectation), the final estimated sample size is around 150 (100 intervention and 50 control).

Primary outcome will be compared at 12, 24 and 30 months post-injury. Descriptive statistics will be used to identify differences between InVoc and usual care groups scores on secondary outcomes. For nominal data, percentage differences, odds ratios with 95% confidence intervals and Chi-squared will be used to determine statistical significance. For parametric data, paired t-tests will be used for normally distributed and Mann-Whitney-U tests for non-normal and non-parametric data.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/08/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/10/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Private Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Rehabilitation Hospital - Coorabel/Moorong - Ryde</hospital>
    <hospital>Hampstead Rehabilitation Centre - Northfield</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Rehabilitation Studies Unit (RSU), University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney Medical School/Northern
 
THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Kolling Institute, Royal North Shore Hospital,  St Leonards, NSW 2065 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NSW Lifetime Care and Support Authority</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>24/580 George St, Sydney NSW 2000

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project's hypotheses are that early access to vocational rehabilitation services for in-patients in NSW spinal units will increase return to work rates and have a positive impact on general health and well being of the participants.

This study will also have other components to complement the quantitative aspect namely a qualitative sub-evaluation (investigating the perspective of the participants and rehabilitation staff), a process sub-evaluation (with reference to the implementation of the intervention),  and a cost sub-evaluation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Central Coast Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2, Building 51
Royal North Shore Hospital 
St Leonards, NSW 2065  </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/HAWKE/91</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ian Cameron</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation Studies Unit, Sydney Medical School/Northern
 
THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Kolling Institute, Royal North Shore Hospital, St Leonards NSW  2065 </address>
      <phone>+61299264962</phone>
      <fax>+61299264045</fax>
      <email>ian.cameron@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ian Cameron</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation Studies Unit, Sydney Medical School/Northern
 
THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Kolling Institute, Royal North Shore Hospital, St Leonards, NSW 2065 </address>
      <phone>+61299264962</phone>
      <fax>+61299264045</fax>
      <email>ian.cameron@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ian Cameron</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation Studies Unit, Sydney Medical School/Northern
 
THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Kolling Institute, Royal North Shore Hospital, St Leonards
NSW  2065 </address>
      <phone>+61299264962</phone>
      <fax>+61299264045</fax>
      <email>ian.cameron@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kumaran Ramakrishnan</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation Studies Unit, Sydney Medical School/Northern
 
THE UNIVERSITY OF SYDNEY
Kolling Institute, Royal North Shore Hospital, St Leonards
NSW  2065 </address>
      <phone>+61299264962</phone>
      <fax>+61299264045</fax>
      <email>kumaran.ramakrishnan@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>