<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371580">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000177358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Omega-3 fish oil for the prevention of Gestational Diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Omega-3 fish oil for the prevention of gestational diabetes: a double-blind, randomized controlled proof of concept study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1192-1425</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gestational Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fetal medicine and complications of pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>2 x 1g fish oil capsules each day (each capsule containing 60mg eicosapentaenoic acid and 430mg docohexaenoic acid) from ~ 14 weeks gestation until 34 weeks gestation. Adherence to trial protocol will be assessed using a capsule log, return capsule count, and erythrocyte fatty acid composition.</interventions>
    <comparator>1 x 1g corn oil capsules/day from ~ 14 weeks gestation until 34 weeks gestation. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulin Resistance, as measured by HOMA-IR (fasting glucose x fasting insulin / 22.5)</outcome>
      <timepoint>14, 20, 28 &amp; 34 weeks gestation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma inflammatory markers (IL-6, TNF-alpha, CRP, IL-1beta) and adipokines (adiponectin, leptin), measured using ELISA assays.</outcome>
      <timepoint>14, 20 and 34 weeks gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood Pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>14, 20 and 34 weeks gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Newborn whole-blood fatty acid composition</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post delivery (48-72 hours after birth)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Matsuda Index (Calculated from 2 hour oral glucose tolerance test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 weeks gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Erythrocyte fatty acid composition, measured by gas chromatography from a fasting blood sample</outcome>
      <timepoint>14, 20 &amp; 34 weeks gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>&lt;14 weeks pregnant
Aged 18-40
Any one of the following:
a) PAPP-A between 0.3 and 0,6 MoM in their Nuchal Translucency Scan
b) previous history of gestational diabetes
c) at risk of developing gestational diabetes according to Health pathway criteria</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>BMI greater than 45kg/m2
Any incidence of ongoing bleeding beyond 8 weeks gestation in the current pregnancy
Is on anti-coagulant therapy or known to have clotting disorders
Known to be pregnant with multiples
Lactating
Established diabetes prior to pregnancy or currently taking anti-diabetic medications
Being diagnosed with gestational diabetes in this pregnancy prior to enrolment in the study
Known allergies to seafood or corn
Currently on medication with Aspirin and Warfarin
Has significant current gastro-intestinal disease
Is incapable of giving informed consent
History of new investigational drug three months prior to this trial
Currently consuming more than 200g oily fish per week or taking supplements delivering 150mg or more of DHA/day
Unable to fast for 10hr before obtaining blood sample</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be allocated to group A or group B. Group allocation will be conducted by someone not associated with this study, and the group allocation will be sealed in 2 x opaque envelopes until data analysis has been completed. The sealed envelope will kept by the person responsible for blinding and one copy with the Chief Investigator, should the need for unblinding arise. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization sequence will be a computer-generated random sequence</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size: This pilot study has been powered to determine whether DHA supplementation has a measurable effect on measures of insulin resistance in pregnancy. Therefore the alpha has been set at 0.1, and power at 80%. A significance level of 10% was chosen to reflect a greater priority of reducing type 2 errors over type 1 errors as this is a proof of concept study. Previous studies have shown that the standard deviation of HOMA-IR is around 1.0 units (Endo et al, 2006; Lacroix et al, 2013), and a 0.5 unit difference in HOMA-IR has clinical significance. 32 participants per group in a parallel design will give an 80% power to detect a 0.5 unit difference in HOMA-IR between intervention and placebo groups at 28-weeks, assuming a standard deviation of 1.0 and an alpha set at 0.1. To allow for drop-outs, 37 will be recruited to each group, giving a total of 74 participants.

Baseline data: Baseline outcome measures will be used as covariates. BMI and other potentially confounding variables such as age may be added as covariates if there appears to be an imbalance between the treatment arms.
Treatment effects: All the data relating the significant effects of n-3PUFA are expressed as mean +/- SEM or median (IQR) as appropriate. The effect of interventions on glucose tolerance, HOMA-IR and blood glucose levels between groups will be estimated by using two-way ANOVA with post hoc comparisons (Tukeys honestly significant difference). With-in group effects will be assessed using one-way ANCOVA with repeated measures or Friedman test if assumptions for ANCOVA are violated. Differences in the proportion of pregnancies that develop gestational diabetes in each group will be assessed using Chi Square or Fishers Exact test as appropriate.
P-values less than 0.1 indicate statistically significant between- treatment group differences in outcome values.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>74</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>John Hunter Hospital - New Lambton</hospital>
    <postcode>2305 - New Lambton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive, Callaghan, NSW, 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Newcastle</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University Drive, Callaghan, NSW, 2308</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>EPAX</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Po box 7047
No- 6028 Alesund</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Norway</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Gestational diabetes (GD) is a form of diabetes which occurs during pregnancy, and generally resolves after delivery. It is diagnosed as high blood glucose during pregnancy, and affects around 510% of all pregnancies in Australia. Recent changes to diagnostic criteria along with an increasingly obese population and older age at which women have their first child, mean the prevalence of GD is rapidly rising. Pregnancy is known to be an insulin-resistant state, and failure to adequately compensate for this inherent insulin resistance through increased insulin secretion results in hyperglycaemia. Whilst the precise mechanisms behind this insulin resistant state are unclear, there is increasing evidence that inflammation of adipose tissue is associated with GD development. Pregnancy is characterized by adipose tissue remodeling and growth, which is modulated by inflammatory markers. However, higher levels of inflammatory markers such as IL-6 and TNF-a, and lower levels of adiponectin are associated with the development of GD. 
Docosahexaenoic Acid (DHA) is an omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acid (n-3PUFA) that is critical to the neural development of the foetus during pregnancy, and may be beneficial to adipose tissue functioning during pregnancy.  Pregnancies complicated by type 2 diabetes and GD are associated with a decline in erythrocyte DHA in late pregnancy when compared with normoglycaemic pregnancies. This fall  can be ameliorated by DHA supplementation during pregnancy. Supplementation of n-3PUFAs in pregnancies affected by GD confers beneficial effects on insulin resistance when compared with control groups  Furthermore, supplementation of EPA + DHA from weeks 10-16 of pregnancy until term results in reduced expression of IL-6, IL-8 and TNF-a in both adipose and placental tissue. The  improved insulin sensitivity and adipokine profile and reduced levels of inflammatory markers suggest improved adipose tissue function in response to n-3PUFA supplementation, which could reduce the risk of developing GD.
To date, research investigating the relationship between n-3PUFAs and GD as an outcome have not reported a relationship. However, supplementation in these trials commenced later in the second trimester, from 17 weeks gestation, with the majority not commencing until 24 weeks gestation. We postulate this is too late in pregnancy as GD has often become apparent by this point. No research has reported the effect of an n-3PUFA intervention in early pregnancy on insulin resistance, adipokines and markers of inflammation. 
We hypothesize that DHA supplementation supports healthy adipose tissue development and functioning during pregnancy, and this in turn reduces the risk of developing gestational diabetes. The aim of the current study is to determine the effect of a low-dose DHA-enriched n-3PUFA supplement on measures of insulin resistance, adipokine profile and inflammatory markers from early pregnancy in women at high risk of developing GD.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 1
New Lambton, NSW, 2305
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016/10/19/3.03</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University Drive
Callaghan
NSW, Australia, 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2017-0012</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Manohar Garg</name>
      <address>305C Medical Sciences Building
University of Newcastle
University Drive, 
Callaghan, NSW, 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 5647</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 2018</fax>
      <email>manohar.garg@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kylie Abbott</name>
      <address>305B Medical Sciences Building
University of Newcastle
University Drive, 
Callaghan, NSW, 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 5638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kylie.abbott@uon.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Manohar Garg</name>
      <address>305C Medical Sciences Building
University of Newcastle
University Drive, 
Callaghan, NSW, 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 5647</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>manohar.garg@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kylie Abbott</name>
      <address>305B Medical Sciences Building
University of Newcastle
University Drive, 
Callaghan, NSW, 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49215638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kylie.abbott@uon.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>