<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336811">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000441910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The role of life style and diet modifications on treatment of chronic pelvic pain syndrome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The role of life style and diet modifications on treatment of chronic pelvic pain syndrome</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>not assigned</utrn>
    <trialacronym>not assigned</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>not assigned</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic pelvic pain syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>chronic prostatitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pelvic inflammatory disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1) Nimesulide 100 mg bidaily for one week
2) Serenoa Repens (Saw Palmetto) one 320 mg tablet each day for three months.
Saw palmetto is an extract of the fruit of Serenoa Repens: it is a phytotherapic agent commonly used worldwide for prostatic conditions. Its effectiveness for prostatitis was already showed in many clinical trials.
3) Intervention: modification of lifestyle and diet for three months.  
patients belonging the interventional arm are strongly recommended to strictly follow some lifestyle rules and dietary recommendations  giving them a list prepared by Dr. Luigi Gallo, (MD specialist un urologist) including the following:
Modifications of diet:
avoidance of alcohol beverages, sodas,  spicy foods, pepper, chilli, coffee, artificial sweeteners, tea.
Modifications of lifestyle: 
1) Walking  and practicing relaxing sport activities (swimming, jogging, free exercises). 
2) regular sexual activity:
a)avoidance of sexual abstinence for more than 4 days          b)Do not try to delay ejaculation in both masturbation and intercourse
c)Do not practice interrupted coitus as contraceptive method.
d)Do not have two ejacultations during the same day
3) Avoidance of sitting position for long time 
4) Avoidance of sports that can be traumatic for the prostate (bicycling, motorcycling,  horse riding etc.)
5) Avoidance of wearing tight underpants or trousers 
At second consultation (at the end of 3 months) patients assigned to this group will be invited to refill a questionnaire  assessing the grade of acceptance to lifestyle modifications. Only the patients who will correctly follow lifestyle recommendations will be considered  for outcome measurements, the others will be excluded.</interventions>
    <comparator>1) Nimesulide 100 mg bidaily for one week
2) Serenoa Repens (Saw Palmetto) one 320 mg tablet each day for three months
3) no lifestyle change:
the patients included in the control group are invited to follow the same diet and the same life style of the previous months.
The patients of this group follow their regular lifestyle and undergo no modification</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in the mean total NIH-CPSI scores of the two groups from baseline to after three months of treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in mean NIH- CPSI subdomains (pain, micturition, QoL) of the two groups pre-  and aftertreatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) patients coming to our center with a diagnosis of Category IIIa or IIIb CPPS (with or without presence of leukocytes) 
2) age between 20 and 50 years 
3) a score of &gt; 1 in pain domain of NIH-CPSI 
4) duration of symptoms for more than 3 months 
5) presence at clinical history of at least one lifestyle or diet risk factors.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) diagnosis of a bacterial form of prostatitis (category I and II of NIH) assessed after lower  urinary tract localisation studies 
2) a previous urinary tract infection within the last year 
3) assumption of drugs which could modify lower urinary tract function during the previous  three months 
4) Severe gastric problems , coagulation problems, renal and/or epatic failure  contraindicating assumption of NSAIDs.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruited patients will be assigned to two different groups according to the baseline value of  NIH-CPSI , age, duration of symptoms and numbers of risk factors.
Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Dynamic (adaptive) random allocation according to baseline value of  NIH-CPSI , age, duration of symptoms and numbers of risk factors.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Campania</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Studio Urologico Gallo</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Via Santa Lucia 97
80132
Naples
Italy</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Italy</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Studio Urologico Gallo</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Via Santa Lucia 97
80132
Naples
Italy</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Italy</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Prostatitis is the most common urologic pathology in men younger than 50 years and represents 13,8% of urologic office visits .The most frequent form is the chronic abacterial 
prostatitis or type III prostatitis, according to the National Institutes of Health (NIH) prostatitis  classification system, called Chronic Pelvic Pain Syndrome (CPPS) . Lifestyle change still represents the first step of medical therapy in many common pathologies . Several studies  have focused the etiology of prostatitis on dietaries habits and some lifestyle activities. However, the potential benefits of a therapeutic regimen based on a strict adhesion to a 
specific lifestyle and dietary reccomendations have never been investigated.
Objectives of  the  present study are: 
1) to review medical literature about risk factors for prostatitis coming from  abnormal lifestyle and dietary habits.
2) to prepare a vademecum of lifestyle and diet  modifications based on scientific evidences
3) to investigate the incidence of these risk factors in a population of patients coming to our centre complaining of CPPS. 
4) to investigate the effectiveness and the compliance to this vademecum associated to the most common therapies actually used for prostatitis like NSAIDs (nimesulide) and phitotherapy (Serenoa repens).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.studiourologicogallo.it</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Studio Urologico Gallo</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Via Santa Lucia 97
80132
Naples</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/07/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>---</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Italy</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Luigi Gallo</name>
      <address>Via Santa Lucia 97
80132 Naples</address>
      <phone>0039-081-7649530</phone>
      <fax>0039-081-7649530</fax>
      <email>info@studiourologicogallo.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Luigi Gallo</name>
      <address>Via Santa Lucia 97
80132 Naples</address>
      <phone>0039-081-7649530</phone>
      <fax>0039-081-7649530</fax>
      <email>info@studiourologicogallo.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>