<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367737">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/02/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000100594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effects of Bolus and Slow Fluid Infusions in Healthy Volunteers with Shock </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Effects of a Bolus or Slow Intravenous Crystalloid Fluid Infusion on Oxygen Delivery in Healthy Volunteers with Compensated Shock</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1166-0487</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Haemorrhagic Shock</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>After the venesection of 10 ml/kg Ideal Body Weight of blood over a 15 minute period from healthy fit adult subjects, participants will be randomised to receive a intravenous crystalloid fluid (Plasma-Lyte 148) for resuscitation. 

The type of fluid used is Plasma-Lyte 148 solution (Baxter Healthcare).

The amount of Plasma-Lyte 148 solution that will be administered is 13 ml/kg (Ideal Body Weight) .  

Plasma-Lyte 148 solution will be infused continuously via the intravenous route through a peripheral intravenous cannula.

The Plasma-Lyte 148 infusion will commence exactly 15 minutes after completion of the venesection. 

Plasma-Lyte 148 solution will infused over 2 time periods/arms depending on randomisation.

1. Over a 10 minutes period (Bolus infusion group)

2. Over a 30 minutes period (Slow infusion group)

The ratio of 1:1.3 ratio of the volume of blood to the volume of Plasmalyte is adopted from the landmark clinical trial, The Saline versus Albumin Fluid Evaluation Study (SAFE).

Once the Plasma-Lyte 148 solution has been infused, data collection will be conducted for 60 minutes.

Once data collection is completed, the venesected blood will be re-infused back to the participant over a 30 minute period.

The study will then be concluded. 

Participants will then be crossed over to the other infusion period/arm between 7 -14 days later i.e there will be a washout period of between 7-14 days between the 2 interventions. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be Bolus infusion group. This group will receive the Plasma-Lyte 148 solution over a 10 minutes period (Bolus infusion group).


 </comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is: Oxygen delivery (mls/kg/min)

This is easily measured by using non-invasive technology which continuously measure cardiac output, O2 saturation and haemoglobin levels throughout the study. 

Determinants of oxygen delivery will be directly measured using state of non-invasive technology (Edwards Life Science ClearSight Device). These will include: 
1. Stroke volume index (independent of heart rate)
2. Haemoglobin concentrations
3. Blood arterial saturation  
4. Heart rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.	Baseline (before venesection)
2.	Immediately post venesection 
3.	30 minute post venesetion; pre-Plasmalyte infusion
4.	Immediately post Plasmalyte infusion 
5.	60 minutes post Plasmalyte infusion
6.	Post reinfusion of the patients venesected blood</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean arterial pressure using the Edwards Lifesciences ClearSite Advanced haemodynamic monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.	Baseline (before venesection)
2.	Immediately post venesection 
3.	30 minute post venesetion; pre-Plasmalyte infusion
4.	Immediately post Plasmalyte infusion 
5.	60 minutes post Plasmalyte infusion
6.	Post reinfusion of the patients venesected blood</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Systolic blood pressure using the Edwards Lifesciences ClearSite Advanced haemodynamic monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.	Baseline (before venesection)
2.	Immediately post venesection 
3.	30 minute post venesetion; pre-Plasmalyte infusion
4.	Immediately post Plasmalyte infusion 
5.	60 minutes post Plasmalyte infusion
6.	Post reinfusion of the patients venesected blood</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diastolic blood pressure using the Edwards Lifesciences ClearSite Advanced haemodynamic monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.	Baseline (before venesection)
2.	Immediately post venesection 
3.	30 minute post venesetion; pre-Plasmalyte infusion
4.	Immediately post Plasmalyte infusion 
5.	60 minutes post Plasmalyte infusion
6.	Post reinfusion of the patients venesected blood</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac index using the Edwards Lifesciences ClearSite Advanced haemodynamic monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.	Baseline (before venesection)
2.	Immediately post venesection 
3.	30 minute post venesetion; pre-Plasmalyte infusion
4.	Immediately post Plasmalyte infusion 
5.	60 minutes post Plasmalyte infusion
6.	Post reinfusion of the patients venesected blood</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Systemic vascular resistance using the Edwards Lifesciences ClearSite Advanced haemodynamic monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.	Baseline (before venesection)
2.	Immediately post venesection 
3.	30 minute post venesetion; pre-Plasmalyte infusion
4.	Immediately post Plasmalyte infusion 
5.	60 minutes post Plasmalyte infusion
6.	Post reinfusion of the patients venesected blood</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stroke volume index using the Edwards Lifesciences ClearSite Advanced haemodynamic monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.	Baseline (before venesection)
2.	Immediately post venesection 
3.	30 minute post venesetion; pre-Plasmalyte infusion
4.	Immediately post Plasmalyte infusion 
5.	60 minutes post Plasmalyte infusion
6.	Post reinfusion of the patients venesected blood</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Venous blood gas including (pH,Pa02,PaCO2, base deficit) using an ABL 800 Blood Gas Monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.	Baseline (before venesection)
2.	Immediately post venesection 
3.	30 minute post venesetion; pre-Plasmalyte infusion
4.	Immediately post Plasmalyte infusion 
5.	60 minutes post Plasmalyte infusion
6.	Post reinfusion of the patients venesected blood</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma haemoglobin using an ABL 800 Blood Gas Monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.	Baseline (before venesection)
2.	Immediately post venesection 
3.	30 minute post venesetion; pre-Plasmalyte infusion
4.	Immediately post Plasmalyte infusion 
5.	60 minutes post Plasmalyte infusion
6.	Post reinfusion of the patients venesected blood</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Atrial natriuetic peptide </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before venesection of the patients blood), immediately post infusion of the Plasmalyte-148 solution, then 30 minutes and 60 minutes post infusion of the Plasmalyte-148 solution</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Interleukin 6</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before venesection of the patients blood), immediately post infusion of the Plasmalyte-148 solution, then 30 minutes and 60 minutes post infusion of the Plasmalyte-148 solution</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Tumour necrosis factor (Alpha)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before venesection of the patients blood), immediately post infusion of the Plasmalyte-148 solution, then 30 minutes and 60 minutes post infusion of the Plasmalyte-148 solution</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Indocyanine green, which will be measured with PULSION non-invasive LiMONTechnology </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before venesection of the patients blood), immediately post infusion of the Plasmalyte-148 solution, then 30 minutes and 60 minutes post infusion of the Plasmalyte-148 solution</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vascular reactivity index using a VENDYs non invasive vascular reactivity machine.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before venesection of the patients blood), then 60 minutes post infusion of the Plasmalyte-148 solution</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma lactate using an ABL 800 Blood Gas Monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before venesection of the patients blood), immediately post infusion of the Plasmalyte-148 solution, then 30 minutes and 60 minutes post infusion of the Plasmalyte-148 solution</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart Rate using the Edwards Lifesciences ClearSite Advanced haemodynamic monitor</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.	Baseline (before venesection)
2.	Immediately post venesection 
3.	30 minute post venesetion; pre-Plasmalyte infusion
4.	Immediately post Plasmalyte infusion 
5.	60 minutes post Plasmalyte infusion
6.	Post reinfusion of the patients venesected blood</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Healthy adults 
2. No regular medication other than contraceptive pill
3. Normal Haemoglobin level 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. &lt;18 years or &gt; 45 years in age 
2. Pregnancy or have given birth within 1 year
3. Hereditary haematological conditions (sickle cell anaemia and thalassemia) that are susceptible to anaemia
4. Recent (within 10 days) history of cold, fever, or upper or lower respiratory tract infection (this may theoretically increase risk of infection with venesected blood when it is being stored prior to re-infusion)  
5. Morbid Obesity (BMI&gt; 35 kg/m2)
6. Body Weight &gt; 100 kg</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be concealment will be by means of sealed opaque envelopes. The sealed envelopes will be stored in a locked facility in the department of Intensive Care at Austin Hospital, where the trial is being conducted. After informed participant consent has been obtained, an independent research assistant/investigator will open the sealed envelope which will contain one of the two randomisation groups.

1)	Bolus Plasmalyte infusion group
2)	Slow Plasmalyte infusion group

After a wash-period of &gt;7days and &lt;14 days, participants will be assigned to the alternative group.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation) will be performed by the Principle Investigator. The computer will be password protected and located in the Research Laboratory in the Department of Intensive Care at Austin Hospital. Participants will be randomly allocated to one of the two infusion groups described above.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Regarding the inference for means: the sample calculations are based on comparing two independent sample populations 
1.	The expected mean oxygen delivery values (mu1) in the slow volume resuscitation group  = 500 ml/min/m2
2.	The expected mean oxygen delivery values (mu2) in the bolus volume resuscitation group = 400 ml/min/m2 
Using a 2-sided test
3.	Sigma value (common standard deviation) of the samples population = 75 ml/min/m2 
4.	Type 1 error rate = 0.05
5.	Desired power = 0.80
Result: A sample size of 9 patients is required 

Statistical analysis will be performed using computerized software (SPSS for Windows version 12.0, and Graphed). For data that is non-normally distributed a MannWhitney test will be used and normally distributed data will be compared using the Student T test. Ordinal and nominal data will be compared using Chi square analysis. A p-value &lt;0.05 will be considered significant.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>22/06/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>9</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>9</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Study Road, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Austin Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Studley Road, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Surgery, and Anaesthesia Perioperative Pain Medicine Unit, University of Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Melbourne, Parkville, Victoria, 3010, Australia
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Department of Surgery, and Anaesthesia Perioperative Pain Medicine Unit, University of Melbourne</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Melbourne, Parkville, Victoria, 3084 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Numerous animal studies have shown that bolus or fast fluid infusion increases blood loss and mortality compared to a slow fluid infusion. Consistently, a high quality human randomised controlled trial also demonstrated that rapid crystalloid infusion increased mortality and complications in children with severe infections compared to those who received no bolus infusion.  To date, no human studies have explored the effects of bolus fluid infusions and the duration of these effects on haemodynamic changes, biochemical, immunological and hormonal responses compared to those effects induced by slow infusions. 

This study is the first human randomised controlled trial to investigate the effects of bolus (fast) and slow infusion of crystalloid (clear) fluids in healthy volunteers.  Participants will be randomly assigned to either a bolus (fast) infusion or a slow infusion group.  The controlled venesection (removal) of 10 ml/kg Ideal Body Weight of blood will be conducted over a 15 minute period.  Following that and after 30 minutes, participants will be resuscitated with 13 ml/kg of a either a bolus (fast) infusion (10 minutes), or a slow infusion (30 minutes) with a balanced crystalloid solution. After a 60-minute measurement period, the participants blood will be re-infused over a further 30-minute period. After 2 weeks, the participants will be crossed over to the other arm. 

Primary end point: Oxygen delivery, which can easily be measured by using a validated non-invasive haemodynamic monitor (Edwards Life Science ClearSight Device), a device that is used routinely as standard of care at Austin Health. 

Secondary endpoints: The effects of the rate of fluid resuscitation on mean arterial pressure, systemic vascular resistance, vascular reactivity index, biochemical, immunological and hormonal responses will also be investigated in similar timeline.  

Study Hypothesis: A slow crystalloid infusion has a more beneficial effect on oxygen delivery than a bolus (fast) crystalloid infusion in healthy volunteers (age 18 to 45 years) with induced compensated shock.  

No of participants: 9

Setting: A single centre University teaching hospital.

Safety: Detailed and stringent safety guidelines will be followed in accordance with advice from the Department of Haematology at Austin Hospital, Austin Hospital Blood Bank, Victorian Red Cross, and the Departments of Anaesthesia and ICU.
Each experiment will conducted by a senior anaesthetist, in a theatre environment, with the appropriate monitoring and safety equipment to effectively and safely conduct this study.  

Clinical significance: These results will used to generate hypotheses and establish outcome benchmarks for future controlled trials that will directly influence how patients with haemorrhagic shock are optimally resuscitated. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Unit </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee 
Austin Hospital, Studley Road, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/Austin/458</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital, Studley Road, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94596421 </fax>
      <email>Laurence.Weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital, Studley Road, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94596421 </fax>
      <email>Laurence.Weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital, Studley Road, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94596421 </fax>
      <email>Laurence.Weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital, Studley Road, Heidelberg, 3084, Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94965000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 94596421 </fax>
      <email>Laurence.Weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>