<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363690">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000242729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Intracoronary Cooling (Evaluation of Outcomes) before Angioplasty Revascularisation in ST Elevation Myocardial Infarction</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of intracoronary hypothermia compared to normal standard of care on infarct size and muscle damage in patients who are having a STEMI caused by thrombus</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ICEOBAR-STEMI</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>ST Elevation Myocardial Infarction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A cooling solution ( Sterile Ringers Lactate cooled to 0 degrees C and 10 degrees C) will be stored at this temperature (monitored fridge temp) and then transfered to an ice bath just before delivery to the patient.  It will be given via infusion through a line set connected to the aspiration catheter and delivered directly into the coronary artery at a rate of 5.0ml +/- 2.5ml for a minimum of 5 minutes.  This will occur before and after the thrombus has been removed.</interventions>
    <comparator>In the control group the patients will be given the normal standard of care for a person experiencing a STEMI.
This consists of a coronary angiogram to repair the "culprit lesion" causing the STEMI.  The treatment may include thrombus removal, baloon angioplasty, PCI or a combination of the three.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in myocardial damage - this will be measured by MRI</outcome>
      <timepoint>42 days post procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time the first onset of chest pain or symptoms to being wheeled into the lab for coronary angioplasty</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time patient physically enters the lab for coronary angioplasty</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>	Inclusion criteria
Patients who meet the following criteria may be included:
1.	Age &gt; then or = to 18 years
2.	The patient (or next-of-kin or legal representative) provided written informed consent.
3.	Clinical symptoms of ongoing ischemic chest pain and 12-lead ECG confirmation of acute STEMI, as defined by the following ECG criteria present upon arrival to the PCI lab:
a.  Anterior infarct: ST-segment elevation &gt;0.2mV measured 0.08 sec after the J point in 2 or more anatomically contiguous precordial leads, V1 - V6; and/or &gt;0.1mV in leads I, AVL.
OR
b.  Higher-risk inferior infarct: ST elevation &gt;0.2mV measured 0.08 sec after the J point in 2 or more anatomically contiguous inferior leads II, III, AVF, and ST depression&gt;0.1mV in 2 or more contiguous anterior leads,
4.	Present to the study PCI lab within eight (8) hours of the onset of acute cardiac ischemic symptoms (such as chest pain or pressure, arm or jaw pain, dyspnea).
5.	Be a candidate for primary PCI and have PCI planned as the immediate intervention.
6.	Be willing and able to comply with study procedures, including returning for the cardiac MRI scan at 3+/-1 days post-procedure and be available for additional follow up.
7.	Target coronary artery is completely or nearly completed occluded at angiography prior to PCI (TIMI 0 or 1 flow).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	Exclusion Criteria
Patients who meet any one of these criteria will be excluded from the investigation:
1.	Is or may be pregnant.
2.	Prior myocardial infarct in the same coronary distribution
3.	Known pre-existing LV dysfunction (LVEF&lt; 40%)
4.	Administration of a thrombolytic agent for the qualifying MI
5.	History of mental illness
6.	Clinical suspicion of a non-thrombotic cause for ST-segment elevation (e.g., pericarditis, vasospasm, takotsubo cardiomyopathy, illicit drug use) 
7.	Allergy or contraindication to heparin, aspirin or thienopyridines
8.	Requires an immediate surgical or procedural intervention other than PCI (e.g. CABG)
9.	Presents in cardiogenic shock
10.	Has undergone at least 10 minutes of cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) prior to presentation to the PCI facility, or have ongoing ventricular arrhythmias
11.	History of surgical coronary artery revascularization (e.g. CABG)
12.	Active bleeding, coagulopathy within previous 3 months
13.	Known significant renal disease (on dialysis, post renal transplant or eGFR&lt;30), known severe hepatic failure (e.g., cirrhosis, or acute hepatitis)
14.	Serious concurrent medical condition likely to result in death during the next 12 months. 
15.	Contraindication to MRI (e.g., cardiac pacemaker, ICD, nerve stimulator, brain aneurysm clips, cochlear implants, claustrophobia)
16.	Participation in another investigational clinical research study that has not reached its primary endpoint
17.	The investigator determines that a patient is not a good candidate for the study despite having met all the eligibility criteria.
18.	TIMI 2 or 3 flow in the target coronary artery
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be admitted to hospital as having or having had a STEMI.  After inclusion criteria has been met, patients will be approached about participation.  A PICF will be given to patients, after time to consider, patients will agree or delcine to participate.
If they agree, they will be consented to the trial by a delegated trial member - normally PI or SI.  
ALlocation concealment will involve contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is "off-site" or at a central administration site.
The the patient will then be randomised by 2:1 by computer generated pseudo-random number.</concealment>
    <sequence>randomised by 2:1 by computer generated pseudo-random number</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Sample size will be a maximum of 27 patients.  18 to the hypothermia group and 9 in the control group.  The trial is not powered to detect a clinically relevant difference in treatment groups.  Primary objective is safety and feasibility and treatment effect. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Paired t-test</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>16/12/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>27</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prospex Medical III Inc</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>900 Long Lake Road
Suite 250
New Brighton
MN 55112
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Prospex Medical III Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>900 Long Lake Road 
Suite 250
New Brighton,
MN 55112
USA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of treatment in a heart attack is to open the blocked coronary vessel causing the heart attack and return normal blood flow to the heart muscle as soon as possible.  Despite this, many patients can suffer damage to the heart muscle.  Hypothermia or cooling is predicted to reduce the extent of the heart muscle damage.  Cooling fluid is infused via a catheter and delivered to the arteries that supply blood to the heart.  This slows the heart muscle activity and reduces the amount of blood supply required for heart function.  This cooling procedure is also proposed to help in the same way when normal blood flow is returned to the heart. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>N/A</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mark Webster</name>
      <address>Auckland City Hospital
2 Park Road
Private Bag 92-024
Grafton
Auckland 1023
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3074949 ext 23665</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mwebster@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Donna Katae</name>
      <address>Auckland City Hospital
2 Park Road
Private Bag 92-024
Grafton
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3074949 ext 24389</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dkatae@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jason Galdonik</name>
      <address>900 Long Lake Road
Suite 250
New Brighton
MN 55112</address>
      <phone>+1 651 207 4717</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jason.galdonik@prospexmedical.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Donna Katae</name>
      <address>Auckland City Hospital
2 Park Road
Private Bag 92-024
Grafton
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3074949 ext 24389</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dkatae@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>