<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363552">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000187741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Telehealth Remote Monitoring for People with Multiple Chronic Conditions</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Utilising Telehealth Remote Monitoring for individuals with multiple chronic illnesses to reduce hospital admissions and improve self-management behaviours.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study is a randomised controlled trial of telehealth remote monitoring of people who have two or more chronic conditions, including; diabetes, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), chronic heart failure (CHF), hypertension and asthma. 
Once an individual has consented to take part in the research and been allocated to the telehealth group, the nurse will collect baseline information and assist the participant to complete the research tools. At this time the telehealth nurse will also provide the participant with a calendar and instructions on how to record any health service contact that they have during the data collection period.
The telehealth nurse will then develop an action management plan with the client designed specifically for their chronic diseases and together they will identify the vital signs and relevant health outcomes that will be monitored.
 
The Telehealth nurse will liaise with the participants GP to provide information about the research and provide them with a password to log-in to the monitoring website should they like to review their patients daily readings.
The telehealth device will then be programmed to reflect the requirements for each individual participant. Following programming of the device, the telehealth nurse will visit the participant again to install the telehealth equipment and train the participant in its use, as well as the correct use of peripheral devices such as blood pressure monitor, thermometer, blood glucose monitor and pulse oximeter. Depending on individual requirements, participants will measure the following daily:
blood glucose
blood pressure
weight
heart rate 
oxygen saturation levels
Questions relating to their general state of health and other symptoms depending on individual requirements

The values for each measure being monitored will be transmitted automatically via the internet to a secure website that can be accessed only by the telehealth nurse and the participants GP. Each participants data will be monitored daily by the telehealth nurse and any change in the vital signs indicating deterioration in health will be managed using established care pathways based on the evidence based guidelines for best practice in the management of their particular chronic illnesses. Participants will monitor their vital signs for a duration of 12 months.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomised to the control group will have the same data collected from them at baseline as the telehealth group. The telehealth nurse will provide participants in this group with a calendar to record health service contacts over the data collection period. This group will not recieve any other intervention and will continue to recieve their normal services from Silver Chain. (Whatever they were recieving before the trial commenced, eg Home Help, Personal Care with showering etc.)

The telehealth nurse will then develop an action management plan with the client designed specifically for their chronic diseases but does not include Telehealth monitoring. 

They will also be given a telephone number to ring should they have any queries about their self monitoring over the data collection period which will last for a total duration of 12 months.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in ED Presentations, hospitalisations and length of stay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hospital Admissions, Emergency Department presentations and length of stay will be recorded by participants in a monthly calendar at the time they occur. Each participant will be telephoned monthly by the research assistant to collect this information to add to the health service use database. This information will then be used to analyse all participants health service use after their completion of 12 months on the project.

Additionally, the hospitalisations and emergency presentations of participants for the two years prior to the study will be sort from the Western Australian Linked Data System to determine the impact of the chronic disease on the health service use of the individual participants leading up to the study period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved quality of life for those in the intervention group compared to the control group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at baseline, 6 months and 12 months using the SF-36 QOL tool.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved self-management behaviours.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Paticipants will complete the Stanford self-efficacy for managing chronic disease 6-item scale at baseline, 6 months and 12 months. The 6-item scale covers several domains that are common across many chronic diseases including symptom control, role function, emotional functioning and communicating with physicians. 
Participants will also be surveyed at the completion of the study(12 months) to collect information on changes in specific behaviours or ways in which they manage their chronic illnesses as a result of recieivng the telehealth monitoring.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceptions on using telehealth technology, benefits and challenges as percieved by participants, their GP's and staff administering the project.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Surveys and interviews with staff at the completion on the project (12 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Potential participants will need to meet the following criteria:

Have a diagnosis of two or more chronic conditions (diabetes, COPD, CHF, hypertension and asthma.)
Have been hospitalised at least once in the last 12 months due to their chronic disease or related complications.
Live in the community (Not residential care facilities)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those that have a diagnosis of dementia
Those that are recieving palliative care services
Those that are not physically able to use the telehealth equipment.

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Silver Chain clients meeting the selection criteria will be identified using Silver Chain's client information system and will be invited to participate in the research by letter. The letter will include an information statement and explain that they will be contacted by a research nurse within a few days. If when telephoned the client says they are interested in participating in the research, the telehealth nurse will visit them in their own home to further explain the project and answer any questions the individual may have. When all questions have been answered to the client's satisfaction and the nurse has confirmed that the individual meets the selection criteria, the client will be asked to sign the consent form and the nurse will open the study envelope containing group assignment. (Process described under sequence generation section.) The nurse will then inform the participant which group they are allocated to.</concealment>
    <sequence>Prior to the commencement of recruitment, 120 study numbers will have been randomly allocated to the intervention or control group (60 in each group), by the Research Officer responsible for the trial. This allocation will be undertaken using the random number generator in the statistical software package, STATA. Envelopes will then be made up which have the study number written on the outside and contain a slip of paper with the group assignment for that number. An electronic master list of the study numbers and group allocation will be kept on a password protected computer and will not be accessible to the nurse who will be recruiting participants.</sequence>
    <masking />
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/02/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Silver Chain</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>6 Sundercombe St, Osborne Park 6017, Perth, Western Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Illawarra Retirement Trust (IRT) Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>3/77 Market Street, WOLLONGONG, NSW 2500.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is a randomised controlled trial of telehealth remote monitoring for people with multiple chronic illnesses. The patient is provided with equipment and trained to measure their vital signs daily which are then reviewed remotely through a secure website by a nurse. The aim is to promote early intervention to detect deterioration in the clients condition before they require hospitalisation. It also aims to empower older individuals to take a more active role in managing their chronic illness.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Silver Chain Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>6 Sundercombe St, Osborne Park 6017, Perth, Western Australia.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>082</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gill Lewin</name>
      <address>6 Sundercombe St, Osborne Park 6017, Perth, WA.</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92016722</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>glewin@silverchain.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kristen De San Miguel</name>
      <address>6 Sundercombe St, Osborne Park 6017, Perth, WA.</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92016757</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kdesanmiguel@silverchain.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kristen De San Miguel</name>
      <address>6 Sundercombe St, Osborne Park 6017, Perth, WA.</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92016757</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kdesanmiguel@silverchain.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kristen De San Miguel</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 8 92016757</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kdesanmiguel@silverchain.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>