<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335153">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/02/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/02/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000166077</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>High-flow Nasal Cannulae as Post-extubation Respiratory Support in Premature Infants: A Continuus Positive Airway Pressure Equivalent? (The HIPERSPACE Trial)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The HIPERSPACE Trial: Comparing the failure rate of high-flow nasal cannulae (HFNC) versus nasal continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) as post-extubation respiratory support in premature infants with gestational age less than 32 weeks.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HIPERSPACE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Respiratory distress syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>High-flow nasal cannulae (HFNC): This intervention involves delivering flow rates of gas (air/oxygen) at a minimum of 2 litres per minute via smaller nasal cannulae than those used with nasal CPAP. Infants randomised to HFNC will remain on this intervention until failure criteria or cessation criteria are met, with changes to flow rate at the discretion of the treating medical team. Infants who 'fail' (based on non-subjective clinical criteria) will be changed to nasal CPAP or re-intubated.</interventions>
    <comparator>Nasal continuous positive airway pressure: This intervention is the standard treatment to be used as the comparator. Nasal CPAP involves the delivery via binasal prongs of a regulated pressure of gas (air/oxygen) to the infant. Infants randomised to nCPAP will remain on this therapy until failure or cessation criteria are met, based on non-subjective clinical criteria. Infants who 'fail' will be re-intubated.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Failure of assigned treatment within seven (7) days of extubation. Failure will be defined by non-subjective clinical criteria including: 1. respiratory acidosis with on blood gas measurement 2. increasing oxygen requirement based on peripheral transcutaneous oxygen saturation measurement 3. clinically observed worsening apnoea, or 4. any emergency deemed to require re-intubation by the treating medical team.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Seven (7) days after the time of extubation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reviewing the bedside charts and patient medical record retrospectively for the number of recorded episodes and duration of mechanical ventilation via an endotracheal tube.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 7 days from the randomised extubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for intubation and mechanical ventilation within the first 7 days from the randomised extubation. This will be recorded either prospective examination of the infant, or from the bedside charts or patient medical record retrospectively.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 7 days from randomised extubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bronchopulmonary dysplasia. This outcome is defined as the infant requiring respiratory support and/or supplemental oxygen at a corrected age of 36 weeks. This information will come from the patient's bedside charts or patient record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Incidence recorded at 36 weeks corrected age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pneumothoraces after trial entry. This will be noted prospectively by examining the infant, or from the patient's medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Incidence continuously monitored until discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nasal septum or skin trauma whilst receiving assigned treatment. A nasal trauma chart has been designed for the trial which will be completed on each nursing shift by the nurse caring for the infant. These charts will be collected and episodes of nasal trauma will be noted. Subsequent management of the nasal trauma will be noted from the patient's medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Incidence continuously monitored until discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Mechanically ventilated infants with gestational age less than 32 weeks Being extubated to respiratory support Inborn or outborn Prospective consent obtained</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Days</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known major respiratory or cardiac anomalies
Prospective consent not obtained</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/05/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/05/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>3/07/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Peter Davis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Newborn Research
Royal Women's Hospital
20 Flemington Road
Parkville
Victoria 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Parade
Parkville, 
Victoria, 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road
Parkville 
Victoria 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>HIPERSPACE is a trial comparing the use of two types of breathing support for premature infants after they have been extubated (come off a mechanical breathing machine) in the Royal Womens Hospital (RWH), Adelaide Women's and Children's Hospital (WCH) or Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital (RBWH) neonatal intensive care units. Premature infants who are born less than 32 weeks of gestation, required support from a mechanical breathing machine, and are planned to be extubated to further breathing support are eligible for inclusion in the trial. The usual way post-extubation breathing support has been provided is by using large prongs in the babies nose which transmit a continuous, and regulated, pressure to the babys lungs to help them breathe more easily. This support, called nasal CPAP, is quite bulky and requires the infant to wear a tightly-fitted hat, and sometimes causes damage to the infants nose. A newer form of support being used around Australian and the world is called high-flow nasal cannulae (HFNC). This method uses smaller prongs in the infants nose and blows gas at 2-8 litres per minute into the infants airway. It is thought this flow also produces a pressure that helps to keep the lungs open, and has been considered to be more comfortable for the infants. However, despite widespread use, HFNC has not been well studied in premature infants. In the HIPERSPACE trial, premature infants who have been extubated will be randomly assigned to receive either nCPAP or HFNC. The main result we will be interested in from the trial will be which treatment the infants do better on. Infants in the HFNC group who are not coping can be offered nCPAP as rescue treatment. Information will be collected about the infants until they are discharged from hospital, including the incidence of lung complications, the amount of different types of breathing support required, rates of complications from using the different types of prongs in the nose, and the comfort of the infant.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>HIPERSPACE is a trial comparing the use of two types of breathing support for premature infants after they have been extubated (come off a mechanical breathing machine) in the Royal Women’s Hospital (RWH) or Adelaide Women's and Children's Hospital (WCH) neonatal intensive care unit. Premature infants who are born less than 32 weeks of gestation, required support from a mechanical breathing machine, and are planned to be extubated to further breathing support are eligible for inclusion in the trial. The usual way post-extubation breathing support has been provided is by using large prongs in the babies’ nose which transmit a continuous, and regulated, pressure to the baby’s lungs to help them breathe more easily. This support, called nasal CPAP, is quite bulky and requires the infant to wear a tightly-fitted hat, and sometimes causes damage to the infants’ nose. A newer form of support being used around Australian and the world is called high-flow nasal cannulae (HFNC). This method uses smaller prongs in the infant’s nose and blows gas at 2-8 litres per minute into the infant’s airway. It is thought this flow also produces a pressure that helps to keep the lungs open, and has been considered to be more comfortable for the infants. However, despite widespread use, HFNC has not been well studied in premature infants. In the HIPERSPACE trial, premature infants who have been extubated will be randomly assigned to receive either nCPAP or HFNC. The main result we will be interested in from the trial will be which treatment the infants do better on. Infants in the HFNC group who are not coping can be offered nCPAP as ‘rescue’ treatment. Information will be collected about the infants until they are discharged from hospital, including the incidence of lung complications, the amount of different types of breathing support required, rates of complications from using the different types of prongs in the nose, and the comfort of the infant.</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Women's Hospital Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>20 Flemington Road
Parkville 
Victoria 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/03/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Brett Manley</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Research
Level 7, Royal Women's Hospital
20 Flemington Road
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</address>
      <phone>+613 8345 3766</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brett.manley@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Brett Manley</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Research
Level 7, Royal Women's Hospital
20 Flemington Road
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</address>
      <phone>+613 8345 3766</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brett.manley@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Brett Manley</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Research
Level 7, Royal Women's Hospital
20 Flemington Road
Parkville, Victoria, 3052</address>
      <phone>+613 8345 3766</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brett.manley@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brett Manley</name>
      <address>Newborn Research Centre
The Royal Women's Hospital
Level 7, 20 Flemington Road
Parkville, VIC 3052
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61383453766</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brett.manley@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>