<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365223">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000022662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Yawn induced limb movements in stroke patients with arm weakness</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Establishing the neuro-anatomical basis for extrapyramidal yawning movements observed in stroke patients with arm weakness</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Yawning Induced Movements in Stroke Study ( YIMSS)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Yawning Induced Movements in an otherwise paralysed limb</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Observation Study:
1. Observe incidence of YIMS (yawning induced movements in stroke survivors) - subjects will be asked to complete regular surveys noting how frequently they observed autonomous movements associated with yawning. 
2. Clinical survey upon admission to tertiary hospital for stroke for up to 6 months following a first stroke
3. Subjects will complete a  survey upon admission and at 2 weeks, 1 and 3 and 6 months to determine  their individual functional level and incidence of yawning induced movements
4. Subjects will be given a survey kit with the two week and 1,3 and 6 month survey forms, information pack and return prepaid envelopes 
5. Investigators provide a reminder phone call prior to each survey to improve adherence
6.As secondary aim, wish to compare neuroanatomical stroke lesions between patients with YIMs against those without YIMs. Identifying these lesions will involve going through Head imaging taken during the diagnosis of stoke and potential fMRI in future studies
</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A - This is an observational study
</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Determine Incidence of Yawning Induced Arm Movements in stroke survivors
Incidence will be determined by participant observation and recollection. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At admission and at 2 weeks, 1 month, 3 months and 6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Establish (if possible) neuroanatomical correlations between subjects with YIMs compared to subjects without YIMs
 This will be assessed through comparison of head imaging done at time of diagnosis and possibly fMRI as a separate study in the future</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. Secondary time point for each patient is 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age &gt;18
Cerebrovascular Accident (aka Stroke) presenting in 3-13 days
Stroke associated with motor deficit (paralysis) of the upper limbs 
Able to give consent/assent
Family member able to give assent on behalf of patient
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Severe stroke or co-morbidities that make early death more likely
Previous Stroke
Significant movement disorders ( Parkinsons Disease, Multiple Sclerosis, Motor Neuron Disease)

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Predicted sample size of 200-300 subjects</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>6</followup>
    <followuptype>Months</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Benjamin Mulo</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Department of Neurology
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands 6009
Western Australia, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>None</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>N/A</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>N/A</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>For many years the phenomenon of involuntary movements provoked by yawning, has been observed in stroke patients with paralysed limbs, particularly the arm. More than a hundred years ago, an analysis suggested that removal of inhibitory pathways, unmasked the associated movements of yawning and limb movements, which had an evolutionary link related back to the swim bladder and pectoral fins of fish. In healthy individuals, yawning is often accompanied by generalised stretching, which may include elevation of the arms, known as pandiculation.  The paralysed arm of stroke patients can be seen to move during a yawn, often bringing the hand towards the mouth, before suddenly dropping again at the end of the yawn. Walusinski coined this, parakinesia brachialis oscitans.  The observation appears to have been regarded as a curiosity, with some texts almost derisively regarding it as something that could potentially give false hope to stroke patients.

There has been some investigation into the neural basis of yawning in healthy subjects, with interest in the possible involvement of the mirror neurone pathways, and other regions distant to the motor cortex, including the ventromedial posterior prefrontal cortex. Movement of the paralysed limb during yawning in patients with pyramidal tract lesions, has been suggested to provide evidence for an independent emotional motor system, separate to the corticospinal motor tracts. Recruitment of these areas and pathways might provide a potential mechanism for recovery of motor function after stroke, particularly in the arm. There may thus be some potential for somehow utilising arm movements associated with yawning to stimulate upper limb recovery.  

Another fascinating aspect of yawning, is the common observation that witnessing yawning in others may result in another individual yawning; so called contagious yawning. This does not appear to be related to hypoxia or hypercarbia8. Some 42-55% of humans witnessing images of subjects yawning, will yawn themselves and the act of thinking of yawning may provoke yawning. 33% of adult chimpanzees yawned in response to seeing videos of other chimps yawning, possibly inferring advanced self awareness and empathy in this species. It is possible, therefore that yawning could be evoked, and thus used as a potential means for stimulating upper limb movements in paralysed patients. The exciting potential could be that yawning could thus be utilised as a neurorehabilitation therapy

The primary purpose of the study is determine the incidence of Yawning Induced Movements in stroke survivors. We hope to use this data to guide the development of future studies with the aim of determining if these movements can have an application in the rehabilitation of stroke survivors </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SCGH Human Ethics Research Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>SCGH HREC
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands 6009
Western Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/11/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David Blacker</name>
      <address>Department of Neurology
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands 6009
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>David.Blacker@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Benjamin Mulo</name>
      <address>Department of Neurology
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands 6009
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b_mulo@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Benjamin Mulo</name>
      <address>Department of Neurology
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands 6009
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b_mulo@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Benjamin Mulo</name>
      <address>Department of Neurology
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands 6009
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9346 3333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b_mulo@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>