<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370763">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000684426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Perceive Recall Plan Perform Assessment with Stroke Survivors
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A preliminary study of the Perceive Recall Plan Perform Assessment with stroke survivors in an early supported discharge setting</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1183-1358</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Ten stroke survivors will be assessed on 3 outcomes measures in their initial Occupational Therapy home visit sessions as part of an early supported discharge service. 

They will be assessed with the Perceive Recall Plan Perform System of Task Analysis (PRPP). This is an observational assessment of occupational performance and cognitive strategy application. It is non-invasive and is standardised, reliable and valid. They will also be assesed on the Functional Independence Measure to measure burden of care and the Lawtons Scale to measure independence in instrumental activities of daily living. These assessments will all occur in their home and will take an average of an hour to complete. This is part of standard care and is in face to face delivery. PRPP will be conducted on two different tasks, and the other scales are once-off. These assessments will be completed within the first 5 OT home visits, ie: early in the episode of care with the service. 

PRPP is an observational assessment. Participants will negotiate tasks to be assessed with their an OT at an appropriate level of challenge. They will be advised that notes will be taken and that they will receive their results once the assessment has been scored. Tasks may include using a computer, preparing a meal or shaving.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PRPP stage one and stage two: raw scores.  This is a composite assessment. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Within first five OT home visits</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional Independence Measure to assess burden of care</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed within first five OT home visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lawtons Scale to assess independence in instrumental activities of daily living </outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed within first five OT home visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility: determined by the number of complete data sets on PRPP and time requirements to use PRPP</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the first five sessions</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of stroke, less than six months post stroke, 18 years and older, able to communicate in basic English, identified post-stroke cognitive impairment and able to give consent. People with aphasia are also potential participants.  Recruitment must have been completed within the first four OT home visits, with the assessments being completed by the fifth visit.  Participants will continue with standard care with the ESD service during and after data collection.  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of a premorbid intellectual impairment, readmission to hospital prior to the assessments being completed and not receiving OT with the ESD service.   </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be analysed with Excel and SPSS. Descriptive statistics will be provided for demographic details and PRPP scores.   Correlation tests will be performed between the three outcome measures to test for relationships

Sample is based on a similar exploratory study: Aubin, G., Chapparo, C., Gelinas, I., Stip, E., &amp; Rainville, C. (2009). Use of the Perceive Recall Plan and Perform System of Task Analysis for persons with schizophrenia: A preliminary study. Australian Journal of Occupational Therapy, 56, 189-199.5 </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>4/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>24/02/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>10</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>24/02/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>6000 - Perth</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Perth Hospital </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rehabilitation in the Home
Royal Perth Hospital
Goderich St Outpatients
Level 4
Goderich St 
Perth WA 6000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>South Metropolitan Health Service</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rehabilitation in the Home
Royal Perth Hospital
Goderich St Outpatients
Level 4
Goderich St 
Perth WA 6000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>dentifying and addressing cognitive impairments post-stroke is a significant component of stroke rehabilitation. However, few cognitive assessments measure real-world performance. One assessment that addresses cognition in the here and now is Perceive Recall Plan Perform (PRPP). PRPP is an assessment and intervention system used by Occupational Therapists (OTs) to identify errors of cognitive strategy application and structure individualised intervention. PRPP is a unique tool: it measures cognitive strategy application in any task, in any setting, and can be used with any client, regardless of diagnosis or age. PRPP is standardised, reliable, valid and criterion-referenced assessment (Chapparo &amp; Ranka, 2012), meaning that it can be used to measure how much of a task that an individual needs to do in their own situation, rather than using generic criteria to measure success. It consists of a two stage assessment framework: stage one uses task analysis to record motor steps and errors. Stage two is used to attribute errors in applying cognitive strategies which occurred during the task. PRPP is widely used for assessment and intervention in brain injury (Nott, Chapparo, &amp; Heard, 2009), however there is little documented evidence of PRPP in stroke rehabilitation. 

This study will be conducted with stroke survivors in an Early Supported Discharge (ESD) setting, titled Rehabilitation in the Home (RITH). Three different assessments will be conducted by OTs: PRPP on two different tasks, the Functional Independence Measure (FIM) to measure burden of care and Lawtons Instrumental Activities of Daily Living (LIADL) to measure domestic task independence. PRPP stage one and stage two scores will be related with these measures and examined for any trends. All data will be collected within the first five OT home visits as a component of standard care and full data sets from ten patients are required for analysis.

This exploratory study aims to examine the use of PRPP in stroke as a tool to identify errors in using cognitive strategy application, measure task mastery and detail trends in the assessment results. The objectives are to: Determine if it is feasible to use PRPP with stroke patients receiving ESD, examine the usefulness of each aspect of PRPP in stroke rehabilitation; and explore the association between PRPP and FIM and LIADL.

It is anticipated that this study will examine the feasibility of using PRPP in stroke ESD, provide evidence for the use of PRPP in stroke to assess cognitive strategy application and explore PRPP as a real-world measure of information processing in stroke rehabilitation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 5 Colonial House
Royal Perth Hospital
Wellington St
Perth 6000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Jocelyn White</name>
      <address>C/O Rehabilitation in the Home
Royal Perth Hospital
Goderich Street Outpatients
Level 4
Perth 
WA 
6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6477 5152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jocelyn.white@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Jocelyn White</name>
      <address>C/O Rehabilitation in the Home
Royal Perth Hospital
Goderich Street Outpatients
Level 4
Perth
WA 
6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6477 5152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jocelyn.white@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Jocelyn White</name>
      <address>C/O Rehabilitation in the Home
Royal Perth Hospital
Goderich Street Outpatients
Level
WA 4
Perth 
6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6477 5152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jocelyn.white@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Jocelyn White</name>
      <address>C/O Rehabilitation in the Home
Royal Perth Hospital
Goderich Street Outpatients
Level 4
Perth 
6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6477 5152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jocelyn.white@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>