<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370521">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000514404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Physical activity levels in Sydney Local Health District (SLHD) allied health professionals.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Physical activity levels of allied health professionals working within the Sydney Local Health District (SLHD).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1181-8964</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Physical inactivity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is an observational study in allied health professionals so there is no intervention. The participants' levels of physical activity will be monitored for seven days using a physical activity monitor (ActiGraph GT1M) which will be worn during waking hours. 


</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of steps per day measured using an activity monitor (Actigraph (GT1M) which the participant will wear for a 7 day period.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>End of the 7 day wear of the activity monitor.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Amount of time in moderate to vigorous physical activity during work time and non-work time. Moderate-to-vigorous physical activity is defined as 3 metabolic equivalents (METS) or more.</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of the 7 day wear of the activity monitor.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity levels measured by the Active Australia Questionnaire 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>This questionnaire will be administered to participants at the initial assessment prior to the 7 day wear of the activity monitor.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Physical activity levels measured by the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>This questionnaire will be administered to participants at the initial assessment prior to the 7 day wear of the activity monitor.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity levels measured by theOccupational Sitting and Physical Activity questionnaire (OSPAQ) </outcome>
      <timepoint>This questionnaire will be administered to participants at the initial assessment prior to the 7 day wear of the activity monitor.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Allied health professionals (aged 20 - 70 years including physiotherapists, speech pathologists, occupational therapists, psychologists, dietitians, pharmacists, radiographers, social workers, podiatrists, and orthotists) employed in the Sydney Local Health District (SLHD) (i.e. Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, Concord Repatriation General Hospital, Balmain hospital, Canterbury hospital) and who are working within their usual professional capacity will be invited to participate in this study.  They will be eligible for study inclusion if they are working within their usual professional capacity during the data collection period (7 days).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria  those employees who are unable to perform their usual work duties over the course of the study period.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be expressed as means and standard deviations. Independent groups t-tests will be performed to compare allied health groups/disciplines.  Significance will be set a p&lt;0.05 with a power at 0.80.
Comparisons will also be made between physical activity levels achieved by the allied health professionals and the Australian physical activity guidelines . 
For the sample size, if there is truly no difference in average step count per day between the allied health professionals and the recommended guideline of 10,000 steps/day, 112 participants are required to be 80% sure that the lower limit of a one-sided 95% confidence interval  will be above the non-inferiority limit of 1000 steps per day (Tudor-locke et al, 2001) 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>7</followup>
    <followuptype>Days</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>25/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>27/05/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>91</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Balmain Hospital - Balmain</hospital>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>Canterbury Hospital - Campsie</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2041 - Balmain</postcode>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord Repatriation Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>2194 - Campsie</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital / Sydney Local Health District</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Rd
Camperdown NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Rd
Camperdown NSW 2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006

</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Physical inactivity has been linked to increases in morbidity and mortality, with major implications for the general health. Participation in sufficient physical activity levels throughout the day is associated with significant health benefits.  The study aims to evaluate the physical activity levels of allied health staff working in Sydney Local Health District (SLHD) to determine the contribution of workplace to daily physical activity levels.
Specifically, the aims of the study are to:
1.	Quantify the number of steps taken and the amount of moderate to vigorous physical activity of allied health professionals during work time and outside work time. 
2.	Determine how the physical activity levels of allied health professionals employed within the SLHD compare to recommended physical activity levels for Australian adults.
3.	Investigate how physical activity levels vary between allied health professionals working in different allied health disciplines.
This study will be an observational cross sectional study.  A recruitment flyer will be distributed to all allied health departments (physiotherapy, speech pathology, occupational therapy, psychology, nutrition and dietetics, pharmacy, radiography, and social work, podiatry, orthotics) across the SLHD (Royal Prince Alfred hospital, Concord hospital, Balmain Hospital and Canterbury Hospital). 
Interested participants will be given a participant information sheet and will be required to sign a consent form.
Inclusion Criteria - Allied health professionals (aged 20 - 70 years) employed in the SLHD and who are working within their usual professional capacity during the data collection period (7 days).
Exclusion criteria  Allied health professionals who are unable to perform their usual work duties over the seven day study period.
Methods
Allied health professionals who agree to participate in this study will have the following baseline measurements collected:
-	Demographic information - age, gender, occupational classification, work department.
-	Basic anthropometric measurements - weight, height, body mass index (BMI), 
-	Administration of validated physical activity questionnaires:  Activity Australia Questionnaire,  International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ),  Occupational Sitting and Physical Activity Questionnaire (OSPAQ).
Participants will then be fitted with a physical activity monitor (uniaxial Actigraph GT1M accelerometer) and asked to wear for 7 days. Participants will also be asked to keep an activity diary.
Physical activity data will be analysed and presented as means and standard deviations of daily step count and amount of moderate-to-vigorous physical activity. Physical activity during work time will be compared with physical activity outside work time. Physical activity levels will be compared with recommended guidelines for Australian adults.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethics and Governance Office SLHD </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics and Governance Office 
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital 
Missenden Rd
Camperdown NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X15-0435 &amp; HREC/15/RPAH/580</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer Alison</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences University of Sydney
University of Sydney
PO Box 170 
Lidcombe NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>+61 414 300 416</phone>
      <fax>+612 9351 9601</fax>
      <email>jennifer.alison@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer Alison</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences University of Sydney
University of Sydney
PO Box 170 
Lidcombe NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>+61 414 300 416</phone>
      <fax>+612 9351 9601</fax>
      <email>jennifer.alison@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer Alison</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences University of Sydney
University of Sydney
PO Box 170 
Lidcombe NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>+61 414 300 416</phone>
      <fax>+612 9351 9601</fax>
      <email>jennifer.alison@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer Alison</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences University of Sydney
University of Sydney
PO Box 170 
Lidcombe NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>+61 414 300 416</phone>
      <fax>+612 9351 9601</fax>
      <email>jennifer.alison@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>