<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364246">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000559718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pregabalin versus Gabapentin in the Treatment of Sciatica</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pregabalin and Gabapentin Prospective Clinical Trial for the Treatment of Sciatica: A Randomised, Double-Blind, Cross-over Study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PAGPROS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sciatica</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Sequence 1 = Pregabalin capsules 150mg  initially 1 capsule daily for 1 week increasing to 1 capsule three times a day for 1 week then increase to 2 capsules three times a day thereafter. Treatment duration will be 8 weeks in total with drug tablet returns to be used to monitor compliance along with accountability logs. This will be followed by a 1 week washout period and then Gabapentin 400mg capsules in the identical titration method for a further 8 weeks treatment.</interventions>
    <comparator>Sequence 2 = Gabapentin capsules 400mg  initially 1 capsule daily for 1 week increasing to 1 capsule three times a day for 1 week then increase to 2 capsules three times a day thereafter. Treatment duration will be 8 weeks in total with drug tablet returns to be used to monitor compliance along with accountability logs. This will be followed by a 1 week washout period and then Pregabalin 150mg capsules in the identical titration method for a further 8 weeks treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the efficacy of pregabalin compared to gabapentin in the treatment of sciatica.
Definition of efficacy is reduction of sciatic pain with measure on an 11-point numerical rating scale from 0=no pain to 10=worst possible pain by patient, assessment by blinded neurosurgeon.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome assessments will be made at baseline, after the first treatment period of 8 weeks and again at baseline in the second treatment phase and after the second treatment period of 8 weeks on the alternate medication. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the frequency and severity of common of side-effects associated with pregabalin and gabapentin including fatigue, sedation, dizziness, ataxia, tremor, diplopia, nystagmus, amblyopia, amnesia, abnormal thinking, hypertension, vasodilation, peripheral oedema, dry mouth, weight gain, rash.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcome assessments will be made at baseline, after the first treatment period of 8 weeks and again at baseline in the second treatment phase and after the second treatment period of 8 weeks on the alternate medication.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>18 years or older
Diagnosis of sciatica 
First presentation to the pain clinic for intervention treatment
Patients with continuous sciatica for over 3 months, with a corresponding physical cause proven on CT or MRI, will be considered.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant or breastfeeding
Prior treatment with pregabalin and or gabapentin
Clinically relevant medical/psychological illness which might affect study participation
Creatinine clearance &lt;60ml/min
Taking antiepileptics, nerve blocks muscle relaxants, anticonvulsants, mexiletine, topical analgesics, or antiviral agents.
Patient history or laboratory results that suggested the presence of an inherited neuropathy or neuropathy attributable to other causes, such as hypothyroidism, vitamin B12 deficiency, connective tissue disease, amyloidosis, and toxic exposure
Major organ system disease, cardiovascular autonomic neuropathy, baseline postural hypotension of more than 20 mm Hg, sedation or ataxia due to concomitant drugs or other cause, urinary symptoms attributable to benign prostatic hypertrophy in male participants, psychiatric or substance abuse disorder, hypersensitivity to any of the study drugs, or a coexisting disorder causing pain as severe as the neuropathic pain.

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Double-blind, with double dummy method to maintain allocation concealment due to differences in dosing. Medications will be identical stored in identical containers.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomisation sequence using a permuted block with varying block size and a ratio of 1:1</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Townsville Hospital - Douglas</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Townsville Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Townsville hospital
100 Angus Smith Drive
Douglas Queensland 4814</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Private Practice Trust Fund - The Townsville Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Townsville hospital
100 Angus Smith Drive
Douglas Queensland 4814</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Pfizer Australia Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Pfizer Australia
38-42 Wharf Rd  West Ryde NSW 2114</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Sciatica or sciatic neuralgia, a common form of lumbosacral radiculopathy, is characterized by low back pain that radiates to the leg below the knee and can be accompanied by sensory loss, motor weakness and reflex abnormalities. Sciatica is considered to be a prognostic indicator of poor outcome among patients with low back pain with a substantial proportion continuing to have persistent pain for two years or longer.  The annual prevalence of sciatica is estimated to be between 14% and 2%. While guidelines provide clear and generally consistent recommendations for the prescription of drugs for non-specific low back pain this is not the case for sciatica.

Patients with a clinical diagnosis of sciatica are about five times more likely to take drugs than those with low back pain only, with analgesic and adjuvant pain drugs being the mainstay of current treatment. The efficacy of these prescribed medications is varied and conflicting in this population. Gabapentin and Pregabalin represent a newer approach to the treatment of sciatica. Both are analgesics of GABA that modulate the calcium-channel subunits, possibly decreasing the neurotransmitter release associated with the central sensitization that occurs in sciatica. 

With the recent PBS listing of Pregabalin for neuropathic pain refractory to treatment with other drugs, we hypothesize pregabalin to be superior to gabapentin in reduction of pain for patients suffering sciatica. This head to head clinical trial will examine the effects of both agents in treating pain associated with sciatica compared to placebo in a randomised controlled setting. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Townsville Health Service District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Townsville hospital
100 Angus Smith Drive
Douglas Queensland 4814</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/QTHS/117</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/06/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Marshman</name>
      <address>The Townsville hospital
100 Angus Smith Drive
Douglas Queensland 4814</address>
      <phone>+61 7 4433 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.a.g.marshman@btinternet.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Kelvin Robertson</name>
      <address>The Townsville hospital
100 Angus Smith Drive
Douglas Queensland 4814</address>
      <phone>+61 7 4433 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kelvin.robertson@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Marshman</name>
      <address>The Townsville hospital
100 Angus Smith Drive
Douglas Queensland 4814</address>
      <phone>+61 7 4433 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.a.g.marshman@btinternet.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>