<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335913">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000730000</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Minimally invasive versus standard open reduction of proximal humerus fractures</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective randomised controlled trial comparing clinical and radiographic outcomes of the deltopectoral and limited deltoid splitting approaches for fixation of displaced proximal humeral fractures in a skeletally mature population</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>No UTN available</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>No secondary ID</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Proximal humerus fractures</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The minimally invasive technique involves reduction of the fracture using closed methods and temporary fixation with k-wires to hold the fracture together. A small incision and approach is then performed directly through the deltoid muscle and a locking plate is placed down onto the bone via this small incision. It is then locked into place with a series of small stab incisions which allow placement of screws through the plate to hold it on the bone. The potential advantage is less surgical dissection with a faster recovery time and less disruption of the fracture fragments which may lead to better rates of fracture union. This duration of this procedure is approximately 90-120 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard open reduction internal fixation is via the deltopectoral approach which uses a large incision and is the most common method of fixing proximal humeral fractures. This technique allows the surgeon to identify all the parts of the fracture and put them back together under direct vision. It however means more surgical dissection and possible disruption of blood supply to the fracture fragments which may lead to higher nonunion rates. It may also take longer to recover from the larger surgical approach. The duration of this procedure is approximately 90-120 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The constant score combines physical examination tests with subjective evaluation by the patients. The subjective assessment consists of 35 points and the remaining 65 points are assigned for the physical examination assessment. The subjective assessment includes a single item for pain and 4 items for activities of daily living. The objective assessment includes range of motion and power. The total possible score is 100 points.  The constant score has become the most widely used shoulder evaluation instrument in Europe.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 3,6 and 12 months following surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand ( DASH ) score is a 30-item, self report questionnaire designed to measure physical function and symptoms in people with any of several musculoskeletal disorders of the upper limb. It is a valid, reliable and responsive tool that is commonly used for clinical and research purposes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 3,6 and 12 months following surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>radiographic outcomes to be assessed are the fracture reduction quality and the rate of union radiographically. We will also be looking at complications which can be seen radiographically eg malunion, nonunion, malposition of the hardware, osteonecrosis</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 3,6 and 12 months following surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Possible complications such as the following:
 - failure of fixation - seen on xrays
 - malunion - seen on xrays
 - nonunion - seen on xrays and clinical examination
 - osteonecrosis - seen on xrays
 - malposition of the hardware - seen on xrays
 - wound infection - clinical examination
 - neurovascular damage - clinical examination</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 3,6 and 12 months following surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>union rate - seen on xrays as evidence of fracture healing with bridging callus. Plus clinical examination of fracture site for pain, movement of the fracture or loss of fixation</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 3,6 and12 months following surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>skeletal maturity
able to sign consent and comply with treatment</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>compound injuries
previous surgery to upper limb
previous known upper limb dysfunction
neuromuscular disorder affecting upper limb
significant neurological deficit at time of injury
pathologic fracture
major medical comorbidities precluding surgical intervention</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a 2 surgeon study with one surgeon performing standard open reduction internal fixation with the other surgeon performing a limited deltoid splitting approach.
When a patient presents to our institution with a proximal humerus fracture and meets the inclusion criteria for the trial, the available imaging will be reviewed by the participating surgeons.  If both agree the patient should be treated with plate fixation then the patient will be approached to enter the trial. If they agree, they will then be randomized by a computer generated random number list to one of the above surgeons. Concealment of allocation is established by using sealed numbered envelopes. The envelope will be opened and the patient will be allocated that operation group. The surgeon will then be informed and the surgery will take place on the next available list.</concealment>
    <sequence>computer generated random number list</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Auckland District Health Board</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>214 Green Lane West
Epsom
Auckland 1042</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Auckland Public Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private bag 92024
Auckland Mail Centre
Auckland 1142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Proximal humerus fractures are increasingly common in societies with maturing populations. These fractures are not simple to treat with most being treated nonsurgically. If surgery is contemplated , a variety of surgical options exist including suture fixation, plating, nailing and arthroplasty. Locking plate technology has shown promising results especially in the setting of elderly patients with osteoporotic bone. More recently, minimally invasive techniques to apply these locking plates have been described. The two main approaches to internally fix these fractures has been the standard deltopectoral approach and the limited deltoid splitting approach. The potential advantages of a limited deltoid splitting approach are less soft tissue dissection and a faster postoperative recovery. However, standard open reduction allows direct anatomic reduction of the fracture at the expense of a larger surgical dissection.   To our knowledge, there have been no randomised controlled trials comparing these 2 approaches.  Our primary aim is to compare clinical outcomes following standard open reduction internal fixation via a deltopectoral approach versus a minimally invasive closed reduction and internal fixation via a limited deltoid splitting approach for treatment of displaced proximal humeral fractures.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Region Ethical Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/08/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jeremy Stanley</name>
      <address>14 Grand Drive 
Remuera
Auckland 1050</address>
      <phone>(64) 021527826</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jellystan@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jeremy Stanley</name>
      <address>14 Grand Drive 
Remuera
Auckland 1050</address>
      <phone>(64) 021527826</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jellystan@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jeremy Stanley</name>
      <address>14 Grand Drive 
Remuera
Auckland 1050</address>
      <phone>(64) 021527826</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jellystan@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>