<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372648">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000527369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of addition of anti-inflammatory medication to anti-depressant medication in the treatment of depression </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of addition of anti-inflammatory medication to anti-depressant medication on C-reactive protein levels in the treatment of depression </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>To be announced</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PREDDICT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is a randomised controlled treatment (RCT) trial over 8 weeks, with a 6 month post-RCT trial period, where study participants have the option to continue Vortioxetine in the post-RCT trial period. The study aims to investigate whether the use of a blood test of inflammation levels, prior to antidepressant treatment, can improve treatment of depression by guiding the decision to add anti-inflammatory medication to antidepressant treatment.
Specifically, the study aims to find out whether adding the anti-inflammatory medication Celecoxib to the antidepressant medication Vortioxetine can improve symptoms of depression. 
At the start of the study, participants would undergo a blood test to measure levels of the inflammatory marker C-reactive protein (CRP). For CRP, a cut-off level of 3mg/L will be used to determine whether participants are assigned to the "Depression with inflammation" arm, or to the "Depression without inflammation" arm. Within each study arm, participants would then be randomly assigned to 6 weeks of treatment with Vortioxetine plus Celecoxib, or Vortioxetine plus placebo.
All study medications are oral tablets. The dose of Vortioxetine is initially 5 mg daily in those receiving Celecoxib, with an option to increase to Vortioxetine 10mg daily 2 weeks into the study (after review by the Psychiatrist, and if it is thought this dose may benefit the study participant). The planned dose of Celecoxib is 400mg daily.
Study participants will be asked at each visit if any doses of study medication have been missed.</interventions>
    <comparator>Vortioxetine plus placebo, for a duration of 6 weeks. The comparator / control treatments are also oral tablets. The dose of Vortioxetine is initially 10 mg daily, with an option to increase to Vortioxetine 20 mg daily 2 weeks into the study (after review by the Psychiatrist, and if it is thought this dose may benefit the study participant). 
The placebo is a microcellulose tablet.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in MADRS, with a primary endpoint of proportion of study participants with a score reduction by 50% from baseline to 6 weeks (end of treatment).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment) and 6 weeks (end of treatment)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in C-reactive protein (CRP) levels, with a secondary endpoint of proportion of study participants with a reduction of CRP levels by 50% between baseline and 6 weeks (end of treatment).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment) and 6 weeks (end of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in levels of the inflammatory markers TNF-a, IL-6, and IL-1b, measured by enzyme linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA), with a secondary endpoint of proportion of study participants with a reduction of 50% of levels of these inflammatory markers between baseline and 6 weeks (end of treatment).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment) and 6 weeks (end of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of the anti-inflammatory Celecoxib 400 mg when combined with Vortioxetine, with a secondary endpoint of measuring adverse events (AEs).  At each visit, study participants will be asked to report adverse events (e.g. nausea, abdominal pain), and these will all be recorded.


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment) and 6 weeks (end of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of cognitive dysfunction, using the THINC-It tool: -secondary endpoint of proportion of study participants with a 50% improvement in subjective (PDQ-5) and each objective (Spotter, Symbol Check, Codebreaker, Trails) cognitive measure from baseline to 6 weeks.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment) and 6 weeks (end of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Clinical Global Impression-Severity (CGI-S) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment) and 6 weeks (end of treatment)

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Clinical Global Impression-Improvement (CGI-I)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment) and 6 weeks (end of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in functional measures, as assessed by proportion of study participants with a 50% improvement in Functioning Assessment Short Test (FAST) from baseline to 6 weeks (end of treatment)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment) and 6 weeks (end of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in WHO-5 Well-being Index, as assessed by proportion of study participants with a 50% improvement from baseline to 6 weeks (end of treatment)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment) and 6 weeks (end of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Sheehan Disability Scale, as assessed by proportion of study participants with a 50% improvement from baseline to 6 weeks (end of treatment)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment) and 6 weeks (end of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in workplace functioning, as assessed by proportion of study participants with a 50% improvement in Work Limitations Questionnaire from baseline to 6 weeks (end of treatment)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment) and 6 weeks (end of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in workplace functioning, as assessed by proportion of study participants with a 50% improvement in Endicott Workplace Productivity Scale from baseline to 6 weeks (end of treatment).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment) and 6 weeks (end of treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. The study participant is willing and able to provide informed consent.
2. Age 18  65 years of age.
3. Diagnosis of a Major Depressive Episode (MDE) as part of Major Depressive Disorder (MDD), using DSM-5 criteria. 
4. Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) score greater than or equal to 26 at screening visit and baseline. 
5. Duration of the current MDE is at least 3 months.
6. Use of a previous treatment in at least one prior episode of depression  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Presence of a co-morbid psychiatric disorder other than MDD that is a focus of clinical concern as confirmed by the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI).
2. A known relevant inflammatory or immune-related disorder such as rheumatoid arthritis, colitis, clinically significant asthma, multiple sclerosis, SLE, acute infections or fever.
3. A known neurodegenerative disease
4. Any medication for a general medical disorder that may affect cognitive function 
5. Electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) within the last 6 months.
6. The study participant has reported having received investigational agents as part of a separate study within 30 days of the screening visit.
7. Contraindications to the study drugs 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is concealed, by the use of central randomisation by phone/ fax/ computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Stratified allocation based on CRP levels at screening (prior to commencement of treatment), with a cut-off level of 3 mg/L to determine whether participants are assigned into the "Depression with inflammation" arm, or the "Depression without inflammation" arm. 
Within each arm, the method of sequence generation used will be simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Given a power of 0.95, and an alpha error of 0.05, the study sample size required to detect a change in MADRS of an effect size of 0.25 between baseline and week 6 would be 50 study participants in each of the four groups. This would be a total of 200 study participants (100 participants in the Depression with inflammation arm, and 100 study participants in the Depression without inflammation arm; 50 participants in each treatment group respectively). 

The primary outcome will be analysed using a mixed model for repeated measurements, using all available data. The baseline CRP level and stratified group (Depression with inflammation vs Depression without inflammation) will be used as a covariate. 
The potential treatment effect on CRP will be separated into the stratified arms (Depression with inflammation vs Depression without inflammation), as well as for total group (all 4 groups).
For dichotomous endpoints, such as response and remission, logistic regression with treatment as a factor and the baseline score as a covariate will be used. 
For continuous endpoints, the same methodology as that described for the primary endpoint will also be used. Continuous endpoints will also be analysed using an ANCOVA (OC and last observation carried forward (LOCF)).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>25/02/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>15/04/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Bernhard Baune</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Professor Bernhard Baune
Chair, Discipline of Psychiatry
University of Adelaide
Level 7, Adelaide Health and Medical Sciences Building
North Terrace
Adelaide
South Australia, 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Adelaide</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Adelaide
North Terrace
Adelaide
South Australia, 5005</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is a randomised controlled treatment (RCT) trial over 8 weeks in individuals with Major Depressive Disorder, with a 6 month post-RCT trial period, where study participants have the option to continue Vortioxetine. 
The purpose of the study is to investigate the effectiveness of using a simple blood test, prior to treatment of depression, to guide the use of anti-inflammatory medication as an addition to antidepressant medication. 
The study aims to find out whether adding the anti-inflammatory medication Celecoxib (also known as Celebrex) to the antidepressant medication Vortioxetine (also known as Brintellix) can improve symptoms of depression. 
There is evidence that raised levels of inflammatory markers in the blood are associated with depression. The study measures the inflammatory marker C-reactive protein (CRP) prior to commencing treatment, with study participants assigned to a study "arm" based on CRP levels. Within each study "arm", participants receive treatment for 6 weeks, with either Vortioxetine plus Celecoxib, or Vortioxetine plus placebo. 
Levels of circulating inflammatory markers, tests of cognitive function, and depression symptoms are measured at baseline (before treatment) and again at the end of this 6 week treatment period.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/17/RAH/111</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Adelaide HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Adelaide
Adelaide, SA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/06/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bernhard Baune</name>
      <address>Discipline of Psychiatry School of Medicine University of Adelaide Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>61 8 8313 7382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernhard.baune@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Mills</name>
      <address>Discipline of Psychiatry School of Medicine University of Adelaide Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 8222 5142</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.mills@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bernhard Baune</name>
      <address>Discipline of Psychiatry School of Medicine University of Adelaide Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>61 8 8313 7382</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bernhard.baune@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Mills</name>
      <address>Discipline of Psychiatry School of Medicine University of Adelaide Adelaide, SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 8222 5142</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.mills@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>