<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362722">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000829819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>In children presenting to the emergency department with a moderate acute asthma attack, does the addition of ipratropium bromide decrease hospital admission rate?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In children presenting to the emergency department with a moderate acute asthma attack, does the addition of ipratropium bromide, to currently accepted therapy (salbutamol and prednisolone) decrease hospital admission rate?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1132-4703</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention group: will receive standard care for moderate acute asthma. That is, salbutamol 6 puffs(100mcg per puff) via MDI/spacer x3 20 minutely over 1 hour for &lt;20kg OR 12 puffs via same method for &gt; 20kg. Plus 1mg /kg prednisolone, as syrup, before 2nd dose of salbutamol. They will also receive 4 puffs of ipratropium bromide(21mcg per puff) via MDI/spacer x3 20minutely for &lt; 20kg and 8 puffs via same method for &gt; 20kg. Ipratropoium will be given at same time as salbutamol.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group: will receive salbutamol and prednisolone as above AND will receive placebo via de-identified puffer instead of atrovent/ipratropium bromide.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of this study is to determine whether the rate of hospitalisation in children with moderate asthma presenting to the Emergency Department is  decreased, if inhaled ipratioum bromide( IB) is added to current practice</outcome>
      <timepoint>Clinical review will include grading as per PASS score(paediatric asthma severity score ), examination of patient by a doctor and respiratory observations, such as; heart rate , respiratory rate, temperature and oxygen saturations. These will be recorded at the following intervals onto a preformed recording sheet. 

0 hours, (pre-treatment)
20  minutes ( pre 2nd treatment)
40 minutes ( pre 3rd treatment)
60-70 minutes 
Then hourly until 3 hours post initial treatment, at which time  decision whether to admit or discharge home will be based as per NSW Clinical Practice Guidelines.(ie. primary outcome measure). 
This is the end of study.(4 hours post initiation of treatment)
If a patient deteriorates, - ie. asthma becomes severe, the study is cease, study code is "unlocked", and the treatment is escalated as per the NSW clinical practice guidelines.

The clinical severity score chosen in this study is the Paediatric Asthma Severity score (PASS). This is a validated clinical scoring system that consists of measuring 3 variables namely accessory muscle score, wheeze score, dyspnoea.  
The PASS is a simple tool that was developed for the use in asthma severity studies.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary aims are to measure reduction in clinical severity score(PASS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of study is either discharge from ED or admission for further treatment as inpatient. ie. disposition(see above)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time spent in ED</outcome>
      <timepoint>Determined at end of study. ie disposition.
All patients who improve, regardless of treatment arms, should be discharged at 4 hours from time of 1st treatment.
Patients who do not, or who deteriorate will be admitted as inpatients for further treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children aged &gt;2 and &lt; 16 years with a clinical diagnosis of acute moderate asthma exacrebation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children with mild or severe/life threatening asthma
Children borne before 34 weeks of gestation
Children suffering from following pathologies: chronic pulmonary diseases (examples: cystic fibrosis, bronchopulmonary dysplasia), congenital heart or lung disease, recurrent pulmonary inhalations, neuromuscular disease
Immunocompromised children
Children with confirmed pneumonia
Children who have received corticosteroid within 24 hours of presentation and/or atrovent or ventolin with 3 hours of presentation
Children for whom parent/carer refused to give informed consent
Children who have had a previous episode of acute asthma requiring ICU admission/intervention, including treatment with magnesium</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All children presenting to the JHH ED with moderately severe asthma as graded by the NSW Clinical Practice Asthma Guidelines will be assessed for eligibility for enrollment  into the study. 
Consent will be sought from eligible patients and their parents.
Consented patients will be randomised into one of two treatment arms.
Randomisation will be by sealed numbered envelope and numbers assigned by random number generator. 
Clinicians and patients will be blinded to the randomisation code and the treatment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Consented patients will be randomised into one of two treatment arms.
Randomisation will be by sealed numbered envelope and numbers assigned by random number generator.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>128</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>john hunter emergency</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>lookout rd new lambton
nsw
2305</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>John Hunter Hospital Emergency Department</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>lookout road, new lambton, NSW ,2305</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In this study we aim to look at the best treatment for children presentling to the emergency department with an acute episode of asthma. Specifically, we are interested in children who have moderate severity of their symptoms on arrival.

The primary purpose of this study is to determine whether there is a decreased need for hospital admission in these children when they atre treated with inhaled ipratropium bromide (IIB), inhaled salbutamol (IS) and  oral steroid , compared with patients treated with Inhaled salbutamol and oral steroid alone</summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethics and Governance Unit</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>locked bag 1
Lookout rd, new lambton
NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/03/21/3.01</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>DRs Lee and Feltrin</name>
      <address>john hunter hospital emergency
lookout rd,
new lambton
2305, nsw</address>
      <phone>+61 02 49213000</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 49213065</fax>
      <email>Mark.Lee@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Drs Mark Lee and Robert Feltrin</name>
      <address>John Hunter Hospital Emergency Department
Lookout Rd, New Lambton
NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+ 61 02 49213000</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 49213065</fax>
      <email>Robert.Feltrin@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Robert Feltrin</name>
      <address>john hunter hospital
lookout rd new lambton
2305, nsw</address>
      <phone>+61 02 49213000</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 49213065</fax>
      <email>Robert.Feltrin@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>