<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372027">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000013369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study of tongue stimulation to improve balance and gait in stroke survivors</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study of cranial nerve non-invasive neuromodulation to improve balance and gait in stroke survivors</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1190-9249 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Balance impairment</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Gait impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants with recent stroke will given sensory tongue stimulation (cranial nerve non-invasive neuromodulation  CNNINM)  through a device called the Portable Neuromodulation Stimulator (PoNS). and concurrent intensive balance and gait training,  in addition to usual rehabilitation. The battery-operated PoNS device is worn around the neck and has a mouthpiece with a hexagonally patterned array of gold-plated circular electrodes that goes into the mouth, resting on the top of the tongue, and is held lightly in place by the lips and teeth. The tongue stimulation is provided concurrently with balance and gait training, and the intensity of stimulation can be adjusted for comfort. Participants will attend for treatment with an experienced physiotherapist twice daily for 1.5 hours, 5 days per week for 2 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be participants with recent stroke who will be given intensive balance and gait training in addition to usual rehabilitation. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>MiniBEST Balance Evaluation Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait assessments, including The Timed Up-and-Go Test and overground walking while wearing inertial sensors at the wrists, ankles, sternum and waist (Mobility Lab System, APDM, Inc. Portland OR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>COGLOG measure of cognitive function</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression Anxiety Stress Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Canadian Occupational Performance Measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events, These may include headaches, clenched jaw leading to temporomandibular joint dysfunction, excessive salivation, or excessive fatigue. Adverse events will be assessed by interviewing the participant at each intervention session.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout 2-week intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Aged between 18 and 75 years
2. Diagnosis of stroke
3. Admitted for inpatient rehabilitation at the Royal Park Rehabilitation Centre
4. Have sufficient cognitive capacity to participate in this study (ascertained by the rehabilitation consultant).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Major co-morbidities, especially other neurological disorders, uncontrolled pain, uncontrolled hypertension, brittle diabetes etc.
2. Oral health problems (e.g. gum disease, active cankers etc.) or a history of oral cancer, precluding them from safe participation in the study.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involves contacting the central administration site to obtain the group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Pilot study</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A t-test will be used to compare the difference between groups on change in the primary outcome measure (miniBEST). Exploratory analyses will be conducted using t-tests or Mann-Whitney U tests to compare the groups on the secondary outcome measures. 

For this study of 10 participants, missing data will be ignored (assuming that they are missing at random) and only the available data will be analysed.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>3/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>14/04/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Royal Park campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Melbourne Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Grattan Street
Parkville, VIC 3050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Private philanthropy</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>c/- Royal Melbourne Hospital Foundation
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Parkville, VIC 3050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many people with stroke have walking and balance dysfunction. Sensory tongue stimulation (cranial nerve non-invasive neuromodulation  CNNINM) provided through a device called the Portable Neuromodulation Stimulator (PoNS) can stimulate regions in the brain that are important for balance and gait.  This study will be a preliminary randomised controlled trial (RCT) of the PoNS combined with a structured task-specific rehabilitation program in stroke survivors undergoing inpatient rehabilitation.The study will be registered with the Therapeutic Goods Administration under the Clinical Trial Notification Scheme (device trial). Ten participants will be randomised to either a 2-week intensive balance and gait training program with a physiotherapist while using the PoNS (intervention), or to a 2-week intensive balance and gait training program with a physiotherapist only (control). Both the intervention and control programs will be conducted at the Royal Park Rehabilitation Centre, and will be additional to the patients' usual rehabilitation program. Training sessions will be tailored to the needs of each participant and comprise five main components: movement control, balance, gait, cognition and breathing and relaxation. Participants will be assessed on a range of outcome measures related to gait and balance, as well as self-perception of performance, depression, cognition and oculomotor function. Assessments will occur at baseline and post-intervention. The primary outcome measures will be the miniBEST Test, which assesses balance. This study will be the first systematic study of the PoNS in Australia, and will establish the safety and preliminary efficacy of the PoNS/training protocol. It will also provide data on which to base a sample size calculation for a future larger RCT.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>C/- Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan St 
Parkville, VIC. 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/MH/103</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mary Galea</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine (Royal Melbourne Hospital)
The University of Melbourne
Parkville, VIC. 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2017</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.galea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mary Galea</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine (Royal Melbourne Hospital)
The University of Melbourne
Parkville, VIC. 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2017</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.galea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mary Galea</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine (Royal Melbourne Hospital)
The University of Melbourne
Parkville, VIC. 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2017</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.galea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mary Galea</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine (Royal Melbourne Hospital)
The University of Melbourne
Parkville, VIC. 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2017</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.galea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>