<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366046">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000595617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The impact of removing financial incentive payments for general practitioners on their chlamydia testing rates in general practice - a randomised controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The impact of removing financial incentive payments for general practitioners on their chlamydia testing rates in general practice - a randomised controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ACCEPt-able</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>chlamydia </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sexually transmitted infections</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Factorial cluster RCT design - 4 study groups
1) Incentive payments: This group will continue to receive incentive for each chlamydia test done for 16 to 29 year old men or women. These payments will range from $5 per eligible test for up to 20% coverage to $8 per test for over 40% coverage. The clinic will also receive another $10 per test if a practice nurse initiates chlamydia testing. The intervention period is up to 2 years.

2) Audit+feedback only: Provision of quarterly chlamydia testing reports to each GP. The report lists the number of patients aged 16 to 29 years the GP has tested during the quarter, his/her chlamydia testing rate for the quarter and for the previous 12 months. The reports will be given both verbally and in writing to the clinic in a quarterly face to face meeting where a study Research Officer will explain the results and discuss how the clinic can further improve their rates. The intervention period is up to 2 years.



3) None: GPs and clinics will NOT receive any incentive payments or audit+feedback on their chlamydia testing performance. The intervention period is up to 2 years.


</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will continue to receive incentive payments and audit plus feedback for chlamydia testing among 16 to 29 year old men and women.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Chlamydia testing proportion: Numerator = total number of unique individuals aged 16 to 29 years who have had at least one test in the last 12 months. Denominator = total number of unique individuals who have had a consultation with a participating GP at least once in the last 12 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of incentives and/or audit+feedback for chlamydia testing in general practice. This will be assessed by semi-structured interviews with GPs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>General Practitioners and Practice nurses who work in a general practice that has been participating in the intervention group of ACCEPt are eligible to participate. 
ACCEPt is a cluster RCT of a chlamydia testing intervention. We propose to re-randomised intervention clinics at the conclusion of the trial to evaluate the importance of incentive payments and audit+feedback. The ACCEPt protocol has been accepted as a Lancet published protocol: Hocking JS, Low N, Guy R, Law M, Donovan B, Kaldor J, Temple-Smith M, Gunn J, Fairley CK. 12 PRT 09010: Australian Chlamydia Control Effectiveness Pilot (ACCEPt): a cluster randomised controlled trial of chlamydia testing in general practice (ACTRN1260000297022) Lancet protocol. Published May 2013.
ACCEPt has been registered on the ANZCTR - 1260000297022.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>  No exclusion criteria</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>When the ACCEPt trial is finished, practices in the intervention group will be invited by Research Officers to participate in ACCEPt-able. All General Practitioners and Practice nurses  will be invited to participate. They will receive a presentation, plain language statement  outlining the trial and will be encouraged to ask questions. They will be required to sign an consent form. </concealment>
    <sequence>The unit of randomisation is a general practice and these will be randomised using a minimisation approach to ensure key variables are evenly distributed across 4 groups. These variables are testing rates, size of practice population and gender of GP. The trial statistician is located at a site away from the participating practices. Allocation of practice to 1 or the 4 groups is according to the computer-generated algorithm. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics
Melbourne School of Population and Global Health
3/207 Bouverie Street
Carlton 3053
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601 



Postal

 National Health and Medical Research Council
 GPO Box 1421
 Canberra ACT 2601
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Financial incentives and external audit plus feedback are designed to motivate General Practitioners (GP) to change their clinical behaviour with the intention of improving the quality of care. Financial incentives are widely used at a significant cost to the Australian Government. Audit plus feedback is a key component of the RACGP Quality Improvement and Continuing Professional Development Program. To date, there is little empirical evidence about the impact of removing financial incentives and/or audit plus feedback on professional performance once they are in place.
Removal of Financial Incentives Trial (ReFIT) is a randomised trial that aims to investigate whether the removal of financial incentives and or audit plus feedback impacts on GPs chlamydia testing performance. ReFIT will follow on from the Australian Chlamydia Control Effectiveness Pilot (ACCEPt), a trial of the impact of a multifaceted intervention including incentive payments and quarterly audit plus feedback on GPs chlamydia testing rates. This trial will be conducted over 36 months involving 70 general practices (approx. 600 GPs) in QLD, NSW, VIC and SA. 
We have the unique opportunity to re-randomise GPs who participated in ACCEPt, to investigate whether chlamydia testing rates are sustained when incentive payments and/or feedback are removed. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>RACGP National Research and Evaluation Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>RACGP
100 Wellington Pde
East Melbourne Victoria 3002</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NREEC14-004</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jane Hocking</name>
      <address>Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics
University of Melbourne
3/207 Bouverie St
Carlton
Victoria 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0762</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jhocking@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Anna Wood</name>
      <address>Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics
University of Melbourne
3/207 Bouverie St
Carlton
Victoria 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 4574</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>annwood@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jane Hocking</name>
      <address>Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics
University of Melbourne
3/207 Bouverie St
Carlton
Victoria 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 0762</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jhocking@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Anna Wood</name>
      <address>Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics
University of Melbourne
3/207 Bouverie St
Carlton</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 4574</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>annwood@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>