<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369718">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000460404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of the Let's Talk about Children recovery model for parents in Victorian mental health and family services: Phase 3</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised control trial of Lets Talk About Children on the mental health recovery of parents with a mental illness: Phase 3.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Family related mental illness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Schizophrenia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Let's Talk About Children is an intervention that is applied by practitioners to engage with and support parents who have a mental illness in relation to their families and children. Within the 2-3 session intervention the practitioner engages with the parent about the impact of their illness on their children.  The mental health practitioner assists the parent to chart the developmental progress of their children, monitor their wellbeing and to talk to their children about the illness and possible impacts on them and the family. This also involves the practitioner helping the parent to understand the impact of the mental illness on their children along with helping the parent to provide ongoing support to their children. The intervention is implemented in 3 sessions however with practitioner and parent agreement this is reduced to 2 sessions based on their judgement that the 3rd session is not required. Let's Talk sessions are logged by the treating practitioner.  Sessions are commonly implemented for 60 minutes once per week. Practitioners are trained in the intervention by completing 4 online modules (1 hour each) along with a follow up 4 hour face to face training session. The face-to-face practitioner training is undertaken within 2 weeks of completing the online modules and the intervention is implemented with parents within 1 month. The face-to-face training is facilitated by a trained experienced practitioner.</interventions>
    <comparator>During the wait list period the control group will continue to receive standard care from their treating clinician and will be offered the intervention after 6 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recovery as measured by the Recovery Assessment Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed at baseline and post intervention (6 weeks post baseline) and 6 months after post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting as measured by the Parenting Stress Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed at baseline and post intervention (6 weeks post baseline) and 6 months after post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Family functioning as measured by the Family Assessment Device</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed at baseline and post intervention (6 weeks post baseline) and 6 months after post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>How often parent engages with children about mental illness as measured by frequency of engagement score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed at baseline and post intervention (6 weeks post baseline) and 6 months after post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>How a parent engages with the mental health practitioner as measured by the working alliance inventory as completed by the parent</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed at baseline and post intervention (6 weeks post baseline) and 6 months after post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life as measured by the Assessment of Quality of Life (AQoL)-8D instrument</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed at baseline and post intervention (6 weeks post baseline) and 6 months after post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Clients of the participating services (adult mental health service, mental health community support service or family support service)
Diagnosed mental illness 
Parent living at least some time with children 
Over 18 years of age 
Capable of giving informed consent as identified by their treating practitioners </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Non-english speaking clients 
Non-custodial parents 
Parents deemed too unwell by the practitioner to participate in the study (where it is deemed by the practitioner for involvement to do harm to the client) or to be able to provide consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Practitioners with an interest in family sensitive practice will communicate interest to be trained in the Let’s Talk intervention and to participate in the research. Randomisation will occur at the practitioner level after the research team has obtained their consent and notified the researchers of potentially eligible parent-clients on their case load. Thus, practitioners will be randomly assigned to the Let’s Talk/intervention condition to be trained and deliver Let’s Talk to parents. The remaining eligible practitioners will be assigned to the wait list/control condition and trained in the intervention to deliver to parents at the completion of the research.

Parent-clients on the case load of consenting practitioners will be advised of a research project into recovery by their treating practitioner. They will also receive a brief introduction to the research containing a consent form to be contacted for further information. If potential parent-clients are interested in receiving more information about the study, the parent-client will complete the contact details form and forward to the researchers (by fax, email or reply paid envelope). The researchers will then contact the parent-client to provide a detailed verbal and written description of the research and to determine their willingness to consent to being involved in the study. 

All parent-clients agreeing to participate in the study will be sent a questionnaire pack containing survey measures on recovery, parenting stress and family functioning. A reply paid envelope will be provided with the questionnaire pack for the parent-client to complete and post themselves, or the parent-clients can nominate to be called by the researchers for completion over the phone if they wish. Parent-clients will also complete questionnaire packs (as above) at two later time frames – after completing Let’s Talk below (or equivalent time frame - an estimated 4-10 weeks after pre questionnaires) for wait list controls and then a third identical questionnaire package at follow-up (6 months after the post questionnaire package). 

Following the completion of the first questionnaire package all participating practitioners will then be randomised to either: (1) wait list control group or (2) Let’s Talk intervention group to receive training in the intervention within a month. The researchers will initially be blind to the allocation of the participant at the collection of informed consent and collection of the baseline data. Following this, an independent administrative officer (based at a different site to the research team) will allocate the practitioner based on the computer generated random sequence (using SPSS). Allocation will involve contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is “off-site” from the central administration team.  The researcher will advise the practitioner of the outcome of the allocation and from this point on the research assistant who will remain blind to the allocation will collect the post and follow-up questionnaire data. 

Following this stage, parent-clients of trained Let’s Talk practitioners will be advised of the intervention by their treating practitioner and asked if they would like to participate in the intervention. The practitioner will undertake the intervention according to agreement with their parent- client. If there is agreement the parent client will receive the two to three session Let’s Talk intervention from their practitioner. If the parent- client declines the Let’s Talk intervention they will continue with treatment as usual with their practitioner. Participants will also be advised that they can decline the intervention but continue to participate in the research study or be involved in the intervention and decline to be involved further in the research.  

The intervention involves a discussion between the parent-client and their practitioner about their children, to discuss with parents the potential impact of the mental illness on the children and to assist parents in supporting their children to better understand and cope with parental mental illness. The intervention includes charting the developmental progress of their children, monitoring their well-being and supporting the parent to talk to their children about the illness and possible impacts on them and the family.  

Both intervention and wait list groups will continue to complete the questionnaires at post and follow up data collections as indicated above. The control group will continue to receive ‘treatment as usual’ from their non-trained (in Let's Talk)  practitioner and will be informed about (and offered) Let's Talk as they complete the final follow up questionnaire following the training of their treating practitioner. Of those parents who also consented to be interviewed they may be invited to participate in a semi-structured interview approximately 10 weeks after completing the first questionnaire package. Primarily the interview aims to ascertain their experience of the intervention and any impact it may have had on them and their family.  All parent-clients who complete questionnaires with receive a $20 supermarket voucher.  Recruitment will occur over a 15 month period.
</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence will be developed by computer generation of random number sequences via SPSS by the project manager prior to commencing the project, and maintained by the admin officer. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Mixed models repeated measures models 

Participant numbers were initially determined by a power calculation indicating a minimum n=72 participants with Crit F=1.90 (using GPOWER 3.1, assuming 6 groups and 3 repetitions, a small effect size, an alpha of 5% and power of 95%) to be required. In addition we also undertook two further power calculations based on different effect size data from our pilot study (from analyses employing outcomes for different subscales from the parenting stress measure).  The first indicated a minimum n=48 participants with Crit F=1.94 (assuming 6 groups and 3 repetitions based on an observed effect size of .09 (GPOWER effect size f of 0.31), an alpha of 5% and power of 95%). The second more conservative calculation indicated a minimum n=114 participants with Crit F=1.87 (assuming 6 groups and 3 repetitions based on an observed effect size of .036 (GPOWER effect size f of 0.19), an alpha of 5% and power of 95%). 

The larger number of participants in the proposed study will account for parent drop out, to allow between group comparisons across sectors and for additional power due to the cluster design. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>23/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>192</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Latrobe Regional Hospital - Traralgon</hospital>
    <hospital>The Northern Hospital - Epping</hospital>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Royal Park campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Maroondah Hospital - Ringwood East</hospital>
    <hospital>Albury Wodonga Health - Wodonga campus - Wodonga</hospital>
    <hospital>Northeast Health Wangaratta - Wangaratta</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wellington Road
Clayton,  
Victoria 3000   
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victorian Department of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50 Lonsdale Street
Melbourne
Victoria 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>La Trobe University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Bouverie Centre
8 Gardiner St  
Brunswick  
Victoria 3056 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Parenting Research Centre</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>5/232 Victoria Parade, 
East Melbourne  
Victoria 3002 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Deakin University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood
Victoria 3025</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Melbourne</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Grattan Street
Parkville
Victoria 3010</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research examines the utility of Let's Talk About Children intervention for its application in Australian mental health services. The objectives of the project are to determine the effectiveness of the Let's Talk program, an innovative, evidence-based program which involves training clinicians in talking to mental health clients about their children. The research will investigate the impact of Let's Talk on parenting confidence and family functioning along with aspects of recovery (e.g. self worth, relationships, independent living) and quality of life, as compared to a control group receiving standard treatment. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Clayton campus
Wellington Road
Clayton
Victoria 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/01/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF13/3300120130017</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Darryl Maybery</name>
      <address>Monash University
3 Ollerton Avenue
Moe
Victoria 3825</address>
      <phone>+61429358470</phone>
      <fax>+69361281080</fax>
      <email>dmaybery@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Julie Irvine</name>
      <address>Monash University
3 Ollerton Avenue
Moe 
Victoria 3825</address>
      <phone>+69361281000</phone>
      <fax>+69361281080</fax>
      <email>julie.irvine@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Darryl Maybery</name>
      <address>Monash University
3 Ollerton Avenue
Moe 
Victoria 3825</address>
      <phone>+61429358470</phone>
      <fax>+69361281080</fax>
      <email>dmaybery@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Darryl Maybery</name>
      <address>Monash University
3 Ollerton Avenue
Moe 
Victoria 3825</address>
      <phone>+61429358470</phone>
      <fax>+69361281080</fax>
      <email>dmaybery@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>