<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335021">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/01/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/01/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000060044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The research project is trying to find out if we can improve the results of best available chemotherapy for Chronic Lymphocytic Leukaemia (CLL) by the addition of a new drug called lenalidomide.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Australasian and French Phase III, Multicentre, Randomised Trial Comparing Lenalidomide Consolidation versus No Consolidation in Patients With Chronic Lymphocytic Leukaemia and Residual Disease Following Induction Chemotherapy </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RESIDUUM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>CLL6</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukaemia (CLL)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Chronic leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>After initial chemotherapy (the standard routine chemotherapy given to patients with CLL) patients will be randomised to either follow-up or to new medication Lenalidomide. Patients randomised to followup will visit their clinician regularly and have blood tests for the same amount of time as those randomised to Lenalidomide. Those randomised to Lenalidomide will commence at 5mg (2.5 mg for those with renal impairment) and, if tolerated, escalate to a maximum of 10mg (5mg in renally impaired) in 2.5mg increments every 2 cycles. At day 28 patient will undergo blood tests to ensure safe to continue with treatment. A new cycle will commence at the appropriate dose. This will occur for 24 months (2years).</interventions>
    <comparator>the observation patients compared to the Lenalidomide treated patients</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to clinical disease progression, or death, from the date of randomisation. Patients will be monitored for evidence of disease progresssion using clinical, radiological and flow cytometry according to standardised international criteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>from randomisation until either disease progresses or death occurs.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Conversion to Minimal Residual Disease (MRD) negativity for randomized patients. Measured by flow cytometry of Bone Marrow sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>from commencement of Lenalidomide. Lenalidomide treatment is for 2years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to requirement for next therapy after Lenalidomide.</outcome>
      <timepoint>from when Lenalidomide is finished to time until next therapy is prescribed for the patient.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of patients with improvement in disease response. Results from routine tests such as bone marrow biospy and blood test will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be monitored for evidence of disease progresssion using clinical, radiological and flow cytometry according to standardised international criteria.At regular timepoins during and after treatment. Timepoints may vary due to patient tolerance of Lenalidomide.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival, measured by clinician at follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>from time of registration to final followup. (for three years from time of last randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability of Lenalidomide consolidation.Measured by assessing patient ability to go on with next planned cycles - involves blood tests to ensure blood counts have recovered satisfactorily so as next cycle can be commenced.</outcome>
      <timepoint>monthly assessment of patient tolerability for the 2years of Lenalidomide maintenance therapy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>B-cell Chronic Lymphocytic Leukaemia (CLL) confirmed according to World Health Organisation (WHO) Criteria. Age 18 years or older. Pre-Fludarabine chlorambucil (FC)/Fludarabine chlorambucil rituximab (FCR) chemotherapy blood sample desirable. Completed 4 to 6 cycles of FC or FCR, and within 3  6 months of last dose of chemotherapy. Achieved partial response or better following chemotherapy. Evidence of residual disease: at least one of clinical or CT lymphadenopathy &gt;1.5cm, clinical or Computed Axial Tomography Scan (CT) hepatomegaly or splenomegaly, positive bone marrow histology (including the persistence of three or
more lymphoid nodules, regardless of immunohistochemical features), or detectable minimal residual disease (MRD) in blood or
marrow obtained from flow cytometry result performed at Westmead Hospital Flow Cytometry Unit. Adequate haematological recovery following chemotherapy (haemoglobin (Hb) &gt; 110g/L, neutrophils &gt; 1.5 x 10^9/L,
platelets &gt;100 x 10^9/L). Alkaline phosphatase and transaminases lessthan or equal to 2 x Upper Limit of Normal (ULN). Creatinine clearance greaterthan or equal to 30 ml/min at Screening (calculated by Cockcroft-Gault formula. Females of childbearing potential must use an effective method of contraception or practice absolute abstinence for 4 weeks prior to lenalidomide therapy, during treatment and 4 weeks after treatment discontinuation Male patients must use contraception during lenalidomide treatment and for 1 week after Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0 to 1. Life expectancy greater than 6 months. Patients written informed consent. Subjects must agree not to donate blood, semen or sperm while on study treatment and for 1 week after treatment discontinuation. Subjects must agree not to share their medication and to return unused supplies.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prior chemotherapy other than any of the following:
a) chlorambucil given for CLL up to a cumulative dose 70mg/m2 b) FC and FCR induction chemotherapy. Active second malignancy currently requiring treatment (except for non-melanoma skin cancer or cervical cancer in-situ). Known hypersensitivity with anaphylactic reaction to lenalidomide. Class III or IV cardiac disease defined by the New York Heart Association (NYHA). Severe or debilitating pulmonary disease. Severe or debilitating central nervous system disease or cerebral dysfunction. Transformation to aggressive B-cell malignancy, e.g. diffuse large cell lymphoma, Richters syndrome or prolymphocytic leukaemia. Active bacterial, viral or fungal infection at Screening. Human Immuno-deficiency Virus (HIV) infection. Positivity for Hepatitis B Virus (HBV) surface antigen or HBV surface antibody unless due to vaccination. Any coexisting medical or psychological condition that would preclude participation in the required study procedures. Pregnancy and lactation. Vaccination with a live vaccine at any time during the study Trial participant not accessible for duration of trial including follow up.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>central randomisation by phone/fax/computer</concealment>
    <sequence>randomised in a 1:1 ratio, as noted above.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/05/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>192</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australasian Leukaemia and Lymphoma Group (ALLG)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>35 Elizabeth Street, Richmond 3121 Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Celgene</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Celgene Pty Ltd
G2/64 Talavera Road
North Ryde, NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>to assess the effect of lenalidomide consolidation (vs observation with no further therapy) in previously untreated CLL patients with measurable disease after at least 4 cycles of FCR therapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hopital HREC </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 2900 Fitzroy Victoria, 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/10/SVHM/67</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor David Gottlieb</name>
      <address>Westmead Hospital
Haematology Department
Westmead
New South Wales</address>
      <phone>610298456033</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>not available</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Marijana Vanevski</name>
      <address>Centre for Biostatistics and Clinical Trials
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place
East Melbourne
3002
Victoria</address>
      <phone>610396561143</phone>
      <fax>610396561420</fax>
      <email>marijana.vanevski@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Delaine Smith</name>
      <address>ALLG, Ground Level, 35 Elizabeth Street, Richmond, 3121 Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61, 03, 8373 9701</phone>
      <fax>+61, 03, 9429 8277</fax>
      <email>delaine.smith@allg.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Gottlieb</name>
      <address>Westmead Hospital Haematology Department Westmead, corner Hawkesbury Road and Darcy Road, Westmead New South Wales 2145</address>
      <phone>+61, 02, 98456033 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.gottlieb@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>