<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336145">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001031055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase Ib/II Clinical Evaluation of the Safety of Combining the mTOR inhibitor Everolimus with 5-Azacitidine in Acute Myeloid Leukaemia (AML).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase Ib/II Clinical Evaluation of the Safety of Combining the mTOR inhibitor Everolimus with 5-Azacitidine in AML</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Myeloid Leukaemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Leukaemia - Acute leukaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Azacitidine injection given sub-cutaneously for 7 doses D1-5 and D8-9 of a 28 day cycle, dosages at 75mg/m2.  Everolimus given orally d5-21, cohorts increasing 2.5mg, 5mg, 10mg.  28 day cycles continue unless disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or stem cell transplant.</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine the safety and tolerability of Everolimus in combination with 5-azacitidine in AML, determined by Quality of Life assessments and Adverse Events.  Examples of adverse events include gastrointestinal (nausea, vomiting and diarrhoea), haematological (anaemia, thrombocytopenia, leukopenia/neutropenia), and injection site reactions, also electrolyte imbalances.  Adverse events will be assessed every day during D1-5 and D8-9 during treatment and twice weekly for the following 2 weeks of the cycle.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuously throughout cycle</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To provide preliminary data that Everolimus in combination with 5-azacitidine may induce meaningful clinical responses and delay leukaemic relapse in patients with AML, determined by blood test and bone marrow biopsies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Contiuously throughout cycle.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess biomarkers of response such as gene specific methylation and phosphorylayion status of mTOR targets, from laboratory studies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Contiuously throughout cycle.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess patient related outcomes for patients receiving the Everolimus/5-azacitidine combination via adverse events and quality of life questionnaries.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Contiuously throughout cycle.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Untreated AML patients (defined by WHO 2008 criteria) over the age of 60 or relapsed/refractory AML over the age of 18 who have received up to 2 previous lines of intensive chemotherapy
* No prior failure to achieve at least a PR with Azacitidine or Everolimus   
* Provision of written informed consent 
* Secondary AML (including therapy-related) are included
* Life expectancy of greater than 3 months in relation to diseases other then AML/MDS
* ECOG performance status 0  3 
* Electrolyte levels (potassium, calcium (albumin-adjusted), magnesium, phosphorous) within normal limits (WNL) or easily correctable with supplements
* Adequate hepatic function as defined by bilirubin = 1.5 x the upper limit of normal (ULN) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) = 2.5 x ULN 
* Adequate renal function, with serum creatinine = 1.5 x ULN or GFR &gt; 30 ml/minute
* Patients with no uncontrolled active infection
* Hydroxyurea ceased 48 hours prior to study therapy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Any serious medical or psychiatric conditions which the investigator feels may interfere with the patients ability to give informed consent or participate in the procedures or evaluations of the study
* History of major non-compliance to medication
* Evidence of CNS leukemia
* Uncontrolled viral infection with known HIV or Hepatitis type B or C
* Currently active gastrointestinal disease (e.g., ulcerative diseases, uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, diarrhoea, malabsorption syndrome, or small bowel resection), or other disease, that prevents the patient from absorbing or taking oral medication
* Any other concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions (eg. acute or chronic liver disease, infection, pulmonary disease) that in the opinion of the investigator could potentiate unacceptable safety risks or jeopardize compliance with the protocol
* Males with a female partner of childbearing potential do not agree to use at least 2 effective contraceptive methods throughout the study and for 6 months following the date of last dose</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will have to pass screening procedures and meet eligability criteria.  Groups of 3 patients will be entered at each dose level of Everolimus.  Dose escalation/stopping rules to determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) are as follows:

Number in cohort experiencing DLT by day 42	Action
2/3 or 3/3	No further dose escalation. Previous level is defined as MTD
0/3	Dose escalate to next level
1/3	Expand cohort to 6 patients
1/6 or 2/6	Dose escalate to next level
&gt;2/6	No further dose escalation. Previous level is defined as MTD

Note that if dose escalation is still indicated at the highest dose level, then the MTD is at or above the last dose level. If the trial stops at the first dose, then the MTD is below the first dose level. In either of the above cases, the MTD is not determined from the trial. 

Once the maximum dose level has been identified, a dose expansion phase will continue recruiting patients at the MTD until a total of 40 patients for the entire study is accrued.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not Applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Alfred Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Commercial Road
Melbourne 
VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To examine the safety and tolerability of Everolimus in combination with 5-azacitidine in Acute Myeloid Leukaemia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Hospital
Commerical Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/10/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/09/0285</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/09/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Andrew Wei</name>
      <address>Level 1 South Block
The Alfred Hospital
Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90763928</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.wei@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Shelley Firth</name>
      <address>Level 1 South Block
The Alfred Hospital
Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90763928</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.firth@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>