<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366933">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001077651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Treating gut flora imbalances in Myalgic Encephalomyelitis/Chronic Fatigue Syndrome: A pilot open label trial examining sex differences and psychological symptoms.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessing actigraphic sleep efficiency, Profile of Mood States and Rapid Visual Information Processing for antibiotic and probiotic treatment to reduce gut dysbiosis in Myalgic Encephalomyelitis/Chronic Fatigue Syndrome patients with high Streptococcus: Comparison between sexes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Myalgic Encephalomyelitis/Chronic Fatigue Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Active Treatment Protocol will be combined antibiotic and probiotic therapy for 4 weeks duration. 
Week 1 = Erythromycin (EES-400mg) - 2 x daily oral capsules 
Week 2 = Pro4 - 50 D-Lactate Free multistrain probiotic (2 x daily oral capsules)
Week 3 = Erythromycin (EES-400mg) - 2 x daily oral capsules
Week 4 = Pro4 - 50 D-Lactate Free multistrain probiotic (2 x daily oral capsules)

Each capsule of Pro4 - 50 D-Lactate Free multistrain contains:
Lactobacillus rhamnosus 	25 billion CFUs
Bifidobacterium lactis	15 billion CFUs
Bifidobacterium breve	5 billion CFUs
Bifidobacterium longum	5 billion CFUs
Total CFU Count:		50 billion


Treatment response and compliance will be monitored by weekly phone calls throughout the intervention phase and assessed through participant self-report questions at the end of the study. The second Bioscreen Faecal Microbial Analysis will provide information about any gut flora changes and will be used in conjunction with participant's self-reported treatment adherence.


This treatment protocol is in accordance with current practice at CFSDC. The use of Erythromycin has been TGA approved for Streptococcal infection whilst not specifically indicated for treatment of ME/CFS populations. EES used in this study is not aimed to eradicate faecal streptococcus; but prophylactically to suppress the index organism. </interventions>
    <comparator>This is a pilot open label trial with a repeated measures design with no placebo control.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean actigraphic sleep efficiency score</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Profile of Mood Scale (POMS) mean scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Rapid Visual Information Processing (RVP) on CANTAB</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bioscreen Fecal Microbial Analysis results</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on the Brain Fog subscale of the Multiple Fatigue Types Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective sleep diary rating of sleep quality and wakefulness</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptom Severity and Symptom Hierarchy Profile scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS-21) mean scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Multidimensional Fatigue Inventory (MFI-20) mean scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on the Insomnia Severity Index (ISI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Mood Adjectives checklist mean scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on Attention Switching Task (AST) on CANTAB</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on Paired Associate Learning on CANTAB</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on Spatial Working Memory (SWM) on CANTAB</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test (RAVLT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on Weschler Memory Scales (WMS-IV) Logical Memory Subscale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on Controlled Oral Word Association Test (COWAT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urinary D-lactate levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and post-intervention (week 5 after conclusion of the 4 week intervention).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be patients who have voluntarily presented or been referred to CFSDC. Prospective participants will be:
 - aged above 18 years
 - meet the CCC diagnostic criteria for CFS (Carruthers et al., 2003). The CCC is more commonly used to make a diagnosis of ME/CFS in clinical practice. 
 - have higher than normal Streptococcus bacteria count levels as indicated by pathology testing (Bioscreen FMA). High levels of Streptococcus are determined by a viable count reference range above 3.00 x 10(exponent 5) cfu/gm and greater than 5% distribution within aerobic microorganisms. Normal levels are below the aforementioned count and distribution levels. 
 - refrain from taking any other antibiotics for 4 weeks prior and throughout the study period.
 - refrain from taking any other probiotics for 2 weeks prior and throughout the study period.
 - agree to refrain from substantially altering their current diet and intake of prescription medication or over-the-counter supplements throughout the 6 week study period - or notify the researchers of any changes required at the time of the change.

We will be recruiting equal proportions of male (n = 20) and female (n = 20) participants to evaluate sex-specific treatment responses. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria are individuals with known adverse reactions to antibiotic/probiotic treatment, concurrent contraindicative medication, or significant comorbid physical or psychiatric illnesses that prevent appropriate completion of the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>1. New patient* presents to first appointment at CFSDC. GP conducts clinical history, sends patients for tests, evaluates appropriateness of ME/CFS diagnosis. Clinic nurse provides brief explanation of research project, distributes VU introductory leaflet. All new patients are informed to contact Bioscreen to order the Fecal Microbial Analysis (FMA) kit to screen for patient eligibility.
2. Patient completes Bioscreen kit and urine sampling (sample collected at same time as stool sample but not an assessment of patient eligibility) in own home and sends direct to Bioscreen as per instructions in the kit.
3. Bioscreen FMA results sent to CFSDC. Results analysed to determine if consistent with inclusion criteria.
4. Clinic nurse contacts patient if they are eligible (i.e., high Streptococcus and no contraindications for treatment protocol) and explains treatment protocol and possible side effects. The clinic nurse explains that the patient can voluntarily choose to temporarily defer the CFSDC whole treatment process and participate in the research or they can continue with treatment as usual at CFSDC. Clinic nurse informs patient to contact VU if interested in participating in the research or the patient can request the clinic nurse to contact VU on their behalf.
5. VU verbally explains the procedures and risks of the research and sends patient the VU Research Pack (including the Information to Participant form, Consent form and screening and background questions). 
6. After reading the VU Research Pack in their own time, patients interested in participating completes Consent Form and Screening and Background Questions and returns to VU via reply-plaid postage.
6. Upon receipt of participant forms, VU notifies CFSDC about patient’s participation in the research.
7. CFSDC fax the treatment protocol prescription to the pharmacy and notifies VU that prescription has been faxed.
8. a) VU contacts participant to arrange start date and book Cognitive Testing Session.
8. b) Pharmacist sends treatment package, labelled with ID code number to participant.

*Current patients at CFSDC who continue to present with ME/CFS symptoms and sleep or cognitive difficulties that may indicate a Streptococci overgrowth are eligible to participate in the same screening process outlined for new patients.</concealment>
    <sequence>No randomised procedures</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Wrist actigraphy: The data collection program is Phillips Actiware 6.1. Raw data is quantified with this program using standard protocols.

Cognitive Testing: The CANTAB program provides quantitative data. Additional cognitive tests will be manually scored and entered as quantitative data.

The quantitative Wrist Acrigraphy, Cognitive Testing and Survey/Questionnaire data will be analysed using SPSS. After using exploratory data analysis techniques to determine descriptive statistics for each variable, multivariate dependence techniques will be used. Independent samples t-tests and 2 x 2 repeated measures ANOVAs (spilt plot/SPANOVAs) will be used to identify any within- and between-group differences. If variables violate the assumptions of normality, transformations will be applied or within- and between- group differences will be analysed using corresponding non-parametric tests. 

Within-group data will include analysis of the a) total sample (n=40; i.e. repeated measures, change across time - baseline and post intervention), the subsamples of b) males (n=20) and c) females (n=20) respectively. 

Between-group data will include comparison of a) males vs females, b) total N responders vs non-responders. The results of the previous pilot suggest that there may be a group of individuals who do not respond to antibiotic treatment, i.e. no reduction in Streptococcus level. If this is found during the current study, non-responders will be used as a comparison group.

Bioscreen assessments use a combination of culture-based testing and polymerase chain reaction (PCR) testing to determine the count and percentage of specific microorganisms in the patient's large intestine.

Urinary lactate concentrations will be determined via chiral high performance liquid chromatography.  D lactate concentrations will be normalised against urinary creatinine levels.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>13/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>8/11/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>44</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>26/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3111 - Donvale</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>CFS Discovery Clinic</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>90 Mitcham Rd, Donvale VIC 3111</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victoria University
College of Arts (Psychology)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ballarat Road
Footscray
VIC, 3011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bioscreen 
Specialist Medical Testing Laboratories</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5 Little Hyde Street
Yarraville 
Victoria, 3013</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Bioscreen
Specialist Medical Testing Laboratories</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>5 Little Hyde Street
Yarraville 
Victoria, 3013</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>CFS Discovery Clinic</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>90 Mitcham Rd, 
Donvale VIC 3111</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>An imbalance in gut microorganisms (referred to as gut dysbiosis) has been shown to be related to illness and some ME/CFS symptoms. More research is needed to understand the relationship between the gut and the brain to help with understanding possible causes and treatment options for individuals with ME/CFS. This project will examine how treatment to reduce high levels of Streptococcus bacteria (determined by Bioscreen stool analysis and indicative of abnormal gut functioning) is related to improvements in sleep, mood and cognitive symptoms in individuals with ME/CFS. There is also preliminary evidence to suggest sex differences in response to gut bacteria, thus, this research will examine if there is a sex-differential response to treatment.

This is an open-label pilot study that will follow a baseline, treatment and follow-up protocol across 6 weeks. The baseline and follow-up phases are one week each. Possible improvement in sleep, mood and cognition will be measured by using a wrist device (Actiwatch), pen and pencil sleep and day diary, questionnaires and an individual cognitive testing session conducted at Victoria University. A second Bioscreen stool analysis will provide information about changes to gut flora.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Victoria University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Building C, Room 303
Footscray Park Campus
Ballarat Rd,
Footscray
VIC 3011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>23659</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Dorothy Bruck</name>
      <address>College of Arts
Victoria University
Footscray Park Campus
Ballarat Rd,
Footscray
VIC, 3011</address>
      <phone>+61481008451</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dorothy.bruck@vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Amy Wallis</name>
      <address>College of Arts
Victoria University
Footscray Park Campus
Ballarat Rd,
Footscray
VIC, 3011</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99195292</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amy.wallis1@live.vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Dorothy Bruck</name>
      <address>College of Arts
Victoria University
Footscray Park Campus
Ballarat Rd,
Footscray
VIC, 3011</address>
      <phone>+61481008451</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Dorothy.Bruck@vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Amy Wallis</name>
      <address>College of Arts
Victoria University
Footscray Park Campus
Ballarat Rd,
Footscray
VIC, 3011</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99195292</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amy.wallis1@live.vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>