<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335603">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/07/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/07/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000573055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Australian Adolescent Type 1 Diabetes Intervention Trial (Aussie AdDIT) - to assess the prevalence and progression of microvascular and macrovascular disease in adolescents with Type-1 diabetes.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Aussie AdDIT - to assess retinal vascular changes, atherosclerosis and neuropathy in an identified sample of adolescents with Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus (T1DM) at low and high risk of microalbuminuria.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1115-4841</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Australian Adolescent Type 1 Diabetes Intervention Trial (Aussie AdDIT)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type-1 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>No intervention - observational study of T1DM in adolescents for a period of 4 years.</interventions>
    <comparator>Not applicable</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the prevalence and progression of microvascular and macrovascular disease where outcome measures include retinopathy (as assessed through retinal photography), aortic intima medial thickness (as assessed through ultrasound technique)and heart rate variability (as assessed through electrocardiogram (ECG).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and annually for 4 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the rate of progression of atherosclerosis and  neuropathy in participants undergoing angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitor and statin treatment. Assessments include retinopathy (by retinal photography), aortic intima medial thickness (by ultrasound technique)and heart rate variability (by electrocardiogram (ECG).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and annually for 4 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Aged 11-16 years
2. Type 1 diabetes for more than one year or Cpeptide negative
3. Assessment of albumin-creatinine ratio in the upper or lower tertile</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>11</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Albumin-creatinine ratio  based on 6 early morning urines deemed to be in the middle tertile.
2. Non-type 1 diabetes
3. Severe hyperlipidaemia and family history data to support diagnosis of hyperlipidaemia.
4. Established hypertension unrelated to diabetic nephropathy
5. Prior exposure to statins and ACE inhibitors
6. Proliferative retinopathy
7. Other co-morbidities considered unsuitable by the investigator
8. Renal disease not associated with type 1 diabetes</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/05/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>530</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>6008</postcode>
    <postcode>3052</postcode>
    <postcode>5006</postcode>
    <postcode>2145</postcode>
    <postcode>4101</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Professor Kim Donaghue</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Institute of Endocrinology and Diabetes
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Locked Bag 4001
Westmead NSW 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The prognosis for childhood onset type 1 diabetes (T1D) remains generally poor with the number of life years lost is 17 years for a child diagnosed aged 10 years. Whilst in the second decade from diagnosis diabetic nephropathy (DN)accounts for around 60% of deaths, by the third decade cardiovascular disease (CVD) accounts for two thirds of all deaths. Although complications are rarely seen during childhood, there is evidence that their pathogenesis begins soon after diagnosis and accelerates during puberty.  Adolescence may be a critical period for lifetime risk of complications in childhood onset diabetes.  During puberty, the first signs of complications become evident. Microalbuminuria, an early risk marker for DN and CVD may be found in 12 to 16% of adolescents and this has been associated with renal pathology indicative of early nephropathy.  

This study is investigating the changes in retinopathy, aortic intima media thickness (aIMT) and heart rate variability which are indicators of macrovascular disease and autonomic neuropathy respectively.  Diabetic retinopathy is the most common cause of blindness in young adults less than 40 years in the developed world. Factors affecting the genesis of autonomic neuropathy include glycaemic control, lipids and blood pressure. Studies have shown that atherosclerosis develops first in the abdominal aorta and precedes that seen in the carotid arteries. 

A study has reported that both high blood pressure and lipids increase neuropathy risk and it is likely therefore that intervention with ACE inhibitors and / or statin impact on neuropathy progression. 

Specific aims:
a. 	To assess retinopathy (by retinal photography), atherosclerosis ( by aortic intima media thickness and carotid intima media thickness) and neuropathy (by heart rate variability) in an identified sample of adolescents with T1DM at high risk of microalbuminuria as compared to adolescents with T1DM at low risk of microalbuminuria.
b. 	To determine whether ACE inhibition/statin therapy during puberty will reduce retinopathy, atherosclerosis and autonomic neuropathy progression in adolescents with T1DM at high risk of Microalbuminuria compared to adolescents with T1DM at low risk of Microalbuminuria.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Women's and Children's Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Women's and Children's Hospital,
72 King street,
North adelaide,
SA 5006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/12/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/11/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Barbara Sheil</name>
      <address>Telethon Institute for Child Health,
100 Roberts Road, Subiaco, 
Western Australia, 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 7858</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Barbara.Sheil@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Barbara Sheil</name>
      <address>Telethon Institute for Child Health,
100 Roberts Road, Subiaco, 
Western Australia, 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 7858</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Barbara.Sheil@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Barbara Sheil</name>
      <address>Telethon Institute for Child Health,
100 Roberts Road, Subiaco, 
Western Australia, 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 7858</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Barbara.Sheil@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>