<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366241">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/05/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000470695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>What is the effect of two different entertainment education styles
on the knowledge and attitudes of older adults relating to
depression?
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>What is the effect of two different entertainment education styles
on the knowledge and attitudes of older adults relating to
depression?
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1156-1975</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants (older adults in a hospital setting) will watch a documentary video that is approx. 10mins in length about three older people's experiences with depression and anxiety, including what it is, common signs and symptoms, reasons why people experience these and strategies to manage/prevent these feelings. The key outcomes will be motivation to seek assistance from a health professional to manage symptoms of depression following discharge from hospital, and knowledge of available treatment
options. The research design will be a Solomon randomised controlled trial. In this design only half of the participants in each group receive the pre-intervention questions but all participants complete the post-test questions. This allows the priming effect of asking pre-intervention questions to be isolated in the analysis, while still allowing the baseline comparability between groups to be investigated.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will watch an instructional video that is approx. 10 minutes in length about depression and anxiety, including signs and symptoms, reasons why people experience these and strategies to manage/prevent them. Participants will then complete the same outcome measures as above, using the Solomon method.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knowledge of signs/symptoms and treatment options for depression and anxiety. This will be assessed using a questionnaire designed specifically for this study, which will be administered pre intervention for half the participants and post intervention for all the participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motivation to seek assistance from a health care professional to manage/prevent symptoms of depression and anxiety. This will be assessed using a questionnaire designed specifically for this study, which will be administered pre intervention for half the participants and post intervention for all the participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post-intervention
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Enjoyment of video measured in the custom-designed questionnaire using Likert scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Must be receiving rehabilitation for a variety of geriatric conditions at a Monash Health site such as Kingston Centre or Casey Hospital
-Aged 65 years and over
-Cognitively intact (determined by GPCog screen)
-Sufficient English language skills</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Palliative</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Ward staff identified patients who potentially met the inclusion criteria and asked them whether they were willing to have researchers approach them. Patients who agreed to this were then provided with project descriptions (both written and verbal), thus allowing informed consent to be obtained. 

Participants will be allocated to groups randomly using a computer-generated number sequence using permuted blocks produced by an investigator who is not involved in recruitment or data collection. The investigators will be blinded to the allocation 
sequence until after the participants give consent and have completed the GPCog screening. 

The interviewer will performed the allocation by opening an opaque, sealed envelope with the participant’s identification number on it, which contains the group allocation. Participants 
will not blinded to the knowledge of the entertainment education video that they receive and the investigators conducting the assessments will also be aware of the participant’s group allocation during the pre and post intervention assessment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants were allocated to groups randomly using a computer-generated number sequence using permuted blocks produced by an investigator who was not involved in recruitment or data collection.

Solomon randomisation will be used to allow only half of the
participants in each group receive the pre-intervention questions but all participants complete the post-test questions. This allows the priming effect of asking pre-intervention questions to be isolated in the analysis, while still allowing the baseline comparability between groups to be investigated.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/05/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Kingston Centre - Cheltenham</hospital>
    <hospital>Casey Hospital - Berwick</hospital>
    <postcode>3192 - Cheltenham</postcode>
    <postcode>3806 - Berwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash University Peninsula Campus
McMahons Road
Frankston Victoria 3199 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Internal departmental funding by Monash Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Allied Health Research Unit
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Road
Cheltenham VIC 3192
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Internal departmental funding by Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Monash University Peninsula Campus
McMahons Road
Frankston Victoria 3199 Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To determine if there is a difference when providing information about seeking management for depression using a narrative documentary Entertainment-Education (EE) approach compared to an instructional EE approach, on older adults knowledge and motivation levels. We hypothesise that there will be a greater knowledge uptake and increased motivation levels to seek assistance for managing depression in the group who view the narrative video compared to those who 
view the didactic video.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, Main Block
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd
Clayton Victoria 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/01/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13407A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/12/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Terence Haines</name>
      <address>Allied Health Research Unit
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Road
Cheltenham VIC 3192</address>
      <phone>61, 03, 92651822 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>terence.haines@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Terence Haines</name>
      <address>Allied Health Research Unit
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Road
Cheltenham VIC 3192</address>
      <phone>+61, 03, 92651822 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>terence.haines@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Terence Haines</name>
      <address>Allied Health Research Unit
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Road
Cheltenham VIC 3192</address>
      <phone>+61, 03, 92651822 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>terence.haines@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>