<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371778">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001603404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can we improve how health providers support smoking cessation in Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander pregnant women? - a pilot study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Indigenous Counselling and Nicotine (ICAN) QUIT in Pregnancy Step-Wedge Pilot Study: feasibility of training health providers in evidence based smoking cessation care for Australian Indigenous pregnant smokers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ICAN QUIT in Pregnancy - pilot</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Management of smoking during pregnancy in Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander women</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will include webinar training, an educational resources package, provision of Oral Nicotine Replacement Therapy, implementation support, and audit and feedback. The duration of the total intervention will be 9 months in all sites. 
1.	Webinar training:
Three 60 minutes (total 180 minutes) training sessions will be provided to all health providers in participating sites. In cases of staff turnover webinar training is repeated as required. Sessions will be delivered by 2 physicians, one a general practitioner and the other a public health physician, both tobacco treatment specialists. 
Attendance of staff members in all of the webinar sessions will be monitored through a specific form.
Training Sessions:
Session 1: Background on smoking in pregnancy and relevance to vulnerable subgroups including the Indigenous context  health risks/psychosocial/environmental/cultural. Non-confrontational history taking. Engagement of vulnerable pregnant smokers. Assessment of smoking in Indigenous and vulnerable women - nicotine dependence and motivation. Assessing socio-cultural aspects and environmental smoking. Culturally competent care - importance and content. Non-didactic counselling styles. Concept and benefit of teachable moments.
Session 2: ABCD approach  Ask-Brief advice-Cessation medications-Discuss psychosocial context. Behaviour change techniques (BCTs) successful in pregnancy, e.g. goal setting, setting a quit date, problems solving, and boosting self-efficacy. How to tailor advice to the client. Interventions of differing intensity - brief to intensive. Involving the family in smoking management and smoke-free environments. Supportive counselling and follow up. Psychosocial support. Use of optimised resources. Referral mechanisms. Ancillary resources available: Quitline, on-line and mobile phone apps.
Session 3: Using NRT in pregnancy, initiating NRT, and how to advise about NRT - NRT algorithm for pregnancy  step-wise titration. Dosage management, side-effects, indications/contra-indications, promoting adherence, recording outcomes. Use of the CO meter as a motivational tool, and for monitoring and validating abstinence. Advising re cannabis and e-cigarettes.

2.	Educational package resources:
Services will receive targeted educational resources including a provider training manual, provider desktop guide, a flipchart and patient booklet to guide patient education. These resources are based on a published pragmatic guide for the management of smoking in Indigenous pregnant women, and were developed collaboratively with two Aboriginal Medical Services and a Stakeholder and Consumer Aboriginal Advisory Panel. They were also put through a stringent 4 step evaluation process that included an expert panel and focus groups with health providers and community female members from three additional Aboriginal Medical Services in three states (NSW, SA, QLD). 

3.	Provision of free Oral NRT: 
Oral forms of NRT are not currently subsidised on Australian Government Schemes, so will be supplied as part of this study.. An oral NRT voucher system will be arranged, redeemable by arrangement at a local pharmacy or through the participating service, thus enabling an open-label free supply of oral NRT. 
The provision of Oral NRT will be monitored through a voucher system. 

4.	Implementation support comprised of three site visits and weekly telephone calls from the research team.

5.	Audit and feedback  - We will analyse the data acquired after 1 month and each service will receive information comparing its work to the other de-identified services in the study. This will be done in line with guidance from the research team on ways to improved provider practices.

</interventions>
    <comparator>We will be collecting data on a service level, and from recruited pregnant women, and from the health providers that will be used as the control data. Recruitment of women receiving usual care will be performed for 2 months prior to the service receiving the intervention. The data collected from these women during this time will serve as control. Furthermore, the service will provide us with aggregated de-identified data regarding # of NRT scripts that were provided to pregnant women who smoke for up to 4 months prior to receiving the intervention. In additional all health providers will be completing a survey prior to receiving the intervention that will serve as the control data. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of NRT prescription to expectant mothers, assessed by number of Oral NRT vouchers and number of NRT Patch prescription that were given to pregnant women who smoke. This will be collected through a monthly computerized report of aggregated de-identified data from the service, and through data collected from the registration of NRT vouchers given to women. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly intervals from site recruitment (0, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28, 32 , 36 weeks)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of performing the intervention and research study including recruitment rates, percent complete follow-up for participating women, and percent of health providers performing the training</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly intervals from site recruitment (0, 4, 8, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28, 32 , 36 weeks)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on patient checklists. Checklist comprise of 11 items that are scored to form a composite score representing quality of smoking cessation care. This was designed specifically for this study, after consulting with experts in the field. </outcome>
      <timepoint> At the exit of each visit to the medical service, from recruitment to the study up till 12 weeks post recruitment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported adherence to NRT using a question in a survey designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Behaviour Change Techniques (BCT) used by providers . These will be assessed through audio-recording of consultations (in regard to smoking), transcribing and coding them for behavior change techniques based on the BCT taxonomy that was previously published. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and post training intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported Growth and Empowerment Measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluation of cultural responsiveness using a Critical Success Measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Home smoking ban/rules using a question in a survey designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Car smoking rules/ban using a question in a survey designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heaviness of smoking index - this is validated index formed of 2 questions that will be included in the  survey designed for the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of Urges to Smoke (SUTS) score - a validated question that will be included in the survey designed specifically for the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of Urges to Smoking (FUTS) score - a validated question that will be included in the survey designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fagerstrom score  - a validated composite score from 6 questions including in the survey designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Quit Attempts that lasted over 24hrs using a question in a survey designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nicotine Replacement Therapy use measured using a question in a survey designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intentions to Quit - Composite Scale of sum of 5 Likert Scales (4-point) - mean value</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Risk Behavior Diagnosis (RBD) Scales  - a composite score using a validated survey  </outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported continuous abstinence using a validated question in a survey designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemically verified continuous abstinence using a validated question in a survey designed specifically for this study, and a CO measurement under or equal to 6 ppm. </outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported 7 days point prevalence using a validated question in a survey designed specifically for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemically verified 7 days point prevalence using a validated question in a survey designed specifically for this study, and a CO measurement under or equal to 6 ppm</outcome>
      <timepoint>at recruitment (baseline), 4 weeks and 12 weeks post recruitment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported provision of SCC - this is a composite score using 12 different items measured with 5-point Likert scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post training and at the end of study (6 months post training)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported prescription of NRT using a 5-point Likert scale in a survey designed for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post training and at the end of the study (6 months post training)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported provision of smoking cessation care according to the ABCD guidelines - this is a composite score using 4 items measured with 5-point Likert scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post training and at the end of the study (6 months post training)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported provision of smoking cessation care according to the 5A's guidelines - this is a composite score using 5 items measured with 5-point Likert scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post training and at the end of the study (6 months post training)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported provision of smoking cessation care according to the AAR guidelines - this is a composite score using 3items measured with 5-point Likert scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post training and at the end of the study (6 months post training)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knowledge on smoking cessation care in pregnancy - this will be measured with 24 True/False statements regarding smoking cessation in pregnancy. These statements will be computed to form a composite knowledge score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post training and at the end of the study (6 months post training)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attitudes to providing smoking cessation care - these will be measured using a composite score from 22 items measured with 5-point Likert scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post training and at the end of the study (6 months post training)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>For participating woman:
1.	Pregnant woman equal or under 28 weeks gestation
2.	Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander (as defined by the health service they are attending) or expectant mothers of Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander babies
3.	Aged equal or over 16 years old
4.	Smoke Tobacco (any level of consumption)

For Health professionals:
1. Be employed by the participating medical service
2. Consult a pregnant women for any reason</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>no additional exclusion criteria for either women or health providers</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This study is a step-wedge design. Some participants are recruited before the service receive the training intervention, and some are recruited after. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We estimate recruiting approximately 50-80 women at up to 6 ACCHS/AMS. As this is a  feasibility pilot study, the aim is not to be able to produce statistically significant results but to get qualitative feedback and process measures, and to determine trends, means and standard deviations, in order to inform the design of a future  clustered randomized controlled study. 
Analysis: An NRT prescription or voucher accepted by patient, checked at each follow up visit, will qualify as a success.  We will compare the proportion of successful audits between baseline (audit of grouped de-identified client records pre intervention - number of NRT scripts given to number of patients) to the number of successful audits at 4 weeks and 12 weeks post intervention. iii)	Changes in health providers knowledge and attitudes relating to smoking cessation in pregnancy will compare baseline to post-training and end of study using McNemar/ Bowkers test for categorical variables and paired T-tests/ Wilcoxon sign-rank tests for continuous variables.  Patient characteristics (e.g. dependence levels, smoking status, home smoking) will be compared between time periods using chi-square tests for categorical variables and t-tests for continuous variables; factors found to be different between time periods will be included in the regression as covariates.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>7/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/08/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive, Callaghan
NSW 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NSW Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3, 73 Miller St North Sydney NSW 2060</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hunter Cancer Research Alliance</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Calvary Mater Newcastle, Locked Bag 7, Hunter Region Mail Centre NSW 2310 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4
414 LaTrobe Street
Melbourne
VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Institute New South Wales</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 9, 8 Central Avenue, Eveleigh,
NSW 2015</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The overall aim is to improve health professionals management of smoking in Aboriginal and/or Torres Strait Islander pregnant woman in a culturally tailored approach. The study will include 6 Aboriginal Medical Services in 3 states (NSW, SA, and QLD). Each service will receive webinar training to all the staff, audit and feedback, an educational resources package and free oral Nicotine Replacement Therapy for participating pregnant women. 
This study is a pilot study aimed to assess how the intervention is likely to be feasible in a full clinical study and foresee any implementation challenges we will need to overcome.  
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Services 
Research Integrity Unit 
The Chancellery 
The University of Newcastle 
University drive, Callaghan NSW 2308 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2015-0438</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>AH&amp;MRC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>3/66 Wentworth Ave
Surry Hills NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1140/15</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>AHREC </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box 719, Adelaide SA 5001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>04-16-652</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Far North QLD HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>William McCormack Place
Level 7 East, 5B Sheridan Street
Cairns QLD 4870
PO Box 902 CAIRNS
Queensland 4870 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QCH/34 – 1040</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gillian S Gould</name>
      <address>Centre for Brain &amp; Mental Health Research
The University of Newcastle
PO Box 833 Newcastle, 2300
NSW

</address>
      <phone>+61403615563</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gillian.gould@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gillian S Gould</name>
      <address>Centre for Brain &amp; Mental Health Research
The University of Newcastle
PO Box 833 Newcastle, 2300
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61403615563</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gillian.gould@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gillian S Gould</name>
      <address>Centre for Brain &amp; Mental Health Research
The University of Newcastle
PO Box 833 Newcastle, 2300
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61403615563</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gillian.gould@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yael Bar Zeev</name>
      <address>Centre for Brain &amp; Mental Health Research
The University of Newcastle
PO Box 833 Newcastle, 2300
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61478040759</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yael.barzeev@uon.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>