<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362090">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/05/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000569808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cluster Randomised Evaluation of a Printed Contraception Educational Material for Young People</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Cluster randomised evaluation of a general audience versus a youth-focused printed education information resource to improve contraception knowledge and attitudes in adolescents and young people</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Contraception</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Contraception</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Family Planning NSW has developed and will evaluate a new print resource (booklet), the purpose of which is to supply relevant and accurate information about contraception for young people. The evaluation aims to compare the effectiveness of the new youth-friendly contraception booklet to our current booklet. Investigators will utilise a cluster randomised design to compare contraceptive knowledge and attitudes before and after reading one of the two booklets. Investigators will recruit 24 Youth Centres to participate in the research and each location will be randomised to one of two groups: 1) current contraceptive booklet, or 2) new youth-friendly booklet. Participating Youth Centre study coordinators will each recruit 15 participants between the ages of 14-24 years. After enrolment and providing informed consent, participants will complete a baseline survey assessing contraceptive knowledge and attitudes and will then be asked to read the booklet over the next one to two weeks. Two weeks after receiving the booklet, each participant will be asked to complete an online follow-up survey also assessing knowledge, attitudes and general satisfaction with the resource.</interventions>
    <comparator>Current general audience contraceptive booklet</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Contraception knowledge increase assessed by 19 knowledge questions in a self-administered baseline paper-based questionnaire and on-line follow-up survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4 weeks post baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Contraception attitude improvement assessed by 12 attitude questions in a self-administered baseline paper-based questionnaire and on-line follow-up survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4 weeks post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>a) aged between 14-24; &amp; b) if 14-15 years old, have previously received in-school or parental / guardian sexual health education.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>14</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>24</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Investigators will utilise a cluster randomised design to compare contraceptive knowledge and attitudes before and after viewing one of the two booklets. Investigators will recruit 24 Youth Centres to participate in the research and each Centre will be randomised to one of two groups: 1) current contraceptive booklet, or 2) new youth-friendly booklet. Participating Youth Centre study coordinators will each recruit 15 participants between the ages of 14-24 years who will be given the pamphlet according to the randomisation assignment.  Study coordinators recruiting subjects at the study locations are unaware of the allocation which has been completed centrally; the contraception booklets are placed in opaque envelopes to be opened by the subject after enrolling and completing the baseline survey.</concealment>
    <sequence>A random numbers table will be used to assign Youth Centres.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Family Planning New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>328-336 Liverpool Road
Ashfield NSW 2131</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Family Planning New South Wales</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>328-336 Liverpool Road
Ashfield NSW 2131</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Family Planning NSW has developed and will evaluate a new print resource (booklet), the purpose of which is to supply essential, relevant and accurate information about contraception for young people. The evaluation aims to compare the effectiveness of the new youth-friendly contraception booklet to our current booklet. Investigators will utilise a cluster randomised design to compare contraceptive knowledge and attitudes before and after viewing one of the two booklets. Investigators will recruit 24 Youth Centres to participate in the research and each Centre will be randomised to one of two groups: 1) current contraceptive booklet, or 2) new youth-friendly booklet. Participating Youth Centre study coordinators will each recruit 15 participants between the ages of 14-24 years. After enrolment and providing informed consent, participants will complete a baseline survey assessing contraceptive knowledge and attitudes and will then be asked to read the booklet over the next one to two weeks. Two weeks after receiving the booklet, each participant will be asked to complete the online follow-up survey also assessing knowledge, attitudes and general satisfaction with the resource.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Family Planning New South Wales</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>328-336 Liverpool Road
Ashfield NSW 2131</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00120</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/02/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anne Dore</name>
      <address>Family Planning New South Wales
328-336 Liverpool Road
Ashfield NSW 2131</address>
      <phone>+61 02 8752 4300</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anned@fpnsw.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anne Dore</name>
      <address>Family Planning New South Wales
328-336 Liverpool Road
Ashfield NSW 2131</address>
      <phone>+61 02 8752 4300</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anned@fpnsw.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>