<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335623">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/07/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000597099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of flexibility and strength training on functional performance in active elderly people</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of 12 weeks of stretching and/or strength training, followed by 6 weeks of detraining, on the functional status in the healthy elderly</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiorespiratory health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>musculoskeletal health.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Forty five healthy elderly individuals (25 female gender; 20 male gender; 67.5±2 years old) completed the following study protocols: Control Group-CG (66±6 years old; n=13) just received advice about a healthy life style via lectures twice a week for 1h each, and carried out no physical or therapeutic exercise during 18 consecutive weeks; resistance group- RG (69±5 years old; n=13 performed resistive exercises; Stretching group- SG (69±6 years old; n=10) carried out stretching exercises; Resistance and stretching group-RSG (66±5 years old; n=09) carried out resistive exercises and immediately after by the stretching.
The exercises were oriented by the work team of the present study and applied under the supervision of a physiotherapist and 3 students from the course in physical therapy at the coastal sector of Universidade Federal do Parana. Blood pressure was checked before and 6 minutes after each session of exercises. The exercises were carried out twice a week, always at the same time, for a total of 24 sessions, each session lasting approximately 55 min, i.e., resistive exercise and stretching. Stretching or resistive exercise sessions were shorter. Individuals who took part in at least 60% of the sessions were considered as active participants of the study. 
Resistive Exercise Protocol 
The ten repetition maximum (10-RM) technique was used to evaluate the muscular strength of each individual in order to choose the ideal weight to use in the exercise. The 10-RM technique evaluates the capacity of the individual with respect to the maximum weight he can move 10 times with little action of muscle groups that are not the primary motors of the movement under evaluation. 
The individuals were submitted to progressive resistive exercises, that is, for the first 5 weeks they used 65% of 10-RM, for the next 4 weeks, 70% and for the last 3 weeks, 75%. Adjustment of the 10-RM was determined immediately before the third and eighth weeks of training.
The protocol of resistive exercises consisted of 3 series of 8 repetitions of each exercise, carried out with both limbs. 
The resistive exercises were carried out twice a week for 12 consecutive weeks for the following muscle groups:  knee extensors (seated position) and knee flexors (standing upright); hip extensors (standing upright) and flexors (lying down on back); and the hip abductors and adductors (standing upright). The plantiflexors were tested in the upright standing position using the bodies own weight modified.
Stretching Procedure 
Stretching exercises consisted of a series of 4 repetitions of active static stretching, each lasting 1 minute, with 1 min of relaxation between each repetition, respecting the tension limit of each individual. The exercises were carried out with both limbs twice a week for 12 consecutive weeks. The type of stretching, duration and number of repetitions.
Stretching of the following muscle groups of the lower limbs was carried out: knee extensors and dorsiflexors in the upright standing position; knee flexors and plantiflexors were stretched using a band of non-elastic material, with the subject lying on his back and the stretched limb with the knee extended and the ankle joint in dorsiflexion, using. In this case the contralateral limb was placed with the hip and knees flexed during the knee flexor stretching procedure.</interventions>
    <comparator>Forty five healthy elderly individuals (25 female gender; 20 male gender; 67.5±2 years old) completed the following study protocols: CG (66±6 years old; n=13) just received advice about a healthy life style via lectures, and carried out no physical or therapeutic exercise during 18 consecutive weeks; RG (69±5 years old; n=13 performed resistive exercises; SG (69±6 years old; n=10) carried out stretching exercises; RSG (66±5 years old; n=09) carried out resistive exercises and immediately after by the stretching.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardio-respiratory performance was evaluated using the 6 minute walk test (6MWT),</outcome>
      <timepoint>It was measured beforehand, after 6 and 12 weeks of training and after 6 weeks of detraining.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lower body muscle strength by standing up from a chair and sitting down (SUCSD).</outcome>
      <timepoint>It was measured beforehand, after 6 and 12 weeks of training and after 6 weeks of detraining.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure assessed by automatic sphygmomanometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>It was measured beforehand, after 6 and 12 weeks of training and after 6 weeks of detraining.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>none</outcome>
      <timepoint>none</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligibility Criteria
Men and women over 60 years of age and in a stable health condition; users of the Brazilian National Health System (SUS); presenting a medical certificate affirming they were able to carry out the proposed exercises; and individual who had not carried out regular physical activity over the last 6 weeks, were included.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The participants were excluded if they had secondary joint injury or surgery; cardiac illness; cancer; neuropathies; were users of prosthesis; had a systolic blood pressure above 200 mmHg and diastolic blood pressure above 110 mmHg at rest; had already taken part in structured exercise for more than 1 day a week during the previous 6 weeks; had any contraindications for exercise; severe functional limitations or cognitive impairment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The participants were recruited at meetings organized by the Municipal Health secretary of Matinhos-PR, via advertisements on the local radio, and information talks at local community and senior citizen groups. It was asked if the person would like to do exercise or only to be evaluated (control group) and they could choose which group theu would like to participate.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Parana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidade Federal do Parana-UFPR</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>R. Jaguariaiva, 512
Matinhos
Parana
Brasil
83260-000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidade Federal do Parana</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>R. Jaguariaiva, 512
Matinhos
Parana
Brasil
83260-000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Federal University of Parana</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Physiotherapy Clinic School
R. Arthur Zanluti, 1402
MAtinhos-PR
BRazil
83260-000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Objective: to evaluate the effects of 12 weeks of stretching and/or strength training, followed by 6 weeks of detraining, on the functional status in the elderly. Methods: Subjects were divided into 4 groups: control (CG; n=13; 66±6 years), stretching (SG; n= 10; 69±6 years), resistance (RG; n= 13; 69±5 years) and resistance and stretching (RSG, n=9, 66±5 years). The CG was not submitted to exercise, while twice a week the SG, RG and RSG carried out a 10 min warm-up prior to exercises for the lower body muscle groups. The SG carried out 4 repetitions of stretching for 60s each. The RG carried out progressive resistive exercises with initial level set at 65% of a 10 repetition maximum (RM) for the first five weeks, 70% for the next four weeks and 75% for the last three weeks. The RSG performed both types of exercise. Cardio-respiratory performance was evaluated using the 6 minute walk test (6MWT), and lower body muscle strength by standing up from a chair and sitting down (SUCSD).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Part of this study was presented as an abstract in The 19th IAGG World Congress of Gerontology and Geriatrics (2009) and XVIII Congresso Brasileiro de Fisioterapia (2009).</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of the Federal University of Parana Health Sciences</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Rua : Padre Camargo,280  Alto da Gloria  Curitiba  Parana. CEP: 80.060-240.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/05/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CAAE 0021.0.091.000-08</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/04/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rafaella Locks</name>
      <address>Rua Eduardo Carlos Pereira, 4021, apto.802  Portao, 81020-770 
Curitiba  PR Brazil</address>
      <phone>55-41-96154487</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rafaellalocks@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anna Raquel Silveira Gomes</name>
      <address>R. Jaguariaiva, 512
Matinhos-PR
Brasil
83260-000</address>
      <phone>55-41-35118300</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>annaraquelsg@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>