<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371243">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001273471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The impact of a structured diabetes education program for improving glycemic control in adults with type 2 diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The assessment of  the impact of a structured diabetes education program on glycaemic control in adult type 2 diabetes patients at initiation of basal insulin analogue </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Basal-EDUC-RO</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Identifiers assigned by the sponsor: DIREGL07301</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>type 2 diabetes mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In enhanced educational group 
- Curriculum Modules 1: information about the importance of glycaemic control, diabetes complications video, reinforce the need of life style changes, how insulin works, training about device, glucometers and self monitoring blood glucose (SMBG), hypoglycaemia and titration+ brochure - guideline for patients realized by Romanian Association od Education in Diabetes  - 45 minutes, provided by a trained nurse, in the first week after first visit, in physician office, one-on-one discussion
- Curriculum Modules 2: a short interview with patients about his/her knowledge and changes that he/her has done in the past 3 months; reinforce the information which was not very well understood, check SMBG diary and insulin titration algorithm; education about insulin treatment complication and the possibility of intensification need (how to check postprandial glycaemia) -  45 minutes, provided by a trained nurse in the first week after visit 2,  in physician office, one-on-one discussion

All enrolled patients have performed 3 medical visits( first - baseline, at initiation, second - after 3 months, third - after 6 months);  the data has been  collected by the Investigators in the Case Report Forms (CRFs) and, on visits 1 and 3, the patients  filled-in EQ5D and Diabetes Empowerment Scale (DES) questionnaires.
Not specific strategies used to monitor adherence
</interventions>
    <comparator>Usually daily practice education that means a short training about device, glucometers used, injection technique and hypoglycaemia done by the nurse or physician - in control group - one to one 15 minutes session or 30 minutes group sessions
Both groups receive the same treatment - with basal insulin + OADs at investigator decision.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the changes of HbA1c from baseline to the end of study in both groups 
 with structured education and control group</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after first visit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proportion of patients reaching individualized target of HbA1c (established  a priori by the physician) in each group (with / without enhanced education)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after the first visit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> the incidence of confirmed symptomatic (&lt;70 mg/dl) hypoglycemic episodes at the end of study for both groups -  in number of events - measured by SMBG</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after enrollment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> the incidence of confirmed symptomatic (&lt;70 mg/dl) hypoglycemic episodes at the end of study for both groups - in number of patients that experienced at least one hypoglycemic events - measured by SMBG</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after enrollment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> the incidence of severe hypoglycemic episodes (required third assistance) at the end of study for both groups  in number of events - from patients interview or documented if was necessary the hospitalization </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after enrollment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> the incidence of severe hypoglycemic episodes (that required third assistance)  at the end of study for both groups - in number of patients that experienced at least one hypoglycemic events - from patients interview or documented if was necessary the hospitalization </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after enrollment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. adults diagnosed with T2 DM
2. patients treated with stable doses of  oral antidiabetics drugs (OADs) ( the dose was not modified in the last 3 months) 
3. the diabetes is inadequately controlled with OADs and at investigator decision the patient is initiated on basal insulin analogues
4. the determination of HbA1c value must be available at the moment of the initiation of basal insulin analogues (determined in the last month)
5. Informed Consent Form signed
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The patient
1.was pregnant or breast-feeding or intented to be pregnant during the study
2.was treated with any systemic corticosteroid
3.was already included in other studies
4.had any contraindication to insulin treatment
5.patients not able to comply with - visit schedule
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>22/10/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>16/02/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>750</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>746</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>17/08/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>sanofi Romania</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sanofi Romania, str Gara Herastrau nr 4, floor 8, Bucharest Romania, postcode 020334</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Romania</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sanofi</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Sanofi Romania, str Gara Herastrau nr 4, floor 8, Bucharest Romania, postcode 020334</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Romania</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There are no data in Romania (and not so many worldwide) explaining why some patients fail to achieve good glycemic control during insulin therapy. Hypothetically, such failure could be the fault of the healthcare professionals (e.g. insufficient advice) or of the patients (e.g. poor adherence, fear of hypoglycemia). Starting from these observations, we had intended to assess effectiveness of enhanced education delivered by trained diabetes educators / nurses on the improvement of diabetes management.
This disease registry evaluated the efficacy of enhanced education of patients with T2DM at the time of starting on basal insulin regimen.  We estimated that we would detect a significant difference in mean value of HbA1c in-between both arms (patients with enhanced or standard education) at the end of 6 months observation period but not less than 0.3%. between the groups.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Romanian National Ethic Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Romania</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cornelia Bala</name>
      <address>Iuliu Hatieganu University of Medicine and Pharmacy Department of Diabetes, Nutrition, Metabolic Diseases 2 Clinicilor St, 400 006 Cluj-Napoca, </address>
      <phone>+40722605501 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cbala@umfcluj.ro</email>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cornelia Bala</name>
      <address>Iuliu Hatieganu University of Medicine and Pharmacy Department of Diabetes, Nutrition, Metabolic Diseases 2 Clinicilor St, 400 006 Cluj-Napoca, </address>
      <phone> +40722605501 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cbala@umfcluj.ro</email>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cornelia Bala</name>
      <address>Iuliu Hatieganu University of Medicine and Pharmacy Department of Diabetes, Nutrition, Metabolic Diseases 2 Clinicilor St, 400 006 Cluj-Napoca, </address>
      <phone>+40722605501 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cbala@umfcluj.ro</email>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Moise Mihaela</name>
      <address>Sanofi, str Gara Herastrau 4, floor 8th, Bucharest Romania</address>
      <phone> +40 21.317.31.36  </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Mihaela.Moise@sanofi.com</email>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>