<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336644">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/12/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001240932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Sealants for smooth surface caries prevention in children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Sealants for smooth surface caries prevention in children</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1119-8464</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>UQSPACE1 University of Queensland</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dental caries on healthy children attending a governemnt dental clinic of Longan-Beaudesert Division of Metro South Queensland</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Application of smooth surface sealant on proximal and occlusal surface of first permanent and primary molars

The sealant to be used is a commercially available and TGA approved product named "G-Coat Plus" manufactured by GC, Tokyo, Japan

The sealant will be applied once at the start of the trial according to standard protocol for clinical application of sealant (eg: clean surface, apply G Coat Plus then set it with a light source)</interventions>
    <comparator>Routine treatment currently used in clinics, this include oral hygiene, diet counselling and topical fluoride treatment</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>prevention of lesion formation on treated surfaces this will be determined using radiographs which would be part of routine check up</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6, 12, 24, 36 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>saliva profile ( the saliva profile will be measured using a Saliva Test Kit,manufactured by GC. Ask subject to spit a drop of saliva into a cup then measure its pH using a pH test strip, collect stimulated saliva by asking subject to chew on paraffin wax and spit in a cup, the volume is recorded and the buffering capacity is measured using a test trip manufactured by GC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 12, 24, 36 ,months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>oral hygiene to be assessed clincially, by obeservation and graded according to the amount of dental plaque found on tooth surfaces. this is performed by the reviewers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 12, 24, 36 ,months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Group 1: intact and exposed caries-free and accessible surfaces in the primary second teeth
Group 2: Intact and exposed caries-free and accessible surfaces in the permanent teeth</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children with 
1/significant medical conditions that can affect dental treatment
2/Significant dental conditions associated with abnormalities of tooth structure and form
3/Preexisitng carious lesions on the test surfaces which have extended into dentino-enamel junctions as diagnosed from radiographs
4/congenitally absent adjacent permanent teeth to the surface to be sealed.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Split mouth design with one side receiving intervention while the other side standard treatment. A toss of a coin will determine which side is control or test
Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Toss of a coin.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>School of Dentistry, University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Queensland
200 Turbot St
Brisbane QLD4000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>School of Dentistry, University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Queensland
200 Turbot St
Brisbane QLD4000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>GC Australasia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 4 Bayview Tower 
1753 Botany Rd
Nalsmeadow NSW 2019</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Traditional approaches for preventing proximal lesions such as flossing and rinsing with fluoride usually have limited success as they rely heavily on patients compliance (Alm et al. 2007). More recently, treatment of proximal caries has been focussed on arresting initial caries by sealing these lesions with low viscosity resins (Ekstrand et al. 2010). Although early success has been reported using this technique, there is a need to gain access to the proximal lesions which requires physical separation of the teeth. As this technique usually involves two appointments, it is not practical for young children.

A more conservative alternative would be to seal the teeth while it is possible to gain access to the proximal smooth surfaces before the contacts with adjacent teeth are established. There are a few stages in the development of the primary and permanent dentitions which provide windows of opportunity to gain such access to specific proximal surfaces of the posterior teeth.

HYPOTHESIS
We hypothesize that smooth surface sealants (SSS) placed prior to establishment of the proximal contacts can prevent proximal caries in teeth.

AIMS
Therefore the aims of the study are to:
 (1)	 Determine the caries incidence in sealed surfaces of primary and secondary teeth compared to unsealed surfaces in the same teeth in other quadrants of the mouth.

(2) 	Evaluate the cost effectiveness of smooth surface sealants in preventing caries</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland Health Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/10/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/QPAH/364</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/04/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Hien Ngo</name>
      <address>School of Dentistry
Univ of Queensland
200 Turbot St, QLD 4000</address>
      <phone>+61 451507145</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.ngo@uq.edu.au; hienngodentistry@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Hien Ngo</name>
      <address>School of Dentistry
Univ of Queensland
200 Turbot St, QLD 4000</address>
      <phone>+61 451507145</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.ngo@uq.edu.au; hienngodentistry@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Hien Ngo</name>
      <address>School of Dentistry
Univ of Queensland
200 Turbot St, QLD 4000</address>
      <phone>+61 451507145</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.ngo@uq.edu.au; hienngodentistry@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>