<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336625">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/03/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000248965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of lutein with milk on physical activity</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of lutein-milk for improving exercise self-efficacy and exercise participation in older adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>physical inactivity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will be encouraged to undertake regular physical activity involving the performance of at least 150 min/week of moderate to vigorous activity in accordance with the national physical activity guidelines for Australian adults for 3 weeks (Week 1-4). The physical activity will be left up to the participant to perform. 
In addition to undertaking regular physical activity, participants will be allocated to the treatment group (capsules containing 21 mg/day of lutein) or the placebo group. Participants will be required to consume a capsule and 250 ml of full cream milk at the same time everyday, preferably in the morning, for 4 weeks (Week 0-4).</interventions>
    <comparator>placebo capsules contain 155 mg of microcrystalline cellulose and 155 mg of lactose</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity levels (measured using accelerometry)</outcome>
      <timepoint>An accelerometer will be worn the week prior to beginning supplementation (Week -1) and again after 4 weeks of supplementation (Week 4).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity levels (step counts from pedometer)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pedometers will be worn for the entire 5 week study period and daily step counts will be recorded</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy to regulate exercise will be assessed using a validated questionnaire portraying different levels of exercise task demands against which participants rate the strength of their belief in their ability to perform their exercise routine regularly using a 100 point scale. The higher the total score the greater the exercise-self efficacy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Exercise self-efficacy will be assessed at the start of Week -1 and again a week later before supplementation begins (week 0) and then again after one week of supplementation (Week 1) and again at the end of the study period (Week 4)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood concentration of lutein</outcome>
      <timepoint>fasting blood samples will be taken at baseline (Week -1) and at the end of the study period (Week 4)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged between 60 and 80 yrs Not currently participating in sufficient physical activity levels to meet Australia guidelines BMI between 18.5 and 29.9 kg/m2</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Typically consume more than two standard serves of dairy products per day
Non weight-stable (body weight change of &gt;3 kg in last 3 months)
Acute or terminal illness 
Moderate or severe cognitive impairment (inability to understand and provide written informed consent and/or follow instructions)
Any medical condition that might be exacerbated by exercise or might limit exercise training
Current smoker or only recently quit smoking (smoked any cigarettes within the last 12 months)
Alcohol consumption (more than four alcoholic drinks per day)
Coeliac disease
Lactose intolerance
Allergy to cows milk protein
Diabetes
Medications (or supplements) changed significantly during the last 12 weeks
Consume carotenoids (lutein, astaxanthin, zeaxanthin) supplements daily
Any other condition which in the opinion of the investigators might confound the outcomes of the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be recruited by newspaper advertisement and flyers. Volunteers will be screened via questionnaire and a medical screening visit to access their eligibility for the trial. Eligibility will be determined by the study coordinator and medical physician. Treatment will be randomised by an investigator not involved in data collection and allocation will be concealed from the participant and study staff.</concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation to treatments will be via the process of minimisation (1) on the basis of gender, age, and current levels of physical activity (assessed by pedometry in the week prior to treatment allocation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>44</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Meiji Dairies Corporation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>540 Naruda, Odawara, Kanagawa 250-0862</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Japan</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Meiji Dairies Corporation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>540 Naruda, Odawara, Kanagawa 250-0862</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Japan</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to determine whether the consumption of lutein with milk increases exercise-self efficacy, leading to increased exercise participation in older adults. The overall purpose is to provide scientific substantiation for a novel nutritional supplement aimed at increasing physical activity to improve health and reduce disability in an ageing population.

Preliminary research in rats demonstrated that the consumption of lutein-fortified milk increased the duration of voluntary wheel running. This increased wheel running was associated with enhanced muscle development and reduced body fat. The mechanism by which the lutein-fortified milk stimulated the rats to increase the volume of wheel running is not known, but it seems likely that there was some change in their mood which promoted exercise behaviour. If this supplement were to elicit a similar effect in people being encouraged to undertake regular physical activity this might result in them undertaking a greater volume of exercise and thus potentially achieving health benefits.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>General Purpose Building, Mawson Lakes Campus Mawson Lakes Boulevard Mawson Lakes, SA 5095</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/02/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>21020</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Jon Buckley</name>
      <address>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1853</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jon.buckley@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Rebecca Thomson</name>
      <address>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.thomson@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Rebecca Thomson</name>
      <address>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre,
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1822</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8302 2178</fax>
      <email>rebecca.thomson@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>