<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371297">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001114437p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Analysing and Using Demographic Information and Treatment Endpoints to Determine Numbers (AUDITED Numbers) for The Sildenafil during Coronary artery bypass graft Operations to Reduce Endpoints for patients with Coronary ARtery Disease (SCORECARD) Project</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Analysing and Using Demographic Information and Treatment Endpoints to Determine Numbers (AUDITED Numbers) for The Sildenafil during Coronary artery bypass graft Operations to Reduce Endpoints for patients with Coronary ARtery Disease (SCORECARD) Project</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1186-4611</utrn>
    <trialacronym>AUDITED Numbers</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary artery disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Retrospective analysis of the clinical notes of all patients who underwent coronary artery bypass graft surgery at Greenlane Cardiothoracic Surgical Unit between 1 August 2015 and 31 July 2016.</interventions>
    <comparator>Not applicable.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnosed myocardial infarction based upon review of the patient's anaesthetic record, Cardiovascular Intensive Care Unit record and discharge summary from the cardiothoracic service.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 30 days post-coronary artery bypass graft surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnosed vasospasm based upon review of the patient's anaesthetic record, Cardiovascular Intensive Care Unit record and discharge summary from the cardiothoracic service.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 30 days post-coronary artery bypass graft surgery based upon review of the patient's anaesthetic record, Cardiovascular Intensive Care Unit record and discharge summary from the cardiothoracic service.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnosed graft failure based upon review of the patient's anaesthetic record, Cardiovascular Intensive Care Unit record and discharge summary from the cardiothoracic service.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 30 days post-coronary artery bypass graft surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality-rate </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 30 days post-coronary artery bypass graft surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnosed acute kidney injury based upon review of the patient's anaesthetic record, Cardiovascular Intensive Care Unit record and discharge summary from the cardiothoracic service.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 30 days post-coronary artery bypass graft surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Repeat revascularisation procedure based upon review of the patient's anaesthetic record, Cardiovascular Intensive Care Unit record and discharge summary from the cardiothoracic service.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 30 days post-coronary artery bypass graft surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of intubation based upon review of the patient's anaesthetic record and Cardiovascular Intensive Care Unit record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of extubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Cardiovascular Intensive Care Unit stay based upon review of the patient's Cardiovascular Intensive Care Unit record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of discharge from Cardiovascular Intensive Care Unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of admission based upon review of the patient's discharge summary from the cardiothoracic service.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Underwent coronary artery bypass graft surgery.
2) Procedure between 1 August 2015 and 31 July 2016.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>This retrospective analysis of all patients undergoing coronary artery  bypass graft surgery at Greenlane Cardiothoracic Surgical Unit within a 12-month period will provide a snapshot of the mean intraoperative and postoperative characteristics of patients such as the average duration of intubation. This analysis will also provide a snapshot of the short-term (30 days) morbidity- and mortality-rates of coronary artery bypass graft surgery patients.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Retrospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/10/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/10/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Rationale of Study
As described in detail elsewhere,  cardiovascular disease is the greatest cause of mortality in New Zealand. Coronary artery disease (CAD) is not only implicated in most of these patients but is also the commonest cause of death, worldwide. In patients with severe CAD, the gold-standard revascularisation approach is CABG which, in low-risk patients, carries a mortality risk of &lt; 1%. Furthermore, the success-rates of CABG have increased substantially over the last several decades as a result of improvements in surgical technique and the development of an increasingly robust literature-base. However, major adverse cardiac events still affect around 5% of patients and they are potently associated with the incidence of vasospasm, graft occlusion and ischaemia-reperfusion injury. Therefore, the continued development and refinement of methods to reduce these complications has the potential to significantly improve CABG outcomes.
A variety of techniques are presently employed to reduce vasospasm and graft occlusion. For example, the use of the no-touch technique during graft harvesting significantly reduces vasospasm and the intraluminal administration of a nitroglycerin-verapamil solution reduces the risk of graft occlusion. However, these approaches are not foolproof. Every graft requires at least some degree of physical contact during anastomosis and the nitroglycerin-verapamil solution is limited by its short half-life and marked systemic effects. Ischaemia-reperfusion injury is also a relatively new concept and, while clinical studies investigating the therapeutic effect of remote ischaemic preconditioning have been successful, routine use in the operating theatre remains scarce.
Sildenafil is a type 5 phosphodiesterase inhibitor that has vasodilatory, antiplatelet and ischaemia-reperfusion injury-preventing properties. Thus, it has been suggested that sildenafil might have novel therapeutic effects in patients undergoing CABG. A double-blind randomised controlled trial is currently being designed in order to investigate this hypothesis. However, it is unknown exactly what proportion of patients undergoing CABG within the Auckland region suffer from short-term vasospasm, graft occlusion and ischaemia-reperfusion injury or which demographic groups are over-represented in patients undergoing CABG. Therefore, the purpose of this study is to determine the demographic makeup and vasospasm, graft occlusion and ischaemia reperfusion-injury complication-rates in patients undergoing CABG within the greater Auckland region.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>None</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Steve Waqanivavalagi</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64275370425</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.waqanivavalagi@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Steve Waqanivavalagi</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64275370425</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.waqanivavalagi@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Steve Waqanivavalagi</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64275370425</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.waqanivavalagi@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Steve Waqanivavalagi</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesiology
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64275370425</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.waqanivavalagi@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>