<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365685">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000821594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Management of ankle deformity after acquired brain injury</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of combining serial casting and botulinum toxin for the management of ankle contractures after traumatic brain injury: a randomised controlled study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>acquired brain  injury admitted for sub-acute rehabilitation </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>contracture</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group receives intervention treatment in addition to usual care. Botulinum toxin will be injected into calf muscles which may include soleus, gastronemius, flexor hallucis longer and flexor digitorium longus. Botulinum toxin injection may also be injected into tibialis posterior where necessary. The injections will be administered by a sole person (the Director of the Brain Injury Unit) with electrical stimulation or sonographic guidance. The dose of botulinum toxin will vary depending on number of muscles needing injections but will be within the recommended maximum dose of 400ml. Serial casting will be commenced within a few days. Cast will be applied to the ankle by physiotherapists. The duration of casting and number of cast applied may vary based on the participants responses to casting. After completion of casting, a customised ankle splint will be used immediately. The splint will be worn 24 hours a day for the initial 2 weeks during which the splint will only be removed for hygiene reasons and therapy. Thereafter ongoing monitoring will be conducted and the splinting time will be maintained or reduced depending on the progress of the participants. The splint will be applied by physiotherapists, nursing staff or physiotherapy assistants as directed by the treating physiotherapists. The participants tolerance to splinting and skin condition will be closely monitored. This treatment program simulates the current clinical practice of a Brain Injury Unit in Sydney. Participants in the control group will be placed on a wait list for 6 weeks during which they receive no botulinum toxin, splinting and passive stretch-based interventions for the ankle. Thereafter, they receive the same treatment as the intervention group. Diaries will be used to record all interventions and adverse events. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive usual care in the 6 weeks prior to receiving the intervention treatment.The usual care includes multidisciplinary rehabilitation provided by the unit as appropriate. This consisted of physiotherapy, occupational therapy, speech therapy, recreational therapy and psychological therapy. Physiotherapy included an individualised motor training program which might involve lower limb exercises, practice of sit to stand, standing and walking. The usual care also involves positioning of participants feet in dorsiflexion while seated and lying. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Passive dosiflexion range at a standardised torque</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary timepoint is post interventions (i.e., following the completion of botulinum toxin and serial casting). The duration of casting and number of cast applied may vary based on the participants responses to casting. It can range from 4 to 9 weeks. The primary timepoint will be within 3 days after completion of serial casting. Follow-up assessments will be conducted at week 2 and 8 post intervention, at time of discharge and if possible 1 year after discharge.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spasticity of ankle plantarflexors (Tardieu Scale score)</outcome>
      <timepoint>The secondary timepoint is the same as the primary timepoint (i.e., following the completion of botulinum toxin and serial casting). The duration of casting and number of cast applied may vary based on the participants responses to casting. It can range from 4 to 9 weeks. The primary timepoint will be within 3 days after completion of serial casting. Follow-up assessments will be conducted at week 2 and 8 post intervention, at time of discharge and if possible 1 year after discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Activity limitations: FIM score for walking item and 10-metre walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>The secondary timepoint is the same as the primary timepoint (i.e., following the completion of botulinum toxin and serial casting). The duration of casting and number of cast applied may vary based on the participants responses to casting. It can range from 4 to 9 weeks. The primary timepoint will be within 3 days after completion of serial casting. Follow-up assessments will be conducted at week 2 and 8 post intervention, at time of discharge and if possible 1 year after discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Therapist questionnaire (perceived effectiveness, adverse events and treatment worth) is a secondary outcome measure. It is designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The secondary timepoint is the same as the primary timepoint (i.e., following the completion of botulinum toxin and serial casting). The duration of casting and number of cast applied may vary based on the participants responses to casting. It can range from 4 to 9 weeks. The primary timepoint will be within 3 days after completion of serial casting. Follow-up assessments will be conducted at week 2 and 8 post intervention, at time of discharge and if possible 1 year after discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-diagnosed with acquired brain injury and admitted for sub-acute rehabilitation
-presents with an ankle contracture of a severe degree
-able to receive botulinum toxin injections and serial casting
-unlikely to be discharged in 12 weeks, and
-provide consent to participate in the study (the participants or the person legally responsible for them (This person can be legal guardian/next of kin or carer as determined by law)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-unstable medical conditions or recent ankle fractures
-within 3 months after receiving botulinum toxin
-severe ankle varus or knee/hip flexion contractures (which affects the reliability of measuring ankle dorsiflexion)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The physiotherapists of the Brain Injury Unit will screen all existing patients and all new admissions. Outcomes of screening will be recorded on the Screening Log. Passive dorsiflexion range of motion of patients will be measured with a goniometer and manual stretch. When an eligible participant is identified, the physiotherapists will notify the Investigators who will confirm participant’s eligibility.
Potential participants or the persons responsible for them will be given the Participant / Person Responsible Information Sheets. An investigator will explain the study protocol to them. No pressure to participate will be placed on the potential participant under any circumstances. The potential participants will be informed that participation in the study is entirely voluntary and they are free to withdraw from the study at any stage without any effect on their current or future treatment. Those who agree to participate will be given the Consent Form to sign and commence involvement in the study. 
Health care interpreters will be used for potential participants who cannot speak English.
The random allocation sequence will be computer-generated by an administrative assistant who will not be involved in the study. Group allocation will be concealed using consecutively numbered, sealed, opaque envelopes which will be kept away from investigators/therapists. After baseline assessment, the investigator will contact the administrative assistant to open the envelope and reveal the group allocation. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>The allocation sequence will be computer generated (i.e.,a simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software - computerised sequence generation) by a person not involved in the recruitment. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>In addition to between group comparisons at completion of casting and 2 weeks following that, there will be follow-up assessments for both the experimental group and control group 8 weeks post-intervention, at the time of discharge and if possible 1 year after discharge. The same assessment as listed in step 4 will be conducted at all these additional timepoints. A questionnaire will be used to collect feedback from participants or persons responsible for them if participants cannot provide feedback themselves.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size has been calculated apriori based on best estimates. A sample of 10 participants will be recruited to provide an 80% probability of detecting a between-group difference of 20 degrees for the primary outcome, assuming a standard deviation of 5 degrees (Moseley 1997) and a 10% drop-out rate.
General Linear Regression analyses were performed to assess passive dorsiflexion, walking speed, Functional Independent Measure score for the walking item and spasticity. The significance level was set at &lt; 0.05. Analyses were conducted separately for the end of intervention and follow-up assessments. Missing data were not imputed. All analyses were performed according to intention-to-treat.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/06/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Rehabilitation Hospital - Coorabel/Moorong - Ryde</hospital>
    <postcode>2112 - Ryde</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Rehab</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>227 Morrison Road, RYDE NSW 2112</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Rehab Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>235 Morrison Road, RYDE NSW 2112</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of the project is to determine the effectiveness of a treatment program combining serial casting with Botulinum Toxin for the management of contractures in adults with acquired brain injury. An assessor blinded, randomised controlled study with a cross-over design will be conducted. Ankle joint is selected as a model to assess the effectiveness of the intervention. Participants will be adults with acquired brain injury admitted to the Brain Injury Rehabilitation Unit of Royal Rehab for sub-acute rehabilitation. Between-group comparisons will be made to determine the effectiveness of the intervention program. The participants in the control group will be placed on a wait list for the same treatment program. Pre-and post-intervention comparisons will also be made within the control group. Follow-up assessments for both the experimental group and control group will be conducted 8 weeks post interventions, at discharge and if possible 1 year after discharge to assess the long-term effects of the interventions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kolling Building, Level 13, Royal North Shore Hospital, St Leonards NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RESP/14/213</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/09/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HREC of Royal Rehab</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>235 Morrison Road, RYDE NSW 2112</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15SSA01</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/12/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joan Wai King Leung</name>
      <address>Brain Injury Unit, Royal Rehab, 227 Morrison Road, RYDE NSW 2112</address>
      <phone>+6, 12, 98099020</phone>
      <fax>+6, 12, 98077484</fax>
      <email>joan.leung@royalrehab.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joan Wai King Leung</name>
      <address>Brain Injury Unit, Royal Rehab, 227 Morrison Road, RYDE NSW 2112</address>
      <phone>+6, 12, 98099020</phone>
      <fax>+6, 12, 98077484</fax>
      <email>joan.leung@royalrehab.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joan Wai King Leung</name>
      <address>Brain Injury Unit, Royal Rehab, 227 Morrison Road, RYDE NSW 2112</address>
      <phone>+6, 12, 98099020</phone>
      <fax>+6, 12, 98077484</fax>
      <email>joan.leung@royalrehab.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joan Wai King Leung</name>
      <address>Brain Injury Unit, Royal Rehab, 227 Morrison Road, RYDE NSW 2112</address>
      <phone>+6, 12, 98099020</phone>
      <fax>+6, 12, 98077484</fax>
      <email>joan.leung@royalrehab.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>