<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82907">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/06/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/07/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000335392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase I, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Dose Escalation Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of EMA401 Following Single Ascending Oral Dosing of EMA401.Na in Healthy Volunteers Administered Orally in the Fasted and Fed State.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Dose Escalation Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of EMA401 Following Single Ascending Oral Dosing of EMA401.Na in Healthy Volunteers Administered Orally in the Fasted and Fed State.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Postherpetic Neuralgia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>EMA401 powder hand-filled into hard gelatin capsules.
4 out of 6 subjects in each cohort will take  a single oral dose of the EMA401 following an overnight fast. There are 6 cohorts with dose levels of 100mg, 200mg, 400mg, 600mg, 800mg, 1000mg. One dose level (cohort) will be asked to return to repeat the study with the drug being taken following a standard meal. There will be 6 subjects per cohort, 2 receiving placebo and 4 receiving the active drug.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo - Lactose monohydrate hand-filled into hard gelatin capsules.
2 out of 6 subjects in each cohort will take  a single oral dose of the placebo following an overnight fast. There are 6 cohorts with dose levels for the active drug of 100mg, 200mg, 400mg, 600mg, 800mg, 1000mg. One dose level (cohort) will be asked to return to repeat the study with the drug being taken following a standard meal. There will be 6 subjects per cohort, 2 receiving placebo and 4 receiving the active drug.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of a single dose of EMA401</outcome>
      <timepoint>Vital signs (x10), clinical laboratory results(x6) and Electrocardiograms (ECGs) (x12) will be recorded over a 48 hour time period post dose and 24 hour cardiac telemetry for the first 24 hours post-dose. Vital signs measurements include resting heart rate, Blood Pressure readings, respiratory rate and body temperature recording. The clinical laboratory results will be from blood samples taken at the screening visit, the day prior to dosing, at 4, 24 and 48 hours post-dose and again at the follow up visit, 7 days post-dose.  Adverse events and concomitant medications required will be monitored over the 48 hour time period post dose. A final follow up evaluation including a physical examination will be performed 7 days post dose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the pharmacokinetic profile of EMA401 following a single oral dose in healthy fasting volunteers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 x pre-dose and 18 post-dose blood samples will be collected over a 48 hour period. Urine will be collected for 24 hours post-dose. Both blood and urine samples will be analysed to profile the pharmacokinetics.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effects of food on the pharmacokinetics of EMA401 following a single oral dose in healthy volunteers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Dosing will be repeated in one dose level, with dosing occurring after a standard meal.  1 x pre-dose and 18 post-dose blood samples will be collected over a 48 hour period. Urine will be collected for 24 hours post-dose. Both blood and urine samples will be analysed to profile the food-effect pharmacokinetics.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy subjects- defined as individuals who are free from clinically significant illnesss or disease as determined by their medical / surgical history, physical examination (including height &amp; weight), 12 lead electrocardiogram (ECG) and clincial laboratory determinations.
Normotensive - Systolic between 90 and 140 mmHg, diastolic between 60 &amp; 90 mmHg.
No clincially relevant abnormality in an electrocardiogram (ECG) - QTc &lt; 450ms, PR interval 120-210 ms, QRS duration &lt;100ms. (QTc = QT interval corrected for heart rate, where QT =  a measure of the time between the start of the Q wave and the end of the T wave in the heart's electrical cycle, PR interval  = measured from the beginning of the P wave to the beginning of the QRS complex and QRS duration (complex) = a structure on the ECG that corresponds to the depolarization of the ventricles.
Resting pulse rate - between 40 and 100 bpm
Body Mass Index (BMI)- between 19 and 30 kg/m2
Human Immunodefeciency Virus (HIV), Hepatitis B virus and Hepatitis C virus negative 
Smoked less than 5 cigarettes or equivalent per month in last 12 months.
Agrees to use 2 methods of contraception during study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Has received  / anticipates receiving  a new prescription systemic / topical mediction within 14 days prior to dosing.
Any disease interfering with drug absorption.
Any abnormal clincial laboratory findings deemed significant by the Medical Officer.
Positive urine drug test /alcohol breath test
History of coronary /cardiovascular/ cerebrovsacular disease, uncontrolled hypertension
Any acute therapy for a serious infection within 30 days of study entry.
Blood donation greater than 550mL within 90 days of dosing.
participation in a clinical trial /received experimental therapy within 30 days of dosing.
Consumption of grapefruit juice/products within 14 days prior to study confinement.
Unwilling to provide consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be allocated a sequentially numbered randomisation number following confirmation of eligibility on day -1 and the Screening visit results. The randomisation number will be matched to the treatment allocation from a randomisation schedule which is computer generated and maintained under controlled access. The subject and all clinical staff will be blinded to the treatment allocation. Only the unblinded staff members involved in the drug dispensing will be aware of the treatment allocation. Emergency codebreak envelopes are stored securely at the site should an emergency situation require the knowledge of what treatment the subject received.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation computer generated block randomisation per cohort.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Dose escalation with single dosing per dose level -6 dose levels + one dose level is repeated for the food effect cohort.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/07/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Spinifex Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 2210, Wattletree Road LPO
Malvern East, Victoria,
3145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Spinifex Pharmaceuticals Pty Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 2210, Wattletree Road LPO
Malvern East, Victoria,
3145</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is to evaluate the pharmacokinetics (the way the body absorbs the drug) and to determine what the safest that can be used.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/06/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tamara Murdock</name>
      <address>Centre for Pharmaceutical Research
University of South Australia
Level 4 Reid Building
Frome Road, Adelaide
SA 5000</address>
      <phone>0061 8 8302 2311</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tamara.murdock@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tamara Murdock</name>
      <address>Centre for Pharmaceutical Research
University of South Australia
Level 4 Reid Building
Frome Road, Adelaide
SA 5000</address>
      <phone>0061 8 8302 2311</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tamara.murdock@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sarah King</name>
      <address>PO BOX 2210
Wattletree Road LPO
Malvern East, VIC, 3145</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9024 2817</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarah.king@spinifexpharma.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>