<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368415">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000606583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of SBP-101 safety and tolerability in patients with previously treated pancreatic cancer </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1a/1b Study of SBP-101 in Previously Treated Subjects with Locally Advanced or Metastatic Pancreatic Ductal Adenocarcinoma
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CL-SBP-101-01</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pancreatic cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pancreatic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>SBP-101
During Phase 1a of the study, participants will be enrolled in each of 8 cohorts sequentially:
1) Cohort 1: SBP-101, 0.05 mg/kg subcutaneously, for up to 5 cycles
2) Cohort 2: SBP-101, 0.10 mg/kg subcutaneously, for up to 5 cycles
3) Cohort 3: SBP-101, 0.20 mg/kg subcutaneously, for up to 5 cycles
4) Cohort 4: SBP-101, 0.40 mg/kg subcutaneously, for up to 5 cycles
5) Cohort 5: SBP-101, 0.80 mg/kg subcutaneously, for up to 5 cycles
6) Cohort 6: SBP-101, 1.20 mg/kg subcutaneously, for up to 3 cycles
7) Cohort 7: SBP-101, 1.60 mg/kg subcutaneously, for up to 2.5 cycles
8) Cohort 8: SBP-101, 2.00 mg/kg subcutaneously, for up to 2 cycles.

All cohorts will receive subcutaneous injections of SBP-101 once daily Monday through Friday, for 3 weeks, followed by a 5- week rest period (3 weeks on, 5 weeks off = 1 cycle). 


Tumour assessment will be performed at the end of each cycle 1 and every 8 weeks thereafter. If the disease is stable or a partial response is seen, participants will continue to receive cycles of SBP-101 up to the maximum number of cycles specified above until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity, whichever comes first. If a participant has a complete response prior to receiving the maximum number of allowed cycles, one additional cycle will be administered.

In Phase 1b of the study, an additional 24 participants will be enrolled at the maximum tolerated dose identified in Phase 1a to further establish the safety and tolerability of SBP-101 and to explore efficacy endpoints. Subjects in the phase 1b expansion study will receive SBP-101 subcutaneously on Monday through Friday for 3 weeks (15 doses per cycle) at the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) confirmed in Part 1a of this trial, repeated every 8 weeks (3 weeks on, 5 weeks off) for up to 5 cycles or a maximum cumulative dose of 60 mg/kg of treatment (depending on the MTD), or until disease progression or unacceptable toxicity, whichever comes first. If a participant has a complete response prior to receiving the maximum number of allowed cycles, one additional cycle will be administered.

</interventions>
    <comparator>No treatment</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of the phase 1a First-Time-in-Human study is to determine the maximum tolerated dose and dose limiting toxicities (DLT) of SBP-101 in participants with previously treated locally advanced or metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma 

This will be done by monitoring each participant for study drug treatment-related toxicities at each dose level. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>After Phase 1a completed.

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of the phase 1b expansion study is to further establish the safety and tolerability of the SBP-101 at the MTD and to explore efficacy endpoints in patients with measureable disease.
This will be done by monitoring safety (number and severity of adverse events, laboratory results, vital signs, changes in bowel habits) and tumour assessment (CT/MRI scan) and tumour biomarker CA19-9.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 24 subjects completed Phase 1b</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the adverse event profile of SBP-101. 
This will be done by monitoring and recording adverse events and by monitoring clinically significant changes in safety laboratory tests, physical findings, vital signs,
electrocardiogram (ECG), and Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed from start of treatment to end of treatment for each participant.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To describe the pharmacokinetics of SBP-101.
This will be done by collecting a number of blood and urine samples from participants.
Phase 1a- blood samples taken at Cycle 1 Day 1-2 and Day 18-19 (before study drug dose and every 30 minutes up to 4 hours, 8 hours, 10 hours and 24 hours after study drug dose) and an additional blood sample taken on Day 12 (1 hour post dose) of Cycles 1 and 2. Urine samples collected before study drug dose at Cycle 1 day 1 and a 24 hour urine collection collected at Cycle 1 day 18.
Phase 1b- blood samples taken before study drug dose at Cycle 1 day 1 and day 19 and 1 hour after dose on Cycle 1 day 19.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Phase 1a- blood samples taken at Cycle 1 Day 1-2 and Day 18-19 (before study drug dose and every 30 minutes up to 4 hours, 8 hours, 10 hours and 24 hours after study drug dose) and an additional blood sample taken on Day 12 (1 hour post dose) of Cycles 1 and 2. Urine samples collected before study drug dose at Cycle 1 day 1 and a 24 hour urine collection collected at Cycle 1 day 18.
Phase 1b- blood samples taken before study drug dose at Cycle 1 day 1 and day 19 and 1 hour after dose on Cycle 1 day 19.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To document any antitumor activity in subjects treated with SBP-101 .
This will be assessed by CT scan and by blood tumour marker CA19-9.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and then every 8 weeks (CT/MRI scan)
and 4 weeks (CA19-9) until end of treatment for each participant.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Histologically or cytologically confirmed locally advanced or
metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma. Patients with acinar cell carcinoma may also be included.
2. Measurable disease on computed tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan by RECIST criteria (Phase 1b only) 
3. ECOG Performance Status 0 or 1.
4. Received, and failed or were intolerant to at least 1 prior systemic therapy for locally advanced or metastatic pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma
5. Adult, aged 18 years or older, male or female
6. Females of child-bearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test within 14 days prior to start of study treatment and must use an adequate method of contraception during the study. All sexually active males must also use an adequate method of contraception during the study 
7. Adequate bone marrow, hepatic, renal and coagulation function 
8. QTc interval less than or equal to 470 msec at Baseline
9. Willing and able to provide written informed consent.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Evidence of severe or uncontrolled systemic disease or any
concurrent condition that, in the opinion of the Investigator or
Medical Monitor, makes it undesirable for the subject to participate in the study or that would jeopardize compliance with the protocol. Subjects with pre-existing well-controlled diabetes are not excluded.
2. Medical or psychiatric conditions that compromise the subject's ability to give informed consent or to complete the protocol or a history of non-compliance
3. Presence of islet-cell or pancreatic neuroendocrine tumor or mixed adenocarcinoma-neuroendocrine carcinoma
4. Symptomatic central nervous system (CNS) malignancy or metastasis. Screening of asymptomatic subjects without history of CNS metastases is not required.
5. Serum albumin less than 30 g/L (3.0 g/dL)
6. Glycosylated hemoglobin (Hgb A1C) greater than  8.0%
7. Life expectancy  less than 16 weeks
8. Presence of known active bacterial, fungal, or viral infection
requiring systemic therapy
9. Known infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV),
hepatitis B or C
10. Presence of interstitial lung disease, pulmonary fibrosis, or
pulmonary hypersensitivity reaction
11. Myocardial infarction within the last 12 months, severe/unstable angina, symptomatic congestive heart failure New York Heart Association (NYHA) class III or IV
12. Maldigestion/malabsorption syndrome pre-dating the diagnosis of pancreatic cancer
13. Known existing coagulopathy or receiving anticoagulants
14. Pregnant or lactating
15. Major surgery within 4 weeks of the start of study treatment, without complete recovery
16. Participation in any other clinical investigation within 4 weeks of receiving the first dose of study drug.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data analyses will be provided by dose groups and for all study subjects combined wherever appropriate. For continuous variables, summary statistics will include number of subjects, mean, median, standard deviation, minimum, and maximum. Categorical endpoints will be summarized using number of subjects, frequency, and percentages. 
Safety analyses will be conducted for all enrolled subjects who receive at least 1 dose of study drug, whether or not they complete all protocol requirements. Safety parameters will be listed and summarized using standard descriptive statistics. Adverse event terms will be coded using the Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities (MedDRA) and will be summarized by dose. Incidence of adverse events occurring during the study will be summarized by system organ class (SOC) and preferred term. Adverse events will also be summarized by causality and grade. Serious adverse events will be listed separately. The rate of DLTs per dose level will be presented. All DLTs will be presented in data listings. Descriptive summary statistics will be used to summarize changes in laboratory values and vital signs by dose. Additional analyses will be performed if warranted upon review of the data.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/12/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>54</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5037 - Kurralta Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>TBC</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sun BioPharma Australia Pty Ltd </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>550 Bourke Street
Melbourne VIC 3000 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sun BioPharma Australia Pty Ltd </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>550 Bourke Street
Melbourne VIC 3000 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Novotech (Australia) Pty Limited</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 3, 235 Pyrmont St
Pyrmont NSW 2009</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main goal of this study is to assess the safety and tolerability of the drug SBP-101 in patients with pancreatic cancer. You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above and have been diagnosed with metastatic or locally advanced ductal adenocarcinoma of the pancreas, which has been previously treated with chemotherapy. Study details: Participants in the first part of this study (Phase 1a) will be administered SBP-101 in a dose-escalation scheme with cohorts at each dose level (0.05, 0.10, 0.2, 0.40, 0.80, 1.2, 1.6 and 2.0 mg/kg). All cohorts will receive injections of SBP-101 once daily Monday through Friday, for 3 weeks, followed by a 5-week rest period (3 weeks on and 5 weeks off = 1 cycle) for up to 5 cycles depending on response. Participants in the second part of this study (Phase 1b) will be administered SBP-101 at the maximum tolerated dose identified in Phase 1a for up to 5 cycles. SBP-101 is a small molecule which is similar to a compound, spermine, found naturally in human cells and important in cell survival / growth. Laboratory and animal studies suggest that SBP-101inhibits cell growth by substituting for spermine, suggesting that SBP-101 is a promising candidate for further development as a treatment for pancreatic cancer. Participants will be regularly assessed during treatment in order to assess safety and tolerability. Other goals of this study are to measure the levels of SBP-101 in the blood and urine over time and test whether SBP-101 can slow the growth of, or shrink tumours.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road
Eastwood SA 5063 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/09/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00372</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dusan Kotasek MB BS FRACP</name>
      <address>Adelaide Cancer Centre, 
Suite 10, Level 1, Tennyson Centre
520 South Road, Kurralta Park SA 5037
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8292 2220</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8292 2230 </fax>
      <email>dkotasek@adelaidecancercentre.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sheri Smith</name>
      <address>Courante Oncology
202 Water Street, Suite 201
Excelsior, MN  55331 </address>
      <phone>+1 952 908 9986               	</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ssmith@couranteoncology.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suzanne Gagnon MD</name>
      <address>100 Shetland Way
Collegeville, PA 19426

</address>
      <phone>+1 215 833 3313 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sgagnon@sunbiopharma.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kim Wong</name>
      <address>Novotech (Australia) Pty Limited
Level 3, 235 Pyrmont St
Pyrmont NSW 2009 
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8569 1400</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 8569 1498</fax>
      <email>kim.wong@novotech-cro.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>