<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1314">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/05/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/05/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000215527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving continuity of clinical care and educating general practitioners  development and evaluation of information sheets about chemotherapy for general practitioners</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Improving continuity of clinical care and educating general practitioners  development and evaluation of information sheets about chemotherapy in patients with cancer for general practitioners</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>GP Fax Sheets</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cancer (general)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2 />
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention involves standardised faxed information (letter and drug information sheets) being sent to the GP of patients receiving chemotherapy at Peter Maccallum Cancer Centre.  The faxed sheet will be one page long and sent immediately after the establishment of a baseline (a questionnaire testing GPs knowledge of their patients chemotherapy regime related side-effects administered directly after a patient begins their chemotherapy regime).</interventions>
    <comparator>The contol gorup will receive usual correspondance from Peter Maccallum, which consists of a non-standardised letter written by the patient's Medical Oncologist.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome of the evaluation will be improved GP knowledge regarding management of patients having chemotherapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured one week after the administration of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome of the evaluation will be improved self-perceived confidence regarding management of patients having chemotherapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured one week after the administration of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For GPs  providing improved care for their patients on the basis of the consistent and comprehensive information provided. </outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For patients  enhanced care through more integrated health care delivery between Peter Mac and GPs and better-informed GPs. This might result in fewer uncontrolled side effects, and greater access to medical staff able to manage their side effects.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For Peter Mac  improved relationship with the GP community, fewer unplanned admissions due to inadequately controlled side effects, potentially fewer admissions of seriously unwell patients; more rapid triage of patients with life-threatening side effects such as febrile neutropenia.  These outcomes will be measured at follow up one week after the administration of the intervemtion.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible GPs must:1.Be the nominated GP of a patient with a defined cancer type, who is scheduled to commence a defined chemotherapy regimen 2.Agree to be randomised to either the intervention group who will receive faxed or e-mailed information or to the usual contact group3.Agree to participate in two brief telephone surveys (pre and post)4.Provide verbal informed consent to participate in this study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Not stated</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>To be eligible GPs must not:1.have already been enrolled in this study (if the same GP is treating two patients who are receiving chemotherapy in the Day Ward at Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre only the 1st patient will be included in this study)2. have a patient is is receiving concurrent radiotherapy.All age ranges and both genders will be included within the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed Opaque Envelope Procedure</concealment>
    <sequence>Biased Coin Procedure</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/05/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Peter Macallum Cancer Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Roche Products</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Roche Products</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Switzerland</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of this project is to demonstrate that the provision of information about chemotherapy and management of chemotherapy side effects
1.is perceived by GPs to be useful and, 
2.when compared to usual care, results in 
(a)improved knowledge; 
(b)enhanced confidence regarding the management of patients having chemotherapy and
(c)higher satisfaction with shared care with Peter Mac</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peter Maccallum Cancer Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>05/33</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carl Baravelli</name>
      <address>Educational Centre - Level 3 St Andrews Place East Melbourne VIC  
Locked Bag 1 A'Beckett Street VIC 8006 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9656 1667</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9656 1337</fax>
      <email>Carl.Baravelli@Petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carl Baravelli</name>
      <address>Educational Centre - Level 3, St Andrews Place East Melbourne Vic  
Postal Address: Locked Bag 1 A'Beckett Street Victoria 8006 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9656 1667</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9656 1337</fax>
      <email>Carl.Baravelli@Petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>