<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81889">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/03/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/03/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000157471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Heparin in Severe Sepsis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does Heparin improve survivial in severe sepsis? A pilot feasability study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>HISS Study</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Severe sepsis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other blood disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Blinded study of low-dose intravenous unfractionated heparin (UFH) (control) compared to subcutaneous fondaparinux (intervention) in patients with severe sepsis. 

Fondaparinux: an injection of fondaparinux 2.5mg in 0.5ml of saline for injection will be administered subcutaneously daily for 7 days commencing within 24 hours of onset of severe sepsis.
For blinding purposes, a continuous infusion of normal saline will also be required at the same time as the control arm.
Duration of the study is 7 days in both arms.</interventions>
    <comparator>UFH: 500 international units per hour will run continuously for 7 days commencing within 24 hours of the onset of severe sepsis. For blinding purposes, a single daily dose of subcutaneous normal saline 0.5ml will also be required.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Survivial from severe sepsis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 28 days after randmisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All cause mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 28 days after randmisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Death from all causes</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 90 days after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Death in Intensive Care Unit (ICU) </outcome>
      <timepoint>28 days after randomisation and at hospital discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ICU and hospital length of stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>Whilst in ICU and hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The need for and duration of organ support(inotropic/vassopressor/mechanical ventilation) measured daily whilst in ICU.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured daily whilst an inpatient in ICU</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events related to drug safety, particularly bleeding episodes, monitored daily.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored daily till death or 90 days post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Diagnosis of severe sepsis 2. Patients able commence study treatment within  24 hours of fulfilling inclusion criteria. 3. Informed consent obtained from the patient or next of kin/legal surrogate.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patient is receiving continued full anticoagulation treatment for any other reason with either unfractionated heparin (UFH) or coumarin agents2. Patients with contra-indication to low dose UFH or fondaparinux including intracranial haemorrhage, active bleeding or heparin induced thrombocytopaenia(HIT) in the past 3 months.3. Patients with prior adverse reaction to UFH or fondaparinux4. Patients with organ dysfunction due to sepsis present for more than 24 hours5. Patients not for full active treatment, except presence of DNR order.6. Patients not expected to survive 28 days due to underlying or comorbid condition.7. Patient is moribund with death or brain death expected within 24 hours.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone via a computerised interactive voice response system.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by a computer  software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Allocation is concealed by blinding clinicians and patients (double-blind). Pharmacist outside the treatment team remains unblinded. The study drug will be administered by the ICU nurses according to the written protocol.The assessment of outcome is the application of objective numerical criteria to the clinical results in the daily clinical record maintained by the hospital staff.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Bio-equivalence</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/06/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/11/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/03/2008</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>7</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Megan S Robertson</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Intensive Care Unit
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan Street Parville Victoria 3050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian and New Zealand Intensive Care Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>level 2, 10 Ievers Terrace Carlton, Victoria 3053</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof J Cade</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Intensive Care Unit
The Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan Street Parville Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In Australia and New Zealand, around 5000 patients are admitted to Intensive Care Units (ICU) annually with severe infection (sepsis). Despite aggressive treatment, around 35% of these patients will not survive, making severe sepsis the most common non-cardiac cause of death in ICU patients.  Even surviving patients often suffer a period of multiple organ failure.  Most patients admitted to ICU receive heparin injections to prevent the formation of blood clots in the leg veins which can travel to the lungs, causing major breathing difficulties.  Traditionally, the agent most commonly given to prevent blood clots was unfractionated heparin, but over the last decade, more purified forms of heparin (low and ultra-low molecular weight heparins) have become available. These more modern agents are replacing the traditional heparin for blood clot prevention because of reported increased effectiveness. Recent studies in animals, healthy humans and critically ill patients with severe sepsis have suggested that unfractionated heparin may have beneficial therapeutic effects in infection, additional to its action to prevent blood clots. These immune-active effects are related to molecular size and thus may be lost with the current trend to use purified heparin forms.  If this is true, then this additional benefit may be lost as we change to more purified heparin forms.  We aim to perform a pilot study to assess the feasibility of conducting a large multi-centre study to investigate whether unfractionated heparin is beneficial for patients with severe sepsis. If unfractionated heparin is shown to be beneficial in these patients, this would be a simple, cheap and widely applicable additional treatment for severe infection that could save lives world-wide, and be accessible in first to third-world environments.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/09/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Perth Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/09/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Megan S Robertson</name>
      <address>Intensive Care Unit
The Royal melbourne Hospital
VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93427441</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93428812</fax>
      <email>megan.robertson@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Megan S Robertson</name>
      <address>Intensive Care Unit
The Royal melbourne Hospital
VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93427441</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93428812</fax>
      <email>megan.robertson@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Megan S Robertson</name>
      <address>Principal Investigator no longer employed at this organisation. Contact details not available </address>
      <phone>Not available</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>not available</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>