<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82778">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/04/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000338268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Phase I trial to assess safety of autologous Human Cytomegalovirus (HCMV) -specific T cell therapy for glioblastoma multiforme (GBM)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase I trial to assess safety of autologous Human Cytomegalovirus (HCMV)-specific T cell therapy for glioblastoma multiforme</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>QIMR P1228 (issued by the Queensland Institute for Medical Research)</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>QGMB01 (issued by Queensland Institute of Medical Research)</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>glioblastoma multiforme</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Brain</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Autologous HCMV-specific T cell therapy administered by fortnightly intravenous infusion. A minimum of 3 infusions and a maximum of 4. The number of infusions will depend on the number of autologous HCMV-specific CTL generated. Between 25 to 40 x 106 cells are required per infusion.</interventions>
    <comparator>None (phase I, single group trial)</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility, to demonstrate that autologous, clinical grade HCMV-specific T cells can be generated to clinical scale from the blood of GBM patients. Expanded CTL lines will be rigorously assessed for HCMV specificity using ELISPOT and Major Histocompatibility Comples (MHC)-peptide pentamers. In addition, the phenotype (CD3, CD4, CD8, CD56 and CD16) of the CTL lines will be analysed by Fluorescence Activated Cell Sorting (FACS) analysis. These T-cell cultures will be assessed for HCMV epitope-specific reactivity on days 14-15. Functional studies of the autologous HCMV-specific CTL will be performed in an appropriate laboratory.
Specifications of release of the investigational product:
1) &gt;2 fold increase in HCMV-specific T cells as detected by intracellular cytokine assay
2) Phenotypic analysis of the culture, &gt;60% CD3+ T cells, &lt; 5% CD19+ B cells
3) Cell viability of &gt;70%
Additionally, the cultures will be tested for sterility and mycoplasma by Q-Gen, the the investigational products manufacturing facility at the QIMR, at the time of cryopreservation of the cells and the product will not be released if sterility or mycoplasma testing fails.
A certificate of manufacture will be issued by Q-Gen when the products are released from the facility.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The investigational product for each study participant will be assessed post production.  Overall assessment will be made when all study participants have received at least 1 treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>to assess the safety and tolerability of infusion of clinical grade HCMV-specific T cells into HCMV-positive GBM patients</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety and tolerability will be assessed by adverse event monitoring.  Patients will be questioned and toxicities recorded according to the International Toxicity Criteria. Assessment will occur at screening/enrolment, baseline, pre and post each of the 4 fortnightly infusions and then at 1, 2, 3, 4, 6 and 12 months after the fourth infusion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To monitor immunological and virological parameters. Laboratory assessment includes the frequency of Human Cytomegalovirus (HCMV)-specific Cytotoxic T Lymphocyte (CTL) measured by tetramer analysis, phenotyping, and Interferon (IFN) production in response to Human Cytomegalovirus (HCMV) peptide stimulation (Enzyme-linked immunosorbent spot (ELISPOT) assay or Interferon (IFN) intracellular cytokine staining). Additionally, the HCMV Deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) levels in both the Peripheral Blood Mononuclear Cells (PBMC) and plasma will be measured by real time polymerase chain reaction (PCR).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immunological and virological monitoring will occur at baseline, pre and post each of the 4 fortnightly infusions and then at 1, 2, 3, 4, 6 and 12 months after the fourth infusion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To monitor clinical response to treatment. Clinical response will be assessed by Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>MRIs will be performed at baseline, 1, 2, 3, 4, and 6 months post the last treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age 18 years or above.
2. Geographically accessible for follow up
3. Informed consent. 
4. ECOG (Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group)  performance status 0, 1, 2 or 3 
5. Life expectancy of at least 3 months
6. Previous histological diagnosis of GBM (WHO (World Health Organization)  grade IV) and radiological and/or clinical evidence of tumour progression or recurrence</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. HCMV negative serology
2. Positive serology for HIV (Human Immunodefficiency Virus)
3. Serology indicating active HBV infection or carrier status for HBV.
4. Serology indicating active HCV infection
5. Significant nonmalignant disease 
6. Psychiatric, addictive or any conditions which may compromise the ability to participate in this trial
7. Prior cancers, except those diagnosed &gt;5 years ago with no evidence of disease recurrence and clinical expectation of recurrence of &lt; 5%, or successfully treated non-melanoma skin cancer, or carcinoma in situ of the cervix.
8. Receiving immunosuppressive therapy, including corticosteroids.
9. Pregnancy, or unwilling to use adequate contraception.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>Not applicable (non randomised trial)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/11/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>7/02/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4001</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland Institute of Medical Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>300 Herston Rd Herston Queensland 4006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Atlantic Philanthropies Award</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Administered by the sponsor, the Queensland Institute of Medical Research, 300 Herston Rd, Herston, Queensland 4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Institute of Medical Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>300 Herston Rd, Herston, Queensland 4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Briz Brain and Spine</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>St Andrew's Place, Suite 297, Level 1, 33 North St, Spring Hill Queensland 4000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study looks at the safety and effectiveness of using T cell therapy targeting Human Cytomegalovirus (HCMV) in treating brain cancer (glioblastoma multiforme or GBM). 

Who is it for? 
You can join this study if you have brain cancer (glioblastoma multiforme) that has progressed or recurred since it was first diagnosed. 

Trial details 
Participants will receive treatment with killer T cells (a type of white blood cell) which have been grown in the laboratory from the participants own white blood cells. Treatment is 4 fortnightly infusions, and patients are monitored for 12 months afterwards to see if treatment is safe and to measure any reduction in tumour and amount of virus in the blood. Recent studies suggest that most gliomas carry a common virus, called human cytomegalovirus (HCMV), which is normally controlled by killer T cells. The study aims to see if killer T cells grown in the laboratory and trained to recognise and kill the virus can also kill HCMV infected gliomas. The standard first-line treatment is usually surgery, radiotherapy and a chemotherapy drug called temozolomide. If the cancer then grows back, there are no known effective treatments.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Queensland Institute of Medical Research Human Research Ethics Committee (QIMR HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>300 Herston Rd, Herston Queensland 4006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/06/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00278</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/11/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Uniting Health Care Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Toowong 4006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/06/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00374</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rajiv Khanna</name>
      <address>QIMR 300 Herston Rd Herston Brisbane Queensland 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0385</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3845 3510</fax>
      <email>Rajiv.Khanna@qimr.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katherine Matthews</name>
      <address>QIMR 300 Herston Rd Herston Brisbane Queensland 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0412</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3845 3510</fax>
      <email>Katherine.Matthews@qimr.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sashika Naidoo</name>
      <address>QIMR 300 Herston Rd Herston Brisbane Queensland 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0433</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3362 0109</fax>
      <email>Sashika.Naidoo@qimr.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Rajiv Khanna</name>
      <address>QIMR 300 Herston Rd Herston Brisbane Queensland 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3362 0385</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3845 3510</fax>
      <email>Rajiv.Khanna@qimr.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>