<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83311">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000807055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot Study of Outcome and Goal Oriented Monitoring of Asthma in General Practice</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pilot Study of Outcome and Goal Oriented Monitoring of Asthma in Adult Patients in General Practice</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>OGOMIA Pilot Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each visit is expected to take approximately 60 to 90 minutes. There are 3 visits over a period of 12 weeks with 6 weeks between visits. At each visit, participants are required to complete the Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire, the Asthma Control Questionnaire as well as a symptom score questionnaire - these questionnaires are validated. At each visit, measurement of lung function via spirometry as well as an inhaled mannitol challenge test of airway hyperresponsiveness will be performed (Australian Register of Therapeutic Goods registration number for the mannitol challenge test = AUSTR 116832). Dependent on the results of spirometry and the inhaled mannitol challenge test, variations may be made to the dose and type of inhaled asthma medications. At Visit 2 and Visit 3, subjects who have been issued with a Smartinhaler (trademark) device to measure inhaled corticosteroid use will have the data from this device downloaded to a computer. At each visit subjects will be encouraged to remain adherent to their dose of inhaled corticosteroid and to state a personal goal for their asthma treatment.</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This is a pilot study into the feasibility and acceptability of outcome and goal orientated monitoring of inhaled corticosteroids in asthma within the general practice context using airway hyperresponsiveness challenge testing. This study is not powered to detect any outcome. The study will be used as the basis for future study designs. The number of patients who participate as well as their impressions of acceptability of the process will form the primary outcome. This pilot will assess the feasibility of implementing this method of managing asthma in general practice - this will be measured by the response rates as well as qualitative data from general practitioners and practice nurses.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This pilot study has 3 visits in total each of which are 6 weeks apart.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>None</outcome>
      <timepoint>None</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Males or females aged 18 to 70 years
Confirmed diagnosis of asthma (By a general practitioner or specialist and taking inhaled corticosteroid medication)
Baseline Forced Expiratory Volume in 1 Second (FEV1) greater than 70% of predicted
Able to perform spirometry in a reproducible manner
Less than 10 pack year history of smoking in reformed smokers
Signed written informed consent to participate in the study
Females of childbearing potential must be using an effective form of contraception during the study
Residing in the community
Able to read and understand English (for questionnaires)
Ambulatory or ambulatory aided (walking frame/stick) 
Compliant with the requirements of the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects aged less than 18 years or 71 years and above
Investigators, site personnel directly affiliated with this study, and their immediate families
Severe asthma defined by an admission to an intensive care unit (ICU) in the last 6 months
Diagnosis of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) with no significant reversibility
Diagnosis of bronchiectasis or cystic fibrosis
Inpatients of a hospital or nursing home
Significant active cerebrovascular, cardiovascular, gastrointestinal (including cirrhosis), haematological, renal, or endocrine, disease
Known aortic or cerebral aneurysm
Uncontrolled hypertension (greater than 180/100mmHg)
Myocardial infarction or cerebral vascular accident in the six months prior to enrollment
Major surgery or cataract surgery within the last 6 months
Subjects requiring total nursing care or confined to a wheelchair
Significant history of drug or alcohol use
Any mental health disorder which would make participation in the clinical trial problematic
Participation in any other clinical trial or investigative drug study within the last 4 weeks prior to the screening visit
Current cigarette smoking or history of smoking within the 6 months prior to enrollment in the study
Any other medical or social condition which in the opinion of the investigator would impair the ability of the subject to participate in this study
Females who are pregnant or breast feeding
Upper or lower respiratory tract infection within the 4 weeks prior to the screening visit
Intolerance/allergy to mannitol (Aridol (trademark)) or beta agonists</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/12/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian National University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>CANBERRA ACT 0200</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>General Practice Education and Training Ltd (GPET)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 2914
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Nicholas Glasgow</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Medical School
Frank Fenner Building 42
The Australian National University
CANBERRA ACT 0200</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr John D Brannan</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Respiratory and Sleep Medicine, 11 West, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital, Missenden Road, CAMPERDOWN, NSW, 2050</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to find out whether a method of monitoring asthma with the potential to improve adherence and control is feasible and acceptable in the general practice environment. It is hoped that this study will lead to improvements in asthma control.

Prospective asthmatic patients will be invited to participate in the study and those who meet the eligibility criteria will proceed in the study. The study will involve 3 visits of no more 2 hours duration, each visit being 6 weeks apart. There will be some flexibility in that the visits can occur 2 weekdays before or after the exact scheduled date. See Attachment 1 for the study timeline.

Subjects will be seen by Dr James Turton (study coordinator) who will conduct all clinical visits. Subjects will have their lung function tested and will be tested for asthma using an inhaled mannitol challenge test (Aridol (trademark)). During clinic visits, subjects will complete questionnaires relating to asthma quality of life, control and symptoms as well as being asked about their experiences during the testing process.

In order to measure whether the subjects are using their inhaled medication as prescribed, subjects who use puffers (pressurised metered dose inhaler) will be issued with an electronic dose counter (Smartinhaler (trademark)). The Smartinhaler (trademark) device will time and date stamp each actuation  subjects will be informed of this feature of the device. Those who use an alternative dry powder inhaler type of medication will have the built-in dose counter on such devices checked at each visit.

As this is a feasibility and acceptability study, both general practitioners and practice nurses will be invited to give their impressions of the monitoring process in brief semistructured interviews.

The information obtained in the pilot study will inform the development of a formal research protocol to test this intervention.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACT Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, 11 Moore Street
Canberra City, ACT, 2601</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/10/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ETH.8/08.759</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian National University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Integrity
Research Office
Chancelry Building 10B
The Australian National University
Canberra, ACT 0200</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/10/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008/497</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/10/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr James Turton</name>
      <address>School of General Practice, Rural &amp; Indigenous Health
ANU Medical School Bldg 4, Level 2	
The Canberra Hospital Campus
PO Box 11
WODEN ACT 2606</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 2946</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 4105</fax>
      <email>james.turton@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr James Turton</name>
      <address>School of General Practice, Rural &amp; Indigenous Health
ANU Medical School Bldg 4, Level 2	
The Canberra Hospital Campus
PO Box 11
WODEN ACT 2606</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 2946</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 4105</fax>
      <email>james.turton@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr James Turton</name>
      <address>School of General Practice, Rural &amp; Indigenous Health
ANU Medical School Bldg 4, Level 2	
The Canberra Hospital Campus
PO Box 11
WODEN ACT 2606</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 2946</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 4105</fax>
      <email>james.turton@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>