<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370959">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001026415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigating the effects of a micronutrient formula on insomnia in teachers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigating the effects of a micronutrient formula on insomnia in teachers: a multiple-baseline design</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Insomnia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention is supplementation with a micronutrient formula. All participants will receive the micronutrient formula for 8 weeks. The brand name of the micronutrient formula is EMPowerplus (EMP+). The micronutrient formula will be taken in capsule form, at a dose of 8 capsules per day (two equal doses of 4), during the 8 week intervention phase. Adherence to taking the capsules will be monitored through face to face meetings with the participant and researcher where participants will bring their capsules in, and pills will be counted by the researcher.
The ingredients contained in an 8 capsule dose are as follows: Vitamin A (as retinal palmitate) 3072 IU, Vitamin C (as ascorbic acid) 320mg, Vitamin D (as cholecalciferol) 768 IU, Vitamin E (as d-alpha tocopheryl succinate) 192 IU, Thiamin (as thiamin mononitrate) 9.6 mg, Riboflavin 7.2 mg, Niacin (as niacin amide) 48 mg, Vitamin B6 (as pyridoxine hydrochloride) 19.2 mg, Folic acid 768 mcg, Vitamin B12 (as methylcobalamin) 480mcg, Biotin 576 mpg, Pantothenic acid (as calcium pantothenate) 11.52 mg, Calcium (as chelate) 704 mg, Iron (as chelate) 7.328 mg, Phosphorus (as chelate) 448 mg, Iodine (from Pacific kelp) 108.8 mcg, Magnesium (as chelate) 320 mg, Zinc (as chelate) 25.6 mg, Selenium (as chelate) 108.8 mcg, Copper (as chelate) 3.84 mg, Manganese (as chelate) 5.12 mg, Chromium (as chelate) 332.8 mcg, Molybdenum (as chelate) 76.8 msg, Potassium (as chelate) 128 mg.


 </interventions>
    <comparator>Intervention is compared to baseline and placebo phases during which measurements are taken. All participants will undergo a 1 week baseline phase. Participants will then be randomly assigned to different placebo lengths of 5, 9, or 14 days, before they enter the micronutrient phase. 
The ingredients contained in an 8 capsule dose of placebo are as follows: Fiber Acacia Gum 2400mg, Maltodextrin 3167.2mg, Cocoa Powder 32mg, Riboflavin Powder 0.8mg.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Pittsburgh Insomnia Rating Scale-20 (PIRS-20) - a 20 item self-report instrument designed to assess severity of insomnia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome 1 completed at weeks 4 and 10 of the micronutrient phase and at follow-up  3 months post end of the micronutrient phase. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Expanded Consensus Sleep Diary for Morning (CSD-M) - collects data about sleep each morning for the previous night, including sleep onset latency, number of awakenings, and sleep efficiency. </outcome>
      <timepoint>To be completed daily from the start of study until end of intervention phase. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Depression, Anxiety, and Stress Scale - 21 (DASS-21) will also be completed during the study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will complete the DASS-21 at the start and end of baseline, as well as during the placebo phases (time points 5, 9, and 14 days), and biweekly once the micronutrient phase has begun until the end of the intervention, and then at 3 month follow up.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maslach Burnout Inventory Educators Survey (MBI-ES) - The MBI-ES will also be completed during the study to assess the two core burnout dimensions of emotional exhaustion and cynicism.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will complete the MBI-ES once at the beginning of baseline and once at the end of intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must be teachers 18 years or over working in earthquake affected schools, and must be registered and have at least 2 years experience working full time. They must meet the criteria of 'insomnia' according to the Pittsburgh Insomnia Symptom Questionnaire which they complete during the screening process, and have scores in the 'moderate' or 'severe' range for insomnia symptoms on the Pittsburgh Insomnia Rating Scale -20.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants must not be taking psychotropic medications (e.g., antidepressants, anxiolytics) or prescribed sleep medications. They must not be pregnant or breastfeeding, or intend to attempt to conceive in the near future, and must not have a child 2 years or under. They must not have sleep apnoea. They will be asked to not take any other products for assisting with sleep during the course of the trial. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation to the three baseline groups is randomised. The randomisation will be done using a computer programme, and a research assistant other than the researcher will place each participants baseline allocation number into a sealed opaque envelope to conceal it from the researcher and participant.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation using a randomisation table using computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Multiple Baseline Design</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/09/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>9/10/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>15</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>17</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>25/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Canterbury</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Psychology
University of Canerbury
Private Bag 4800
Ilam 8140
Christchurch</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Canterbury - The cost of the study are coming from research grants allocated for a Master's project through the university</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 4800
Ilam 8140
Christchurch</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Neville Blampied</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Psychology
University of Canerbury
Private Bag 4800
Ilam 8140
Christchurch</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Julia Rucklidge</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Psychology
University of Canerbury
Private Bag 4800
Ilam 8140
Christchurch</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Professor Kathleen Liberty</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>College of Education,
Health and Human Development
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800
Ilam 8041
Christchurch</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to look at the effect that a micronutrient formula (vitamins and minerals) has on insomnia in teachers working in earthquake affected schools. The null-hypothesis that intervention with micronutrients does not alleviate the symptoms of sleep difficulties will be tested. The alternative hypothesis is that the intervention will alleviate the symptoms of insomnia Participants in this study are teachers working in earthquake affected schools, therefore they are working in a stressful environment. Previous research has shown that these nutrients can lower levels of anxiety and stress. Such symptoms are often related to insomnia and therefore a reduction in these symptoms may lead to a reduction in sleep difficulties in teachers. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Canterbury Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Committee, 
University of Canterbury 
Private Bag 4800
Christchurch 8140 
New Zealand</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Alison Carley</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
University of Canterbury
Private Bag 4800
Christchurch 8140
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 27 3754496</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.carley@pg.canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Neville Blampied</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
University of Canerbury
Private Bag 4800
Ilam 8140
Christchurch</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3642987 ext6199</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>neville.blampied@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Neville Blampied</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
University of Canerbury
Private Bag 4800
Ilam 8140
Christchurch</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3642987 ext6199</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>neville.blampied@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>