<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367377">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/11/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/12/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001282673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving Wellness: A randomised controlled trial comparing the Mindfulness eHealth and Physical Activity eHealth programs.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing the Mindfulness eHealth and Physical Activity eHealth programs on wellness outcomes in adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Well being in adults</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A randomized controlled trial will be employed to investigate the effectiveness of the Mindfulness eHealth program and the Physical Activity eHealth program in comparison to a delayed access (8 weeks) wait control group as a means to increase wellbeing. People visiting the Wellbeing study website, in response to advertisements or through self interest, will be informed of the availability of the study and invited to register their interest. Following completion of the pre-intervention assessments, people taking part in the study will be randomly allocated to one of the three groups above. 

The Mindfulness eHealth program consists of three weekly online modules designed to help an individual become more mindful or more aware of moment-to-moment experiences (e.g., thoughts, feelings, images, sensations). The Physical Activity eHealth program consists of three weekly online modules designed to increase physical activity, through increased awareness regarding the benefits, understanding the barriers to physical activity. The online modules from both programs will take approximately 15 minutes to complete each week, as well as some offline activities (e.g., engaging in a brief physical activity, practicing mindfulness). All participants are asked to answer questions about how they are feeling and what they have been doing via the secure website and a mobile app survey form. All participants will also wear the BASIS wrist watch continuously, which is just like a normal watch but it also automatically tracks the number of steps taken and their sleep (e.g., total time asleep, number of interruptions, quality of sleep) over the first 7 weeks of the study. Participants will also receive emails (e.g., when to complete post questionnaires) to help keep them on track. 

Participants allocated to the immediate start intervention groups (Mindfulness or Physical Activity eHealth) will complete online questionnaires via a secure website at pre-intervention (Week 0), during-intervention, post-intervention (Week 4), 4 weeks post intervention (Week 8) and at a three month follow-up (Week 16). 

The delayed start wait group will be provided access to their choice of either the Physical Activity eHealth or Mindfulness eHealth program following the Week 8 assessment phase. Therefore participants allocated to the delayed start wait group will complete pre-intervention (Week 0), during-wait intervention, post-wait intervention (Week 4), 4 weeks post-wait intervention (Week 8) and a post intervention assessment once they have completed a ehealth program (Week 12). 

All participants will also be asked to meet with the researchers on two occasions (Week 0 and Week 8) to undertake three brief computerised cognitive tests (15 minutes), have their resting heart rate variability measured (10 minutes) and to provide a salivary cortisol and blood sample.</interventions>
    <comparator>Mindfulness eHealth Intervention vs Physical Activity eHealth Intervention vs Wait list control.

The wait list control condition will receive access to the intervention of their choice (mindfulness or physical activity) after the completion of the 1 month follow-up assessments.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression symptoms using the depression scale of the DASS-21 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Main analysis - Pre-intervention, during intervention (Week 2 and 3), post intervention and at the 1 month follow up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety symptoms using the anxiety scale of the DASS-21 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Main analysis - Pre-intervention, during intervention (Week 2, Week 3), post intervention and 1 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stress symptoms using the stress scale of the DASS-21 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Main analysis - Pre-intervention, during intervention (Week 2, Week 3), post intervention and 1 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotional Regulation using self report measures (Difficulties in Emotional Regulation Scale; Attention and Action Questionnaire; Affective Style Questionnaire) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Main analysis - Pre-intervention, post intervention and 1 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological Distress using the Kessler-6</outcome>
      <timepoint>Main analysis - Pre-intervention, post intervention and 1 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived Stress using the Perceived Stress Scale and as a biomarker of stress, cortisol sampling (drool method) will be used</outcome>
      <timepoint>Perceived Stress - Pre-intervention, post intervention and 1 month follow-up (main analysis)
and cortisol at pre-intervention and the 1 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wellbeing using self report measures (Mental Health Continuum-Short Form; Revised  Life Orientation Test; Mindfulness Attention Awareness Scale; International Physical Activity Questionnaire  Short Form; Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Main analysis - Pre-intervention, post intervention and 1 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physiological functioning using resting heart rate variability. HRV will be measured using the Polar RS800CX HRV device. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention and the 1 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Personality traits using the Ten Item Personality Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive changes using the computerised Stroop Test, Go/No Go and Trail Making Tests</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention and at the 1 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biometric data from the BASIS wrist watch (e.g., sleep quality, physical activity (number of steps)).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuously from intervention start until the 1 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Real time mood changes via the Affective mobile app survey. Participants will receive random alerts during the day, asking them to complete a brief mobile app survey addressing how they are feeling/what they are doing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Alerts are sent from intervention start to the 1 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intervention Credibility as measured by the Treatment Credibility Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intervention Satisfaction as measured by the Intervention Satisfaction Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood bio-markers of health: Health changes caused by the intervention will be measured in context with the latest genome-wide microarrays and validated (by quantitative PCR or sequencing) to identify blood biomarkers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention and the 1 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>18 years of age or older, have access to the internet, an internet-connected mobile phone, and be able to attend two assessment sessions onsite.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Given the nature of the assessments, self-monitoring and the inclusion of the physical activity intervention, those meeting the following criteria would not be able to participate: pregnant, having a documented life threatening illness (e.g., cancer) or traumatic brain injury, cardiovascular disease, debilitating physical mobility issues or a current untreated severe (psychotic) mental illness. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be asked to consent and register their interest online via the Wellness site. Participants will then be contacted and an appointment made to meet with one of the researchers face to face. Following the completion of all of the pre-assessment measures, the participant will be informed about what condition they have been randomly allocated to (and details provided regarding intervention URL address for those receiving immediate access to one of the two eHealth programs). Participants will be randomly allocated using a block design method.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation via block design method (1,2,3)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Repeated measures ANOVA/multilevel modeling. 

Previous research has reported medium effects for the primary measures of interest (depression, anxiety and stress symptoms). Therefore, assuming a small-medium effect (i.e. GPower f(v) test = 0.35), significance set at 5% (p = .05), power at 80%, a sample of 52 will be required to demonstrate statistical significance. However allowing for a 40% attrition rate, we will be required to recruit a total of N = 87 participants or n = 29 in each group.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/12/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/01/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/02/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>22/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>79</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>14/02/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Federation Universtiy</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive, Mt Helen Campus, 3350 Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Federation University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University Drive, Mt Helen Campus, 3350 Victoria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A randomised controlled trial will be employed to investigate the effectiveness of the Mindfulness eHealth program and the Physical Activity eHealth program in comparison to a delayed access (8 weeks) wait control group as a means to increase wellbeing. People visiting the Wellbeing study website, in response to advertisements or through self interest, will be informed of the availability of the study and invited to participate. Following completion of the pre-intervention assessments, people taking part in the study will be randomly allocated to one of the three groups above.

Participants allocated to the immediate start intervention groups (Mindfulness or Physical Activity eHealth) will complete online questionnaires at pre-intervention (Week 0), during-intervention, post-intervention (Week 4), 4 weeks post intervention (Week 8) and at a three month follow-up (Week 16).

The delayed start wait group will be provided access to their choice of either the Physical Activity eHealth or Mindfulness eHealth program following the Week 8 assessment phase. Therefore participants allocated to the delayed start wait group will complete pre-intervention (Week 0), during-wait intervention, post-wait intervention (Week 4), 4 weeks post-wait intervention (Week 8) and a post intervention assessment once they have completed a ehealth program (Week 12).

All participants will also be asked to meet with the researchers on two occasions (Week 0 and Week 8) to undertake three brief computerised cognitive tests (15 minutes), have their resting heart rate variability measured (10 minutes) and to provide a salivary cortisol and blood sample. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://www.wellness.fedehealth.org.au/ </trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Federation University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University Drive, Mt Helen Campus, 3350 Victoria.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/08/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>A14-095</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Britt Klein</name>
      <address>Federation University,
University Drive, Mt Helen Campus, 3350 Victoria</address>
      <phone>61 03  5327 6717</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.klein@federation.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Britt Klein</name>
      <address>Federation University,
University Drive, Mt Helen Campus, 3350 Victoria</address>
      <phone>61 03 5327 6717</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.klein@federation.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Britt Klein</name>
      <address>Federation University,
University Drive, Mt Helen Campus, 3350 Victoria</address>
      <phone>61 03  5327 6717</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.klein@federation.edu.aui</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Britt Klein</name>
      <address>Federation University,
University Drive, Mt Helen Campus, 3350 Victoria.</address>
      <phone>61 03 5327 6717</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.klein@federation.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>