<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83006">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/07/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/08/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000390381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Home based rehabilitation to reduce falls and disability in Parkinson's disease (PD)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Home based rehabilitation to reduce falls in people with Parkinson's disease (PD): a randomised controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will participate in a 6 week home-based rehabilitation program comprising a once weekly 60 minute individual program delivered by a trained therapist, together with a once weekly 60 minute self-directed home exercise program. The intervention is designed to provide particpants with an integrated "package" of evidence based therapy, including movement strategy training, strengthening (progressive resisted exercise) and falls education. 
At the initial home visit, the therapist will conduct a once-off environmental analysis, observe functional mobility and performance of activities of daily living within the participant's home environment in order to identify any falls risk factors that may be present. This assessment will take approximately 20 minutes and the information obtained will allow the therapist to tailor the falls education component of the home based rehabilitation program to the individual participant's needs. The falls prevention education component of the intervention will be provided to the participant and their care-giver during each of the weekly home visits.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will participate in a 6 week home-based "life skills" program comprising a once weekly 60 minute individual program delivered by a trained therapist, together with a once weekly self-directed life skills home program. The life skills program is designed to provide education to people with Parkinson's disease, and will cover a range of topics including medication, hand writing, diet, stress management, fatigue management and self-care activities such as grooming and eating. The life skills program will include any content related to falls, physical exercise or gait rehabilitation.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls frequency for the 12 month period immediately following the home-based rehabilitation program. Falls will be recorded on a calendar by each participant and the accuracy of this information will be verified during a phone call from the researchers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The falls calendar will be returned to the researchers monthly for the 12 months following the rehabilitation program.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motor disability: Measured on the motor section of the Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 6 weeks (immediately post therapy) and 12 months post therapy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global disability: Measured as the total score on the Unified Parkinson's Disease Rating Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 6 weeks (immediately post therapy) and 12 months post therapy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life: Measured by the PDQ39 (Parkinson's Disease Questionnaire) and the EuroQol-5D</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 6 weeks (immediately post therapy) and 12 months post therapy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Economic data: Medicare and hospitalisation costs over the 12 month study period</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post therapy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Diagnosis of idiopathic Parkinson's disease (confirmed by a neurologist)
2. Living in the community
3. Classified on the Hoehn &amp; Yahr scale as stage I-IV</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) Suffer from a cardiopulmonary, musculoskeletal, endocrine or other medical condition that prevents safe participation in a home exercise program (as determined by the referring neurologist or medical practitioner)
(3) Participant or their care-giver/ family are unwilling to have therapy and assessments in their home
(4) Unable to communicate in English (interpreters are not available)
(5) Have dementia, score &lt; 24 on the Mini Mental State Examination or are unable to provide informed consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants may be recruited from a variety of sources; however the primary source will be referral from 3 neurologists who are associated inevstigators in the trial.
Each participant will be required to have an initial screening by one of the researchers to ensure they meet the eligibility criteria. Participants are then asked to sign a form to provide consent for the researchers to contact the treating neurologist or GP to confirm the diagnosis of Parkinson disease and safety for participation in the exercise program.
Randomised group allocation for each participant will be performed by an independent researcher from a different organisation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be stratified; participants recruited by each neurologist will be randomised separately into control or experimental groups. Concealed randomisation will be prepared using a computer generated random number sequence. Random permuted blocks will be used to ensure that after every block of participants the control and experimental groups have equal numbers. Those involved in recruitment will be blinded to the random sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/04/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>20/12/2011</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>28/12/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>143</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Health Exercise and Sports Medicine
School of Physiotherapy
The University of Melbourne
Victoria 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421 Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>La Trobe University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Bundoora, Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>La Trobe University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Physiotherapy
La Trobe University
Bunddora
Victoria 3086</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Falls and movement disorders are both common and disabling in people with idiopathic Parkinson's disease (PD), which affects more than 80,000 Australians. Whereas one-third of community dwelling elders fall every year, the incidence in people with PD is as high as 50-68%.  Many people with PD experience repeated falls and over 25% sustain a hip fracture (as the result of falling) within 10 years of diagnosis. Along with balance impairment, movements progressively become slower and scaled down in size. Anti-PD medications initially provide effective symptomatic relief although movement disorders and postural instability again become problematic with disease progression. Preliminary trials have shown that hospital based movement rehabilitation programs are an effective adjunct to pharamacological therapy in the short term. Nevertheless hospital inpatient and outpatient programs are costly and can be inconvenient for some people who do not have transport. This randomised controlled trial will compare the outcomes of home based integrated rehabilitation with a control intervention in a sample of 180 people with PD. Participants in the treatment group will receive a 6 week home-based rehabilitation program comprising movement strategy training, progressive strengthening and education regarding falls and mobility, delivered by an experienced physiotherapist. The control group will receive a life-skills home program delivered by an allied health professional (physiotherapist, PD nurse or occupational therapist). The life-skills program will provide participants with education on relevant topics including PD pathology, medications and relaxation techniques, without falls education, strategies or exercises. Participants will undertake all assessments and interventions associated with this trial within their own home.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Morris, M.E., et al., Protocol for a home-based integrated physical therapy program to reduce falls and improve mobility in people with Parkinson's disease. BMC Neurology, 2012. 12: p. 54.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee
The University of Melbourne
Victoria 3010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/05/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC 0824406</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Meg Morris</name>
      <address>School Allied Health, Level 5 HS3
La Trobe University
Plenty Road
Bundoora
3086
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94680100</phone>
      <fax>+6194677186</fax>
      <email>meg.morris@healthscope.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Meg Morris</name>
      <address>School Allied Health, Level 5 HS3
La Trobe University
Plenty Road
Bundoora
3086
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61394680100</phone>
      <fax>+61394677186</fax>
      <email>meg.morris@healthscope.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Meg Morris</name>
      <address>School Allied Health La Trobe University &amp; Healthscope</address>
      <phone>+61 394680100</phone>
      <fax>+6194677186</fax>
      <email>meg.morris@healthscope.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Meg E. Morris</name>
      <address>School Allied Health, Level 5 HS3
La Trobe University
Plenty Road
Bundoora
3086
Victoria
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61394791111</phone>
      <fax>+61394677186</fax>
      <email>meg.morris@healthscope.com.au;m.morris@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>