<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365474">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001380785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study to assess the visual performance of prototype contact lenses.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective, participant-masked, bilateral wear, crossover clinical trial to assess visual performance of multiple prototype contact lens designs compared to commercial contact lenses in presbyopes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Presbyopia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The contact lenses being studied are prototype soft contact lenses made from Etafilcon A material. The lenses differ only in their power profile - all are made from the same material. 

Participants will test up to 25 pairs of lenses with a minimum overnight wash-out period between each pair. Ideally, all participants would test all 25 pairs, however as they are able to withdraw at any time, the number of lenses tested is essentially determined by the participant.

Lenses will be inserted bilaterally on the participant by the investigating optometrist, and worn for a maximum of 1.5 hours.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will test up to 4 commercially available contact lenses as controls (minimum 2) with a minimum overnight wash-out period between each pair. Ideally all participants would test all 4 controls, but as they are able to withdraw at any time, some participants may not test all controls.

The control lenses are AirOptix Aqua single vision, AirOptix Aqua Multifocal, Proclear Multifocal and Acuvue Oasys for Presbyopia. Lenses will be inserted bilaterally on the participant by the investigating optometrist, and worn for a maximum of 1.5 hours.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the visual performance of prototype contact lenses compared to commercial equivalents.

Objective measurements of high contrast visual acuity, low contrast visual acuity and contrast sensitivity will be assessed for each pair of lenses with a computerised LogMAR chart. Near visual acuity will be assessed with MNRead Acuity chart.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1.5 hours of inserting each lens design.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective responses of participants wearing the prototype contact lenses.

Subjective ratings of clarity, ghosting, overall vision satisfaction and comfort will be assessed for each pair of lenses with a questionnaire based on a 1-10 scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1.5 hours of inserting each lens design.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants' willingness to purchase the lenses, identified in a questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1.5 hours of inserting each lens design</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Positive and negative aspects of each prototype lens design, identified in a questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1.5 hours of inserting each lens design.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent.
Be at least 40 years old, with presbyopia (reading add of 1 Dioptre or more).
Willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the Investigator.
Have ocular health findings considered to be normal and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses.
Is correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses.
Be experienced or inexperienced at wearing contact lenses.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including infection or disease) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses.
Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves disease, and auto immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjogrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosus.  Conditions such as systemic hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants.
Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication at enrolment and/or during the clinical trial.
Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings / are known to affect a participants ocular health / physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse or beneficial manner at enrolment and/or during the clinical trial. 
NB: Systemic antihistamines are allowed on an as needed basis, provided they are not used prophylactically during the trial and at least 24 hours before the clinical trial product is used.
Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial.
Previous corneal refractive surgery.
Contraindications to contact lens wear.
Known allergy or intolerance to ingredients in any of the clinical trial products.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be screened for general clinical trial suitability by way of a routine eye examination which includes refraction, visual acuity and general eye health.  Informed consent will be obtained prior to any clinical trial procedures. 

At each scheduled lens fitting visit, participants will be allocated one pair of contact lenses to correct their refractive error. Initially the single vision control lens will be tested. For the remaining scheduled visits, one pair of multifocal control or prototype contact lenses will be allocated for each lens fitting/assessment visit.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A minimum of 10 participants are required in order to demonstrate a statistically significant paired difference between the control lenses and each iteration in visual acuity of 0.1 +/-0.1 logMAR units at the 5% level of significance and 80% power. The minimum sample size is a requirement at each stage of the cross over trial. The sample size is not adjusted for drop outs due to the short nature of each stage.

Statistical analysis is planned to commence on completion of trial monitoring and the submission of the data analysis request form. Any interim analysis will be conducted as described in this section, unless a documented request is received from the Sponsor and approved by the trial PI.

Data stored in relational databases will be imported into PASW / SAS / STATA software for statistical purposes. Data will be investigated for quality using range checks and frequency distribution. Underlying distributions of variables will be tested. In general, variables measured on an interval scale with a sufficiently large sample size will be considered to follow a normal distribution. Outputs from the statistical analysis such as statistical tables will be copied over to Excel. Graphs will generally not be created from the statistical software. All statistical results will be reported in Excel format. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>23/07/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>119</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>23/07/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2052 - Unsw Sydney</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Ravi Bakaraju</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Brien Holden Vision Institute
Level 5, North Wing,
Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street
UNSW Sydney  NSW  2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, North Wing,
Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street
UNSW Sydney  NSW  2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To assess the visual performance of multiple prototype soft contact lens designs.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Sha J, et al. Short-term visual performance of soft multifocal contact lenses for presbyopia. Arq Bras Oftalmol 2016;79:73-77.
Tilia D, et al. Short-Term Visual Performance of Novel Extended Depth-of-Focus Contact Lenses. Optom Vis Sci 2016;93:435-444.
Tilia D, et al. Short-term comparison between extended depth-of-focus prototype contact lenses and a commercially-available center-near multifocal. Journal of Optometry 2016; In Press, Corrected Proof.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road, Eastwood
South Australia 5063 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012-07-967</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Pauline Xu</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute
Level 5, North Wing,
Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street
UNSW Sydney  NSW  2052</address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.xu@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Pauline Xu</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute
Level 5, North Wing,
Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street
UNSW Sydney  NSW  2052</address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.xu@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Pauline Xu</name>
      <address>Brien Holden Vision Institute
Level 5, North Wing,
Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker Street
UNSW Sydney  NSW  2052</address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.xu@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>