<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364789">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001023741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving recognition of heart failure using lung ultrasound</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Multicentre randomised controlled trial incorporating bedside lung ultrasound into the diagnosis of congestive cardiac failure in breathless older patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>LUS+2014</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Using bedside ultrasound to improve the recognition of heart failure in the emergency department</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Breathless patients over 60 years old presenting to an emergency department will receive bedside lung ultrasound as part of the assessment phase of the breathlessness.

All participants in the trial will receive the standard emergency work-up for breathless.

The intervention group will also receive a bedside lung ultrasound.

The scan protocol for bedside lung ultrasound takes approximately 2 minutes to complete and involves taking 4 longitudinal images in both lungs.

The scan will be interpreted as demonstrating a 'wet' lung - consistent with pulmonary oedema - or a 'dry' lung which is inconsistent with pulmonary oedema.</interventions>
    <comparator>The patient will receive standard work-up for the investigation of the breathless patient.  This can vary depending on the provisional diagnosis following history and examination, but includes arterial blood gas, chest Xray or CT pulmonary angiogram.  Bedside lung ultrasound is not typically performed in the assessment phase currently.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The difference in diagnostic accuracy between the lung ultrasound augmented assessment and conventional assessment of breathlessness in the emergency department.

The interpretation of the lung ultrasound as wet (pulmonary oedema) or dry (not pulmonary oedema) will be compared to the CXR report and final diagnosis to examine diagnostic accuracy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The data to evaluate this time point will be collected by a research assistant within a week of the patient's presentation, once a diagnosis for the breathlessness is available.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sensitivity and specificity of lung ultrasound for the differentiation of breathlessness.

Again, the interpretation of the lung ultrasound as wet (pulmonary oedema) or dry (not pulmonary oedema) will be compared to the CXR report and final diagnosis to examine diagnostic accuracy.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The data to evaluate this time point will be collected by a research assistant within a week of the patient's presentation, once a diagnosis for the breathlessness is available.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital length of stay will be obtainable from the electonic record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be obtained by a research assistant within one week of the patient's discharge from hospital.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of cases where the Chest Xray contributed extra information above that contributed by the Lung US</outcome>
      <timepoint>The data to evaluate this time point will be collected by a research assistant within a week of the patient's presentation, once a diagnosis for the breathlessness is available.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Breathless patients presenting to the emergency department who are over 60 years old.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The patient is excluded if they are requiring active airway support, if they were involved in trauma or if there are any contagious lesion in the areas for scanning (eg shingles)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>If the patient meets the inclusion criteria at triage, they are identified by the triage nurse and their details are placed in a screening logbook with the senior medical officer (SMO) being notified.  The SMO will approach the patient or proxy and obtain informed consent to participate in the trial.  If consenting the patient will be allocated to a registrar who has been taught the trial protocol who will select a randomisation envelope.  If the patient is randomised to the intervention group, the registrar performs a lung scan early in the course of the episode of care and writes his or her impression of the scan in the trial book and in the patients notes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation envelopes contain 2 identical stickers with a trial code number and selection of control or intervention eg IP LUS 34 control.  Randomisation will be determined using  a simple randomisation table from a statistics book.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Demographic data will be used in non identifiable form to describe summary statistics of the population studied.
The data will be compared using qualitative statistical methods to give test statistics (diagnostic accuracy, sensitivity and specificity, positive and negative predictive values) for the use of basic bedside lung ultrasound by
inexperienced practitioners in the investigation of shortness of breath.

Sub group analysis will include the proportion of cases in which the diagnosis changed between lung ultrasound
result and chest xray will be calculated, and the proportion of cases where chest xray did not influence the diagnosis,
or where it appears to have adversely affected the diagnosis.
Multilinear regression analysis will be used to see if, when accounting for age, sex and severity of symptoms,
whether an incorrect diagnosis makes a significant effect on the length of stay in hospital.

Reanalysis of the deidentified scan sets may be used to test other diagnostic cut points that have been suggested
by other research groups.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/09/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Ipswich Hospital - Ipswich</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland Emergency Medicine Research Fund</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suite 5B, The Terrace Suites, 19 Lang Parade, Milton Qld 4064</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Emergency Medicine Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 5B, The Terrace Suites, 19 Lang Parade, Milton Qld 4064</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NONE</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to improve patient care by putting evidence into practice.  Secondary gains include improving ultrasound practices, establishing robust predictive values,and eventually reducing certain unnecessary xrays. This technique, once validated, will be of particular use in regional Australia.

Many older persons present to the emergency department complaining of breathlessness. This can be an important
forewarning of heart failure, but is present in many conditions. In most cases, several tests are carried out to identify those patients with heart failure. Despite these investigations, heart failure is initially misdiagnosed in up to one quarter of patients. The interpretation of chest xray by treating physicians is notoriously fallible.

Many European hospitals use bedside lung ultrasound(LUS) to improve their recognition of heart failure, but as the
European practice model is significantly different from the Australian, the practice is not common here. The method
is cheap, rapid, safe, readily available and causes trivial interference to current management.

Our pilot study has already tested the lung ultrasound method in parallel with conventional investigation, without
allowing it to influence management. Now we aim to incorporate it within the testing paradigm, by unblinding the
treating doctor.

We wish to see if the augmented assessment paradigm has a superior diagnostic accuracy to the conventional assessment paradigm. We will start by teaching a cohort of emergency trainee doctors to perform the test. Older patient who present with breathlessness to the ED will be randomised to either conventional or augmented investigation paradigm, track the emergency doctor's diagnosis after lung scan and again after full workup, and then compare the accuracy of these diagnosed in each group against a reference standard of delayed expert chart audit (which includes all prior and subsequent tests and course of disease).

The primary endpoint is the difference in diagnostic accuracy between the LUS augmented investigation and the
conventional investigation of breathlessness in the emergency department. Secondary endpoints are the sensitivity and specificity of LUS for differentiation of breathlessness. Exploratory endpoints will be the difference in length of stay in hospital between the groups, and the proportion of cases where chest xray contributed extra informationabove that contributed by the LUS.


</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Is currently under construction, but is intended to be a facebook page.</trialwebsite>
    <publication>It is intended to publish several papers from this research, in emergency medicine journals and via open access
publishing.Findings will be presented at local,national and international meetings. Information will be used to
improve teaching at workshops.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Health Service District HREC (EC00167)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/QPAH/285</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kylie Baker</name>
      <address>Ipswich General Hospital Emergency Department
Chelmsford Ave
Ipswich Qld 4305</address>
      <phone>+617 38101111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kyliebaker888@bigpond.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kylie Baker</name>
      <address>Ipswich General Hospital Emergency Department
Chelmsford Ave
Ipswich Qld 4305</address>
      <phone>+61738101111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kyliebaker888@bigpond.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kylie Baker</name>
      <address>Ipswich General Hospital Emergency Department
Chelmsford Ave
Ipswich Qld 4305</address>
      <phone>+617 38101111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kyliebaker888@bigpond.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>