<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369773">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000102471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Water-based exercise training in people with stable coronary heart disease- Study B</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, controlled trial of water-based exercise training in people with stable coronary heart disease (Study B)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary heart disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Study B is part of a broader project investigating the effects of water-based exercise in people with coronary heart disease. This study will involve a 12 week randomised controlled trial involving participants who will be randomised into one of three groups:
*12 weeks of land-based exercise
*	12 weeks of water-based exercise
*	A control group who will maintain their usual activities for 12 weeks.

The training groups will be supervised by a health professional (majority of sessions supervised by a physiotherapist) and group training sessions (maximum of 10 participants) will be conducted three times per week, for one hour and 10 minute sessions, for 12 weeks (36 sessions total). 
The training programs will commence and conclude with 5 minutes of light aerobic activity (e.g. walking) and stretching. Moderate intensity exercises will alternate resistance (strength) and aerobic (fitness) stations. There will be 7 resistance and 8 aerobic stations lasting for 90 seconds, with 30 seconds of active recovery between exercises. Participants will build up to completing 2 circuits per session. During water-based exercise participants will be submerged to their xiphoid process (lower chest) in a heated swimming pool.
Aerobic exercises will be monitored and matched by heart rate (60-80% of a participants heart rate maximum) and rating of perceived exertion (11-14 rating on the Borg Rating of Perceived Exertion Scale). Training will commence at approximately 60% of participants VO2peak and progress to 80% over the course of the training, as individually tolerated. Water-based aerobic exercises will include jogging, quick stepping/ jumping and high knees. Land-based aerobic exercises will include cycling, treadmill jogging and recumbent cycling. 
Resistance exercises will be matched for muscle group, Borg rating (between 11-14) and quantified resistance per station. Water-based exercises will utilise custom-designed resistance equipment (paddles), developed by this research team previously. Water-based resistance exercises will include; shoulder flexion and extension, shoulder abduction and adduction, hip flexion and extension, knee flexion and extension and hip abduction. Land-based exercises will include; shoulder flexion/ extension, modified shoulder abduction/ adduction, knee extension, hamstring curls, hip flexion/ extension and hip abduction. Resistance will be provided by machines, pulleys, free weights and ankle weights and the weight lifted can be used to quantify resistance. 
Participant attendance will be recorded for each session, as will a selection of perceived exertion, heart rate and resistance measures for each session. 
 
Strength, fitness, vascular function, brain blood flow, body composition, blood profiles and elements of cognition will be assessed before and after the 12 week period. Vascular function will be assessed fortnightly during the 12 week period in a subgroup of  14 participants from each of the training groups. Participants will be invited to take part in this as they enroll chronologically, until we reach the 14 participants required. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The randomised controlled trial will compare water-based exercise to both land-based exercise (conventional treatment) and a usual activities control group</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Flow mediated dilation (FMD) of the brachial artery will be used to assess endothelial function. A 10MHz multi-frequency linear array probe attached to a high resolution ultrasound machine (T3000; Terason, Burlington, Massachusetts, USA) will record baseline images of the brachial artery for one minute. FMD will subsequently be assessed by inflating a blood pressure cuff to 200mmHg over the proximal forearm for 5 minutes. Recording of the artery will commence 30 seconds prior to cuff deflation and will continue for 3 minutes post deflation. Custom designed edge detection and tracking software will be used to analyse the images.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at baseline (week 0) and at the end of the 12 week randomised controlled trial.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cerebral blood flow, (CBF) will be assessed using transcranial doppler ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at baseline (week 0) and at the end of the 12 week randomised controlled trial.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscular strength by assessing 1 repetition maximum strength for leg press and latissimus dorsi using weights machines. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at baseline (week 0) and at the end of the 12 week randomised controlled trial.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Aerobic capacity (VO2peak) will be assessed using the Modified Chronotropic Protocol on a treadmill. Indirect calorimetry will be employed to assess the participants VO2 peak. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at baseline (week 0) and at the end of the 12 week randomised controlled trial.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index (BMI) will be calculated from weight (measured using electronic scales) and height (measured using a stadiometer) </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at baseline (week 0) and at the end of the 12 week randomised controlled trial.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vascular function- Flow Mediated Dilation (FMD) of the brachial artery (as per primary outcome) will be assessed fortnightly in a subgroup of participants using ultrasound. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Every second week throughout the 12 week intervention period in a subgroup of the training groups (14 per group)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood profiles: Assessment will include a full blood picture (baseline only), urea and electrolytes, liver function, C-reactive protein, cholesterol, triglycerides, low density lipoprotein cholesterol and high density lipoprotein cholesterol. These will be assessed externally by PathWest. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at baseline (week 0) and at the end of the 12 week randomised controlled trial.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Elements of cognition, such as reaction speed, will be assessed using specialised CogState software.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at baseline (week 0) and at the end of the 12 week randomised controlled trial.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist and hip circumference will be measured using a steel measuring tape</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at baseline (week 0) and at the end of the 12 week randomised controlled trial.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Endothelium independent vascular function of the brachial artery- A 10MHz multi-frequency linear array probe attached to a high resolution ultrasound machine (T3000; Terason, Burlington, Massachusetts, USA) will record baseline images of the brachial artery for one minute. Subsequently a 400µg sublingual dose of glyceryl trinitrate (GTN) will be administered. Imaging will recommence 3 minutes post administration for 5 minutes to ensure the peak dilation is captured. Custom designed software will be used to analyse the images. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at baseline (week 0) and at the end of the 12 week randomised controlled trial.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Stable, documented coronary heart disease and be at least 6 months following a myocardial infarction, coronary artery bypass graft or percutaneous coronary intervention
*	Have been taking stable medical therapy for the last 2 months 
*	Be able to participate in exercise training 3 days per week and organise their own transport 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Renal impairment, hepatic impairment, proteinurea or hyperuricaemia 
*	Left ventricle ejection fraction below 45%
*	Musculoskeletal or neurological condition or injury that precludes exercise training
*	Any current or recent neoplasms or cancer treatment
*	Current smokers 
*	Premenopausal females (due to the potential effects of hormonal cycle on vascular assessment) 
*Currently participating in a formal exercise program at least 3 times per week, or have done so in the last 6 weeks
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will select a sealed envelope with their allocation at the first testing session to allocate to group. </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be recruited using a rolling enrollment, as such we will be using block randomisation. Each block will contain even allocations for each group (water-based training, land based training or usual activities) for the study. This will ensure approximately even subject numbers per group for the duration of the study. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>
    </designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Fiona Stanley Hospital - Murdoch</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aims:
The aim of this project is to assess the effects of water-based exercise training in people with stable heart disease. This study is being conducted in conjunction with an acute study assessing the physiological effects of a single submerged session compared to a single session of matched intensity land-based exercise.
Justification:
Exercise is an important component of rehabilitation and preventing recurrent heart problems in people with heart disease.  However, exercise participation is sub-optimal in this population and increasing the range of exercise options for people with heart disease may increase exercise participation. For example, water-based exercise may be more appealing to people with heart disease who have other health issues, such as arthritis or obesity, which may make land-based exercise difficult or painful. Furthermore, preliminary research suggests that water-based exercise may have additional vascular and brain benefits due to the effects of water immersion on blood flow.  However, this has not previously been investigated in people with heart disease. 
Participants:
Patients who have had a heart attack or bypass surgery at least six months prior to enrolment, or documented blockages in the arteries of their heart based on the results of an angiogram (a scan of the heart) will be recruited to the study. Participants must be medically stable prior to participation and not be undertaking a formal exercise program. 
Design and methods:
 60 participants will be randomised into one of three groups for the duration of a 12 week program:
	*12 weeks of land-based exercise
*	12 weeks of water-based exercise
*	A control group who will maintain their usual activities for 12 weeks.
Strength, fitness, vascular function, brain blood flow, body composition, blood profiles and aspects of cognition will be assessed before and after the 12 week period. Vascular function will be assessed fortnightly during the 12 week period in a subgroup of participants.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee, EC00270</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Southern Integrated Research Organisation (SIRO)
Locked Bag 100, PALMYRA DC WA 6961</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>REG 15-165</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kent Street, Bentley, Perth, Western Australia, 6102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR227/2015</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Andrew Maiorana</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61433567369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.maiorana@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Anna Scheer</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61452236661</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anna.scheer@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Anna Scheer</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61452236661</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anna.scheer@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>