<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365919">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000295640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Perfectionism treatment for obsessive compulsive disorder: A randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The efficacy of cognitive behavioural therapy for perfectionism in the treatment of obsessive compulsive disorder symptoms for patients with obsessive compulsive disorder and elevated perfectionism

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1154-1322  </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obsessive Compulsive Disorder </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obsessive Compulsive Personality Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The purpose of the study is to determine whether directly targeting elevated perfectionism traits is an effective first-line therapeutic intervention in a clinical population of OCD participants, relative to a waitlist control group. The intervention is based on the transdiagnostic intervention developed by Egan, S. J., Wade, T. D., Shafran, R., &amp; Antony, M. M., Cognitive Behavioral Treatment of Perfectionism (2014). The intervention involves psycho-education, self-monitoring, behavioral experiments, cognitive restructuring and motivation work. 
Administration and duration: Group therapy sessions run by two therapists, once-weekly for 2 hours over an eight week period, plus homework exercises. Following an 8-week waitlist period, control participants receive the same intervention. </interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomly allocated to waitlist control receive the same 8-week group CBT for perfectionism intervention following their 8-week waitlist period. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine pre and post treatment obsessive compulsive disorder symptom severity as measured by the Yale-Brown Obsessive Compulsive Scale (YBOCS) whereby scores will indicate the following: 32-40 extreme; 24-31 severe; 16-23 moderate; 8-15 mild; 0-7 sub-clinical. </outcome>
      <timepoint>CBT for perfectionism treatment condition - pre-treatment, post treatment, 3 month follow up
Waitlist control - baseline, post-waitlist/pre treatment, post treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine pre and post-treatment obsessive compulsive personality disorder symptom severity as measured by the 49-item Pathological Obsessive Compulsive Personality Scale (POPS). </outcome>
      <timepoint>CBT for perfectionism treatment condition - pre-treatment, post treatment, 3 month follow up
Waitlist control - baseline, post-waitlist/pre treatment, post treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure pre and post treatment perfectionism symptom severity as measured by the 12-item Clinical Perfectionism Questionnaire (CPQ) and 35-item Frost Multidimensional Perfectionism Scale (FMPS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>CBT for perfectionism treatment condition - pre-treatment, post treatment, 3 month follow up
Waitlist control - baseline, post-waitlist/pre treatment, post treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To To measure pre and post treatment quality of life as measured by Quality of Life and Enjoyment Satisfaction Questionnaire Short Form (14-item QLES-Q), where by higher scores are indicative of a higher subjective quality of life satisfaction. </outcome>
      <timepoint>CBT for perfectionism treatment condition - pre-treatment, post treatment, 3 month follow up
Waitlist control - baseline, post-waitlist/pre treatment, post treatment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>A current primary diagnosis of OCD (as measured by Structured Clinical Interview for DSM-IV, Curtin Adult Psychology Clinic Version)
Presence of perfectionism pathology as determined by a score of 22 or higher on the concern over mistakes subscale of the FMPS
*18 years of age or above
*If on pharmacotherapy, participants will be asked to be on a stable dose for one month before the study and to stay on that dose during the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*If the individual's primary pathology is consistent with another principal diagnosis and determined to be more relevant at the time of assessment as indicated by the American Psychiatric Association (2013) 
*If undergoing concurrent psychological intervention between baseline and follow-up
*Presence of an organic mental disorder or serious active suicidal ideation as determined by the SCID-IV. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligibility and diagnostic assessments will be completed by clinical psychology trainees from Curtin University as part of their supervised clinical placements. Individuals who express interest in participating in the study will be screened via telephone to determine their eligibility to participate. If eligible, a face-to-face diagnostic assessment will take place using baseline measure and participants will be randomly allocated to groups. Whilst the trainees will have knowledge of the broad purpose of the study, they will be blind as to the exact hypotheses and expected outcomes from treatment in order to reduce experimental bias. A registered psychologist supervisor external to the study with experience in the delivery of CBT will randomly select and view group therapy sessions during supervision with therapists to confirm that treatment protocol is adhered to.</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomization with a maximum of 8 participants per condition (CBT for perfectionism or waitlist control) is used to allocate participants. Participants randomised to waitlist will be allocated to the next available treatment group as practicable in the study. An independent clinician will conduct the randomisation process to minimise selection bias. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>An initial G*Power (3.1) statistical calculation used to calculate the minimum power required to detect a small to moderate (f = .10 - .25) group x time interaction in this study (power = 0.8, two-tailed alpha = .05), suggested that a total of 102 participants would be required, equating to 34 participants, for each of the three conditions. However, given the difficulties experienced with recruitment and participant attrition, this has been modified. A total of 11 participants have completed the intervention (inclusive of CBT for perfectionism and wait-list). Given the smaller sample size, Reliable change (RC) and Clinically Significant Change analyses will be used to assess the treatment outcomes of this study,

The pre-post reliable change (RC) score will be interpreted as the degree to which participants change on the main outcome variables divided by the standard error of difference between the pre-test and post-test and pre-test and follow up scores. The standard error of difference between pre-intervention and post-intervention scores will be obtained derived from the reliability of the measures used or previously reported Cronbach's a for the existing measures, as appropriate. As per standard convention, an RC score of greater than or equal to 1.96 will be considered a reliable change. Clinically significant change will be operationally defined i.e. a reliable improvement from a pre-test score of above 14 points on the YBOCS, to a post-intervention score of less than or equal to 14 will be indicative of clinically significant improvement. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>6/07/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>6/07/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>102</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>13</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/09/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. Sarah Egan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Curtin University 
School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
GPO Box U1987
Perth 
Western Australia 6845

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kent Street
Bentley WA 6102
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Shalane Sadri (PhD student)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Curtin University 
School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
GPO Box U1987
Perth 
Western Australia 6845

</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Rebecca Anderson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Curtin University 
School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
GPO Box U1987
Perth 
Western Australia 6845

</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Robert Kane</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Curtin University 
School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
GPO Box U1987
Perth 
Western Australia 6845

</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Peter McEvoy</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Curtin University School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology GPO Box U1987 Perth Western Australia 6845</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this research is to determine whether targeting perfectionism directly in treatment, using an evidenced based transdiagnostic CBT, is an effective intervention for obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) and elevated perfectionism; and to compare the outcomes of this with a waitlist control condition. 

It is hypothesized that individuals who receive the intervention will demonstrate superior outcomes as indexed by reliable change and clinically significant change, compared to wait listed participants. Data obtained whilst the ERP arm of the study was still in operation will be reported if and where appropriate for comparison purposes. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Curtin University 
Office of Research and Development
GPO Box U 1987
Perth
Western Australia 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/02/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>All ethics modifications approved (trial no. HR38/2014</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/12/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Egan</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth 
Western Australia 6845

</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 2367</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 2464 </fax>
      <email>S.Egan@curtin.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Egan</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth 
Western Australia 6845
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 2367</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 2464 </fax>
      <email>S.Egan@exchange.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Shalane Sadri</name>
      <address>Curtin University
Health Sciences Graduate Research Hub
Building 603, Technology Park
6 Sarich Way
Bentley 6102
Western Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61 431370733</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 2464 </fax>
      <email>shalane.sadri@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>