<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364485">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000703707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An observational study comparing efficacy and safety of warfarin brands in cardiovascular patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open-label, prospective, observational study comparing efficacy and safety of two warfarin brands in adult patients already receiving warfarin treatment 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atrial fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Venous thrombosis </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary embolism </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Recurrent emboli</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Prosthetic valve replacement</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Acute myocardial infarction (to prevent systemic embolism)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The participants will be opportunistically followed up for the clinical outcome of warfarin for 6 months. The participants will continue with their usual treatment with the same brand of warfarin for the whole study period. Warfarin dosage adjustment is determined by physicians as necessary at any time during the study period in accordance with the standard treatment guidelines.</interventions>
    <comparator>This study is designed as an open label, prospective, observational study. Three hundred patients currently receiving warfarin (any brand) treatment will be recruited and allocated into 2 groups. Group I is the patients receiving the brand Coumadin (n=150) and Group II is the patients receiving the brand Marevan (n=150). The participants will be followed opportunistically as their usual anticoagulant visits. The duration of study is approximately 1 year (from 1 July 2013 31 July 2014).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of the patients whose International Normalized Ratio fall within and outside target ranges</outcome>
      <timepoint>For 6 months after enrolment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety profile (adverse drug events). The significant adverse events of warfarin are bleeding at any tissues.
The adverse events will be evaluated by a questionnaire given to the patients on each visit about "head to toe" disorders that they experience during each brand treatment period.

Also the investigator will interview the patients and evaluate the adverse events to double check with the answers in the questionnaire.

The data from the questionnaire and interview will be compared with warfarin concentrations and INR values to confirm the drug-induced adverse events possibility. </outcome>
      <timepoint>For 6 months after enrolment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age greater than or equal to 18 years
2. Receiving warfarin treatment 
	</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Age less than 18 years
2. Pregnancy or breast feeding
3. Non-adherence tendency
4. Psychiatric disorder or dementia
5. Taking any medications, food or dietary supplement that significantly interact with warfarin
6. Limited English communication proficiency
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS version 15.0) will be used for data analysis. Students paired t-test will be used for comparison of continuous variables, including mean warfarin dose requirement, warfarin concentrations in plasma and percentage of adverse events. Two-way ANOVA will be used to detect the differences of ratios of means INR and warfarin concentration between the groups. A Chi-square test will be used for the analysis and comparison of the proportions of participants with INR within target range and outside target range between the two brands. Time-in-therapeutic-range (TTR) of these two groups will also be compared by using a Students t-test for independent samples. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital - Woodville</hospital>
    <postcode>5011 - Woodville South</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Therapeutcs Research Centre, University of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>37a Woodville Road
Woodville South
SA 5011 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Therapeutcs Research Centre 
University of South Australia
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>37a Woodville Road
Woodville South
SA 5011 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Substitution of an innovator to a generic drug product has been continuously rising. In the US, approximately $8 billion to $10 billion is the average cost saving per year of brand substitution and the generic drug prescription has increased from 19% in 1984 to 60-70% in 2009. The increase in drug brand substitution is a call for scientific
attention of the appropriateness of available bioequivalence (BE) study guidelines at present. If two products are said to be bioequivalent it means that they would be expected to be, for all intents and purposes, the same. The conclusion of BE studies is based on the assumption that if the test and reference drug products exhibit similar in vitro (i.e. acceptable drug content, similar dissolution/release profile) and in vivo performance (i.e. acceptable bioavailability), these drug products should possess therapeutic equivalence which includes efficacy and safety. However, because bioequivalence studies are conducted in healthy volunteers, these studies may or may not provide definitive evidence to guarantee the therapeutic equivalence in patients.
This study aims to compare efficacy and safety of two warfarin products marketed in Australia, namely Coumadin  registered trademark or Marevan registered trademark. The study is designed as an openlabel,
prospective, observational trial. A total of 300 patients who
are prescribed with either brand of warfarin will be recruited in accordance with the inclusion and exclusion criteria.
The patients will be followed up opportunistically as their medical appointments for anticoagulant evaluation. The
additional 5 mL of the participant blood samples and about 25 mL of urine samples will be collected at each visit.
Total and free racemic, R- and S-warfarin enantiomer concentration in plasma, as well as 4',6,7,8, and 10hydroxywarfarin metabolites in urine will be quantified by LC MS/MS. The efficacy of the two warfarin brands will be
compared by evaluating International Normalized Ratio (INR) values. The safety profile evaluation will be achieved by recording any adverse drug reactions or adverse events in a questionnaire. The frequency of adverse events
reported from two groups of patients will be analyzed and compared.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (TQEH/LMH/MH) </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Basil Hetzel Institute DX465101
The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
28 Woodville Road
Woodville South SA 5011 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/TQEHLMH/45</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UniSA's Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Innovation Services
Ethics and Integrity
Mawson Lakes Campus 
University of South Australia 
GPO Box 2471, Adelaide, SA, 5001 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rachada To-a-nan </name>
      <address>Therapeutics Research Centre 
Basil Hetzel Institute for Translational Research 
37a Woodville Road, Woodville South 
SA 5011 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 7719</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>toyry002@mymail.unisa.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tom Robertson</name>
      <address>Therapeutics Research Centre 
Basil Hetzel Institute for Translational Research 
37a Woodville Road, Woodville South 
SA 5011 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 6521</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Tom.Robertson@unisa.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Roberts </name>
      <address>Sansom Institute, University of South Australia 
G.P.O. Box 2471, Adelaide
SA 5001 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 2816</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.roberts@uq.edu.au, Michael.Roberts@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>