<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373289">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001069347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>ROTEM® and platelet function in pre-eclamptic obstetric patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>ROTEM® and platelet function in pre-eclamptic obstetric patients: A prospective observational study on labour ward inpatients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1199-1145</utrn>
    <trialacronym>RPM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pre-eclampsia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fetal medicine and complications of pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Only patients with a diagnosis of pre-eclampsia will be included and blood tests in the form of ROTEM NATEM, Multiplate and the standard coagulation profile will be processed at the point of routine blood tests being done.</interventions>
    <comparator>A substudy of a cohort of 20 patients will be included from patients with uncomplicated pregnancies who are undergoing elective Caesareans</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Extent of platelet dysfunction in pre-eclampsia will be assessed via Multiplate results</outcome>
      <timepoint>Peripartum upon diagnosis of pre-eclampsia and presentation for obstetric review.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Platelet function will be assessed by the Multiplate test in both the substudy cohort and the study population.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-elective Caesarean</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Volume of blood loss (assessed via visual estimation)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 24 hours of delivery (whether it be a vaginal delivery or Caesarean section)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of primary postpartum haemorrhage (if this volume is &gt;500mL for a vaginal delivery or &gt;1000mL for a Caesarean section this would be defined as a primary postpartum haemorrage) (assessed via visual estimation)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 24 hours of delivery of the baby.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Key inclusion criteria:
	Potential study participants will be identified as per antenatal booking lists initially for the provision of information leaflets
	Patients must have clinically diagnosed pre-eclampsia (the whole spectrum of the disease, including HELLP (haemolysis, elevated liver enzymes, low platelets) syndrome)
	Potential participants will include inpatients of the labour ward which will include patients not yet in established labour, as well as parturients.
	These patients will be included into the study upon presentation to the labour ward at the point of requiring intravenous (IV) cannulation and/or venepuncture, either for medical management, for the insertion of a labour epidural, or for induction or augmentation of labour. 
	Pregnant patients of any gestation will be included, as long as they have the diagnosis of pre-eclampsia confirmed or are treated for suspected pre-eclampsia
	Patients requiring communication via an interpreter, mild to moderate mental illness; mild intellectual impairment; Aboriginal and Torres Strait Island patients will be coincidentally included.
Key inclusion criteria for substudy of 20 patients: 
* Patients undergoing an elective Caesarean section
* Patients with uncomplicated pregnancies and no history of coagulation abnormalities</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	All labour ward inpatients without a diagnosis of pre-eclampsia
	Age &lt; 18, age &gt; 55, SEVERE* cognitive impairment, SEVERE mental illness, moderate to SEVERE intellectual disability.  
	Sampling time: ROTEM® samples must be processed within four hours and some of these samples may be missed if samples taken after-hours are unable to be processed by the limited pathology staff rostered on for that period.  Processing of other specimens will take priority during the after-hours period, which may render some ROTEM® samples non-viable due to the time-constraints and these will be excluded from the study.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical advice has been provided by the Statistics Department of the Queensland Institute of Medical Research.   The proposed study period will be 12 months and based on estimates, there will be approximately 100-150 patients potentially included in the study, at which point we will review our data to assess the need for further extension of this study.  There were 131 pre-eclamptic patients who presented to RBWH in 2014.  Demographic and baseline data will be presented as frequencies/percent for categorical data or means/standard deviations for continuous data.  Continuous data will be analysed using analysis of variance (ANOVA), and the chi square test will be applied to categorical data.  Correlation between Multiplate® values, standard coagulation profiles, ROTEM® NATEM values and platelet counts will be assessed via Pearsons correlation.   Factors that affect the strength of the correlation will be assessed using general linear models.  Data relating to pregnancy and neonatal outcome will be collected as this may be affected by anaesthetic technique as well as any coagulation defect resulting from platelet dysfunction.

Subcategories of pre-eclampsia (mild PET, HELLP, severe PET) will be analysed if sufficient numbers are recruited from each group, but this will be dependent on the distribution of pre-eclamptic patients recruited during the study period.  The method of statistical analysis will be determined once recruitment is complete.


</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>23/10/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>10/02/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Butterfield St, Herston, QLD 4006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian and New Zealand College of Anaesthetists</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>630 St Kilda Rd, Melbourne, VIC 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>St Lucia, QLD 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>National Blood Authority</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 2, 243 Northbourne Avenue, Lyneham ACT 2602</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We intend to undertake this research project on ROTEM®, which is a rapid and specific blood clotting test which has been recently introduced to analyse clotting. This is a rapid test in that results can be obtained within 10 minutes, compared with 30 to 60 minutes for the current standard clotting test. It is specific in that it further defines parameters to assist in deciding what blood products need to be given in the event of bleeding. We will also analyse platelet function using a test called Multiplate®.

The purpose of this study is to better understand the type and extent of clotting issues that are potentially seen with the pregnancy-related condition known as pre-eclampsia. You will not receive any direct benefit from participating in this study, but the knowledge gained from this research will help us to improve the management of major bleeding in pregnant patients.

If a patient develops pre-eclampsia (uncommon condition) throughout the course of their pregnancy and if they agree to participate, then we will obtain a 7.5mL blood sample either through their IV drip or cannula when it is placed, or when they have blood tests done. This blood sample will be used to process for Multiplate® results, ROTEM® clotting test and the standard clotting test. If the patient has further routine blood tests performed, we will perform matched samples until the pre-eclampsia resolves. If a patient's pregnancy is uncomplicated and if they do not require an IV drip or any blood tests during their labour, then they will not be included in the study.

As a substudy, we intend to recruit 20 women undergoing an elective Caesarean, who have experienced uncomplicated pregnancies and have no history of coagulation disorders, to establish a normal range against which the results of our main study cohort will be compared.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Butterfield St, Herston QLD 4006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/06/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/QRBW/97</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373289-15-97 signed amendment approval RPM Study - Multiplate 07-2017.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373289-15-97 signed amendment approval for sub-study 08-2017.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Julie Lee</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine, 
Level 4 Ned Hanlon Building,
Butterfield St,
The Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital,
Herston QLD 4006</address>
      <phone>+617 3646 5453</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julielee01@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Julie Lee</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine, 
Level 4 Ned Hanlon Building,
Butterfield St,
The Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital,
Herston QLD 4006</address>
      <phone>+617 3646 5453</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julielee01@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Claire Manning</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine, 
Level 4 Ned Hanlon Building,
Butterfield St,
The Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital,
Herston QLD 4006</address>
      <phone>+617 3646 5453</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>clairemmanning@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Julie Lee</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine, 
Level 4 Ned Hanlon Building,
Butterfield St,
The Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital,
Herston QLD 4006</address>
      <phone>+617 3646 5453</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julielee01@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>