<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363255">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001237875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessing the cost effectiveness of a preventive dental intervention in public dental clinics.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Undertake a clinical trial that would demonstrate that the implementation of a Minimal Intervention Dentistry approach to a group of community dental patients (adolescents aged 11-14 years) who are at high risk to dental caries is likely to be 'cost-effective' compared to 'current practice' in achieving  positive oral health outcomes for this population group.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ACE MID Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Pilot Study Registration ID:ACTRN12610000901000</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dental Caries</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Adolescents recruited to the intervention arm will receive the preventive strategies of Minimal Intervention Dentistry during the 2 year study at following timpoints: baseline, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months, 18 months and 24 months. 

At the baseline, 12 and 24 month examination  appointments,   all study participants will complete the Child Health Utility-9D questionnaire and a self-administered questionnaire developed for the study. The questions relate to the participant's knowledge of oral  health, oral hygiene behaviour and snacks and beverages consumed. This will be followed by a 45-60 minute examination by an oral health examiner who will also develop a treatment plan. Participants in the test group only, will then visit the Dental Assistant (Certificate IV in Oral Health Promotion) who will provide the following preventive strategies: 
1.Based on the examiners treatment plan and participant information obtained from participants responses to the questionnaire, the Dental Assistant (Certificate IV in Oral Health Promotion) will develop a new homecare plan which will outline agreed goals with respect to diet modification, oral hygiene practice including demonstration of tooth brushing, flossing techniques and if indicated the application of tooth mousse. The participant will receive a copy of their Homecare Plan.  
2.Saliva testing ( At baseline and 24 months only) 
a.If low stimulated saliva rate tooth mousse will be provided with 5000ppm fluoride toothpaste
b.If normal stimulated saliva rate - 5000ppm fluoride toothpaste  will be recommended with instructions that it should not be used on children younger than 10 years of age   
3.Oral hygiene instructions will be given to the participant and where required, issue a disclosing tablet to educate the participant about the presence of plaque 
4. Diet counseling 
5. Fluoride varnish (2.26% NaF varnish) will be applied to all teeth  and issue an oral care pack consisting of oral health promotion resources, 5000 ppm toothpaste, toothbrush, floss and , if indicated, Tooth Mousse.
At the 3, 6 and 18 month review appointments the Dental Assistant (Certificate IV in Oral Health Promotion) will i.Review the homecare plan to assess a change in participants oral health habits and diet. The participant will receive a copy of their revised homecare plan. 
ii.provide diet assessment, education, oral hygiene instructions including demonstration of tooth brushing and flossing techniques and where required, issue a disclosing tablet to educate participant about the presence of plaque using the Turesky Score apply Fluoride Varnish (2.26% NaF varnish) to all teeth and issue an oral care pack. The duration of each visit with the Dental Assistant (Certificate IV in Oral Health Promotion) will be approximately 45-60 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Adolescents receiving current standard care for management of carious lesions in community dental clinics. As per the community dental clinic protocol, using the American Academy of Pediatric Dentistry (AAPD) Caries-Risk Assessment Tool for Children, all children and adolescents attending community dental clinics are routinely assessed for their risk to developing dental caries. Patients are categorised as high, moderate or low risk as assessed against the clinical, environmental and general health indicators. Those assessed as high risk to dental caries are placed on a 12 month recall appointment, Standard clinical care at 12 month recall appointment requires a re-evaluation of the childs caries-risk status children using information collected from undertaking the following diagnostic and clinical measures: ICDAS II, Plaque Index, Bleeding Index and Calculus Assessment, bitewing x-rays and restorations of newly developed carious lesions.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A reduction in the number of new and progressing smooth surface carious lesions in the intervention arm, using the following measure, the ICDAS II.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 and 24 month recall</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A reduction in Plaque Index score and Bleeding Index Score. The plaque index score and bleeding index score will form part of the examination. These are indicative of changes in oral hygiene behaviour.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 and 24 month recall</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2. 
Salivary flow rates (test participants only).  A GC saliva kit will be used to measure the stimulated saliva flow rates.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 month recall</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant's oral health knowledge, attitudes and health behaviours and diet related behaviour. Participants will complete a self-administered questionnaire developed for the study and the Child Health Utility-9D tool.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 and 24 month recall</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Socio-economic data relating to parent/carer. Parent's  oral health knowledge, attitudes and health behaviours including factors influencing their health behaviours such as cost and access to healthy foods and oral health services and cost of oral care products. Parents/carers will complete a self-administered questionnaire developed for the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 and 24 month recall</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Identification of possible barriers to uptake of preventive oral health behaviours and diet changes. A random sample  of test participants and their carers from each of the participating agencies allocated to the intervention arm,  invited to attend a focus group.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post Study at 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 6 
Identification of barriers and enablers amongst participating community dental clinics, to the implementation of an MID approach in community dental clinics. Study examiners, Dental Assitants ( with Cert IV in Oral Health Promotion), agency administration staff, program managers and clinicians will complete a non-validated written questionaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post study at 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Canvas the knowledge, attitude, acceptance and practice with respect to the Minimal Intervention Dentistry approach, among oral health practitioners employed at the participating community dental clinics. Clinicians will complete a self-adminstered questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Undertake an economic appraisal to asess whether Minimal Intervention Dentistry is likely to be 'value for money' and so how best to implement it from an efficiency perspective. Participating community dental clinics will complete a self administered questionnaire to appraise procedures and resources currently allocated to patient recall. The tool will also provide a profile of allocation and structure of oral health workforce in the participating community dental clinics.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and post study at 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adolescent patients aged 11 -14 years who: 
1.are holders of or dependents of  a Health Care Card or Concession Card AND 
2.attend their 12 months high-risk recall visit and completed their general course of care AND
3.are assessed as having developed more than one carious lesion in the last 12 months (including white spot lesions) AND
4.have had all occlusal fissures of premolars,molars and partially erupting molars sealed</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>11</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria for this study include:
methamphetamine users and drug addicted patients

patients with diagnosed medical conditions that may, in the opinion of the investigators, compromise the study outcome

e.g. requiring anticoagulant therapy, chemotherapy or radiotherapy, congenital heart disease. 

patients with a diagnosed intellectual or mental health condition which may impair the patients comprehension of the MID protocol instructions and their capacity to meet Study requirements 

patients with diagnosed physical disabilities that inhibit the patient from performing the oral health care instructions as part of the MID protocol   
 
patients with more than four deciduous molars remaining 

adolescents undergoing fixed or removable orthodontic treatment 

An allergy to milk protein (not lactose intolerance). (Applies to intervention group only)  
  
An allergy to the preservative, Sodium Benzoate (Applies to intervention group only)

History of severe asthma, requiring hospitalisation (Applies to intervention group only)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Each of the 12 clinics enrolled in the study will be randomized to either standard  treatment (control arm) or MID (intervention arm). The treatment received by participants will be determined by the study arm to which the clinic has been randomised. The allocation was not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/12/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>504</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3199</postcode>
    <postcode>3939</postcode>
    <postcode>3915</postcode>
    <postcode>3095</postcode>
    <postcode>3021</postcode>
    <postcode>3029</postcode>
    <postcode>3156</postcode>
    <postcode>3195</postcode>
    <postcode>3011</postcode>
    <postcode>3181</postcode>
    <postcode>3205</postcode>
    <postcode>3031</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dental Health Services Victoria</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>720 Swanston St 
Carlton, 3053
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dental Health Services Victoria</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>720 Swanston St 
Carlton, 3053
Victoria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Melbourne</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Melbounre 
Victoria 3010</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Deakin University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>221 Burwood Highway
Burwood
Victoria 3125</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study aims to demonstrate that the implementation of a Minimal Intervention Dentistry approach to a group of community public dental patients (adolescents aged 11-14 years) is likely to be cost-effective compared to current practice in achieving positive oral health outcomes for this population group. 

The study targets adolescents who are assessed as being at high risk to dental caries and are currently accessing community dental clinics in Metropolitan Melbourne. Equal numbers of community dental clinics will be recruited from local government areas with low and high SEIFA indexes to join the study. The design of the Study is that of a cluster randomised control trial.     

Minimal Intervention Dentistry (MID) is a multi-pronged approach which comprises of a range of strategies including prevention, early intervention, non-surgical and surgical management of the condition. 

Minimal Intervention Dentistry is based on the premise that early carious lesions can be reversed through remineralisation  and changes to diet and oral hygiene habits to arrest the progression of the disease.

The primary outcomes of the study are to: 

Demonstrate a reduction in the number of new and progressing carious lesions amongst the participants who have undertaken this approach 
Demonstrate a cost effectiveness of the MID approach in this study population  

The study is scheduled for completion June 2015.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Melbourne 
Victoria 3010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1237643</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Adjunct Professor Hanny Calache</name>
      <address>Dental Health Services Victoria 
720 Swanston St 
Carlton 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 39341 1328</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hanny.calache@dhsv.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kerina Princi</name>
      <address>Dental Health Services Victoria 
720 Swanston St 
Carlton 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 39341 1708</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kerina.princi@dhsv.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>