<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371611">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000226303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Treating preterm preeclampsia with sulfasalazine: An early phase clinical trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pharmacokinetics of sulfasalazine for the treatment of preterm preeclampsia: An early phase clinical trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Preeclampsia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fetal medicine and complications of pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>3 grams of sulfasalazine will be administered orally daily to participants until they require delivery.  Patients will be admitted and adherence monitored using the in patient drug chart.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) Our primary outcome is to assess the pharmacokinetic profile of sulfasalazine in patients with preeclampsia. Pharmacokinetic parameters include maximum concentration (Cmax) and time to maximum concentration (Tmax), area under the concentration time curve (AUC), apparent oral clearance (CL/F), half life and renal clearance.

2) These will be assessed in maternal blood and urine over a 24 hour period. We will also assess sulfasalazine levels in maternal blood, cord blood and placenta at delivery. </outcome>
      <timepoint>* Serial blood samples of 6 mls will be collected over one 24 hour period, after at least 24 hours of sulfasalazine treatment, to assess levels of sulfasalazine levels at 0, 2, 4, 8, 12 and 24 hours. 
* Urine will be collected before the dose, and then at 0-4, 4-8, 8-12 and 12-24 hours and sulfasalazine excretion assessed.
* Maternal, umbilical cord and placenta will be collected at time of delivery to assess sulfasalazine and sulfapyridine levels. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the effects of sulfasalazine on clinical markers of preeclampsia including:
Headache. This will be assessed by asking the patient daily whether they have a headache.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be examined daily antenatally and postnatally until patient discharge. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemical markers of preeclampsia including full blood count in particular haemoglobin and platelet count, electrolytes: including creatinine, urea and uric acid and coagulation profile using a serum blood sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be examined daily antenatally and postnatally until patient discharge. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In the fetus/neonate we will assess mortality </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be obtained by accessing the patient records.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual symptoms. This will be assessed by asking the patient daily whether they have spots in their vision or any visual disturbance.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed daily until patient discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Right upper quadrant abdominal pain. This will be assessed by asking the patient daily whether they have abdominal pain.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed daily until discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severe hypertension (blood pressure of systolic greater than or equal to 160 and diastolic greater than or equal to 110). </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed daily until discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Electrolytes: including creatinine, urea and uric acid using a serum blood sample.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be examined daily until delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>coagulation profile in patient serum.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed as decided by the treating clinician</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>proteinuria</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed daily until delivery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In the neonate neurological morbidity including intraventricular haemorrhage diagnosed with clinical examination and ultrasound.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed by paediatricians daily after delivery to the date of discharge of the neonate. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In the neonate respiratory morbidity including respiratory distress syndrome will be assessed clinically by paediatricians and with x-ray if clinically indicated. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed by paediatricians daily after delivery to the date of discharge of the neonate. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In the neonate retinopathy of prematurity will be assessed clinically by the paediatrician. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed daily by paediatricians after delivery to the date of discharge of the neonate. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In the neonate gastrointestinal morbidity including necrotising enterocolitis will be assessed clinically by the paediatrician.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed by paediatricians daily after delivery to the date of discharge of the neonate. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The diagnosis of preeclampsia will be made using the Society of Obstetric Medicine Australia and New Zealand guidelines. Eligible women will be 18 years or older with singleton, non-anomalous pregnancies between 30+0 and 36+0 weeks gestation. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>We will exclude women with multiple pregnancy, known fetal malformation, contraindication to sulfasalazine treatment, women already taking sulfasalazine and women with an immunodeficiency disorder.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Mercy Hospital for Women - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Sunshine Hospital - St Albans</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3021 - St Albans</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mercy Hospital for Women</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Mercy Hospital for Women
163 Studley Road
Heidelberg 
Victoria 
3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Norman Beischer Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Mercy Hospital for Women
163 Studley Road
Heidelberg 
Victoria
3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NA</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Preeclampsia is a common, serious complication of pregnancy and leading cause of maternal, fetal and neonatal death and disability. Currently there is no medical treatment and the only way to stop disease progression is to deliver the pregnancy. At early gestations this inflicts the serious risks of prematurity on the newborn whilst the mother is exposed to the risk of disease progression during the delivery process. A treatment that stabilises the disease to allow the safe prolongation of pregnancy would be a major advance. 

Excitingly we have discovered that a medication safe in pregnancy, sulfasalazine, can reverse key features of preeclampsia disease pathophysiology in laboratory studies using primary human pregnancy tissues. Firstly we showed that sulfasalazine reduces the placental secretion of antiangiogenic factors sFlt-1 and soluble endoglin that cause preeclampsia. Secondly we demonstrated sulfasalazine reduced features of vascular dysfunction specific to preeclampsia. 

Given these promising findings and that sulfasalazine is safe in pregnancy (category B) we hope to progress this concept and translate these findings from the laboratory to the clinic with a proof of concept early phase clinical trial. We propose to recruit 20 women with preterm preeclampsia (30+0 weeks to 36+0 weeks gestation) at The Mercy Hospital for Women and treat them with 2-3 grams of sulfasalazine per day. We will assess the pharmacokinetics of sulfasalazine in women with preeclampsia and monitor key clinical and biochemical features of the disease. 

If successful, at the completion of this study, we will have evidence to progress the study of sulfasalazine as a treatment for preeclampsia to randomized clinical trial. It may form the basis for a medical treatment for preeclampsia and reduce the devastating burden of this common obstetric disease.  
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mercy Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mercy Hospital for Women
163 Studley Road
Heidelberg 
Victoria
3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>R16/65</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Fiona Brownfoot</name>
      <address>Mercy Hospital for Women
163 Studley Road
Heidelberg   
Victoria
3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8458 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fiona.brownfoot@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Fiona Brownfoot</name>
      <address>Mercy Hospital for Women
163 Studley Road
Heidelberg   
Victoria
3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8458 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fiona.brownfoot@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Fiona Brownfoot</name>
      <address>Mercy Hospital for Women
163 Studley Road
Heidelberg   
Victoria
3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8458 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fiona.brownfoot@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Fiona Brownfoot</name>
      <address>Mercy Hospital for Women
163 Studley Road
Heidelberg   
Victoria 
3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8458 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fiona.brownfoot@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>