<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367141">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001068651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Examination of the effect of Negative Pressure Wound Therapy in Acute Paediatric Burns on Re-epithelialisation, Pain and Injury Progression  A pilot study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Examination of the effect of Negative Pressure Wound Therapy in Acute Paediatric Burns on Re-epithelialisation, Pain and Injury Progression  A pilot study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1162-0654 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Paediatric burns</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Burns</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Negative pressure wound therapy (Smith and Nephew (TM) Renasys Go)- applied at time of randomisation to intervention group within 12 hours of burn injury and left insitu for three days until first dressing change. From day three onwards all children (regardless of group) will receive standard dressing which for our centre is Acticoat (TM) and Mepitel (TM) secured with hypafix. Feeding tubes are incorporated into the dressing to allow for regular irrigation by parents at home to keep dressing moist.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard dressing at our centre which is Acticoat (TM) and Mepitel (TM) secured with hypafix. Feeding tubes are incorporated into the dressing to allow for regular irrigation by parents at home to keep dressing moist.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wound progression - assess difference in laser doppler imaging from day of injury to day 3.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 3 post injury</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wound re epithelialisation
- Clinical judgement by surgeon treating the patient
- Blinded second assessment from digital photographs</outcome>
      <timepoint>Expected day 10-14 following injury</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pain while dressing in situ (days 1-3 following injury). Pain at dressing change. Assessed via multiple methods - FACES-R/VAS-P/FLACC </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ease of management of dressing - 5 point Likert scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 3 following injury at first dressing change</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children with acute partial thickness burns presenting to the Department of Emergency Medicine, Royal Childrens Hospital aged 3-15.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Age younger than 3 years or older than 16 years 
Superficial (erythema only) &amp; full thickness burns
Burns &gt;10% TBSA
Chemical and friction burns
Known sensitivity to silver
Non English speaking
Cognitive impairment
Current involvement with Department Communities (Child Safety)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The surgical registrar will identify eligible patients and ask if a member of the research team can approach the family and discuss the project. Informed consent will be gained. Sequentially numbered, sealed, opaque envelopes prepared by an independent party will be used for treatment allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is a proof of concept, feasibility pilot study. As this is a pilot study statistical analysis will be limited. Data will be presented as mean (standard deviation) or median (range) where appropriate. Comparison between groups will be undertaken, however the investigators acknowledge the limitations of this given it is a pilot study. Data from this study will be utilised to design a larger prospective RCT if the pilot study determines that the study is feasible.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>21/09/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Children's Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Royal Brisbane Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute, University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level Four Foundation Building
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Road
Herston
Qld 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Smith and Nephew Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Healthcare Division
PO Box 242
Mount Waverley VIC 3149
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The ultimate goal of burn wound management is to promote early healing as this has considerable influence on the long term quality and appearance of scarring. Negative pressure wound therapy (NPWT) is a device that is applied to a wound to ultimately help promote healing. It is widely used in both hospitals and the home on a wide range of wounds. A dressing is applied to the wound bed
and covered with a transparent film dressing and attached to the therapy device using tubing and a canister. A
number of studies have demonstrated improved graft take following split skin graft when NWPT was used
compared to standard dressings. However, there is very little information regarding the use of NWPT as a primary
treatment for burns with respect to wound progression and pain management. A small number of studies have
demonstrated improvement in acute burn wounds with the application of NPWT in the first 48 - 72 hours following
injury. In addition, clinically we have seen a reduction in pain with the use of NPWT.
The aim of this pilot study is to determine the feasibility of the novel application of NPWT on acute burn wounds. The
outcomes of interest being pain, burn wound progression and healing.
All children presenting to the Royal Children's Hospital Department of Emergency Medicine with a partial thickness
burn injury aged 3 - 15
years of age will be considered for the study. Treating surgical registrars of all children meeting the inclusion/exclusion criteria presenting to the Royal Childrens Hospital, Brisbane will determine eligibility for enrolment in the study. With the parent/caregivers permission an investigator aligned with the study will
discuss the study with the parents/caregivers and seek informed consent. Once informed consent is obtained
participants will be randomised to one of two treatment groups (standard dressings or standard dressings plus
NPWT). Dressings (+/negative pressure depending on group allocation) will be changed at day three post burn
injury. Following day three all children will be managed with standard dressings until full re epithelialisation or
grafting. Negative pressure will not be reapplied from day three onwards.
Outcome measures include burn wound progression measured using laser Doppler imaging on day 0 and day 3,
wound healing and pain.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children's Health Services Queensland HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3 Foundation Bldg
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston 4029
Qld</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/QRCH/78</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/05/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Queensland HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University Queensland
St Lucia 4067
Qld
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/06/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014000757</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/06/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Roy Kimble</name>
      <address>Department Paediatrics and Child Health
Level 3 Foundation Bldg
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston 4029 Queensland</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 8513</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>royk@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kellie Stockton</name>
      <address>Queensland Children's Medical Institute
Level 4 Foundation Bldg
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston 4029
Queensland</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 1278</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.stockton@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kellie Stockton</name>
      <address>Queensland Children's Medical Institute
Level 4 Foundation Bldg
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston 4029
Queensland</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 1278</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.stockton@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kellie Stockton</name>
      <address>Queensland Children's Medical Institute
Level 4 Foundation Bldg
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston 4029
Queensland</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 1278</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.stockton@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>