<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369252">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001044516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Methylphenidate in Adults with Severe Traumatic brain injury for the Enhancement of Recovery (MASTER)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study of the effects of Methylphenidate (MPD) on cognition, mood, behaviour, participation and quality of life after severe traumatic brain injury in adults
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1173-9960 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>MASTER</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Traumatic brain injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>3-month randomised double-blind placebo-controlled trial with oral active or placebo medication (Methylphenidate, Ritalin long acting 10mg DAILY for the first 7 days, to be increased to 20mg  DAILY for 5 days) to be administered over 12 days and followed up for 3 months to assess outcomes. The medication will be administered by registered nursing staff on inpatient Brain Injury Unit.The principal researchers (Drs Browne and Bui) or MD Medical students will be undertaking assessments of attention and cognition as well as participation, mood and quality of life measures.

All participants will be given a baseline assessment and then undergo further assessments after administration of either active or placebo medication.</interventions>
    <comparator>Methylphenidate (Ritalin LA) 10mg and then increased to a 20mg after 7 days compared with placebo, which will contain microcellulose. Total duration of treatment with either active agent or placebo is 12 days. All patients are randomised at enrolment to active or placebo. Methylphenidate or placebo ceased on day 12 and follow up assessment at 3 months.

</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attention, assessed by Paced Auditory Serial Addition Test (PASAT)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1, day 5, day 12, day 19, day 96</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attention, assessed by Digit Span Test (DST)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1,5,12,19,96</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Working memory, assessed by Symbol Digit Modality Test (SDMT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1,5,12,19,96</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life as assessed by World Health Organisation Quality of Life-Bref (WHOQOL-Bref).

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 96</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Review of hospital records to assess length of inpatient stay
</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of enrolment to day 96 of participation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Side effects as measured by side effect questionnaire which has been designed specifically for this study
</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of enrolment to days 12,19,96 of participation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of enrolment to days 1,5,12,19,96</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mayo-Portland Adaptability Inventory-4 (MPAI-4)</outcome>
      <timepoint>From date of enrolment to day 96 of participation </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>A participant is identified to be eligible if they are aged between 18-65yo, have a new traumatic brain injury within the past 6 months, a measurable PTA of greater than 7 days.
All participants need to be able to give informed consent.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Non-English speaking
Dysphasia
Current treatment with psycho-active medications
cardiac events
hypertension 
abnormal ECG
tics
post-traumatic seizures
pregnancy (negative bhCG)
prior history of alcohol or drug abuse
Any medications which are contra-indicated with MPD: monoamine oxidase inhibitors, clonidine, dopamine agonists or antagonists, certain anaesthetics



</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The participant will be enrolled into the study after informed consent has been obtained if the participant has met all inclusion criteria and has none of the exclusion criteria.  The participant will receive a study enrolment number which allocates them to either active or placebo treatment. This study number has been randomly generated by a computer. This study number will be used to record information on the database. </concealment>
    <sequence>All eligible patients who consent will be enrolled into the study. The participant will be randomly allocated to receive either active or placebo treatment via a computer generated random number.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>At the completion of the study, un-blinding of the code will allow identification of participants into the two treatment arms.  Subsequent statistical analysis will employ parametric techniques to determine within-subject and between-subject effects.  Independent samples t tests will be used to test the null hypothesis that MPD does not affect performance on attentional tests, mood, participation, and quality of life.  ANOVA tests will be used to assess the effect of repeated performance on the assessments.  Regression analyses will be used to assess the influence of independent factors, such as age, gender, injury type and severity.  This pilot study will provide valuable information on effect sizes of the instruments to allow appropriate sample size calculation for a future, larger, appropriately-powered randomised, double-blind trial.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Rehabilitation Hospital - Coorabel/Moorong - Ryde</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Rehab</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>235 Morrison Rd
Ryde 
NSW 2112</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The research aims to learn more about the potential benefits of methylphenidate (Ritalin) as people recover from traumatic brain injury.  Ritalin is a stimulant medication, most-widely known for its use in children with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder.  It works by increasing the concentrations of certain neurotransmitters within the brain, especially those involved in attentional processes. 

Past studies have shown that methylphenidate has been effective in patients with a traumatic brain injury in improving attention. This study looks at whether it not only improves attention but also day to day function and sense of well-being after three months.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee (EC0012)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 13 Kolling Building 
Royal North Shore Hospital
Pacific Highway
St Leonards
NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2/12/2015</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tram Anh Bui</name>
      <address>Royal Rehab
235 Morrison Rd
Ryde
NSW 2112</address>
      <phone>+61 29808 9222</phone>
      <fax>+61 29809 6071</fax>
      <email>tram.bui@royalrehab.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stuart Browne</name>
      <address>Royal Rehab
235 Morrison Rd
Ryde
NSW 2112</address>
      <phone>+61 29808 9222</phone>
      <fax>+61 29809 6071</fax>
      <email>stuart.browne@royalrehab.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Clayton King</name>
      <address>Royal Rehab
235 Morrison Rd
Ryde
NSW 2112</address>
      <phone>+61 29808 9222</phone>
      <fax>+61 29809 6071</fax>
      <email>clayton.king@royalrehab.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tram Bui</name>
      <address>Royal Rehab
235 Morrison Rd
Ryde
NSW 2112</address>
      <phone>+61 29808 9222</phone>
      <fax>+61 29809 6071</fax>
      <email>tram.bui@royalrehab.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>