<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367447">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate />
  <approvaldate>8/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000010594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The SWIFT trial - Supporting weight loss in adults with whole-food diets, intermittent fasting and high-intensity interval training</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of different support strategies on weight loss, indicators of health, and lifestyle behaviours in overweight men and women</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>SWIFT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomised to one of 5 intervention groups for a 12 month period followed by a further 12 month follow-up: 1) control, 2) brief support - will meet with researchers once a month for 5-10 minutes to be weighed and have a brief discussion about progress and to address any concerns, 3) self-weighing - will be asked to weigh themselves at the same time every day and enter weight into our online database, email feedback on progress will be provided once a month, 4) My Fitness Pal - participants will be shown how to use this online/mobile app which allows them to track their dietary intake. Participants will use the app daily for the first month and then one week per month for 11 months, 5) Hunger training - participants will be taught how to eat to hunger and satiety using a combination of fingerprick blood glucose testing and awareness of hunger types. Participants will meet face-to-face with a dietitian for a 2-hour training session on day 0, followed by a quick phone call to assess progress on day 2 and a 30-60 minute face-to-face session on day 14. Participants will be monitoring their blood glucose and using the booklet daily for the first fortnight, after which blood glucose monitoring becomes optional. They will continue to use the booklet daily for the second fortnight, and then one week every month for the remaining 11 months.

While participants are randomised to a certain support group and thus have no choice in this, they are allowed to choose which diet and exercise regime they would like to follow over the course of the 24 month study (including group 1 - the control group). Potential dietary approaches they can choose from include the Mediterranean diet, a modified Paleo approach (allows limited legumes and dairy) and intermittent fasting (5:2 approach). The mediterranean diet approach encourages wholegrains, fresh fruit and vegetables but limits red meat, sugar and saturated fat. The modified paleo (whole-food diet) approach encourages consumption of minimally processed foods with an emphasis on plant foods and animal proteins, but limiting sugar or grain-based foods. Small amounts of dairy and legumes are permitted if wanted by participants. The intermittent fasting approach outlines restriction of energy intake on 2 days a week to a quarter of normal intake.  All dietary interventions are given with an extensive printed resource with recipes and guidance, as well as a half hour session with one of the researchers to answer questions.
Potential exercise approaches include current recommendations, or a home-based high-intensity interval training (HIIT) programme. Participants choosing current recommendations discuss their choice of exercise type with a researcher and HIIT participants undergo a medical assessment and a one-off HIIT session training with heart rate monitoring. </interventions>
    <comparator>Control participants will receive the dietary and exercise intervention as outlined earlier but no additional support. They will undertake all outcome assessments as for the other participants.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body weight will be measured in duplicate using electronic digital scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6, 12, 24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage body fat by DXA</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intuitive Eating Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 12, 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disordered eating questionnaire - EDE-Q</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 12, 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity by 7-day accelerometry (Actigraph)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 12, 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to support strategies:
Brief support - by electronic records of attendance at monthly sessions
Self-weighing - participants enter weight online each day onto a specialised database which is checked weekly by researchers for completion.
MyFitnessPal - Data are collected by the app, which the participant shares with the researchers by setting their food diary as "public"
Hunger training - from participant completed diaries which outline when they ate, what their blood glucose was, and what their hunger ratings were before eating</outcome>
      <timepoint>Brief support monthly from 0-12 months
Self-weighing daily from 0-12 months
MyFitnessPal daily for month 1, then one week in each of months 2-12
Hunger training daily for month 1, then one week in each of months 2-12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to diet and exercise interventions
Adherence to the dietary regimes will be measured using the 3-day diet records. Those choosing to follow intermittent fasting will complete a 4-day diet record (2 fasting, 2 non-fasting days) at 6, 12 and 24 months. Adherence to the exercise regime will be measured by the accelerometers. In addition, HIIT participants will wear a Polar RC3 GPS heart rate monitor during all home HIIT sessions for a one-week period at baseline, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months to evaluate intensity attained during the sessions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Diet records at 0, 6, 12 and 24 months
Accelerometry at 0, 12, 24 months
Heart rate monitoring (for HIIT participants only) for a one-week period at 0, 3, 6, 9, 12, and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Body mass index greater than 27 and otherwise healthy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pre-existing disease (diabetes, cancer, cardiovascular disease requiring medical management), endocrine disorders, systemic inflammatory diseases, or history of serious medical problems
Pregnant or planning to become pregnant in the next two years
Musculoskeletal disorders preventing exercise
Fasting blood glucose greater than 7 mmol/L (as not suitable for hunger training)
Systolic blood pressure greater than 160 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure greater than 100mmHg (as require medical intervention)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will complete an initial eligibility questionnaire online. If eligible, researchers will contact them, establish their willingness to continue participation and schedule the participant for baseline measurements. After informed consent has been obtained, additional baseline measurements are undertaken. One a participant has been confirmed eligible and has completed all baseline assessments, they choose which diet and exercise regime they would like to try. Randomisation to support condition will occur using sequentially numbered opaque sealed envelopes prepared by the statistician. The participants will be stratified by sex and random length blocks will be used to allocate the treatment. Participants will then be booked into their first intervention session.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>SWIFT is a 24-month RCT involving a 12-month intervention with a follow-up at 24 months. Weight (primary outcome) will be measured at 0, 6, 12 and 24 months as will most of the secondary outcomes, with the exception of the accelerometers and some questionnaires (0, 12 and 24 months only). 

Based on a standard deviation (SD) for baseline weight of 15kg, and a correlation between repeat measures of r = 0.90 (obtained from our previous studies involving similar populations), our study has 90% power using a two-sided 5% level of significance to detect a clinically important difference in change in body weight of 4kg between any pair of groups with 42 participants per group. Thus we will recruit 250 participants in total across the five groups which allows for 15% drop-out/unusable data. Fifty per group at baseline also provides 80% power to detect differences of 5cm in waist circumference (baseline SD 12, r = 0.80). 

The primary analysis will follow modified intention-to-treat principles (using all available data) and will compare the outcomes resulting from the five different support strategies (RCT analysis). Linear mixed models will be used to model outcomes at 6, 12 and 24 months after adjusting for baseline values. Standard mixed model diagnostics will be performed.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/10/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>8/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>250</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>8/05/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/05/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Private bequest</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Edgar Diabetes and Obesity Research Centre
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Although people argue over whether there is a "best" diet for weight loss, it is becoming increasingly apparent that a variety of diets are healthy and appropriate. What is more important is determining how best we can support people to adhere to appropriate dietary change over the long-term. This project will let people choose from a selection of appropriate dietary approaches that they would like to follow (a paleo-type diet, intermittent fasting, or a mediterranean diet) as well as choosing whether to try high-intensity interval training or current recommendations, then randomise them to one of five different ways of supporting them to make those changes to their diet/activity over a two-year period.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://swift.otago.ac.nz</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Taylor RW et al. Determining how best to support overweight adults to adhere to lifestyle change: protocol for the SWIFT study. BMC Public Health 2015;15:861.
Jospe MR et al. Adherence to hunger training using blood glucose monitoring: a feasibility study. Nutr Metab 2015;12:22
Jospe M et al. The effect of different types of monitoring strategies on weight loss: a randomised controlled trial. Obesity 2017;25(9):14901498.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H14/024</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Rachael Taylor</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 470 9180</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rachael.taylor@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jenny McArthur</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 5953</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jenny.mcarthur@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Rachael Taylor</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 470 9180</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rachael.taylor@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Rachael Taylor</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin</address>
      <phone>+64 3 470 9180</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rachael.taylor@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>