<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373391">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001128381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Footwear and insoles to improve balance and gait in older people</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Preliminary evaluation of prototype footwear and insoles to optimise balance and gait in older women</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>falls</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is a pair of footwear and insoles designed to improve balance.

1. Footwear
The prototype footwear is based on an existing model (Dr Comfort® Vigor, Mequon, WI, USA) which was selected as it incorporates many of the features previously shown to be beneficial for balance. Specifically, the footwear had a firm (Shore A hardness 55) rubber sole of 25 mm thickness under the heel and 18 mm under the forefoot, laces plus Velcro® fastening, a high collar to support the ankle, and a firm heel counter. Across the size range, the weight of the prototype footwear is 310 to 360 gm. The outersole has been modified to optimise slip resistance by grinding a 10 degree bevel into the heel region, placing grooves perpendicular to the sole (1.2 mm deep and 2.4 mm wide) across the heel surface area, and placing perpendicular grooves (5 mm deep and 12 mm wide) across the rest of the sole. 

2. Insoles

The footwear incorporates a textured insole, constructed from 4 mm thick ethyl vinyl acetate (Shore A 25 ) with dome-shaped projections (3 mm high and 8 mm diameter, Shore A 85 ) placed across the forefoot in a 15 mm diamond pattern and along the lateral border, extending to the heel. The design of the textured insole was informed by previous studies reporting improvements on balance in older people when similar insoles were worn.

The prototype footwear with the insoles inserted will be worn for a single assessment session. Testing for each of the footwear conditions will take approximately 30 minutes. In between each footwear condition, there will be a brief 10 min washout period.</interventions>
    <comparator>1. Participant's own footwear
For the own footwear condition, participants will be asked to bring to the testing session the footwear they wear most often when outdoors.

2. Flexible footwear (Dunlop Volleys)
The flexible footwear (Dunlop Volley, Pacific Brands, Australia) has a rubber sole of uniform 18 mm thickness, a hardness of Shore A 35 , and lace fixation. Across the size range, the weight of the flexible footwear is 280 to 420 gm. The flexible footwear was selected as a control condition as it has no features considered to be either beneficial or detrimental to balance.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postural sway
Using the Neurocom Balance Master system, postural sway will be measured in °/sec from three trials of 20 sec duration while standing on a foam rubber mat (46 cm wide x 46 long x 13 cm thick).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediate effect (repeated measures experiment)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Limits of stability
Using the Neurocom Balance Master system, the limits of stability test, which quantifies the maximum distance the participant can intentionally displace and maintain the stability of their centre of gravity, will be performed with participants leaning in eight directions at 45 degree intervals represented by targets on a computer monitor. Participants will be instructed to keep their feet on the ground and use their body to lean towards each target. Maximum excursion (expressed as a percentage of each participants limits of stability, determined by their height) and directional control (expressed as a percentage, with 100% representing a straight line from the centre of pressure to the target) will be averaged across the eight directions. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediate effect (repeated measures experiment)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tandem stance test
Using the Neurocom Balance Master system, the tandem walk test will require participants to walk heel to toe from one end of the force plate to the other three times. After reaching the end of the platform, participants will be instructed to maintain their tandem stance position for five seconds while their sway is recorded. Measured parameters during this test are speed (cm/sec) and step width (cm) while traversing the platform, and endpoint sway velocity (°/sec) at completion of the task.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediate effect (repeated measures experiment)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Velocity
Using the GAITRite walkway, participants will be asked to walk at their normal comfortable speed, and an average of three trials of each footwear condition were documented. Velocity is measured as the metres per second. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediate effect (repeated measures experiment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cadence
Using the GAITRite walkway, participants will be asked to walk at their normal comfortable speed, and an average of three trials of each footwear condition were documented. Cadence is measured as the number of steps per minute. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediate effect (repeated measures experiment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Step length
Using the GAITRite walkway, participants will be asked to walk at their normal comfortable speed, and an average of three trials of each footwear condition were documented. Step length is measured in cm. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediate effect (repeated measures experiment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Step width
Using the GAITRite walkway, participants will be asked to walk at their normal comfortable speed, and an average of three trials of each footwear condition were documented. Step width is measured in cm. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediate effect (repeated measures experiment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Female
2. Aged 65 years and over
3. Living independently in the community
4. Able to walk household distances without a walking aid
5. Able to understand English in written and verbal form</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Cognitive impairment (defined as a score of &lt;7 on the Short Portable Mental Status Questionnaire)
2. Neurodegenerative condition such as Parkinsons disease
3. Lower limb amputation
4. Foot and ankle surgery in previous three months</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Repeated measures experiment</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Differences between the three footwear conditions (flexible footwear, participants own footwear, and prototype footwear) will be evaluated using repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) with Bonferroni-adjusted post-hoc tests for pairwise comparisons. The effect sizes for all significant main effects will be calculated using the eta-squared statistic and will be interpreted using the following cut-offs: 0 to 0.06 (small), &gt;0.06 to 0.14 (medium) and &gt;0.14 (large) .</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>28/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>25/07/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>25/07/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>La Trobe University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Plenty Rd and Kingsbury Drive
Bundoora
Victoria 3086</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>La Trobe University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Plenty Rd and Kingsbury Drive
Bundoora
Victoria 3086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Footwear has the potential to influence balance in either a detrimental or beneficial manner, and is therefore an important consideration in relation to falls prevention. The objective of this study was to evaluate balance ability and gait patterns in older women while wearing prototype footwear and insoles designed to improve balance.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Menz HB, Auhl M, Munteanu SE. Effects of indoor footwear on balance and gait patterns in community-dwelling older women. Gerontology. 2017;63:129-136.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>La Trobe University Faculty of Health Sciences Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Plenty Rd and Kingsbury Dr
Bundoora
Victoria 3086</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>FHEC14/254</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Hylton B Menz</name>
      <address>La Trobe Sport and Exercise Medicine Research Centre
School of Allied Health
College of Science, Health and Engineering
Kingsbury Drive
La Trobe University
Bundoora, Victoria 3086
</address>
      <phone>+61394795801</phone>
      <fax>+61394795415</fax>
      <email>h.menz@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Hylton B Menz</name>
      <address>La Trobe Sport and Exercise Medicine Research Centre
School of Allied Health
College of Science, Health and Engineering
Kingsbury Drive
La Trobe University
Bundoora, Victoria 3086</address>
      <phone>+61394865274</phone>
      <fax>+61394795415</fax>
      <email>h.menz@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Hylton B Menz</name>
      <address>La Trobe Sport and Exercise Medicine Research Centre
School of Allied Health
College of Science, Health and Engineering
Kingsbury Drive
La Trobe University
Bundoora, Victoria 3086</address>
      <phone>+61394865274</phone>
      <fax>+61394795415</fax>
      <email>h.menz@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Hylton B Menz</name>
      <address>La Trobe Sport and Exercise Medicine Research Centre
School of Allied Health
College of Science, Health and Engineering
Kingsbury Drive
La Trobe University
Bundoora, Victoria 3086</address>
      <phone>+61394865274</phone>
      <fax>+61394795415</fax>
      <email>h.menz@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>