<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371881">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001634460p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Ivabradine in the Prevention of Cardiac Injury in patients undergoing major Orthopaedic surgery.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Ivabradine in the Prevention of Peri-operative Myocardial Injury in patients undergoing major Orthopaedic surgery,</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1190-0434 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>IPMI</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac injury</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mortality</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Orthopaedic Surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients undergoing major Orthopaedic Surgery will be randomised to receive Ivabradine (Arm 1) above standard of care, or no intervention (Arm 2: usual standard of care).

Ivabradine will be dosed at 5mg, orally, twice a day for patients with initial heart rate of 60-90 beats per minute (at randomisation), OR 7.5mg orally twice a day for heart rates of &gt;90 beats per minute. 

First dose of medication will commence between 2 - 48 hours prior to surgery, and continue for a total of 7 days. Once a patient is scheduled for major orthopaedic surgery (with an estimate of date and time), information regarding trial will be provided. Once informed consent is obtained, randomisation will take place and first dose of medication commenced immediately after randomisation. If surgery is expected to be delayed by more than 48 hours, the patient will be withdrawn from study, as it does not fit with the intended study population (requiring emergent surgery). If surgery is expected to take place within 2 hours of study medication becoming available to the patient, the patient will be withdrawn as well, as it is considered too short a period for the medication to reach effect pre-operatively.

All patients will be interviewed at 30 days, and compliance will be assessed accordingly.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will receive standard of care (without any additional intervention). Standard  of care consists of routine monitoring of heart rate and blood pressure. Clinically significant tachycardia (rates above 100 bpm), bradycardia (rates below 50 bpm), and hypotension (systolic blood pressure below 90 mmHg and symptomatic) will be thoroughly investigated and treated, by the discretion of the attending clinician.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peri-operative myocardial injury (PMI) after undergoing major orthopaedic surgery. PMI is defined by troponin I levels above 0.04 mcg/L (if baseline was 0.04 mcg/L or less), or rise in blood levels of troponin I above 20% (if baseline was above 0.04 mcg/L).

Troponin I levels will be measured from bloods samples, collected at randomisation, and days 1, 2 and 3 post-operatively.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-operative days 1, 2, of 3.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinically significant hypotension, defined by symptomatic systolic blood pressure below 90 mmHg requiring active intervention, such as intravenous fluids or vasopressors, at the discretion of the treating clinician.

This outcome will be assessed from the review of medical records, based on daily blood pressure charts, as well as clinical notes from the attending physician.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-operative days 1, 2, and 3.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint>30-day and 1 year.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients above the age of 60 undergoing major Orthopaedic surgery (related to long bones, such as femur fractures), who understand and willing to comply with study activities.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Bradycardia (heart rates below 60 beats per minute)
Current Ivabradine (study intervention drug) use
Patient's with pacemaker</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome of PMI will be calculated and reported by cumulative incidence, and compared between the treatment arms for significant differences. Study end point analysis will be conducted on an intention-to-treat principle, as well as the per-protocol basis.

All time-to-event outcomes (such as mortality, myocardial infarction and stroke) will be calculated from the date of randomisation to the date of first documented event, and examined by time-to-event survival analysis (log rank test), and presented in a Kaplan-Meier curve. Cox Proportional Hazard models will be used to examine a range of covariates and their possible interactions. 

Descriptive statistics will be presented as counts and percentage frequencies, mean +/- standard deviation (SD) or median with inter-quartile range (IQR) to summarise patient characteristics and outcomes. Categorical variables will be evaluated using the Chi-square test or Fishers Exact test on occasions of frequencies of less than 5. Continuous variables will be analysed with logistic regression. Multivariate logistic regression will be used to identify significant correlations, with only variables having a p-value of &lt;0.1 on univariate analysis being included in the multivariate analysis. A two-tailed p-value of 0.05 was considered indicative of statistical significance.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Northern Hospital - Epping</hospital>
    <postcode>3076 - Epping</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Cardiology, Northern Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>185 Cooper Street, Epping VIC 3076.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Cardiology, Northern Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>185 Cooper Street, Epping VIC 3076.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>During or after a major operation (such as bones or joints operations, also known as orthopaedic operations), our body increases its heart rate as a response to the stress of the surgery. As the heart pumps faster to manage the stress, it can sometimes damage itself in the process. As previous study observed that up to 52% of patients undergoing major orthopaedic operations demonstrated some evidence of injury to the heart, and these patients have poorer clinical outcomes.

This has led to previous studies examining the benefits of heart rate lowering agents to prevent damage to the heart after surgery, to improve clinical outcomes. Unfortunately, many heart rate lowering agents have a common side effect of lowering the blood pressure as well. Hence, whilst these trials demonstrated promising benefit in reducing damage to the heart, they caused significant problems with low blood pressure.

Ivabradine is an agent that reduces heart rate, but does not drop blood pressure. It is currently approved for use in Australia for another condition called chronic heart failure. But given its unique properties, we postulate that it can reduce damage to the heart after a major operation as well, without the negative effect of causing low blood pressure. As a result, this trial was conceived to examine this effect.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Health Human Reseach Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>185 Cooper Street Epping 3076 VIC</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371881-IPMI_Study Protocol.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371881-IPMI_PICF.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>William van Gaal</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiology
The Northern Hospital
185 Cooper Street, Epping, VIC 3076</address>
      <phone>+61384058000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>william.vangaal@nh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dominic Chow</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiology
The Northern Hospital
185 Cooper Street, Epping, VIC 3076</address>
      <phone>+61384058000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dominic.chow2@nh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dominic Chow</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiology
The Northern Hospital
185 Cooper Street, Epping, VIC 3076</address>
      <phone>+61384058000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dominic.chow2@nh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dominic chow</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiology
The Northern Hospital
185 Cooper Street, Epping, VIC 3076</address>
      <phone>+61384058000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dominic.chow2@nh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>