<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370245">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000320459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cerebral oxygenation and carbon dioxide in patients undergoing surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of cerebral oxygenation in response to changes in arterial carbon dioxide in patients undergoing major surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1180-2285 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>Not applicable</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral blood flow</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Postoperative confusion</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Mild Hypercapnia Group

Patient with age greater than 50 years undergoing major surgery of at least 2 hours duration with be treated with controlled ventilation maintaining an arterial CO2 level (PaCO2) between 45 to 55 mmHg. The duration of mild hypercapnia will be from induction of anaesthesia to end of the surgical procedure i.e. skin closure. Controlled ventilation will be managed by the anaesthetist responsible for the conduct of the case. The target CO2 will be achieved by adjusting the minute ventilation on the ventilator by changing the respiratory rate, tidal volume, or adjusting both of these variables. These will  be adjusted by the treating clinical anaesthetist by following a standardised algorithm:-  first the respiratory rate will be adjusted by 2 breaths/min. The blood gas will then be repeated 5-minutes later. Second, if the CO2 is still not within target rage, the tidal volume will be adjusted by 20%. These steps will be repeated until the target CO2 is achieved.  Once the target CO2 has been achieved,  adherence to the intervention i.e. maintaining an arterial CO2 level between 45 to 55 mmHg, will be verified by the clinical anaesthetist checking the PaCO2 on arterial blood gases at hourly intervals. Blood gases will be performed on a blood gas analyser located in the theatre complex.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Control Group/Normocapnia Group

Patient with age greater than 50 years undergoing major surgery of at least 2 hours duration with be treated with controlled ventilation maintaining an arterial CO2 level (PaCO2) between 35 to 40 mmHg. The duration of mild hypercapnia will be from induction of anaesthesia to end of the surgical procedure i.e. skin closure. Controlled ventilation will be managed by the anaesthetist responsible for the conduct of the case. The target CO2 will be achieved by adjusting the minute ventilation on the ventilator by changing the respiratory rate, tidal volume, or adjusting both of these variables. These will  be adjusted by the treating clinical anaesthetist by following a standardised algorithm:-  first the respiratory rate will be adjusted by 2 breaths/min. The blood gas will then be repeated 5-minutes later. Second, if the CO2 is still not within target rage, the tidal volume will be adjusted by 20%. These steps will be repeated until the target CO2 is achieved.  Once the target CO2 has been achieved,  adherence to the intervention i.e. maintaining an arterial CO2 level between 35 to 40 mmHg, will be verified by the clinical anaesthetist checking the PaCO2 on arterial blood gases at hourly intervals. Blood gases will be performed on a blood gas analyser located in the theatre complex.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cerebral oxygenation measured with non-invasive  cerebral oximetry using SedLine(R) brain function monitor (Masimo Corp Inc, USA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured continuously commencing prior to induction of anaesthesia until completion of surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraoperative end-tidal CO2. Measurement will be done on an ABL Blood Gas Analyzer with a fully automated micromode.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to anaesthesia and at completion of surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraoperative plasma pH. Measurement will be done on an ABL Blood Gas Analyzer with a fully automated micromode.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to anaesthesia and at completion of surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraoperative plasma bicarbonate. Measurement will be done on an ABL Blood Gas Analyzer with a fully automated micromode.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to anaesthesia and at completion of surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraoperative base excess.  Measurement will be done on an ABL Blood Gas Analyzer with a fully automated micromode.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to anaesthesia and at completion of surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intraoperative plasma potassium. Measurement will be done on an ABL Blood Gas Analyzer with a fully automated micromode.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline prior to anaesthesia and at completion of surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postoperative delirium. Measurement will be done using the "Confusion Assessment Method" (CAM).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperative Day 1</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients (age &gt; 50 years) undergoing major surgery (greater than 2 hours duration)  that require the routine use of an arterial line for continuous blood pressure monitoring and intermittent positive pressure ventilation via an endotracheal tube as part of standard anaesthesia care.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. All patients aged less than 50 years
2. Patients undergoing cardiac surgery
3. Intracranial procedures
4. Glasgow Coma Score &lt; 15
5. Thoracic surgery requiring for one lung isolation
6. Moderate pulmonary hypertension (MPA greater than or equal to 40 mmHg)
7. American Society of Anaesthesiologists (ASA) physical status V</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All adult patients undergoing major surgery who require controlled ventilation and invasive monitoring using an arterial line will be evaluated preoperatively at the anaesthesia pre-admissions clinic at least 1-2 weeks prior to surgery. Patients will be identified for study entry by the investigators, an anaesthetist or research co-ordinator acting on behalf of the principle investigators by surveillance of patients in the pre-admissions clinic.  Informed written consent in the form of a Participant Information and Consent Form (PICF) will then be obtained. 

Once informed consent has been obtained, randomisation will be by means of sealed opaque envelopes with permuted blocks of variable size. Each envelope will contain a study arm allocation with the partial pressure of CO2 allocated i.e. normocapnia (PaCO2 35-40mmHg) or Mild hypercapnia  (PaCO2 45-55mmHg) </concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation will be used using computer generated software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Normal  cerebral saturations (rSO2) prior  to  the  induction  of  general  anaesthesia,  range  from  60%  to  80%. Sample size calculations for this study are based on normal rSO2 values for awake patients.  Sample  size  calculations  used  inferences  for  means  and  comparing two  independent  samples. We consider a 15% change in absolute rSO2 values from baseline to be clinically important. Therefore, assuming a mean  rSO2 of 65% in the normocapnic  group  (mu1),  and  an  15%  increase  in rSO2 values  to  75%  in  the  mild hypercapnic group (mu2) and sigma/common standard deviation of  9.5%, with an a-value of (type I error rate) of 0.05, and a desired power of 90%, 19 participants will be required in each group.  To allow for any breaches in protocol, we will randomise 20 subjects in each group. A total of 40 participants will be included.
  
Statistical analysis will be performed using computerized software (SPSS for Windows version 12.0). For data that is non-normally distributed a Mann-Whitney test will be used and normally distributed data will be compared using the Student T test. Ordinal and nominal data will be compared using Chi square analysis. A p&lt;0.05 will be considered significant. Correlation coefficients will be used to measure how strong the relationship is between changes in PaCO2 and cerebral oximetry. Repeated measures ANOVA will be used to examine changes in mean CO2 and cerebral oximetry over the duration of surgery. Where appropriate, a mixed linear regression model will be used to adjust for variables such as age, gender and duration of surgery.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/03/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>40</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>14/04/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deparments of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Measurement of actual cerebral blood flow during surgery is difficult due to the invasive or unpractical nature of the measurement tools needed. In contrast, cerebral oximetry is the continuous non-invasive measurement of cerebral oxygenation (amount of oxygen in the blood) and perfusion (the delivery of blood to the tissues of the brain). This allows anaesthetists to make critical decisions to maximise oxygen delivery and improve patient outcomes. Cerebral oximetry has been studied for more than 30 years and been commercially available for more than 2 decades.

Numerous studies demonstrate that increases in blood carbon dioxide (PaCO2) increase blood flow to the brain. Carbon dioxide is a normal waste product of body metabolism, and is eliminated via the lungs. However, there are no physiological studies to date comparing the effects of normal blood carbon dioxide (normocapnia - defined as PaCO2 levels between 35-40 mmHg) and mildly elevated carbon dioxide levels (mild hypercapnia - defined as PaCO2 levels between 45-55 mmHg) on cerebral oximetry in patients undergoing major surgery.

The primary aim of this study is to evaluate the effects of changes in PaCO2 on cerebral oximetry in patients undergoing major surgery. Secondary aims include the evaluation of the effects of normocapnia and mild hypercapnia on acid base blood variables, serum potassium levels, and postoperative delirium.

A total of 40 subjects will be included at the Austin Hospital</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084, Australia </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/01/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/Austin/488</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370245-HREC Approval Letter For Study.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital, 145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg, VIC, 3084</address>
      <phone>+61394965000</phone>
      <fax>+61394596421</fax>
      <email>laurence.weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital, 145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg, VIC, 3084</address>
      <phone>+61394965000</phone>
      <fax>+61394596421</fax>
      <email>laurence.weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital, 145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg, VIC, 3084</address>
      <phone>+61394965000</phone>
      <fax>+61394596421</fax>
      <email>laurence.weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Laurence Weinberg</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia, Austin Hospital, 145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg, VIC, 3084</address>
      <phone>+61394965000</phone>
      <fax>+61394596421</fax>
      <email>laurence.weinberg@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>