<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373254">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000982314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Phase I, Double-Blind, Randomized Study of Daily, Twice-Weekly and Once-Weekly APL 2 in Healthy Volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase I, Double-Blind, Randomized Study of Daily, Twice-Weekly and Once-Weekly APL 2 in Healthy Volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>None</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Paroxysmal Nocturnal Hemoglobinuria (PNH)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects in Cohort 1 will be randomly assigned to treatment with APL-2 360 mg (4 subjects) or matching placebo (1 subject) by subcutaneous injection (SC) once daily for 28 days. Subjects in Cohort 2 will be randomly assigned to treatment with APL-2 1,300 mg (4 subjects) or matching placebo (1 subject) SC twice weekly for 28 days. Subjects in Cohort 3 will be randomly assigned to treatment with APL-2 2,600 mg (4 subjects) or matching placebo (2 subjects) SC once per week for 28 days. Subjects in Cohort 4 will receive APL-2 or placebo SC for 28 days but the exact dose and dose frequency will be determined following evaluation of safety, tolerability and pharmacokinetics parameters in previous cohorts. The Subjects will participate in one cohort only. Cohort1 and Cohort 2 will be conducted in parallel. Cohort 3 will be conducted after completion of Cohort 1 and Cohort 2. Cohort 4 is an optional cohort which may be conducted after completion of Cohort 3.
Doses will be administered by healthcare professionals at the study site.
Subjects will attend a Screening visit (Day -28 to Day -14), reside in the clinic for 35 days from Day -1 (the day before the first dose) until Day 35, and return to the clinic for 3 follow-up visits on Day 42, 56, and 70, and for a final exit visit on Day 84. </interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (subcutaneous injection of acetate buffered sorbitol solution) </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The pharmacokinetics of daily, twice a week and once a week regimens of SC APL-2  in healthy volunteers. Noncompartmental PK parameters of AUC0-24, AUCtau, kel, Cmax, tmax, CLss/F, Vz/F, t1/2, Cssav, %fluctuation, %swing, and Accumulation index (as appropriate) will be calculated from serum concentrations of APL-2 for Day 1 and/or for Day 29. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the study, blood samples will be collected for pharmacokinetic (PK) testing, including a blood sample before dosing and at 1, 2, 4, 8, and 12 hours post-dosing on Day 1, and then once per day on Day 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 15, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 35, 42, 56, 79, and 84.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The safety and tolerability of daily, twice a week and once a week regimens of SC APL-2  in healthy volunteers. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the study, routine clinical tests will be conducted, including vital signs, ECGs, and blood and urine tests. Vital signs will be recorded at screening, upon check-in to the clinic on the day before dosing, and on Day 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23, 24 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 42, 56, 79, and 84. ECGs will be recorded at screening, and on Day 1, 8, 15, 22, 25, 29, 35, 42, 56, 79, and 84. Blood samples will be collected for safety testing at screening, at check-in on the day before dosing, and on Day 7, 14, 21, 28, 35, 56, and 84. Urine samples will be collected for safety testing at screening, at check-in on the day before dosing, and on Day 7, 14, 21, 28, 35, and 84. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The pharmacodynamics (PD) of daily, twice a week and once a week regimens of SC APL-2  in healthy volunteers. PD assessments include the serum complement activation markers  CH50, AP50, C3, and C3a.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the study, blood samples will be collected to measure serum complement activation markers (CH50, AP50, C3, and C3a), including blood samples at screening and on Day1, 8, 15, 22, 25, 29, 35, 42, 56, 79, and 84.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Medically healthy adults

Weigh more than 49 kg and less than 91 kg and have a BMI higher than 18.4 kg/m2 and lower than 32.1 kg/m2.

Have been vaccinated against Neisseria meningitidis, Streptococcus pneumoniae, and Haemophilus influenza within two years or willing to receive vaccinations. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Mentally or legally incapacitated or has significant emotional problems or has a history of a significant medical or psychiatric condition or a history of hypersensitivity to compounds related to APL-2 or a history of chronic infections or a recent active infection or recent surgery.
Use of any prescription or non-prescription medications, herbal remedies, or vitamin supplements within the last 14 days 
Blood donation or significant blood loss within previous 56 days or plasma donation within previous 7 days
Participation in another clinical trial within the previous 28 days
Female subjects who are pregnant or lactating</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A statistician will prepare a Randomization Schedule and send a copy to the Clinical Trial Pharmacist. The Pharmacist will fill dosing syringes with either APL-2 or placebo, and will label the syringes in a blinded fashion in accordance with the Randomization Schedule (i.e. the label for each syringe will include the Randomization Number but will not include the identity of the treatment). The Randomization Schedule will not be made available to the clinical trial team except for the Pharmacists. 
Subjects who complete the screening assessments and meet all of the eligibility criteria will be enrolled into the study and will be assigned a unique Randomisation Number. 
Randomisation Numbers will be comprised of the letter R followed by a four-digit number of the format ‘Rprnn’, where p denotes the cohort number (i.e. for Cohort 1, p=1), r is a replacement indicator and nn is a sequential randomisation number, i.e. R1001, R1002, etc. If a subject is replaced, the digit represented by r will be sequentially increased by one, e.g. R2003 would be replaced by R2103. The replacement subject will be administered the same treatment allocated to the original participant, as indicated by the last two digits of the randomisation number (i.e. 03 for participant R2003 and R2103). 
Dosing syringes will be dispensed to the subject with the corresponding Randomisation Number and the injections will be administered by blinded study personnel or by personnel who will not be involved in the study assessments. </concealment>
    <sequence>A computerised randomisation schedule will be created by a statistician who is not otherwise involved in the study. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>There will be up to 4 cohorts of 5 subjects. Cohort 1 and Cohort 2 will include will be enrolled in parallel and each will include 4 subjects randomised to receive APL-2 and 1 subject randomised to receive placebo. Cohort 3 will be conducted after completion of Cohort 1 and Cohort 2 and will include 2 Sentinel subjects with 1 randomised to receive APL-2 and 1 randomised to receive placebo, followed by 4 more subjects one week later, with 3 randomised to received APL-2 and 1 randomised to receive placebo. Cohort 4 is an optional cohort of 5 or 6 subjects which may be conducted after completion of Cohort 3. Subjects will participate in one cohort only. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics / pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Given the exploratory nature of the study no formal statistical hypothesis testing will be performed. As no formal hypothesis testing will be conducted, the study sample sizes were not based on statistical power calculations.
Data will be presented by cohort/dose (including placebo where applicable), study day and nominal time post-dose (if appropriate). Subjects receiving placebo will be pooled across dosing cohorts for summaries. All data will be listed by cohort and dose (including placebo where applicable).
PK parameters for APL-2 will be computed from the individual serum concentrations-time data, using actual sample times and a non-compartmental approach. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>22</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>0</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Nucleus Network - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Clinical Network Services Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 4, 88 Jephson Street
Toowong QLD 4066 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Apellis Pharmaceuticals Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>6400 Westwind Way, Suite A 
Crestwood KY 40014 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>APL-2 is a small peptide coupled to each end of a linear polyethylene glycol (PEG) chain. The peptide portion of the drug binds to complement C3 and is a broad inhibitor of the complement cascade, a biological process that is part of innate immunity. The PEG chain imparts longer residence time in the body after administration of the drug. 
APL-2 is being developed for the management of paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria (PNH) and daily SC administration of APL-2 is being investigated in two ongoing studies in patients with PNH. However, daily SC infusions are burdensome. The aim of this study is to evaluate and confirm whether less frequent dosing such as twice or once a week is safe and associated with a pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic profile likely to provide clinical benefits comparable to the daily SC infusions. 
An exploratory objective of the study is to compare the pharmacodynamics (PD) of daily, twice a week, and once a week dose regimens of APL 2 in healthy volunteers. 
For each subject, the study will consist of:
* Screening Visit(s) between Day -28 and Day -14 
* Admission into clinic on Day -1 
* First APL-2 dose on Day 1
* Discharge from clinic on Day 35
* Follow-up visits on Day 42, 56, and 70
* Exit visit on Day 84
The total duration of each subjects participation is expected to be approximately 112 days.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>89 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/09/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>307/17</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jason Lickliter</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network Limited
Level 5, Burnet Institute, AMREP Precinct
89 Commercial Road
Melbourne VIC 3004 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 8906 </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9076 8911 </fax>
      <email>j.lickliter@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lil Edis</name>
      <address>Apellis Australia Pty Ltd
Level 16, 120 Edward Street 
Brisbane Queensland 4000 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 6236 9091</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lil@apellis.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lil Edis</name>
      <address>Apellis Australia Pty Ltd
Level 16, 120 Edward Street 
Brisbane Queensland 4000 </address>
      <phone>  + 61 2 6236 9091</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lil@apellis.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lil Edis</name>
      <address>Apellis Australia Pty Ltd
Level 16, 120 Edward Street 
Brisbane Queensland 4000 </address>
      <phone>+61262369091</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lil@apellis.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>