<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81902">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/03/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/03/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000166471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of Mindfulness-Based Cognitive Therapy Compared to Treatment-as-usual for Preventing Depressive Relapse in Subjects at Very High Risk</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In people who have had at least three prior episodes of major depressive disorder is mindfulness based cognitive therapy more effective than treatment as usual in preventing relapse of major depression.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Depression Awareness Recovery Effectiveness (DARE)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NHMRC Grant: 436897</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Major Depressive Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is a randomised controlled trial, whereby participants will be randomised to mindfulness-based cognitive therapy (MBCT) or treatment as usual (TAU).  

Mindfulness-based cognitive therapy (MBCT) is a manualised group based intervention designed to reduce rates of relapse of MDD. It integrates aspects of cognitive therapy with components of a mindfulness-based stress reduction program. It teaches clients to become more aware of, and to relate differently to, thoughts, feelings and bodily sensations; in particular, to view thoughts and feelings as passing events in the mind rather than as necessarily reflecting reality. The program teaches skills in disengagement from habitual (automatic) dysfunctional cognitive routines, especially depression-related ruminative thought patterns.  Its efficacy in doing this has been demonstrated in two randomised controlled trials.  It is now included in the UK Governments National Institute of Clinical Excellence (NICE) Guidelines for prevention of depressive recurrence for patients who have suffered three or more episodes of depression. It has not been similarly recommended in other countries.

After an initial individual orientation session the MBCT program is delivered by an instructor in eight weekly 2 hour group training sessions involving up to 10 clients. Optional booster sessions will be available on a 3-monthly basis following completion of the core program. Sessions incorporate mindfulness practices including meditation and also cognitive-behavioural therapy exercises. Homework for participants includes formal daily meditation practices and exercises for the development of mindful awareness within everyday activity. Emphasis later in the course is on combining cognitive-behaviour therapy (CBT) techniques such as conventional CBT activity scheduling with meditative practices into synergistic strategies for responding to negative mood states. Finally the course participants develop personal documentation detailing warning signs and related action plans, as well as considering how to maintain practices and habits they have found helpful.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control condition will be treatment as usual. Participants will be encouraged to attend their regular treating practitioner(s) as they would if they were not involved in the trial. Also, both MBCT and treatment as usual groups are encouraged to use their regular research data monitoring of depressive symptoms as an aid to early recognition of relapse of MDD and to seek usual care if indicated in a process described as Depression Relapse Active Monitoring (DRAM).  Antidepressant medication and other psychological interventions will be permitted in both arms of the trial if treating practitioners consider necessary. Such interventions will be monitored through collection of service contact information in both groups.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relapse of Major Depressive Disorder (MDD).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two year follow up following MBCT group, so approximately 26 months total for both groups. Status monitored with short questionnaire monthly, more extensive questionnaires three monthly and face to face interviews after 14 and 26 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to relapse of MDD</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to clinical intervention for MDD</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monthly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of time spent in depressive episodes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Based on monthly responses and also yeaarly interviews</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety symptoms </outcome>
      <timepoint>Three monthly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three monthly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social functioning</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three monthly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health care costs</outcome>
      <timepoint>Annual review</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to routinely prescribed antidepressant medication.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three monthly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rumination</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three monthly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neuroticism</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three monthly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Open-ness to experience</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three monthly</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Ability to speak and read English fluently; and meeting DSM-IV criteria for three previous major depressive episodes. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A current episode of MDD; current symptoms of a psychotic disorder, or a past diagnosis of a psychotic disorder where the treating clinician believes the therapy may be contraindicated; current significant eating disorder or obsessive-compulsive disorder, organic mental disorder or pervasive developmental delay; current borderline or antisocial personality disorder; current alcohol or drug dependency other than tobacco; or current benzodiazepine intake of more than 20mg diazepam equivalent a day.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrolment will be through face to face interview with a researcher at which point informed consent will be invited. Allocation to treatment will be by a statistician in another centre.</concealment>
    <sequence>Stratified and using computer software, stratification according to gender, status in regards to prescribed medication and referral origin (Primary or Specialist services)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Assessors will as far as possible be blinded</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>196</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash University, Clayton 3800</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (Grant number: 436897)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Southern Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Clayton Campus
246 Clayton Road, Clayton.
Victoria 3168</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>More than one in twenty Australians experience depression in a single year and it is commonly a relapsing disorder.  At least 60% of people who have had a depressive episode will have another, the vast majority within two years of the index episode.  For those who have had three episodes, the relapse rate is 90%.  Even with guideline-based pharmacotherapy relapse is not uncommon so there is a need for non-pharmacological approaches to relapse prevention. The economic burden of depression in Australia has been estimated as perhaps 2.8 billion annually. Mindfulness-based cognitive therapy (MBCT) is an innovative psychological treatment, combining principles of cognitive therapy and mindfulness meditation.  It is designed to prevent relapse in people who have recovered from depressive episodes.  MBCT aims to teach people to become more aware of, and to related differently to, their thoughts, feelings and bodily sensations; in particular, to view these thoughts and feelings as passing events in the mind rather than identifying with them.  Through gaining these skills in increased awareness of thoughts and feelings, participants in the treatment learn to avoid negative ruminations, which have a powerful role in triggering relapses of depression.  This project will examine the effectiveness of MBCT for the first time in Australians with a history of recurring depression.  The primary aim of this project is to determine if MBCT when added to existing treatment as usual (TAU) is more effective than TAU in preventing depressive relapse over a two-year period in people who have had at least three prior episodes of depression.  The study also aims to establish whether the mechanisms by which MBCT is proposed to work  by decreasing rumination, increasing levels of mindfulness and self-awareness  do in fact operate.  We also hope to establish whether MBCT also has any impact on anxiety, another disabling condition that commonly occurs with depression.  Cost utility analysis will enable specific policy recommendations for Australia. Positive findings from this study would lead to MBCT having a high degree of evidence-based support examining its use, so that it could be considered as an intervention for which high, rather than moderate, levels of evidence exist. Hence, if outcomes are positive, this study would provide internationally significant findings to support consideration of inclusion of this treatment into guidelines for routine clinical management of the serious and disabling problem of recurrent depression.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.dare.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Publication. Shawyer, F., Meadows, G.N., Judd, F., Martin, P.R., Segal, Z., Piterman, L. (2012). The DARE study of relapse prevention in depression: design for a phase 1/2 translational randomised controlled trial involving mindfulness-based cognitive therapy and supported self monitoring. BMC Psychiatry, 12, 3.

Oral presentation. Shawyer, F., Meadows, G., Judd, F., Martin, P., Segal, Z., Piterman, L. Findings from the DARE study, a multisite study of MBCT with two year follow up, focusing on subgroups and time course. 10th Annual International Scientific Conference for Clinicians, Researchers and Educators: Investigating and Integrating Mindfulness in Medicine, Health Care and Society 28 March  1 April 2012, Norwood, USA.

Poster presentation. Shawyer, F., Meadows, G., Judd, F., Martin, P., Segal, Z., Piterman, L. A randomised controlled trial of mindfulness-based cognitive therapy: study protocol and design highlighting phase 1 and phase 2 translational research elements. 10th Annual International Scientific Conference for Clinicians, Researchers and Educators: Investigating and Integrating Mindfulness in Medicine, Health Care and Society 28 March  1 April 2012, Norwood, USA.

Oral presentation. Prowse, P., Meadows, G., Shawyer, F., Segal, Z. An exploratory study into the effectiveness of fidelity scales in the delivery of Mindfulness-Based Cognitive Therapy as part of the Depression Awareness Recovery Effectiveness (DARE) Program in Australia. 10th Annual International Scientific Conference for Clinicians, Researchers and Educators: Investigating and Integrating Mindfulness in Medicine, Health Care and Society 28 March  1 April 2012, Norwood, USA.

Oral presentation. Meadows, G., Shawyer, F., Özmen, M., Judd, F., Martin, P., Segal, Z., Piterman, L. Introducing the DARE study, a multisite study of MBCT with two year follow up and including health economic evaluation. 10th Annual International Scientific Conference for Clinicians, Researchers and Educators: Investigating and Integrating Mindfulness in Medicine, Health Care and Society 28 March  1 April 2012, Norwood, USA.

Oral presentation. Shawyer, F., Meadows, G., Judd, F., Piterman, L, Martin, P., Segal, Z., Piterman, L. Mindfulness-Based Cognitive Therapy for preventing relapse in recurrent depression: outcomes from the first year follow up of a randomised controlled trial. 34th Australian Association for Cognitive &amp; Behaviour Therapy National Conference 26-30 October 2011, Sydney, Australia. 

Oral presentation. Shawyer, F., Meadows, G., Judd, F., Martin, P., Segal, Z., Piterman, L. Preliminary findings from a randomized controlled trial of Mindfulness-based cognitive therapy for recurrent depression. 27th International Congress of Applied Psychology, 11-16 July 2010, Melbourne, Australia. 

Poster presentation. Shawyer, F., Meadows, G., Judd, F., Martin, P., Segal, Z., Piterman, L. Does mindfulness-based cognitive therapy improve awareness and reduce rumination in recurrent depression and, if so, does antidepressant medication help? World Congress of Behavioral and Cognitive Therapies, June 2-5 2010, Boston, USA.

Poster presentation. Meadows, G., Shawyer, F., Graham, A. An exploratory effectiveness study with MBCT: findings and design issues. Investigating and Integrating Mindfulness in Medicine, Health Care and Society. 8th Annual International Scientific Conference. April 7-11 2010, Worcester, Massachusetts, USA.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/05/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>07056B</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/03/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>280/07</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Barwon Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/02/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>07/86</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peninsula Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/01/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2007/53</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Standing Committee on Ethics in Research involving Humans.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash University, Vic 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/07/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF07/1275-2007/0191MCC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Graham Meadows</name>
      <address>Southern Synergy, Monash University Notting Hill Campus, c/- Wellington Rd Clayton, Victoria 3800</address>
      <phone>613 99029696</phone>
      <fax>613 9902 9900</fax>
      <email>Graham.Meadows@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Graham Meadows</name>
      <address>Southern Synergy, Monash University Notting Hill Campus, c/- Wellington Rd Clayton, Victoria 3800</address>
      <phone>613 99029696</phone>
      <fax>613 9902 9900</fax>
      <email>Graham.Meadows@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Graham Meadows</name>
      <address>Southern Synergy The Southern Health Adult Psychiatry Research Training &amp; Evaluation Centre. Southern Area Mental Health Services PO Box 956 Dandenong VIC 3175</address>
      <phone>03 9554 1847</phone>
      <fax>03 9554 1955</fax>
      <email>Graham.Meadows@med.monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>