<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373562">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001306303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The addition of a physical activity intervention within pulmonary rehabilitation on physical activity levels: a pilot study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The addition of a physical activity intervention within pulmonary rehabilitation on physical activity levels: a pilot study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Respiratory Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Materials: G-Sensor 3D tri-axial pedometers, Participant Physical Activity Diary.  Sedentary Behaviour Questionnaire (SBQ). Participant Physical Activity Log Sheet.

Procedures: 
Tasks for participants include:
- Complete consent form pre intervention
- Complete the Sedentary Behaviour Questionnaire pre and post intervention
- Wear the pedometer and fill out participant physical activity diary (record number of steps taken per day) for length of intervention (5 weeks).
- Attend standard pulmonary rehabilitation classes twice a week for 8 weeks.  Classes will be run by senior respiratory physiotherapists.  Each class will run for 60 mins and the participants will complete lower limb endurance exercises, lower limb strengthening exercises and upper limb strengthening exercises.

Mode of Delivery: Face to face on an individual basis between a senior respiratory physiotherapist and the participant.  The intervention will run once a week for 5 weeks. Each session will run for approximately 10-15 mins.  At these sessions the participant will have their steps per day for the last week recorded (from the pedometer).  They will then receive some counselling on how to improve their physical activity and then a new goal will be set for the next week. The new goal will aim to be a 5-10% increase on last weeks average daily step count.  However, the senior clinician will decide in concert with the participant a suitable goal for the upcoming week. The physiotherapist will record if the target is reached at the next session. 

Location: The intervention will take place at the pulmonary rehabilitation gym of each hospital or community health centre across the Northern Sydney Local Health District.

</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will attend standard pulmonary rehabilitation classes twice a week for eight weeks. Classes will be run by Senior Respiratory Physiotherapists.  Each class will run for 60 mins and the participants will complete lower limb endurance exercises, lower limb strengthening exercises and upper limb strengthening exercises.  The participants in the control group will not receive a pedometer, complete any physical activity counselling or goal setting or receive a physical activity diary.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in physical activity levels measured via steps per day.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial assessment prior to intervention (baseline).
Final assessment at Day 35 post intervention (final).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in sedentary behaviour time as measured in minutes per day using the Sedentary Behaviour Questionnaire (SBQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Initial assessment prior to intervention (baseline).
Final assessment at Day 35 post intervention (final).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Attending exercise rehabilitation
- Diagnosis of chronic respiratory disease
- Able to speak, read and write in English
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if they have cognitive impairment or who do not speak/read sufficient English to understand the sedentary behaviour questionnaire.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size Estimation: A total of 62 participants will be enrolled to ensure that 49 participants complete the study (accounts for a 20% drop-out rate). Forty-nine participants will be sufficient to provide 80% power to detect as significant, at the (two-sided) 5% level, a minimum 1100 steps improvement in the mean daily PA levels (i.e. which is the minimum important difference for daily steps) following pulmonary rehabilitation, assuming a standard deviation of 2000 steps per day.
Statistical Analysis Plan: The effects of the PA intervention will be determined by calculating the mean differences within the group for all outcomes from pre to post intervention using a paired t test.  Uncertainty about the size of the mean differences within groups will be quantified with 95% confidence intervals. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>2/10/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>62</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>14/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Manly Hospital - Manly</hospital>
    <hospital>Mona Vale Hospital - Mona Vale</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Hornsby Ku-ring-gai Hospital - Hornsby</hospital>
    <hospital>Ryde Hospital - Eastwood</hospital>
    <postcode>2095 - Manly</postcode>
    <postcode>2103 - Mona Vale</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>2077 - Hornsby</postcode>
    <postcode>2122 - Eastwood</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Chronic Disease Community Rehabilitation Service - Northern Sydney Local Health District - NSW Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Lodge - Building 37, 
Macquarie Hospital, 
Cnr Twin and Badajoz Rds, North Ryde NSW 2113
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Chronic Disease Community Rehabilitation Service - Northern Sydney Local Health District - NSW Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Lodge - Building 37, 
Macquarie Hospital, 
Cnr Twin and Badajoz Rds, North Ryde NSW 2113
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of this project is to evaluate the effects on physical actviity (PA) levels (daily steps) of the addition of a PA intervention (PA counselling and feedback [tri-axial pedometer]) into standard exercise rehabilitation in patients attending the CDCRS programs across the NSLHD. The hypothesis is that patients undertaking the PA intervention will increase their daily physical activity levels.  A secondary objective of this project is to evaluate the effects on sedentary behaviour levels of the addition of a PA intervention into standard exercise rehabilitation in patients attending the CDCRS programs across the NSLHD.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>NSLHD Research Office
Level 13, Kolling Building
Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/07/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LNR/17/HAWKE/173</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/04/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Alexander Alam</name>
      <address>The Lodge - Building 37, 
Macquarie Hospital, 
Cnr Twin and Badajoz Rds, North Ryde NSW 2113</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8877 4041</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8877 5370</fax>
      <email>alexander.alam@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Alexander Alam</name>
      <address>The Lodge - Building 37, 
Macquarie Hospital, 
Cnr Twin and Badajoz Rds, North Ryde NSW 2113</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8877 4041</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8877 5370</fax>
      <email>alexander.alam@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Alexander Alam</name>
      <address>The Lodge - Building 37, 
Macquarie Hospital, 
Cnr Twin and Badajoz Rds, North Ryde NSW 2113</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8877 4041</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8877 5370</fax>
      <email>alexander.alam@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Alexander Alam</name>
      <address>The Lodge - Building 37, 
Macquarie Hospital, 
Cnr Twin and Badajoz Rds, North Ryde NSW 2113</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8877 4041</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 8877 5370</fax>
      <email>alexander.alam@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>