<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347728">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/11/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001226998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MIHO Study - Milk drink to Improve the Health of Oocytes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A two week randomised, placebo-controlled, double blinded study of the efficacy of a novel milk drink for increasing follicular fluid insulin-like growth factor 1 concentration in women who respond poorly to ovarian stimulation during in vitro fertilisation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MIHO</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>in vitro fertilisation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fertility including in vitro fertilisation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will undergo their usual IVF treatment, but from the 3rd day of the IVF cycle they will be asked to consume 250ml of a milk-based drink in the morning and evening that will contain active components that might increase ovarian blood flow and follicular fluid insulin-like growth factor 1 concentrations, or a placebo. They will continue to consume the 250ml drink daily until the end of their IVF stimulation cycle. At the start and end of their cycle a blood sample will be collected to measure circulating IGF-1 concentrations and the concentrations of reproductive hormones. During their routine day 9/10 follicle tracking scan, blood flow to the ovaries will also be measured using ultrasound. When their eggs are retrieved at the end of their IVF cycle the follicular fluid surrounding the eggs will be collected and analysed for IGF-1 and reproductive hormone concentrations.</interventions>
    <comparator>standard IVF treatment with a flavoured milk drink with no active components</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>insulin-like growth factor 1 concentrations will be measured in follicular fluid using commercially available kits</outcome>
      <timepoint>egg retrieval operation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ovarian blood flow by Doppler ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 9/10 follicle tracking scan</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>reproductive hormone (Estradiol, progesterone, testosterone, FSH, hCG, AMH), lactacte and glucose concentrations will be measured in follicular fluid using commercially available kits</outcome>
      <timepoint>egg retrieval operation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>insulin-like growth factor 1 concentrations will be measured in blood serum samples using commercially available kits</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline (before IVF cycle) and egg retrieval operation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>IVF outcomes will be assessed by granulosa cell function by measuring follicle estrogen, progesterone and testosterone concentration using commercially available kits
and oocyte competence by measuring fertilisation rate, ability to form a good quality blastocyst embryo.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at time of oocyte retrieval (follicular fluid analysis) or first 5 days of embryology development (fertilization, embryo quality)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>pregnancy rates will be calculated using the number of viable fetal hearts seen on ultrasound per 100 embryos transferred</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 week gestation pregnancy scan</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Undergoing a gonadotrophin-releasing hormone antagonist cycle of IVF treatment and a poor responder to ovarian hyperstimulation. This includes meeting two of the following three criteria: 1. 40 years or older 2. previously only produced 3 or less mature eggs in response to maximal dose ovarian stimulation during IVF treatment 3. serum anti-mullerian hormone concentration &lt; 7.8 pmol/l or a total antral follicle count &lt;7 (both being accurate markers suggesting a reduced number of eggs left within your ovaries relative to your age).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>intolerant/allergic to cow's milk protein, lactose, soy, wheat, egg, gluten, nuts or seeds, concurrent use of human growth hormone, Elonva, long down regulation IVF cycle, oral corticosteroids (Prednisolone) therapy have used dehydroepiandrosterone therapy in last month</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Women who appear to be eligible for the study will be informed about the study by the principle investigator or their own treating doctor when attending
Repromed for their IVF treatment. Experimental therapy will be randomly allocated and allocation will be concealed from the participant and study staff. The randomization sequence will be computer generated by a third party not involved in the study. Treatment packs will be sequentially numbered and prepared with either active medication or placebo by a third party contractor. Both active and placebo powder used to produce the study milk drink will be identical in appearance and taste.</concealment>
    <sequence>Women will be randomised to one for three treatment beverages using a minimisation randomisation schedule to ensure equal numbers of patients in the two main types of diminished ovarian reserve in each group (women &lt;40yrs with low ovarian reserve and women &gt;40 yrs with age appropriate poor ovarian reserve).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/11/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>18/08/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>39</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA
5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Itek</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 546
Salisbury South SA 5106</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine if nutrients that have been shown to improve blood flow and increase circulating insulin-like growth factor 1 concentrations in the blood can improve both blood flow in the ovary and elevate the concentration of insulin-like growth factor 1 in the follicular fluid surrounding the eggs. The ability to increase the concentration of IGF-1 in follicular fluid surrounding the eggs in the ovary in this way may provide an inexpensive and simple alternative to growth hormone treatment for improving egg quality in patients undergoing IVF treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>none</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>26785</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kelton Tremellen</name>
      <address>Repromed Adelaide
180 Fullarton Road, 
Dulwich, SA 5065</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8333 8113</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8333 8188</fax>
      <email>KTremellen@repromed.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebecca Thomson</name>
      <address>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA
5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.thomson@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Rebecca Thomson</name>
      <address>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA
5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.thomson@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kelton Tremellen</name>
      <address>Repromed Adelaide
180 Fullarton Road
Dulwich SA 5056
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8333 8113</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>KTremellen@repromed.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>