<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81614">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/09/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/10/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000435583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exercise for women with lymphoedema</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised trial to evaluate the effect of  resistance training on volume of lymphoedema for women with
lymphoedema secondary to breast cancer.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Women with unilateral upper limb lymphoedema following breast cancer surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Exercise group: women will attend 3 times a week for 10 weeks to be instructed in a resistance training program aimed at improving upper limb muscle strength.Each session will last approximately 60 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control Group: will be requested to attend weekly for 10 weeks for an assessment of their lymphoedema. This assessment will take approximately 30 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in upper limb composition. Multi frequency bio-impedance (MFBIA) will be used to identify changes in tissue density, and in particular, extracellular fluid. In addition, measures of limb volume will be undertaken using a perometer and arm circumference measures with a tape measure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 10 weeks (or following the completion of training) and 6 months following the completion of training</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Maximal isometric shoulder strength will be measured objectively using a standardised protocol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures will be taken at baseline, 10 weeks (or following the completion of training) and 6 months following the completion of training.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Quality of Life will be assessed using the European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire Version 3 (QLQ-C30), a 30 item survey specific to cancer patients in conjunction with Breast Module (BR23), a 23 item survey specific to women with breast cancer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures will be taken at baseline, 10 weeks (or following the completion of training) and 6 months following the completion of training.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Have had unilateral surgery for breast cancer* have completed treatment for breast cancer at least 6 months ago* have unilateral upper limb lymphoedema* have had lymphoedema present for at least 6 months* finished treatment for lymphoedema at least 1 month ago* are willing to attend training and follow-up sessions* are willing to be randomised into either treatment group.* are able to understand written and spoken english.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Have metastatic cancer* have a pacemaker or other inbuilt stimulator* are pregnant* have a previous fracture, undergpne surgery in the upper limbs or suffer any neurological deficit or other injury to either upper limb that may interfere with test procedures.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>numbered opaque sealed envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>computer generated random allocation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The assessor will be blinded at the 10 week and 6 month measures</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>East Street Lidcombe NSW 2141</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>RT Hall Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Nexia court and co post office box h195 Australia square Sydney NSW 1214</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a study on the benefits of exercise for women with lymphoedema.

Who is it for?

You can join this study if you have arm swelling following breast cancer treatment, whether this is induced by surgery or radiotherapy. 

Trial details

Participants will be randomly divided into two groups. One group will attend a 60 minutes exercise program three times a week for 10 weeks, aimed at improving upper limb strength The other group will asked to attend for a 30 minute assessment of their lymphoedema each week for 10 weeks (the control group will not have an exercise program).  Both groups will have their lymphoedema assessed each week for 10 weeks.  The trial looks at any change in upper limb composition measured using a technique known as multifrequency bio-impedance (which is a way to measure tissue density, particularly the amount of fluid in the arm) and arm circumference at 10 weeks and 6 months following completion of treatment.

There is no standard intervention recommended for women with arm swelling.  The trial will determine the effects of vigorous supervised resistance training on arm lymphoedema.  The trial will document whether women with lymphoedema can use their affected arm in vigorous exercise.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/10/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>11-2004/4/7885</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Sharon Kilbreath</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health Sciences
University of Sydney
C42
PO Box 170
Lidcombe NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93519272</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93519160</fax>
      <email>s.kilbreath@fhs.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sharon Czerniec</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health Sciences
University of Sydney
C42
PO Box 170
Lidcombe NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93519545</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93519160</fax>
      <email>S.Czerniec@fhs.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>