<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367839">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/02/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000112561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Behavioural and Cognitive Changes During Self-Guided Internet-Delivered Cognitive-Behavioural Therapy for Anxiety and Depression: A Randomised Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Behavioural and Cognitive Changes During Self-Guided Internet-Delivered Cognitive-Behavioural Therapy for Anxiety and Depression: A Randomised Controlled Trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly allocated to either an active internet-delivered cognitive-behavioural therapy (iCBT) treatment group, or to a wait-list control group, who will receive the same iCBT treatment when the active treatment group has finished. The iCBT treatment course, The Wellbeing Course, is a 5-lesson program focusing on the management of anxiety and depression. All 5 Lessons will be administered online (via the internet); each lesson will be completed every 7 to 10 days. Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to complete. Participants will also have access to summaries of each lesson, and will read anonymous stories about other people with depression and anxiety, taking a further 20 minutes per summary. All participants will also receive weekly reminder emails informing them when lessons become available. The duration of the reminder emails will take an additional 2 minutes to access and read. The duration of the program is 8 weeks. Study questionnaires will be administered at application, pre-treatment, during the treatment, post-treatment, and 3 months post-treatment. These questionnaires at application, pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3-months follow up will take about 10-15 minutes to complete. The questionnaires administered during the treatment will take approximately 3 minutes to complete. The software presenting the iCBT treatment course will also record information to inform adherence to the intervention (e.g. lessons completed, download history of other treatment materials in the course, number of logins, and duration of logins)</interventions>
    <comparator>Wait-list control group

The Wait-list control group will begin the Wellbeing Course after the 8-week intervention period for the active treatment group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Health Questionnaire 9-Item (PHQ9), which is a measure of depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Application; pre-treatment; once per week throughout treatment; post-treatment, and; 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-Item (GAD7), which is a measure of anxiety.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Application; Pre-treatment; once per week throughout treatment; post-treatment, and; 3 month follow-up
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of Actions and Thoughts Scale (FATS)
This is a 24-item scale developed by the research team that measures the frequency of cognitions and behaviours related to mental health outcomes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Application; Pre-treatment; once per week throughout treatment; post-treatment, and; 3 month follow-up
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mini Social Phobia Inventory (MINI-SPIN):

This is a measure of social anxiety</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, post-treatment, 3-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction With Life Scale 5-item (SWLS), a measure of life satisfaction
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment; post-treatment, and; 3 month follow-up
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sheehan Disability Scale 5-item (SDS), which is a measure of general disability and impairment.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment; post-treatment, and; 3 month follow-up
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Panic Disorder Severity Rating Scale-Self Report (PDSS-SR). A measure of panic disorder symptoms</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, post-treatment, and 3-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>MINI diagnostic Interview.

A brief, structured interview for diagnosing mental health disorders.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-treatment, and 3-month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Self-reported difficulties with anxiety or depression.
- Internet access + Printer access
- Australian resident</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Receiving concurrent CBT
- Severe symptoms of depression
- Severe depression, suicidal intent or plan (PHQ-9 total score &gt; 23; or &gt;2 to PHQ-9 question assessing frequency of self-harm or suicide ideation)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants apply online via the clinic's website (www.ecentreclinic.org.au). Successful applications are followed by a telephone interview to confirm suitability for the trial. Randomisation will occur prior to application and concealment occurs through the use of locked and concealed cells in a spreadsheet, which recruitment staff are required to open serially.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomized using a list generated prior to the study via a software program (www.random.org) using permuted block randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analyses of clinical outcomes will be done using conservative intention-to-treat principles and using mixed-linear models analyses to handle missing data. Mixed-models are a robust statistical approach for analysing clinical trial data and these analyses will employ an appropriate covariance structure and maximum likelihood estimation, which provides unbiased estimates in the case of missing data; under the assumption that data is missing at random.

Mixed multilevel mediation analysis will also be conducted to investigate the FATS measure as a mediator of symptom change.


With alpha set at .05, and power at .80, a total sample size of 200 participants will be sufficient to observe medium and larger effect sizes (i.e. Cohen's D &gt;0.5) on outcome measures using mixed linear modelling, while hedging against attrition.

For multilevel mediation analysis, less is known about required sample size, as it is a relatively new statistical technique, and there is not much empirical data available on our constructs of interest. However, Li and Beretvas (2013) suggest that these models can successfully converge with a sample size of at least 80, and Preacher, Zhang, and Zyphur (2011), using simulated data, suggest that sample sizes between 100 and 300 have sufficient power, provided that the population intraclass correlation is high (&gt; .4), and the effect size is at least moderate (.3). Based on our previous single-group open trial, the pre-post within group effect size on our constructs of interest were large (&gt;.8), and based on sample data from our previous trials, the intraclass correlation is also high (&gt;.4), suggesting that a sample size of 200 will be sufficient to detect our effects of interest, and hedge against attrition.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>25/03/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>141</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>eCentreClinic, the Centre for Emotional Health (CEH), Macquarie University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>eCentreClinic, The Centre For Emotional Health (CEH), Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, North Ryde, NSW, 2109, Australia.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>eCentreClinic, the Centre for Emotional Health (CEH), Macquarie University
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>eCentreClinic, The Centre For Emotional Health (CEH), Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, North Ryde, NSW, 2109, Australia.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project is part of a research program examining the role that certain cognitions and behaviours play in mediating symptom reduction of internet-delivered cognitive behavioural therapy for depression and anxiety.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.ecentreclinic.org
</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Macquarie University, NSW, 2109, Australia.
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5201401119</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blake Dear</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic, The Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109.
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9979</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 8062</fax>
      <email>blake.dear@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Matthew Terides</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic, The Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109.
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 8724</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 8062</fax>
      <email>matthew.terides@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blake Dear</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic, The Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109.
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9979</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 8062</fax>
      <email>blake.dear@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blake Dear</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic, The Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109.
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9979</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 8062</fax>
      <email>blake.dear@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>