<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335546">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000441011</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Detection of Myocardial Fibrosis by Cardiac Magnetic Resonance relaxometry</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Detection of Myocardial Fibrosis by Cardiac Magnetic Resonance relaxometry in apparently healthy volunteers versus patients with high blood pressure with normal/ abnormal cardiac function</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>MYOCARDIAL FIBROSIS</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Fibrosis tissue accumulation is an integral feature of the adverse structural remodelling of cardiac tissue seen with hypertensive heart disease. Given the importance of fibrosis tissue in leading to myocardial dysfunction and failure. 
The volunteers and patients will undergo an Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) for one time only. 
MRI is a painless non-invasive technique that involves lying in a scanner to create image based on magnetic signal of the protons inside the human body.
Cardiac MRI relaxometry has variuos techniques, which includes standard magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) sequences including tagging, Modified Look-Locker Inversion recovery imaging (MOLLI), to early detection of myocardial fibrosis. These technique have ability to assess abnormal structure and function of the heart. The scanning takes  about 20 to 25 minutes for normal volunteers and the patients takes about 45 Minutes due to repeat of MRI technique after 8 minutes delay injection of MRI contrast agent. The patients will be injected by MRI contrast agent (Gadolinium) to assess any possibility of scarring tissue in the myocardium.   
Then, the MRI result will correlate with echocardiography and histopathology findings.</interventions>
    <comparator>A)- 50 healthy subjects,
b)- 100 patients with high blood pressure with normal (50) and abnormal (50) cardiac function,
c)- and 50 patients undergoing bypass surgery

All groups will undergo the same MRI protocols. The patients group will indergo the same technique plus injection of Gadolinium contrast agent to assess possibility of myocardial infarction. The Gadolinium is a safer standard clinical MRI contrast agent and the Gadolinium dose will Intravenously (I.V) administration at rate of  0.15 mmol/Kg.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>By using the MRI techniques, we can achieve two different contrast appearance of the heart, T1 and T2 star weighted imaging.
T1 and T2 star relaxation time of the heart can be measured by analyses the image with offline software e.g. MRmap software. this software allow us to measure the value of relaxation time in a seconds.
then, T1 and T2 star relaxation time of normal myocardium can be quantified.</outcome>
      <timepoint>assessed at a once scan time.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the hypertensive group will undergo with same MRI technique to assess any Alteration of relaxation times for early fibrosis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>assessed at a once scan time.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The patient cohort (OVER 40 YEARS) will comprise apparently healthy patients and patients with high blood pressure with normal and abnormal cardiac function recruited from the hospital clinic and the community</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1)- Women who are pregnant and the human fetus.
2)- Children and/or young people (i.e. &lt;40 years).
3)- People with an intellectual or mental impairment.
4)- People highly dependent on medical care.
5)- People in existing dependent or unequal relationships with any member of the research team, the researcher(s), and/or the person undertaking the recruitment /consent process.
6)- A history of drug abuse that would interfere with the ability to comply with the study protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The patient cohort will comprise apparently healthy volunteers and patients with high blood pressure with normal and abnormal cardiac function recruited from the hospital clinics and the community.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>a)- 50 healthy subjects,
       b)- 100 patients with high blood pressure with normal (50) and abnormal (50) cardiac function,
       c)- and 50 patients undergoing bypass surgery.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/05/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>the University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Centre for Advanced Imaging
University of Queensland,
St Lucia, QLD, 4072
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>the University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Centre for Advanced Imaging
University of Queensland,
St Lucia, QLD, 4072
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ministry of Higher Education - Kingdom of Saudi Arabia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Cultural Mission of Royal Embassy of Saudi Arabia
P.O. BOX 1206
DICKSON , ACT, 2602
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Fibrotic tissue may cause myocardial dysfunction and failure. So its important to establish a non invasive method to assess myocardial fibrosis. Cardiac MR relaxometry can quantify myocardial fibrosis using tagging, T2 star quantification, T1 mapping, first pass perfusion and delayed enhancement techniques. 
These results will correlate with the echocardiography methodology and myocardial biopsy findings.
the aims of this study to determine a MRI relaxometry of normal myocardium and any Alteration of relaxation times for early fibrosis in hypertensive disease. also, To detect possible fibrosis of remote myocardium in patients with prior infarction by analysis of delayed enhancement images after injection of MRI contrast agent. 
The hypothesis of this study is that Magnetic Resonance relaxometry can assess and measure early diffuse fibrosis in hypertensive heart disease.
the expected benefits from this study is Understanding the Tost effective clinical treatments will lead to improved health outcomes at lower cost. also, Early intervention is known to reduce the cost burden to the community and healthcare delivery system. in addition, Validation of non invasive methods of measuring early fibrotic changes in myocardium is essential to direct the clinical decision making</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>METRO SOUTH HEALTH SERVICE DISTRICT HUMAN RESEARCH ETHICS COMMITTEE</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>CENTRE FOR HEALTH RESEARCH - PRINCESS ALEXANDRA HOSPITAL -
IPSWICH ROAD
WOOLLOONGABBA 
QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/05/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/09/QPAH/277</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/10/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Qurain Alshammari</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland -
Southern School of Medicine - Princess Alexandra Hospital,
Ipswich Rd Woolloongabba
QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61731765340</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3176 5399</fax>
      <email>Qurain.alshammari@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>QURAIN ALSHAMMARI</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland -
Southern School of Medicine - Princess Alexandra Hospital,
Ipswich Rd Woolloongabba
QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 5216</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3176 5399</fax>
      <email>qurain.alshammari@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mark strudwick</name>
      <address>The Centre for Advanced Imaging
University of Queensland,
St Lucia, QLD, 4072
Australia</address>
      <phone />
      <fax>(+61 7) 3365 3833</fax>
      <email>mark.strudwick@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>