<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365071">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001122741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A comparison between Tinnitus Retraining Therapy (TRT) and Tinnitus Adaptation Level Therapy (TALT) for the treatment of tinnitus</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An investigation of the benefit of adaptation counselling and spatial sound therapy versus tinnitus retraining therapy and bilateral masking for the alleviation of distress in tinnitus patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1148-5703 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Tinnitus</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hearing impairment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Ear</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Deafness</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All subjects will receive a single 1.5 hour counselling session at the  beginning of each phase of the trial. Counselling will be conducted at the beginning of the trial and again 8 weeks later, following the 6 week trial of the hearing device and 2 week wash out period. The participants will be divided into two groups with group one receiving counselling based on Tinnitus Adaptation Level therapy (TALT) and the other receiving directive counselling as specified by tinnitus retraining therapy (TRT). Counselling will be individual face to face. 
The effect of this initial counselling will be evaluated 1 week following counselling, using scales of tinnitus severity (TSNS), and a depression index (HADS).
Subjects will then be fitted with binaural prototype GN Resound hearing devices, capable of delivering masking noise in 2D and 3D. Those subjects who received the adaptation level therapy will be fitted with the hearing devices matched to the location of their tinnitus site.  Those that received the TRT counselling will have the hearing devices set to deliver sound to both ears set to the mixing point as defined for TRT by Jastreboff. 
At 5 weeks fitting, measures of tinnitus annoyance will be measured using the TFI, TSNS, THQ, HHI, CGI. This will be followed by a minimum 2 week wash out period. The subjects will then be crossed over so that those who received TRT and 2D masking will now receive and TALT and 3D masking and those who received TALT and 3D will now receive TRT and 2D.
Evaluation of the benefit of the devices and counselling will again be made at one week following counselling and 5 weeks post fitting. 
All the participants will be fited bilaterally with GN Reound open-fit hearing devices at a separate appointment following the assessment and counselling session (irrespective of which group they were in). A modified DSL(I/O) v5.0 will be used as the amplification perscription target and the fitting will be adjusted according to participants comfort and preference. Care, maintenance and use of the hearing devices will be explained to participants during the hearing device fitting  session and they will be reccomended to use the devices in a variety of everyday listening situations. Participants will be told to contact the researcher if they require any further assistance before the next follow up, which will be in 2 weeks. </interventions>
    <comparator>The proposed research is to evaluate he effectiveness of the new sound therapy and counselling concept (TALT) against the standard control treatment, TRT</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tinnitus Functional Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed at 6 weeks following each counselling session and 5 weeks following the hearing device fitting. The counselling combined with the device fiting is the intervention. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The advantage of TALT versus TRT the following tests of tinnitus adaptation and hearing device benefit;
TFI- Tinnitus functional index
TSNS- Tinnitus Severity numeric scale
CGI- Clinical Global improvement scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed at 6 weeks following each counselling session and 5 weeks following the hearing device fitting. The counselling combined with the device fiting is the intervention. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure of psycoacoustic improvement using software to measure tinnitus characterisitcs, e.g. pitch, loudness, minimum masking level. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed at 6 weeks following each counselling session and 5 weeks following the hearing device fitting. The counselling combined with the device fiting is the intervention. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hearing device benefit will be ascertained using a modified DSL(I/O) vs5.0 as the amplification perscription target and the fitting will be adjusted according to participant's comfort and preference. The amount of gain provided will be measured using an insertion gain procedure to match the device gain to the the DSL target</outcome>
      <timepoint>Hearing deivce benefit will be ascertianed 5 weeks following fitting by means of the HHI- hearing handicap index and the CGI- measure of global improvement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>mild-moderate sensorineural hearing loss in the fitting range of the test devices.  They will have moderate-severe (minimum score of 25 on the TFI) chronic (duration greater than 6 months) tinnitus with non-center clearly identified localized tinnitus.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Normal hearing, severe hearing loss
No or mild tinnitus
Hyperacusis
Acute tinnitus (&lt; 6 months)
Previous users of sound generators or combination devices
Undergoing other treatment for tinnitus or anxiety/depression
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A linear Mixed Model analysis using SPSS software will be undertaken on the data.  Based on a power analysis a total of 10 patients will enter this two-treatment crossover study. The probability is 80 percent that the study will detect a treatment difference at a two-sided 0.05 significance level, if the true difference between treatments is 7 TFI units. This is based on the assumption that the within-patient standard deviation of the response variable is 5, which is based on previous evaluations of test-retest variance of the TFI in a similar participant population.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>5/11/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Morrin Street
St John
Auckland 1072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>G N Resound</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GN ReSound A/S Lautrupbjerg 7 Ballerup, 2750 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Denmark</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Grant Searchfield</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Auckland
Morrin Street
St John
Auckland 1072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Determine the effectiveness of the new 3D sound therapy concept relative to existing standard sound therapy for tinnitus treatment
Determine the instrument setting preferences and preferences for Resound 3D hearing devices
Determine the effectiveness of 3D assessment and tinnitus adaptation counselling versus TRT directive counselling and maskimg at mixing point as prescribed. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Auckland human participant’s ethics committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences 
The University of Auckland
 Private Bag 92019
 Auckland 1142
 New Zealand </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>6192</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Grant Searchfield</name>
      <address>University of Auckland
Level 3, Bldg. 730, School of Population Health 
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences 
261 Morrin Road 
Glen Innes 
Auckland 1072 
</address>
      <phone>+64 923 86316</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.searchfield@auckland.ac.nz </email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Shirley-Anne Hodgson</name>
      <address>University of Auckland
Level 3, Bldg. 730, School of Population Health 
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences 
261 Morrin Road 
Glen Innes 
Auckland 1072 
</address>
      <phone>+64 923 86542</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.hodgson@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Grant Searchfield</name>
      <address>University of Auckland
University of Auckland
Level 3, Bldg. 730, School of Population Health 
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences 
261 Morrin Road 
Glen Innes 
Auckland 1072 
</address>
      <phone>+64 923 86316</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.searchfield@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Shirley-Anne Hodgson</name>
      <address>University of Auckland
Level 3, Bldg. 730, School of Population Health 
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences 
261 Morrin Road 
Glen Innes 
Auckland 1072 
</address>
      <phone>+64 923 86542</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.hodgson@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>