<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83752">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/03/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/04/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000162213</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prospective randomized trial of two-stage treatment with preoperative endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography (ERCP) versus single-stage treatment with intraoperative ERCP in patients with gallbladder and bile duct stones</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective randomized trial of two-stage treatment with preoperative endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography (ERCP) versus single-stage treatment with intraoperative ERCP in patients with gallbladder and bile duct stones for stone clearance</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients with gallbladder and bile duct stones</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Single-stage treatment with intraoperative ERCP (ERCP is a technique that combines the use of endoscopy and fluoroscopy to diagnose and treat certain disease of the biliary or pancreatic ductal systems, e.g. biliary stone. Then a flexible endoscope is inserted through the mouth, into the duodenum where the ampulla of Vater exists. The region can be directly visualized with the endoscopic camera. A plastic cannula is inserted through the ampulla, and radiocontrast is injected into the bile ducts. Fluoroscopy is used to look for any pathology such as stones. Then, endoscopist can treat it accordingly. The procedure lasts around 30 minutes) and laparoscopic cholecystectomy (Gallbladder with stones was dissected and removed by minimally invasive surgery with  laparoscopic approach by four small wound ports. Intraoperative cholangiogram may be performed also, if needed. The procedure lasts around 90 minutes); Patients will undergo laparoscopic cholecystectomy and intraoperative ERCP simutaneously under general anestheisa.</interventions>
    <comparator>Two-stage treatment with preoperative ERCP (ERCP will be performed under sedation; The procedure lasts around 30 minutes) and then laparoscopic cholecystectomy (The procedure lasts around 90 minutes); Patients will undergo preoperative ERCP and after a short period of clinical monitoring (2472 hours), laparoscopic cholecystectomy will be received.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Failure of ERCP (inability to visualize or to cannulate the common bile duct)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After ERCP</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Failure of stones extraction (inability to obtain complete common bile duct stones clearance at completion cholangiogram)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After ERCP</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age ranged from 18-75 years old
2. Patients with ultrasonography(USG)/magnetic resonance cholangiopancreatography (MRCP)/computed tomography (CT) scan evidence of gallbladder stones and common bile duct (CBD) stones
3. Patients recovered from episode of acute cholangitis or biliary pancreatitis, and were treated with ERCP and temporary biliary stenting for the biliary stone obstruction during acute phase. Patients were randomized only if they demonstrated evidence of resolved acute episode, as determined by a decreasing white cell count, bilirubin level, fever and reduced abdominal pain</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients with acute cholangitis or acute severe pancreatitis at acute phase
2. American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) class IV and V health status
3. Patients with suspected biliary malignancy
4. Patients with Mirizzi syndrome 
5. Patients with recurrent pyogenic cholangitis
6. Patients with previous cholecystectomy/bile duct exploration/gastrectomy
7. Patients have contraindications to ERCP/laparoscopic surgery
8. On long term anticoagulant treatment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>88</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Surgery, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan, Hong Kong</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The ideal management of common bile duct stones (CBD) in the era of laparoscopic cholecystectomy remains controversial. However, ERCP remains the prevailing method of treating CBD stones, but its ideal timing in respect to laparoscopic cholecystectomy is not defined yet.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Ethics Committee of Hong Kong East Cluster of Hospital Authority</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital, 3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan, Hong Kong</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HKEC-2009-006</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lai Eric C.H</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital, 3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan, Hong Kong</address>
      <phone>852-2595 6111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ericlai@alumni.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lai Eric C.H.</name>
      <address>Department of Surgery, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital, 3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan, Hong Kong</address>
      <phone>852-2595 6111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ericlai@alumni.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>