<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365965">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000320651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effects of Allopurinol in Chronic Kidney Disease Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Effects of Allopurinol on Metabolic Acidosis and Endothelial Functions in Chronic Kidney Disease Patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Kidney Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Hyperuricemia and metabolic acidosis have emerged as important risk factors for progression of kidney disease. In this study, we aimed to investigate the effects of allopurinol on metabolic acidosis and endothelial functions in hyperuricemic stage 2-4 chronic kidney disease (CKD) patients. Thirty patients with stage 2-4 CKD and serum uric acid levels over 5.5 mg/dL were included in the study group. They were prescribed 300 mg/day per oral allopurinol treatment for three months. In order to monitor adherence to the intervention, we have counted allopurinol tablets in the clinical visits. Age and gender matched CKD patients (n=30) with similar clinical characteristics were taken as the control group and they were not given allopurinol treatment. Endothelial functions were measured via flow mediated dilatation over forearm. pH and HCO3 levels in venous blood, Cr clearance and proteinuria levels from 24 hour urine collection were calculated in all patients at baseline and during the third month.</interventions>
    <comparator>The CKD patients who admitted to the Nephrology Outpatient Clinic of Suleyman Demirel University Hospital were searched and patients fulfilling the inclusion criteria were entered into the study. They were separated into two groups in a consecutive manner. Thirty patients with stage 2-4 CKD and serum uric acid levels over 5.5 mg/dL were included in the study group. They were prescribed 300 mg/day per oral allopurinol treatment for 3 months. Age and gender matched CKD patients (n=30) with similar clinical characteristics were taken as the control group and they were not given allopurinol treatment. The dosage of antihypertensive drugs, lipid-lowering agents, and antiplatelet drugs were continued and adjusted according to the each patients clinical condition.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>differences in creatinine clearance. Creatinine clearances of the patients were assessed via 24 hour urine collection</outcome>
      <timepoint>assessed at three months from baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>serum bicarbonate levels. It was acquired from venous blood gas analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>three months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of flow mediated dilation values: Flow mediated vasodilatation (FMD) measurements of the brachial artery were performed by using high-resolution ultrasound with a 12-MHz probe. Assessments were made by a single observer who was blind to the baseline characteristics and laboratory investigations. The subjects remained at rest in the supine position for at least 15 min before the examination started. Two adjacent measurements of end-diastolic brachial artery diameter were performed from single two-dimensional frames. A pneumatic tourniquet was inflated to 200 mm Hg with obliteration of the radial pulse and after five minutes, the cuff was deflated. Flow measurements were made 60 seconds after deflation. The maximum dilatation diameters were calculated as the average of two consecutive maximum diameter measurements. The FMD was then calculated as the percentage change in diameter compared with baseline resting diameters (?FMD percentage). Like all other assessments, ?FMD  measurements were also repeated at the third month. </outcome>
      <timepoint>three months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The inclusion criteria were as follows; being a CKD patient at stage 2-4, age between 18 and 80 years old, having serum uric acid levels over 5.5 mg/dl and giving written informed consent to enter this study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The exclusion criteria were: being on renal replacement therapy, hyperuricemia due to malignancy, having peripheral arterial disease, gouty arthritis, a history of allopurinol intolerance, being already on allopurinol treatment, having active infections or inflammatory diseases.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/01/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/01/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/11/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Isparta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dilara Bayram</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suleyman Demirel University, School of Medicine,32260, Cunur, Isparta</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Salih Inal</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Suleyman Demirel University, School of Medicine,32260, Cunur, Isparta</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Turkey</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Hyperuricemia and metabolic acidosis have emerged as important risk factors for progression of kidney disease. In this study, we aimed to investigate the effects of allopurinol on metabolic acidosis and endothelial functions in hyperuricemic stage 2-4 chronic kidney disease (CKD) patients. Thirty patients with stage 2-4 CKD and serum uric acid levels over 5.5 mg/dL were included in the study group. They were prescribed 300 mg/day per oral allopurinol treatment for three months. Age and gender matched CKD patients (n=30) with similar clinical characteristics were taken as the control group and they were not given allopurinol treatment. Endothelial functions were measured via flow mediated dilatation (FMD) over forearm. pH and HCO3 levels in venous blood, Cr clearance and proteinuria levels were calculated in all patients at baseline and during the third month. Serum uric acid levels significantly decreased in the study group. Cr clearance, serum bicarbonate levels and FMD values have increased significantly in allopurinol group. There were not any significant changes except FMD values in the control group. FMD variations within two groups were clearly significant in repeated ANOVA general linear model. In conclusion, we assume that decreasing uric acid levels with allopurinol treatment seems to be helpful in order to restore endothelial functions, prevent metabolic acidosis and slow down the progression of CKD.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Suleyman Demirel University, School of Medicine, Local Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Suleyman Demirel University, School of Medicine, 32260, Cunur, Isparta</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Salih Inal</name>
      <address>Suleyman Demirel University, School of Medicine, Department of Internal Medicine, Division fo Nephrology

32260, Cunur, Isparta, TURKEY</address>
      <phone>+902462119212</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>salihinal@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Salih Inal</name>
      <address>Suleyman Demirel University, School of Medicine, 32260, Cunur, Isparta</address>
      <phone>+902462119219</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>salihinal@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Salih Inal</name>
      <address>Suleyman Demirel University, School of Medicine, 32260, Cunur, Isparta</address>
      <phone>+902462119219</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>salihinal@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Salih Inal</name>
      <address>Suleyman Demirel University, School of Medicine, 32260, Cunur, Isparta</address>
      <phone>+902462119219</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>salihinal@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>