<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335534">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000444088</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving lower limb function in patients with major muscular loss or denervation following resection of a sarcoma.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a 4 stage rehabilitation programme on lower limb physical function in patients with major muscular loss or denervation following resection of a sarcoma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>N/A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients with a previous malignancy diagnosis, with major muscular loss, damage to either Sciatic or Femoral nerves, following limb salvage surgery.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sarcoma (also see 'Bone') - soft tissue</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will be required to attend the Hollywood Functional Rehabilitation Clinic 3 times per week, for 1.5 hours. The rehabilitation intervention is for twelve weeks and will be fully supervised by an Accredited Exercise Physiologist (Miss Chrissie Mavros).

The rehabilitation intervention consists of four stages, with the ultimate goal of restoring function of the affected limb to 80% of the unaffected limb, or aged matched population from published normative data.

Stage 1 aims (wks 1-2): restoring hip, knee and ankle range of motion (ROM); re-activating and recruiting the appropriate lower limb muscles; introducing cardiovascular exercises.

Stage 2 aims (wks 3-5): strengthening the lower limb musculature; introducing core stability; further developing cardio-vascular fitness.

Stage 3 aims (wks 6-8): develop lower limb muscle strength simulating functional tasks.

Stage 4 aims (wks 9-12): restore and improve physical function during all activities of daily living.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control is each patients contra-lateral limb (ie the unaffected limb, which does not undergo rehabilitation)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To improve the physical and psychological function of patients.

This is going to be assessed through 5 tools:
1) The six minute walk test: which measures functional ambulation capacity
2) the up and go test: also measures physical function
3) The Toronto Extremity Salvage Score: is a self administered questionnaire specific for limb salvage patients. It measures physical function and describes changes over time
4) The short-form 36 question: measures mental and health dimension (self-administered questionnaire)
5) High mobility assessment tool: assesses uni-dimensional function through various physical tests.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 baseline tests (administered 2 weeks apart). If these two tests are not within 10% of each other a third baseline test will be administered. If this test is not within 10% of the second baseline test, the patient will be omitted due to instability in their results; 12 weeks (this will occur the week following the last rehabilitation session)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcomes is lower limb muscle strength.

Muscle strength is made up of four components:
- Knee flexion/extension: will be measured by an isokinetic dynamometer
- Hip flexion/extension: will be measured isotonically via a 3repetition maximum protocol
- Hip abduction: will be measured isotonically via a 3repetition maximum protocol
- plantar flexion: will be measured isometrically via a cable tensiometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 baseline tests (administered 2 weeks apart). If these two tests are not within 10% of each other a third baseline test will be administered. If this test is not within 10% of the second baseline test, the patient will be omitted due to instability in their results; 12 weeks (this will occur the week following the last rehabilitation session)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Joint range of motion.

Hip Flexion/Extension will be measured by a bubble inclinometer, knee flexion/extension and ankle plantar-flexion will be measured by a goniometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 baseline tests (administered 2 weeks apart). If these two tests are not within 10% of each other a third baseline test will be administered. If this test is not within 10% of the second baseline test, the patient will be omitted due to instability in their results; 12 weeks (this will occur the week following the last rehabilitation session)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- last cancer treatment &gt;6months
- estimated life expectancy &gt;12months
- an indication for rehabilitation
- must live in Perth metropolitan area
- must speak and read english competently</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- presence of severe cardiovascular disease
- cognitive disturbances that may interfere with participation in the rehabilitation programme
- serious psychopathology and emotional instability that may impede participation.
- Formal rehabilitation in the last 3months</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Only patients of Professor David Wood and Dr Richard Carey Smith will be recruited for the study. Patients will be sent a subject information sheet and an expression of interest form from their orthopaedic surgeon, with contact details of the study coordinator.

Each patient will receive the rehabilitation intervention, with their contra-lateral limb acting as their own control</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Specifically this is a repeated measures design</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/05/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University Of Western Australia; School of Sports Science, Exercise and Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Western Australia,
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, WA, 6009,
Perth, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University Of Western Australia; School of Sports Science, Exercise and Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Western Australia,
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley, WA, 6009,
Perth, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study looks at how supervised exercise programs can help in rehabilitating people with a major loss of muscle or nerves following surgery for sarcoma.

Who is it for?
You can join this study if you are recovering from a major loss of muscles or nerves after surgery for sarcoma.

Trial details
Participants will take part in a 12 week supervised rehabilitation program with exercises, 3 times per week, for 1.5 hours. The opposite unaffected limb is not used in the exercise program, and is monitored for comparison. Five tools will be used to monitor the psychological and physiological wellbeing of patients. The ultimate goal is to restore function of the affected limb to 80% of the unaffected limb,
The study aims to see how well exercise is tolerated, and how effective exercises are at increasing muscle strength and mobility, and also quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Western Australia (UWA) ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/05/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/04/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chrissie Mavros</name>
      <address>1 Bay Road, Claremont, WA, 6010</address>
      <phone>+61 423 5155 99</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mavroc01@student.uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chrissie Mavros</name>
      <address>1 Bay Road, Claremont, WA, 6010</address>
      <phone>+61 423 5155 99</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mavroc01@student.uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>