<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363155">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001107819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Febuxostat-thiopurine combination therapy in patients with moderately severe inflammatory bowel disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Febuxostat-thiopurine combination therapy in patients with moderately severe inflammatory bowel disease (IBD): a pilot study of a novel drug combination that may influence thiopurine bioavailability</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1135-8358</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Febuxostat-thiopurine bioavailability trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>inflammatory bowel disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To use the combination of febuxostat and 6-mercaptopurine over 4 weeks. 40mg febuxostat will be taken orally once daily together with 6-mercaptopurine at a dose of 1/3 that based on thiopurine methyl transferase activity (TPMT) prediction. (The rule of thumb of 1/3 dosing is based on our published experience with the other xanthine oxidase inhibitor (allopurinol)-thiopurine combination</interventions>
    <comparator>not applicable - will be monitoring drug levels with the combination treatment</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>therapeutic drug monitoring of drug efficacy using concurrent monitoring of total 6-thioguanine (6TG) methyl 6-mercaptopurine (me6MMP) in red blood cells (method of Dervieux and Bouleau)
 together with the ratio of mean red blood cell volume : white blood cell count in peripheral venous blood</outcome>
      <timepoint>1,2,4 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>drug combination efficacy by -

clinical measures of disease activity: Harvey Bradshaw for Crohn's or Simple severity of colitis index for ulcerative colitis as appropriate, together with C-reactive protein and requirement for and dose of steroid</outcome>
      <timepoint>1,2,4 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i) moderately severe IBD
ii) patients who accumulate methylated thiopurine metabolites</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>i) allergic reaction to 6-mercaptopurine
ii) not so severe as to fit PBS criteria for anti-TNFa treatments
iii) TPMT &lt; 0.3</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Single site, pilot study

STUDY SETTING/LOCATION
Single site, Mater Adults Hospital, Gastroenterology department 

STUDY DURATION
One year from patient recruitment to write up

STUDY POPULATION
Patients with moderately severe IBD 
Recruitment Process
Patients will be recruited at their routine clinic visit.</concealment>
    <sequence>not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>6</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Tim Florin</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dept Gastroenterology, Mater Health Services, Raymond Terrace, South Brisbane, QLD 4101</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>1. BACKGROUND 
Febuxostat is a novel xanthine oxidase inhibitor licensed in USA, Europe and Japan for treatment of gout and other hyperuricemic disorders. There has been no attempt to license it in Australia because the market is considered too small.  In Australia, the only xanthine oxidase inhibitor on the market is allopurinol. Allopurinol is an analogue of xanthine, which competitively binds xanthine oxidase. Febuxostat is not a xanthine analogue and so works by a different mechanism to competitively inhibit xanthine oxidase. 
The cornerstone of treatment of patients with moderately severe IBD is thiopurine therapy. Thiopurines are cytotoxic and immunosuppressive therapies originally designed for treatment of acute childhood leukemias and for organ transplantation. Patients have regular monitoring of treatment response as well as blood tests (FBC = full blood count) to ensure that there is no over-immunosuppression and that there is no excessive build-up of methylated metabolites which are hepatotoxic (therapeutic drug monitoring of thiopurine metabolites).
Prof Florin and others have pioneered the combination of allopurinol  thiopurine co-therapy in IBD. The advantages of this therapy are that there the thiopurine requires a considerably lower dose (about 1/3 normal dose) to achieve a beneficial treatment outcome and there are less of its toxic methylated metabolites. Currently, there is debate about why allopurinol can result in less methylated metabolites because allopurinol has no known action on methylating enzymes. Some people think that a metabolite of allopurinol inhibits the methylation enzyme but this has not been proven. 
Allopurinol is generally well tolerated but there are known severe adverse drug reactions including hepatitis, fever, severe skin rash, eosinophilia and renal failure which occurs especially in Asian populations. Febuxostat is a good alternative therapy to allopurinol, but its therapeutic action when combined with thiopurines is unknown. We wish to investigate whether febuxostat  thiopurine co-therapy also works for IBD patients.

2.	AIM(S) OF STUDY
A pilot experiment with highly motivated patients who accumulate increased methylated metabolites on thiopurine monotreatment.

3	HYPOTHESES
3.1  The combination of thiopurine  febuxostat will allow us to use less thiopurine to effect immunosuppressive and therapeutic success.		
3.2 Febuxostat will cause a reduction in methylated metabolites of thiopurines.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Health Services HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Quarters Building, Raymond Terrace, South Brisbane, QLD 4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1926A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tim Florin</name>
      <address>Mater Health Services
Qld 4101</address>
      <phone>+61412764379</phone>
      <fax>+61412764379</fax>
      <email>t.florin@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof Tim Florin</name>
      <address>Mater Health Services, Raymond Terrace, South Brisbane, QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61412764379</phone>
      <fax>+61731631548</fax>
      <email>t.florin@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tim Florin</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax>+61731631548</fax>
      <email>t.florin@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>