<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343192">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000740998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparative effects of A1 versus A2 milk on gastrointestinal symptoms and systemic exposure to beta-casomorphin-7 (BCM7)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Adults and the effect of A1 versus A2 milk consumption on gastrointestinal symptoms and systemic exposure to beta-casomorphin-7 (BCM7)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gastrointestinal symptoms related to milk intolerance</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This will be a randomised, crossover study over an 8 week period consisting of 2 weeks of an initial washout. Following washout, 40 participants will be randomised to either the A1 milk or A2 milk group (Crossover 1), with 20 in each group. This is then followed by another 2 weeks washout after which Subjects will then  start the alternative A1 or A2 milk Intervention for another 2 weeks intervention (crossover2).  

During washout, participants will consume their normal diet (excluding all dairy) and use rice milk and rice yoghurt alternatives to replace habitual daily dairy intake.

Intervention consists of either:
1) a normal diet (excluding all dairy) + 750mL A2 beta-casein protein containing milk consumed in 3 serves daily (~7-8g A2 type beta-casein/day) 
or 
2) Normal diet (excluding all dairy) + 750mL A1 containing milk per day, which is equivalent to ~7-8g A1 type beta-casein/day; 

Milk will be given as UHT long life, skim milk (A2 Dairy Products Australia)
Average composition: 
energy 189kJ/100mL
total protein 3.1g/100mL
total fat 0.1g/100mL
carbohydrate (including lactose) 5.2g/100mL</interventions>
    <comparator>Normal diet (excluding all dairy) + 750mL A1 beta-casein protein containing milk consumed in 3 serves daily (~7-8g A1 type beta-casein/day) for 2 weeks. Milk will be given as UHT long life, reduced fat milk (A2 Dairy Products Australia) Average composition: energy 189kJ/100mL total protein 3.1g/100mL total fat 2.5g/100mL carbohydrate (including lactose) 5.2g/100mL </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gastrointestinal symptom management.
Participants will record gastrointestinal symptoms of intolerance in their Symptom Report Diary and daily bowel movement frequency/stool consistency using the Bristol Stool Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Symptoms recorded during each 2 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Investigation of the presence of BCM-7 in serum from fasting and postprandial blood samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the beginning and end of each 2 week intervention period
1 hour postprandial sample after consumption of 500mL of milk intervention at the end of each 2 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of gastrointestinal tract permeability from a dual sugar test and urine analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each 2 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of gut inflammation from analysis of faecal calprotectin to investigate possible precursors to BCM-7 effects</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each 2 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Caucasian
Do not drink more than 1 serve milk/day
Those who report lactose intolerance but have not received medial diagnosis
Willing to consume milk for 8 weeks
Able to sign and understand informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Milk allergy
Diagnosed lactose intolerance
Pregnancy and lactation
Cardiovascular event in the last 6 months
Current, habitual opioid consumption
Antibiotic treatment within the last 8 weeks prior to screening
Immunosuppressive medications or anti-inflammatory drugs within the last 4 weeks prior to screening</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be screened and attend a briefing session to assess suitability. Suitable participants will be allocated to a group by central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer program generated randomisation plan</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/02/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>14/06/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>A2 Dairy Products Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kew Executive Suites
Locked Bag 8000, MDC, Kew,Victoria 3102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>At present there is debate surrounding the effects of the A1 variant (A1) of the beta-casein protein contained in bovine milk compared to the progenitor A2 variant (A2) in terms of potential health outcomes. However, there is evidence to suggest that the beta-casein composition of milk can have an impact on gastrointestinal symptoms of intolerance which may be due to exposure to A1 beta-casein derived digestion products. Given the Australian Dietary Guidelines recommend the consumption of at least 2-3serves of dairy foods per day, the effects of milk variety on digestive function and exposure to beta-casein digestion products is important and warrants investigation. Most available milk and milk products contain comparable amounts of both A1 and A2, protein variants which are reported to have potential differences in bioactivity upon digestion. This stems from the release of the seven amino acid opioid peptide, termed beta-casomorphin-7 (BCM-7) from the digestion of A1 but not A2 beta-casein. However, further research is required to demonstrate clearly any differential in vivo effects between A1 and A2 beta-casein consumption on biological responses, including those associated with gastrointestinal symptoms of milk intolerance. The general aim of this blinded, cross-over trial is to demonstrate that A2 beta-casein containing milk will have a neutral effect on gastrointestinal symptoms and exposure to BCM-7 relative to A1 beta-casein containing milk.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/10/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR102/2011</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/07/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Assoc Prof Sebely Pal</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 4755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.pal@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Assoc Prof Sebely Pal</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 4755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.pal@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Assoc Prof Sebely Pal</name>
      <address>School of Public Health
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 4755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.pal@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Sebely Pal</name>
      <address>School of Public Health Curtin University GPO Box U1987 Perth WA 6845  </address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 4755</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.pal@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>