<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365643">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000141640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigation of the Impact of Degree of Weight Loss on Physiological Adaptations to Weight Loss</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An interventional study investigating if starting BMI or degree of weight loss affect physiological adaptations to weight loss using a VLED (very low energy diet)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1146-9120</utrn>
    <trialacronym>nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Very Low Energy Diet (VLED) (OptiFast) for 12 weeks.  All participants will be placed on OptiFast for a duration of 12 weeks. The OPTIFAST program is a total food
replacement for the overweight. It is intended for use as part of the management of the moderately to severely overweight persons. The OPTIFAST program has been clinically developed and scientifically formulated to totally replace normal food intake. Weight loss is comparable to that achieved by total fasting whilst minimising the complications of severe ketosis and muscle loss. The OPTIFAST formulation includes high quality protein, sufficient quantities of protein (for nitrogen sparing
and to preserve lean body mass), carbohydrates, fatty acids, and follows the Recommended Dietary Intake (RDI) for vitamins, minerals and trace elements.  Fortnightly measurements of urinary ketones will be taken to gauge adherence to diet.</interventions>
    <comparator>Overweight adults compared to obese adults</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Degree of reduction in body weight required to bring about compensatory mechanisms (assessed using weight measurements via calibrated scales, measurements of gut hormones (amylin, PYY, GLP-1, leptin ,ghrelin, GIP,PP and INSL5)glucose, insulin and free fatty acids via serum assays) </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate if body weight is equally regulated across a range of BMIs (assessed using weight measurements via calibrated scales, measurements of gut hormones (amylin, PYY, GLP-1, leptin ,ghrelin, GIP,PP and INSL5)glucose, insulin and free fatty acids via serum assays) </outcome>
      <timepoint>week 64</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Degree of weight regain from week 13-64 (assessed via weight measurements using calibrated scales)</outcome>
      <timepoint>week 64</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline to week 12; and week 13-64 in gut hormone measurements, fasting glucose measurement, fasting insulin measurement and appetite (as measured by visual analogue scale)(assessed using weight measurements via calibrated scales, measurements of gut hormones (amylin, PYY, GLP-1, leptin ,ghrelin, GIP,PP and INSL5)glucose, insulin and free fatty acids via serum assays) </outcome>
      <timepoint>week 64</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Written informed consent obtained
*Age 18  65 years
*BMI 25-50kg/m2
*Stable body weight
*In good health</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Body builders
*Significant illness
*History of recent weight loss
*Past history of bariatric surgery
*Use of weight affecting pharmacotherapy
*Current smokers
*History of unstable thyroid disorder
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The power calculations for this study were based on the expected change in ghrelin levels after weight loss. We propose that average percentage change in ghrelin between the 5% weight loss measurement and 15% weight loss measurement is at least in the vicinity of 0%.  To account for natural variation not associated with weight loss we suppose that the percentage change between these two time periods is SD = 25.  We assume that equivalence proven if mean percentage change is within +/- 10%. Assuming SD=25%, 70 subjects are required to achieve a power of 90%.  To account for attrition, it is proposed that a total recruitment of 100 subjects as an appropriate sample size to study based on an expected attrition rate of 30%.


Additional to the exploration of equivalence between groups, for comparisons between two time points, changes in measurements will be analysed using either a paired t-test or the non-parametric Wilcoxon signed-rank test as appropriate. Changes in hormones and VAS will be analysed using linear mixed effect (lme) models to factor in fixed effects week (i.e. week of visit), time (time of measurement within week), , subject as the random effect and  will also allow for adjustment and analysis with respect to covariates. Additionally, changes in hormones will also be modelled using various baseline anthropometric predictors and change in these measures after phase I.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>5/02/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>5/06/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>100</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital - Heidelberg West</hospital>
    <postcode>3081 - Heidelberg Heights</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1100 Grattan Street,
Parkville, Victoria, 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1100 Grattan Street,
Parkville, Victoria, 3010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is evidence that public health measures aimed at reducing the burden of obesity have not been effective. Whilst there are several possible reasons for this, including a multitude of competing messages, the overabundance of energy dense food and the near absence of obligatory physical activity, it is likely that the more important reason is the fact that weight appears to be physiologically regulated and defended. This means that using public health measures to combat obesity is not likely to work for obese subjects. What is not yet known is if subjects who are overweight (as opposed to obese), defend weight loss, nor is it known if modest (~5%) weight loss is defended. If overweight or modest weight losses are not defended, it would allow the targeting of public health messages towards the overweight and to focus on modest weight loss in the obese.
This study aims to investigate if overweight people defend weight loss as vigorously as obese people, and to determine at what degree of weight loss these physiological changes begin. Overweight and obese people will be recruited and placed on a VLED (very low energy diet) for a period of 12 weeks, aiming to decrease body weight by 15%. Measurements in body weight and a number of biomarkers will be taken at proscribed intervals. All participants will be followed up for a period of two years, to observe weight regain (if any).  Gut hormone and other biomarker changes over the trial will be compared between the overweight cohort and the obese cohort, to determine any differences. For both cohorts, changes in gut hormones and other biomarkers will be compared at 5%, 10% and 15% baseline body weight lost, to determine when physiological defences increase.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>145 Studley Rd
Heidelberg VIC 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/Austin/154</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Joseph Proietto</name>
      <address>University of Melbourne, Department of Medicine
L2 Boronia Centre, Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital
300 Waterdale Rd
Heidelberg Heights VIC 3081</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 2250</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 2672</fax>
      <email>j.proietto@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kira Edwards</name>
      <address>University of Melbourne, Department of Medicine
L2 Boronia Centre, Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital
300 Waterdale Rd
Heidelberg Heights VIC 3081</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 2124</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 2672</fax>
      <email>kedwards@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Joseph Proietto</name>
      <address>University of Melbourne, Department of Medicine
L2 Boronia Centre, Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital
300 Waterdale Rd
Heidelberg Heights VIC 3081</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 2250</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 2672</fax>
      <email>j.proietto@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kira Edwards</name>
      <address>University of Melbourne, Department of Medicine
L2 Boronia Centre, Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital
300 Waterdale Rd
Heidelberg Heights VIC 3081</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 2124</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 2672</fax>
      <email>kedwards@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>