<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371218">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/12/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001676404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot randomised controlled trial comparing three different physiotherapy interventions to treat rotator cuff tendinopathy/subacromial pain syndrome. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to compare the clinical outcomes of isotonic concentric, isotonic eccentric and isometric exercises in the physiotherapy management of patients diagnosed with rotator cuff tendinopathy/subacromial pain syndrome: a pilot study to determine feasibility for a larger trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Subacromial Pain Syndrome </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Rotator Cuff Tendinopathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants are randomly assigned to one of three intervention groups: 
(i) isotonic concentric exercises
(ii) isotonic eccentric exercises 
(iii) isometric exercises. 

All groups will receive similar physiotherapy treatment directed at improving postural deficits, scapular control, shoulder muscle strength and flexibility. The variation in the intervention between the groups will be the specific type of rotator cuff strengthening exercises incorporated into the rehabilitation program: these will involve either (i) isotonic concentric; (ii) isotonic eccentric or (iii) isometric contractions,  taught and prescribed in accordance with current best evidence. 

The treatment sessions will occur once per week over 4 consecutive weeks (weeks 2-5). 

Exercises: 
Treatment 1: re-training of scapular/humeral head movement patterns.
Scapular control exercises will be patient specific and relate to symptom modification of   scapular postures identified at assessment including scapular rotation and/or tilt. Once the patient has learned how to re-position the scapular so that for example, downward rotation and anterior tilt is corrected, they will perform scapular muscle strengthening exercises  including (i) modified shrug drills in standing with arm abducted &lt;30 degrees with weight  and (ii) standing rows at 45 and 90 degrees using elastic resistance band.  
  
Treatment 2: rotator cuff strengthening (external rotation) exercises. These will be performed in standing, arm by side, elbow flexed to 90 degrees, using (i) elastic resistance band  for concentric and eccentric and (ii) rigid band for isometric contractions. 
    
Treatment 3: rotator cuff strengthening (internal rotation) exercises. These will be performed in standing, arm by side, elbow flexed to 90 degrees, using (i) elastic resistance band for concentric and eccentric and (ii) rigid band for isometric contractions.
 
Treatment 4: flexibility exercises. These will include (i) an anterior shoulder stretch (standing in corner of room or using door jamb) and (ii) thoracic extension range of motion exercises in either a) sitting or b) supine lie over rolled up towel.
 
The above exercises will be taught during the physiotherapy sessions and then performed independently and daily as part of a home exercise program with dose dependent on exercise type and specifically: 

1) Scapular retraining (motor relearning) exercises,  scapular shrugs and standing rows: 1-2 times daily, 1-2 sets of 20, 5-10 second rest in between each set. 
Progression of sets, repetitions and weights dependent on individual participant ability to achieve control.  

2) Rotator Cuff strengthening exercises: varies with muscle contraction group: 
Isotonic: 1-2 times daily, 1-2 sets of 20 repetitions, 5-10 second rest in between each set; 
Isometric: 1-2 times daily, 1 set of 3-5 repetitions with 10 second isometric hold, 5 second rest in between each hold. 1-2 times daily. 

3) Flexibility: all exercises 1-2 sets daily; stretch held for 15 seconds and repeated 2-4 times with a 5-10 second rest in between each stretch, 1-2 times daily. Thoracic mobility:. 1 set of 10 reps with 5 second hold and 5-10 second rest in between sets. 1-2 times daily.
 
Both scapular retraining and rotator cuff strengthening exercises will be taught/undertaken in standing but temporarily modifiable to side lie/prone positions dependent on patient symptoms and/or ability to control the scapular/humeral head in the standing position. 

The home program will take 15-20 minutes to complete each day with sets and repetitions as described above. 

At week 6 patients will be provided with an exercise sheet that they will use from week 6-12. The exercise sheet is the same for each group and will include most of the exercises taught and practiced during the physiotherapy intervention, as well as additional exercises designed to further increase strength, range and flexibility. Until they receive this exercise sheet at week 6, patients undertake their group specific home exercise program that consists only of the exercises they are taught during their physiotherapy sessions. The  exercise sheet given at week 6 replaces the previous sheet. It incorporates most of the exercises already performed as part of the home exercise program during weeks 2-6 but progresses these so they are no-longer group specific. 
Specific exercises detailed on the exercise sheet include: 
1): scapular setting through progressive range of  motion; 
2) rotator cuff internal/external rotation with elastic resistance band    
3): posterior muscle strengthening - (i) standing rows with resistance band; 45, 90 and 120 degrees; single bent forward row with weight. 
4): flexibility exercises: (i) thoracic mobility in sitting, (ii) thoracic mobility in lie over rolled towel; (iii) anterior shoulder stretch (pectorals in door jamb); 

At week 9, they will attend a check-review to ensure compliance with the exercise sheet. 

The assessment and treatment sessions will be carried out by a designated musculoskeletal Physiotherapist at each site, with at least 5 years experience. Prior to recruitment of participants into the study, all clinicians involved in assessment and treatment delivery will receive training in the techniques to be used in each group, as per the study protocol. All treatment interventions will be recorded on standardised report forms. The treatment sessions will be individual 1: 1 sessions lasting up to 30 minutes per session.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants are randomly assigned to one of three intervention groups: 
isotonic concentric exercises
isotonic eccentric exercises 
isometric exercises. 

All groups will receive the intervention as outlined above.  The variation in the intervention between the groups will be the specific type of rotator cuff strengthening exercises incorporated into the rehabilitation program: these will involve either (i) isotonic concentric; (ii) isotonic eccentric or (iii) isometric contractions at 0 degrees, taught and prescribed in accordance with current best evidence. 

The isotonic concentric group is considered to be a control.

At the 6 week stage, all groups will receive the same exercise sheet designed to progress the scapular and rotator cuff strengthening exercises through range.  Details are outlined above. 

At week 9, all groups will attend a check-review to ensure compliance with the exercise sheet. 

Prior to recruitment of participants into the study, all clinicians involved in assessment and treatment delivery will receive training in the techniques to be used in each group, as per the study protocol. All treatment interventions will be recorded on standardised report forms. The treatment sessions will be individual 1: 1 sessions lasting up to 30 minutes per session.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>determine feasibility of a full-scale randomized controlled trial.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>weeks 6 and 12
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perception of pain (current/usual/night) using 11 point numerical rating scale (NRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Within-treatment during rotator cuff strengthening intervention (weeks 3 and 4)
Week 6 
Week 12



</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Shoulder muscle strength  (using hand held dynanometer). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Within-treatment during rotator cuff strengthening intervention (weeks 3 and 4)
Week 6 
Week 12

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Western Ontario Rotator Cuff Index (WORC) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline  
Week 6 
Week 12 
6 months     </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Shoulder Pain and Disability Index (SPADI) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline  
Week 6 
Week 12 
6 months   </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived global rating of change score (GRCS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 18-80 years (likelihood of patients &gt; 80 of having degenerative changes in the shoulder is increased)   
Pain localised to the proximal anterolateral shoulder region
Since no single impingement test has shown high specificity, clinical history plus a cluster of 2 or more tests from the following is recommended to identify patients with SPS:   
Pain on elevation (abduction/flexion/scaption) and/or a painful arc in elevation 
Positive impingement test (Hawkins-Kennedy and/or Neers test)  
Pain on isometric abduction (positive full can or empty can) 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>large, full thickness rotator cuff tear 
Moderate-severe glenohumeral joint (GHJ) or acromioclavicular joint (ACJ) Osteoarthritis
GHJ instability including previous shoulder dislocation/subluxation
Previous shoulder fracture 
Current neck pain/dysfunction  with a somatic or radicular referral pattern indicative of cervical spine &gt; shoulder primary source of symptom and/or pathology
Neurological deficits of the upper limb
Systemic inflammatory arthritic conditions
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>In order to minimise bias: patients will not be told which intervention group they have been randomised to. All data will be de-identified and data analysis will be performed with group allocation undisclosed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Since there could be a difference in baseline demographics in participants recruited in the public and private sectors, block randomisation will be used to ensure that participants from each of the three clinics have an equal chance of receiving any of the interventions.  Once consented, participants will be randomly allocated using an off-site randomiser and computer generated allocation sequence to one of three groups

</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome of this study is to determine feasibility of a full-scale RCT. Feasibility will be evaluated by assessing the ease of recruiting participants (number and rate), adherence to the intervention (home-exercise program and log-book recording), non-completion (drop-out number and rate) and, adverse events. 

Comparison of between-group changes in secondary outcomes at each of the follow up time-points will be used to determine treatment efficacy.Data will be analysed on intention to treat principles for all participants using SPSS statistical packages (Version 24, SPSS Inc. Chicago, IL) and significance set at p&lt;0.5. 
Baseline between-group participant characteristics will be evaluated and included in covariate/regression analysis if deemed to have a potential influence on outcomes.  



</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/12/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>22/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>23/03/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>41 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy, Melbourne, VIC, 3065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Hospital, Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>41 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy, Melbourne, VIC, 3065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Arthritis Foundation of Australia </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 255 Broadway, Glebe, NSW 2037 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>La Trobe University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>La Trobe Sport and Exercise Medicine Research Centre,
School of Allied Health
College of Science, Health and Engineering
La Trobe University 
Corner of Kingsbury Drive and Plenty Rd
Melbourne (Bundoora), VIC 3086</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mill Park Physiotherapy Centre</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>22/1 Danaher Drive, South Morang, Melbourne, VIC 3752</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Clifton Hill Physiotherapy Clinic </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>11 Queen's Parade, Clifton Hill, Melbourne, Vic 3068  </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Shoulder disorders are a leading cause of pain and disability in our society with 1 in 3 people experiencing shoulder pain at some stage in their lives.  Recurrence is common and symptoms are often persistent. The rotator cuff muscles are considered the prime source of symptoms with a diagnosis of rotator cuff tendinopathy/sub-acromial pain syndrome (SPS) accounting for approximately 30% of all diagnoses made by GPs. 

Physiotherapy, particularly involving structured exercises, has been shown to be as effective as surgery in this patient group and is associated with less time off work and reduced adverse events.  However, definitive conclusions have not been drawn regarding which specific types of exercise are most effective in the treatment of this condition. 

The aim of this study is to compare the effects on pain and function of three different rehabilitation programs, each incorporating one of three types of strengthening exercises - (i) isotonic concentric (ii), isotonic eccentric and (iii) isometric rotator cuff contractions - into a structured exercise-based physiotherapy rehabilitation program in patients diagnosed with rotator cuff tendinopathy/SPS. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>41 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy, Melbourne, VIC, 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/11/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LNR/16/SVHM/169</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Faculty of Human Ethics Committee Faculty of Health Sciences, Latrobe University, Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>La Trobe Sport and Exercise Medicine Research Centre,
School of Allied Health
College of Science, Health and Engineering
La Trobe University 
Corner of Kingsbury Drive and Plenty Rd
Melbourne (Bundoora), VIC, 3086</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rita Kinsella</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
St Vincent's (Public) Hospital 
41 Victoria Parade
Melbourne VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 451 090 729</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rita.Kinsella@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rita Kinsella</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
St Vincent's (Public) Hospital 
41 Victoria Parade
Melbourne VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 451 090 729</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rita.Kinsella@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rita Kinsella</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
St Vincent's (Public) Hospital 
41 Victoria Parade
Melbourne VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 451 090 729</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rita.Kinsella@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rita Kinsella</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
St Vincent's (Public) Hospital 
41 Victoria Parade
Melbourne 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 451 090 729</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rita.Kinsella@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>