<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372471">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001270303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Blood flow restriction training for hand osteoarthritis: A randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of blood flow restriction training on strength, function, and pain in people with hand osteoarthritis: A randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U111111891726</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hand osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: Blood flow restriction exercise.
Training period: 6 weeks.
Training frequency: 3 days per week.
Exercise mode: Thumb abductors/extensors, interosseous, pinching, gripping muscle exercises.
Training intensity: 30% to 40% of maximum voluntarily contraction.
A physiotherapist will prescribe the exercises. Blood flow restriction will be applied using a pneumatic cuff with a handheld sphygmomanometer. The cuff will be applied to the arm, proximally to the muscles exercised. The cuff will provide an individualised restriction of the blood flow, but will not cause arterial occlusion. Participants will be individually supervised throughout the training session by a physiotherapist, ensuring adherence and safety. Each exercise session will last approximately 30 minutes.
The blood flow restriction exercise group will receive education about disease through a brochure provided after group randomisation.

Arm 2: Traditional high intensity exercise.
Training period: 6 weeks.
Training frequency: 3 days per week.
Exercise mode: Thumb abductors/extensors, interosseous, pinching, gripping muscle exercises.
Training intensity: 60% to 70% of maximum voluntarily contraction.
The same physiotherapist as for arm 1 will prescribe the exercises. The traditional high intensity group will undertake exercise without blood flow restriction, and without application of a blood flow restriction cuff. Each exercise session will last approximately 30 minutes.
The traditional high intensity exercise group will receive education about disease through a brochure provided after group randomisation.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 3: Advice only
Training period: Not applicable.
Training frequency: Not applicable.
Exercise mode: Not applicable.
Training intensity: Not applicable.
The control group will receive education about disease through a brochure provided after group randomisation.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OARSI-OMERACT responder criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum grip strength (kg), hand held dynamometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 7 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hand pain, 11-points Numerical Pain Rating Scale (NRS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 7 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient specific functional scale (PFSF).</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 7 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional Index of Hand Osteoarthritis (FIHOA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 7 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand (DASH) questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 7 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise induced pain, 11-point NRS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At every training session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant's intervention acceptability, using a 6 points Likert scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>7 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hand left/right judgment task and a control left/right judgement task</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 and 7 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Symptomatic and radiographic hand osteoarthritis.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participated in strength training in the last six months. Uncontrolled cardiovascular disease such as high blood pressure, history of rhabdomyolysis, conditions affecting blood clotting, and neurological diseases.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The allocation will be concealed to the researchers enrolling and assessing participants. Sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes will be prepared by a researcher who is independent from participants’ enrollment and participants assessment. Envelopes will be kept in a locked drawer and opened only after the enrolled participant completes all baseline assessments.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computerised random number generator will be uitilised.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A power calculation was performed to determine the sample size. A Fishers exact test with an a priori computation for sample size was utilised. The calculated relative probability, based on the OARSI-OMERACT responder criteria in the study by Hennig et al. (2015), was seven. Using G*power 3.1.7 software (Faul, Erdfelder, Lang, &amp; Buchner, 2007) with an alpha level (p-value) of 0.05 and a power of 0.80, the sample size calculated, for a one-tailed hypothesis, was 57 participants in total. The sample size was increased to 66 participants to account for 16% attrition rate.

Analysis will be performed on an intention-to-treat basis.
Chi-square procedures will be utilised to assess differences in numbers of treatment responders (OMERACT-OARSI criteria) between the intervention groups and the control group.
If normality assumptions are met, two-way repeated measures Analyses of Variance (ANOVAs) will be utilised to assess differences between groups at pre and post treatment. In case of differences on baseline measures a two-way repeated measures Analysis of Covariance (ANCOVAs) will be utilised to control for confounding variables. Planned contrasts will be used to test the main effects. Percentage error calculations will be used to calculate the proportion of results likely to be type I errors (Ottenbacher, 1991).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>66</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nicoló Edoardo Magni</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Auckland University of Technology
90 Akoranga Drive
Northcote
Auckland
0627</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Auckland University of Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>90 Akoranga Drive, Northcote, Auckland, 0627</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Physiotherapy New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 27386, Wellington, 6141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Peter John McNair</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Auckland University of Technology
90 Akoranga Drive
Northcote
Auckland
0627</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>David Andrew Rice</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Auckland University of Technology
90 Akoranga Drive
Northcote
Auckland
0627</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Rationale. Hand osteoarthritis (OA) is a painful degenerative condition, which often leads to muscle performance impairments and disability in older people. Despite its social and economic burden on the health care system, limited interventions are available. Conservative interventions such as high intensity strength training have been successfully trialled and utilised in people with knee and hip OA. In people with hand OA however, high intensity training is not always possible due to pain exacerbations. An alternative form of low load strength training called blood flow restriction training (BFR) has been shown to be effective and more acceptable than traditional high intensity strength training in people with knee OA. It is the aim of this study to explore the effectiveness of BFR in people with hand OA and compare its acceptability to a traditional high intensity strength training.
Methods. A randomised controlled trial will assess the differences across three groups, which will undergo blood flow restriction training exercise, traditional high intensity exercise or a control group undergoing no exercise. Each group will include 22 participants for a total of 66 participants. The intervention will last 6 weeks and outcome measures, which include grip strength, joint pain and hand function, will be measured immediately before starting the intervention and one week after trial completion. Repeated measures Analysis of Variance, Pearsons correlation, t-test and chi square tests will be utilised to analyse the data collected.
Expected Outcomes. The present study may improve participants grip strength, joint pain and hand function. Furthermore, clinicians may be provided with additional treatments to improve patients function and quality of life. Finally, if BFR is effective, its use for additional rehabilitation studies may be justified.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Health and Disability Ethics Committees
Ministry of Health
133 Molesworth Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/CEN/191</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nicoló Edoardo Magni</name>
      <address>Auckland University of Technology
90 Akoranga Drive
Northcote
Auckland
0627</address>
      <phone>+64 99219999 ext 6581</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nico.magni@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nicoló Edoardo Magni</name>
      <address>Auckland University of Technology
90 Akoranga Drive
Northcote
Auckland
0627</address>
      <phone>+64 99219999 ext 6581</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nico.magni@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nicoló Edoardo Magni</name>
      <address>Auckland University of Technology
90 Akoranga Drive
Northcote
Auckland
0627</address>
      <phone>+64 99219999 ext 6581</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nico.magni@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>