<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364811">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000936729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessment of the accuracy of Total Knee Replacement's (TKR's) performed using patient matched technology by computed tomography</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of patient-matched instrumentation on degree of alignment achieved postoperatively in patients undergoing total knee replacement for osteoarthritis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patient matched total knee replacement involves a preoperative CT scan which is then processed by the manufacturer to produce a preliminary preoperative report outlining proposed resection levels. This is then reviewed by the surgical team and, if approved, is then sent back to the manufacturer where the custom made cutting block is manufactured. 

During surgery, the cutting block is attached directly to the patients bony anatomy during and promotes accurate resection of the both the femoral and tibial bones. The procedure takes approximately 60 minutes. 

The system used in this study will include but is not limited to Medacta Orthopaedic patient matched knee system-MyKnee Registered Trademark. Proposed benefits of this system include improved accuracy, reduced cost and decreased operating times. </interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator/control treatment</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Identify the mechanical axis of the limb in the coronal anteroposterior and sagittal lateral planes measured by a CT scan.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured preoperatively and within 7 days following total knee replacement surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2.Calculate the varus/valgus positioning of the femoral component and tibial components using a CT scan .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured preoperatively and within 7 days following total knee replacement surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3. Determine the flexion/extension of the posterior flange of the femoral component using a CT scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured preoperatively and within 7 days following total knee replacement surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	The individual has read and understood the patient information statement (PIS) and signed a consent form specific to this study.
2.	The individual is over 18 years of age.
3.	The individual has been given a primary diagnosis of osteoarthritis.
4.	The individual clinically qualifies for total knee arthroplasty surgery based on physical examination and medical history.
5.	The individual is physically and mentally willing and able to comply with scheduled clinical and radiographic evaluations (i.e., not currently being treated for a psychiatric disorder, senile dementia, Alzheimers disease, alcohol or substance abuse).
6.	The individual does not have a systemic disease that would affect their welfare or the overall outcome of the study, is not immunologically suppressed, or receiving steroids in excess of physiologic dose requirements.
7.	The individual is skeletally mature.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	The individual is unable or unwilling to read the patient information statement (PIS) and sign the consent form specific to this study.
2.	The individual has had a previous fracture of the femoral condyles, tibia plateau, or femora/tibial shaft.
3.	The individual has had a previous osteotomy around the knee.
4.	The individual is physically or mentally compromised (i.e., is currently being treated for a psychiatric disorder, senile dementia, Alzheimers disease, alcohol or substance abuse), and is unable to comply with scheduled clinical and radiographic evaluations.
5.	The individual has a neuromuscular or neurosensory deficiency which limits their ability to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of the device.
6.	The individual has an active infection within the affected joint.
7.	The individual has had a previous total knee replacement.
8.	The individual is pregnant.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be collected in paper case report forms (CRFs). The data will then be entered on Microsoft excel software. The percentage of patients who have reached the level of accuracy outlined in the preoperative planning report will be calculated.

There will be no formal sample size analysis for this study. A sample population of 50 patients should provide an appropriate number to allow a robust analysis of the accuracy of patient matched cutting blocks, and is in excess to patient numbers used in similar studies performed previously.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/10/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Campbelltown Private Hospital - Campbelltown</hospital>
    <postcode>2560 - Campbelltown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. Arash Nabavi</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney Bone and Joint Clinic
105-119 Longstaff Avenue, 
Chipping Norton NSW, 2170. </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dr Arash Nabavi</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>105-119 Longstaff Avenue, Chipping Norton NSW, 2170. </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Malalignment in total knee replacement is a major cause of failure. Traditionally, alignment is facilitated through the use of mechanical jigs to position cutting blocks. There is however debate as to the accuracy of such jig systems. This study will employ a relatively new alternative method in which patient matched instrumentation as opposed to conventional jig-assisted techniques are used.

This study will look at the accuracy of TKRs performed using instrumentation which is specific to the patient. A CT scan will be performed on the patients knee after the operation to assess how accurate this patient specific instrumentation is.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee
Grants Management Office
Level 3, Rupert Myers Building South Wing
University of New South Wales
Kensington Campus NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Arash Nabavi</name>
      <address>Sydney Bone and Joint Clinic
105-119 Longstaff Avenue 
Chipping Norton
NSW 2170</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 9821 2599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nabaviarash@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Caroline Olwill</name>
      <address>Sydney Bone and Joint Clinic 
105-119 Longstaff Avenue
Chipping Norton
NSW 2170</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 9821 2599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caroline.olwill@sbjc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Arash Nabavi</name>
      <address>Sydney Bone and Joint Clinic 
105-119 Longstaff Avenue 
Chipping Norton
NSW 2170</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 9821 2599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nabaviarash@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Caroline Olwill</name>
      <address>Sydney Bone and Joint Clinic 
105-119 Longstaff Avenue 
Chipping Norton
NSW 2170</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 9821 2599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caroline.olwill@sbjc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>