<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366128">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000403639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled video vignette study on the effect different timing and lengths of discharge summaries have on the ability of general practitioners to identify ongoing problems in patients recently discharged from the hospital.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled video vignette study on the effect different timing and lengths of discharge summaries have on the ability of general practitioners to identify ongoing problems in patients recently discharged from the hospital.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Discharge Summary</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic and on-going medical problems</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All GPs commenced the study by viewing a five-minute video-recording of a monologue by an actor-patient as he might present to a GP after leaving the hospital. This was viewed online at the GPs own location. The actor described his ideas, concerns, and expectations about his current health. The issues described were drawn from the cases of several anonymous patients who were under the recent care of a general surgeon. The video was supplemented with case notes of medical, family, and drug history, which were provided to all GPs at the time of viewing the video. To optimise face validity, the monologue and case notes were reviewed by researcher-clinicians, including a surgeon, two GPs, and a pharmacist.
GPs assigned to groups A and C received a discharge letter at the time of viewing the video, while groups B and D received this letter one week later. </interventions>
    <comparator>Control: Groups A and B received a short letter of 450 words , while Intervention: Groups C and D received a longer letter of 911 words. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of patient problems identified by the participants in each group. This is based on the number of problems identified from a predetermined list of patient problems as identified by the research team and then assessed from the responses to the survey from each participant by two independent researchers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The GPs will complete the survey either immediately after viewing the video and discharge letter or immediately and again after receiving the delayed discharge letter.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>No secondary outcomes planned.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Not applicable.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>General practitioners or registrars working in Australia</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Non-general practitioners</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>GPs from seven Australian states and territories were recruited by the research team via email and personal contact. Organisations approached for recruitment included Australian Divisions of General Practice, which (at time of study) were geographically-defined organisations with comprehensive coverage of Australian GPs, university departments, research networks, and personal contacts. A total of 102 GPs agreed to participate in a series of video vignette studies. Following informed consent, GPs were provided with information via email on how to participate in the study. 

Participating GPs were randomly assigned to one of four groups, A to D, by a computer-generated numbering system</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants were randomised on enrollment by a computer-generated numbering system.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Fishers exact test was used to determine group differences in: (1) the number of health problems identified after the video; and (2) GP ratings of timeliness, information content, and the utility of the short and long referral letters. Linear regression was used to determine group differences in the average number of health problems identified by the GPs. The full regression model included: the four GP groups; age; sex; country of graduation; years after graduation; years of GP experience; status as established GP or GP registrar (trainee); Fellowship status with the Royal Australian College of General Practitioners (FRACGP); the remoteness of their primary practice; the number of GPs at their primary practice; and status as a principal within their primary practice. Binary logistic regression models were used to determine: (1) the probability that the health problems would be identified; and (2) the influence of letter-length and demographic information. In addition to the aforesaid variables, a full binary logistic regression model included the health problems.

Regression models were constructed using both backwards elimination and forward selection. Variables with a p value of less than .05 were retained in the final model and reported, with the exception of the variable of intervention group, which remained in the model regardless of significance level. Stata version 12.1 (StataCorp LP, College Station, TX, USA) was used to perform the analyses. Multivariate regression models were adjusted for the lack of independence between individual GPs by estimating the clustered standard errors to account for intra-group correlation (vce option in Stata).

Given the influence of documented patient information on clinical judgement, groups A and C were anticipated to identify twice as many health problems, relative to groups B and D. For this reason, a sample of twenty GPs per group was deemed sufficient in this exploratory study to estimate the effect size of an immediate discharge letter within 95% confidence intervals ranging from 0-34% 

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/06/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/09/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/09/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box U1987,
Perth, Western Australia 6845</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>General practitioners (GPs) were randomised into four groups. Each viewed a video monologue of an actor-patient as he might present to his GP following a hospital admission with ten problems. GPs were provided with a medical record as well as a long or short discharge letter, which was available at time of viewing the video or one week later. GPs indicated if they would prescribe, refer, or order tests for the patients problems.A short or long hospital discharge summary enumerating the patients problems. 
Intervention: Discharge summary available at time of consultation or a week later.
To determine the relationship between the timing and length of hospital discharge letters and the identification of ongoing patient problems by GPs
Number of ongoing patient problems identified for management by the GPs.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box U1987,
Perth, Western Australia, 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RD-13-11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Moyez Jiwa</name>
      <address>Curtin University,
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+ 61 8 9266 1768</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.jiwa@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Moyez Jiwa</name>
      <address>Curtin University,
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 1768</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.jiwa@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Moyez Jiwa</name>
      <address>Curtin University,
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 1768</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.jiwa@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Moyez Jiwa</name>
      <address>Curtin University,
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 1768</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.jiwa@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>