<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336361">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000044921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Intra and inter-examiner reproducibility of probing pocket depth in vivo</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>"Intra and inter-examiner reproducibility of probing pocket depth with a manual probe in healthy volunteers".</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prevention and diagnosis of periodontal diseases</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The three trained examiners measured PD in the 20 patients to determine the intra- and inter-examiner reproducibility. PD is defined as the measurement in millimeters from the gingival margin to the bottom of the gingival sulcus. The study used a Williams manual periodontal probe (1, 2, 3, 5, 7, 8, 9 and 10 mm), introducing the probe in the interior of the gingival sulcus and following the length of the tooth until resistance was felt by the penetrating probe. Each patient had six sites probed per tooth (mesial buccal, buccal, distal buccal, mesial lingual, lingual and distal lingual), excluding third molars. The PD measurements were done using the following criteria: all measurements were rounded to the closest 0.5 mm (up or down) and when the PD measurement was exactly between two marks on the probe (except between 3 mm and 5 mm, where the middle measurement equaled 4 mm), the closest millimeter immediately above the mark was recorded. Each patient had to have a minimum of six teeth per quadrant in order to be included in the study. The initial probe depths (baseline) were taken using the following methodology: on Day 1, Examiner 1 did an initial PD (baseline); two days later (day 3), Examiner 2 did an initial PD; and on day 5, Examiner 3 did an initial PD. On day 7 the second round of PD began on the patient by Examiner 1, with Examiners 2 and 3 probing on days 9 and 11, respectively. This same methodology was used on all 20 patients until data was recorded for all of them. Each patient was probed a maximum of six times (two probes per examiner: the initial and the repeated probing). Therefore, the 20 patients were probed twice in different appointments by the three examiners. The sequence of the examiners was random (a lottery).</interventions>
    <comparator>-Intra-examiner reproducibility: Comparison of initial probing depth measurements and repeated probing depth measurements by each examiner
-Inter- examiner reproducibility: between three examiners. Comparison of repeated measurements of each examiner with repeated measurements of others examiners on probing pocket depth with a manual periodontal probe on healthy patients.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: Assess the intra and inter-examiner reproducibility on clinical register of probing pocket depth in healthy patients (without periodontal disease) using a measurement tool (periodontal probe).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: During a period of one month, the examiners selected subjects who will be participating in the study based on exclusion and inclusion criterions (subjects selection).
After selection of subjects, during a period of 4 months, the examiners worked on calibration process until demonstrate that they were calibrated (in subjects that was not part of the experimental group) according to parameters: Substantial kappa values, 90% agreement for +/- 1mm and an exact agreement in 75% of the PD repeated measurements. 
Once the examiners demonstrated that they had been trained within the abovementioned parameters the study was initiated. Finally, 8 months after calibration to collect and assess the datas.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: To assess the reproducibility differences between the Probing depth with a manual probe on mesial tooth surfaces  vs. distal tooth surfaces</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 8 months after calibration to collect the datas.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2: To assess the reproducibility differences between the Probing depth with a manual probe on anterior vs. posterior mouth areas.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 8 months after calibration to collect the datas.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3: To assess the reproducibility differences between the Probing depth with a manual probe on buccal vs. lingual tooth surfaces.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 8 months after calibration to collect the datas.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 4: To assess the reproducibility differences between the Probing depth with a manual probe on superior vs. inferior dental arch.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: 8 months after calibration to collect the datas.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients participating in the study could not have: a loss of clinical attachment levels; fixed or partial prosthetics, individual crowns or orthodontia; surgical or non-surgical periodontal treatments in the last eight months; been taking antibiotics; or be pregnant.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Presence of periodontal disease (attachment lost or bone lost)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>El Salvador</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Roberto Antonio Andrade Acevedo</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centro de Salud Integral 4212. Colonia Escalon. San Salvador, El Salvador, Central America</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>El Salvador</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: The periodontal probe remains the best clinical diagnostic tool to collect information regarding the health status and the attachment level of periodontal tissues. The aim of the present study was to evaluate the intra e inter-examiner reproducibility of probing pocket depth (PPD) measurements with a manual probe. Methods: Previously accepted by an Ethical Committee and after informed consent, 20 subjects without periodontal disease were selected if they presented at least 6 teeth per quadrant without antibiotic therapy in the last 8 months. 3 calibrated students (k&gt;0.6) at thesis level, assessed PPD from all teeth at 6 sites/tooth with William periodontal probe from the gingival margin to the bottom of the periodontal sulcus (rounded to the next 0.5mm). Initial and consecutive measurements were performed in duplicates by three examiners (n=19,692). Results: The intra-examiner agreement +/- 1mm &gt;90% was 99.85%, 100%, and 100% for the 3 examiners, respectively. However, no significant differences in reproducibility was detected at the intre-examiner level (p&lt;0.05). There were significant differences in the measurements of the anterior and posterior sites in the 3 examiners. No differences vestibular/lingual surfaces, mesial/distal surfaces, or superior/inferior jaws were detected. Conclusions: A high intra-examiner but low inter-exminer reproducibility of PPD in healthy individuals in vivo was detected. There were differences in PPD measurements between the anterior and posterior sites in the intra-examiner measurements for the three examiners</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Presentation: VII Session of International Association of Dental Research (IADR). Panama Section.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CIE. Institutional Ethics Comite of  Universidad Evangelica de El Salvador (Evangelic University of El Salvador)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Universidad Evangelica de El Salvador. First Building, Third floor. Prolongacion Alameda Juan Pablo II, Calle El Carmen, San Salvador, El Salvador, Central America.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/11/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Certificate assessment of clinical study n0 9</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/10/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>El Salvador</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Roberto Antonio Andrade Acevedo</name>
      <address>Centro de Salud Integral 4212. Colonia Escalon, San Salvador, Central America.</address>
      <phone>+(503) 2264 6321 (for San Salvador, El Salvador, Central America)</phone>
      <fax>+(503) 2275 4000-ext 4052</fax>
      <email>robertoandrade_periodoncia@yahoo.com.br, robertoandrade67@yahoo.com.br, acevedoroberto@hotmail.com.</email>
      <country>El Salvador</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Roberto Antonio Andrade Acevedo</name>
      <address>Centro de Salud Integral 4212. Colonia Escalon, San Salvador, Central America.</address>
      <phone>+(503) 2264 6321 (for San Salvador, El Salvador, Central America)</phone>
      <fax>+(503) 2275 4000-ext 4052</fax>
      <email>robertoandrade_periodoncia@yahoo.com.br, robertoandrade67@yahoo.com.br, acevedoroberto@hotmail.com.</email>
      <country>El Salvador</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Roberto Antonio Andrade Acevedo</name>
      <address>Centro de Salud Integral 4212. Colonia Escalon, San Salvador, Central America.</address>
      <phone>+(503) 2264 6321 (for San Salvador, El Salvador, Central America)</phone>
      <fax>+(503) 2275 4000-ext 4052</fax>
      <email>robertoandrade_periodoncia@yahoo.com.br, robertoandrade67@yahoo.com.br, acevedoroberto@hotmail.com.</email>
      <country>El Salvador</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>