<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82225">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/08/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/09/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000451404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot investigation of post burn itch - a randomised control trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Will those people with partial or full thickness burns have diminished post burn itch using Medilixir and massage in comparison to acqueous creme and massage?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ITCH (Investigating the effect of Treatment Creme to Help reduce post burn itch)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Burns</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Burns</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Medilixir is a topical creme which is a combination of bees wax and herbal oils. Patients will apply the Medilixir to the area of their newly healed burn twice daily for two weeks. Following this period they will 'crossover' and use aqueous creme twice daily on their newly healed burn for a further one week. There will be no washout period for this study between crossover as lotions applied topically for the relief of post burn itch are effective for short periods of time only. As cremes will crossover on the commencement of a new calander day there will be 12 hours or more between topical applications and an additional seven days to determine the elevation or decline or any further itch. The massage component of this study involves application of either creme. Each creme will be applied over a 5 to 10 minute period and massaged well into the newly healed skin.</interventions>
    <comparator>Aqueous creme - the current standard treatment for post burn itch at the Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital (RBWH) is currently applied topically to to the area of the patients newly healed burn twice daily until the patient deems this unnecessary (this period varies from days to months depending upon the relief from itch the creme may generate). For the purpose of this trial aqueous creme (as with Medilixir) will be applied twice daily to the newly healed burn. Depending upon group allocation (control or experiment) participants will receive aqueous for 1 week (if in the experiment where they will receive Medilixir for 2 weeks followed by aqueous for 1 week) or 2 weeks (if in the control where they will receive aqueous for the initial two weeks followed by one week of Medilixir creme).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diminished post burn itch as measured by a visual analogue scale (previously validated in other burn itch studies).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two weeks following application of either aqueous or Medilixir creme itch measures for the control and experimental groups will be statistically compared.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dimished antihistamine use</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two weeks following application of either aqueous or Medilixir creme antihistamine use between control and experimental groups will be statistically compared.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with partial or full thickness burns to their body surface area or greater. Those able to provide informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>110</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those unable to provide informed consent. Those unable to answer questions accurately given communication difficulties.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Each potential participant will be approached by the research assistant when their burn has healed and aqueous creme treatment would routinely commence. The patients will have the study explained to them (their involvement, the study timeframes, as well as their options to either refuse study inclusion or withdraw from the study). As patients are not aware of what either aqueous creme or Medilixir looks like this will form their blinding. Allocation to this trial will be concealed with the use of sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer random number generator will be used to allocate participants to either group.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/03/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/03/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>8/08/2008</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>18/08/2008</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>52</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4006</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Herston Rd
Herston
Brisbane</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland University of Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Victoria Park Rd
Kelvin Grove
4059</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital Foundation.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>RBWH
Herston Rd
Herston 
Brisbane</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Smith and Nephew</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Smith &amp; Nephew Pty Limited
Unit 9, 211 Montague Road
West End
Queensland 4101
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Between the years 2000 and 2004 approximately 46,611 people were hospitalised in Australia as a result of burn or scald related injury.1 While comorbidities such as infection and psychosocial health alterations are readily described, patients recovering from burn injury frequently experience a post burn itch.2,3 Post burn itch affects up to 80% of the burn population.4 While post burn itch varies in time frame as well as severity, some patients experience severe and debilitating itch disturbing their sleep, activities of daily living as well as their quality of life for months following wound healing.3 Post burn itch treatments, while multimodal, remain consistently ineffective.3 In line with current literature The Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital (RBWH) Burns Unit utilises various combinations of antihistamine medications, regular bathing, massage and aqueous crème in their management of post burn itch. Despite these varied interventions and the reputation of the RBWH Burn Unit as a centre of clinical excellence, itch remains the problem here that it is globally. Recent anecdotal evidence from several RBWH burn outpatients, however, suggests Medilixir (a combination of bees wax and herbal oils) to successfully assist in the minimisation of post burn itch. For this small patient cohort the change from aqueous crème to Medilixir markedly reduced their post burn itch. 1. Harrison, J., &amp; Steel, D. (2006). Burns and scalds. Australian Institute of Health and Welfare National Injury Surveillance Unit Briefing, 7, October 2006. 2. Smith, J.S., Smith, K.R., Rainey, S.L., &amp; DelGiorno, J. (2006). The psychology of burn care. Journal of Trauma Nursing, 13(3), pp.105-106. 3. Matheson, J.D., Clayton, J., &amp; Muller, M.J. (2001). The reduction of itch during burn wound healing. Journal of Burn Care and Rehabilitation, 22(1),pp.76-81. 4. Demling, R.H., &amp; DeSanti, L. (2003). Topical Doxepin significantly reduces itching and erythema in the chronically pruritic burn scar. Wounds, 15(6), pp.195-200.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Lewis, P.A., Wright, K., Webster, A., Steer, M., Rudd, M., Doubrovsky, A., &amp; Gardener, G. (2012). A randomized controlled trial comparing aqueous crème with a beeswax and herbal oil crème in the provision of relief from post-burn pruritis. Journal of Burn Care &amp; Research. 33(4), pp.195-200. 

Savovic, J., &amp; Lewis, P. (2013), A pilot randomised trial of Medilixir cream shows some promising results, but control treatment may have been inappropriate. Focus on Alternative and Complementary Therapies. 18(2), pp.104106. 

RBWH Health Care Symposium, Brisbane, Australia, 2008. P.A.Lewis, K.Wright, A.Webster, M.Steer, G.Gardner.
A randomised controlled trial comparing aqueous crème with bees wax crème in the provision of relief from post-burn itch

32nd Annual Scientific Meeting of the Australian and New Zealand Burns Association, Melbourne, Australia, 2008. P.A.Lewis, K.Wright, A.Webster, M.Steer, R.Cinco, G.Gardner, M.Rudd.
A randomised controlled trial comparing aqueous crème and bees wax crème in the provision of relief from post-burn itch</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>RBWH HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>RBWH
Herston Rd
Herston
Brisbane</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00172</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/08/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Lewis</name>
      <address>Queensland University or Technology 
Kelvin Grove Rd
Kelvin Grove
4059</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3138 3834</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.lewis@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kay Wright</name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital - Stuart Pegg Burns Unit
Herston Rd
Herston 4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 3496</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kay_wright@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Lewis</name>
      <address>ACU - Nudgee Campus</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3861 6094</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.lewis@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>