<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83189">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000230257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Bacterial adhesion to unworn and worn silicone hydrogel lenses</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, randomised, cross over, open label, bilateral design clinical trial to investigate the differences in the adhesion of various bacteria to a range of silicone hydrogel contact lenses worn by experienced contact lens wearers and to determine whether lens wear modulates adhesion</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Effect of lens wear on bacterial adhesion</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Nine silicone hydrogel lenses (Acuvue Advance, Acuvue Oasys, Acuvue Trueye, Night and Day, Air Optix Aqua, Biofinity, Avaira, Purevision, PremiO) will be tested. Each lens type will be worn by participants on a daily replacement schedule for approximately two weeks with a one day wash out between lens types. A minimum of 3 worn lenses will be collected for each lens type from each participant for bacterial adhesion testing.</interventions>
    <comparator>Nine unworn silicone hydrogel lenses (Acuvue Advance, Acuvue Oasys, Acuvue Trueye, Night and Day, Air Optix Aqua, Biofinity, Avaira, Purevision, PremiO) will undergo bacterial adhesion testing.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To establish baseline data for bacterial adhesion to unworn silicone hydrogel lenses. Outcome will be assessed using microbial adhesion assay and recovery of viable bacteria attached on the lens surface.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six (6) months from baseline.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To identify whether lens wear changes the level of bacterial adhesion to individual lens types.Outcome will be assessed using microbial adhesion assay and recovery of viable bacteria attached on the lens surface.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six (6) months from baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Identify whether lens wear alters the relative ranking of bacterial adhesion to lenses.Outcome will be assessed using microbial adhesion assay and recovery of viable bacteria attached on the lens surface and comparison of the results between worn and unworn lenses.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Six (6) months from baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Be able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent;
Be at least 18 years old;
Be willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the Investigator;
Have ocular health findings considered to be "normal" and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses; 
Is correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses at baseline;
Be experienced at wearing contact lenses at baseline;
Owns spectacles with current prescription.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses;
Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health and auto-immune diseases;
An active corneal infection or any active ocular disease that would affect wearing of contact lenses;
A need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication up to 12 weeks prior to and during the trial;
Any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings/are known to affect a participants ocular health/physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse manner or risk providing a false positive. 
Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial;
Previous corneal refractive surgery;
Contraindications to contact lens wear;
Currently enrolled in another clinical trial;
Participation in a clinical trial within the previous 2 weeks for dispensing studies.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomised plan will be generated by a computer.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Institute for Eye Reseach</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14, Barker Street, Kensington NSW 2052 Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Institute for Eye Reseach</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14, Barker Street, Kensington NSW 2052 Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To determine differences in the adhesion of various microorganisms on various silicone hydrogel lens materials and to determine whether lens wear modulates this adhesion.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Vision Cooperative Research Centre Ltd and Institute for Eye Research Human Ethics Commitee (VIHEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14, Barker Street, Kensington NSW 2052 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/09/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/08/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Mark Willcox</name>
      <address>Institute for Eye Research
Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14, Barker Street, Kensington NSW 2052 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>m.willcox@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Jerome Ozkan</name>
      <address>Institute for Eye Research
Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14, Barker Street, Kensington NSW 2052 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Jerome Ozkan</name>
      <address>Institute for Eye Research
Level 5, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building, Gate 14, Barker Street, Kensington NSW, 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>