<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369736">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000068460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Reducing Negative Behaviours in Daily Routines for Young Children with Autism</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Reducing Negative Behaviours in Daily Routines for Young Children with Autism</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Autism </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Global developmental delay</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The primary intervention drew on sensory integration theory (Bundy, Lane, &amp; Murray, 2002). Five components built on an approach adapted from Anzalone and Williamson (2000) were considered as follows with a hypothetical example : 1) Observing and reframing sensory processing challenges in context (e.g., the child has an extreme reaction to the vacuum cleaner due to auditory over-responsiveness). The mother and the therapist, together, observed and discussed the behavior and developed management strategies. 2) Modifying the environment to reduce contributing sensory input (e.g., close doors to place a barrier between the child and the vacuum cleaner). 3) Modifying the activity to minimize unpleasant sensations (e.g., vacuum when the child is not home). 4) Managing the activity (e.g., use visuals to prepare for vacuuming; use calming sensory activities). 5) Promoting agency in the child in response to sensory challenges (e.g., teach the child to turn on a favorite TV show during vacuuming)..Four sessions occurred in the home for an hour once a week at a convenient time nominated by the family. The mother was the focus of the intervention, discussing intervention strategies and how they could be applied in the context of family routines. Sessions occurred over a four week period,  however final scheduling was responsive to family needs.
A second intervention was provided to all participants based on the  Being Responsive  (Braithwaite, Keen, &amp; Rodger, 2004) program. The program outlines four roles and six strategies to promote responsiveness and encourage interaction that are common in autism early intervention programmes (Roberts and Prior, 2006) . In this study, the program was modified, identifying and applying specific roles and strategies to manage the target behaviour of concern. The four intervention sessions occurred in the home, with the mother the focus of intervention in coaching/consultation model. The focus of the sessions were to identify how to apply strategies to increase responsiveness in the context of family routines. The mother applied the strategies identified with the child in the main, with some modelling or demonstration by the therapist as needed.  
A fidelity checklist was completed by an independent rater, unfamiliar with the study. The rater completed the checklist after listening to a randomly selected audio recording of one session for each participant.
Two weeks break occurred between the two interventions which were randomly allocated to order of intervention for each participant.</interventions>
    <comparator>Being Responsive is the comparator intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>An individualized VAS was developed for each participant to rate behaviors that interfered with family routines that could be linked with sensory processing challenges. The VAS was programmed into an electronic handheld device (Palm Z22) using The Experience Sampling Program (ESP, Barrett &amp; Barrett, 2005). Mothers received training with the Palm and were encouraged to find a suitable time to rate their perceptions of the childs behavior each day. The VAS was anchored at both ends by statements relevant to the target behavior; specific criteria describing the target behavior were displayed each time the VAS was opened. The language and phrasing of these descriptors was developed collaboratively with the mothers to ensure focus on the same behavior over time. Mothers moved a slider along the VAS to reflect their perceptions of the behavior over the whole day generating a score out of 100.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary outcome was measured repeatedly over the baseline and intervention phases of the study, consistent with single case experimental design methodology. Mothers were asked to rate behaviour  and their stress on a daily basis during the active phases of the study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Developmental Behaviour Checklist (DBC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three months after completion of intervention phases.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parenting Stress Index (PSI)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three months after completion of intervention phases</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent stress rated on a Visual Analogue Scale on a daily basis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months after intervention was completed</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>staff provided study information to parents of children newly diagnosed with ASD.  Families were assessed on entry to the study and included if their child was between 3 and 5 years of age and had: (1) atypical sensory processing on the Infant Toddler Sensory Profile  (ITSP, Dunn, 2002); (2) a behavior, nominated by the family that interfered with daily routines that was logically linked with sensory challenges (judged by the therapist); (3) autistic disorder based on scores on the Autism Diagnostic Observation Schedule(Lord, Rutter, &amp; Le Couteur, 1995) administered by a psychologist trained to research reliability level; and (4) global developmental delay confirmed by clinic reports provided by parents.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>5</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No autism diagnosis;
Older than 5 years of age;
Parents unable to identify behaviour of concern
No atypical sensory processing</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation to order of intervention was concealed from the families and the therapists. On confirmation of meeting the entry criteria, an independent researcher allocated to order of intervention using a random number generator.</concealment>
    <sequence>Random number generator was used for sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Visual analysis of graphed repeated measures data from visual analogue scale outcome measure. Single case experimental design standards recommend 3 replications of a functional relationship between the introduction of intervention and behaviour change. Based on this requirement a minimum of 3 participants were required.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>16/04/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>11/06/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>7</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Children's Hospital at Westmead - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Sydney Children's Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Surry Hills</postcode>
    <postcode>2135 - Strathfield</postcode>
    <postcode>2204 - Marrickville</postcode>
    <postcode>2035 - Maroubra</postcode>
    <postcode>2193 - Hurlstone Park</postcode>
    <postcode>2207 - Bexley</postcode>
    <postcode>2218 - Carlton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Health Sciences, 
Cumberland Campus,
East St 
Lidcombe, NSW 2141</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Not applicable</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Not applicable</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The project will explore the efficacy of an occupational therapy intervention in common use clinically with young children with autism, provided in the home to address a problematic behaviour indentified by the family. Two different interventions will be provided to each child in random order, one a sensory based intervention and the other is a relationship based intervention, Being Responsive. Ten participants will be included in a single case experimental design study, undergoing intervention and baseline phases over a 14 week period with daily behaviour ratings and parent stress levels monitored on a visual analogue scale. Each participant acts as their own comparison across phases. This study will help to understand the responses to each intervention. A follow up data collection will occur for two weeks, 6 months after the completion of the intervention. Intervention sessions will be audio recorded to allow for checking of the application of the intervention.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Bulkeley, K., Bundy, A., Roberts, J., &amp; Einfeld, S. (2013). ASD intervention research in real world contexts: Refining single case designs. Research in Autism Spectrum Disorders(7), pp. 1257-1264. doi:10.1016/j.rasd.2013.07.014</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Childrens Hospital Westmead</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Cnr Hawkesbury Rd and Hainsworth St,
Westmead, NSW 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/12/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/CHW/58</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/06/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369736-MainStudyEthicsApprovals2008-09.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Anita Bundy</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences,
The University of Sydney,
Cumberland Campus,
East St.
Lidcombe, 
NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9857</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anita.bundy@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kim Bulkeley</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences,
The University of Sydney,
Cumberland Campus,
East St.
Lidcombe, 
NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93519034</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kim.bulkeley@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kim Bulkeley</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences,
The University of Sydney,
Cumberland Campus,
East St.
Lidcombe, 
NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9034</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kim.bulkeley@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kim Bulkeley</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences,
The University of Sydney,
Cumberland Campus,
East St.
Lidcombe, 
NSW 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9034</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kim.bulkeley@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>