<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82843">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/05/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/05/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000270314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Tai chi for long-term low back pain</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of tai chi exercise on pain and disability in subjects with long-term non-specific low back pain: a randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TAICHI</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Long-term low back pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Tai Chi Exercise Program: based on sun style tai chi, which compared to other styles of tai chi, involves less deep-knee bending promoting a more upright stance, a decreased stepping distance which utilizes more forward, backward and side-stepping movements. This tai chi program has 21 moves in total and was designed by Dr. Paul Lam, General Physician and Tai Chi Master. It has been entitled Tai Chi for Back Pain and can be viewed on DVD of same name. The dosage of treatment will be18 sessions over a 10 week period (2x/week for 8 weeks and 1x/week for 2 weeks). This dosage is consistent recent tai chi research and reflects the norm for general tai chi practice in the community.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control treatment is no tai chi. 
All participants are allowed to continue with their usual health care for their low back pain. We have defined usual as participating in these therapies for a minimum of 4 weeks prior to trial entry. The participants of both treatment and control are asked not to seek new forms of treatment for their back pain during the 10 week period of the trial.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bothersomeness of Pain Symptoms measured with the 0-10 Bothersomeness Numerical Rating Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported Disability measured with
The Quebec Pain Disability Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain measured with The Pain Disability Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subject's global impression of change measured with the Global Perceived Effect Scale (-5 to 5)</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related Quality of Life measured with Short Form 36 (SF-36) Health Survey v2</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Non-specific low back pain +/- leg pain of at least 3 months duration.
2. A score of moderate or higher on item 7 or 8 of the SF-36
3. Not currently receiving any new treatments within the last 4 weeks for their low back pain
4. Agree not to seek any new treatments for their back pain during the course of the trial 
5. Aged greater than 18 and less than 75 years
6. English Speaker 
7. Literate in English
8. Expects to continue residing in Sydney for study duration.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Suspected or confirmed serious spinal pathology (fracture, metastatic, inflammatory or infective diseases of the spine, cauda equina syndrome/widespread neurological disorder).
2. Suspected or confirmed pregnancy
3. Unable to speak English
4. Nerve root compromise (2 of strength, reflex or sensation affected for same nerve root)
5. Spinal surgery. 
6. Scheduled for major surgery during treatment or follow-up period 
7. Any of the contraindications to exercise listed on page 42 of the American College of Sports Medicine guidelines (ACSM's Guidelines for Exercise Testing and Prescription, 1995).
8. If participant is receiving workers compensation, all relevant treatment parties need to agree to Tai Chi treatment.
9.  Participation in a tai chi program within the last 6 months.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be screened via telephone during their initial telephone call to determine eligibility. All screening questionnaires are listed in a booklet separate to the assessment booklet.

If the volunteer is determined to be eligible for the study, they will be asked to attend an initial group session where they and 7 others will fill out the baseline assessment booklet. Upon completion of the assessment booklet they will be assigned a sealed opaque envelope from a randomly generated sequence that contains the treatment code and allocates them to either receive the tai chi intervention or continue with their usual care and join the wait-list control.</concealment>
    <sequence>The allocation sequence will be generated using the random number function in excel.  The treatment codes will be placed in consecutively numbered sealed opaque envelopes. Participants will be allocated to treatment by selecting the next envelope in sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2000</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Faculty of Medicine, The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The George Institute for International Health 
Musculoskeletal Division
Level 7, 341 George St.
Sydney, NSW
2000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>One in ten Australians suffer from long-term low back pain (Australian Institute of Health and Welfare, 2000). Long-term low back pain is extremely difficult to treat because it does not respond to most treatments, leading to an enormous social and economic burden. Exercise therapy may provide a potential solution as there is biological plausibility for effect. However, the types of exercise to be used and resulting efficacy have not been well established.  Tai chi has been used as an exercise prescription as part of Traditional Chinese Medicine for many years. Recent studies have shown that tai chi is a safe exercise for elderly adults suffering from arthritis (Kirstiens 1991). Since a high percentage of patients with long-term low back pain are over 55yrs, tai chi should also be considered as a potential exercise in the treatment plan for this group. However, there are few randomised controlled trials studying tai chi and its efficacy for improving pain is not well known. We propose to conduct the first randomised-controlled trial of tai chi exercise for those who have long-term low back pain, which will inform best practice for managing long-term low back pain in clinical settings.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Level 3, Old Teacher?s College 
Camperdown Campus, Paramatta Road 
Sydney, NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/11/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10452</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Chris Maher</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Internaltional Health
Musculoskeletal Division
Level 7, 341 George St. 
Sydney, NSW
2000</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9657 0382</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9657 0301</fax>
      <email>cmaher@george.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amanda Hall</name>
      <address>The George Institute for International Health
Musculoskeletal Division
Level 7, 341 George St. 
Sydney, NSW
2000</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9657 0391</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9657 0301</fax>
      <email>amandahall@george.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Amanda Hall</name>
      <address>The George Institute for International Health
Musculoskeletal Division
Level 7, 341 George St. 
Sydney, NSW
2000</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9657 0391</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9657 0301</fax>
      <email>amandahall@george.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>