<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362817">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000928819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A prospective, randomised, controlled trial of smoking cessation through personalised intervention</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, randomised, controlled trial of smoking cessation through personalised intervention</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1133-0502</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SCUPI 3 (Smoking Cessation through Personalised Intervention 3)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Smoking</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Personalised video dramatising the potential consequences of having a heart attack secondary to smoking.
The video is personalised by inserting photos of the subject, non-smoking partner and family into the video. The video duration is 8 minute.  It is viewed on 2 occasions separated by approximately one week, and is viewed by the participant alone, accompanied by a study investigator.</interventions>
    <comparator>The non-personalised video is the same as the personalised video except that the primary characters in the video are actors ie not the participant or family members.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Smoking Cessation Rate.  The outcome is assessed by carbon monoxide breath test, and subject self-report.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary timepoint:  6 months
Secondary timepoints:  2 weeks, 3 months, 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological impact of the personalised video. We will evaluate psychological impact using a Video Response Scale (7 point Likert scale) we have developed for this proposal, and will also assess subjective distress response to the video using the Impact of Event Scale (IES) (Horowitz et al.1979).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urge to smoke.  This will be measured by the Questionnaire on Smoking Urges (QSU ? Brief Version) (Tiffany et al., 1991).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Awareness of the negative consequences of smoking. This will be assessed on a number of dimensions including health risks and as measured by the Risk Perception Scale (adapted from Borelli et. al., 2010).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Smoking subject with non-smoking spouse/partner willing to attend enrolment session (for having pictures taken)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Psychotic disorder, Substance Dependence (including alcohol), Pregnancy.  Screening for psychotic and substance disorders will be conducted with the use of the MINI Neuropsychiatric Inventory.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Prospective subjects and partners will receive an information sheet and consent form.  They will then be seen by study investigators and eligibility confirmed.  Once they have signed consent, treatment allocation will occur through contacting a central blinded person. Randomisation will be used with a randomisation table created by computer software, with stratification for study centre.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence will be generated by randomisation computer software, with stratification for study centre.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal North Shore Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Reserve Road, St Leonards NSW 2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>North Shore Heart Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 543 St Leonards NSW 2065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Smoking remains a major preventable risk factor for cardiovascular disease. This research proposal builds on 2 observations; firstly, experiencing a heart attack is a teachable moment that enables up to 60% smokers to abruptly quit once they have experienced a heart attack; and secondly, we have demonstrated in a pilot study that it is feasible to induce smoking cessation through subjects watching a DVD containing images of him/herself, his/her partner and family digitally superimposed into a scenario depicting the person having a heart attack as a result of smoking, and the potential consequences to the partner and family.  Using this novel approach, which we describe as a personalized simulated teachable moment, 7 of 13 smokers (53%) were abstinent at 6 months (published in Am J Cardiol 2010).  We have since completed 20 subjects of whom 12 (60%) were abstinent at 12 months. 

In the current proposal, we will evaluate the simulated teachable moment hypothesis in a prospective randomized controlled study. We will compare smoking cessation rates using the personalized DVD with the same video using actors.  In addition, we will evaluate the psychological impact of the personalized video.  If this study demonstrates an additive effect of the personalized simulated teachable moment in smoking cessation, its use would be supported as an adjunct to smoking cessation, which in turn would have major health benefits in our society.  We will conduct the study in selected General Practices and Pharmacies to investigate its broad applicability and ability to be disseminated widely.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Northern Sydney Local Health District (NSLHD) Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Business Unit
Level 13, Kolling Building Royal North Shore Hospital St Leonards NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>1206-179M</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/06/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Geoffrey Tofler</name>
      <address>Cardiology Department
Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards, NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>61-2-99268688</phone>
      <fax>61-2-99067807</fax>
      <email>gtofler@nsccahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Geoffrey Tofler</name>
      <address>Cardiology Department
Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards, NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>61-2-99268688</phone>
      <fax>61-2-99067807</fax>
      <email>gtofler@nsccahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Geoffrey Tofler</name>
      <address>Cardiology Department
Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards, NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>61-2-99266359</phone>
      <fax>61-2-99067807</fax>
      <email>gtofler@nsccahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>