<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335453">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/05/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000398000</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Influence of Omega 3 fatty acids on osmosensation and thirst signaling</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Influence of Omega 3 fatty acids on osmosensation and thirst signaling in ambulatory patients aged 65-85 to improve thirst sensation, voluntary fluid intake and improve quality of life in elderly subjects.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Improving dehydration in elderly by supplementation of Omega 3 fatty acids</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Improving thirst sensation by supplementation of Omega 3 fatty acids</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Improving quality of life by supplementation of Omega 3 fatty acids</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fluid intake</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Stage1 (Questionnaire survey) : A selfstructured questionnaire survey (assessment for eligibility to participate) and mini-mental state examination (MMSE- psychological assessment for cognitive impairment) will be conducted among all elderly residents from aged care group facilities in Victoria, (aged 65-85y, inclusive), to screen them for stage 2 and 3 studies. Each participant will be provided an information sheet and consent will be obtained (subjected to approval from Victoria University Human Ethics Committee).
Stage 2 (Prospective study- 5 days) 
This phase study is designed to identify the subjects who are prone to dehydration, thirst deficit, low erythrocyte omega 3 fatty acid levels and whether it is possible accept omega 3 fatty acid supplementation. The fluid intake of the participants in stage 2 will be recorded for 5 days inclusive of a week end. A blood and urine sample will be collected for biochemical analysis. Other clinical assessments include blood pressure and heart rate (both standing and lying position), Body mass index calculation, presence of dry tongue, tongue furrows or dry oral membrane (physical examination) and thirst ratings. A sensory screening test will be conducted to evaluate the participants level of acceptance of the fish oil or the placebo oil. 
Stage 3:The recruitment will be based on subjects found to exhibit dehydration and thirst deficit (from prospective study). In this single blinded study, the participants will be randomly allocated based on age, sex, body weight to 
Intervention
(a) Intervention group: 3 months consumption of omega 3 fatty acids (5 ml fish oil once a day(Melrose, Norwegian fish oil; which contains 815 mg of Eicosapentaenoic  and 540 mg of Docosahexaenoic) will be given to intervention group
or

 (b) Control Placebo group: 3 months consumption of 5 ml of cold pressed soya bean oil, both floated on fruit juice (lemon) once a day will be given to placebo participants . Both cohorts will be given additional 5 ml of fruit juice to rinse the mouth.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control placebo group</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Voluntary fluid intake with omega 3 fatty acid supplementation

Tool:Graduated bottled water will be provided to participants to monitor the daily volume of water consumption. This will be recorded in a nutrition diary in addition to all other fluids like tea, coffee, soup or juice etc for both intervention and placebo cohorts.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Thrice a week throughout for the entire study period of 3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improving thirst sensation

Tool: Measured by a scored visual analogue scale, where the participants will be asked to mark a scale between 0-5 for both intervention and placebo cohorts. The thirst rating scale comprises of: 0 score- not at all thirsty, 1-slightly thirsty, 2-moderately thirsty, 3-strongly or very thirsty and 4-extremely thirsty and 5- severve thirst.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measuring the thirst rates at the base line, in end of month 1, end of month 2 and end of month 3 at the blood sampling time and at 2 instance of thirst challenge with salt meal/drink for both cohorts.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life change with omega 3 fatty acid supplementation

Tools: Quality of life will assessment by SF-36 assessment tool for both cohorts. at the start of the trial ( month 1) and at the end of 3 month trial period for both cohorts.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Base line assessment of quality of life at the start of the trial (month 1) and at the end of 3 month trial period for both cohorts.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The participants who meet the following criteria will be included in the study
Age between 65 - 85y (inclusive) of both sex (ambulatory subjects).
Provide an informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Mandatory exclusion criteria
	Subjects who are included in any other clinical trials.
	Abnormal kidney function, liver function and incomplete bladder control (enuresis).
	Subjects on anticoagulant and diuretic medications.
	Subjects with cardiac and/or chronic inflammatory conditions.
	Subjects with hemorrhagic stroke and high diabetics conditions.
	Allergy to fish products and currently on fish oil or flax seed supplements. 
	Subjects on fluid / salt restriction diet and severe cognitive impairment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed 
Stage1 (Questionnaire survey) : A self–structured questionnaire survey (assessment for eligibility to participate) and mini-mental state examination (MMSE- psychological assessment for cognitive impairment).
Stage 2 (Prospective study- 5 days) 
This phase study is designed to identify the subjects who are prone to dehydration, thirst deficit, low erythrocyte omega 3 fatty acid  levels and whether it is possible accept omega 3 fatty acid supplementation
Stage 3 (Pilot clinical trial)
The recruitment will be based on subjects found to exhibit dehydration and thirst deficit (from stage 2).</concealment>
    <sequence>All the subjects will be randomized based on sex, Age and body weight by using procedures such as coin-tossing. The participants with similar age group (65-80) and body weights (60-80 kg) and equal number of males and females will be allocated for randomisation . The coin will be tossed and all the heads will be intervention group and tails will be in the control placebo group till all the participants are equally divided in two cohort groups. Previous treatment is used for the stratification.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3011</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Victoria University, Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Biomedical and Health Sciences 
Victoria University, St Albans Campus,
Building 6, McKechnie st, VIC 3021
Melbourne, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victoria University, Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Biomedical and Health Sciences 
Victoria University, St Albans Campus,
Building 6, McKechnie st, VIC 3021
Melbourne, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Anitha Dudhani and Dr. Michael Mathai</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Biomedical and Health Sciences 
Victoria University, St Albans Campus,
Building 6, McKechnie st, VIC 3021
Melbourne, Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim: To conduct a prospective trial in a cohort of elderly people to discover the prevalence of dehydration and any association with Omega 3 fatty acid deficiency. This will be followed by a pilot clinical trial aiming to test if 3 month nutritional supplementation with Omega 3 fatty acid may improve thirst sensation, voluntary fluid intake and improve quality of life in comparison with elderly on placebo control. 

Hypothesis 
We hypothesise that, there is a positive correlation between prevalence of dehydration and omega 3 fatty acid  deficiency in the elderly and supplementation with omega 3 fatty acid will reduce the occurrence of dehydration and improve Quality of life
Factors that predispose elderly to dehydration
1. Changes to kidney function and insufficient sensation of thirst.
2. Hormonal changes; normal /increased production of vasopressin, increased response to osmotic stimulation and decreased nocturnal secretions. Atrial natriuretic peptide (ANP) increases secretions with increased stimulation, decreased renin activity and aldosterone production. 
                                                                                                3. Neurological impairments altering the hypothalamus and pituitary gland, which affect sensation of thirst.

4. Medication (for example, diuretics and laxatives).

5. Chronic illness, communication issues cognitive difficulties and limited mobility.
	
6. Not drinking enough water to avoid occurrence of incontinence.
7. Fuid loss due to diarrhoea or vomiting and not compensating for loss.
Outcome
Improved thirst sensation, voluntary fluid intake and improve quality of life in elderly subjects.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Victoria University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HRETH 10/97</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/05/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Michael Mathai</name>
      <address>School of Biomedical and Health Sciences 
Victoria University, St Albans Campus,
Building 6, McKechnie st, VIC 3021
Melbourne, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9919 2211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.mathai@ vu.edu.au.</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anitha Dudhani</name>
      <address>School of Biomedical and Health Sciences 
Victoria University, St Albans Campus,
Building 6, McKechnie st, VIC 3021
Melbourne, Australia</address>
      <phone>+610431586077</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anitha.dudhani@live.vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anitha Dudhani</name>
      <address>School of Biomedical and Health Sciences 
Victoria University, St Albans Campus,
Building 6, McKechnie st, VIC 3021
Melbourne, Australia</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>