<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365863">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000307606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An open label study to investigate the safety and efficacy of treatment with ACH-0143102 and sofosbuvir in hepatitis C patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A phase 2, open-label, randomized, controlled, partial crossover study to evaluate the efficacy, safety and tolerability of 8 weeks or 6 weeks of ACH-0143102 and sofosbuvir in treatment-naive subjects with chronic hepatitis C genotype-1 viral infection</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1153-5593</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Protocol Number ACH102-017</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hepatitis C</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Active treatment is ACH-0143102 (2 x 25mg capsules) and sofosbuvir (1 x 400mg tablet) to be taken orally once a day.

The study is divided into 2 groups and will enrol up to 36 people. The study will initially randomize 18 subjects in an open label fashion into two treatment groups: Group 1A and Group 1B. Twelve (12) subjects will receive active treatment (50 mg ACH-0143102 + 400 mg sofosbuvir) starting on Day 1 for 8 weeks (Group 1A), and be followed for an additional 24 weeks. The other 6 subjects (Group 1B) will have a 12 week observational period, in which they will receive no treatment. Group 2 will only proceed if 100% of the subjects in Group 1A have virus not detected in the blood at 4 weeks after treatment is finished. A total of approximately 18 subjects could participate in Groups 2A and 2B. Up to six subjects from Group 1B will enter Group 2A. In addition, 12 new subjects will be randomized (1:1) in an open label fashion to either Group 2A (active treatment with 50 mg of ACH-0143102 + 400 mg of sofosbuvir for 6 weeks) or to Group 2B (observational period). Subjects in Groups 1B or 2B who received no treatment will be offered either 6 or 8 weeks of the same regime, depending on the results of the Groups 1A and 2A. Every patient will be checked throughout the study to ensure that the treatment is working and to record any side effects

Medication compliance will be monitored by tablet/capsule count at each study visit.

Subjects randomized to the 8 week regime will be required to attend clinic visits on 17 occasions over a 32 week period - a screening visit, a day 1 (baseline visit), a visit once a week for 8 weeks, and then for 8 follow up visits (at week 10, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28 and 32).
Those subjects who are randomised to the observation period will not be required to attend clinic after week 12.

Subjects randomized to the 6 week regime will be required to attend clinic visits on 15 occasions over a 30 week period - a screening visit, a day 1 (baseline visit), a visit once a week for 6 weeks, and then for 7 follow up visits (at week 8, 10, 14, 18, 22, 26 and 30. Those subjects who are randomised to the observation period will not be required to attend clinic after week 10.


Follow up visits will include a range of  assessments (vital signs, pregnancy tests, safety laboratory tests, ECGs,  adverse event assessments, concomitant medication review) and PK sampling.

No washout period is required as the only participants who are permitted to cross over are participants who did not receive any treatment.</interventions>
    <comparator>Observation group will receive no treatment. 

Once the week 12 HCV RNA results from Group 1A have been reviewed by Achillion Pharmaceuticals, Inc., sites will be informed how subjects in the observational group will proceed according to this algorithm:

1. If Sustained Virologic Response (SVR) is less than 90% at the week 12 time point for subjects in Group 1A, no further enrollment will occur, and subjects in Group 1B will receive appropriate standard of care, provided they were compliant with the protocol.  
2. If SVR is greater than or equal to 90% but less than 100% at the week 12  time point for subjects in Group 1A, then subjects in Group 1B will be eligible to crossover from the observational treatment period and receive the same treatment as subjects in Group 1A (8 weeks of active treatment with 50 mg of ACH-0143102 + 400 mg of sofosbuvir) followed by 24 weeks of follow-up.
3. If 100% SVR is achieved at the 12 week  time point for subjects in Group 1A, the 6 subjects who were in Group 1B, will be eligible to crossover into Group 2A and receive 6 weeks of active treatment with 50 mg of ACH-0143102 plus 400 mg of sofosbuvir

Once the week 10 HCV RNA results from Group 2A have been reviewed by Achillion Pharmaceuticals, Inc., sites will be informed how subjects in the observational group will proceed according to this algorithm:

If SVR is less than 90% at the EOT+4 week time point for subjects in Group 2A, then subjects in Group 2B will crossover from the observational period and receive the same treatment as subjects in Group 1A (8 weeks of active treatment with 50 mg of ACH-0143102 + 400 mg of sofosbuvir) followed by 24 weeks of follow-up.
2. If SVR is greater than or equal to 90% at the EOT+4 time point for subjects in Group 2A, then subjects in Group 2B will crossover from the observational period and receive the same treatment as subjects in Group 2A (6 weeks of active treatment with 50 mg of ACH-0143102 plus 400 mg of sofosbuvir) with 24 weeks of follow-up.

The standard of care provided to subjects will be determined by the principal investigator and will be the most effective available treatment for genotype 1 hepatitis C infection at the time of the study.

In order for the HCV RNA analyses to take place, there may be a time delay (days or weeks) between the end of the observation period and the next treatment course for patients in Group 1B/2B.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the incidence of sustained virologic response (SVR) in subjects who received 8 weeks of active treatment.

This will be assessed by HCV RNA analysis on blood samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks after the completion of dosing</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the incidence of sustained virologic response (SVR) in subjects who received 6 weeks of active treatment.

This will be assessed by HCV RNA analysis on blood samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks after the completion of dosing</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the safety and tolerability of 8 weeks of ACH-0143102 in combination with sofosbuvir in subjects with genotype-1 viral infection.  Assessed by collection of adverse event data, laboratory tests, ECG, echocardiogram, vital signs, physical examination</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety will be assessed at weeks 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8, 10, 12, 16, 20, 24, 28 and 32 
 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the safety and tolerability of 6 weeks of ACH-0143102 in combination with sofosbuvir in subjects with genotype-1 viral infection.  Assessed by collection of adverse event data, laboratory tests, ECG, echocardiogram, vital signs, physical examination</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety will be assessed at weeka 1,2,3,4,5,6,8,10,14,18,22,26 and 30.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the incidence of sustained virologic response in subjects who received active treatment for either 6 or 8 weeks. 
This will be assessed via HCV RNA analysis on blood samples. </outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8 and 24 weeks after the completion of dosing</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Chronic HCV infection
- HCV GT-1
- HCV RNA greater than 10,000 IU/mL at screening
- Signed and dated written consent
- Treatment naive subjects
- Biopsy or fibroscan confirming no evidence of cirrhosis</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- BMI greater than 36kg/m2
- Pregnant or lactating females. Men whose female partners are pregnant or contemplating pregnancy
- Clinically significant laboratory abnormality at screening
- Known HIV infection
- Positive hepatits B surface antigen
- History of participation in a clinical trial with pegylated interferon, RBV, or a direct-acting anti-viral agent, or previous treatment with any of these where at least one dose was taken
- Use of dietary supplements, herbal supplements, potent PGP inducers in the intestine, anticonvulsants, antimycobacterials and HIV protease inhibitors.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation generated by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Due to the exploratory nature of this study, no power or sample size calculations were performed. The number of subjects was chosen on an empirical basis</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>9/04/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>36</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Achillion Pharmaceuticals, Inc</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>300 George Street
New Haven, CT 06511</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Achillion Pharmaceuticals, Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>300 George Street
New Haven, CT 06511</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Clinical Network Services Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 78312, Grey Lynn, Auckland 1245</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will evaluate whether 6 or 8 weeks treatment with two antiviral agents, Sofosbuvir and ACH0143102, will be safe and effective in patients infected with Hepatitis C genotype 1 who have never been treated.

The study is divided into 2 groups and will enrol up to 36 people.

The study will initially randomize 18 subjects in an open ­label fashion into two treatment groups: Group 1A and Group 1B. Twelve (12) subjects will receive active treatment (50 mg ACH­0143102 + 400 mg sofosbuvir) starting on Day 1 for 8 weeks (Group 1A), and be followed for an additional 24 weeks. The other 6 subjects (Group 1B) will have a 12 week observational period, in which they will receive no treatment.

Group 2 will only proceed if 100% of the subjects in Group 1A have virus not detected in the blood at 4 weeks after treatment is finished. A total of approximately 18 subjects could participate in Groups 2A and 2B.
Up to six subjects from Group 1B will enter Group 2A. In addition, 12 new subjects will be randomized (1:1) in an open ­label fashion to either Group 2A (active treatment with 50 mg of ACH­0143102 + 400 mg of sofosbuvir for 6 weeks) or to Group 2B (observational period).

Subjects in Groups 1B or 2B who received no treatment will be offered either 6 or 8 weeks of the same regime, depending on the results of the Groups 1A and 2A.

Every patient will be checked throughout the study to ensure that the treatment is working and to record any side­ effects
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>NA. Analysis ongoing</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern B Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/NTB/24</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Edward Gane</name>
      <address>Auckland Clinical Studies Ltd
PO Box 8963
Symonds Street
Auckland 1150</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 3474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>EdGane@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Michael Mader</name>
      <address>Achillion Pharmaceuticals Inc
300 George Street
New Haven CT 06511</address>
      <phone>+1 203-752-5441</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mmader@achillion.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hetal Kocinsky</name>
      <address>Achillion Pharmaceuticals Inc
300 George Street
New Haven CT 06511</address>
      <phone>+1 203 752 5490</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hkocinsky@achillion.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lynda Bluck</name>
      <address>Clinical Network Services Ltd
PO Box 78312
Grey Lynn
Auckland 1245</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>lynda.bluck@clinical.net.au</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>