<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370059">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000231448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised Controlled Trial (RCT) of iCanADAPT, an internet Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (iCBT) program for the treatment of depression and anxiety in early stage
cancer patients and cancer survivors.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Controlled Trial (RCT) of iCanADAPT, an internet Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (iCBT) program for the treatment of depression and anxiety in early stage
cancer patients and cancer survivors.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1179-1481</utrn>
    <trialacronym>iCanADAPT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>INTRODUCTION 
The Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression (CRUfAD) have developed an online cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) intervention for anxiety and depression in cancer patients and survivors. It is called iCanADAPT. Aspects of existing online interventions for anxiety and depression were adapted to the cancer context in the development of the iCanADAPT program. iCanADAPT is a 16week self-managed, mixed anxiety and depression program that is tailored to unique aspects of the cancer context, such as fear of cancer recurrence and adapting to illness, side-effects and survivorship. 

PROPOSAL 
The proposed study will evaluate the efficacy of the newly developed program as a cancer specific, online intervention for anxiety and depression and will aim to demonstrate that iCBT is an effective program for reducing anxiety and depressive symptoms in cancer patients and survivors.

ALLOCATION 
Participants with elevated anxiety and depression scores and either a current early stage cancer or a prior cancer diagnosis will be recruited. They will complete online screening questionnaires on CRUfAD's clinical trials website (www.virtualclinic.org.au) to assess eligibility to participate, and provide informed consent, before being interviewed over the telephone to assess eligibility for inclusion into the study. If accepted into the study, the participant will be randomly allocated into one of two groups:
GROUP 1 receive access to the iCanADAPT program
GROUP 2 treatment as usual group (may access care at any point) and after a 16 week period, will then be offered access the iCanADAPT program. 

OVERVIEW OF PROGRAM 
The iCanADAPT program consists of eight Modules based on cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT). It includes all treatment components typically seen in face-to-face CBT (the first-line treatment for depression and anxiety in early stage cancer patients and survivors). Each of the eight Modules can be considered as a discrete package. Each of the Modules contains: 
-	A Lesson (consists of a comic based, easy to read story, pertinent to all participants), 
-	An associated Lesson Summary (consists of more dense reading material, likely pertinent to all participants) 
-	Any additional resources for that part (which may not be needed by all participants)
-	Any additional worksheets for that part (pertinent to all participants)

THEMES of THE MODULES 
The overriding messages in each Module i.e. the each Lesson and its associated Lesson Summary, and any additional resources is arranged by themes. The main themes are: 
Module/Lesson 1	Learning about Depression and Anxiety in the cancer context
Module /Lesson 2 	Identifying and Tackling Thoughts 
Module/Lesson 3 	Tackling Unhelpful Behaviours  
Module/Lesson 4  	Helpful Coping  
Module/Lesson 5  	Adjusting to Change 
Module/Lesson 6 	Tackling Avoidance 
Module/Lesson 7 	Mastering Your Skills 
Module/Lesson 8  	Staying Well in the Long Term and Getting Even Better

EXAMPLE of a MODULE 
Hence, for Module 3 the theme is Tackling Unhelpful Behaviours, hence the Lesson shows the characters addressing their unhelpful behaviours in a comic based, easy to follow story. Further specific, more detailed, writing is contained in the Lesson summary, in this case under the following headings: 
1.	Tackling Low Activity 
2.	Before starting activity scheduling and physical activity 
3.	Daily Activity Scheduling 
4.	Physical Activity
5.	Structured Problem Solving
6.	Assertive Communication Skills
7.	Your Checklist
8.	Summary
In this case, the Extra Resources in Module 3 are:
3.1 - 100 Things To Do (List of Pleasant Activities)
3.2 - Diet 
3.3 - Smoking 
3.4 - FAQs Module 3
Furthermore, worksheets relevant to the Lesson/ Lesson Summary are provided: 
3.W1 - Activity planning and Monitoring worksheet 
3.W2 Structured Problem Solving worksheet
3.W3 Pros and Cons Worksheet

HOW TO WORK THROUGH THE PROGRAM 
Participants will asked to complete the Lesson (including the questionnaires beforehand for that lesson). Each lesson will take approximately 45 - 60 minutes to complete. They may go through all slides in a single sitting, or they may take multiple sittings to get to the end. Once they have completed the Lesson, the computer system automatically releases the associated Lesson Summary (i.e. it becomes available for download on completion of the lesson). They participant are asked to practice any associated skills/activities over the course of the following 14 days. Furthermore, upon completion of the Lesson, the extra resources for that part of the course, that Module, similarly become available. We ask participants to aim for an additional 3 hours per week to read these associated resources and to put into practice the CBT skills. 

TIMING of EACH MODULE
There is a purposeful lock-out time of 5 days between release of the subsequent Module i.e. next Lesson &amp; Lesson Summary etc. The 5-day lock-out refers to specific time points for the release of the next lesson and its associated lesson summary. For example, if a participant undertook Lesson 4 in one sitting &amp; hence downloaded the Lesson 4 Summary on 01st of the month, we purposely do not allow them to start Module 5, i.e. Lesson 5, until at least 5 days later, the 05th of the month. We will recommend instead that they spend up to two weeks (until the 14th of the month) reflecting and working through the prior Module i.e. Lesson 4, Lesson 4 Summary/ recommendations. However, as some patients prefer to progress at a quicker pace we do not necessitate the full 14 day period. Instead a five day minimum is set; to ensure that the patient does not get information overload and to encourage them to reflect and undertake activities for at least a short time period.  

CONTACT
Routine email contact from the clinician (registered clinical psychologist or psychiatry trainee/ medical officer) after completion of the first two lessons will occur. Further email contact will occur then as required. The participant is also able to email or phone the clinician at any point during the trial as required. The participant completes a measure of psychological distress before each lesson and if their scores increase by one or more standard deviations the clinician is automatically alerted and initiates contact with the participant by phone or email.

ADHERENCE 
Strategies used to improved adherence to intervention protocols and procedures for monitoring adherence include: automated email reminders, monitoring the downloading of homework, collection of data on how long participants spent reading lessons and practicing skills.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Control GROUP - treatment as usual group (may access care at any point) and after a 16 week period, will then be offered access the iCanADAPT program.  

These participants will complete 3 sets of questionnaires during their waiting period. Once the immediate treatment group has completed the iCanADAPT online program and post-treatment questionnaires (at week 17), the control group will be offered the same program. 

Should participants wish may access standard care for depression/anxiety through their usual healthcare pathway. In the case of these participants we foresee that they may attend local mental health practitioners/ GP, or psycho-social support staff at their local cancer centre during this time period. Should they choose to do so, we ask them to let us know. They are not excluded from the trial if they choose to access assistance. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in combined mean anxiety and depression scores according to the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale Total Score (HADS-T)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (just prior to commencing the program i.e. prior to Lesson 1).
Midpoint of the program (before Lesson 5, approximately 8 weeks after commencement of the program).
One week post-treatment (1 week post end of the program), 
At 3-months post-treatment (3 months post end of the program, for treatment group only).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in severity of psychological distress according to mean scores on the
Kessler-10 (K10)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (just prior to commencing the program i.e. prior to Lesson 1).
Prior to every subsequent lesson of the program.
One week post-treatment (1 week post end of the program), 
At 3-months post-treatment (3 months post end of the program, for treatment group only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in fear of cancer recurrence (Fear of Cancer Recurrence Inventory, FCRI) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (just prior to commencing the program i.e. prior to Lesson 1).
Midpoint of the program (before Lesson 5, approximately 8 weeks after commencement of the program).
One week post-treatment (1 week post end of the program), 
At 3-months post-treatment (3 months post end of the program, for treatment group only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in physical, social, emotional and functional status as measured by the Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-General Version (FACT-G QOL). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (just prior to commencing the program i.e. prior to Lesson 1).
Midpoint of the program (before Lesson 5, approximately 8 weeks after commencement of the program).
One week post-treatment (1 week post end of the program), 
At 3-months post-treatment (3 months post end of the program, for treatment group only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in suicidal ideation and/or passive death wish (as measured by the The Patient Health Questionnaire, Question 9  (PHQ-9, Q9) and the Beck Depression Inventory-II, Item 9 (BDI-II, Item 9). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (just prior to commencing the program i.e. prior to Lesson 1).
Midpoint of the program (before Lesson 5, approximately 8 weeks after commencement of the program).
One week post-treatment (1 week post end of the program), 
At 3-months post-treatment (3 months post end of the program, for treatment group only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with a change in the frequency of service use
and days out of role according to the Service Use and Days out of Role
Questionnaire (SUDOR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (just prior to commencing the program i.e. prior to Lesson 1).
Midpoint of the program (before Lesson 5, approximately 8 weeks after commencement of the program).
One week post-treatment (1 week post end of the program), 
At 3-months post-treatment (3 months post end of the program, for treatment group only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The feasibility of the treatment in terms of acceptability to patients and practicality for clinicians (as measured by changes in the Credibility/Expectancy Questionnaire; CEQ) - composite measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (just prior to commencing the program i.e. prior to Lesson 1).
Midpoint of the program (before Lesson 5, approximately 8 weeks after commencement of the program).
One week post-treatment (1 week post end of the program), 
At 3-months post-treatment (3 months post end of the program, for treatment group only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in mean anxiety scores according to the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale - Anxiety sub scale score (HADS-A)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (just prior to commencing the program i.e. prior to Lesson 1).
Midpoint of the program (before Lesson 5, approximately 8 weeks after commencement of the program).
One week post-treatment (1 week post end of the program), 
At 3-months post-treatment (3 months post end of the program, for treatment group only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in mean depression scores according to the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale - Depression sub scale score (HADS-D)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (just prior to commencing the program i.e. prior to Lesson 1).
Midpoint of the program (before Lesson 5, approximately 8 weeks after commencement of the program).
One week post-treatment (1 week post end of the program), 
At 3-months post-treatment (3 months post end of the program, for treatment group only).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults, aged over 18 years old with no maximum age. 
Self-identified as suffering from depression and/or anxiety and have online questionnaire scores indicating a clinical level of anxiety and/or depression on the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). 
Results of telephone diagnostic interview consistent with one, or more, diagnoses of Major Depressive Disorder (MDD), Generalised Anxiety Disorder (GAD), Panic Disorder or Agoraphobia, Illness Anxiety Disorder (IAD), or Adjustment disorder. 
Presence of current early stage cancer, or early stage cancer survivorship, will be based on self-report. 
Participants must be prepared to provide name/location of primary cancer care centre. 
Prepared to provide own name, phone number and address. 
Prepared to provide the name and address of a local general practitioner, and to provide written informed consent.  
English language skills equivalent to a School Certificate level. Have access to a phone and a computer with internet and a printer.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Mental health exclusion criteria will include psychosis, bipolar disorder, substance abuse or dependence and current suicidality. 

Cancer related exclusion criteria will include:  
-	Any metastases (cancer spread). The rationale being that the iCanADAPT program is specifically designed for early stage cancer i.e. cancer with curative intention to treat.
-	Currently in-patient.
-	Being within the first 6 weeks of cancer diagnosis.
-	Brain cancer/ malignancy. 

Physical health status exclusion will be an ECOG (Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group) performance status of greater than 1 (Oken et al., 1982). 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Random allocation to groups will be stratified according to cancer status (current cancer/cancer survivorship). Within those two groups patients who meet inclusion criteria for the study will be randomly allocated to one of the two groups (Group 1 iCBT; Group 2 deferred iCBT). 

Allocation concealment will occur in the following way: A staff member not involved in the clinical trial will generate the sequence using computer software (www.random.org) and place each choice in a sequentially numbered, opaque sealed and stapled envelope.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be done via www.random.org </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Deferred treatment. 
All participants will be given access to the treatment program. 
Group one will receive prompt access (for a 16 week period). 
Group two will wait until the first group have completed the program, and at the 16 week point will be given access to the program. 
</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>SAMPLE SIZE CALCULATION
We would expect pre-post improvement of Effect Size (ES) 1.0 for the iCBT group on the primary outcome measures. We also expect the iCBT group to improve more than the waitlist group by an ES of 0.6. Sample size is powered to have an 80% chance of detecting differences at p&lt;.05.

ANALYSIS PLAN
All analyses will be undertaken using liner mixed models. Relationships between observations at different occasions will be modelled with an unstructured covariance matrix. For each experimental group, planned contrasts will be used to compare changes between pre- treatment and post-treatment, and at 3-month follow-up for the iCBT group only. Planned pairwise comparisons will be used to compare between-groups at post-treatment, and effect sizes will be calculated (Cohens d) to measure the size of the between-groups difference on primary and secondary outcome measures. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>22/11/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>113</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/05/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>10/08/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <postcode>2010 - Darlinghurst</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Wentworthville</postcode>
    <postcode>2747 - Kingswood</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St. Vincent's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst 
NSW 2010 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Psycho-oncology Co-operative Research Group (PoCoG)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Psycho-oncology Co-operative Research Group (PoCoG)
Level 6, Chris O'Brien Lifehouse (C39Z)
The University of Sydney, NSW, 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Psycho-oncology Co-operative Research Group (PoCoG)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Psycho-oncology Co-operative Research Group (PoCoG)
Level 6, Chris O'Brien Lifehouse (C39Z)
The University of Sydney, NSW, 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this trial is to evaluate the efficacy of an internet program, iCanADAPT, for depression and anxiety in adults diagnosed with cancer.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to participate in this study if you are aged 18 or over, suffer from anxiety or depression and have an early stage cancer, or have survived an early stage cancer in the past. 

Study details
All participants enrolled in this study will be randomly allocated (by chance) to receive the iCanADAPT program soon after enrolment or 16 weeks later. The iCanADAPT program is a 16 week online program which involves learning about tackling depression with a form of therapy called Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT). CBT looks at improving how we manage our thoughts, actions and feelings. There are 8 lessons, each one taking up to an hour to complete, with the recommendation to do a new lesson every 1  2 weeks. There will also then be additional activities to do for around 3 hours per week.  The program is tailored to unique aspects of the cancer context, such as fear of cancer recurrence and adapting to illness, side effects, and survivorship.
Participants will complete a number of important questionnaires to assess their depression and anxiety levels among other psychological factors, at the beginning of the program, mid-way through, then again at the end of the program and the last time is 3 months after finishing the program. Participants will also be asked to complete a short questionnaire before every lesson. 

It is hoped that the findings of this trial will provide information regarding the efficacy of the iCanADAPT program in reducing depression and anxiety in cancer patients and cancer survivors.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.virtualclinic.org.au </trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil as yet</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital HREC (EC00140)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St. Vincent's Hospital Research Office 
Level 6, de Lacy Building 
390 Victoria Street 
Darlinghurst 
NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/01/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/SVH/432</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370059-Letter - HREC FINAL approval at HREC Exec meeting 12 01 2016 - 15 286.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression (CRUfAD)
4, The O'Brien Centre, St Vincent's Hospital, 394-404 Victoria St, Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61283821400</phone>
      <fax>+61283821401</fax>
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Murphy</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression (CRUfAD)
4, The O'Brien Centre, St Vincent's Hospital, 394-404 Victoria St, Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61283821400</phone>
      <fax>+61283821401</fax>
      <email>michael.murphy4@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Murphy</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression (CRUfAD)
4, The O'Brien Centre, St Vincent's Hospital, 394-404 Victoria St, Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61283821400</phone>
      <fax>+61283821401</fax>
      <email>michael.murphy4@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Murphy</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression (CRUfAD)
4, The O'Brien Centre, St Vincent's Hospital, 394-404 Victoria St, Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61283821400</phone>
      <fax>+61283821401</fax>
      <email>michael.murphy4@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>