<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336204">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/11/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001037099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Specialist mental health consultation for depression in Australian aged care residents with dementia.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In aged care residents with dementia, is specialist mental health consultation more effective than care as usual in the management of major depression?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1117-7992</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In the intervention condition, a psychiatrist and clinical psychologist provided individually tailored medical and psychosocial recommendations to facility care staff and General Practitioners.  The intervention was thus a form of consultation and training designed to improve care staff and GP management of depression.  The frequency with which the psychiatrist and psychologist had contact with those providing direct care varied on a case by case basis, throughout the course of the study.  The duration of the intervention was 15 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control treatment was standard care, which typically involved GP management of depression (including the use of various antidepressants) and involvement in an activities program at the facility.  Activity programs offered at each facility varied markedly, as did the level of involvement of individual participants.  Standard care paralelled the intervention for approximately 15 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 15-weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DSM-IV Depression Diagnosis were also made, facilitated by checklists of DSM-IV criteria.  Note that standard diagnostic tests could not be used, because our participants all had considerable cognitive impairment.  The assessing clinician reviewed all potential cases with a senior team member in order to confirm the diagnosis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 15-weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rating Anxiety in Dementia (RAID) Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 15-weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Behavioral and Psychological Symptoms of Dementia, as measured by the BEHAVE-AD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 15-weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Permanent resident of aged care facility; &lt;/= 23 on the MMSE and a PAS Cognitive Decline Informant History of greater than or equal to 4 or their facility record referred to presence of cognitive impairment; diagnosis of DSM-IV Major Depression.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No history of English language proficiency; the resident did not have a family member or friend who could provide information about the resident's emotional well-being.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Study was a clustered randomized controlled trial where individual facilities were randomized.  Allocation was not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Facilities were randomized by coin-toss.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Study was a clustered randomized controlled trial where individual facilities were randomized.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>44</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3192</postcode>
    <postcode>3162</postcode>
    <postcode>3196</postcode>
    <postcode>3186</postcode>
    <postcode>3191</postcode>
    <postcode>3194</postcode>
    <postcode>3163</postcode>
    <postcode>3181</postcode>
    <postcode>3168</postcode>
    <postcode>3206</postcode>
    <postcode>3174</postcode>
    <postcode>3187</postcode>
    <postcode>3150</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash University
Victoria 3800
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>beyondblue: the national depression initiative</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 6100
Hawthorn West 
VICTORIA 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project sought to determine whether specialist mental health consultation was more effective in treating the depressions of aged care residents with dementia than standard care.  We screened 389 aged care residents for dementia and major depression. Forty-four were ultimately included in the intervention sample, selected from 20 aged care facilities located in Melbourne, Australia. Facilities were allocated to an intervention condition involving the provision of multidisciplinary specialist consultation surrounding the best-practice management of depression in dementia, or to a care as usual condition. Consultations involved individually tailored medical and psychosocial recommendations provided to care staff and General Practitioners (GPs). All residents participated in a comprehensive pre-intervention diagnostic assessment, including the administration of the Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD).  This assessment was repeated approximately 15 weeks post-intervention by a rater blind to study condition. We found that specialist mental health consultation was significantly more effective in treating the clinical depressions of aged care residents with dementia than care as usual.  At follow-up, the majority of the intervention group no longer met criteria for major depression, nor did they score above critical values on the CSDD.  These results suggest that the psychosocial and medical management of depressed aged care residents can be improved by increasing access to specialist mental health consultation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Office
First Floor, Building 3e
Monash Research Office
Clayton Campus
Monash University VIC 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/04/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF07/0146 - 2007/0032</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Daniel O'Connor</name>
      <address>Aged Mental Health Research Unit 
Kingston Centre 
Warrigal Road  
Cheltenham 
VICTORIA  3192</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9265 1700</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9265 1711</fax>
      <email>daniel.oconnor@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Daniel O'Connor</name>
      <address>Aged Mental Health Research Unit 
Kingston Centre 
Warrigal Road  
Cheltenham 
VICTORIA 3192</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9265 1700</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9265 1711</fax>
      <email>daniel.oconnor@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kate McSweeney</name>
      <address>Aged Mental Health Research Unit 
Kingston Centre 
Warrigal Road  
Cheltenham 
VICTORIA  3192</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9265 1700</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9265 1711</fax>
      <email>kate.mcsweeney@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>