<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336391">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000034932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Promoting activity for frail aged in post-acute hospital settings: a randomised controlled trial of accelerometry</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In frail aged rehabilitation inpatients is provision of activity data from accelerometry monitoring to assist goal setting more effective than usual rehabilitation care in increasing activity levels?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>UTN 1111-1118-9227</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>APP: 1007886 National Health and Medical Research Council</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Musculoskeletal De-conditioning</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mobility decline</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will wear an accelerometer from the time of waking in the morning until going to bed in the evening ie during waking hours. The accelerometer will be removed for showering. At commencement, the treating physiotherapist will discuss with the patient their mobility goals, including provisional targets for daily walking time.  These goals will be re-examined and modified, informed by the accelerometer data, to motivate the patient to improve activity levels and reach set targets. The targets will be reviewed weekly until discharge or 4 weeks, whichever is sooner. Feedback of the previous days walking time will be given to the patient and treating therapist and will be recorded in the patients records. Walking times over a week will be summarised in chart form and made available at the weekly case conference. All staff will be trained in the use of accelerometry data and be asked to encourage patients to meet their activity goals.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual rehabilitation care including the setting of mobility goals. Neither staff nor patients will receive data on monitored walking times to aid in the setting of walking time targets.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily walking times as assessed by accelerometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Repeated daily measures during the study period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lower  extremity function as measured by the Short Physical Performance Battery</outcome>
      <timepoint>At study entry and exit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional status as assessed using the interRAI Post-Acute Care instrument</outcome>
      <timepoint>At study entry and exit and 28 day phone follow-up post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise self-efficacy as measured by the Short Self-Efficacy and Outcome Expectation for Exercise Scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>At study entry and exit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life as measured by EQ-5D</outcome>
      <timepoint>At study entry and exit and 28 day phone follow-up post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of stay recorded on hospital discharge records</outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge from rehabilitation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients admitted to post-acute care rehabilitation who are (1) aged greater than or equal to 60 years; (2) able to ambulate independently or with supervision, or who have a rehabilitation goal to become ambulant within the context of the current admission; and (3) expected to have a length of stay of at least 2 weeks will be eligible to participate.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria will be those (1) with lower limb amputation; (2) with delirium/agitated dementia; or (3) not expected to walk within 4 weeks of admission.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>At each site, within 3 days of admission to post acute care rehabilitation, eligible patients will be identified by a staff member from the rehabilitation team and the names will be given to the research member, who will obtain informed consent for participation. At point of entry into the study, and prior to random allocation to either the intervention or control group, consenting participants will be stratified by mobility status - either walking independently (with or without walking aids) or walking with supervision. A random number sequence will be generated for the order of group allocation within the two strata. Random group allocation will be centrally managed by a member of the research staff who is not involved in assessment of measures or intervention delivery.</concealment>
    <sequence>A random number sequence will be generated using computerised sequence generation for group allocation within the two strata. Random group allocation will be centrally managed by a member of the research staff who is not involved in assessment of measures or intervention delivery.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/10/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>12/09/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>270</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>270</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Hornsby Ku-ring-gai Hospital - Hornsby</hospital>
    <hospital>Repatriation Hospital - Daw Park</hospital>
    <postcode>4102</postcode>
    <postcode>2077</postcode>
    <postcode>5041</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Research and Innovation Division,  The University of Queensland, St Lucia, QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>BACKGROUND
A goal in rehabilitation for older people is promotion of mobility to reverse functional decline and deconditioning. Recent developments in accelerometry for quantifying ambulatory activity can assist clinical practice in rehabilitation settings.

AIM
The study tests the hypothesis that use of accelerometry to provide accurate activity data to patients and clinicians, in the context of explicit goal setting, substantially increases patient walking activity. The study will also explore the effects of increased activity on patient outcomes and undertake a cost utility analysis.

RESEARCH PLAN
A randomised controlled trial will be conducted in Geriatric Rehabilitation Units at 3 sites (QLD, NSW, SA). Eligible patients are aged greater than or equal to 60 and able to ambulate. Based on pilot data, a sample size of 270 patients (135 per group) is required to demonstrate a mean significant differencein daily walking time of 33% between intervention and control groups.Accelerometers will be fitted to eligible subjects to monitor daily activity. Intervention subjects will be offered a formal activity-related rehabilitation goal, and receive daily feedback, sourced from the accelerometer, of their activity levels. Neither staff nor subjects in the control arm of the trial will receive data on walking times. The primary outcome measure will be walking times measured by accelerometry. Secondary outcome measures will include lower extremity function, quality of life, length of stay, post discharge hospital readmissions and level of care at one month follow-up. The time frame for the study is two years six months.

SIGNIFICANCE
If patient activity can be increased through the use of accelerometer data, it will revolutionise the management of activity in hospital. There will be enormous impetus to further develop accelerometer technology for clinical application so that activity prescription will be a routine component of a rehabilitation care plan.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Dakin LE, Gray LC, Peel NM, Salih SA, Cheung VH. Promoting walking amongst older patients in rehabilitation: are accelerometers the answer? J Nutr Health Aging 2010;14(10):863-5.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Alexandra Hospital, Brisbane, Queensland, 4102, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/03/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/QPAH/043</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/01/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2 Building 31, Royal North Shore Hospital, St Leonards, NSW 2065 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/03/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/HAWKE/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/02/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flinders Medical Centre, Bedford Park, SA 5042, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/03/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SAC HREC 012.11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/01/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Len Gray</name>
      <address>Centre for Research in Geriatric Medicine, The University of Queensland School of Medicine, Level 2, Building 33, Princess Alexandra Hospital, Woolloongabba, QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 5530</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3176 6945</fax>
      <email>len.gray@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Nancye Peel</name>
      <address>Centre for Research in Geriatric Medicine, The University of Queensland School of Medicine, Level 2, Building 33, Princess Alexandra Hospital, Woolloongabba, QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 7402</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3176 6945</fax>
      <email>n.peel@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nancye Peel</name>
      <address>Centre for Research in Geriatric Medicine, The University of Queensland School of Medicine, Level 2, Building 33, Princess Alexandra Hospital, Woolloongabba, QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 7402</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3176 6945</fax>
      <email>n.peel@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Leonard Gray</name>
      <address>Centre for Research in Geriatric Medicine
The University of Queensland School of Medicine
Level 2 Building 33 
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Woolloongabba QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 5530</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>len.gray@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>