<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373553">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001315303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Using communication strategies to increase influenza vaccination coverage in Australian indigenous infants.  </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Using behavioural communication to optimise flu vaccination in infant indigenous populations in Victoria</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1201-3903</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Influenza</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A. Mailed letter addressed to parents / guardians of indigenous children under 5 years of age residing in Victoria, Australia. The letter states that indigenous children under 5 are eligible to receive a free influenza vaccine, outlines why vaccination is important and encourages the parent / guardian to arrange this with a local healthcare provider. The letter is a standard letter with text only. 

B. Mailed pamphlet addressed to parents / guardians of indigenous children under 5 years of age residing in Victoria, Australia. The pamphlet states that indigenous children under 5 are eligible to receive a free influenza vaccine, outlines why vaccination is important and encourages the parent / guardian to arrange this with a local healthcare provider. The pamphlet contains similar information to the letter in group A, but is presented using text + illustrations rather than text only. 

For intervention groups, one letter (group A) or pamphlet (group B) was delivered by surface mail early in the influenza season in Victoria (May 17 2017) . Eligible parents / guardians were identified through the Australian Immunisation Registry (AIR) by the Victorian Department of Health and Human Services (DHHS). </interventions>
    <comparator>C. Control group receive no mailed communication </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of eligible infants receiving the influenza vaccine, assessed by pre and post trial reference to the Australian Immunisation Register (AIR), which records details of vaccinations given to children under 7 years of age who live in Australia. The AIR database will be queried against trial eligibility criteria by staff at DHHS on behalf of the research team, who are blinded to all identifying information. </outcome>
      <timepoint>August 31 2017 </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inward correspondence (mail, phone calls) pertaining to the trial received by DHHS as the contact identified on the materials during the intervention period (May 17 - August 31 2017) will be grouped into the following categories:  
1. Mail recipient is not eligible as they do not identify as Aboriginal / Torres Strait Islander; 
2. Mail recipient does not reside at address; 
3. Other e.g. complaints or queries regarding the trial
</outcome>
      <timepoint>August 31 2017 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Parents / guardians of indigenous (Aboriginal or Torres Strait Islander) infants / children aged between 6 months and 5 years of age and residing in Victoria, Australia. 

This trial recruited participants (parents of indigenous children aged 6 months  5 years) through the Australian Immunisation Register (AIR). This registry records all immunisations given at general practices, community clinics and other providers since Sep 30 2016 on a national database which can be accessed by state and territory health departments. AIR is an opt-out registry  the uses of the data are made public, and those who do not want their information shared with third parties can opt out. (see: https://www.humanservices.gov.au/individuals/services/medicare/australian-immunisation-register#group-128 ). 

The participants were recruited behalf of the researchers through the Victorian Department of Health and Human Services (DHHS), and sent one of two forms of communication encouraging them to make an appointment for a free influenza vaccine for their child. 

It was not possible for DHHS to identify the birthdates of the parents on the AIR database. Therefore, parents of eligible infants for this trial aged under 18 years of age were not excluded from this study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Parents / guardians of NON-indigenous infants / children</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible participants were centrally randomised at DHHS by computer into one of the three study conditions. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using Microsoft Excel's =RANDBETWEEN feature to allocate individuals a group number (1, 2 or 3). Once allocated, the distribution of postcode and gender across groups was checked to ensure samples were not biased.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The population for the study was 6,619 with an existing compliance rate of approximately 2%. The population was split into three groups with around 2200 in each. Assuming a 95% level of confidence and an 80% power level, we should be able to detect a minimum difference of 1.36 percentage points.

Basic descriptive statistics will be used to describe participant groups (gender, postcode). Differences in proportions between the three groups will be analysed using Chi-Square. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>10/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/05/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>6619</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>6499</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/08/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wellington Road
Clayton
Victoria 3800
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Public Sector Innovation Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Victorian Department of Premier and Cabinet
Level 29, 35 Collins St, Melbourne Victoria 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Infants are susceptible to a large number of illnesses and diseases. As a result, Australia has a strict protocol for immunising infants and young children at various ages. One of the few immunisations which is not mandatory for infants is the influenza vaccine. Influenza is often perceived as an 'adult' illness, however, as with many illnesses infants are even more susceptible than adults and it is recommended that both children and adults are immunised
annually. The Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander community in Victoria are considered a high-risk group for illnesses such as influenza and as a a result, the vaccine is offered for free for Indigenous infants and children and has been so since 2010. Unfortunately, the rate of immunisation is only around 2% which means many children are at risk of contracting this preventable disease. The aim of this project is to develop and test different messages for parents of Indigenous children to educate and encourage them to seek out the free flu vaccine for their infant/young child.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>not applicable</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Borg K, Bragge P, Beasley M, Sutton K, Halliday J, Knott, C. Optimising flu vaccination among Aboriginal children in Victoria. Annual NHMRC Symposium on Research Translation. Oral presentation, November 14  15 2017, Queensland, Australia.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics, Research Office, 
Chancellery Building E
MONASH UNIVERSITY VIC 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>8632</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Bragge</name>
      <address>BehaviourWorks Australia, Monash Sustainable Development Institute, Monash University
8 Scenic Boulevard, Clayton Campus
Clayton VIC 3800 </address>
      <phone>+61 403 197 275</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.bragge@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Bragge</name>
      <address>BehaviourWorks Australia, Monash Sustainable Development Institute, Monash University
8 Scenic Boulevard, Clayton Campus
Clayton VIC 3800 </address>
      <phone>+61 403 197 275</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.bragge@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Bragge</name>
      <address>BehaviourWorks Australia, Monash Sustainable Development Institute, Monash University
8 Scenic Boulevard, Clayton Campus
Clayton VIC 3800 </address>
      <phone>+61 403 197 275</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.bragge@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Bragge</name>
      <address>BehaviourWorks Australia, Monash Sustainable Development Institute, Monash University
8 Scenic Boulevard, Clayton Campus
Clayton VIC 3800</address>
      <phone>+61 403 197 275</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.bragge@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>