<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368536">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000612516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A new toothbrushing technique for patients with orthodontic braces.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A new toothbrushing technique to enhance oral hygiene in patients with fixed appliances.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>oral hygiene</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention group will be taught the orthodontic toothbrushing technique, which is designed by combining the horizontal strokes and a bite and wiggle motion behind arch wires. 
Briefly, the toothbrush was firstly placed gingival to the brackets and angled 45 degrees towards the occlusal surface. The same motion was repeated with the bristles perpendicular to the labial surface of the brackets. Lastly, with the toothbrush perpendicular to the occlusal area of the brackets, the individual was asked to bite and wiggle. By biting on the toothbrush head, bristles entered into the space behind the arch wires and between the brackets.

An orthodontist will teach the toothbrushing techniques to participants during individual consultation at baseline. Each participants will be required to brush their teeth for 2 minutes and twice daily (in the morning and before sleeping) for 3 months. Patient's compliance will be assessed and monitored by checking the wear of their toothbrushes.

</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will be taught the traditional Modified Bass toothbrushing technique for oral hygiene.
An orthodontist will teach this toothbrushing techniques to participants during individual consultation at baseline. Each participants will be required to brush their teeth for 2 minutes and twice daily (in the morning and before sleeping) for 3 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plaque index</outcome>
      <timepoint>The 1st month, 2nd month, and 3rd month after the interventions.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gingival index</outcome>
      <timepoint>The 1st month, 2nd month, and 3rd month after the interventions.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bracket bond failure will be be recorded if the bracket is debonded from the enamel during the trial.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The 1st month, 2nd month, and 3rd month after the interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. aged between 11 and 40 years,
2. undergoing orthodontic treatment with fixed appliances,
3. residual treatment duration of at least 3 months,
4. presence of 20 natural teeth or more.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>11</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. fixed lingual orthodontic appliances,
2. systemic diseases that may affect oral hygiene or gingival health,
3. periodontal disease,
4. extensive dental restorations.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>A balanced block randomisation will be generated by computer and concealed in an opaque envelope. 
Investigator who will conduct the measurements will be blinded to the group allocation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be analysed using SPSS (version 22.0. for Macintosh; IBM Corp.; Armonk, NY). An intention-to-treat analysis will be carried out, with aerror set to 0.05, using the Mann-Whitney U test to compare Plaque Index and Gingival Index at the baseline; and the Wilcoxon test will be used to assess Plaque Index and Gingival Index reduction at different time points. 

The calculation of sample size is based on previous estimates of plaque index variability (standard deviation = 0.4), of a similar population group requiring orthodontic treatment. With a-error set to 0.05 and ß error set to 0.20 (80% power), a total of 29 participants were required for each group to detect a plaque index reduction of 0.25. We aim to recruit a total of 60 participants based on these parameters and accounting for the possible dropouts during the study.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>29/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Dunedin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Faculty of Dentistry, University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>310 Great King Street, Dunedin, 9016.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Faculty of Dentistry, University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>310 Great King Street, Dunedin, 9016.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Traditional tooth brushing techniques, such as the Modified Bass technique, are designed and aimed at the general population without orthodontic appliances. An effective tooth brushing technique for patients wearing orthodontic fixed appliances is still lacking.

We will design an Orthodontic tooth brushing technique to enhance the oral hygiene of patients with fixed orthodontic appliances, and compare its efficacy with that of the traditional Modified Bass technique.

This study will be conducted as a single blind randomised controlled clinical trial with two parallel arms. We will aim to recruit 60 patients. Plaque index (PI) and Gingival index (GI) will be used to assess the oral hygiene of participants. Outcome measurements will be taken at baseline (T0) and one-month (T1), two-month (T2), and three-month (T3) after the intervention.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>A Master thesis has been completed based on this trial.
Title of the thesis: An orthodontic tooth brushing technique to enhance oral hygiene in patients with fixed appliances: interim results of a randomized controlled clinical trial.
Author: Austin Kang.
Supervisor: Mauro Farella and Li Mei.
University: Faculty of Dentistry, University of Otago.
Date: March 2015.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>362 Leith Street, Dunedin, 9016</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H14/060</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Li Mei</name>
      <address>Department of Oral Sciences, Faculty of Dentistry, University of Otago. 310 Great King Street, Dunedin, 9016</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7480</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>li.mei@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Li Mei</name>
      <address>Department of Oral Sciences, Faculty of Dentistry, University of Otago. 310 Great King Street, Dunedin, 9016</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7480</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>li.mei@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Li Mei</name>
      <address>Department of Oral Sciences, Faculty of Dentistry, University of Otago. 310 Great King Street, Dunedin, 9016</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7480</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>li.mei@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>