<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335755">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/07/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/08/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000668000</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Is one year mortality and morbidity influenced by anaesthesia after major surgery?  A Pilot Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, randomised, double blind, safety and efficacy study comparing "light" and "deep" general anaesthesia monitored with the Bispectral Index (BIS) or Spectral Entropy (SE) to investigate whether "light" anaesthesia is associated with lower postoperative mortality than "deep" anaesthesia in patients having major surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Balanced Anesthesia</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The depth of anaesthesia used in major surgery and its impact on postsurgical morbidity and mortality</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention General anaesthesia monitored with bispectral index (BIS) or spectral entropy (SE). Targets in the two groups will be BIS (or SE) 50 and 35. We expect 95% of anaesthesia time to be within 5 units of the target range, and no deviations to be greater than 5 minutes. Maintenance phase will be from ten minutes after induction until switching off volatile or hypnotic at the end of the operation.
Anaesthesia Standard care using standard anaesthetic hypnotics, volatiles, opioids and relaxants, Intravenous (IV) or gas induction and maintenance, continuous BIS or SE monitoring with computerised data logging (ie: propofol, thiopentone, midazolam, isoflurane, sevoflurane, desflurane, all opioids, all Nonsteroidal Antiinflammatory Drugs (NSAIDs), ketamine, paracetamol, all antihypertensives, statins &amp; diabetic medication etc) as per usual care.  Blood pressure target range will be set before opening the BIS randomization envelope and anaesthetists will be requested to maintain patients within these parameters as much as possible.</interventions>
    <comparator>Dose comparison will be made from within the Bispectral index target groups outlined in the intervention.  Both the intervention and comparator will be managed as per standard of practice to maintain the targets in the two groups will be BIS (or SE) 50 and 35.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Recordings
Pre-operative Charlston co-morbidity score, height, weight, American Society of Anaesthesia Score (ASA),Electrocardiography (ECG), Full Blood Count (FBC), Urea and Electrolytes (U&amp;E), Albumin, Cancer status including Tumour Classification (TNM - Tumour, Nodes, Metastasis).
Peri-operative Electronic record capable of being easily read or manual record with minimum of 5 min recording intervals of BIS/SE, Volatile, Blood Pressure (BP), Heart Rate (HR), Arterial Blood oxygen saturation (Sa02), Temp and all drugs administered, so that mean hypnotic depth and deep hypnotic times can calculated. ECG, FBC, U&amp;E, C-reactive protein (CRP). Review of hospital/ outpatient/General Practitioner (GP) notes and self reporting for evidence of: unscheduled Intensive Care Unit (ICU) admission, post-operative wound infection, pneumonia, Deep Vein Thromobis (DVT), Pulmonary Embolism (PE), Myocardial Infarction (MI), Stroke, sepsis, renal/liver dysfunction, post-operative quality of recovery score, cancer status including TNM.
30 days Death rate, ongoing analgesic or antiemetic requirements, review of hospital/outpatient/GP notes and self reporting for evidence of: post-operative wound infection, pneumonia, DVT, PE, MI, Stroke, sepsis, renal/liver dysfunction, overall patient satisfaction
One Year Death rate, DVT, PE, Stroke, MI, Cancer recurrence, Chronic pain related to surgical site.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Morality and Morbidity review</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age 60 and over, American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) Score 3 or 4, major surgery lasting over 2 hours, expected to stay in hospital two or more nights post-operatively, general anaesthesia including with major regional block, anaesthesia duration expected to be over two hours.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable to monitor processed Electroencephalography (EEG)(eg most neurosurgery), not expected to survive one year with or without surgery, unable to consent, eg: dementia, , major psychiatric illness, not expected to be contactable one year later, surgery with wake-up test</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be identified by the Anaesthesia Consultant.  Allocation will be concealed and treatments assigned by a randomisation envelope</concealment>
    <sequence>randomisation envelopes were done using a minisation algorithm</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/07/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3052</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state>sha tin, new territories</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Timothy Short</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Anaesthesia
Support Building, level 8
Auckland City Hospital
Park Rd
Grafton
Auckland 1023</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Auckland District health Board (ADHB) Research Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Park Rd
Grafton
Auckland 1023</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australasian College of Anaesthetists</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Australian and New Zealand College of Anaesthetists (ANZCA) House
630 St Kilda Road
Melbourne Vic 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Australasian College of Anaesthetists</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>ANZCA House
630 St Kilda Road
Melbourne Vic 3004</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Recently five overseas studies have found an association between deep anaesthesia and subsequent mortality within one year. There is a need for a large prospective randomised trial of "deep" versus "light" anaesthesia to determine if the relationship is a causal one. This would require the study of about 6000 patients. In this pilot study, 100 patients will be randomised to either "light" or "deep" anaesthesia using the Bispectral Index depth monitor. In all other respects the anaesthesia will be unaltered in choice of anaesthetic drugs or techniques used. We will then follow up all patients for one year to ascertain the incidence of complications of anaesthesia and surgery, cancer recurrence if relevant and survival. The study has the support of the Clinical Trials group of the Australian and New Zealand College of Anaesthetists.  If successful, the pilot study will be used as the basis for a large project grant to the Health Research Council in New Zealand (NZ), hopefully combined with an application to the National Health and Medical Research Council in Australia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern X Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>3rd floor, Unisys building 
650 Great South Rd
Penrose
Auckland 1061</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/05/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTX/10/04/034</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/03/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Timothy Short</name>
      <address>Department of Anesthesia
Level 8 Support Building
Auckland City Hospital
Park Rd
Grafton
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+6493797440</phone>
      <fax>+6493754378</fax>
      <email>TimS@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Davina McAllister</name>
      <address>Department of Anesthesia
Level 8 Support Building
Auckland City Hospital
Park Rd
Grafton
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+6493797440</phone>
      <fax>+6493754378</fax>
      <email>davinams@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Davina McAllister</name>
      <address>Department of Anesthesia
Level 8 Support Building
Auckland City Hospital
Park Rd
Grafton
Auckland 1023</address>
      <phone>+6493797440</phone>
      <fax>+6493754378</fax>
      <email>davinams@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>