<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364507">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000744752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The stroke-IMPACT trial (Improving Physical Activity via Treadmill Training): A single blinded Randomised Controlled Trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In stroke patients undergoing rehabilitation, does high intensity treadmill training embedded in a self-management approach result in increased levels of physical activity at 8 and 26 weeks compared to usual physiotherapy care.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1145-1004 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>IMPACT RCT (Improving Physical Activity via Treadmill Training)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>People with stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>(1) Treadmill walking - 30 minute sessions, 3 times a week for 8 weeks at 60% of heart rate reserve. Total dose of treadmill walking is 12 hours. Participants will be individually monitored throughout the treadmill sessions by a physiotherapist. 

(2) Chronic Disease Self Management (CDSM) - During the same 8 week period that participants are receiving treadmill training, they will also receive a CDSM program. This will involve 5-10 minute sessions, 3 times a week for 8 weeks. The sessions will be delivered individually to the participants by the physiotherapists prior to or during the treadmill sessions. Participants will be taught behaviour change techniques such as goal setting and action planning to encourage initiation and maintenance of physical activity. 

(3) Usual care - Participants will also receive usual physiotherapy and rehabilitation during this time although treadmill training will replace over-ground gait retraining.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care - the comparison group will receive a usual physiotherapy rehabilitation program based on motor relearning principles. It is recommended that stroke patients receive up to 2 sessions of physiotherapy per day on 5 days of the week, prescribed by their treating physiotherapist.  Usual hospital based care will be delivered by treating physiotherapists for the duration of the participant's hospital stay.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity - Actual activity levels (steps per day) measured over a 4-day period using an accelerometer (ActivPal)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0, week 8, week 26</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking ability (speed and endurance) as measured by the 6-minute walk test and the 10m walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0, week 8, week 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiorespiratory fitness (VO2 Peak, Heart Rate, Blood Pressure and Rate Pressure Product) measured during the 6-minute walk test by a fully portable compact metabolic system using breath by breath analysis </outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0, week 8, week 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiovascular risk will be measured from lipid profile and inflammatory markers. Lipid profile (TC, HDL, LDL, TRG, TC/HDL) will be taken via a fingerstick and analysed on a point of care device. Inflammatory markers (hs-CRP) will be measured by a pathology blood test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0, week 8, week 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy of walking ability will be measured using the Ambulatory Self Confidence Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8, week 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health related quality of life will be measured using the EuroQual-5D + VAS questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8, week 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participation will be measured using the Impact on Participation and Autonomy Questionnaire (IPAQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8, week 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjectively measured physical activity will be measured using the Physical Activity Scale for Individuals with Physical Disabilities (PASIPD) questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8, week 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression will be measured using the Hospital and Anxiety Depression Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 8, week 26</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Within 2 months of stroke 
Aged over 18 years 
Able to walk independently for 10m with or without an aid 
Able to understand 3-stage commands</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable to walk independently prior to current stroke 
Have co-morbidities that might limit walking (e.g., arthritis, brain injury, Parkinson's Disease) 
Unstable cardiac status 
Unable to understand/follow instructions 
Unable to return for assessment or training
Unable to give informed consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Principal investigator will peruse admission list to identify potential participants. Regular contact will be made with treating physiotherapists. Once potential participant is identified, medical clearance will be sought from treating consultant. All potential participants will undergo assessment to ensure suitability. Once approval gained and participant consented, assessment by a blinded assessor will be arranged. Following assessment, subjects will be randomised. Allocation will be concealed through the use of consecutively numbered opaque sealed envelopes and will be maintained at a central location. </concealment>
    <sequence>Offsite investigator using computer generated random number program will randomise subjects into experimental and controlled groups.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A sample size of 128 will be recruited to this study. To guide our effect size estimate of physical activity, we estimated that stroke patients would walk 4000 +/-2000 steps/day at baseline, that usual care would increase this by 1200 steps/day, and our intervention would further increase this by 50% (1200 steps/day, or a min of 3hrs/wk walking), putting them above a sedentary level for older adults. Thus we undertook a power analysis to detect an effect size of 0.5; which reflects a between independent group difference in physical activity of 1200 steps per day  with 80% power at a two-tailed significance level of 0.05. This calculation resulted in requiring 55 participants per group, 110 participants in total. On the assumption from previous trials we have completed with this population that approximately 15% of participants may be lost to follow up during the course of the study, we have set a target of 128 participants in total.  

Analysis will be intention to treat and between groups statistical analysis will be performed on all outcome measures. Results will be reported as point measures and measures of variability. Baseline demographic characteristics and outcome measures will be compared between participants according to group allocation and between those who completed the study and those who were lost to follow up. Primary and secondary outcome measures will be analysed using generalised estimating equations for continuous data. This approach is similar to repeated measures ANOVA but is tolerant of missing data and does not require casewise deletion due to missing values. Variables different between groups at baseline will be included as covariates. Kruskal-Wallis tests will be performed for non-parametric data. Results will be accepted as statistically significant at P&lt;=0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>128</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Queen Elizabeth II Jubilee Hospital - Coopers Plains</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Logan Hospital - Meadowbrook</hospital>
    <postcode>4006 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
    <postcode>4108 - Coopers Plains</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>4131 - Meadowbrook</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Brisbane St Lucia, QLD 4072 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Stroke is a leading cause of disability amongst Australians. After stroke, activity levels are low, with few people able to exercise at an intensity which will reduce the risk of future cardiovascular events. This project examines the effectiveness of implementing a combined high intensity treadmill training program embedded in a self-management approach to improve activity levels, mobility, cardiovascular risk profile in stroke survivors, increasing their independence and reducing the burden of care. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Brisbane St Lucia, QLD 4072 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013000639</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Health Service District Human Research Ethics Committee (HHS HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Centres for Health Research
Level 2 Building 35, Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba  Qld 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00167</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sandra Brauer</name>
      <address>Therapies Building (84A)
The University of Queensland
St Lucia
QLD 4072 Australia </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2317</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 2775</fax>
      <email>s.brauer@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sandra Brauer</name>
      <address>Therapies Building (84A)
The University of Queensland
St Lucia
QLD 4072 Australia </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2317</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 2775</fax>
      <email>s.brauer@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sandra Brauer</name>
      <address>Therapies Building (84A)
The University of Queensland
St Lucia
QLD 4072 Australia </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2317</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 2775</fax>
      <email>s.brauer@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Sandra Brauer</name>
      <address>Therapies Building (84A)
The University of Queensland
St Lucia
QLD 4072 Australia </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 2317</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3365 2775</fax>
      <email>s.brauer@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>