<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373490">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001275358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can Functional Lung Ventilation Imaging in Asthma and Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease identify response to treatment.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can functional lung ventilation imaging identify treatable traits in obstructive airway disease?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ITT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Severe asthma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Functional lung ventilation imaging with quantification using Technegas will be used. Tomographic pulmonary scintigraphy (ventilation/perfusion single photon emission computed tomography: V/P SPECT) is a nuclear medicine investigation that gives a 3dimensional functional map of the ventilation and perfusion of the lungs and shows how these are affected by disease. The participant will breathe in a very small amount of nanoparticle suspension for ventilation images and be given an injection of radioactive material, called Technetium99mTc, for the perfusion images. The VQ scan takes less than an hour. A low radiation CT scan will also be performed as part of the imaging. 
All 100 participants will undergo the baseline imaging. A subgroup of 30 participants will receive a second imaging session after 12 weeks of add-on therapy. This treatment will be part of their current clinical practice at the John Hunter Hospital Respiratory Clinic, under the supervision of the patients treating physician. 
Participants in the sub-group will receive either Mepolizumab, Omalizumab or Macrolide antibiotics. Mepolizumab is administered by subcutaneous injection of 150mg every 4 weeks. Omalizumab will also be administered by subcutaneous injections every 2 weeks or 4 weeks with the patient's pre-treatment serum total IgE level (IU/mL) and body weight (lb or kg) being used to determine doses (mg) and dosing frequency. The dosing table can be found at: https://www.xolair.com/allergic-asthma/hcp/determining-the-dose.html.. Macrolide antibiotics will be administered as oral azithromycin as either 250mg daily or 500mg, 3 times per week depending on the patient's preference and perceived adherence.
The overall time-frame of each add-on therapy may vary between participants, however the second imaging scan will happen after they have undergone 12 weeks of their treatment.
Medication adherence will be routinely assessed by respiratory nurses and clinicians at each clinic review by open ended questions. Adherence will also be checked by the clinical research assistant at the 12-week follow-up study visit.  
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ventilation heterogeneity among patients with severe obstructive airways diseases as assessed using technegas functional lung ventilation and perfusion with imaging and quantification</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 weeks (all participants) </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Technegas functional lung ventilation and perfusion imaging quantification responsiveness to change following intervention in patients with severe obstructive airways diseases.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks (30 participants)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ACQ score</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 weeks (all participants) and 12 weeks (30 participants)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults (greater than or equal to 18 years) with severe treatment refractory asthma defined according to ATS/ERS criteria:
-Asthma which requires treatment with guidelines-suggested medications for GINA steps 4-5 (high dose ICS and LABA or leukotriene modifier/theophylline) for the previous year or systemic corticosteroids for greater than or equal to 50% of the previous year to prevent it from becoming uncontrolled or which remains uncontrolled despite this therapy
-Uncontrolled asthma defined as at least one of the following:
*Poor symptom control: ACQ consistently &gt; 1.5, ACT &lt; 20
*Frequent severe exacerbations: 2 or more bursts of systemic corticosteroids (greater than 3 days each) in the previous year
*Serious exacerbations: at least one hospitalisation, ICU stay or mechanical ventilation in the previous year
*Airflow limitation: after appropriate bronchodilator withhold FEV1 &lt; 80% predicted (in the face of reduced FEV1/FVC defined as less than the lower limit of normal)
OR 
Adults (greater than or equal to 18 years) with obstructive airways disease (either asthma or COPD) who are to be treated with add on therapies (macrolides, monoclonal antibody therapies or itraconazole). This includes moderate or severe asthma or COPD, with persistent symptoms, and/or frequent exacerbations.  Exacerbations will be defined as indicated below.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability to attend study visits.
Current lung cancer or other blood, lymphatic or solid organ malignancy
Diagnosis with primary respiratory disease other than asthma or COPD (e.g. active tuberculosis, pulmonary fibrosis)
Expected prognosis poor &lt;3 months survival
Pregnancy or breast-feeding
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>A cross-sectional analytic design will be used to assess baseline imaging sessions in all participants. A before-after clinical trial will be used to assess a subgroup of participants at a second imaging session after they undergoes a standard treatment as part of routine clinical practice.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Summary statistics will be reported for the cross sectional characterisation study.  Parametric results will be reported as mean (SD) and non-parametric results as median (q1,q3).
To compare differences in before and after treatment responses of continuous variables, we will perform Students¹ paired t-tests for parametric data and the two-sample Wilcoxon Rank Sum for non parametric data, and the Chi-squared or Fisher¹s exact test for categorical variables. Associations will be determined using Pearson¹s or Spearman¹s correlation coefficients as appropriate.
Results will reported as significant when p&lt;0.05.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>6/09/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>5/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>John Hunter Hospital - New Lambton</hospital>
    <postcode>2305 - New Lambton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Vanessa McDonald</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 2, Hunter Medical Research Institute
1 Kookaburra Circuit, New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cyclopharm Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 4, The Crescent Kingsgrove, NSW 2208</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease and Severe Asthma are chronic obstructive airway diseases associated with a high disease burden. They are complex diseases that can be complicated by significant comorbidity. A new and emerging approach to these conditions is to focus on the identification and treatment of the processes that underlie individual disease. These components are termed treatable traits.
An important aspect of the treatable traits approach is objective monitoring to select and continue therapy. Most current monitoring approaches are assessed using nonobjective
measures, that do not capture improvements after treatment. 
Functional lung ventilation imaging with quantification using Technegas may address this clinical need. Tomographic pulmonary scintigraphy (ventilation/perfusion single photon emission computed tomography: V/P SPECT) is a nuclear medicine investigation that gives a 3dimensional functional map of the ventilation and perfusion of the lungs and shows how these are affected by disease. 
We believe that this new imaging approach may be a useful objective measure of disease and treatment response in severe asthma and COPD.
In the current study, we aim to quantify:
1. Whether functional lung ventilation technology can objectively quantify ventilation heterogeneity in patients with severe obstructive airway disease (asthma or COPD).
2. Determine whether functional lung ventilation imaging can be used to quantify response to therapies.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lookout Road, New Lambton Heights, NSW 2208</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/12/14/4.02</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Vanessa McDonald</name>
      <address>Level 2, Hunter Medical Research Institute
1 Kookaburra Circuit, New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4042 0146</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4042 0046</fax>
      <email>vanessa.mcdonald@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Gabrielle LeBrocq</name>
      <address>Level 2, Hunter Medical Research Institute
1 Kookaburra Circuit, New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4042 0131</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4042 0046</fax>
      <email>gabrielle.lebrocq@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Gibson</name>
      <address>John Hunter Hospital, Respiratory and Sleep Medicine
Locked Bag 1, HMRC NSW 2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4042 0143</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4042 0046</fax>
      <email>peter.gibson@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Gabrielle LeBrocq</name>
      <address>Level 2, Hunter Medical Research Institute
1 Kookaburra Circuit, New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4042 0131</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4042 0046</fax>
      <email>gabrielle.lebrocq@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>