<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373733">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/10/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001396314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Strength-Based, Peer Education Approach to helping Maori elders work through later-stage life transitions</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Kaumatua managing life-transitions through tuakana-teina/peer-education: Impacts on health-related quality of life and mana motuhake</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>KMM</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Life transitions in ageing</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We developed a Tuakana-teina (older sibling/younger sibling)/peer education orientation programme for life-transitions of kaumatua (elders). The orientation includes four 4-hour sessions over two-weeks for the peer educator (tuakana) comprised of the following material: (a) Maori values; (b) definitions of tuakana-teina/peer support; (c) four kinds of peer support; (d) forms of Maori communication; and (e) specific communication tools to support the peer educator (tuakana) working with their peers (teina). There will be at least one follow-up orientation session to tuakana progress. After the orientation programme, each tuakana will have a face-to-face semi-structured conversation with six teina at least three times over a four-month period to address relevant life-transitions of their teina. The tuakana will have a checklist to guide the conversations and assess the needs, and interests in learning about resources, around five life transitions (loss of independent living, loss of drivers licence, loss of spouse, serious change in health condition, and retirement). The tuakana will provide various types of emotional and tangible support including linking to health and social services. Fidelity of the conversations will be assessed through coding of recorded conversations against the checklist.

The development of the orientation programme was a collaboration of academic and community researchers working in consultation with advisory boards of experts (medical, social services, ageing) and a board of trustees (i.e., as cultural advisors). The orientation programme is a written manual including instructions, activities, information, and questions for the people delivering the sessions. Including in the manual is a written handouts for participants in the training. Each session is to be delivered face-to-face by members of the academic research team who are experts in Maori communication, Maori worldviews and ageing. and have doctoral degrees supported by community researchers and doctoral students.. The sessions include some didactic information although mostly interactive discussions, reflections and chances to practice the peer education (i.e., role plays with feedback). </interventions>
    <comparator>The comparison group is a similar group of older people who will not receive the intervention during the initial phase of the project. They will receive the intervention approximately 6.5 months after the initial group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life; SF-8</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention assessment of outcomes; post- first group intervention assessment of outcomes-6.5 months follow-up (primary timepoint); post-second group intervention assessment of outcomes-13 months follow-up </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mana motuhake (identity, autonomy): items from Te Kupenga Maori Social Survey measuring perceived autonomy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention assessment of outcomes; post- first group intervention assessment of outcomes-6.5 months follow-up (primary timepoint); post-second group intervention assessment of outcomes-13 months follow-up </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mana motuhake: Cantril's ladder</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention assessment of outcomes; post- first group intervention assessment of outcomes-6.5 months follow-up (primary timepoint); post-second group intervention assessment of outcomes-13 months follow-up </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>People aged 55 or above who are registered/receive services at Rauawaawa Kaumatua Charitable Trust</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>55</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Severe forms of dementia and related cognitive impairment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The research design for the evaluation of the orientation programme is a pre- and post-test, clustered staggered design with Tuatahi (first group) and Tuarua (second group/comparison) groups. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size of tuakana and teina was determined by a balance of resources and statistical power to determine the optimal design. There are 6 participants for each tuakana. We conducted power and sample size estimates based on the research design  and confirmed with the od.exe software package. The following assumptions were made: (a) probability value = .05; and (b) rho (intra-class correlation) = .10. Six teina for each tuakana results in power of .80 with a medium effect size (d=.55). 

Using the pre-test data, we will (re-)establish the psychometric properties of measures. Factorial and discriminant validity will be assessed with confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) and reliability established with Cronbachs alpha. 

The intervention analysis will compare the two groups and identify if there are intervening variables that explain differential patterns in the changes in the dependent variables. The primary dependent variables are mana motuhake and HRQOL. The independent variables are the time receiving the orientation programme (tuatahi/tuarua) and the three time periods (pre-test, 1st post-test, final post-test). Potential intervening variables that will be controlled for include characteristics about the conversations, characteristics of the tuakana/teina, and whether participants talked with each other during the intervention.
The quantitative data analysis will be a hiearchical, repeated measures analysis. to account for the  characteristics about the conversations with the tuakana. Further, we will determine estimates of cost effectiveness using incremental cost effectiveness analysis (ICEA). We have some open-ended questions and will analyse these qualitative data using thematic analysis 

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>25/09/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>210</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>30</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/11/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Waikato</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 3105
Hamilton 3240
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Business Innovation and Employment --Ageing Well National Science Challenge</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ageing Well National Science Challenge
School of Physiotherapy
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The New Zealand population is ageing and numerous studies demonstrate with this increasing age comes increases in non-communicable diseases, injuries and healthcare costs among other issues. Further, there are significant inequities  between Maori (Indigenous people of New Zealand) and non-Maori around poor ageing and health outcomes. Most research addressing these issues takes a deficit approach. However, the current research project takes a strengths-based approach that highlights the potential of kaumatua (elders) by asserting mana motuhake (autnomy, identity). We believe that the esteem of elders in Maori culture signals transformative potential. Specifically, this project utilises a tuakana-teina(older sibling/younger sibling) peer-educator model, where kaumatua work with other kaumatua in relation to health and wellbeing. The objectives of the project are (1) to develop the capacity of kaumatua as peer educators and have positive impacts on their sense of purpose and health and wellbeing; and (2) To enhance the social and health outcomes for kaumatua receiving the intervention. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Te Manu Taiko: Human Research Ethics Committee Faculty of Maori &amp; Indigenous Studies, University of Waikato</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Private Bag 3105 
Hamilton 3240
New Zealand</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/08/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Brendan Hokowhitu</name>
      <address>Faculty of Maori and Indigenous Studies
University of Waikato
Private Bag 3105
Hamilton 3240</address>
      <phone> +64 7 838 4075</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brendan.hokowhitu@waikato.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Brendan Hokowhitu</name>
      <address>Faculty of Maori and Indigenous Studies
University of Waikato
Private Bag 3105
Hamilton 3240</address>
      <phone> +64 7 838 4075</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brendan.hokowhitu@waikato.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Oetzel</name>
      <address>Faculty of Management
University of Waikato
Private Bag 3105
Hamilton 3240</address>
      <phone>+64 7 838 4431</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john.oetzel@waikato.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>John Oetzel</name>
      <address>Faculty of Management
University of Waikato
Private Bag 3105
Hamilton 3240</address>
      <phone>+64 7 838 4431</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john.oetzel@waikato.ac.nz</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>