<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373007">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000862347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Weight management attempts following a brief consultation for patients with obesity in a tertiary hospital </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of a brief consultation for adult patients with obesity in a tertiary hospital in improving weight management </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>BIFO (brief intervention for obesity)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>weight management </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: a brief intervention for obesity. 

This 'brief intervention' will involve a 5-10 minute private conversation between the patient and their doctor in hospital which is integrated into their existing interaction during their hospital admission (timing at the discretion of the doctor) or during the pre-admission clinic consultation. :
1) Informing the patient of their weight and diagnosis of obesity.  
2) Providing a pamphlet (developed by the Nutrition and Dietetics Department at The Alfred) which contains educational material on the problem of obesity, basic advice on weight loss and links to community resources (LiveLighter.com and The Alfred website to a page also developed by the Nutrition and Dietetics Department). 
3) Advising the patient to see their GP for further support 
4) Informing the patient's GP of the diagnosis of obesity via discharge summary or letter  

Medical staff involved have been instructed that the objective of the conversation is to prompt the patient to take further steps following up with weight management post-discharge.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will receive standard care during their hospital visit.  Patients are routinely weighed by nursing staff so if obesity is identified, they are alerted that this is a risk to their health and advised to seek further support from their GP.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants who have commenced a weight management attempt. 

Assessed by online or phone survey asking:
 - if patient has accessed the online information in pamphlet (if provided)
 - if patient has newly attempted weight management (yes or no)
 - if yes, what strategies they have tried (diet, exercise, referral to allied health such as dietitian/exercise physiologist, pharmacological agents, referral for bariatric surgery, other)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post randomisation </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants who have discussed weight management with their GPs since discharge from hospital, assessed via online/phone survey 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post randomisation 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants who complete the consultation in hospital, assessed by treating doctors reporting to trial coordinator  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Upon patient discharge from hospital </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient weight assessed by self-report on online/phone survey </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post randomisation </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Consumer feedback on the intervention, as assessed by online/phone survey of participants asking:
- did you find the programme acceptable
- did you find the programme helpful
- suggestions for improvement
- further comments </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post randomisation </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Staff satisfaction with the program as assessed by a 5-Point Likert Scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>At end of rotations with units involved </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP satisfaction with intervention as assessed by a 5-point Likert Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post randomisation </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Body mass index (BMI) &gt; 30 kg/m^2
Admitted to inpatient ward or attendance at a scheduled pre-admission clinic appointment 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with current or past history of bariatric surgery 
Major medical illness which contraindicates weight loss
Non-English speaking</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation with computer software and opaque envelopes </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Power calculation:
We estimate that if 5% of patients have a discussion with their GP about their weight following discharge in the control group and we are able to increase this to 20% with the brief intervention this would be clinically significant.  To detect a difference of this magnitude with a two-sided a of 0.05 and power of 0.8 we would require 75 patients in each arm.  Allowing for a 15% drop out rate, we aim to recruit a total of 174 patients.

Data anaylsis:
Standard statistical tests will be used.  For primary endpoints categorical outcomes (yes/no) will be analysed using fisher exact or chi-squared test, adjusting for baseline imbalances and potential covariates .  Logistic regressions will be used for continuous outcomes (weight).  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>28/02/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>174</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Prahran </postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre of Obesity Research and Education, Monash University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne Vic 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Centre of Obesity Research and Education, Monash University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne Vic 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Alfred</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004

Postal address
The Alfred 
PO Box 315
Prahran VIC 3181</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Alfred</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004

Postal address
The Alfred 
PO Box 315
Prahran VIC 3181</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obesity is one of the most prevalent and challenging diseases affecting our community.  According to the latest census figures, 63.4% of Australians aged 18 years and over were overweight or obese, namely, 35.0% overweight and 28.3% obese.
Significant weight loss (&gt;20% body weight) delivers impressive health and economic benefits, but even modest weight loss (&gt;5% body weight) leads to significant health benefits and cost savings. Weight loss, therefore, has the potential to be one of the most important heath care interventions in our community.

Yet despite the recognised benefits for both the obese individual and society as a whole from weight loss, obesity remains a disease that is largely under-diagnosed and under-treated.  The reasons for this paradox are complex and include the difficulty treating obesity, along with a lack of effective treatment options.  The situation is then complicated by societal stigmatisation of the obese individual.  It is well recognized that healthcare professionals also stigmatize the obese, and often feel uncomfortable raising the issue of weight control with their patients.  

In this study, we aim to pilot a programme designed to increase awareness of the importance of diagnosing obesity in the tertiary hospital setting.  We hypothesise that if a tertiary hospital provides a diagnosis of obesity to a patient, this will motivate the patient to make an attempt at weight loss and by providing the patient's GP the opportunity to raise obesity as a health issue, will help to reduce the stigma associated with obesity.  

Building on Alfred Healths success with a brief intervention for smokers, we have worked with the Nutrition and Dietetics Department to design a brief intervention tool to be provided to patients.  This tool provides simple information on healthy eating, exercise and community resources to support weight loss.  

Given that The Alfred protocol requires weight, height and BMI calculation on admission to the Alfred, we plan to provide a diagnosis of obesity to all patients with a BMI &gt;30 and then provide them with this tool as well as inform the General Practitioner (GP) of the diagnosis and recommend weight management in the discharge summary. 

Prior to broadly implementing this programme we wish to test feasibility and acceptability of this approach. We plan to trial the programme by randomizing patients to either standard care or the new programme.  Three months post discharge we will ascertain if the GP did discuss weight management with their patient, if there has been any attempt at weight loss as well as GP and patient satisfaction.  Feedback from the hospital staff will also be collected.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Old Baker Building, Level 1,
55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/11/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>514/16</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office Location: First floor, 26 Sports Walk (formerly 3D), Clayton Campus, Monash University 

Postal address: Monash Research Office,  26 Sports Walk, Monash University, Wellington Road, Clayton VIC 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>7825</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Wendy Brown</name>
      <address>Centre for Obesity Research and Education (CORE), Monash University 
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0725</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9903 0717</fax>
      <email>wendy.brown@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Tiffany Tie</name>
      <address>Centre for Obesity Research and Education (CORE), Monash University 
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61399030369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tytie2@student.monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Tiffany Tie</name>
      <address>Centre for Obesity Research and Education (CORE), Monash University 
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61399030369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tytie2@student.monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Tiffany Tie</name>
      <address>Centre for Obesity Research and Education (CORE), Monash University 
Level 6 The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61399030369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tytie2@student.monash.edu</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>