<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369137">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000920594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised double blinded placebo controlled study investigating Atopis for the improvement of skin health in subjects with eczema</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised double blinded placebo controlled study investigating Atopis for the improvement of skin health in subjects with eczema</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1171-3932</utrn>
    <trialacronym>DECI2700</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Eczema</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>atopic dermatitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Herbal remedies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Atopis skin cream which contains the extract DEC033 at 10% (contains peptilipids and fatty acids), cetearyl olivate, sorbitan olivate, shea butter, safflower oil, macadamia oil, glycerine, Vitamin E, geogard (preservative), Tangerine Oil, deionised water.
The cream is applied topically twice daily to the affected areas for four weeks. The cream is applied liberally.  In the previous clinical trial tubes were returned at each visit and weighed. The subjects used on average 1.3g/day. A daily diary is also used to track usage.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Mineral oil, glycerine, emulsifying wax, colour (to match active cream) and deionised water.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> 
Change in redness - as assessed using SCORAD (Visual Analog Scale) and Dermatological Examination by the site investigator
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subjects are assessed at baseline, week 2 and week 4 for changes between timepoints.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in severity scoring of atopic dermatitis (SCORAD)</outcome>
      <timepoint>The subjects are assessed at time 0 baseline, week 2 and week 4 for changes in SCORAD</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in itching - as assessed using SCORAD (Visual Analog Scale) and Dermatological Examination by the site investigator
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The subjects are assessed at time 0 baseline, week 2 and week 4 for changes in SCORAD</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the the number of eczema skin lesions - these are measured (length, width, location) by the site investigator and documented using the Dermatological examination documentation form.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The subjects are assessed by the site investigator at time 0 baseline, week 2 and week 4 for changes in length, width and number of lesions</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in scaling - The subjects are assessed by the site investigator at time 0 baseline, week 2 and week 4 and assessed using visual analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>The subjects are assessed for changes at time 0 baseline, week 2 and week 4</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Healthy male or female between 16 and 70 years of age.
2.	Subjects with mild to moderate eczema; which will be determined using the Eichenfield Revised Criteria of Hannafin and Rajka at screening visit.
3.	Judged by the Investigator to be in general good health on the basis of medical history.
4.	Agree to use the Study-supplied investigational product as the only body cosmetic applied to irritated skin.
5.	Agree to stop all dietary supplements including probiotics, dermatological medications and creams for eczema, during the entire length of the study 
6.	Agree not to change their current diet or exercise program during the entire study period.
7.	Understands the study procedures and signs forms providing informed consent to participate in the study and authorization for release of relevant protected health information to the study investigator.
8. Females of child bearing potential must agree to use appropriate birth control methods during the entire study period.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a)	Clinically significant renal, hepatic, endocrine (including diabetes mellitus), cardiac, pulmonary, pancreatic, neurologic, hematologic, or biliary disorder.
b)	Known allergy or sensitivity to Herbal products
c)	Use of systemic corticosteroids in the past 30 days.
d)	History of malignancy in the past two years.
e)	Recent history of alcoholism (within 12 months) or strong potential for alcohol or substance abuse.
f)	Participation in a clinical study with exposure to any non-registered drug product within 30 days prior.
g)	Individual has a condition the Investigator believes would interfere with his or her ability to provide informed consent, to comply with the study protocol or which might confound the interpretation of the study results or put the person at undue risk. Including subjects who are bed or wheelchair-bound.
h)	Pregnant or lactating during the duration of the study.
i)	Smoking  must be nonsmoker for at least 12 months prior to screening. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is by numbered containers</concealment>
    <sequence>computer generated randomized numbers</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>SAS analysis using ANOVA/T-Test
The number of subjects was calculated based on the results of the first clinical trial for which we had 20 subjects resulting in clinical significance.
A power calculation was then carried out and for 80% powered the answer was 50 subjects.  Because there is such a strong placebo effect with eczema, 50 was considered the bare minimum so we increased the number to 60 to ensure that we were indeed above a power calculation of 80%.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>6/11/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>61</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>2/02/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Decima Health Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>6 Blake St
Rangiora,
Christchurch 7400
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Decima Health Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>6 Blake St
Rangiora 7400
Christchurch</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This clinical trial is for testing a natural cream for relieving the symptoms of eczema</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HDEC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/NTA/89</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Simon Carson</name>
      <address>Southern Clinical Trials Group
6 Strickland St
Beckenham
Christchurch 8242</address>
      <phone>+64 3 337 1979</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>simon@sctrials.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Simon Carson</name>
      <address>Southern Clinical Trials Group
6 Strickland St
Beckenham
Christchurch 8242</address>
      <phone>+64 3 337 1979</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>simon@sctrials.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Iona Weir</name>
      <address>Decima Health Ltd,
6 Blake St
Rangiora
Christchurch 7400</address>
      <phone>+64 21 309 084</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>iona@decima.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Iona Weir</name>
      <address>6 Blake St
Rangiora
Christchurch 7400</address>
      <phone>+64 21 309 084</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>iona@decima.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>