<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362797">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001248853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Enhancing engagement for adolescents referred for mental health treatment.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Enhancing engagement for adolescents referred for mental health treatment using Motivational Interviewing</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety for adolescents referred for mental health treatment.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression for adolescents referred for mental health treatment.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Engagement for adolescents referred for mental health treatment.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Attendance for adolescents referred for mental health treatment.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mechanisms of action for motivational interviewing with adolescents referred for mental health treatment.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Therapeutic outcome for adolescents referred for mental health treatment.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Motivational Interviewing, one session approximately 50 minutes in duration prior to group therapy. These sessions will be conducted one on one by a Registered Clinical Psychologist. The group therapy will commence within two weeks following the motivational interviewing session. The group therapy will be cognitive behavioural therapy based and will be 5 weekly sessions for the duration of approximately 90 minutes. The primary facilitator for the group will be a trained mental health professional and Capital and Coast District Health Board staff member, and will be blind to the pre-treatment intervention received by group members.</interventions>
    <comparator>Befriending (active control), one individual session approximately 50 minutes in duration prior to group therapy. Befriending was developed to control for nonspecific aspects of psychotherapy, and is a form of social support delivered without focusing on difficulties relating to anxiety and depression. These sessions will be conducted one on one by a Registered Clinical Psychologist. The group therapy will commence within two weeks following the befriending session. The group therapy will be cognitive behavioural therapy based and will be 5 weekly sessions for the duration of approximately 90 minutes. The primary facilitator for the group will be a trained mental health professional and Capital and Coast District Health Board staff member, and will be blind to the pre-treatment intervention received by group members.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of group therapy sessions attended. A record of participant attendance for each of the 5 group sessions was kept using a checklist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Attendance for each of the 5 group sessions will be recorded.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Readiness for treatment using a readiness ruler, and The University of Rhode Island Change Assessment Questionnaire (URICA; McConnanaughy, DiClemente &amp; Prochaska, 1989).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and following intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms of Anxiety using The Revised Children's Manifest Anxiety Scale (RCMAS; Reynolds &amp; Richmond, 1985) and 
Symptoms of Depression using the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II; Beck, Steer, &amp; Brown, 1996).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, immediately following group therapy, and at 3 months follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived coercion assessed using Admissions Experience Scale (Bindman, 2004).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms of Depression using the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II; Beck, Steer, &amp; Brown, 1996).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, immediately following group therapy, and at 3 months follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Coping strategies using the Cognitive Emotion Regulation Questionnaire (CERQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, following group therapy and at 3 months follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Client motivation for therapy as assessed by the Client Motivation for Therapy Scale (CMOTS; Pelletier, Tuson &amp; Haddad, 1997).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and following intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life as assessed by the Clinical Global Impressions (CGI), the Children's Global Assessment Scale (clinician rated), and the Kidscreen Questionnaire as parent and participant-rated quality of life measures.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to the intervention, following group therapy and at 3 months follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sense of autonomy as assessed by The Adolescent Autonomy Questionnaire (Noom, 1999; Noom, Dekovic, &amp; Meeus, 2001).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and following intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Personal values as assessed by an open question "What do you most value (what is important to you in your life)?</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and following intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Therapeutic alliance will also be assessed on a session-by-session basis using the Session Rating Scale (Miller, Duncan, Brown, Sparks, &amp; Claud, 2003).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following the intervention session, and all five group therapy sessions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sense of self efficacy will be measured using The Perceived Competence Scale for Adolescents (PCSA; Harter 1982).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and following intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Individuals (males and females between 13 and 19 years of age), meeting diagnostic criteria for an anxiety or mood disorder, will be recruited through specialist mental health services.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>13</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>19</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those individuals with a non-anxiety or mood principal diagnosis, any learning disability or other major deficits in neurocognitive functioning, or active substance abuse will be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealed. Participants were randomised as they arrived for the intervention. The person who determined if a subject was eligible for inclusion in the trial was unaware, when this decision was made, to which group the subject would be allocated. Allocation was concealed such that the holder of the allocation schedule was off-site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Randomised cluster trial whereby individuals are randomised one of two groups for group therapy. As such in individuals in one group will have received motivational interviewing prior to the group and the other will have receieved the active control, befriending. Summary statistics for each cluster (group) will be derived.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/07/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago, Wellington</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Social Psychiatry &amp; Population Mental Health Research Unit
University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington	6242</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago, Wellington</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Social Psychiatry &amp; Population Mental Health Research Unit
University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington	6242</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The first aim of this study is to assess whether motivational interviewing (MI), as a brief pre-treatment intervention, will enhance treatment engagement and psychotherapeutic outcome in adolescents with anxiety and depressive disorders. 

The second aim is to explore factors that may be implicated in treatment adherence in the unique developmental stage of adolescence, such as, perceived coercion, sense of autonomy, sense of self-efficacy, readiness to change, motivation for therapy, symptoms of anxiety, symptoms of depression, coping strategies, and personal values. Thus, specific factors associated with the mechanisms of action of MI will also be identified.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>n/a</trialwebsite>
    <publication>n/a</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>New Zealand Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LRS/12/01/002</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/01/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Lower South Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Central Regional Ethics Committee
Ministry of Health
PO Box 5013
1 The Terrace
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LRS/12/01/002</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/01/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Shaystah Dean</name>
      <address>Social Psychiatry &amp; Population Mental Health Research Unit
University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington	Postcode	6242</address>
      <phone>+64,2102174293</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>deash101@student.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Shaystah Dean</name>
      <address>Social Psychiatry &amp; Population Mental Health Research Unit
University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington	Postcode	6242</address>
      <phone>+64,2102174293</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>deash101@student.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Shaystah Dean</name>
      <address>Social Psychiatry &amp; Population Mental Health Research Unit
University of Otago, Wellington
PO Box 7343
Wellington	Postcode	6242</address>
      <phone>+64,2102174293</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>deash101@student.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>