<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363553">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000105741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to compare the effect of three burns dressings on burns in children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of three different burns dressings on time to re-epithelialisation of partial thickness burns in children: a randomised control trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Paediatric partial thickness burns</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Burns</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A comparison of three dressings currently being used. Group 1: Burn wound will be dressed with Acticoat (a silver containing dressing without a silicone skin interface). Participants will have their dressing changed twice weekly until the wound re-epithelialises or grafting is required; Group 2: Burn wound will be dressed with Acticoat and Mepitel (a silicone coated nylon grid dressing) Participants will have their dressing changed twice weekly until the wound re-epithelialises or grafting occurs; Group 3: Burn wound will be dressed with Mepilex Ag (soft foam, silver containing dressing with safe-tac technology). Participants will have their dressing changed twice weekly until the wound re-epithelialises or grafting occurs. </interventions>
    <comparator>There is no placebo group in this study as it would be unethical not to dress burn wounds or to use an older, inferior dressing. Therefore the Acticoat, Acticoat and Mepitel and MepilexAg groups will be compared to each other as active control groups. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time (days) to re-epithelialisation of burn wound will be measured using two methods. 1: The VisitrakTM (Smith and Nephew) digital device will be used (by an unblinded assessor) to calculate wound area and assess wound re-epithelialisation; 2: Digital photography (3D LifeViz camera software, Quantificare) will be used by a blinded assessor (burns surgeon not involved in patient's care) to measure the area of re-epithelialisation. Both measurement methods to be undertaken at each dressing change (every 3 days).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 days (each dressing change) after intervention commencement until wound is re-epithelialised. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impact of dressings on pain and anxiety during changes: Child self report using the Revised Faces scale (FACES); Caregiver-report (or self-report of child 8 years or older) of child's level of pain using a 0-10 visual analogue scale. Pulse rate, respiratory rate and analgesia requirements also to be recorded. All measurements to be taken by a blinded assessor at each dressing change (every 3 days).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 days (each dressing change) after intervention commencement until wound is re-epithelialised.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Scar assessment using the Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale v2 (POSAS); digital photography; and ultrasound to determine scar thickness and ratio of scar thickness to normal adjacent skin. Measures taken by blinded assessor from point of healing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Point of healing, 3 and 6 months post-healing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect of wound dressing on physical functioning using parent/caregiver and child (&gt;8years) self report on a visual analogue scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 days (each dressing change).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Grafting of wound required (yes/no)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness of each dressings trialled (number of nurses required at each dressing change, time taken for procedure, amount and type of dressing used, grafting requirements, scar management costs (clinic attendance and use of resources)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 3 days (each dressing change) and at point of healing, 3 and 6 months post-healing</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative data from nursing staff on each dressing combination (e.g. ease of use).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Conclusion of trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children with acute superficial partial to deep partial thickness burn injuries &lt;10% TBSA (total body surface area), presenting to Royal Children's Hospital, Brisbane within 72hours of injury.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Superficial and full thickness burns
Burns &gt;10% TBSA
Known sensitivity to silver
Chemical and friction burns
Non-English speaking
Cognitive impairment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Treating physicians/nursing staff of all children meeting the inclusion/exclusion criteria presenting the to the Royal Children's Hospital, Brisbane will determine eligibility for enrolement in the study. An investigator aligned with the study will discuss the study with parents/caregivers/child and seek informed consent. Participants will then be randomised into one of the three treatment groups. Allocated concealment will be undertaken by the use of sealed, opaque, idential and serially numbered envelopes prepared by an independent party.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Demographic and baseline outcome measures will be compared.
An ANOVA or suitable non-parametric test will compare outcome measures between groups. 
Analysis will be by intention to treat and per protocol.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/03/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>12/01/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Children's Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Royal Brisbane Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sir Fred Schonell Dr  
St Lucia QLD 4072
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Molnlycke Healthcare Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 1.01
10 Tilley Lane
Frenchs Forest NSW 2086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>At the Royal Children's Hospital in Brisbane the standard of care in burns dressings for small to medium partial thickness burns has changed over the years. Currently, silver containing dressings are used to prevent infection and promote healing.  However despite the large number of burns dressings available on the market, very few high level trials have been conducted in children or adults. This study aims to determine the effect of various silver and silicone containing burns dressings for the treatment of partial thickness burns in children. 

The study hypothesises that:
1. Rate of healing, need for grafting and subsequent scarring from a burn wound is partly determined by the choice of dressing used.
2. The choice of dressings used can partly assist with pain and anxiety strategies during dressing change procedures; and impacts on a child's comfort and engagement in activities.
3. The dressing which best fulfils the above qualities will also be the most cost effective.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children's Health Services Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>EC00175</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>EC00179</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Roy Kimble</name>
      <address>Queensland Children's Medical Research Insitute
Level 4 Foundation Bldg
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>royk@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Roy Kimble</name>
      <address>Queensland Children's Medical Research Insitute
Level 4 Foundation Bldg
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>royk@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Roy Kimble</name>
      <address>Queensland Children's Medical Research Institute
Level 4 Foundation Bldg
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3636 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>royk@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>