<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83461">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/12/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/01/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000054213</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of a novel rehabilitation strategy in people undergoing primary total knee replacement surgery. The MARKER (Maximum Recovery After Knee Replacement Surgery) Study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of a novel rehabilitation strategy in people undergoing primary total knee replacement surgery. The MARKER (Maximum Recovery After Knee Replacement Surgery) Study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Primary total knee replacement surgery for osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Novel rehabilitation strategy, consisting of rehabilitation provided in 2 stages.

Stage 1: Initial home exercise programme (usually Week 1 to 6 after hospital discharge). The exercises will focus on maintaining and improving active knee flexion and extension range of motion. Participants will perform 5 to 10 times of 3 to 5 exercises 3 times per day. Participants progress, including adherence to the home exercise programme, walking ability and knee symptoms will be monitored weekly by a research physiotherapist, with clinic visits in the first one or two weeks and by telephone calls thereafter.

Stage 2: Outpatient exercise classes (usually Week 6 to 14 after hospital discharge)
About four weeks after total knee replacement surgery, a research physiotherapist will commence screening during the weekly telephone calls to assess eligibility to commence the classes: (i) surgical wound healed, (ii) full weight-bearing tolerated on the operated limb, (iii) ambulating independently outdoors for more than 50 m, and (iv) not requiring daily opioid-based analgesics for knee pain.
The exercise classes will be circuit-based and supervised by a physiotherapist. The one hour classes will be conducted twice a week for eight weeks. Each class will consist of a warm up and cool down component, progressive functional and strengthening exercises, and a 20-minute monitored aerobic exercise session on stationary bicycles.
At the beginning of each exercise class, knee pain, range of motion and swelling will be evaluated to allow appropriate exercise progression. Class size will be restricted to a maximum of six participants. Participants will be required to do at least one additional intensive exercise session per week at home, consisting of 30 minutes of walking outdoors or stationary bicycle. In addition, one education class will be provided to participants, focusing on the rationale for increasing lower limb muscle strength and beneficial lifestyle behaviours appropriate after total knee replacement.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care after discharge from the acute orthopaedic ward. This is could be inpatient or outpatient rehabilitation, or no treatment, according to the recommendation of the orthopaedic surgeon or to the usual practice at the recruitment centre.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain subscale on the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities (WOMAC) Scale (pain in the knee over the last 48 hours)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical function subscale on the Western Ontario and McMaster Universities (WOMAC) Scale (difficulties in physical activities in the knee over the last 48 hours)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life (SF-12 version 2)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arthritis severity and priority for surgery (Multi-attribute Arthritis Prioritisation Tool, MAPT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participation in leisure time physical activity (measured by the self-reported frequency and total duration over the past week of walking continuously, moderate physical activities and vigorous physical activities)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue ('how much of a problem has fatigue or tiredness been for you in the last week?'. Responses will be required on a 100-mm visual analogue scale, ranging from 'fatigue is no problem' to 'fatigue is a major problem')</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Use of analgesics over past 7 days (self-report survey)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking speed on the 50 ft walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee flexion and extension range of motion measured by an extendable goniometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximal isometric knee flexion and extension strength measured with a hand-held dynamometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lower limb power measured on the stair climbe test (ascending 10 stairs)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee stability - the self-reported degree to which knee instability (partial giving way or full giving way) affects daily activities</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 6 months and 12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>undergoing unilateral or bilateral primary total knee replacement surgery, able to provide informed consent, able to be discharged home from the orthopaedic ward</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>74</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) previous unicompartmental replacement or tibial osteotomy on the same knee, (ii) previous lower limb joint replacement surgery within the last six months, (iii) further lower limb joint replacement surgery anticipated within the next 12 months, (iv) major co-morbidity precluding aerobic exercise at 50-60% maximum heart rate, (v) rheumatoid arthritis, (vi) major neurological conditions, or (vii) inability to return to one of the participating sites for outpatient exercise classes</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Marlene Fransen</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Clinical and Rehabilitation Sciences Research Group, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Sydney, PO Box 170, Lidcombe NSW 1825</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>HCF Health and Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO BOX 4242, Sydney, 2001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>MBF Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50 Bridge St, Sydney NSW 2000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Sydney
Camperdown
NSW 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The MARKER (Maximum Recovery After Knee Replacement Surgery) Collaborative Group</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>C/O Associate Professor Marlene Fransen, 
Clinical and Rehabilitation Sciences Research Group, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Sydney, PO Box 170, Lidcombe NSW 1825</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is little scientific evidence to support the usual practice of providing outpatient rehabilitation to patients undergoing total knee replacement surgery (TKR) immediately after discharge from the orthopaedic ward. It is hypothesised that the demonstrated lack of benefit is due to the low exercise intensity tolerated at this time, with patients still recovering from the effects of major orthopaedic surgery. The aim of this study is to investigate the effectiveness of a novel rehabilitation strategy, consisting of an initial home exercise programme followed, about six weeks later, by outpatient exercise classes. It is hypothesised that the novel rehabilitation strategy will be more beneficial than the usual practice of providing outpatient rehabilitation immediately following discharge from the orthopaedic ward.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Marlene Fransen</name>
      <address>Clinical and Rehabilitation Sciences Research Group, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Sydney, PO Box 170, Lidcombe NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>+612 93519829</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.fransen@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Marlene Fransen</name>
      <address>Clinical and Rehabilitation Sciences Research Group, Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Sydney, PO Box 170, Lidcombe NSW 1825</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 93519829</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mfransen@george.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>