<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320491">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/09/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/09/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000801213</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Is Inspiratory Flow Rate (IFR) appropriate for the puffers patients use for their lung conditions, and will training them to achieve the appropriate IFR improve their shortness of breath and reduce their need for health services?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Appropriateness of Inspiratory Flow Rate (IFR) of Patients with Respiratory Disease for the Inhaler Devices they use, and the Effect of Training on Improving IFR and Reducing Demand for Healthcare Services.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Suboptimal use of Inhalers due to inappropriate Inspiratory Flow Rate</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Training patients to achieve an appropriate Inspiratory Flow Rate (IFR) for the Inhaler Device they use. Verbal training is provided by a pharmacist while utilising an inspiratory flow meter, and is followed up by individualised written instructions on how to achieve the appropriate IFR range for each of the inhalers a patient is using. Verbal training would take between 5-10 minutes until the patient achieves appropriate IFR or the pharmacist determines that the patient is unable to achieve such IFR. Written instructions should be provided 1-2 days after verbal training is offered. All training is offered only once to participants.</interventions>
    <comparator>No training provided.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% patients with improved shortness of breath (SOB). This is measured on the Borg Dyspnoea Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week, 2 week, 3 weeks, and 4 weeks after assessment of, or training on, IFR is provided.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emergency Departmemt (ED) presentation rate. This will be assessed by accessing patients' electronic records that show their presentation rate and admission details.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month, 2 months, and 3 months following IFR assessment/training.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average length of stay (in days). This will be assessed by accessing patients' electronic records that show their presentation rate and admission details.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Average of all hospital stays over the 3-months period following IFR assessment/training.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% patients achieving an IFR appropriate for the inhalers they use. This is determined by assessing patients' ability to achieve appropriate IFR, half an hour after training was offered by the pharmacist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Half an hour after training is provided.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of hospital admissions. This will be assessed by accessing patients' electronic records that show their presentation rate and admission details.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Average over the 3-months period following IFR assessment/training.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life as measured by the St George's Respiratory Questionnaire (SGRQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month after intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reliever Use Extent (RUE). This describes the extent to which a patient has been using their short acting B-agonist medications, for the relief of their shortness of breath.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for 1 month after intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality rate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months, 6 months, 12 months after intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>St Vincents Health patients older than 18 years of age with any respiratory disease, who use respiratory inhalers for the administration of their medications.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Patients with active respiratory infection, as indicated by current treatment with short term antibiotic therapy. Long term prophylactic antibiotic therapy is not an exclusion criterion.

* Patients on current short term oral corticosteroids.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation was not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by coin tossing is used to allocate a patient to "intervention" group or "no intervention" group, if the patient does not achieve appropriate IFR for at least one inhaler they use, during IFR assessment.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Kyrillos Guirguis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>2nd Flr Daly Wing,
St Vincent's Hospital,
35 Victoria Pde,
Fitzroy 3065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Kyrillos Guirguis</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2nd Flr Daly Wing,
St Vincent's Hospital,
35 Victoria Pde,
Fitzroy 3065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many patients with lung disease who use inhalers (puffers) are unable to generate enough strength when breathing in through their puffers. Often, they breathe too hard with some puffers. This breathing strength is generally known as the Inspiratory Flow Rate (IFR). Inappropriate IFR leads to sub-optimal use of puffers, compromising the effectiveness of patients' treatment. This study aims to know how common this problem is and to test the idea that training patients to achieve appropriate IFR leads to better outcomes. These outcomes include improved breathing, better quality of life, and reduced emergency department visits, as well as shorter hospital stays.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/09/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kyrillos Guirguis</name>
      <address>2nd Flr Daly Wing,
St Vincent's Hospital,
35 Victoria Pde,
Fitzroy 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9288 2392</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kyrillos.guirguis@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kyrillos Guirguis</name>
      <address>2nd Flr Daly Wing,
St Vincent's Hospital,
35 Victoria Pde,
Fitzroy 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9288 2392</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9288 2192</fax>
      <email>kyrillos.guirguis@svhm.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>