<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367285">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/11/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001216606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Trial of prescribed water intake in polycystic kidney disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised controlled trial to determine the efficacy and safety of prescribed water intake to prevent kidney failure due to Autosomal Dominant Polycystic Kidney Disease (PREVENT-ADPKD)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PREVENT-ADPKD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Autosomal Dominant Polycystic Kidney Disease (ADPKD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human Genetics and Inherited Disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Group A- Standard treatment and ad libitum water consumption for 36 months.
Group B- Standard treatment and prescribed water consumption for 36 months.
The daily volume of water prescribed for Group B will be tailored for each participant. It will be based on calculation of free water clearance from the urine collected. It will also take into account the fluid loss, seasonal changes and physical activity of the participant. Participants will be asked to self-monitor their fluid intake (using either a paper-based diary or smart-phone compatible website) and measure the gravity in their urine using a urine dipstick. Participants will be required to reply to short message service (SMS) sent twice weekly in the first six months, then monthly thereafter, to their mobile phones with the result of the urine dipstick test. Participants in Group B will be contacted by the study nurse/dietitian by telephone at weeks 1,3, 6, then monthly in Year 1 and 3-monthly in Years 2-3 to monitor adherence to water intake and if necessary adjust the water intake based on results from pathology tests and urine dipstick.
Standard treatment is defined as generic approaches to slow the progression of chronic kidney disease; which include the standard care from the participants' usual physician.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment and ad libitum water consumption.
Standard treatment is defined as generic approaches to slow the progression of chronic kidney disease; which include lifestyle changes (smoking cessation, dietary salt restriction. moderate alcohol intake, weight maintenance), management of blood pressure and caffeine intake.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage annual rate of change in height-corrected Total Kidney Volume (Ht-TKV) from Baseline to 36 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline to month 36</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment efficacy measured by changes in markers of systemic arginine vasopressin (AVP) activity; serum copeptin and 24-hour urine osmolality and volume.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline to month 36</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment efficacy measured by change in markers of Kidney Disease Progression: Rate of eGFR decline; resting mean arterial pressure (MAP); urine albumin to creatinine ratio and kidney pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline to month 36</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment adherence measured by proportion of times each patient (Group B) responds to SMS text messages (sent twice-weekly during Months 0 to 6, and then monthly thereafter) within 12 hours requesting the results of the late-afternoon urine specific gravity (SG)</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline to month 36</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment adherence measured by proportion of patients with 24 hr-urine osmolality &lt;300 mosmol/kg at all timepoints</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline to month 36</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety measured by monitoring adverse events.
Hyponatraemia is a possible adverse event. This will be monitored regularly by monitoring blood sodium levels during the study. If the sodium levels go below a minimum level, the participant will be wtihdrawn from the intervention (but continued to be followed up) and appropriate medical management undertaken.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From baseline to Month 36</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment acceptability measured by the proportion of patients reporting that water intake can be maintained life-long.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline to month 36</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment acceptability measured by the proportion of patients withdrawing from the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline to month 36</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Renal disease progession in ADPKD measured by the changes in biomarkers, including urinary, serum samples and 24 hour urine sodium and urate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline to Month 36. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Adult patients (18-65 years of age) providing informed consent
2. Adult patients with a diagnosis of ADPKD
3. eGFR of 30 mL/min/1.73m2 within 6 weeks of randomisation as determined by the chronic kidney disease epidemiology collaboration (CKD EPI) formula</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	 Patients who in the opinion of the trial investigators present a safety risk (including serum Na+ &lt;135 mmol/L at screening; requirement for concomitant medications with a high risk of precipitating hyponatraemia, such as chronic use of diuretics; concomitant medical conditions that require fluid restriction, such as heart failure, chronic liver disease, nephrotic syndrome or generalised oedema; abnormalities in the voiding mechanism; pregnant or breast-feeding women).
2. Contraindication to or interference with MRI assessments (e.g. ferro-magnetic prostheses, aneurysm clips, severe claustrophobia or other contraindications)
3. 	Patients who are unlikely to adequately comply with trials procedures (such as history of non-compliance with anti-hypertensive or other important medical therapy; history of substance abuse within the previous 2 years)
4.	 Patients having concomitant illnesses or treatments likely to confound endpoint assessments (such as advanced and poorly controlled diabetes; evidence of significant renal disease not due to ADPKD, such as active glomerulonephritis, renal cancer or single kidney; severe co-morbid illnesses)
5.	 Patients participating in other clinical trials to slow ADPKD or CKD
6. 	Patients with Baseline TKV in Mayo Clinic Imaging Classes 1A
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be randomly allocated in a uniform 1:1 ratio to either Group A or B.  Randomisation is centrally controlled and concealed with a secure web based randomisation service. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation is centrally controlled and concealed with a secure web based randomisation service. Participants will be randomly allocated in a uniform 1:1 ratio (in permuted blocks), stratified according to baseline eGFR level.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The general analytical approach for all endpoints will be descriptive in nature. All summaries will present the data by treatment group as well as by all patients combined. Intent-to-treat principles will be followed. The patient characteristics (age, gender, TKV, eGFR) will be compared at baseline.  Analysis of covariance will be used to analyse log10 Ht-TKV at months 18, and 36, with baseline log10 Ht-TKV as the covariate. The assumptions of the analysis of covariance of normally distributed residuals and constant variance will be assessed with normal probability plots, and residual versus fitted plots. Linear-mixed effects models will be used to test the interaction between Treatment groups, and Time if assumptions of equal covariance between Times cannot be guaranteed. By using the proportion of times each patient responds to the SMS within 12 hours we will construct the distribution of adherence in the intervention arm.    In these analyses the outcome measure will be transformed to approximate normality if required.  Chi-squared or Fisher exact test will be used to test the association between categorical variables.  

A sample size of 90 participants per arm will have at least 80% power to detect a difference in mean osmolality between Group A and B. This assumes a 15% drop out rate and 5% significance level and two-sided test.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>Simon Roger Gosford Renal Research - Gosford</hospital>
    <hospital>Norwest Private Hospital - Bella Vista</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>2750 - Penrith</postcode>
    <postcode>2250 - Gosford</postcode>
    <postcode>2153 - Bella Vista</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Westmead Millennium Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Transplant and Renal Research 
176 Hawkesbury Road
Westmead, NSW 2145
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Westmead Millennium Institute
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Centre for Transplant and Renal Research 
176 Hawkesbury Road
Westmead, NSW 2145
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Sydney </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Camperdown, NSW 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Danone Nutricia Research </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>RD 128, 91767 Palaiseau Dedex
France</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>France</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>-</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>-</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>ADPKD is an inherited condition, characterized by the growth of hundreds of cysts (fluid-filled sacs) in the kidney. This results in an enlarged kidney and pain, high blood pressure and an increased risk of chronic kidney disease. Kidney failure usually develops in late adulthood in about half of affected people. There is currently no treatment that can cure ADPKD or stop cysts forming and growing in the kidneys.

In the last few years, people with ADPKD have been advised to drink more water to suppress anti-diuretic hormone (ADH, or vasopressin). However, it is not clear if this approach is feasible in the long-term and without risk and/or if there is an ideal amount of water to drink that will benefit disease progression.

The aim of this study is to determine the efficacy and safety of prescribed water intake in ADPKD. 

Eligible patients with ADPKD will be randomised (1:1) to either:
Group A (control) to continue with their usual (ad libitum) water consumption (including standard treatment) or Group B (intervention) to adjust their daily water intake to reduce the urine osmolality to less than or equal to 270 mosmol/L for the next 36 months in addition to their standard treatment. The volume of prescribed water consumption will be calculated according to free water clearance based on baseline and progress measurements of 24 hour urine collection. 

All patients will be expected to have blood collections at 3, 6, 9, 12, 18, 24, 30 and 36 months.   In Group B subjects, additional samples will be collected at Week 3 and 6 for safety check and also titration of the water prescription. 

After the Month 36 visit, Group B patients may return to their previous ad libitum water consumption habits.  All patients will have a Post-treatment Study Visit at Month 37 with post-treatment blood test (2 and 4 weeks post-treatment) and a 24 hour urine sample (4 weeks post-treatment). </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>WSLHD Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Corner of Hawkesbury and Darcy Roads, 
Westmead, NSW, 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Gopala Rangan</name>
      <address>Westmead Institute for Medical Research
Centre for Transplant and Renal Research 
176 Hawkesbury Road 
Westmead, NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9845 6962</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>preventadpkd@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Gopala Rangan</name>
      <address>Westmead Institute for Medical Research
Centre for Transplant and Renal Research 
176 Hawkesbury Road 
Westmead, NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9845 6962</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>preventadpkd@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Gopala Rangan</name>
      <address>Westmead Institute for Medical Research
Centre for Transplant and Renal Research 
176 Hawkesbury Road 
Westmead, NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9845 6962</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>preventadpkd@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Gopala Rangan</name>
      <address>Westmead Institute for Medical Research
Centre for Transplant and Renal Research 
176 Hawkesbury Road 
Westmead, NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9845 6962</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>preventadpkd@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>