<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369212">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000607471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of the Effectiveness of Mindfulness Practice in reducing Autonomic Dysfunction associated with Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised control trial to evaluate the effectiveness of mindfulness practice in increasing heart rate variability and improving physical symptoms and quality of life in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease compared to pulmonary rehabilitation alone.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1173-7698</utrn>
    <trialacronym>MB-SMART for COPD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Autonomic dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1-Pulmonary rehabilitation and Mindfulness Training and education of cognitive skills to self manage effects on cardiovascular autonomic nervous system.  Weekly 1 hour sessions for 8 weeks and homework.

Arm 2-pulmonary rehabilitation only as their standard care as usual

Mindfulness Intervention
Mindfulness program is designed with practices with a specific emphasis in increasing awareness of automatic behaviour following emotional reactivity using body and emotional awareness.  Enhanced awareness on thoughts, emotions and automatic behaviour can reduce psychological reactivity and thereby reduce the autonomic nervous system activity (psycho-neurological sympathetic over-activity). This program is called Mindfulness Based Self -Managed Auto-Regulation Treatment (MB-SMART). The mindfulness program includes a one-hour weekly practice session for 8 weeks and follow up sessions at 3, 6, 9 and 12 months intervals, in addition to home practices guided by a manual at the volunteers discretion. The sessions are small group sessions at the study center. The mindfulness teaching sessions are conducted by the principle researcher who has undertaken training in MBSR online and a few other mindfulness training courses including Mindfulness integrated cognitive behaviour therapy. She is a daily mindfulness practitioner. and conducts sessions under guidance of her supervisor who is a clinical psychologist. 
It has two main components; Patient Education and Mindfulness Practices 
Week 1.. 
Patient education.
a. How stress affects the body- Stress response and its consequences
b. What the science tells us about the mind body connection.
c. Introduction to mindfulness
d. Patients role in disease management, address their concerns
e. Consequences of untreated disease

Week 2 to 8. 
Mindfulness practices: (45 minutes)
a.  Mindfulness of Breath followed by group discussion
b.  Mindfulness of Sound followed by group discussion
c.  Mindfulness of body sensation followed by group discussion
d.  Mindfulness of Movement followed by group discussion
e.  Mindfulness of mental activity followed by group discussion
f.   Insight meditation with Body Scan (Lying Down)

Objectives of mindfulness sessions:
a. Participants will identify their own stressors that trigger stress related behaviours
b. Participants will identify strategies to overcome stress related behaviours.
c. Participants will review progress in avoiding stress related behaviours followed by:
d. Learning and cultivating equanimity and loving kindness

Homework is to practice what was learnt during previous weeks at least for 10 minute in each technique. Participants are asked to journal their activities with their experience and feedback.
The control group will also be offered MB-SMART at the end of the year if they are willing to have, as a reward for participating in the study. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment of weekly two and half hour pulmonary rehabilitation sessions for 8 weeks</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart Rate Variability is the primary outcome.
HR monitoring will be done using the Bodygurad 2 monitor of Firstbeat Technologies commencing at the intake assessment and sent home with the patient attached to the patient's chest with two electrodes. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Base line :
Primary outcome (HRV) will be assessed for 24 to 48 hours after recruitment before starting the mindfulness  intervention and pulmonary rehabilitation for base line. The volunteers are asked to bring the monitor back the following week.

During weekly sessions:
Each participant in both groups will be asked to wear a monitor during pulmonary rehabilitation and those who participate in mindfulness will be monitored during mindfulness sessions each week.. 

At the end of the program: 
  At  HR will be monitored again for 24 to 48 hours at the the end of the 7th week and the monitors will be returned to the researcher on the 8th week. Heart rate monitoring will be repeated at 3, 6, 9 and 12 months follow up mindfulness sessions. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mindfulness level as assessed by Freiburg Mindfulness Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>At base line and post commencement of intervention at 8 weeks,3 months, 6 months and 12 months..</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological state by DASS21 questionnaire 


</outcome>
      <timepoint>At base line and at post commencement of intervention at 8 weeks, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease specific functionality and severity assessed by
the St. Georges Questionnaire
Modified Dyspnoea scale, 
BODE scale and 
Peak expiratory flow rate.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At base line and post commencement of intervention at 8 weeks, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functionality and quality of life assessed by OQ45 </outcome>
      <timepoint>At base line and post commencement of intervention at 8 weeks, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients attending pulmonary rehabilitation for COPD
2. Stable patients likely to be maintained on the same drug therapy at least over a period of 8 weeks 
3. Adult men and women
4. Have the willingness and ability to comply with assessment protocols
5. Be prepared to be contacted by the researcher to monitor and follow up mental and physical health status
6. Those who give consent to obtain clinical history, examination and investigations from their medical practitioners


 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Pregnancy- because it can complicate the clinical picture. 
2. Physical disability that affects patients mobility and requiring walking aids
3. Cognitive impairment- because it will affect patients understanding and the ability to participate in the study
4. Those who do not have sufficient proficiency in English language to communicate and comprehend study requirements. 
5. The patients who are not committed to complete a 6 week program.
6. Requirement of inpatient hospital care within 8 weeks
7. Severe mental disorder
8. Unable to avoid being substance dependent for the period of study from the time of volunteering to participate. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Quasi randomised allocation by assigning alternative male and female volunteers for intervention and control groups at the time of recruitment by the pulmonary rehabilitation staff.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/06/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>15/02/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4509 - North Lakes</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. S Jayamaha</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>St Lucia QLD 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Firstbeat Technologies Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Yliopistonkatu 28 A
Jyvaskyla 40100</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Finland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim of the study:
Overall Purpose for the research: is to explore scientific basis for preliminary and anecdotal evidence of psychosomatic nature patho-physiology in chronic physical diseases and to evaluate a psychological approach to treat physical disease.
The primary aim of this study is to assess the effectiveness of a Mindfulness based programs in improving autonomic nervous system dysfunction associated with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). Autonomic dysfunction is measured by measuring heart rate variability (HRV). Percentage of increase in HRV before and after the treatment is calculated to compare the effectiveness of  the two groups who undergo Pulmonary Rehabilitation with or without Mindfulness practice.
The proposed plan of this study has 3 components:
1.	Literature Review is to understand the scientific basis to psychological stress associated with sympathetic over-activity in COPD 
2.	Monitoring sympathetic over-activity using heart rate variability (HRV) parameters in moderate and severe COPD patients who are undergoing pulmonary rehabilitation 
3.	Testing effectiveness of a psychological method (Mindfulness practice) which has been successfully used as a stress management therapy as an adjunct therapy for COPD.
Hypothesis: The hypothesis tested in this study is that Mindfulness Practice increases HRV in moderate and severe COPD patients undergoing pulmonary rehabilitation.
Cohort: Adult male and female participants who are diagnosed to have moderate or severe chronic COPD and participating in a pulmonary rehabilitation program.
Design: 
This is a pilot study and a phase trial of a randomised control trial. 
Phase 1:
We intend to recruit 40 moderate and severe COPD patients attending a pulmonary rehabilitation program. All participants will be attending a weekly pulmonary rehabilitation program (PRP) for 8 weeks. While they are attending PRP, half the group will be randomised to receive concurrent training in mindfulness practice after PRP each week for 8 weeks. The other half will be receiving only the treatment as usual which is PRP and usual pharmacology treatment. This second group will act as the control group.
Phase 2: 
In the phase 2, the same study will be expanded to include an additional number of participants based on findings of the pilot study and extended to explore other different non communicable diseases associated with autonomic dysfunction.

The Mindfulness program (MBSMART)
Mindfulness program is designed with practices with a specific emphasis in increasing awareness of automatic behaviour following emotional reactivity using body and emotional awareness.  Enhanced awareness on thoughts, emotions and automatic behaviour can reduce psychological reactivity and thereby reduce the autonomic nervous system activity (psycho-neurological sympathetic over-activity). This program is called Mindfulness Based Self -Managed Auto-Regulation Treatment (MB-SMART). </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Prince Charles Hospital Ethics Committee and University of Queensland Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>TPCH, Rode Road, Chermside, QLD 4032 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/QPCH/274</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Lucia QLD 4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015001267</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amarasinghe Sophie Sepalika Jayamaha</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital, Rode Road, Chermside, QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>_+61 7 3139 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sophie.jayamaha@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Bambling</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland, Herston, campus, QLD, 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 5142</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.bambling@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sophie Jayamaha</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital, Rode Road, Chermside, QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sophie.jayamaha@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sophie Jayamaha</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital, Rode Road, Chermside, QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3139 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sophie.jayamaha@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>