<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364785">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000932763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An open label, phase I study to determine the pharmacokinetic, safety and tolerability profiles of oxymorphone delivered from multiple applications of a transdermal oxymorphone patch.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open label, multiple dose, phase I study in healthy volunteers to determine the pharmacokinetic, safety and tolerability profiles of oxymorphone delivered from a transdermal oxymorphone patch to promote pain relief.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>POH032-13</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>To promote pain relief, tested in healthy volunteers.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Single centre, open-label, multiple application study in a total of 12 healthy participants. 

Eligible participants will receive 4 x 3 day sequential applications of transdermal patches containing 56.8 mg of oxymorphone per application in combination with TPM (tocopheryl phosphate mix) during a 12 day in-house stay. A subsequent 4 day in-house stay will follow to ensure washout of the oxymorphone to a safe level prior to discharge.During the entire study period, participants will receive naltrexone 50mg orally twice a day to block the systemic effects of oxymorphone.</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To characterise the pharmacokinetic profile of oxymorphone delivered transdermally using the oxymorphone patch.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pharmacokinetic profile will be assessed through collection of blood samples at various time points during each 3 day patch application and during the wash out period. A total of 59 blood samples will be collected from each participant and analysed
Timepoint:	Pharmacokinetic profile will be assessed through collection of blood samples at various time points. On Day 1 there will be an intensive blood sampling period in which samples will be collected every 1-2hrs and for the duration of the in-house period sample will be collected every 4-8hrs. A total of 59 blood samples will be collected from each participant and analysed.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of oxymorphone delivered transdermally from the oxymorphone patch.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety and tolerability will be assessed by:
* The frequency of Adverse Events. Known/ possible adverse events that have associated with the oxymorphone patch include application site reaction, nausea and dizziness.
* The frequency of skin irritation at site of application
* Clinically important changes in Vital signs 
* Clinically important changes in laboratory tests and assessments
Timepoint:	Safety and tolerability will be assessed by:
* The frequency of Adverse Events measured throughout study participation
* The frequency of skin irritation at site monitored after patch removal
* Clinically important changes in Vital signs monitored twice daily throughout the in-house period 
* Clinically important changes in laboratory tests and assessments monitored at screening, check-in, Day 4, Day 10, discharge and follow up (5-7 days post discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy male subjects, aged 18 to 55 years inclusive, body mass index greater than or equal to 19 and less than or equal to 27 kg/m2, weight &gt;50 kg, free from clinically significant illness or disease, as defined.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Evidence of clinically significant impairment/disorders.
* History of coronary disease, peripheral vascular disease, cerebrovascular accident, transient ischaemic attack, uncontrolled hypertension or signs/symptoms of ischaemic heart disease. 
* Have a rested systolic blood pressure of &lt; 90 mmHg or &gt; 160 mmHg and/or diastolic blood pressure of &lt; 50 mmHg or &gt; 95 mmHg.
* History of obstructive airway disease or any condition that may increase the risk for respiratory depression. 
* A resting pulse rate at rest of &lt; 45 Beats Per Minute (BPM) or &gt; 100 BPM. 
* History of neurologic conditions or convulsive disorders, severe head injury or increased intracranial pressure.
* A calculated creatinine clearance of &lt; 85 mL/minute
* Have undergone surgery or received anaesthetic within 30 days of Day 1.
* Use of central nervous system depressants within 30 days of Day 1.
* Use of macrolide antibiotics, azole antifungal agents or protease inhibitors within 30 days of Day 1.
* Use of any prescription medication, over the counter product, herbal product, diet aid, or hormone supplement, within 14 days of Day 1 and for duration of study. 
* Known intolerance any ingredients in the patch , naltrexone or naloxone. 
* Any history of a dermatological condition or recurrent generalised skin disorder within the last 5 years. 
* Any tattoos, bruises, scars or skin lesions on the area where the patch is to be applied.
* Consumption of grapefruit, grapefruit juice or any products containing CYP3A4 inhibitors and inducers within 14 days of Day 1 and through to discharge.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>13/09/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>4/09/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Phosphagenics Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>11 Duerdin Street Clayton, Victoria 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Phosphagenics Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>11 Duerdin St Clayton, Victoria, 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to understand how well oxymorphone in combination with tocopheryl phosphate mix (TPM), is absorbed through the skin and into the bloodstream, with the use of a patch.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>229 Greenhill Road Dulwich South Australia 5065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Janakan Krishnarajah</name>
      <address>Linear Clinical Research
1st Floor, B Block, Hospital Avenue, Nedlands WA  6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 6382 5124   </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>JKrishnarajah@linear.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alisha Smith</name>
      <address>Phosphagenics Ltd , 11 Duerdin Street, Clayton VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9565 1119</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>asmith@phosphagenics.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alisha Smith</name>
      <address>Phosphagenics Ltd, 11 Duerdin Street, Clayton VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9565 1119</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>asmith@phosphagenics.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>