<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364794">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000940774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A comparison of 2 modes of non-invasive ventilation applied on patients after extubation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Noninvasive ventilation-neurally adjusted ventilatory assist (NIV-NAVA) compared to noninvasive ventilation-pressure support (NIV-PS) in post-extubated subjects on synchrony and work of breathing</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Respiratory failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>use of non-invasive ventilation in the neurally adjusted ventilatory assist mode (NIV-NAVA) with PEEP set at 5 cmH2O. NAVA gain level will be titrated to achieve an equivalent peak inspiratory pressure as in PSV (NAVA0). Another 2 levels will be set at 0.5 cmH2O/uV above and below NAVA0 (NAVA+1 and NAVA-1 respectively). Inspiratory trigger Edi will be set at 0.5uV above Edi min, while expiratory trigger is fixed by the manufacturer at 70% of Edi peak. The subject will breathe at each setting for 20 minutes as wash-out and recordings are obtained in the next 2 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>non-invasive ventilation in the pressure support mode (NIV-PS) with PEEP set at 5 cmH2O, PS titrated to achieve a tidal volume of 6-8ml/kg, inspiratory flow trigger at 5, expiratory trigger at 30% of maximal peak flow, rise time at 0.1 ms. The subject will breathe at this setting for 20 minutes and recordings are obtained in the next 2 minutes </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of patient-ventilator asynchrony index will be measured by studying airway pressure, flow (obtained using the Servo Tracker software) and esophageal pressure tracings measured using a balloon esophageal catheter, an analog-to-digital converter system and Labview software.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at the end of 20 minutes on each NIV setting</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>inspiratory work of breathing will be measured using the diagram method of Campbell by integrating the area plotted between the esophageal pressure-volume and chestwall compliance curves. Esophageal pressure-time-product will also be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured at the end of 20 minutes of each NIV setting</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>patient's comfort score assessed by a visual analog scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured at the end of 20 minutes on each NIV setting</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Are currently or previously on mechanical ventilation for acute respiratory failure 
2.	Are considered fit for extubation (defined as hemodynamic stability without the need for vasopressor support and a heart rate less than 110 beats per minute (bpm), respiratory rate less than 30 per minutes, and a Glasgow coma scale of E4VtM6), or has been extubated already
3.	Are indicated for NIV with &gt;=1 of the risk factors for reintubation, including: chronic heart failure, COPD initially intubated because of an episode of acute hypercapnic respiratory failure, age &gt;65, more than one consecutive failure of weaning trial before extubation, PaCO2 &gt;45 mmHg (6 kPa) after extubation, weak cough
4.	Expected to require NIV for &gt;=2 days
5.	Able to give consent to the study by him/herself. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>patients less than 18 years of age, pregnancy, with contraindications for insertion of nasogastric tube, or with contraindications for NIV (esophageal varices or obstruction, bleeding of the upper gastrointestinal tract, recent gastroesophageal surgery, hemodynamic instability or severe arrhythmia, facial surgery or trauma or deformity, severe upper airway obstruction, inability to cooperate or protect the airways, inability to cough or clear respiratory secretions, absence of a gag reflex and severe gastric distention), or contraindications to NAVA mode (known or suspected phrenic nerve dysfunction, and impaired respiratory drive). </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a cross-over study. After extubation, each subject will receive NIV in both NAVA and PS modes but in a random sequence. </concealment>
    <sequence>4 pieces of paper labelled as PS mode, NAVA0, NAVA-1 and NAVA+1 are folded and placed inside a paper bag. The sequence of NIV levels per subject is determined by the sequence of paper drawn from the paper bag. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Prior studies provided only non-parametric data. Reduction in the median asynchrony index using NIV-NAVA compared to NIV-PS was 10.9% (from 15.8% (interquartile range, IQR 5.5-49.6%) to 4.9% (IQR 2.5  10.5 %) using data from Piquilloud et al 2012. With an estimated standard deviation of 13, a power of 90% and an alpha error of 5%, and using paired t test, the sample size calculated is 17. 
Results will be presented as mean +/- SD. Comparisons between NIV-PS and NIV-NAVA will be done using the Mann-Whitney U test. P values of 0.05 or less will be considered significant.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>17</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Intensive Care, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan, Hong Kong</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Intensive Care, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan, Hong Kong</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Hong Kong</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Noninvasive ventilation (NIV) has been found to reduce ventilator associated pneumonia, total duration of mechanical ventilation, length of intensive care unit (ICU) and hospital stay and mortality in patients with respiratory failure when they are connected after extubation. However, this benefit will be annihilated if NIV cannot be tolerated by the patient. Because NIV is delivered through an interface prone to leakage in a conscious but not necessarily cooperative patient, there could be more problems in patient-ventilator synchrony as compared to invasive positive pressure ventilation (IPPV). NAVA was found to be able to improve patient-ventilator synchrony through its benefits in better ventilator triggering and cycling off using the electrical activity of the diaphragm (Edi) signal instead of pressure or flow changes in the ventilator circuit. This could translate into a reduction in the work of breathing (WOB) as has been found in an animal study using NAVA in IPPV, but detailed analysis of WOB in NIV-NAVA has not been reported.  We hypothesized that patient-ventilator asynchrony and WOB would be reduced using NAVA-NIV. 
The aim of this study is therefore to find out whether there would be a reduction in asynchrony and WOB using NIV-NAVA compared with standard NIV-PS, and to find out its comparative benefits in post-extubation NIV. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hong Kong East Cluster Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital,
3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>LAM Sin-Man</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital, 3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan</address>
      <phone>852-25957133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lamsm2@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>LAM Sin-Man</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital, 3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan</address>
      <phone>852-25957133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lamsm2@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>LAM Sin-Man</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care, Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital, 3 Lok Man Road, Chai Wan</address>
      <phone>852-25957133</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lamsm2@ha.org.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>