<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365040">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001069741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The combined effect of Liraglutide and Sleeve Gastrectomy on Metabolic, Cardiac, Neurological and Sleep Function in Obese Diabetes: A Twelve-Month Randomised Study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The combined effect of Liraglutide and Sleeve Gastrectomy on Metabolic, Cardiac, Neurological and Sleep Function in Obese Individuals with Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus: A Twelve-Month, Randomised, Parallel-Group, Placebo-Controlled Study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1137-7794</utrn>
    <trialacronym>LIRASLEEVE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients who have elected to have bariatric surgery or medical management for weight loss will be randomised to receive 1.8mg liraglutide daily, administered subcutaneously, for 12 months. Participants will commence liraglutide/placebo treatment within 2 weeks of bariatric surgery taking place or starting medical management for obesity.
Participants will be asked to return any unused study drug at each study visit; this will be used as a way to monitor adherence to the study medication protocol. Furthermore, fasting blood glucose will be measured at each study visit, as a way of monitoring glycaemic control in the study participants.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo, containing the same constituents and excipients as the liraglutide pen injector, apart from the active component (liraglutide).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in body weight, as assessed by standard anthropometric measures, such as weight, height, waist circumference, BMI calculation and body composition (evaluated by dual x-ray absorptiometry).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in metabolic variables, including glycaemic control, which will be determined by glycosylated HbA1c, fasting plasma glucose, fasting insulin, number of patients taking insulin compared to baseline, insulin dose and medication usage.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in cardiac function, determined by change in clinical cardiac endpoints such as heart rate and blood pressure. Cardiac magnetic resonance will be used to measure left ventricular mass, left ventricular mass index, left ventricular ejection fraction, left ventricular diastolic function, left atrial size, right ventricular function and aortic function-distensibility. Echocardiography will be used to measure left ventricular ejection fraction and left ventricular diastolic function.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in neural and neurocognitive function, assessed by MRI brain and the IntegNeuro cognitive assessment tool.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in sleep function, as measured by the Epworth Sleepiness Scale, and overnight polysomnography, from which the apnoea-hypopnoea index will be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Subjects diagnosed with type 2 diabetes mellitus who have elected to undergo bariatric surgery or medical management for weight loss
- Body mass index greater than 35kg/m2 or 30kg/m2 with at least 2 medical co-morbidities
- Body weight less than 150kg; waist circumference less than 150cm
- HbA1c: 7%-10% (both inclusive) in subjects on anti-diabetes combination therapy
- HbA1c: 7%-11% (both inclusive) in subjects on anti-diabetes monotherapy</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Impaired liver function, defined as alanine aminotransferase (ALT) greater than or equal to 3 times the upper limit of normal (one retest within one week is permitted with the results from the last sample being conclusive)
- Impaired renal function, defined as serum-creatinine greater than or equal to 135umol/l for males and 110umol/l for females (one retest within one week is permitted with the results from the last sample being conclusive)
- Clinically significant active cardiovascular disease including history of myocardial infarction within the past 6 months and/or heart failure (New York Heart Association (NYHA) class III and IV) at the discretion of the Investigator
- Proliferative retinopathy or maculopathy requiring acute treatment as judged by the Investigator
- Recurrent major hypoglycaemia as judged by the Investigator
- Use of any drug (except for anti-diabetes medication), which in the Investigator's opinion could interfere with the glucose level (e.g. systemic corticosteroids)
- Pregnancy or lactation
- History of pancreatitis or pancreatic cancer
- Patients with a past history of GLP-1 analogue associated pancreatitis
- History of medullary thyroid cancer
- Contraindications to liraglutide or any of its excipients
- Hypersensitivity to liraglutide or similar drugs
- Suspected or known abuse of alcohol or narcotics</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be screened and recruited to the study at visit 1 (-6 weeks before administration of study drug/placebo). Subsequently, participants will be randomised to treatment (liraglutide or placebo) at visit 3 (-1 weeks before administration of study drug/placebo). In order to avoid bias, both researchers and participants will be blind to the treatment group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation list will be created by the allocation study nurse using a Microsoft Excel spreadsheet, in consultation with The George Institute for Global Health, Australia. Block randomisation will be used, such that balance across the treatment groups is achieved. On site randomisation will be carried out by an un-blinded study nurse, who will ensure allocation of participants to the correct treatment group. A study independent advisor from The George Institute will oversee the randomisation process.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based on previous studies, which have determined the effect of liraglutide on weight loss, we have determined that with a sample size of 120, we will be able to detect a weight difference of 5.1kg, with 80% power and a significance level of 0.05. Furthermore, we will be powered (80%) to detect a difference in fat mass of 1kg by DXA scanning, with a significance level of 0.05.
Statistical analysis will be performed using SPSS version 19 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, Illinois). The George Institute will assist with statistical analysis of results obtained throughout the study. Statistical methods to be used will include analysis of covariance, logistic regression models and survival analyses. Specific statistical tests will include student's t-test, Mann-Whitney U test, and Wilcoxon rank tests. All data will be analysed using the intention-to-treat principle.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/12/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - Royal North Shore Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Northern Sydney Local Health District</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal North Shore Hospital
Reserve Road, St Leonards,
NSW 2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Novo Nordisk</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3
21 Solent Circuit
BAULKHAM HILLS NSW 2153
AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project will examine the effect of weight loss induced by the administration of the GLP-1 analogue, liraglutide, in combination with bariatric surgery or medical management on factors associated with metabolic and end-organ abnormalities. It is likely that liraglutide will improve the metabolic and neurohormonal profile of patients with obesity. Complications of obesity including cardiac pathology, neurocognitive dysfunction and sleep-disordered breathing may improve as a result of weight loss, with the use of a GLP-1 analogue.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office,
Level 13, Kolling Institute,
Reserve Road,
Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards,
NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1211-383M</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Greg Fulcher</name>
      <address>Department of Diabetes, Endocrinology and Metabolism,
Level 3, Acute Services Building,
Royal North Shore Hospital,
Reserve Road,
St Leonards,
NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61294631680</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>greg.fulcher@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel McGrath</name>
      <address>Department of Diabetes, Endocrinology and Metabolism,
Level 3, Acute Services Building,
Royal North Shore Hospital,
Reserve Road,
St Leonards,
NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61294631470</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rachel.McGrath@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel McGrath</name>
      <address>Department of Diabetes, Endocrinology and Metabolism,
Level 3, Acute Services Building,
Royal North Shore Hospital,
Reserve Road,
St Leonards,
NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61294631470</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rachel.McGrath@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rachel McGrath</name>
      <address>Department of Diabetes, Endocrinology and Metabolism,
Level 3, Acute Services Building,
Royal North Shore Hospital,
Reserve Road,
St Leonards,
NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>+61294631470</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Rachel.McGrath@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>