<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82620">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/02/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/02/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000103369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Spontaneous versus spontaneous timed mode of assisted ventilation in patients with chest wall disease and stable neuromuscular disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Spontaneous versus spontaneous timed mode of assisted ventilation in patients with chest wall disease and stable neuromuscular disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neuromuscular disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chest wall disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We aim to compare 2 commonly used modes of ventilation in patients with respiratory failure from either neuromuscular disease or chest wall disease, such as kyphoscoliosis. The first mode is called "spontaneous mode of pressure supported mechanical ventilation"; where the patient would trigger the ventilator totally on his/ her own; and the second is called "spontaneous timed mode of pressure supported mechanical ventilation"; where the ventilator has a set breath rate but also allows him or her to trigger the ventilator as required. The target population are patients with respiratory failure from neuromuscular disease and chest wall disease, who are already on mechanical ventilation usually in one of these 2 modes described. The patients will remain on each mode of ventilation for a period of 2 weeks, which is followed by a sleep study to assess efficacy of ventilation and sleep quality on each mode. They will also fill out a standardised questionnaire asking them, which mode caused any discomfort, and which one they prefered?. A washout period of 2 weeks will follow the initial mode when the participants will go back on their original ventilator.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a crossover study with the patients acting as their own control, comparing the 2 modes of ventilation together.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correction of hypoventilation measured as the difference between evening (pre-ventilation) and morning (post-ventilation) PaCO2, and by trends in transcutaneous CO2 measurement across the whole of sleep, and during raid eye movement (REM) sleep periods.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed after 14 days of ventilation on each mode</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep quality as assessed by the number of events overnight [arousals and apnea hypopnea index (AHI)] and sleep efficiency</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed after 14 days of ventilation on each mode</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Degree of desaturaion as assessed by the total sleep time below 90% and lower. Also the lowest value of desaturation during Non-Rapid Eye Movement sleep (NREM) and Rapid Eye movement sleep (REM).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed after 14 days of ventilation on each mode</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient preference for mode of ventilation according to a standardised questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed after 14 days of ventilation on each mode</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient?s perception of sleep quality according to a standardised questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed after 14 days of ventilation on each mode</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Under-triggering or over-triggering as assessed from the sleep study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed after 14 days of ventilation on each mode</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Patients with chest wall disease such as kyphoscoliosis or stable neuromuscular disease will be eligible
- Patients have evidence of hypoventilation (defined as day time PaCO2 of &gt; 45 mmHg) at the time of initiation of ventilatory support.
- Patients are already on nocturnal assisted ventilation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Patients aged less than 18 years of age
- Patients with Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)
- Patients with progressive neuromuscular disease such as motor neurone disease
- Patients with a tracheostomy in situ
- Patients in whom we are unable to obtain informed consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Once patient eligibility is established, subjects will be sent a Patient Information and Consent Form (PICF). An appointment will be made to gain informed consent prior to enrolment. The patients will be randomly allocated either treatment A or B according to a computer generated program. Neither the researchers nor the patients will know which mode of ventilation does A or B represent. Only one unblinded staff member will have access to the computer generated list, which will be kept in a sealed opaque envelope. The same unblinded staff member will also set the blinded patient onto the treatment allocated. The scientist scoring the study as well as the researchers analysing the sleep study data will remain blinded.</concealment>
    <sequence>The patients will be randomly allocated either treatment A or B according to a computer generated program.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3084</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Institute for Breathing And Sleep</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Austin Health
Studley Rd, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Institute for Breathing And Sleep</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Austin Health
Studley Rd, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study aims to compare 2 commonly used modes of ventilation in patients with respiratory failure from neuromuscular disease or chest wall disease such as kyphoscoliosis. The study population will be patients already on mechanical ventilation to assist their breathing. As there is no current evidence that one treatment is better than the other, we wish to study the 2 ventilation modes in a crossover design (i.e. one treatment will be followed by the other on each patient) with regards to efficacy of ventilation and sleep quality on each mode. The study hypothesis is that there is no difference between the 2 modes (called the null hypothesis). The study will then attempt to prove whether this is true (i.e. accept the null hypothesis meaning that there is no difference), or false (i.e. reject the null hypothesis meaning that there is a difference between the 2 modes ). The study will help in the long term to determine which mode is more efficacious and comfortable to the patients with neuromuscular or chest wall disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Studley Rd, Heidelberg, Vic, 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/02/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Murad Ibrahim</name>
      <address>Austin Health
Studley Rd, Heidelberg, VIC, 3084</address>
      <phone>03 94965000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>muradibrahim@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Murad Ibrahim</name>
      <address>Austin Health
Studley Rd, Heidelberg, VIC, 3084</address>
      <phone>03 94965000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>muradibrahim@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Murad Ibrahim</name>
      <address>Austin Health
Studley Rd, Heidelberg, VIC, 3084</address>
      <phone>03 94965000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>muradibrahim@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>