<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362788">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000833864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing outcomes of oral versus intravenous antibiotic therapy for the treatment of the diabetic foot wound complicated by osteomyelitis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open-label randomised pilot trial comparing outcomes of oral versus intravenous antibiotic therapy for the treatment of the diabetic foot wound complicated by osteomyelitis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetic foot osteomyelitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two clinical management strategies. These are:
Comparator treatment: Prolonged intravenous (IV) antibiotic strategy (that is, 6 weeks of intravenous antibiotics) and
Intervention: Early oral antibiotic strategy (that is, early commencement of oral antibiotic therapy for a duration of 6 weeks, following less than two weeks of initial treatment with intravenous antibiotics).
The type of antibiotic and dose (below doses are according to normal renal function) will be determined on a case-by-case basis at the discretion of the treating team. A standardised approach to treat diabetic foot osteomyelitis (using drugs, listed below, with already proven efficacy for this condition) will be followed for participants in both groups. This approach takes into account patient co-morbidities, drug allergies, and microbiology results, such as pathogen susceptibility to specific antimicrobial drugs.
The oral antibiotics may include: 
- Clindamycin (450mg orally every 6- 8 hours) PLUS ciprofloxacin (450mg orally every 6-8 hours), 
- Co-trimoxazole (Trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole; 160/800mg x 2 8 hourly to every 12 hours) PLUS metronidazole (400mg orally every 8 hours), 
- Rifampicin (300mg orally every 12 hours [or 600mg orally daily]) PLUS fusidic acid (500mg orally every 8-12 hours) PLUS ciprofloxacin (450mg orally every 6-8 hours).

Participants in both groups will continue to receive usual standard care, which may include pressure offloading, wound dressings, revascularisation, and non-surgical sharps debridement.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator group is the prolonged intravenous (IV) antibiotic strategy for 6 weeks.
The type of antibiotic and dose (below doses are according to normal renal function and administered intravenously) will be determined on a case-by-case basis at the discretion of the treating team. The antibiotics may include: 
- Vancomycin (initial starting dose: 1.5g every 12 hours), 
- Piperacillin/tazobactam (4.5 g every 6 hours or 18g daily over 24 hour continuous infusion), 
- Ertapenem (1g daily), 
- Meropenem (1g three times per day or 3g over 24 hour continuous infusion), 
- Teicoplanin (initial starting dose of 12mg/kg (800mg) 12 hourly for three doses then maintenance 12mg/kg (800mg)  daily).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resolution of osteomyelitis as evaluated by the absence of infection and the infection severity grading following examination of clinical signs and symptoms. 
Criteria for determining presence of infection will be based on the current recommendations from the Infectious Diseases Society of America and the current consensus document from the International Working Group on the Diabetic Foot.
Grading of infection severity is based on Infectious Diseases Society of America - International Working Group on the Diabetic Foot validated criteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks post treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resolution of osteomyelitis as evaluated by plain X-ray</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks post treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent reduction in wound size</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 1 - 6 (treatment period), Week 10 (4 weeks post treatment), Week 14 (8 weeks post treatment) and Week 18 (12 weeks post treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The clinical utility of using the EuroQol 5D (EQ-5D) for quality of life assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week 4, Week 18 (12 weeks post treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reaching 30 minimum number of participants in a 6 month period</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored continuously throughout the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Completion of study in at least 90% of all recruited participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored continuously throughout the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analysis of costs of oral antibiotic therapy compared to costs of intravenous therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>At completion of study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>18 years or older; currently treated patient at Southern Health; Diagnosis of Type I or Type II diabetes mellitus; Diabetic foot osteomyelitis confirmed on MRI, Plain X-ray and clinical signs and symptoms; adequate macrovascular blood supply; adequate debridement of infected tissue; known pathogen(s); suitable for oral and intravenous antibiotic therapy; two weeks or less of IV antibiotic therapy for diabetic foot osteomyelitis at baseline.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Females that are pregnant or breastfeeding; sepsis at presentation; positive blood culture within 14 days of presentation; inadequate macrovascular supply; amputation of infected limb planned/performed; pathogen unknown; known pathogens resistant to appropriate oral and/or IV antibiotics included in treatement strategy; more than 14 days of IV antibiotic therapy prior to baseline; allergy or other absolute contraindication to the oral and/or IV antibiotics listed in treatment strategy; implant or prosthetic device in infected limb; has another condition that requires treatment with antibiotics for greater than one week prior to baseline.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be identified by their treating team. These patients will be approached about the study and provided with a Participant Information and Consent form if they are interested. If they are agreeable to participating, participants will be allocated the next available  study number by the research coordinator. This number will correspond with a sealed opaque envelope containing one of two clinical management strategies (oral or IV). This is an open-label study, therefore once the treatment group has been assigned, the participant, their treating team and the researchers will be aware of the treatment group.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by a computer program. This will be conducted by an individual who is not directly involved in this research project. Once a participant is enrolled in the study, they will be assigned the next available study number. The study numbers will be randomly assigned to a treatment group that will be recorded in sealed opaque envelopes labelled with the corresponding study number.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Southern Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton VIC 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Southern Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Diabetes Department
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton VIC 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Novo Nordisk Pharmaceutical Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Novo Nordisk Regional Diabetes Support Scheme
Level 3, 21 Solent Circuit
Baulkham Hills
NSW 2153</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This pilot study aims to evaluate the feasibility of the methods and procedures used in order to guide a larger open-label randomised trial. In addition, this pilot study will examine the primary outcome measures and the ability to recruit 50 participants in a 6-month period. This study will also involve a cost analysis to compare the cost attributed to both groups. 
The study aims to measure and compare clinical outcomes for two clinical management strategies for the treatment of diabetic foot osteomyelitis, these are a) prolonged IV treatment and b) early commencement of oral antibiotic therapy (following a brief initial treatment with IV antibiotics); and to compare  the quality of life of participants receiving prolonged treatment with an oral antibiotic strategy and those receiving prolonged treatment with an intravenous antibiotic strategy.
Data regarding the infection (presence or absence and infection severity), the wound size and the participants quality of life will be collected at various time-points. There will also be three follow up visit at 4 weeks, 8 weeks and 12 weeks post cessation of antibiotic treatment, which will evaluate the infection (presence or absence and infection severity grade) and the wound size. Whilst an additional plain X-ray will be performed at 4 weeks post cessation of treatment in order to determine if the infection has resolved.
The tentative hypothesis for the pilot study is that a treatment strategy of predominantly oral antibiotics with high oral bioavailability and expected high bone concentration will have a success rate equivalent to that of a strategy of six weeks of intravenous antibiotics, but a lower rate of major complications, a lower cost and a better quality of life.
Although this pilot study will not formally test these hypotheses it will enable the researchers to assess the ability of these hypotheses to be formally tested in a future definitive randomised controlled trial.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Directorate
Southern Health
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12018A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jennifer Wong</name>
      <address>Dandenong Diabetes Unit, Southern Health
Dandenong Hospital
Level 2, 105 David Street
Dandenong VIC 3175</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9554 1550</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9554 1544</fax>
      <email>jennifer.wong@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jennifer Wong</name>
      <address>Dandenong Diabetes Unit, Southern Health
Dandenong Hospital
Level 2, 105 David Street
Dandenong VIC 3175</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9554 1550</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9554 1544</fax>
      <email>jennifer.wong@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jennifer Wong</name>
      <address>Dandenong Diabetes Unit, Southern Health
Dandenong Hospital
Level 2, 105 David Street
Dandenong VIC 3175</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9554 1550</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9554 1544</fax>
      <email>jennifer.wong@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>