<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371087">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001050448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of probiotics and/or intermittent fasting to improve prediabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>PRObiotics and intermittent FASTing to improve prediabetes (PROFAST) study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1185-3564</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PROFAST</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>prediabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1.	Daily probiotic capsule (containing Lactobacillus rhamnosus HN001, at a dose of 6x10^9cfu) for 1 year plus usual healthy diet (according to standard dietary guidelines) for 1 year
2.	Daily probiotic capsule (containing Lactobacillus rhamnosus HN001, at a dose of 6x10^9cfu) for 1 year plus intermittent fasting (2 out of 7 days) when 600kcal/day is consumed by women and 650kcal/day is consumed by men, for 1 year
3.	Daily placebo capsule (containing corn-derived maltodextrin with identical appearance and similar smell to the probiotic capsule) for 1 year plus intermittent fasting (2 out of 7 days) when 600kcal/day is consumed by women and 650kcal/day is consumed by men, for 1 year
4.	Placebo capsule (containing corn-derived maltodextrin with identical appearance and similar smell to the probiotic capsule) for 1 year plus usual healthy diet (according to standard dietary guidelines) for 1 year

Strategies to monitor adherence with daily capsules will be empty capsule packet return and self-reported adherence.
Strategies to monitor adherence with diet will be food diary and reported adherence
Guidance on intermittent fasting will include 4 x 1 hour duration group/individual sessions with a dietitian for tailored IF advice (at baseline, 2, 4 and 8 weeks), and resource list with written material, choice of apps, books and invited, closed social networking site for intermittent fasting study group members moderated by a dietitian. Participants will self-select individual or group sessions.  The intermittent fasting days will be selected by the participants as either consecutive or non-consecutive days. No specific instruction for the 5 non-fasting days will be given other than usual healthy diet pamphlet and recommendations regarding physical activity will be provided to both dietary groups. 
Guidance on usual health diet will include only a usual health diet pamphlet. No specific contact with a dietitian or additional resources will be provided.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo capsule (containing corn-derived maltodextrin with identical appearance and similar smell to the probiotic capsule)
Routine dietary advice (as per NZ Ministry of Health Eating and Activity Guidelines) and pamphlet (diabetes prevention brochure by Auckland DHB &amp; Diabetes Projects Trust, available on www.pt.org.nz/upload/pdfs/ENG_diabetes_prevent.pdf)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in HbA1c from baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months and 1 year</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in weight (measured by digital scales)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 3 months and at 1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in well being scores using SF12</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months and 1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>metabolic syndrome components (blood pressure measured by sphygmomanometry, lipids measured by Roche Diagnosticc cobas analyser) from baseline</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 3 months and at 1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>composite secondary outcome of any change in liver and pancreatic fat content on MRI/MRS</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 3 months and at 1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite secondary outcome of change in gut hormones and inflammatory markers (active GLP-1, total GIP, active ghrelin, glucagon, pancreatic polypeptide, leptin, Il-6, MCP-1, TNF-alpha, using Luminex magnetic bead technology of plasma samples)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 3 months and 1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite secondary outcome of alteration in insulin sensitivity and OGTT derived measures of beta cell function
Insulin sensitivity is assessed using HOMA-S
OGTT derived measures of beta cell function uses insulinogenic index (insulin[30min]-insulin[0min])/([glucose[30min]-glucose[0min], and disposition index as product of 1/(fasting insulin x IGI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 3 months and at 1 year</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Prediabetes defined by HbA1c 41-49 mmol/mol inclusive
BMI of 30-40 (or 27-40 if Asian Indian ethnicity)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous bariatric surgery, BMI &gt;40kg/m2, on glucose lowering medications, conditions that might influence body weight regulation (eg: malabsorption, thyroid disorders, eating disorders, use of systemic steroids, excess alcohol intake (&gt;21 units per week in men, &gt;14 units per week in women), stable body weight in previous 6 months, planned major changes in physical activity during the study to an extent that might interfere with the study outcome, blood donation withthin past 2 months prior to the study (and at the endpoints), adults with a weight change of &gt;3kg within 3 months prior to first baseline visit, psychiatric disease, pregnant women or lactating, or intending to become pregnant within the study duration, significant renal disease (GFR&lt;30), congestive heart failure, unexplained syncope, recent myocardial infarction or stroke within 6 months, porphyria, thalassemia (or other blood disorders in which HbA1c is inaccurate for glycemia), splenectomy, participation in other clinical studies within the previous 6 months, not accepting of 5:2 intermittent fasting or probiotic supplementation.  For the MRI studies, those with any implanted metal or electornic devices will not be able to take part.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>allocation concealment will be ensured by central randomisation schedule by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>web-based protocol, with random number codes</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To allow for 10% loss to follow up, we will recruit 560 participants with prediabetes. A total sample size of 504 people with prediabetes (126 per arm), provides 90% power to detect a minimum effect size of 2.5mmol/mol difference in HbA1c in one of the 3 intervention strategies: arms (1), (2) or (3), relative to control arm (4), using the Dunnett (with control) multiple comparison test at a 5% significance level (PASS 13, version 13.0.4).  The standard deviation for change in HbA1c is assumed to be 4mmol/mol as reported in other prediabetes nutritional intervention studies. The effect size of 2.5mmol/mol has been chosen to be the minimum clinically significant reduction in HbA1c among patients selected to have prediabetes.  This sample size will also have 90% power to detect an interaction effect of 2.3mmol/mol between intermittent fasting and probiotic.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>7/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>560</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>7/12/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142, New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>HRC, Level 3, 110 Stanley St, Grafton, Auckland 1010, NZ</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Preventing the progression from prediabetes to Type 2 Diabetes (T2D) is a health priority for New Zealand.   We wish to test the effectiveness of two promising, simple interventions on reducing progression of prediabetes: a daily probiotic supplement and intermittent fasting.  

Lactobacillus rhamnosus HN001 probiotic (6x109 cfu dose) has been shown to reduce the incidence of gestational diabetes, so may also prevent progression of prediabetes. The benefits of daily caloric restriction on reducing the risk of T2D are well-known, but this strategy is difficult to sustain.  There is some evidence that the benefits of intermittent fasting may be similar, but with greater adherence and acceptability than continuous caloric restriction. Given both of these approaches target the gut microbiota, there is a possibility of synergistic effects through altered pancreatic and liver fat deposition.

The aim of the overall project is to determine whether daily supplementation with a capsule containing L. rhamnosus HN001 or intermittent 5:2 fasting or the combination will reduce  progression of prediabetes. 

We are proposing a one-year, clinical trial among 560 people with prediabetes who will be randomised to either (1) intermittent fasting (reducing calories to 600kcal/day for women and 650kcal/day for men, on 2 days of every week) + daily probiotic capsule (2) intermittent fasting + daily placebo (3) daily healthy eating efforts + daily probiotic (4) daily healthy eating efforts + daily placebo (control).  The primary outcome of this study is HbA1c at 1 year.  Key secondary outcomes include change in body weight, body composition (fat partitioning), fasting glucose and fats. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rinki Murphy</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland
Private Bage 92019
Auckland 1142
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+649,9,9236313</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>R.Murphy@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rinki Murphy</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland
Private Bage 92019
Auckland 1142
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+649,9,9236313</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>R.Murphy@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rinki Murphy</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland
Private Bage 92019
Auckland 1142
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+649,9,9236313</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>R.Murphy@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>