<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="491">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000543684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of prophylactic probiotic lactobacilli in enteral feeding on nosocomiial pneumonia rates in critically ill patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of prophylactic probiotic lactobacilli in enteral feeding on nosocomiial pneumonia rates in critically ill patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Nosocomial pneumonia rates in critically ill patients.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients are randomised to one of three treatment groups, each comprising 100 patients:1. Standard therapy patients will receive enteral feeding (with fibre) aiming for the target rate determined by the treating clinician and the ICU dietician, as is current standard practice. Two capsules containing placebo will be given via the feeding tube twelve hourly as per active treatment group.2. The first active treatment group will receive enteral feeding (with fibre) plus probiotic Lactobacillus fermentumincluded in the feeding regimen.  2 capsules containing Lactobacilli fermentum (1011 organisms per capsule) will be delivered via the feeding tube twelve hourly.  3. The second active treatment group will receive enteral feeding (with fibre) plus probiotic Lactobacillus acidophilus included in the feeding regimen.  2 capsules containing Lactobacilli acidophilus (2 x 109 organisms per capsule) will be delivered via the feeding tube twelve hourly.Enteral feeding volume will aim for the target rate determined by the treating clinician and the ICU dietician, as is current standard practice. Patients will receive study lactobacillus/placebo until enteral feeding is ceased or for a maximum time period of 14 days.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if enteral feeds plus probiotic Lactobacilli are associated with a reduced rate of nosocomial pneumonia in critically ill patients during ICU stay.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the incidence of complications of enteral feeding with and without added probiotic Lactobacilli.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess if the efficacy of enteral feeding in critically ill patients during their ICU stay is improved by the addition of probiotic Lactobacilli.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.Adult patient admitted to the ICU with an expected stay of more than 48 h.2.Patients who are to be commenced on enteral feeding via gastric or post-pyloric routes.3.Patients who consent or if the patient is incompetent, the next-of-kin who consent, to inclusion in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Patients aged less than 18 years.2.Patients who are already receiving probiotic treatment.3.The Lactobacillus acidophilus preparation to be used in this study contains a very small amount of MSG (total dose 20 mg/day, equivalent to 10% of the initial dose used to test for MSG sensitivity) and as a precaution, patients with asthma or recurrent urticaria will be excluded.4.Patients with a known sensitivity to MSG will be excluded.5.Patients with HIV infection, pre-existing immunosuppression, or who are pregnant.  As the Lactobacillus preparation contains live micro-organisms, immunosuppressed and pregnant patients will be excluded.6.Patients with a contra-indication to enteral feeding.7.Patients with a contra-indication to placement of an enteral feeding tube.8.Patients or next-of-kin who do not consent to inclusion in the study.9.Patients who are already enrolled in another study that may influence the outcome of the probiotic study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>sequentially numbered opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated randomisation matrix.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/08/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Intensive Care, Royal Melbourne Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Intensive care departmental Funds, Royal Melbourne Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Melbourne Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Belinda Howe</name>
      <address>Intensive Care Unit
Royal Melbourne
Grattan Street
Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93427710</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93428812</fax>
      <email>belinda.howe@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof cade</name>
      <address>Intensive Care Unit
Royal Melbourne Hospital
Grattan Street
Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93427710</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93428812</fax>
      <email>jack.cade@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>