<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373568">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001324303p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing electronic-cigarettes to traditional oral nicotine replacement therapy for smoking cessation among low-socioeconomic status smokers: a randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparing electronic-cigarettes to traditional oral nicotine replacement therapy for smoking cessation among low-socioeconomic status smokers: a randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1201-4903 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Smoking</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>E-cigarette containing e-liquid nicotine (18mg/ml nicotine) for 12 weeks plus Quitline behavioural support. 
The e-cigarette device used is the Innokin Endura T18 Personal Vaporizer, which has a refill-able 2.5ml tank for the e-liquid. The e-liquid will be provided in 10ml dropper bottles with childproof caps and each will contain nicotine (1.8%), glycerol (82.2%) and purified water (16.0%) . Participants are permitted to use the study product ad libitum throughout the day and encouraged to stop smoking completely, or reduce smoking if unable to stop completely. Participants will be provided with detailed instructions on how to use the e-cigarette device effectively.
Adherence will be monitored via weekly text message surveys and in check-in calls one month and two months into the treatment period. These check in calls will also assess smoking status, short term outcomes, and adverse events at these time points.
The Quitline behavioural support component consists of one to two pre-quit telephone calls to help the person prepare and five post-quit counselling calls: on the quit date, three days, seven days, two weeks and one month after the quit date. Participation in the quitline component will be optional, interested participants will be referred to Quitline, and Quitline will initiate contact.</interventions>
    <comparator>Oral nicotine replacement therapy (NRT) (2mg or 4mg nicotine gum/lozenge) for 12 weeks plus Quitline behavioural support..
For the oral NRT, participants can choose gum or lozenge, and will be allocated to 2mg or 4mg depending on heaviness of smoking:  2  mg  are  suitable  for  smokers  with  a  low  nicotine  dependency  e.g those  smoking  their  first  cigarette  of  the  day  more  than  30  minutes  after  waking up, or those who smoke fewer than 20 cigarettes per day). Those receiving the lozenge will be instructed to use 9-15 lozenges per day, approximately one every 2 hours or when they have an urge to smoke. Those receiving the gum will be instructed to use 10 to 20 pieces per day for the 2mg gum and 4 to 10 pieces per day for the 4mg gum, approximately one every 2 hours or when they have an urge to smoke. Participants will be provided with detailed instructions on how to use the NRT effectively and encouraged to to stop smoking completely, or reduce smoking if unable to stop completely. 
Adherence will be monitored via weekly text message surveys and in check-in calls one month and two months into the treatment period. These check in calls will also assess smoking status, short term outcomes, and adverse events at these time points.
The Quitline behavioural support component consists of one to two pre-quit telephone calls to help the person prepare and five post-quit counselling calls: on the quit date, three days, seven days, two weeks and one month after the quit date. Participation in the quitline component will be optional, interested participants will be referred to Quitline, and Quitline will initiate contact.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Carbon monoxide verified six-month continuous abstinence (smoking not more than five cigarettes) from the quit date</outcome>
      <timepoint>9 month follow-up from baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported 7-day point prevalence abstinence at each follow-up (self-report of having smoked no cigarettes [not even a puff])</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 and 2 month check-in calls and 9 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported continuous abstinence: defined as self-report of smoking not more than five cigarettes from the designated quit date</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 and 2 month check-in calls and 9 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported number of cigarettes smoked per day among continuing smokers</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 and 2 month check-in calls and 9 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported 30-day point prevalence abstinence at each follow-up (self-report of having smoked no cigarettes [not even a puff])</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 and 2 month check-in calls and 9 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean reduction in number of cigarettes smoked per day based on participant self-report </outcome>
      <timepoint>1 and 2 month check-in calls and 9 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants that achieved a 50% reduction of baseline cigarette consumption based on participant self-report </outcome>
      <timepoint>9 month follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported continued use of nicotine products to assess maintenance use and dual use</outcome>
      <timepoint>9 month follow-up </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be at least 18 years of age; current daily smoker (at least 10 cigarettes daily); motivated and willing to make a quit attempt using medications (NRT/e-cigarettes); speak English; able to provide verbal informed consent; receipt of government pension or allowance (proxy for low-SES); own/access to a mobile phone; access to internet; and willing to complete baseline and follow-up telephone interviews. The term current smoker in this trial will refer to those who use either factory-made or roll-own cigarettes. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women who are pregnant, breastfeeding or planning to become pregnant in the next 12 months will be excluded from this trial, as will current users of smoking cessation medications (i.e., NRT, buproprion [Zyban], clonidine, nortriptyline, electronic nicotine cigarettes ), or those who are participating in another smoking cessation program or study. People will also be excluded if they report any of the following medical conditions in the previous three months: serious chronic lung diseases, arrhythmia, heart attack, stroke, or severe angina.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be completed by an external contract research organisation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Immediately after baseline data collection, all eligible participants will be randomised (block randomisation with unequal block sizes of 12 and 16) to either of the treatment arms in 1:1 ratio.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The trial will be single-blinded. The person collecting outcome data and the trial statistician will be blinded until database is locked and the primary analysis completed. The participants and the administrative staff who perform day to day activities cannot be blinded due to the nature of the study and dissimilarities between treatment arms (i.e. treatment type and dosage form).  </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>868</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>UNSW Sydney, NSW 2052
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NA</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a parallel, single-blinded, randomised clinical trial evaluating the effectiveness and cost-effectiveness of 12 weeks of treatment with electronic cigarettes and liquid nicotine compared to traditional oral nicotine replacement therapy (NRT; gum or lozenge), in addition to standard Quitline treatment for smoking cessation among low-socioeconomic smokers. We hypothesize a higher 6-month cessation rate among the electronic cigarette group, compared with the NRT group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UNSW HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW Research Ethics &amp; Compliance Support

The University of New South Wales

Sydney NSW 2052 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/09/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard P Mattick</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
The University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052 Australia</address>
      <phone>+612 93850333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.mattick@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alexandra Aiken</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
The University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052 Australia</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 0111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.aiken@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alexandra Aiken</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
The University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052 Australia</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 0111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.aiken@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alexandra Aiken</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
The University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052 Australia</address>
      <phone>+612 93850111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.aiken@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>