<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369576">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001252505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The clinical and cost effectiveness of shoe inserts in people with established rheumatoid arthritis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The clinical and cost-effectiveness of foot orthoses in people with established rheumatoid arthritis: an exploratory trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym>None</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>rheumatoid arthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Rheumatoid arthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Two foot orthoses were prescribed over 16 weeks and included: (1) Custom-made foot orthoses and (2) simple insoles. The custom-made foot orthoses were manufactured from high density ethyl vinyl acetate, with a thickness of 20mm and a shore density of 50, a contoured medial arch, high heel cup and external medial posting correction customised to each patient according to the amount of valgus rearfoot deformity present and maximum forefoot balancing technique, determined by the external manufacturer providing the interventions (Langer Biomechanics Group, Cheadle, UK). All foot orthoses were covered with 1.6mm cushioning material extending the length of the foot. The simple insoles were a simple 6mm cushioning insole made from a breathable foam core on a rubber-silicone-ethylene compound, cut to fit the exact shape of the participants footwear. Both interventions were the same top colour.

Each participant was asked to wear the foot orthoses or simple insole as frequently as possible. Each participant completed a diary with the number of hours worn during the week and any adverse events.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants were randomly allocated to receive either custom-made foot orthoses in the intervention group, or SIs in the control group. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Foot Pain.  Foot pain was measured using the Foot Function Index. The Foot function Index is a self-administered questionnaire consisting of 23-items grouped in three domains: foot pain (nine items), disability (nine items) and functional limitation (five items). Higher scores indicate greater pain, disability and limitation of activity and thus poorer foot health. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 16 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We estimated the effects on health related quality of life (utilities) of the intervention and the control and undertook a cost-utility analysis using QALYs as the measure of effect.  We estimated participant utilities by administering the EQ5D instrument at baseline and 16 weeks; combined them with the area under the curve method to calculate QALY gains over the 16 week study period; and corrected for baseline EQ5D.  We estimated the cost per QALY gain by dividing differences in cost by differences in QALYs and compared by the thresholds recommended by NICE </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 16 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Foot impairment. Foot impairment was used using the Foot Function Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 16 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants were eligible if they were over 18 years old, history of foot pain, ability to walk a required distance of 5 metres for measurement of foot function and had a diagnosis of RA according to the American Rheumatism Association revised criteria. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants with a history of previous foot surgery or ulceration, those with an unstable medical regime or in a state of flare, currently using foot orthoses or unwilling to change their footwear to accommodate an orthotic, or with poor language ability or inability to understand the research protocol were excluded</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Simple random allocation was used. A plan for allocating to either intervention or control groups was independently generated using randomisation software available from St George’s Hospital Medical School website, http://www.sgul.ac.uk/depts/chs/chs_research/stat_guide/guide.cfm. 

Participants were recruited by the primary researcher and once baseline data had been collected the primary researcher contacted the independent investigator for group allocation. Participants were blinded to the intervention.</concealment>
    <sequence>A plan for allocating to either experimental or control groups was generated by one supervisor using randomisation software available from  St George’s Hospital Medical School website, http://www.sgul.ac.uk/depts/chs/chs_research/stat_guide/guide.cfm (accessed January 2006).  The software applied was ‘Randomisation.com’.  </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We analysed data in SPSS version 22.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago II, USA) and MS Excel 2010 (Microsoft Corporation, Redmond, Washington DC, USA). Results were reported according to the CONSORT statement. All descriptive data and health status measurements were obtained at baseline and 16 weeks. All participant data was included in the final data analysis to ensure continuity of balance in both arms of the trial to reduce bias. All data was subjected to tests for accuracy and quality before analysis was undertaken. Normalcy tests were also undertaken to ensure the data was normally. No transformation of data was undertaken.  Differences between the two groups were determined by analysis of covariance (ANCOVA), to assess the impact of the two different FOs interventions on participants scores across the time periods of the trial. Where appropriate, as when dealing with categorical data, non-parametric tests such as Mann Whitney U tests were used. R (R-Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria) and Statistical Analysis Software (SAS Institute Inc) using the sub-heading Proc Mixed for the ANCOVA. Differences between and within groups were presented as mean differences and 90% confidence intervals (CI). This has been recommended as an appropriate confidence level and also as a way of discouraging reinterpretation of the CI as significant or non-significant at the 5% level.  

Because of the small numbers of participants in our trial we performed boot-strapped t-tests to estimate the differences between utilities at each of the three time points and report means and standard deviations of the boot-strapped samples. To estimate effects on quality-adjusted life years (QALYS), we performed a linear regression with QALY gain as the dependent variable with treatment group and baseline utility as independent variables. To quantify the uncertainty around the estimated incremental cost effectiveness ratio, we ran a simulation of 1000 non-parametric bootstrapped iterations using R to generate a cost-effectiveness plane and a cost utility acceptability curve. The cost effectiveness plane shows the joint distribution of incremental costs and effects. The cost effectiveness acceptability curve using a net benefit technique also shows the probability that an intervention is more cost-effective than the alternative across a range of threshold values of willingness to pay for a QALY.  The level of statistical significance was set at 0.05.

Sample Size: For a large effect size (d) of 0.8, it was calculated that the trial would require 20 or 28 participants per group (40 or 56 in total) to detect group differences with 80% and 90% power respectively.  For a smaller effect size (d) of 0.5, it was calculated that the trial would require 51 or 70 participants per group to have 80% and 90% power. Over the one year recruitment period a total of 41 patients were recruited to the trial. From the above calculations this was estimated to be sufficient to have 80% power to detect a large effect size.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>10/06/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>10/09/2007</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>52</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>41</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Teesside</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Health and Social Care Institute
School of Health and Social Care
Teesside University
Middlesbrough
TS1 3BA
UK</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United Kingdom</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Arthritis Research UK</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Arthritis Research UK
 Copeman House
 St Mary's Gate
 Chesterfield
 Derbyshire
 S41 7TD
 United Kingdom</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor John Dixon</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Health and Social Care Institute
School of Health and Social Care
Teesside University
Middlesbrough
TS1 3BA
UK</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United Kingdom</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Joanna Gray</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Healthcare, 
Faculty of Health and Life Science, 
Northumbria University,
Newcastle, NE7 7AX. UK</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United Kingdom</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Heidi Clark</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>South Tees Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust
Podiatry Department
Marton Road
Middlesbrough
TS1 3QY, UK</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United Kingdom</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Peter McMeeken</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Healthcare, 
Faculty of Health and Life Science, 
Northumbria University,
Newcastle, NE7 7AX. UK</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United Kingdom</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Michael Plant</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>South Tees Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust
James Cook University Hospital
Rheumatology Department
Marton Road
Middlesbrough
TS1 3QY, UK
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United Kingdom</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: 
Foot orthoses are commonly prescribed by health care professionals as an intervention for people with rheumatoid arthritis. The aim of the study was to evaluate the clinical and cost effectiveness of foot orthoses in people with established rheumatoid arthritis.
Methodology: 
A single-blind randomised controlled trial was undertaken to compare a customised foot orthoses and a simple insole in 41 people with established rheumatoid arthritis. The Foot Function Index measured foot pain, disability and functional limitation. Costs were estimated from the perspective of the NHS and from the societal (patient and family) perspective to include costs from outside the NHS.  Effects were assessed in terms of health gain expressed as quality adjusted life years (QALYS).
Results: 
At baseline, 20 participants received the customised foot orthoses and 21 participants received a simple insole. At 16 weeks, (n = 15) 75% participants in the customised foot orthoses group and (n= 14) 66% participants in the simple insole group completed the study. Pain scores improved significantly in both groups (p&lt;0.05). Custom-made foot orthoses significantly improved disability scores (p&lt;0.000) but not for the SI group (p=0.40). The cost effectiveness results demonstrated no difference in cost between the groups (custom-made foot orthoses: £159.10; simple insole: £79.10 p=0.35), with the customised foot orthoses being less effective in terms of cost per QALY gain (p&lt;0.001). 
Conclusion: 
In people with established RA, semi-rigid customised foot orthoses can improve pain and disability scores in comparison to simple insoles. From a cost effectiveness analysis perspective the customised foot orthoses were far more expensive to manufacture, with no significant cost per QALY gain. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>NA</trialwebsite>
    <publication>NA</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Tees NHS Trust and School of Health Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>South Tees NHS Trust and School of Health Research Ethics Committee, 
School of Health and Social Care
Teesside University
Middlesbrough
TS1 3BA
UK</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/03/2003</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>02/03/61: A study to evaluate the cost-effectiveness, functional ability and quality of life of foot orthoses in rheumatoid arthritic patients</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/02/2003</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>United Kingdom</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Keith Rome</name>
      <address>AUT University
90 Akoranga Drive, 
AA Building, 
Northcote 0627, 
Auckland 

</address>
      <phone>0064-9-921-9999 ext 7688</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>krome@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Keith Rome</name>
      <address>AUT University
90 Akoranga Drive, 
AA Building, 
Northcote 0627, 
Auckland </address>
      <phone>0064-9-921-9999 ext 7688</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>krome@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Keith Rome</name>
      <address>AUT University
90 Akoranga Drive, 
AA Building, 
Northcote 0627, 
Auckland </address>
      <phone>0064-9-921-9999 ext 7688</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>krome@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Keith Rome</name>
      <address>AUT University
90 Akoranga Drive, 
AA Building, 
Northcote 0627, 
Auckland </address>
      <phone>0064-9-921-9999 ext 7688</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>krome@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>