<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83106">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/08/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/09/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000490370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Use of the anaesthetic conserving device in the Intensive Care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Use of the anaesthetic conserving device in post operative patients requiring ventilation to assess if time to extubation and quantity of intravenous sedation can be reduced</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sedation in post-operative patients in ICU (Intensive Care Unit)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Anaesthetic conserving device 'Anaconda' for sedation in post- operative cardiac patients requiring temporary ventilation.  It is placed between the endotracheal tube and the ventilator tubing. It will be used until the time of extubation, or until 24 hours after commencement.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard sedation with intravenous benzodiazepines and opioids. That is Midazolam at 1-10mg/hr, and morphine at 1-10mg/hr</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to extubation</outcome>
      <timepoint>When extubation occurs or 24 hours post commencement of the AnaConda</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in the amount of intravenous sedation required. This will be compared with non- trial post-operative cardiac patients who will solely receive intravenous agents.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 Hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Troponin levels in both groups will be measured and compared. Troponin is a cardiac enzyme which is released by damaged cardiac muscle into the bloodstream. It is measured by taking a blood test. In this study, troponin levels will be measured immediately post-operatively, and after 24 hours.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-operatively and at 24 hours.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Post operative Coronary Artery Grafting Surgery (CAGS) patients; Patients post prolonged surgery requiring short term ventilaion in ICU</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with history/family history of malignant hyperthermia. Patients with liver failure</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Warwick Butt</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>ICU, Alfred Hospial, Commercial Road, Prahran, VIC 3181</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>A/Prof Warwick Butt</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>ICU, Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road, Prahran, VIC 3181</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients who are post cardiac surgery, and frequently patients after other prolonged surgery require mechanical ventilation in the ICU until they are stable for extubation. The majority of these patients require some sedation, mainly for endotracheal tube tolerance, cough suppression and to allow routine procedures be performed.
Currently , intravenous sedatives are used in our ICU. The use of inhalational agents such as Sevoflurane and Isoflurane in the intensive care setting, has been widely described in the literature. The advantage of these agents are that they are easily titrated to effect, the level of sedation can be easily monitored, and as they are exceted by the lungs, and not by the liver and kidneys, may be more advantageous in patients with hepatic or renal impairment. Furthermore more, they have been shown to have a cardioprotective effect on those post cardiac surgery in particular and reduce the morbidity and mortality in this group. 
In our study, we will enrol 10 patients post CABG surgery to receive Isoflurane via the Anaesthetic Conserving Device (AnaConDa) until the time of extubation. We believe that the time to extubation following cessation of sedation will be shorter compared to those receiving intravenous sedation. We will measure troponin levels, which is a marker of cardiac injury, and compare the levels in those receiving inhalational sedation compared to intravenous sedation. 

Patients cardiac and respiratory status will be carefully monitored in the ICU setting, and their sedation scores measured. We believe we can reduce the amount of intravenous sedation used in this group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/08/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Eilis Condon</name>
      <address>ICU, Alfred Hospial, Commercial Road, Prahran, VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>0390762000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.condon@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Eilis Condon</name>
      <address>ICU, Alfred Hospial, Commercial Road, Prahran, VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>0390762000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>E.condon@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Eilis Condon</name>
      <address>ICU, Alfred Hospial, Commercial Road, Prahran, VIC 3181</address>
      <phone>0390762000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.condon@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>