<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373616">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001331325p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Nasal High Flow Rhinothermy (rNHF) in Influenza</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, open-label, two arm, parallel groups trial of Nasal High Flow rhinothermy (rNHF) therapy, versus daily vitamin C in the treatment of influenza infection</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1200-2912</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>MRINZ 17/04</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Influenza</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>100% humidified air delivered by the rNHF device, via nasal cannulae, at 35L/min at 41 °C for two hours on Day 1, administered under the supervision of investigators at the clinic, and then at home for up to 5 days, depending on resolution of symptoms. 

The participant will be encouraged to use the rNHF device as a single administration for 2 hours in total per day at home during this period. If the participant is unable to use the rNHF device for 2 hours in one session, then it can be used in a second session to achieve the 2 hour period for each day. Participants may reduce the flow to a minimum of 30L/min at home according to comfort.

Adherence to the rNHF device treatments will be assessed by investigator review of the device data, downloaded directly from the device on Day 5. Adherence will be defined as a minimum of 90 minutes use per day, delivered in no more than 2 sessions per day.


</interventions>
    <comparator>Vitamin C 100mg capsule (Healtheries Vit C containing 100mg vitamin C) once per day for 5 consecutive days (Day 1 to Day 5 inclusive) will be used as the control treatment.  

Adherence to Vitamin C tablets will be assessed by study investigators after return of the packaging and any remaining tablets by the participant on Day 5. Adherence will be defined as a minimum of four vitamin C tablets consumed between Day 1 and Day 5, and will be assessed by participant diary information and by tablet count</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the area under the curve (AUC) quantitative PCR influenza log10 viral load (Day 1 to Day 5) between the treatment groups using Quantitative PCR influenza log10 viral load Days 1, 3 and 5 per Canterbury District Health Board; Canterbury Health Laboratories (CDHB: CHL) laboratory testing.   
The influenza viral load is assessed from the nasopharyngeal swabs taken on Days 1, 3 and 5.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 5 </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the composite influenza symptom score adjusted for baseline score, between the treatment groups From Day 1 through to Day 14, using the Composite influenza symptom score as captured by participant daily diary between Day 1 and Day 5 inclusive.

The composite influenza score has previously been utliised in trials of antiviral medication (Nicholson KG, Aoki FY, Osterhaus AD, Trottier S, Carewicz O, Mercier CH, Rose A, Kinnersley N, Ward P. Efficacy and safety of oseltamivir in treatment of acute influenza: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet 2000;355:1845-1850 AND Hayden FG, Treanor JJ, Betts RF, Lobo M, Esinhart JD, Hussey EK. Safety and efficacy of the neuraminidase inhibitor GG167 in experimental human influenza. JAMA.  1996; 275: 295-299. doi:10.1001/jama.1996.03530280047035), and in a previous trial of the use of paracetamol in the treatment of influenza that the MRINZ undertook in 2013/2014 (Jefferies S, Braithwaite I, Walker S, Weatherall M, Jennings L, Luck M, et al. Randomized controlled trial of the effect of regular paracetamol on influenza infection. Respirology. 2016;21(2):3707).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will complete a diary relating to their symptoms for each day of the 14 day trial period. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the number of days until a participant returns to normal activity between the treatment groups, using Date entered in Date you returned to normal activities box in participant daily diary..</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 14</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the number of days until a participant reports they are a little better  between the treatment groups, using Date entered feel a little better,  in box in participant daily diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 14</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the daily mean and maximum temperature (Days 1 to Day 5) between the treatment groups, using tympanic thermometer, and recorded by the  participant daily diary between Day 1 and Day 5.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 5</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the time until resolution of symptoms (daily composite influenza score equal to or less than 1 and remains so for 24 hours), between the treatment groups, using Composite influenza symptom score as captured by participant daily diary between Day 1 and Day 14 inclusive.

The composite influenza score has previously been utliised in trials of antiviral medication (Nicholson KG, Aoki FY, Osterhaus AD, Trottier S, Carewicz O, Mercier CH, Rose A, Kinnersley N, Ward P. Efficacy and safety of oseltamivir in treatment of acute influenza: a randomised controlled trial. Lancet 2000;355:1845-1850 AND Hayden FG, Treanor JJ, Betts RF, Lobo M, Esinhart JD, Hussey EK. Safety and efficacy of the neuraminidase inhibitor GG167 in experimental human influenza. JAMA.  1996; 275: 295-299. doi:10.1001/jama.1996.03530280047035), and in a previous trial of the use of paracetamol in the treatment of influenza that the MRINZ undertook in 2013/2014 (Jefferies S, Braithwaite I, Walker S, Weatherall M, Jennings L, Luck M, et al. Randomized controlled trial of the effect of regular paracetamol on influenza infection. Respirology. 2016;21(2):3707).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 14</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the number of days until a participant reports they are 'a lot better between the treatment groups, using Date entered feel a lot better  in box in participant daily diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 14</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>	Aged 18 to 75 years.
	In the Investigators opinion, is able and willing to comply with all trial requirements.
	Onset of symptoms within the last 48 hours at time of consent. 
Presence of an influenza virus form nasopharyngeal swab using using the Xpert® Xpress Flu/RSV point-of-care test (Cepheid, Ca, USA).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	Immunocompromised condition: Conditions causing immunosuppression e.g. HIV/AIDS, active cancer or Currently prescribed systemic steroids or other immunosuppressant medication
	Nasal conditions such as deviated septum, chronic rhinitis, which the investigator considers could impair nasal breathing
	Current use of or requirement for oral or parenteral antibiotics or steroids. Daily inhaled or intra-nasal steroids will be allowed if part of the participants regular therapy. If not taken prior to enrolment, they should be withheld for the duration of this study.
	The investigator believes the participant or their caregiver will be unable to safely use rNHF without medical supervision.
	Have any other condition which, at the investigators discretion, is believed may present a safety risk or impact the feasibility of the study or the study results.
	Have an implantable medical device.
	Have a notifiable disease
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomised 1:1 to receive one of the treatment arms 
a)	rNHF therapy  (N=70 participants)
b)	Vitamin C tablets (N=70 participants)

A permuted block randomisation method, stratified by duration of illness (lesser or greater than one day), and temperature (less than or greater than 38.5OC) will be used to allocate patients to either regimen. The computer-generated sequence will be supplied by the study statistician, independent of the investigators. The electronic case report form (eCRF) system will conceal the allocations and will release a participant’s randomisation outcome at the time of randomisation. The randomisation schedule will be accessed only by the study statistician and the eCRF provider; other study staff will not have access to the randomisation schedule. </concealment>
    <sequence>A permuted block randomisation method, stratified by duration of illness (lesser than one day, versus greater than or equal to one day), and temperature (less than 38.5 degreesC versus greater than or equal to 38.5 degreesC) will be used to allocate patients to either regimen. 
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The standard deviation (SD) for AUC for quantitative PCR influenza viral load for Days 1 &amp; 5 is between 1.4 and 2.2 log10 units (Nicholson et al. Lancet, 2000:355:1845-1850). An RCT of anti-viral therapy in influenza reports a difference from placebo therapy of 2.2 log10 units (Hayden et al. JAMA: 1996; 275: 295-299). If the effect of rhinothermy is half that of the difference found with anti-viral therapy (1.1 units), and using the mean of the SDs above, if there is a 10% drop out rate, a total sample size of 140, with 70 in each of two treatment arms, has 90% power to detect this difference, with a type I error rate of 5%. Although retention was 100% in our previous common cold pilot RCT, the lower confidence limit was 88%, and so a 10% drop out rate is justified. 

Statistical analysis will be by intention to treat. The primary outcome variable will be analysed by ANOVA with the log PCR as the response variable and the randomised treatment as an explanatory variable. For the continuous secondary variables ANCOVA will be used with the baseline measurements where appropriate as a continuous covariate. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>140</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>18/12/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Fisher and Paykel Healthcare Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>15 Maurice Paykel Place
East Tamaki
Auckland 2013
New Zealand.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Fisher and Paykel Healthcare Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>15 Maurice Paykel Place
East Tamaki
Auckland 2013
New Zealand.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We want to know if breathing in 100 % humidified air at 41 °C through the nose may kill the influenza virus as well as reduce the symptoms and the number of days people remain unwell. Some people will be familiar with steam therapy, like holding ones face over a bowl of steaming hot water with a towel over ones head.

Rhinothermy via Nasal High Flow, or rNHF for short, is a therapy that delivers warmed and humidified air to the nostrils and down to the lungs via nasal prongs. This kind of device has been used for delivering NHF therapy to patients with lung illnesses worldwide in hospitals and at home since 2013. 

The aim of the study is to show whether rNHF changes infectivity of flu patients, changes symptoms (length and severity), reduces the number of days lost to the illness, as well as things like how often people will use rNHF at home.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>New Zealand Health and Disability Ethics Committee (Southern)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
133 Molesworth Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/09/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373616-HDEC_Letter_17-STH-177_expedited_review.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Irene Braithwaite</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand,
 Level 7, Clinical Services Building, 
Wellington Regional Hospital, 
Newtown, 
Wellington 6021, 
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050245</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>irene.braithwaite@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Irene Braithwaite</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand,
 Level 7, Clinical Services Building, 
Wellington Regional Hospital, 
Newtown, 
Wellington 6021, 
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050245</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>irene.braithwaite@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Irene Braithwaite</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand,
 Level 7, Clinical Services Building, 
Wellington Regional Hospital, 
Newtown, 
Wellington 6021, 
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050245</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>irene.braithwaite@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Irene Braithwaite</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand,
 Level 7, Clinical Services Building, 
Wellington Regional Hospital, 
Newtown, 
Wellington 6021, 
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050245</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>irene.braithwaite@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>