<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368891">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000780550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of a sound wave vibration intervention on heart rate and blood pressure. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of a sound wave vibration intervention on heart rate and blood pressure after triggering the sympathetic nervous system in healthy controls, healthy participants with elevated sympathetic activity and participants with early to mild hypertension.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1171-9027</utrn>
    <trialacronym>VIVA-SNS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension mechanisms</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sympathetic Nervous System Activity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Sympara Therapeutic System (STS) device is a non invasive device worn as a necklace across the front of the neck with adherent pads to both clavicles which delivers therapeutic acoustic energy (sound waves). These sound waves are conducted via the clavicle to the nerves in the neck, shoulders, and armpit.  We are investigating whether this device will decrease blood pressure and heart rate.

The acoustic parameters of the sound waves/vibrations are proprietary and therefore amplitude, frequency and modulation are unknown to the investigators. 

The testing protocol consists of the subjects undergoing standardized autonomic reflex testing in order to evaluate the sympathetic and cardiovagal function. All experiments will be conducted in a dimly lit thermoneutral laboratory (22 degree -25 degree Centigrade).  Prior to any testing, subjects will be connected to a 3-lead ECG to monitor HR, a finger blood pressure cuff and a pneumotrace to monitor respiratory movement continuous throughout the testing protocol.  Subjects will perform a Valsalva maneuver, static handgrip test and cold pressor test at baseline (following 10 min of rest in a supine position).  The STS device will then be applied to the subject for approximately 120 minutes, during the last 20 minutes of which the subject will repeat the testing protocol.  The STS device will then be removed and the subject will rest in a supine position for an additional 20 minutes, followed by a final round of the testing protocol.  Between the  testing procedures (approximately 100 minutes) subjects will remain in a relaxed reclined position in the testing room.

Descriptions of the tests are below:
1. Valsalva Maneuver: Subjects will be asked to forcefully exhale with an open glottis into a mouthpiece connected to the mercury column of a sphygmomanometer with an air leak. A 40-50 mmHg pressure is maintained for 15 seconds.
2. Static Handgrip Test: Subjects will be asked to squeeze a hand dynamometer with their maximal force. The highest force attained from three attempts will be considered the subjects maximum voluntary contraction (MVC).  The subjects will perform the static handgrip test by squeezing the hand dynamometer at 30% of MVC in a sustained manner for 3 min. The subject will be instructed to avoid inadvertent Valsalva maneuvers and to maintain normal breathing patterns during this test.
3. Cold Pressor Test:  Subjects will submerge their entire hand (up to the wrist) in ice-cold water for 1 min.  The temperature of the water will be maintained at approximately 01 degrees C. The subject will be instructed to avoid inadvertent Valsalva maneuvers and to maintain normal breathing patterns during this test.

The testing protocol will take approximately four hours to complete.  Subjects will be exited from the study following the completion of the testing protocol. 

The test will be performed in the order Valsalva, Hand grip then cold pressor. In the control group an identical procedure will be employed without the device activated. All testing will be supervised by specific research scientists with medical backup if required. The protocol will be identical in the three specified groups, namely healthy controls, healthy individuals with known elevated sympathetic activity and otherwise healthy individuals with early to mild hypertension.


</interventions>
    <comparator>Sympathetic Testing Protocol that will be conducted during the testing visit:
1.     Valsalva Maneuver 
2. 	Hand Grip Test
3.	Cold Pressor Test

The sham treatment procedure is identical to the active protocol saving that the device is turned off.  Placebo groups will be included in all 3 pre-defined participant groups.

</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in blood pressure by continuous non-invasive monitoring using the commercially available Finapres equipment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to any testing, subjects will undergo baseline assessment.
  
The STS device will be applied to the subject for ~120 minutes, during the last 20 minutes of which the subject will repeat the testing protocol.  The STS device will then be turned off and the subject will rest in a supine position for an additional 20 minutes, followed by a final round of the testing protocol.  
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in heart rate using the commercially available Finapres monitor and from the continuously recorded ECG.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to any testing, subjects will undergo baseline assessment.
  
The STS device will be applied to the subject for ~120 minutes, during the last 20 minutes of which the subject will repeat the testing protocol.  The STS device will then be turned off and the subject will rest in a supine position for an additional 20 minutes, followed by a final round of the testing protocol. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Between the ages of 18 and 50 years
2. Competent and willing to provide written, informed consent to participate in the study

Normal, healthy controls:
1. Free of any comorbidities

Healthy with elevated sympathetic activity:
1. Free of any comorbidities
2. Naturally high resting heart rate 
3. May have previously been diagnosed with an anxiety disorder
 
Early to mild hypertension:
1. Documented diagnosis and treatment of hypertension within the last six months
2. Hypertension controlled by diet and exercise or no more than one anti-hypertensive medication
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Previous renal denervation or carotid barostimulation implant
2. History of a clavicle fracture as an adult (over 18 years)
3. Haemodynamically significant valvular heart disease for which, in the opinion of the Investigator, a significant reduction of BP is contraindicated
4.History of an implanted cardiac (e.g., implantable cardioverter-defibrillator, pacemaker, cardiac resynchronisation therapy) or neurostimulation device
5. History of having undergone any type of cardiac surgery including coronary artery bypass graft and/or valve surgery
6. History of stent grafting
7. Known secondary causes of hypertension or primary pulmonary hypertension
8. Prior surgery or radiation to the area of the carotid sinus, or presence of a stent or other implant in the carotid artery
9. Known or suspected baroreflex failure or significant orthostatic hypotension (one or more episodes in the past year not related to medications.  Defined as reduction in SBP of equal to or more than 20mmHg or diastolic blood pressure (DBP) equal to or more than 10 mmHg within three minutes of standing).
10. One or more hospital admissions for a hypertensive crisis within the past year.  Hypertensive crisis is defined as severely elevated BP [greater than 180/110 mmHg] that is not related to confirmed non-adherence with medications, together with progressive or impending target organ damage, requiring hospitalization and typically admission to the intensive care unit
11. History of a myocardial infarction, unstable angina, or documented multi-vessel coronary artery disease
12. History of syncope, transient ischemic attack and/or cerebral vascular accident within the last 6 months
13. Subject with atrial fibrillation, supraventricular tachycardia, or other documented sustained arrhythmias that required hospitalization within the last 6 months
14. Type 1 diabetes mellitus
15. Chronic renal disease requiring dialysis
16. Kidney or liver transplant
17. Females who are pregnant

</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Three distinct groups of subjects (1. healthy controls, 2. healthy subjects with known elevated sympathetic activity and 3. subjects with early to mild HTN) will undergo a series of in-office tests intended to cause an increase in sympathetic activity (Valsalva maneuver, hand-grip test and cold presser test) with and without the STS device in order to assess the device’s effect on overall sympathetic activity.  

Prospective subjects will complete a screening visit to confirm they meet all of the inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion criteria.  Eligible subjects will then be enroled into the study.  Subjects will then return to complete the testing protocol, which consists of repeating a series of in-office tests at baseline, with the STS device on and following cessation of STS device use.  The length of study participation is approximately four to five hours.  

Allocation to placebo will be via sealed opaque envelopes in the required 1 to 4 ratio pre-prepared for each group held centrally by an independent person.</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will be randomized in a 1:4 ratio to either a sham (i.e. the device does not deliver therapeutic energy) or active STS device.  

Pre-prepared, opaque sealed envelopes will be shuffled by an independent person and drawn at random to allocated active/placebo at time of recruitment. This will be done for each group separately.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This prospective, acute study intends to enroll up to 50 subjects at MonashHeart to determine if acute use of the STS triggers an autonomic-mediated reflex that, in turn, results in a clinically significant reduction in blood pressure and heart rate physiological effect compared to baseline values. This is a pilot study, there is no data available to calculate required sample size. Results at the three measurement points will in the first instance be compared by analysis of variance. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>21/08/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>2</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>246 Clayton Rd
Clayton Victoria 3168
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>246 Clayton Rd
Clayton Victoria 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The hypothesis of this study is that transmitted acoustic energy delivered via the collar bones to the pressure receptors in the neck will modulate the nervous system to reduce blood pressure and heart rate in normal individuals.

The main aim is to investigate the effect of mechanical vibration delivered non-invasively via the collar bones to affect the heart rate and blood pressure. 

Primary Objective: To determine if acute use of the Sympara Therapeutic System (STS) device reduces sympathetic
activity in three distinct subject populations.
A.  Healthy controls
B.  Healthy individuals with elevated sympathetic activity (e.g. anxiety)
C.  Individuals with early to mild hypertension

Study Design: Acute, prospective, study to evaluate the potential mechanism of action for the STS.Participants will be
randomized in a 1:4 ratio to either a sham or active STS device.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>246 Clayton Rd Clayton
Victoria 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15198A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ian Meredith</name>
      <address>MonashHeart 
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd 
Clayton 3168 Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 95942726</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>iam.meredith@myheart.id.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Julie Plunkett</name>
      <address>MonashHeart 
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd 
Clayton 3168 Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 95944597</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julie.plunkett@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>James Cameron</name>
      <address>MonashHeart 
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Rd 
Clayton 3168 Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 95944264</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>james.cameron@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>