<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371930">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001652460p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Protein absorption in critical illness</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To determine if critical illness impairs protein absorption compared to health</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PACE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Critically ill</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Protein absorption</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each subject/patient will be studied on one occasion only. Following consent a small intestinal feeding catheter will be inserted using the Cortrak device by a trained research dietitian or intensive care physician. Patients and healthy subjects will undergo an overnight fast (no food or fluid, including water) from midnight until study commencement. The plasma phenylalanine and leucine pool will primed for 2.5 hours with a single intravenous dose of d5-phenylalanine (2.2 ug/kg), L-[3,5-D2]-tyrosine (0.674 ug/kg) and L-[1-13C]-leucine (0.110 ug/kg), after which a intraduodenal infusion for 1 hour of L-[1-13C]phenylalanine-labelled and L-[1-13C]-leucine casein milk protein will be commenced (25 g, 100 kcal, 1.7 kcal/min). Following this a continuous IV infusion of 5 hours of the tracers d5-phenylalanine (0.055 umol/kg/min), L-[3,5-D2]-tyrosine (0.017 umol/kg/min) and L-[1-13C]-leucine (0.110 umol/kg/min) will be administered. At study completion, healthy subjects will be provided with a buffet meal, and enteral feeds will be recommenced in ICU patients.

Protein infusions will be prepared by the hospital pharmacy department to ensure dosing accuracy and safety precautions.  Administration of infusions will be by trained intensive care research practitioners. </interventions>
    <comparator>This study will recruit 20 healthy control volunteers whom will receive identical treatment to those with critical illness.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate and extent of labelled phenylalanine absorption. This is a composite primary outcome assessed by the rate of appearance and disappearance of phenylalanine from the ingested protein compared with the body stores (i.e. exogenous and endogenous phenylalanine rate of appearance). This is assessed through analysis of tracer levels in the blood samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples taken prior to IV priming dose (-180 min, -60 min and -30 min). Then at time point 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, 240, 300 and 360.

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate and extent of labelled leucine absorption. This is a composite primary outcome assessed by the rate of appearance and disappearance of leucine from the ingested protein compared with the body stores (i.e. exogenous and endogenous leucine rate of appearance). This is assessed through analysis of tracer levels in the blood samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples taken prior to IV priming dose (-180 min, -60 min and -30 min). Then at time point 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, 240, 300 and 360.

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Amino acid concentrations</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to IV priming dose (-180 min, -60 min and -30 min). Then at time point 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, 240, 300 and 360. Plasma amino acids will be determined by stable isotope dilution tandem mass spectrometry.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fractional synthetic rate (FSR) of mixed muscle protein</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to IV priming dose and at the commencement of the 6 hour continuous IV infusion. Measured via muscle biopsy. Muscle biopsies taken at 0 min and 360 min. Local anaesthetic will be injected and using a Bergstrom needle a small muscle biopsy (~55mg) will be collected from the middle region of the vastus lateralis muscle at 0 and 360min.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glucose concentrations. Blood glucose will be determined immediately by the glucose oxidase method, with accuracy confirmed by the hexokinase technique at predefined time points.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to IV priming dose (-180 min, -60 min and -30 min). Then at time point 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, 240, 300 and 360. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glucagon concentrations. Measured from blood samples by radioimmunoassay using commercially available antibodies</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to IV priming dose (-180 min, -60 min and -30 min). Then at time point 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, 240, 300 and 360. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CCK concentrations. Measured from blood samples by radioimmunoassay using commercially available antibodies</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to IV priming dose (-180 min, -60 min and -30 min). Then at time point 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, 240, 300 and 360. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PYY concentrations. Measured from blood samples by radioimmunoassay using commercially available antibodies</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to IV priming dose (-180 min, -60 min and -30 min). Then at time point 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, 240, 300 and 360. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ghrelin concentrations. Measured from blood samples by radioimmunoassay using commercially available antibodies</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to IV priming dose (-180 min, -60 min and -30 min). Then at time point 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, 240, 300 and 360. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>ICU patients:
*Adults (greater than or equal to 18 years of age)
*Admitted to the Royal Adelaide Hospital Intensive Care Unit
*Mechanically ventilated 
*Suitable for enteral feeding
*Arterial line insitu
*Consent obtained

Healthy volunteer arm:
*Adults (greater than or equal to 18 years of age)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>ICU patients:
*Recent upper abdominal surgery
*Vegan
*Lactose intolerance 
*Any order to withhold active treatment
*Jehovahs Witness
*For muscle biopsy: Bleeding diathesis (INR &gt; 1.5; APTT &gt; 50) including those receiving anticoagulants (other than low dose for DVT prophylaxis) and anti-platelet agents 


Healthy volunteer arm:
*Significant illness
*Smokers (cigarettes/cigars/marijuana)
*Intake of &gt;2 standard drinks on &gt;5 days per week
*Intake of &gt;4 cups of caffeinated drinks per day
*Intake of any illicit substance
*Vegan
*Lactose intolerance
*Use of prescribed or non-prescribed medications that may affect gastrointestinal function 
*Significant gastrointestinal symptoms, disease or surgery (apart from uncomplicated appendectomy)
*For muscle biopsy: Bleeding diathesis (INR &gt; 1.5; APTT &gt; 50) including those receiving anticoagulants (other than low dose for DVT prophylaxis) and anti-platelet agents 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, 5000, Adelaide, South Australia, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Committee Project Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, 5000, Adelaide, South Australia, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Single centre exploratory unblinded observational study. Using a unique method that has been developed to label intact proteins rather than amino acids by infusing cows with large quantities of D5-phenylalanine and then collecting their labelled milk. This labelled cow milk can then be administered to humans for research purposes and the metabolic fate of the protein determined. This technique allows the fate of intact protein to be followed from ingestion, through digestion and absorption to muscle deposition. The biological value of the protein can thus be determined i.e. the proportion that becomes incorporated into body tissues, particularly muscle. This is relevant in the critically ill as the protein content of enteral feed formulae is usually presented as a protein such as casein or whey protein. Reduced amino acid absorption has been reported in rats following haemorrhagic shock, in patients with pancreatitis, and in critically ill patients following trauma. However the mechanisms underlying protein malabsorption are not well understood. A more comprehensive understanding of protein absorption during critical illness, and the effect of feeding intolerance on protein uptake will allow the rational development of feeding strategies to improve nutritional outcomes in these patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Marianne Chapman</name>
      <address>Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, 5000, Adelaide, South Australia, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 4624</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marianne.chapman@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lee-anne Chapple</name>
      <address>Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, 5000, Adelaide, South Australia, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 4624</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lee-anne.costello@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lee-anne Chapple</name>
      <address>Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, 5000, Adelaide, South Australia, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 4624</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lee-anne.costello@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lee-anne Chapple</name>
      <address>Royal Adelaide Hospital, North Terrace, 5000, South Australia, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 4624</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lee-anne.costello@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>