<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81725">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/11/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/12/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000498594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of a specific medication or placebo on modulating induced muscle pain</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The pharmacologic modulation of experimentally simulated tennis elbow (lateral epicondylalgia) in healthy controls by administration of a ketamine (generic and specific name) or placebo lozenge: improving our understanding of musculoskeletal pain mechanisms</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Experimentally simulated tennis elbow (lateral epicondylalgia) in healthy controls</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2 />
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Ketamine (25mg sublingual) will be administered prior to an intense bout of eccentric exercise used to induce delayed onset muscle soreness (DOMS) in the wrist extensors of healthy control subjects. Verum and placebo lozenges will look identical to maintain double blinding. Twenty four hours post-exercise, subjects will receive an infusion of hypertonic saline (1.0mls @ 5%) into the extensor carpi radialis brevis muscle. 
Methodology: 1. Induced delayed onset muscle soreness:
The exercise protocol will be performed using the isokinetic mode of the Kin-Com dynamometer (Chattecx Corp. Hixson, TN) as previously described (Slater et al. 2005).                                                                                The total exercise period will be 25 minutes, with 5 bouts each of 5 minutes duration (60 repetitions per bout), with each bout separated by a minute rest interval;                                                                         2. Intramuscular infusion of hypertonic saline: Hypertonic saline will be infused using a computer-controlled pump (IVAC, model 770, USA), with a 10 ml plastic syringe (Graven-Nielsen et al. 1997). A tube (IVAC G30303, extension set with polyethylene inner line) will be connected from the syringe to the disposable needle (27G, 20mm). A bolus injection of 1.0 ml of sterile hypertonic (5.8%) saline will be injected over 40 seconds.
The duration of the total experimental time will therefore be approximately 26 hours with the drug intervention (if active) peaking at 45 minutes after administration. Subjects will partake in one experimental session only and  receive either ketamine or placebo, NOT both.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo will be administered prior to an intense bout of eccentric exercise used to induce delayed onset muscle soreness (DOMS) in the wrist extensors of healthy control subjects. Verum and placebo lozenges will look identical to maintain double blinding. Twenty four hours post-exercise, subjects will receive an infusion of hypertonic saline (1.0mls @ 5%) into the extensor carpi radialis brevis muscle.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           In healthy control subjects, DOMS will be induced with repeated eccentric wrist extension contractions in the non-dominant arm. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quantitative sensory testing battery including: Mechanical pressure pain sensitivity in muscles</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and post exercise at Day 0 and pre, during and post hypertonic saline induced muscle pain at Day 1and 2.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quantitative sensory testing battery including: Pain intensity profile (VAS, onset, duration), and referred pain areas.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During hypertonic saline induced muscle pain at Day 1and 3.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quantitative sensory testing battery including: McGill Pain Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post hypertonic saline induced muscle pain at Day 1 and 4.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quantitative sensory testing battery including: Maximal grip strength and maximal wrist extension force.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and post exercise at Day 0 and at Day 1 pre, during and post hypertonic saline induced muscle pain</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle soreness (modified Likert scale).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre and post exercise at Day 0 and at Day 1 pre, during and post hypertonic saline induced muscle pain.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy controls; comprehensive musculoskeletal physical examination will be performed on both upper limbs to ensure full pain free range of elbow and wrist motion, and no abnormal tenderness to palpation of the soft tissues in the extensor muscles of the forearm and wrist (Haker 1993), or abnormally reduced muscle length. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Involvement of the contralateral arm, cervicothoracic spinal pathology, other upper limb musculoskeletal disorders or neurological disorders.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involves contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is at central administration</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Subjects and assessor (CI) will be blinded. Drug randomisation will be performed independently by Curtin Pharmacy ensuring blinding of allocation. Initial data analysis of will be performed by a research assistant blinded to subject allocation.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/12/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/12/2006</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>20/12/2007</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>22</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Helen Slater</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science, Curtin University, GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Tony Wright</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science, Curtin University, GPO Box U1987, Perth, WA 6845</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Stephan Schug</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Chair of Anaesthesiology,
Pharmacology, Pharmacy and Anaesthesiology Unit,
School of Medicine and Pharmacology, University of Western Australia
Director of Pain Medicine, Royal Perth Hospital
Faculty of Medicine, Dentistry &amp; Health Sciences | The University of Western Australia¦
UWA Anaesthesiology¦Level 2, MRF Building, Royal Perth Hospital, GPO Box X2213, Perth, 6847</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of this study is to quantitatively measure, in healthy controls, the effects of a pharmacologic agent in attenuating experimentally induced responses simulating the clinical characteristics of lateral epicondylalgia (tennis elbow). The primary hypothesis to be tested in this study is: in comparison with a placebo intervention, a pharmacological intervention targeting processes of central sensitisation via blockade of the N-methyl-D-asparate (NMDA) receptor will attenuate the somatosensory and motor effects of experimentally induced pain in healthy control subjects with simulated characteristics of clinical lateral epicondylalgia

Lay version: In the experiment we will investigate what happens to forearm muscle function and pressure pain sensitivity when given a lozenge containing either an active medication or placebo prior to experimentally induced pain in those muscles. These muscles are involved in tennis elbow problems in occupational and sporting settings. 

What does it involve? This experiment will be conducted over two days taking about 1.5 hour per session. At the first session you will be given a lozenge (either placebo or an active drug) 1 hour prior to undertaking an intense bout of eccentric exercise in your non-dominant arm. One day later, a muscle in your exercised arm will be injected with hypertonic saline. This injection may generate a short period of muscle pain. Before and after each session a number of measures will be taken:
1. Pressure pain sensitivity at sites around forearm muscles and tendons using a device to measure mechanical pressure sensitivity (pressure algometer); 2. muscle strength of specific elbow muscles. These measures will also be repeated at Day 1 during the hypertonic saline-induced pain.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Slater H, Graven-Nielsen T, Wright A, Schug SA, Low-Dose Sublingual Ketamine Does Not Modulate Experimentally Induced Mechanical Hyperalgesia in Healthy Subjects, Pain Medicine 2012; 13: 12351246</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>School of Physiotherapy, Curtin University of Technology</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/10/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>107/2006</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>A/Prof Helen Slater</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science, Curtin University, GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92663099</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 92663699</fax>
      <email>h.slater@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>A/prof Helen Slater</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science, Curtin University</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92663099</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 92663699</fax>
      <email>h.slater@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Slater</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science, Curtin University, GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3099</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.slater@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Slater</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science, Curtin University, GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3099</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.slater@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>