<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336205">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/10/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/10/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001061921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Move More for Life: A tailored physical activity program for Australian breast cancer survivors</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Move More for Life Study: Evaluating the efficacy of two theory-based print interventions promoting physical activity adoption and maintenance in Australian breast cancer survivors.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1117-8005</utrn>
    <trialacronym>MM4L</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sedentary behaviour</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Physical inactivity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1- Theory-based Tailored-print intervention   

Participants randomised into this condition will be mailed three theory-based computer-tailored newsletters over a 12 week period. Each newsletter will provide advice and feedback unique to the individual that relates to key determinants of physical activity adoption and maintenance among breast cancer survivors (as stipulated by previous research in the field and Social Cognitive Theory). The advice participants receive will be tailored using information derived from individual assessments at baseline, 4 weeks and 8 weeks post-baseline (materials will be iteratively tailored). In each case, participants will be mailed the tailored-newsletters immediately after the completed assessment is received.  

Arm 2 - Theory-based Targeted-print intervention 

Participants randomised into this group will receive a copy of a theory-based exercise guidebook developed specifically for promoting physical activity among breast cancer survivors. The guidebook is based on the Theory of Planned Behaviour and includes a 12 week walking program.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard recommendation control group  
Participants randomised into this condition will receive the An active way to better health brochure published by the Australian government, detailing the national physical activity guidelines for adults. A copy of the brochure can be downloaded free of charge from www.healthyactive.gov.au</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome variables, minutes of PA (aerobic and resistance) per week will be assessed using an adapted version (Liebreich, Plotnikoff et al. 2009) of the validated Godin Leisure-Time Exercise Questionnaire (GLTEQ) (Godin and Shepard 1997). 

The adapted version will incorporate a resistance training (RT) measure (Plotnikoff, Taylor et al. 2006; Liebreich, Plotnikoff et al. 2009) that asks participants to report the frequency (times per week) and duration (average times per session) of resistance training activities on average over the last month</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4months and 10months post baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>self-reported sitting time

Assessed using the self-reported sitting time questionnaire (Marshall et al, 2009)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4months and 10months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Steps per day 

Assessed using digiwalker pedometers and diary</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4months and 10months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to PA guidelines

Participants will be categorised as "inactive" (not doing any activity), "insufficiently active (not meeting the guidelines)" or "sufficiently active (meeting the guidelines)" based on wheather they meet the physical activity guidelines (outlined by Hayes, Spence et al. 2009).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4months and 10months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events due to physical activity 

Assessed by 6-items asking participants to rate if they have experienced a problem due to engaging in physical activity in the last month on a five point likert scale ranging from not at all (1) to very much (5) .

An example item is
I have experienced an exercise related injury.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4months and 10months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life

Assessed with the 37-item Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Breast (FACT-B; Brady et al., 1997), which uses the sum of 5-point Likert scales to determine physical well-being, social well-being, emotional well-being, functional well-being, and additional concerns.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4months and 10months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cancer-related fatigue

Assessed using the 13-item FACT-Fatigue (FACT-F) scale (Yellen et al., 1997).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4months and 10months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proposed mediators (i.e. SCT constructs) will also be assessed using previously published, validated instruments where available. 

Outcome expectations will be measured using 6- items from previous studies (Courneya and Friedenreich 1999; Plotnikoff, Blanchard et al. 2001; Plotnikoff, Lippke et al. 2008) and  an addition 5-items developed for this study based on formative research among breast cancer survivors (Rogers, Matevey et al. 2004),  including our own qualitative research and discussions with experts in the field. The response scale consists of a 5-point agreement scale (1=strongly disagree; 2 = disagree; 3 = not sure; 4 = agree; 5 = strongly agree).  

Expectancies will be assessed by asking participants to rate how important each of the outcome expectations are to them (e.g. How important is preventing a cancer recurrent to you) on a 3-point scale (1 = unimportant/it?s ; 2 important; 3 very important). 

Task self-efficacy will be assessed using 4-items developed (Rogers, Shah et al. 2005) and evaluated (Rogers, Courneya et al. 2006) in previous studies with breast cancer survivors and 3 additional items developed for this study to assess task-self efficacy for resistance-training activities (e.g. I can do two small sessions a week of resistance training). Participants will be asked to rate their confidence in their ability to perform a variety of tasks (e.g walk 20 minutes without stopping) on a scale from 1 to not at all confident to 5- extremely confident.  

Barrier self-efficacy was assessed using 12 items based on previous scales used in chronic disease populations (Plotnikoff, Blanchard et al. 2001; Rogers, Courneya et al. 2006; Plotnikoff, Lippke et al. 2008) and unpublished qualitative data (2-items).  Participants were asked how confident they were that they could engage in PA when faced by a range of barriers (e.g. when you lack discipline to exercise). The same scale was used for barrier self-efficacy as for task self-efficacy. 

Behavioural capability, will be assessed using 6-items  developed for this study. Participants were asked to rate on a 5-point likert scale (ranging from 1 strongly disagree to 5 strongly agree) how much they agree with the statement that they are knowledgeable about how to warm up and cool down and about what intensity, duration and type of activity they should do to gain health benefits. Participants were also asked to rate if they agreed that they have the skills to engage in aerobic and resistance-based activities . An example item is "I have the skills I need to engagin in resistance-based activities" 

Self-regulation will be assessed using a 12-item measure developed by Umstattd et al (2009). Participants will be asked to rate how often they used each self-regulation strategy in the past 4 weeks on a scale from 1 to 5 (never, rarely, sometimes, often, very often). A sample item includes I rearranged my schedule to ensure I had time for PA

Action planning will be assessed using 4-items developed by Rise et al, and adapted by Rhodes et al  to say physical activity instead of exercise.  A sample question from this 4-item scale includes
I have made plans concerning when I am going to engage in regular physical activity over the next 2 weeks. All items were asked using a 5-point scale ranging from 1 (no plans) to 5 (detailed plans).

Social support will be assessed using the 15-item social support for exercise habits scale (Sallis, Grossman et al. 1987). Participants were asked to rate how often during the past three months their friends and family (separately) supported them/discouraged them to exercise in a variety of ways. Response options ranged from 1-none to 5 very often and an N/A option was also available. Example item: Gave me encouragement to stick with my exercise program</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 4months and 10months post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 18 years or older
Female 
Have previously been diagnosed with breast cancer at any time point 
Proficient in the English language to read intervention materials and complete surveys
Residing within Australia</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>At time of program commencement still undergoing active treatment (i.e. chemotherapy, radiotherapy, surgery)  
If advised by a health professional that they are unable to partake in physical activity at a level equivalent to a 10 minute walk at a light pace.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Breast cancer survivocipants will be required to return the signed consent form to the research team. Returned consent forms will be allocated a studrs interested in participating in the study will contact the researchers. Potential participants will be sent a study information pack, including an information sheet, consent form and a physical activity readiness questionnaire, via email or via the post. To enrol in the study potential partiy ID number in order to de-identify participants. Once concent is obtained, participants will be randomised into one of the study conditions. To ensure concealment, the random allocation sequence will be generated by a statisticain and given to the project manager. Randomisation will be completed by a research assistant who is not involved in the assessment of participants. As randomisation will occur using the study IDs only, the identify of potential participants will be unknown to those involved in allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC,ACT,QLD,SA,WA,NT,TAS</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive,
Callaghan, NSW 2308  
AUSTRALIA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Institute NSW</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Australian Technology Park
Level 9, 8 Central Avenue
EVELEIGH NSW 2015
Australia.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>A/Prof Erica James</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Medicine and Public Health
Priority Research Centre for Health Behaviour 
Level 3, David Maddison Building, University of Newcastle
University Drive,
Callaghan, NSW Australia 2308.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Prof Ron Plonikoff</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Education
Priority Research Centre for  Physical Activity and Nutrition 
Advanced Technology Centre
University of Newcastle, 
University Drive,
Callaghan, NSW 2308</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to evaluate the feasibility and efficacy of two print-based interventions for increasing physical activity in Australian breast cancer survivors. Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are a woman aged 18 years or more who has previously been diagnosed with breast cancer at any time point. You must not be undergoing active treatment at the commencement of this study (i.e. chemotherapy, radiotherapy, surgery). Trial details Participants in this trial will be randomly (by chance) allocated to one of three groups. Participants in group one will be mailed three theory-based computer-tailored newsletters over a 12 week period. Each newsletter will provide advice and feedback unique to the individual that relates to key determinants of physical activity adoption and maintenance among breast cancer survivors. Participants in group two will receive a copy of a theory-based exercise guidebook developed specifically for promoting physical activity among breast cancer survivors. Participants in group three will be provided with brochure  outlining the physical activity guidelines for Australian adults. Participants will be assessed at baseline, 4 months and 10 months to determine physical activity levels, quality of life, safety and individual expectations and barriers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Publications:
Short C, James E, Plotnikoff R, Girgis A (2011). Efficacy of tailored-print interventions to promote physical activity: A systematic review of randomised trials. IJBNPA. Accepted for publication 28/09/11

Presentations: 
Short C, James E, Plotnikoff R. (2011). How theory-directed questions can help us understand physical activity behaviour in female breast cancer survivors (poster).  2011 Annual Conference of the International Society of Behavioural Nutrition and Physical Activity, Melbourne, Australia, 16-18 June 2011.

Short C, James E, Plotnikoff R, Girgis A. Efficacy of tailored-print interventions to promote physical activity: a systematic review of randomised trials (poster).  2011 Annual Conference of the International Society of Behavioural Nutrition and Physical Activity, Melbourne, Australia, 16-18 June 2011.


Short C, James E, Girgis A.  Tailored lifestyles programs: A `how to' guide for researchers and health professionals. The annual IPOS World Congress of Psycho-Oncology, Vienna, Austria, 21-25 June 2009.

Short C, James E, Girgis A. Tailoring to promote physical activity and broken sedentary time amongst chronic disease populations.  2009 Annual Conference of the International Society of Behavioural Nutrition and Physical Activity, Lisbon, Portugal, 18-21 June 2009.

Short, C., James E, Girgis A. Tailoring to promote physical activity in breast cancer survivors. 10th Behavioural Research in Cancer Control Conference 'Behavioural research leading chronic disease control', Fremantle, 14-16 April 2010.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, University of Newcastle</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee			
	Research Office					
	East Wing, The Chancellery				
	The University of Newcastle
        University Drive.  
	Callaghan   NSW   2308
	Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/07/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2010-1103</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/05/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Research Ethics &amp; Governance Unit</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag No 1
New Lambton NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>N/A access request form approved.</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/05/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Camille Short</name>
      <address>Postal address:
Priority Research Centre for Health Behaviour 
University of Newcastle 
Room 230A, Level 2, David Maddison Building
Callaghan  NSW  2308  Australia
 
Street address:
Priority Research Centre for Health Behaviour 
Room 230A, Level 2, David Maddison Building
Cnr King  &amp; Watt Sts
Newcastle 2300
The University of Newcastle 
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 49138617</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Camille.short@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Camille Short</name>
      <address>Postal address:
Priority Research Centre for Health Behaviour 
University of Newcastle 
Room 230A, Level 2, David Maddison Building
Callaghan  NSW  2308  Australia
 
Street address:
Priority Research Centre for Health Behaviour 
Room 230A, Level 2, David Maddison Building
Cnr King  &amp; Watt Sts
Newcastle 2300
The University of Newcastle 
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 49138617</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Camille.short@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Camille Short</name>
      <address>Postal address:
Priority Research Centre for Health Behaviour 
University of Newcastle 
Room 230A, Level 2, David Maddison Building
Callaghan  NSW  2308  Australia
 
Street address:
Priority Research Centre for Health Behaviour 
Room 230A, Level 2, David Maddison Building
Cnr King  &amp; Watt Sts
Newcastle 2300
The University of Newcastle 
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 49138617</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Camille.short@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>