<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362570">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000595819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of physiotherapy booster sessions on home exercise outcomes in people with knee osteoarthritis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of limited physiotherapy booster sessions on pain and function outcomes with home exercise in people with knee osteoarthritis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1131-3821</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Knee osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Prior to entering this trial, participants will have visited a physiotherapist on 14 occasions to be taught home exercises - either a neuromuscular exercise program that focused on functional exercise and balance/co-ordination and included six exercises or a quadriceps strengthening program that comprised five exercises. During this trial, participants will be asked to continue with their home exercise program three times per week (approx 30 minutes per session) for 24 weeks. An exercise log book will be provided to participants with encouragement to record exercise sessions to assist with motivation. However, this will be an optional self monitoring tool. Participants will additionally receive two 30-minute booster physiotherapy exercise sessions at weeks 8 and 16 at the physiotherapists' clinic.  At these visits, the physiotherapist will review the exercises and discuss progress with the participant. Discussion will also focus on barriers to home exercise performance and strategies to enhance adherence.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be asked to perform the same home exercises three times per week but will not receive the two physiotherapy booster sessions</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average overall knee pain during the past week using 100 mm visual analogue scale with terminal descriptors of no pain and worst pain possible</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported physical function using the disease-specific Western Ontario McMaster Universities (WOMAC) Osteoarthritis Index. The physical function subscale comprises 17 questions in a Likert format</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average pain on walking during the past week assessed using 100 mm visual analogue scale with terminal descriptors of no pain and worst pain possible.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain subscale of the disease-specific Western Ontario McMaster Universities (WOMAC) Osteoarthritis Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived a) overall change, as well as change in b) pain and in c) physical function (compared to baseline) on a seven-point ordinal scale (1-much worse to 7-much better)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life will be measured using the Assessment of Quality of Life instrument version two (AQoL II).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Habitual physical activity will be measured using the Physical Activity Scale for the Elderly (PASE), a self-report questionnaire which records both the level and type of recreational and occupational physical activity undertaken by participants over the previous week.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence: The number of physiotherapy sessions attended will be recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence:  to the home exercise program will be measured by asking participants via telephone, how many times they completed the home exercises in the previous week.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 7 and 15</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to home exercise: participants will self-rate their adherence to the prescribed home exercise program using an 11-point numeric rating scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arthritis self efficacy scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain catastrophising scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arthritis impact measurement scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Coping strategies questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events such as increased pain from exercise and co-interventions - specially designed questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All participants who completed a clinical trial comparing the effects of a 12-week physiotherapist-supervised exercise program plus home exercises (either neuromuscular exercise or strengthening exercise) will be recruited (ACTRN12610000660088): 
People were eligible for the feeder trial if they reported average knee pain over the past week greater than or equal to 25 on a 100 mm visual analogue scale, had predominant pain/tenderness over the medial knee region, and had radiographic evidence of medial tibiofemoral joint OA with varus knee alignment</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) knee surgery or intra-articular corticosteroid injection within past six months; (ii) current or past (within four weeks) oral corticosteroid use; (iii) systemic arthritic conditions; (iv) history of hip or knee joint replacement or tibial osteotomy surgery; (v) any other condition affecting lower limb function; (vi) participation in a strengthening or neuromuscular exercise program within the past six months or planning to commence exercise or other treatment for knee OA; (vii) other non-pharmacological treatment for their knee pain in the past six months including physiotherapy, acupuncture, massage therapy; or (viii) unable to ambulate without a gait aid.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Consecutively numbered, sealed, opaque envelopes containing group allocation will be prepared by a researcher with no other involvement in the study. Allocation will be revealed by a person not involved in recruitment.</concealment>
    <sequence>A person not involved with the study generated the sequence a priori using the random number function in Excel. It involved  
random permuted blocks according to the type of exercise (neuromuscular or strengthening) performed in the feeder trial.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/11/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/11/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>21/09/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>78</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Parkville
Vic 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke St
Canberra, ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Osteoarthritis of the knee is common in older people, giving rise to pain and loss of function. Exercise is a key treatment for knee osteoarthritis with studies revealing short-term benefits of exercise for pain and function. However, exercise is generally not effective in the longer-term due to reduced adherence. Following an initial period of more intensive exercise supervision, this randomised controlled trial will investigate whether a limited number of additional physiotherapy visits will improve outcomes with home exercise over 24 weeks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken). 2014 Nov;66(11):1680-7.
Effects of two physiotherapy booster sessions on outcomes with home exercise in people with knee osteoarthritis: a randomized controlled trial.
Bennell KL, Kyriakides M, Hodges PW, Hinman RS.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee University of Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Melbourne Research Office
University of Melbourne
Parkville
Vic 3010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/04/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0932813.1</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Kim Bennell</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy
University of Melbourne
Parkville
Vic 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83444135</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.bennell@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Kim Bennell</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy
University of Melbourne
Parkville
Vic 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83444135</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.bennell@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kim Bennell</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy University of Melbourne Parkville Vic 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83444135</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.bennell@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>