<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369072">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/08/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000981527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Oral paracetamol versus intravenous indomethacin for the treatment of patent ductus arteriosus in premature infants: A Randomised Control Trial (The OVID Trial)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In preterm infants with a haemodynamically significant ductus arteriosus, does oral paracetamol treatment compared to intravenous indomethacin result in greater narrowing or closure of the ductus arteriosus?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The OVID Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prematurity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Patent ductus arteriosus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Paracetamol, delivered orally
Dosage: 15 mg/kg 6 hourly for 3 days, per course of treatment.
The assessment for ductal status after the first course will be made by the neonatologist responsible for the infant who will base decision-making based on the echocardiography performed after the first course of treatment (within 72 hours after first treatment). The neonatologist will then decide if a second course of treatment is required (with input from paediatric cardiology). 
The second course of treatment will be given if on the second echocardiography (within 72 hours after first treatment) shows the presence of a hemodynamically significant ductus arteriosus and if the attending neonatologist decides. 
The maximum number of treatment courses will be two. 
Infant randomised to oral paracetamol arm will receive intravenous placebo. The intravenous placebo will be normal saline, which will be administered at 24 hourly interval for 3 days.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Indomethacin, delivered intravenously
Dosage: 0.2 mg/kg 24 hourly for 3 days, per course of treatment.
Second course of treatment will be given if on second echocardiography (within 72 hours after first treatment) shows the presence of a hemodynamically significant ductus arteriosus.
Infant randomised to intravenous indomethacin arm will receive oral placebo. Oral placebo will consist of water given 6 hourly for 3 days.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of participants with ductus arteriosus (DA) closure OR DA diameter narrowing 50% or more (composite primary outcome) compared to pre-treatment diameter, as assessed echocardiographically.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 72 hours after completion of first course OR second course of treatment for the ductus arteriosus.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PDA closure after the first course of medical treatment, as measured by echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 72 hours of completion of the first course of treatment
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Size of PDA after the first course of medical treatment, as measured by echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 72 hours of completion of the first course of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PDA closure after the second course of medical treatment, as measured by echocardiography.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 72 hours of completion of second course of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Size of PDA after the second course of medical treatment, as measured by echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 72 hours of completion of second course of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of PDA re-opening after the first course of medical treatment, as measured by echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 72 hours of completion of the first course of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of PDA re-opening after the second course of medical treatment, as measured by echocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 72 hours of completion of the second course of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for re-treatment or surgical ligation after 2 completed courses of medical treatment (as decided by clinical team based on clinical and echocardiographic findings).</outcome>
      <timepoint>After completion of second course of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of ventilation, by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the NICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to achieve full enteral feeding, review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the end of first treatment course to time of full enteral feeding.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum creatinine, by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before entry into trial and within 72 hours of completion of treatment course</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pulmonary haemorrhage or pneumothorax, by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the NICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severe intraventricular haemorrhage (Papille Grade III or IV), by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the NICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Necrotizing enterocolitis (according to  Bell classification, Stage 2 or greater), by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the NICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Abdominal distension or feeding intolerance, by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the course of treatment and up to 48 hours after treatment course</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Culture-positive sepsis, by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the course of treatment and up to 48 hours after completion of treatment course</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oliguria (defined as &lt;1.0 ml/kg/hour), by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the course of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Chronic lung disease (defined as oxygen dependence at 36 weeks corrected gestation and based on the physiological test described by Walsh et al), by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 36 weeks postmenstrual age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Retinopathy of prematurity, highest grade, by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At any time during the NICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of hospital stay, by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time until discharge home, i.e. from time of admission to time of discharge home.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Death (all cause mortality)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Death before discharge from hospital during initial NICU admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mode of ventilation, by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During NICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum bilirubin, by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before entry into trial and within 72 hours of completion of treatment course.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST), by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before entry into trial and within 72 hours of completion of treatment course.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) levels, by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before entry into trial and within 72 hours of completion of treatment course.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Gestation: less than 32 weeks (up to 31 weeks 6 days) gestation
Post-natal (or post-gestation) age of greater than/equal to 7 days OR following the second routine cranial ultrasound assessment
Clinical suspicion of a haemodynamically significant PDA, e.g.
Active praecordium, loud murmur or wide pulse pressure
The need for respiratory support (defined as CPAP/NIMV/IMV/HFO) with FiO2 greater than or equal to 30%. These infants should have an echocardiographic assessment to confirm the presence of PDA
Echocardiographic evidence of either:
Significant left-to-right shunting across PDA (hsDA score of equal or greater than 6) comprising transductal diameter, velocity and left atrial aortic root ratio OR 
A composite score of greater than or equal to than 16 based on the Sehgal score
Infant is on minimal enteral feed defined as less than or equal to 10ml/kg/day</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Days</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Days</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Major congenital abnormalities, including congenital heart disease
Severe intraventricular haemorrhage (IVH) (grade 3 or 4)
Evidence of coagulation dysfunction: Platelet count &lt; 100,000/microlitre or presence of blood in endotracheal/gastric aspirate, haematuria
Intrauterine growth restriction defined as &lt;3rd centile and/or reverse end diastolic flow on antenatal Dopplers.
Echocardiographic evidence of significant right-to-left shunting across PDA
Elevated serum creatinine &gt; 100 micromol/L
Concerns about abdominal problems (feeding intolerance aspirates &gt; feeding volume, bilious colour, abdominal distension)
Life threatening sepsis
Urine output of less than 1ml/kg/hour during the preceding 8 hours
Evidence of liver dysfunction or hyperbilirubinaemia requiring exchange transfusion
Decision not-to-treat by the attending neonatologist
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be enrolled after written consent is obtained from parents. An echocardiogram will be performed prior to the study enrolment. Participants will be randomly assigned to treatment groups in a 1:1 ratio using a computer generated list of random allocation schedule. </concealment>
    <sequence>Random permuted blocks of varying sizes will be employed to ensure approximate balance of treatment allocation within each group. Allocation of patients to treatment arm will be concealed at all times from the treating team, as it will be performed independently by the pharmacy department research section who will maintain the allocation key; unless there are extenuating clinical reasons.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Infant randomised to oral paracetamol arm will receive intravenous placebo
Infant randomised to intravenous indomethacin arm will receive oral placebo</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>There will be a statistician for the trial who will conduct the statistical analyses. The database will be stored in an online database (REDCap). Based on a hypothesis of superiority of oral paracetamol in DA closure, a sample size of 68 babies in each group (136 in total) will provide 80% power at the 5% level of significance to detect a difference increase of 56% in ductal closure rate between groups (i.e. increase to 70% closure rate), based on a closure rate of 45% with indomethacin from a previous NICU audit. Taking into account possible drop-outs, the sample size is adjusted upwards by 10% to get the required number of subjects to be recruited into the trial. Therefore the final sample size will be 150 infants in total (with 75 infants per treatment arm).

An interim analysis will be performed for the main outcome at 50% recruitment.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/11/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash Newborn, Monash Children's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>246 Clayton Road
Clayton
Victoria
VIC 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Pharmacy Department, Monash Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>246 Clayton Road
Clayton
Victoria
VIC 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Pharmacy Department, Monash Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>246 Clayton Road
Clayton
Victoria
VIC 3168</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This will be a placebo randomised control trial conducted in the neonatal intensive care unit. The trial will compare oral paracetamol against current standard therapy for a haemodynamically significant ductus arteriosus, which is intravenous indomethacin.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton
Victoria 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15084A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kenneth Tan</name>
      <address>Monash Newborn
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61-3-95945191</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kenneth.tan@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kenneth Tan</name>
      <address>Monash Newborn
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61-3-95945191</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kenneth.tan@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Arvind Sehgal</name>
      <address>Monash Newborn
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61-3-95945191</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>arvind.sehgal@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kenneth Tan</name>
      <address>Monash Newborn
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton
Victoria 3168</address>
      <phone>+61395945191</phone>
      <fax>+61395946115</fax>
      <email>kenneth.tan@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>