<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336595">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/02/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000352909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effects of Parecoxib in Children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Pharmacokinetic and Pharmacodynamic of Parecoxib in Children</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1119-0062</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Not applicable</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The Pharmacokinetic and Pharmacodynamics of Parecoxib.

The perioperative pain relief in children and the effects of parecoxib in children</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Research Design
Parecoxib is a intravenous drug and will be administered as a single bolus injection at the induction of anaesthesia for the purpose of this study.
Recruitment
Group 1
-60 patients age 4 to 15yr.
-This allows for the loss of patients either to refusal for further investigations or cannula malfunction. 
-Tonsillectomy model is being utilised for this study
-Patients undergoing tonsillectomy with or without adenoidectomy will be recruited
Parental or patient consent will be obtained
Patients in group 1 will be randomised to  receive parecoxib in either one of these doses 0.25mg/kg, 1mg/kg or 2mg/kg.   
-Patients will then have 6 blood assays taken in total
- 1st blood assay 30 minutes post administration of drug
-2nd blood assay in post anaesthesia care unit
- 3rd to 6th blood assay taken in day stay unit at 30 minute to 1 hour intervals
-Pain scores will also be taken simultaneously with blood assay 2-6

Group 2
-All patients in group 2 will receive 1mg/kg of parecoxib as a single bolus at induction of anaesthesia.
-15 patients age 4 to 15yr.
-General or Orthopaedic patients 


All study patients will receive the following drugs.
Paracetamol 30mg/kg orally as per day stay protocol prior to induction. 
Intravenous induction using propofol 2-3mg kg -1 or inhalation induction using sevoflurane. 
Anaesthesia will be maintained using total intravenous anaesthesia (TIVA), propofol and remifentanil infusion will be used.   Lignocaine 1-2mg kg -1 will be used to spray the vocal cords prior to intubation.
Ondansetron 0.15mg kg -1 and Dexamethasone 0.15mg kg -1will be used as antiemetics for Group 1 patients.  Ondansetron 0.15mg kg -1 will only be given at the discretion of the anaesthetist for the Group 2 patients.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients will be randomised into 3 groups with the following doses 0.5mg/kg, 1mg/kg and 3mg/kg.  There will be no control group as this trial is looking comparing the effect of different doses of Parecoxib to ascertain the appropriate pain relief dose of Parecoxib in children.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) Pain scores of patients in Group1 receiving either 0.25mg/kg, 1mg/kg and 2mg/kg of Parecoxib.  Patients will have pain scores done in the post anaesthesia care unit and with simultaneously with blood assay 3-6 on the ward. Revised faces pain scale will be utilised.    Pain score will be used as an effect of the pharmacodynamic of Parecoxib</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pain scores will be done for group 1 patients only.  
1st pain score - in post anaesthesia care unit approximately 40 minutes post administration of drug
2nd to 5th pain score - done simultaneously with blood assay 3rd -6th  of parecoxib on the day stay unit.  This will be at 30 min to 1 hour intervals.  Therefore, this will be at 30 min to 1 hour intervals for 4hours after administration of the parecoxib.
 Pain scores will not be done for patients in Group2</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood tests will be taken when the pain scores are done to test for Parecoxib levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>For patients in Group 1:
Sample 1 will be taken after parecoxib has been administered in theatre. 
Sample 2 will be taken in the post anaesthesia care unit. 
Samples 3 at 1-2 hr post dose, sample 4 at 2-3hr, sample 5 at 3-4hr, sample 6 at 4-5hr.

For patients in Group 2:
Blood levels for Parecoxib will be taken at 12hours post dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Group 1- Patients undergoing tonsillectomy with or without adnenoidectomy

Group2 - Patients undergoing appendicectomy or repair of fractures</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>4</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>EXCLUSION CRITERIA IN BOTH GROUPS
Patients with hepatic, renal or cardiac sequelae.
Learning difficulties.
Coagulation defects.
Allergy to NSAIDS.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Group 1
-Parents will be sent patient information leaflets with the booking letters prior to the surgery.  Therefore, they will have the time to consider the enrolment at their leisure.
- Patients will be recruited by the research nurse or the anaesthetist running the list.  Once the parents or patients have shown an interest the research nurse will then discuss the trial with the parent.
- Patients in Group1 will then be randomised to either receive 0.25mg/kg, 1mg/kg or 2mg/kg of Parecoxib during the induction of anaesthesia.  They will only receive one dose or parecoxib.
- Once randomisation has occurred the anaesthetic team, post anaesthesia care unit team, research nurse and day stay unit nurses will be blinded to the dose the patient will receive.

BLINDING
-The drug will be reconstituted in a separate room by a separate anaesthetist who will not be involved in the care and subsequent pain analysis of the patient.  
-Irrespective the dose the drug will be reconstituted to a volume of 2ml thus blinding the primary anaesthetist to the dose of the drug.
-The dose that the patient has been randomised to will be logged on the research computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>RANDOMISATION
-20 cards with the respective doses mentioned above (total 60 cards) will be placed in a box.  
-When the patient has been selected a second anaesthetist will then pick a card from the mentioned box and the dose will then be allocated to the patient.
-As mentioned above only the second anaesthetist will have knowledge of the drug allocation and will reconstitute the appropriate dose of parecoxib.
-The allocation will then be logged on the research computer</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics / pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/08/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>75</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. Elsa Taylor</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Anaesthesia and Operating Rooms,
Starship Children's Health
2 Park Rd Grafton
1023 Auckland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Pfizer</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Pfizer New Zealand Ltd
Level 3, Pfizer House
14 Normanby Road
Mt Eden
Auckland
1024</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Lena Tan</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Anaesthesia and Operating Rooms,
Starship Children's Health
2 Park Rd Grafton
1023 Auckland</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Brian Anderson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Anaesthesia and Operating Rooms,
Starship Children's Health
2 Park Rd Grafton
1023 Auckland</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Intravenous non-steroidal anti-inflammatory (NSAIDs) parecoxib has been utilised in both adult and paediatric practice for some years.  However, there is only adult data on the pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamics of parecoxib.  There is currently no data regarding the appropriate dose in paediatrics.  NSAIDS in paediatric practice are usually administered via the oral or rectal route.  However, the bioavailability of these routes are variable and inconsistent.  NSAIDS when used with paracetamol are effective as morphine sparing analgesia especially in day surgery.  Numerous studies have been done on the pharmacokinetics of other nonsteroidals like ketorolac and diclofenac. Group 1 patients will provide data on the pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of Parecoxib.  Group1 patients are day stay patients thus will be discharged within 6 hours.  As Parecoxib has a half life of 6-8 hours we require data from Group 2.  Group 2 patients will be inpatients who will provide pharmacokinetic data beyond 6 hours. We would like to study the effects of Parecoxib in children in order to find the appropriate pain relieving dose</summary>
    <trialwebsite>nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern X Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Postal address:
650 Great South Rd Penrose 1061</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/03/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Lena Tan</name>
      <address>Anaesthesia &amp; Operating Rooms
Starship Children's Health,
2 Park Road
Grafton 1023
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64226700449</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lenatan@doctors.org.uk</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lena Tan</name>
      <address>Anaesthesia &amp; Operating Rooms
Starship Children's Health,
2 Park Road
Grafton 1023
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64226700449</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lenatan@doctors.org.uk</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Lena Tan</name>
      <address>Anaesthesia &amp; Operating Rooms
Starship Children's Health,
2 Park Road
Grafton 1023
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64226700449</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lenatan@doctors.org.uk</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>