<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362114">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000213842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Internet Self Help Therapy for Problem Drinking: Retention and Effectiveness</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Internet Self Help Therapy for Problem Drinking: Retention and Effectiveness</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Problematic alcohol use</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The current study aims to conduct a randomised controlled trial over 3 months that investigates the effectiveness of an internet-delivered alcohol intervention. The intervention consists of an interactive, internet based, self-help program comprising 5 modules, each covering a specific theme (e.g. mindfulness, cognitive restructuring). Each module was designed to take between 30 and 60 minutes to complete (i.e. approximately 5 hours in total). Participants are able to skip certain sections and can complete modules in any order. The study also aims to enhance retention rates to the online program with the addition of reminder text messages to motivate clients to continue logging on to the program. Text messages will be sent on average 3-4 times per week over the three month trial period. 
Thus, the intervention condition involves open access to an online alcohol intervention and the addition of reminder text messages.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control condition involves open access to the same online alcohol intervention, without the addition of reminder text messages.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUDIT-C (a screener to help identify persons who are engaging in problematic alcohol use)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, and 2, 4, 6 and 12 weeks post baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kessler-10 (general well-being scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, and 2, 4, 6 and 12 weeks post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life Inventory (measures quality of life)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, and 2, 4, 6 and 12 weeks post baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Attrition or retention rates from the study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the end of the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants overall engagement in the program (as measured by number of log-ins and number of pages accessed)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the end of the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be included in the study if they (1) currently engage in problematic alcohol use (i.e., consumption above recommended drinking levels as suggested by the National Health and Medical Research Council of Australia: i.e. the present intake is greater than or equal to 14 standard drinks per week; or 4 standard units on a single occasion for men or 3 for women); (2) have access to the internet and a mobile phone; (3) are above the age of 18; (4) agree to undergo no other psychological treatment throughout the study; and (6) have sufficient English and literacy skills to understand the written interventions without translation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded from the study if they meet criteria for other serious psychological disorders (i.e. schizophrenia or suicidality); or if they have used injected drugs in the previous month or report daily use of an illicit substance.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will visit www.ontrack.org.au in response to referral or advertising and are led to a registration page where they are provided with information about the research and are asked to consent to participating in the study. They are also required to register to receive a screening call.
During the call a screening information sheet is read over the phone and the participant is asked for verbal consent for screening. If the participant meets screening eligibility criteria, they are invited to complete a baseline assessment. Participants are emailed a link that takes them to the online assessment questions. After they have completed all baseline assessments, they are randomly allocated to one of the two treatments and are provided with a username and password to log in to the program. Participants then complete the program at their own pace.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization will occur via a true random number service and carried out by an independent researcher.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Charlotte von Schuckmann</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>5/45 Frederick Street, Annerley, 4103, QLD</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland University of Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Victoria Park Road, Kelvin Grove, QLD, 4059</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current study aims to conduct a randomised controlled trial over 3 months (with the possibility of a 6 month follow up) that compares the impact of the following two internet-delivered interventions on alcohol consumption:
1. Online alcohol intervention: includes open access to the OnTrack alcohol intervention
2. Online alcohol intervention with text messaging: includes open access to the OnTrack alcohol intervention plus the addition of text messages reminding participants to log on to the program and stay on track

The study has three major research aims: 
Aim I: to investigate the impact of text messaging as a supplementary support for online treatments. 
* determine to what extent the addition of text messaging impacts participants engagement in the program 
* does the addition of text-messaging impact the effectiveness of the program 
* are drop-out rates lower in the text messaging condition than in the control condition
Aim II: to determine the average dose of treatment required for improvement 
* investigate the effectiveness of the intervention in relation to the amount of time spent utilising it 
Aim III: to learn more about people who prematurely discontinue online treatments 
* gain a better understanding of why individuals drop-out through follow-up interviews 
* identify to what extent these individuals are still utilising the skills and techniques they acquired within the intervention after drop-out 

It is predicted that the web-based alcohol intervention with text messaging will result in lower attrition rates, greater engagement with the program and greater utility of skills than the treatment alone condition. Further, it is predicted that the addition of text messages will improve the effectiveness of the program by reducing self-reported alcohol intake.

We also hope to determine whether the intervention improves quality of life; and general well-being and if it is considered useful, relevant, satisfying and easy to use.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.ontrack.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/02/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Robert King</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health, School of Psychology and Counselling (Level 5, O'Block)
Victoria Park Road, Kelvin Grove, 4059, QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 (07) 3138 4722</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robert.king@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Charlotte von Schuckmann</name>
      <address>5/45 Frederick Street, Annerley, 4103, QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 0414652543</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.vonschuckmann@connect.qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Charlotte von Schuckmann</name>
      <address>5/45 Frederick Street, Annerley, 4103, QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 0414652543</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.vonschuckmann@connect.qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>