<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347823">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/12/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/12/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001278921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Integrated Problem Based Management of Obstructive Airways Disease in Older people</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Integrated Problem Based Management of Obstructive Airways Disease in Older people with Asthma and Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) and its impact on quality of life.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma and Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention consists of individualised management based on the baseline multidimensional assessment. A personalised care plan is developed by the study physician and study co-ordinator. The clinicians and participants agree on the tailored interventions for each of the identified problems.  An inflammometry algorithm is used to inform treatment decisions for airway and systemic inflammation and mucus hypersecretion.  Other tailored interventions are standardised according to best available evidence .  A case manager coordinates the plan. The interventions are delivered over the first 3 months during several individualised visits. Participation in pulmonary rehabilitation occurs concurrently.
The tailored interventions are standardised according to best available evidence and will include: optimal medical management including tailoring pharmacotherapy according to airway and systemic inflammation and guiding the exacerbation plan, individualised smoking cessation counseling and pharmacotherapy, management of anxiety and depression, management of mucous hypersecretion, exacerbation management, management of dysfunctional breathing, correction of nutritional and metabolic disorders, implementation of domiciliary oxygen, self management education and support, management of airflow obstruction and co-morbidities, correction of adherence, exercise training, treatment of infection, management of dyspnea, symptoms and patient identified problems.  

Pharmacotherapy tailored to airway inflammation (AI)
Macrolide Antibiotics for the treatment of neutrophilic bronchitis.  Participants with a sputum neutrophil count greater than 61% and a productive cough are treated with oral Azithromycin 250mg three times weekly.  

Corticosteroid therapy for eosinophilic bronchitis 
 The treatment algorithm published by Siva is used to guide any changes to the maintenance ICS dose. 

Allergic Aspergillosis
Assessment: total IgE, aspergillus specific IgE
Intervention: Participants with with a clinical diagnosis of Allergic Bronchopulmonary Aspergillosis are treated with (oral)Itraconazole 200mg daily for 16 weeks

Systemic Inflammation: Serum CRP is measured.  Systemic inflammation is defined as CRP&gt;3mg/l.  In the absence of any contraindications these participants are treated with oral simvastatin 20mg nocte.

Individualised Self Management education 
Intervention: Information about the pathophysiological changes related to their airways disease, guidance in appropriate symptom recognition and assisted with behavioral change strategies to improve outcomes.  

In addition to this participants are given an individualized written self management plan with instruction for the management of exacerbations, have their inhaler device skills assessed, reviewed and corrected and adherence assessed and corrected.

Tailored Pulmonary Rehabilitation 
Participants attend a Pulmonary Rehabiltation programme involving an 8 week exercise and education programme.  

Breathing Strategies
Intervention: A range of different breathing techniques are taught including pursed lip breathing, active expiration, diaphragmatic breathing, adapting specific body positions, and coordinating paced breathing with activities. 

Muco-ciliary clearance
Assessment: We screen for the presence of mucus hypersecretion by patient report using a validated assessment of mucus hypersecretion.   A volume of greater than 25mls of mucus produced per day is used to define mucus hypersecretion as a problem.   
Intervention: Review by a physiotherapist for assessment and instruction in the use of devices (PEP, Accapella, Pari pep or Flutter) to assist with muco-ciliary clearance (MCC).   In those with excessive secretions, nebulised hypertonic saline 6% 10mls is used.

Cardiac Failure
Assessment: BNP is measured in all patients. 
Intervention: Participants will be managed according to Australian heart failure guidelines.

Anxiety management  
Assessment: The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) A score of &gt; 8 in either domain indicates possible anxiety or depression. 
Intervention: Patient are taught how to recognise symptoms of stress and panic and how to implement stress management strategies.  Relaxation methods are taught and supplementary audiovisual material provided for use at home. 

Management of nutritional and metabolic disorders
3 pronged intervention tailored to BMI. 
All receive an individualised dietetic intervention, delivered by a dietitian. Advice: the components of a balanced diet, promoting anti-inflammatory foods  high in Omega 3 fatty acids, antioxidants and calcium for  bone health. 
Underweight Healthy intervention plus nutritional supplements and counselling.  Dietetic information regarding weight gain, including a high protein (1.2-1.5g Protein per Kg Ideal Body Weight), high energy (120% of Estimated Energy Requirements) eating plan and a nutritionally complete oral supplement (Two Cal HN, Abbott Nutrition and/or Sustagen Hospital Formula, Novartis Nutrition). 
Overweight  Healthy intervention plus dietetic intervention that focused on weight reduction/weight maintenance through a non very low calorie diet. Lose it Fast 

Osteoporosis:  Dual-energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA) is performed.   Pharmacotherapy based on the Australian Osteoporosis guidelines
Smoking: Counselling plus Nicotine Replacement therapy (topical) or oral Varenicline

The overall duration of this study is 2 years.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual Care
Usual care involves guideline based management including medical assessment by a respiratory physician and referral to a standard pulmonary rehabilitation programme in a community based setting.  The participants usual specialist physician provides a medical assessment, a review a co-morbidities, an assessment of lung function and oxygenation by spirometry and pulse oximetry, and a diagnosis.   The treating physician schedules follow up appointments as they deem appropriate.  

The treating physician  arranges a referral to a community based pulmonary rehabilitation programme.  This programme has been developed based on the intervention group programme and includes a baseline assessment by a pulmonary nurse which  include a 6 minute walk, spirometry, assessment of SaO2, a social assessment, assessment of smoking status and brief advice, screening for anxiety and depression and a medication and skills assessment.  This is followed by an 8 week twice weekly multidisciplinary education and supervised exercise programme with prescription of a home exercise programme (pulmonary rehabilitation).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health Status measured by the St George Respiratory Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 12 and 24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of clinical problems
This is assessed using a previously developed and published multidimensional assessment. This number of problems identified is summed to give the total number of problems.
The clinical assessments include: Dual energy X-ray absorpitomerty, spiromerty, sputum induction, exhaled nitric oxide, blood collection (serum for C Reactive Protien, full blood count and Brain natriuretic peptide), 6 minute walk test, questionnaires, assessment of inhaler technique and exhaled carbon monoxide.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 12 and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peripheral blood will be collected and C Reactive Protien (CRP) measured from serum by ELISA</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 12 and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sputum eosinophils and neutrophils

Induced sputum is collected by inhalation of nebulised hypertonic saline or normal saline.   The saline is delivered using a mouthpiece and two-way valve connected to an ultrasonic nebuliser.  A short-acting beta2 agonist (SABA) is administered via pressurised metered dose inhaler (pMDI) and valved holding chamber prior to the induction commencing. Saline is delivered via the ultrasonic nebuliser in time incremental intervals (30 seconds, 1 minutes, 2 minutes, and 4 minutes x 2).  One minute after each saline dose, airway calibre is assessed by lung function and participants are instructed to vigorously cough, huff and empty the expectorant into a sterile container. If at any time the FEV1 falls below 15% of baseline, further SABA is administered.  
Airway inflammation is assessed using induced sputum. Lower respiratory sputum portions are selected from saliva, processed using dithiothreitol and differential cell counts obtained.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 12 and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung Function
Airflow obstruction is assessed in each participant using spirometry (KoKo K313100 PDS Instrumentation, Louisville, CO, USA) to measure pre and post bronchodilator FEV1, FVC and FEV1/FVC%.  Predicted FEV1 and FVC are calculated using NHANES III</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 12 and 24 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>&gt;55 years
pre bronchodilar FEV1 &lt;80%, FER &lt;0.7
Doctor diagnosed COPD or Asthma 
Disease stability in the previous 4 weeks
Participants are postponed if they have required antibiotics or oral corticosteroids for an acute exacerbation of their airways disease within the previous month, or if they are experiencing a current acute illness.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>55</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants are excluded if they have a malignancy, or a significant co-morbidity that the study visits and interventions may impact on or have a poor prognosis with an anticipated life expectancy of  &lt;3 months. Participants must be able to attend the visits and have satisfactory written and verbal English language skills</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants who consent to the study and live outside the JHH PR catchment area act as the control.  The consenting participants referred John Hunter Hospital  receive the intervention.  Allocation to usual care or IPBM is independent of the physician and patient.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>John Hunter Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Locked bag 1 HRMC, 2310, NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Newcastle</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Univeristy Drive, Callaghan 2308, NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>John Hunter Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked bag 1 HRMC, 2310, NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Newcastle</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Univeristy Drive, Callaghan, 2308, NSW</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obstructive Airway Diseases (OAD) such as asthma and Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) are common among older people  and cause a significant and increasing disease burden.  Management of these conditions in older people is complex.

The need for new approaches to managing asthma and COPD in older people is widely recognised by the clinical and scientific community. We have suggested a multidimensional approach. 
  	
The aim of this trial was to test a novel model of management in older people with asthma and COPD using multidimensional assessment and individualised management.  We hypothesized that in older patients with asthma and COPD, a model of MDAIM would result in a clinically important improvement in health related QOL compared to usual care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>John Hunter Hospital
Locked Bag 1 HRMC 2310, NSW</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/09/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/08/20/3.10</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/07/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Newcastle</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/01/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Vanessa McDonald</name>
      <address>John Hunter Hospital 
Locked Bag 1 HRMC 2310, NSW</address>
      <phone>+61249213470</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Vanessa.McDonald@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kelly Steel</name>
      <address>Department of Respiratory and Sleep Medicine
John Hunter Hospital
Locked bag 1 HRMC 2310, NSW</address>
      <phone>+61249213470</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Vanessa.McDonald@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>