<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364542">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000756729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of the efficacy, safety and tolerability of topically applied tretinoin formulated with TPM, a lead commercially available tretinoin cream and a vehicle (placebo) in the treatment of mild to moderate acne vulgaris</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase II, randomized, active and vehicle controlled, Investigator blind, multi-centre study to evaluate the efficacy, safety and tolerability of topically applied tretinoin formulated with TPM as an anti-acne preparation in human subjects with acne vulgaris.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>POH031-13</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Treatment of acne vulgaris</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects will receive tretinoin (0.05%) formulated with tocopheryl phosphate mixture (TPM), a commercially available tretinoin formulation (0.05%), or a vehicle (placebo), which will be applied once daily for 3 months.  TPM is a delivery system derived from Vitamin E that is able to increase the dermal absorption of tretinoin without increasing irritation.

Each subject will be given written instructions entitled Instructions for facial cleansing and study treatment application that will outline the facial cleansing and study treatment application instructions.  

The instructions are briefly summarised below:
1.	Gently wash entire face with the supplied skin cleanser, rinse immediately, pat the face dry with a towel
2.	Leave the skin for 20 - 30 minutes before applying study treatment.
3.	30 - 60 minutes before bed, squeeze about a centimetre of the assigned study treatment onto your fingertip  (while that should be enough for your whole face, after you have some experience with the medication you may find you need slightly more or less to do the job).  
4.	Dabbing it on your forehead, chin and both cheeks, then spreading it over the entire face.  Smooth gently into the skin. The medication should become invisible almost immediately. If it is still visible, or if dry flaking occurs from the gel within a minute or so, you are using too much.
5.	Keep the medication away from the corners of the nose, mouth, eyes and open wounds.
6.	Wash hands thoroughly after application of the study treatment.
7.	Ensure product is absorbed prior to sleeping.
8.	Leave treated areas undisturbed overnight. 

Compliance will be monitored by use of a daily patient diary.    
</interventions>
    <comparator>Subjects will receive tretinoin (0.05%) formulated with TPM, a commercially available tretinoin formulation (0.05%), or a vehicle (placebo), which will be applied once daily for 3 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The mean absolute change in total acne lesion count  

Lesion count will be scored by a dermatologist during clinical examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From Baseline to Week 12.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The percent of subjects with a successful outcome on a global acne grading scale.

Success on the Acne Global Severity Scale is a reduction of 2 from baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 12.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The percent change in total acne lesion counts

Lesion count will be scored by a dermatologist during clinical examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 2, 4, 6, 8, and 12 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The percent change using a global acne grading scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 2, 4, 6, 8, and 12.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The percent change in blackhead/whitehead lesion counts

Blackhead/whitehead lesion count will be scored by a dermatologist during clinical examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 2, 4, 6, 8, and 12
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The percent change in papules/pustules lesion counts

Papules/pustules lesion count will be scored by a dermatologist during clinical examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 2, 4, 6, 8, and 12 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in responses to acne self assessment questionnire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 4 and Week 12 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of location reaction between formulations 

Irritation will be scored using the Local Reaction Grading Scale by a dermatologist during clinical examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 2, 4, 6, 8, and 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The percentage of treatment related Adverse Events
Adverse reactions reported with tretinoin are as follows:

The skin of certain sensitive individuals may become excessively red, oedematous, blistered or crusted. If this occurs, the medication should be either discontinued until the integrity of the skin is restored or the medication should be adjusted to a level the patient can tolerate.

Temporary hyperpigmentation or hypopigmentation has been reported with repeated application of tretinoin.

Some individuals have been reported to have heightened susceptibility to sunlight while under treatment with tretinoin. To date, all adverse effect of tretinoin have been reversible upon discontinuation of therapy.

Isolated occurrences of allergic contact dermatitis have been reported after treatment with tretinoin.

Reversible changes in liver function tests have been reported following topical use of tretinoin. Elevated serum levels of bilirubin, alkaline phosphatase, aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) were observed, and thymol turbidity and thymol flocculation were increased.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of Study (consent until follow up visit).

Follow up visit will occur during week 14.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Minimum of 15 and Maximum of 60 inflammatory lesions on the face (papules and/ or pustules) and no more than one small nodulocystic lesion;
* Existence of a minimum of 50 non-inflammatory lesions on the face (blackheads/whiteheads);
* A score of 2 or 3 on the Investigator's Global Assessment (IGA) scale; 
* Willing to minimise exposure to the sun, and avoid tanning booths and solariums</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Severe acne vulgaris
* Facial skin condition other than acne vulgaris
* Facial hair, excessive scarring, sunburn or other disfigurement that may obscure assessment of acne counts or severity
* History of retinoid intolerance
* Subjects that are on topical/systemic acne treatment that does not meet the washout period
* Nursing/pregnant women
* The women were planning for pregnancy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/04/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Hamilton</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Phosphagenics</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>11 Duerdin Street Clayton, Victoria 3168 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Phosphagenics</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>11 Duerdin Street Clayton, Victoria 3168 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A multi centre, investigator blind, study in a total of 45 subjects with mild to moderate acne vulgaris aiming to evaluate the efficacy, safety and tolerability of topical tretinoin formulated with TPM compared with a commercially available tretinoin formulation, and a vehicle. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>229 Greenhill Road Dulwich South Australia 5065  </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lynda Spelman</name>
      <address>Specialist Connect
68 Ipswich Rd, 
Woolloongabba, QLD, Australia 4102
</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3039 1300</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Kurt.davidson@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alisha Smith</name>
      <address>Phosphagenics Ltd 
11 Duerdin Street
Clayton, VIC, Australia 3168
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9565 1119</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>asmith@phosphagenics.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alisha Smith</name>
      <address>Phosphagenics Ltd 
11 Duerdin Street
Clayton, VIC, Australia 3168
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9565 1119</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>asmith@phosphagenics.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alisha Smith</name>
      <address>Phosphagenics Ltd 
11 Duerdin Street
Clayton, VIC, Australia 3168
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9565 1119</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>asmith@phosphagenics.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>