<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373120">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000972325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Surveying the health of women associated with Universal Medicine</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A cross-sectional health survey of 407 women associated with Universal Medicine</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>BMI</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Summary Mental Health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Abnormal pap test</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Low iron</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Abnormal mammogram</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Bronchitis / Emphysema</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Breast cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cervical cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Heart disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Osteoporosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Skin cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Thrombosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Back pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The survey's name is "Women in Livingness Survey". It is a one-off 1 hour survey participants fill in on the survs survey platform www.survs.com. The survey contains both questions designed specifically for this survey and questions from the ALSWH (Australian Longitudinal Study of Women's Health).

There were no conditions observed beyond the ones asked about in the survey. The participants were exposed to an online platform where they indicated their consent. If they consented, there were progressively given the questions of the survey to answer in a standard internet survey format, having the ability to go back and forth between pages and answering multiple-choice type questions.</interventions>
    <comparator>The data of the Universal Medicine participants was collected on the online survey platform between July 4th, 2015 and September 5th, 2015.

The survey results are compared with the summary survey results from the Australian Longitudinal Study of Women's Health (ALSWH). The summary survey results can be downloaded from the ALSWH website: https://www.alswh.org.au/for-researchers/data/data-books. The ALSWH data covers surveys from 1998 to 2013.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SF-36 scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of the survey and, from memory, at the time of them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms: Allergies, hayfever, sinusitis; Breathing difficulty; Indigestion / heartburn; Chest pain; Headaches / migraines; Severe tiredness; Stiff or painful joints; Back pain; Urine that burns or stings; Haemorrhoids (piles); Other bowel problems; Vaginal irritation or unusual discharge; Hot flushes; Night sweats; Eyesight problems; Leaking urine; Mouth, teeth or gum problems; Avoided eating some foods because of problems with your teeth, mouth or dentures; Toothache; Hearing problems; Depression; Anxiety; Episodes of intense anxiety (eg panic attacks); Palpitations (feeling that your heart is racing or fluttering in your chest)

All symptoms were assessed by asking how often the respondent experienced the symptom in the previous 12 months: Never, rarely, sometimes or often. All questions were copied from the ALSWH survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the 12 months prior to the survey and, from memory, in the 12 months prior to them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medical history: Whether respondent ever been diagnosed for any of 28 ailments: Insulin dependent (Type 1) diabetes; Non-insulin dependent (Type 2) diabetes; Hyperthyroidism (Overly active thyroid); Hypothyroidism (Under active thyroid); Impaired glucose tolerance; Osteoarthritis; Rheumatoid arthritis; Other arthritis; Heart disease (including heart attack, angina); Hypertension (high blood pressure); Thrombosis; Stroke; Low iron level (iron deficiency or anaemia); Asthma; Bronchitis / emphysema; Osteoporosis; Endometriosis; Polycystic Ovary Syndrome; Breast cancer; Cervical cancer; Skin cancer (including melanoma); Other cancer; Depression; Anxiety / nervous disorder; Other psychiatric disorder; Chronic Fatigue Syndrome; Sexually transmitted infection (eg genital herpes or warts, chlamydia); Polyps or Fibroids related to female organs.

Whether any of 17 operations or procedures had ever been performed: A non-cancerous cyst removed; Polyps or fibroids related to female organs removed; Thyroid removed; One but not both ovaries removed; Both ovaries removed; Repair of prolapsed vagina, bladder or bowel?; Endometrial ablation (removal of the lining of the uterus); Joint replacement (eg hip, knee); Mastectomy (removal of one or both breasts); Lumpectomy (removal of lump from breasts); Removal of skin cancer; Any cancer surgery (other than skin or breast); Chemotherapy or radiotherapy for any cancer; Breast biopsy (taking a sample of breast tissue); Hysteroscopy (investigative procedure to examine the uterus); Cholecystectomy (gall bladder removed); Gastroscopy / colonoscopy.

Also: Whether respondents ever had an abnormal pap test or mammogram or hysterectomy. Whether respondents take the contraceptive pill or hormone replacement therapy or had a recent menstrual bleeding, whether the frequency of their periods has changed in the previous 12 months, start and stop age of menstrual bleeding. Condition of teeth dentures or gums.

These items were asked asked through a Yes/No response in the survey. All questions were copied from the ALSWH survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From birth up to the time of the survey</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CESD (Depression) Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of the survey and, from memory, at the time of them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived Control Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of the survey and, from memory, at the time of them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Questions re menstrual health issues in the previous 12 months. These questions had little or no overlap with ALSWH questions. Respondents answered three different sets of questions depending on whether they were in menses, perimenopausal or menopausal. 

Menopausal questions:
Ovarian Pain or Cramps; Abdominal Cramps; Endometriosis; Very sensitive, tender or sore breasts; Tiredness, worse than in the past; Exhaustion; A desire to have more order in my life; Pre-full moon tension but few people notice; Pre-full moon tension noticed by many; Feeling bloated; Hot flushes; Sudden sweats during the day; Weight gain; Emotional or sad; Feeling dizzy or faint; Food or drink cravings; Nausea or vomiting; Feeling uncomfortable in the presence of others more frequently; Difficulty concentrating; Being more forgetful at times; Feeling anxious; Having bursts of energy; Having back aches; Mood swings - rapid changes in how you feel; Headaches; Pimples, dry skin, greasy skin, erratic skin in general.

Perimenopausal:
Ovarian Pain or Cramps; Abdominal Pain; Abdominal Cramps; Endometriosis; Painful periods; Heavy periods; Heavy periods that are worse than before; Heavy periods that last longer than before; Normal periods that last longer than before; Period cycles that are substantially longer than in the past; Irregular period cycles; Very sensitive, tender or sore breasts; Tiredness, worse than in the past; Exhaustion; A desire to have more order in my life; Pre-menstrual tension but few people notice; Pre-menstrual tension noticed by many; Feeling bloated; Hot flushes; Sudden sweats during the day; Feeling relief or appreciation when my periods arrive; Feeling upset or disappointed when my periods arrive; Weight gain; Crying for no reason; Feeling dizzy or faint; Food or drink cravings; Nausea or vomiting; Trouble breathing.

Menses:
Abdominal Cramps; Endometriosis; Painful periods; Heavy periods; Skipped periods; Heavy clotting, slight clotting; Constipation and other unusual bowel movements; Swollen breasts; Very sensitive, tender or sore breasts; Severe tiredness; Exhaustion; Tired or aching legs; A desire for everything to be neater and more tidy; Pre-menstrual tension but few people noticed; Pre-menstrual tension noticed by many; Intense irritation with others; Feeling bloated; Feeling bothered or inconvenienced by my periods; Feeling controlled by my periods; Weight gain; Emotional or sad; Feeling dizzy or faint; Food or drink cravings; Nausea or vomiting.

These items were collected by the respondents being asked whether they had these symptoms in the previous 12 months "Yes, definitely"; "Yes, sometimes"; "No, not much"; "No, not at all"</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of the survey and, from memory, at the time of them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kessler-10 Psychological Distress Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of the survey and, from memory, at the time of them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visits to health practitioners in the previous 12 months, duplicating items from the ALSWH. For doctors frequency of visits, for other practitioners Yes/No:
A family doctor or another General Practitioner (GP); A hospital doctor (eg in outpatients or casualty); A specialist doctor; Physiotherapist; Counsellor / Psychologist / Social worker; A community nurse, practice nurse, or nurse practitioner; Optician / Optometrist; Dietitian; Podiatrist; Massage therapist; Naturopath / Herbalist; Chiropractor; Osteopath; Acupuncturist; Other alternative health practitioner (eg aromatherapist, homeopath, reflexologist, iridologist); An Esoteric Practitioner

</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the 12 months prior to the survey and, from memory, in the 12 months prior to them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>BMI</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of the survey and, from memory, at the time of them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>History of weekly alcohol usage, question designed specifically for this survey:
In each life decade - nil, 1-7, 8-14, 15+; 12 months before attending their first Universal medicine event.
Current usage, copied from ALSWH: &gt; 1 per day, 1 per day, 1-6 times per week, &lt; once per week, not for past 12 months, not for past five years.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of the survey and, from memory, at the time of them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleep quality questionnaire as copied from ALSWH which used questions from the Nottingham health profile sleep subscale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of the survey and, from memory, at the time of them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight loss strategies employed in the previous 12 months. This was done through the respondents answering the following questions on a Yes/No basis. These questions were copied from the ALSWH survey:
Commercial weight loss programs (eg Weight Watchers, Lite n' Easy, Sureslim, Jenny Craig); Meal replacements or slimming products (eg OPTIFAST, Herbalife); Exercise; Cut down on the size of meals or between meal snacks; Cut down on fats (low fat) and / or sugars; Low glycaemic index (GI) diet; Diet book diets (eg Atkins, Zone, CSIRO diet, Liver Cleansing diet); Laxatives, diuretics or diet pills (eg Xenical, Reductil); Fasting; Smoking; Other</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of the survey and, from memory, at the time of them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tobacco consumption as per ALSWH question: Daily; At least weekly (but not daily); Less often than weekly; Not at all</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of the survey and, from memory, at the time of them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weekly time spent on activities  as per ALSWH question:
Full time paid work; Part-time paid work; Casual paid work; Home duties (own / family home); Work without pay (eg family business); Looking for work; Unpaid voluntary work; Active leisure (eg walking, exercise,; sport); Passive leisure (eg TV, music, reading,; relaxing); Studying</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of the survey and, from memory, at the time of them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feeling rushed questionnaire as employed by ALSWH surveys.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of the survey and, from memory, at the time of them attending their first Universal Medicine event.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This question was designed for this survey, with the respondents responding to a question for the current usage of the below  &gt; 1 per day, 1 per day, 1-6 times per week, &lt; once per week, not for past 12 months, not for past five years:

Coffee, tea, energy drinks or anything with caffeine; Items with added or concentrated sugar in it (sweets, mints, cakes, biscuits,; chewing gum, ice cream, flavoured yoghurt, healthbars, chocolate, dried fruit,; lemonade or soda, coffee, tea or other); Salty foods (crisps, salted nuts or similar); Dairy (cheese, yoghurt, ice cream, milk, butter, cream even if part of another dish; like cheeseburger or many cakes); Alcohol (beer, wine, spirits)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of filling in the survey.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participant in Universal Medicine workshops and lectures</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Summary analysis, regression analysis</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>14/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>5/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>407</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>5/09/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Portugal</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Germany</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Norway</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Colombia</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Christoph Schnelle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Queensland
Herston Road
Herston QLD 4007</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Christoph Schnelle</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Queensland
Herston Road
Herston QLD 4007</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current study is part of a larger quantitative, cross-sectional survey of women. A sample of 461 female UM participants from 17 countries responded to 43 questions taken from the Australian Longitudinal Study of Womens Health (ALSWH). The survey compared health indicators for UM participants with those of ALSWH respondents. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>School of Public Health Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Faculty of Medicine
University of Queensland
Herston Road
Herston QLD 4007</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CS23062015</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Christoph Schnelle</name>
      <address>School of Public Health, Faculty of Medicine
University of Queensland
Herston Road
Herston QLD 4007</address>
      <phone>+61266244242</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christoph.schnelle@uq.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Christoph Schnelle</name>
      <address>School of Public Health, Faculty of Medicine
University of Queensland
Herston Road
Herston QLD 4007</address>
      <phone>+61266244242</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christoph.schnelle@uq.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Christoph Schnelle</name>
      <address>School of Public Health, Faculty of Medicine
University of Queensland
Herston Road
Herston QLD 4007</address>
      <phone>+61266244242</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christoph.schnelle@uq.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>