<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308022">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000594224</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of chromosomal abnormalities by fluorescent in-situ-hyberdisation (FISH),  and quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) in Multiple Myeloma patients and correlations with treatment outcomes.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study for chromosomal abnormalities by fluorescent in-situ-hyberdisation (FISH),  and quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) in Multiple Myeloma patients and correlations with treatment outcomes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CAMM (Chromosomal abnormalities in Multiple Myeloma)</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chromosomal Abnormalities in Multiple Myeloma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Myeloma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Multiple Myeloma (MM) is a plasma cell dyscrasia resulting in high levels of monoclonal immunoglobulin (Ig) production leading to immunosuppression and other physiological disturbances. 
A median survival of about 2 years is usually obtained with conventional chemotherapy, however trials using 
high-dose therapy with subsequent autologous stem cell rescue have improved the remission rate, event-free survival, and overall survival (OS) in certain cohorts of patients. Various chromosomal abnormalities have been reported in MM patients but the 13q- and t(4:14) abnormalities are present in over 50% of abnormal plasma cells in these patients though the clinical significance of this has not been elucidated. Reports have linked the presence of the 13q- abnormality with 
altered therapeutic responses to common treatments. 
Strong evidence now indicates that conventional cytogenetics fails to recognise about 50% of these abnormalities because of slow growth of MM cells in cell culture as compared to fluorescence in situ hyberdisation (FISH) or quantitative polymerase chain reaction (qPCR). Both techniques are representing molecular high technology methods studying and amplifying both cell nuecleus ontent Deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) and Ribonucleic acid (RNA) of myeloma cells. Furthermore FISH detects chromosomal aberration in both actively dividing cells and interphase nuclei. 
Therefore our approach utilises patients blood and bone marrow samples at time of diagnosis or relapse assessed by commercially available probes for FISH analysis on CD 138+ cells and 
reliably detects the prognostically significant genomic aberration, thus allowing clinicians to assess the 
biological risk of disease progression in patients with multiple myeloma (MM). The bone marrow studies will be performed as part of routine investigations for myeloma with extra 10 ml sample to conduct this research. The procedure takes approximately 30 min. 
This project will involve the validation of Fluorescence In-Situ Hybridisation (FISH) analysis of the 13q- and t(4:14) chromosomal abnormalities and development of rapid qPCR assays for the detection of these chromosomal abnormalities in bone marrow samples from denovo patients with MM. 
The aim of this project is to develop rapid qPCR assays for analysis of 13q- and t(4:14) chromosomal abnormalities and correlate the frequency of these abnormalities with treatment modalities and outcomes. 
The impact of these abnormalities in the context of high-dose therapy (HDT) or conventional therapy will help to identify those patients who would maximally benefit from HDT and those who would be refractory to HDT and might benefit from other therapeutic options. 
The Launceston General Hospital (LGH) is a tertiary referral centre of North and North West of Tasmania. We currently have at the LGH, 35-40 patients diagnosed with multiple myeloma with approximately 15-20 new cases every year and this observationall study will run for a total of 4 years ending in Dec 2011.</interventions>
    <comparator>not applicable</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This study aims at evaluating the prognostic value of chromosome 13 deletions as well as t(4,14) as detected 
by the FISH/qPCR techniques in multiple myeloma patients. The impact of these abnormalities in the context of high-dose therapy (HDT) or conventional therapy will help to identify those patients who would maximallybenefit from HDT and those who would be refractory to HDT and might benefit from other therapeutic options.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at diagnosis of multiple myeloma or at time of relapse of the disease</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Study of the prevalence of these chromosomal abnormalities in newly diagnosed and relapsed multiple myeloma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>yearly for 4 years ending in Dec 2011.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who are newly diagnosed with multiple myeloma or who has relpased multiple myeloma and are above 18 years old.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients under 18 years. Since this is an observational study, no other exclusion criteria.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Clifford Craig Medical Research Trust</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 1963
Launceston
Tasmania 7250</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Clifford Craig Medical Research Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 1963
Launceston
Tasmania 7250</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Launceston General Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Charels Street, Launceston, Tasmania</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims at evaluating the prognostic value of chromosome 13 deletions as well as t(4,14) as detected 
by the FISH/qPCR techniques in multiple myeloma patients. The impact of these abnormalities in the context of high-dose therapy (HDT) or conventional therapy will help to identify those patients who would maximally benefit from HDT and those who would be refractory to HDT and might benefit from other therapeutic options. 
Furthermore, it would be of great value for determining the prognosis of the disease to study the prognostic factors of myeloma, including -13q and t(4;14), at the time of diagnosis, prior to and after transplantation, and at the time of relapse, with special emphasis on the outcome of patients who underwent HDT. 
Moreover, these data might supply valuable guidance regarding identification and cloning of a MM-tumour 
suppressor gene.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tasmania Health and Medical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Executive officer
University of Tasmania (UTAS) Research and Development Office
GPO Box 252-01
Hobart
Tasmania 7001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/09/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0009451</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Assoc Prof Alhossain Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital
Charles St
Launceston
Tasmania 7250</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6348 7111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>+61 3 6348 7111</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Assoc Prof Alhossain Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital
Charles St
Launceston
Tasmania 7250</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6348 7111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Assoc Prof Alhossain Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital
Charles St
Launceston
Tasmania 7250</address>
      <phone>+61 3 6348 7111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>