<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82725">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/04/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/04/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000180314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of Mepilex dressings on radiation-induced skin reactions in women with breast cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of mepilex lite dressings on the management of radiation-induced skin reactions in women with breast cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Radiation-induced skin reactions in women that receive radiation therapy for breast cancer.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Mepilex Lite dressings consist of a thin flexible foam with silicon webbing which does not react with chemicals in and on the skin. The dressings will be used to cover parts of skin that shows signs of radiation-induced skin reactions (mild erythema). Progression from mild to severe erythema and to dry desquamation will be monitored and compared to parts of the irradiated skin that is treated with standard skin care (in-patient controls).
The dressings will be applied from the moment erythema is seen (usually 2 weeks into the 5 week treatment). They will be replaced weekly for the duration of the treatment and for four weeks after treatment has been completed.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard care for radiation-induced skin reactions in Dunedin Hospital is an emollient aquaous cream. The cream will be applied to the skin (topically) daily from the moment radiation treatment starts till 4 week after completion of treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Slower progression from mild to severe erythema and lack of progression to dry desquamation in areas of skin that are covered with the dressing compared to standard treatment. Erythema will be assesses by a standard Radiation Induced Skin Reaction Assessment Scale (RISRAS) and by digital photographs (Canon, with customized setting and photoshop software)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three times a week from the moment erythema is seen (usually in week 2 of treatment) till end of treatment (which is 5 weeks). Further time points are 1 week and 4 weeks after completion of treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mepliex Lite dressings decrease erythema by a cooling effect of the skin. This will be assessed by skin temperature measurements using a Derma Temp infrared surface skin scanner (Exergen).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three times a week from the moment erythema is seen (usually in week 2 of treatment) till end of treatment (which is 5 weeks). Further time points are 1 week and 4 weeks after completion of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All women that are having radiation therapy for breast cancer and have not had a previous radical mastectomy at Dunedin Hospital;, Department of Oncology (Radiation Therapy)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women who have had a previous radical mastectomy are excluded from this trial</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Patients act as their own controls. Parts of the skin that show erythema will be covered with dressings and part will receive standard care. If the dressings prove to stop progression to dry desquamation and the standard treatment does not, all affected skin areas will be covered by dressing. If there is an adverse reaction to the dressings, all skin will be treated with standard skin care.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/05/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/06/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/05/2009</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>10/05/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>28</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>South Island, Dunedin</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago, Wellington</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Mein Street,
PO Box 7343
Wellington South</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago, Wellington</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Mein Street,
PO Box 7343
Wellington South</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Otago Distric Health Board (Dunedin Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>201 Great King Street
PO Box  1921
Dunedin</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Radiation therapy of the breast aims to eradicate all possible remaining tumour cells and, in addition, can cause skin reactions, varying from a slight reddening of the skin to itching, cracking, blistering or peeling, leaving the underlying tissues exposed. Although there are several ways to manage radiation-induced skin reactions, there is currently no standard protocol in New Zealand. 

A promising new range of Swedish silicon-foam skin dressings, (Mepilex Lite, Molnlycke), is currently in use in many hospitals in New Zealand for the treatment of burns. This project aims to investigate the cooling effects of the dressings on radiation-induced skin reactions in 40 women undergoing radiation treatment for breast cancer in Dunedin Hospital. When reddening of the skin is seen, several parts of the irradiated breast area will be covered with dressings, whilst the other parts will be treated with a moisturizing cream. Skin condition will be assessed three times a week for the duration of treatment, as well as 1 and 4 weeks after treatment has been completed, using an established skin assessment scale, digital photographs and heat measurements.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Diggelmann, K.V., Zytkovicz, A.E., Tuaine, J.M., Bennett, N.C., Kelly, L.E., Herst, P.M. Mepilex Lite dressings for the management of radiation-induced erythema: a systematic inpatient controlled clinical trial. Br J Radiol. 83(995): 971-934 (2010).</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Lower South Island Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>229 Morray Place
PO Box 5849
Dunedin</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/05/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/03/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/82725-Diggelmann,  BJR 2010.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Patries Herst</name>
      <address>Department of Radiation Therapy
University of Otago, Wellington
Mein Street
PO Box 7343
Wellington South 6242</address>
      <phone>+64-4-3855475 ext 4753</phone>
      <fax>+64-4-3855375</fax>
      <email>patries.herst@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Noelle Bennett</name>
      <address>Department of Oncology (Radiation Therapy) 
Dunedin Hospital
201 Great King Street
PO Box 1921
Dunedin</address>
      <phone>phone:+64-3-4747047</phone>
      <fax>fax:+64-3-4747656</fax>
      <email>noelle.bennett@otagodhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Patries Herst</name>
      <address>Department of Radiation Therapy
University of Otago, Wellington
Mein Street
PO Box 7343
Wellington South 6242</address>
      <phone>+64-4-3855475 ext 4753</phone>
      <fax>+64-4-3855375</fax>
      <email>patries.herst@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Patries Herst</name>
      <address>Department of radiation Therapy
University of Otago, Wellington
POBox 7343
Wellington South
Postcode 6242</address>
      <phone>+64-4-3855475</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>patries.herst@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>