<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320881">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/03/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/07/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000585022</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Moving forward in anorexia nervosa treatment.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of the Loughborough Eating disorders Activity therapy versus general cognitive behavior therapy efficacy in reducing pathological exercise behaviours and cognitions.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1112-6553</utrn>
    <trialacronym>LEAP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) protocol 634922</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anorexia nervosa</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Eating disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention tested is an extended manualised cognitive behaviour therapy.The overarching aim is the promotion of healthy (i.e., non-excessive/non-eating disorder related) attitudes, beliefs, and behaviours toward both structured exercise and physical activity in general. It is important to emphasise that the aim of the treatment program is not to make patients stop exercising, but rather to educate them about what constitutes healthy/non-excessive exercise and equip them with the knowledge and skills that will enable them to regain control of their exercise behaviour in order to participate in age, goal and health-status appropriate exercise. The program is designed around four core themes of education, guided discovery, cognitive skills, and relapse prevention. Specifically the following are addressed:
Education about the cognitive view on the maintenance of excessive exercise
Promotion of insight into the factors affecting (maintaining) the patients attitudes, beliefs and behaviours toward exercise
Education about what constitutes healthy exercise
Introduction to the cognitive skills and strategies necessary to challenge maladaptive attitudes, beliefs and behaviours toward exercise
Introduction to alternative (adaptive) emotion coping strategies
Education about relapse prevention
 
We expect reduced driven exercise behaviour and cognitions.
The intervention will be administered during day time hours by a trained therapist. The therapy will comprise 8 weekly one hour sessions and is followed by 6-8 months of weekly cognitive behaviour therapy and then 6 months follow-up after that. The cognitive behaviour therapy admistered in the next 6-8 months (or 8-10 months in the control therapy group) is that developed by Pike et al. (Pike KM, Walsh BT, Vitousek K, et al. Cognitive behavior therapy in the post-hospitalization treatment of anorexia nervosa. Am J Psychiatry,2003; 160, 2046-2049.) All therapy is administered on an individual basis.</interventions>
    <comparator>Cognitive behaviour therapy (CBT) is an active treatment aimed at restoring weight and normal eating habits by challenging underlying beliefs and thoughts through cognitive restructuring and behaviour change.  The CBT utilised in this study  follows three clearly defined phases of treatment and to accommodate the present study aims the phases are 34 weeks duration. The three broad phases are:
Phase I: Building trust and setting treatment parameters. In the first phase of treatment, the principal aims are to build a positive therapeutic alliance, assessing key features of the eating disorder, providing education about starvation symptoms and other related topics, giving a rationale and advice for restoring normal nutrition and body weight, and prescribing eating patterns and establishing a regular eating pattern. Interventions are aimed at regulating the chronic dieting with the focus on helping patients to eat regular meals at regular times.
Phase II: Changing beliefs related to food and weight, then broadening the scope of therapy.  The principal aims of this phase of treatment are to continue the emphasis on weight gain and normalising eating and to bring these about by reframing relapse, identifying dysfunctional thoughts, schemas and thinking patterns, developing cognitive restructuring skills, modifying self-concept, and developing an interpersonal focus in therapy. 
Phase III: Preventing relapse and preparing for termination. The final phase, relapse prevention, clarifies the changes the patient has already made, and prepares the patient for residual problems that may be found once treatment has been terminated.
We expect improved weight and reduced eating disorder thoughts and behaviours after the CBT therapy. 
CBT will be delivered once over   8-10 months  in 50 minute weekly sessions and followup is to 6 months. It is delivered on an individual (not group) basis by a psychologist. Both the intervention and the comparator group recieve the same cognitive behaviour therapy but it is shorter in the intervention group to allow for additional sessions of Loughborough Eating and Activity TheraPy (LEAP).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in pathological exercise behaviours and cognitions by questionnaires (The Commitment to Exercise Scale , Compulsive Exercise Test , Exercise Beliefs Questionnaire )</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 10 sessions and after 20 sessions, end therapy after 34 sessions or final session, 3 and 6 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improved weight , by measurement  weight with balance beam scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 10 sessions and after 20 sessions, end therapy after 34 sessions or final session, 3 and 6 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in eating disorder cognitions by interview (the Eating Disorder Examination)</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 10 sessions and after 20 sessions, end therapy after 34 sessions or final session, 3 and 6 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age &gt;18 years with primary diagnosis of anorexia nervosa  according to American Psychiatric Association Diagnostic and Statistical Manual version IV (DSM-IV) of either the restrictive or binge-purge type. 
Engaging in some form of exercise behaviour over the previous week. Therefore, they will each score &gt;/=1 on item 2 on the Exercise Participation Screening Questionnaire.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of psychosis or bipolar disorder
A high level of suicide risk and/or medical compromise precluding outpatient care and/or body mass index (BMI)  &lt; 14.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Initial contact will be by clinic referral or inquiry from advertising. Potential subjects will be screened for eligibility either over the phone or via email. Screening will identify those patients at least 18 years and likely to meet eligibility criteria, particularly current exercise. Those deemed eligible will be scheduled for further assessment including obtaining informed consent. Assessment procedures will include an exercise frequency measure, BMI and the structured clinical  interview for the diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders (Spitzer et al., 1992)) to determine diagnosis/co-morbid diagnoses and suicide risk. Allocation will be by an independent  investigator blind to the findings of the assessment (accepting that the person is eligible).</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization will use an internet assisted scheme (sealedenvelope.com) according to biased coin method and will be stratified by location, subtype of illness and whether a participant is on psychotropic medication.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>19/08/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/01/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>78</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>2/05/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Loughborough</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>New York</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South DC
1797 NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Sydney</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Loughborough</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Leicestershire, UK
LE11 3TU</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United Kingdom</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Prof Evelyn Attia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Psychiatry
Columbia University
21 Bloomingdale Road
White Plains, NY 10605
USA</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose is to investigate an enhanced psychotherapy for anorexia nervosa. 
 
Anorexia nervosa is a serious psychological illness that is associated with much distress and many difficulties for people living with the illness.  Many people do not get better with current therapies. Dr Meyer and her colleagues in Loughborough (England) have developed an enhanced form of cognitive behaviour therapy (CBT), which is a psychotherapy or talking therapy for anorexia nervosa. CBT in anorexia nervosa treatment focuses on how people think about eating, weight and shape and what they do about them (e.g. diet to lose weight). The therapy we are testing in this study has been enhanced  by focussing more on some features of anorexia nervosa that have been found to be prevent people getting better from anorexia nervosa.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>not applicable</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Touyz S, Meyer C, Taranis L, La Puma M, Hay, PJ., Arcelus J, Madden S, Pike K, Crosby R. The loughborough eating disorders activity therapy (leap) - a new approach to driven exercise in anorexia nervosa. Research paper
-	Eating Disorders Research Society 16th Annual Meeting, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 	USA, 7-9 October 7-9 2010. 
Hay P., Meyer C, Touyz S Taranis L, Arcelus J, Madden S, Pike K, Crosby R.The Loughborough Eating Disorders Activity Therapy (LEAP)  A new approach to driven exercise in Anorexia Nervosa. Workshop
-	Academy of Eating Disorders International Conference. Miami, Florida USA. April 28-30 2011.
Hay P. The Loughborough Eating Disorders Activity Therapy (LEAP)  A new approach to driven exercise in Anorexia Nervosa.
Presented at an Invited Symposium at the 34th National Conference of The Australian Association for Cognitive and Behaviour Therapy, October 2011 Enhancing the diagnosis and treatment of patients with anorexia nervosa.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Western Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 1797
Penrith South DC
NSW 1797</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/02/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H7732</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Phillipa Hay</name>
      <address>School of Medicine
University of Western Sydney (UWS)
Locked bag 1797
Penrith South DC NSW 1797</address>
      <phone>+61 412330428</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.hay@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Phillipa Hay</name>
      <address>School of Medicine
University of Western Sydney (UWS)
Locked bag 1797
Penrith South DC NSW 1797</address>
      <phone>+61 412330428</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>treatmenttrials@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Phillipa Hay</name>
      <address>School of Medicine
University of Western Sydney (UWS)
Locked bag 1797
Penrith South DC NSW 1797</address>
      <phone>+61 412330428</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.hay@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Phillipa Hay</name>
      <address>Centre for Health Research
School of Medicine
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith UWS 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 412330428</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 46203891</fax>
      <email>p.hay@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>