<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82030">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/05/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/06/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000317493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Attention re-training for social phobia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does attention re-training provide an additive or multiplicative effect when used in conjunction with group cognitive behavioural therapy in reducing the symptoms and severity of social phobia in outpatients with a primary diagnosis of social phobia?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Social Phobia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will be completing our highly efficacious, best-practice Cognitive Behavioural Group program for Social Phobia. The program consists of 12 weekly sessions, each of approximately 2.5 hours duration, conducted over consecutive weeks.  This enhanced group program has been developed through an National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) funded Randomised Controlled Trial (RCT) at our clinic and has been shown to have treatment effects superior to standard treatment packages for social phobia. Treatment will be led by a clinical psychologist or graduate student in clinical psychology in groups of between six to eight participants. 
    In addition to all participants receiving the best available treatment through our clinic, each group of participants will also be block allocated to receive either active attention re-training, or a placebo attention task as an adjunct to treatment. In both conditions participants will be required to complete an attention task approximately ten minutes in length which is delivered via a computer program. This task will be conducted at the beginning of each group session at the clinic, and is then completed as homework by the participants on their personal computer for the subsequent six days prior to the next session. Participants will each be provided with a USB flash drive from which they can both run the program and save their data (coded by a de-identified number) for retrieval by the research assistant. Arrangements will be made to loan computers to those participants who do not have a computer at home.
   The attention re-training task involves simultaneous presentation of a socially threatening word (e.g. foolish) with a neutral word (e.g. portion) followed by a probe in the position of one of these words. Participants are instructed to indicate the position of the probe as quickly as possible using the left and right arrow key on their keyboard. In the condition designed to train attention away from threat the probe will always replace the neutral verbal cue. In the placebo condition the probe will appear in the position vacated by the threatening or neutral cue with equal probability. Thus participants in the placebo condition will experience all the same training contexts as those in the re-training condition, but will not be trained to focus away from threat.   
    Four weeks after the final session of the 12 week group program all participants will be complete the Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule 4th Edition (ADIS IV) and the same battery of measures that was collected at the initial assessment. This same procedure will also be completed six months after the date of group completion. Any participants who require further follow-up at the completion of the program will be provided with suitable referral options for ongoing care.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is reduction in symptoms and severity of social phobia.
Measures - 
Diagnosis: All participants will attend a clinical interview aimed at providing a formal diagnosis which will be made on the basis of the Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule (ADIS-IV: (Di Nardo, Brown, &amp; Barlow, 1994) according to DSM-IV criteria. All diagnostic interviews will be audio-taped and a random 25% will be listened to and scored by an experienced interviewer to determine diagnostic reliability for this study.
Questionnaire Measures: To assess symptoms and severity of social phobia four measures will be used: The Social Phobia Scale (SPS; Mattick and Clarke 1998) assesses fear and avoidance of situations where there is the prospect of being observed by others (performance fears). The Social Interaction Anxiety Scale (SIAS; Mattick and Clarke 1998) assesses distress when meeting or talking to other people (interaction fears). The Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale - Self-Report version (LSAS-SR; Baker, Heinrichs et al. 2002) assesses fear and avoidance for 11 interaction and 13 performance situations. The Personal Report of Confidence as a Speaker (PRCS; Paul 1966) measures fear of public speaking. The SPS, SIAS, LSAS-SR, and PRCS have all been demonstrated to have sound psychometric properties. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Four weeks after the final session of the 12 week group program all participants will be complete the ADIS IV and the same battery of measures that was collected at the initial assessment. This same procedure will also be completed six months after the date of group completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcomes are a reduction in the level of interference caused by social phobia to overall functioning, including daily activities and health utilisation.
Measures:
In order to examine socially relevant treatment effects, two measures will be included to assess broader aspects of overall functioning in addition to basic symptomatology and diagnosis. The SF12 (Ware, Kosinski et al. 1996) assesses the overall degree to which an individuals symptoms influence his or her life and cause an impact on their daily activities and health utilisation, and the Life Interference Scale is a series of Likert scales which measure the degree to which symptoms limit various aspects of an individuals life. Finally, participants will complete the Anxiety Change Expectancy Scale (ACES; Dezois and Westra 2005) which is a reliable and valid measure of expectancies for changing anxiety.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four weeks after the final session of the 12 week group program all participants will be complete the same battery of measures that was collected at the initial assessment. This same procedure will also be completed six months after the date of group completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must meet Diagnostic &amp; Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 4th Edition (DSM-IV) criteria for social phobia. If multiple anxiety disorders are present, social phobia must be the principal diagnosis based on severity and life interference. Participants will be required to be fluent in their use of English.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current, active suicidal ideation, organic mental disorders, a co-morbid psychotic disorder, or current, unmanaged substance dependence. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation to a treatment condition is managed by the Research Coordinator from a central administration site. The Research Coordinator is contacted when it is determined that a participant is eligible for treatment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a computer generated randomisation table.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Both the participants in the trial, and the therapists delivering the treatment are blind to the allocation of treatment condition.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Ronald M Rapee</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the study is to find out whether the addition of an attention re-training component to our best-practice treatment program can provide a significantly greater treatment effect, and enhance the maintenance of effects. This will inform the development of future programs to help people suffering from social phobia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University, Centre for Emotional Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/05/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RO5197</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Ron Rapee, Chief Investigator</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
Balaclava Rd
North Ryde NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98508032</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 98508062</fax>
      <email>Ron.Rapee@psy.mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Leigh Carpenter, Research Coordinator</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
Balaclava Rd
North Ryde NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98507971</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 98508062</fax>
      <email>Leigh.Carpenter@psy.mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>