<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367081">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001030662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised clinical trial comparing peri-discharge management of Acute Decompensated Heart Failure with usual clinical care in terms of rates of death, rates of hospitalisation, health care utilisation, and cost-effectiveness.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised clinical trial comparing peri-discharge management of Acute Decompensated Heart Failure with usual clinical care in terms of rates of death, rates of hospitalisation, health care utilisation, and cost-effectiveness. 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1157-8380</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The IMPERATIVE-HF trial </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>450 eligible patients admitted with Acute Decompensated Heart Failure (ADHF) will be enrolled and randomised to Natruiretic Peptide (NP)-guided group with treatment adjusted if NP levels are raised, or standard clinically-guided care. Baseline tests including NP levels will be measured by a blood tests at admission and then repeated on the day of discharge. Day of discharge will be determined by the attending physician and care will be transferred to the research team at point of discharge for the NP group to manage follow up visits. Pre-discharge NP levels will only be available for patients randomised to the NP group. Off-label measurement of NP levels outside of guidelines approved indications, will be discouraged and prohibited by study design in both study groups. Patients randomised to usual care will be managed according to usual ADHF care. Patients in the NP group will receive management guided by NP levels. All study participants will be monitored for treatment adherence by phone or in person visits at 2 days, 2, 6 &amp; 12 weeks and additional visits will be arranged as required.
NP group - As for usual care but for patients with NTproBNP &gt;1000pg/ml prior to discharge, delay of discharge for 24hrs will be considered to optimise diuretic and other HF therapy. After discharge, NP levels will be measured during HF nurse review at home within 2 days of discharge. Patients with NT-proBNP &gt;1000pg/ml will receive alternate day telephone contact, weekly in-home HF nurse clinical review and 2-weekly HF clinic visits until NTproBNP &lt;1000pg/ml. NTproBNP / estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) testing will be performed at least weekly to guide up-titration of HF treatment  including increased diuretic dose if congestion or volume overload present, addition of spironolactone, alternate up-titration of ACE inhibitor and beta-blocker doses on a weekly basis.
The overall duration of the intervention period is 12 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual Care as per current standard of care pathways at Christchurch &amp; Auckland Hospitals.
Management: Usual care group  patients will receive usual care for ADHF including in-hospital education about HF, weight self-monitoring, low salt diet, an exercise program, review in primary care and HF clinic within 2 weeks of discharge, coordinated input from district nursing and allied health at discretion of attending physician to ensure adequate support and housing, optimisation of medications according to HF guidelines. Further clinic follow-up will be guided by assessment at the 2-week visit.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first Heart Failure readmission or all cause death within 90 days</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first Heart Failure readmission or all cause death within 180 days</outcome>
      <timepoint>180 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first Heart Failure readmission within 30 days; within 90 days; and within 180 days.</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 30 days; within 90 days; and within 180 days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to all cause death within 30 days; within 90 days; and within 180 days</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 30 days; within 90 days; and within 180 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients aged &gt;18 year, living independently and able to provide informed consent, admitted with ADHF as evidenced by typical clinical features plus either radiological evidence of Heart Failure or an NTproBNP level &gt;1000pg/ml. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A primary diagnosis of acute coronary syndrome (ACS), myocarditis/pericarditis, pericardial constriction, a life expectancy due to non-cardiac disease of &lt;6 months, concurrent severe hepatic or pulmonary disease ,severe renal impairment (plasma creatinine &gt;250 micro mol/L), severe valvular disease requiring surgery, severe aortic stenosis (valve area &lt;1cm^2), or HF due to mitral stenosis, or a patient under consideration for cardiac transplantation</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A computer generated randomisation sequence arranged in permuted blocks will be generated prior to any recruitment. Once a patient has met inclusion/exclusion criteria and given written informed consent, the next sequential randomisation envelope will be opened. Randomisation will be stratified above and below 75 years of age.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated randomisation sequence arranged in permuted blocks </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Primary and secondary clinical outcomes will be analysed on an intention to treat basis as time-to-event data using Cox proportional hazards regression models. Health care utilisation over 90 days including all hospital admissions and lengths of stay, nurse visits, clinical tests, clinician times and therapy costs will be summarized individually and totaled for each patient to allow a comparison between NP-guided and usual care groups to determine their relative cost-effectiveness. 

Sample Size and Power Analysis : based on an expected 90-day event rate of 35% a cohort of 450 patients will provide 80% power to show a 33% reduction in this event rate in the BNP-guided group and 90% power to show a 40% reduction, with a two-tailed alpha level of 0.05'.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/11/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/11/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>450</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Christchurch Heart Institute. University of Otago </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3, 110 Stanley Street, Auckland. 1010 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Heart Foundation of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 17-160,
Greenlane,
Auckland 1546</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>450 eligible patients admitted with ADHF will be enrolled and randomised to NP-guided or clinically-guided care. Baseline tests including NP levels will be measured at admission and then repeated on the day of discharge. Day of discharge will be determined by the attending physician and care will be transferred to the research team at point of discharge. Pre-discharge NP levels will only be available for patients randomised to the NP group. Off-label measurement of NP levels outside of guidelines approved indications, will be discouraged and prohibited by study design in both study groups. Patients randomised to usual care will be managed according to usual ADHF care. Patients in the BNP group will receive management guided by NP levels
Management: Usual care group  patients will receive usual care for ADHF including in-hospital education about HF, weight self-monitoring, low salt diet, an exercise program, review in primary care and HF clinic within 2 weeks of discharge, coordinated input from district nursing and allied health at discretion of attending physician to ensure adequate support and housing, optimisation of medications according to HF guidelines. Further clinic follow-up will be guided by assessment at the 2-week visit.   
NP group -   As for usual care but for patients with NTproBNP &gt;1000pg/ml prior to discharge, delay of discharge for 24hrs will be considered to optimise diuretic and other HF therapy. After discharge, NP levels will be measured during HF nurse review at home within 2 days of discharge. Patients with NT-proBNP &gt;1000pg/ml will receive alternate day telephone contact, weekly in-home HF nurse clinical review and 2-weekly HF clinic visits until NTproBNP &lt;1000pg/ml.  NTproBNP / estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR)  testing will be performed at least weekly to guide up-titration of HF treatment  including increased diuretic dose if congestion or volume overload present, addition of spironolactone, alternate up-titration of ACE inhibitor and beta-blocker doses on a weekly basis. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 The Terrace
Wellington Central
Wellington 6011 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/CEN/147</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/09/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard Troughton</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140 </address>
      <phone>+643 364 0640</phone>
      <fax>+643 364 1115</fax>
      <email>richard.troughton@cdhb.health.nz </email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lorraine Skelton</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140 </address>
      <phone>+643 364 1063</phone>
      <fax>+643 364 1115</fax>
      <email>lorraine.skelton@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard Troughton</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140 </address>
      <phone>+643 364 0640</phone>
      <fax>+643 364 1115</fax>
      <email>richard.troughton@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lorraine Skelton</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140 </address>
      <phone>+643 364 1063</phone>
      <fax>+643 364 1115</fax>
      <email>lorraine.skelton@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>