<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371783">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000391370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>'Role of Tranexamic acid on blood loss in hip fracture patients'</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Role of Tranexamic acid on post operative blood loss and blood transfusion in intra capsular neck of femur fracture patients undergoing hip arthroplasty (total hip arthroplasty or hemiarthroplasty)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1189-6122</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ROTANOF</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Intra capsular neck of femur fractures</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention group - Patients presenting with intra-capsular neck of femur fractures undergoing arthroplasty (Total hip or hemiarthroplasty) will be administered intravenous Tranexamic acid in three doses (15mg/kg). First dose will be administered at the time of induction and remaining two at post operative eight and sixteen hours.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group - Patients with intra capsular neck of femur fractures requiring total hip or hemiarthroplasty. The control group will not be administered Tranexamic acid or any blood loss medications as compared to intervention group which will be administered intravenous Tranexamic acid in three doses.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of acute postoperative blood transfusion in patients presenting with intra capsular neck of femur fractures undergoing hemiarthroplasty or total hip arthroplasty.                               </outcome>
      <timepoint>Within seven days of administration of Tranexamic acid.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of acute post-operative deep vein thrombosis (DVT) which will be assessed with a bilateral lower limb doppler ultrasound.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day seven post administration of Tranexamic acid</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess whether the administration of TA in a three-dose intravenous protocol leads to a reduction in post-operative drop in Haemoglobin in the study population. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Hb check on post op day 1,3 and 5.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients with intra-capsular neck of femur fractures undergoing hemiarthroplasty (cemented or uncemented) or total hip arthroplasty (cemented, hybrid or uncemented) within 48 hrs from the time of injury.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Neck of femur fractures requiring fixation by other methods e.g. by cannulated screws, dynamic hip screw or intra-medullary nail device.
2.Patients presenting 48 hours from the time of injury. This includes patients transferred to Nepean hospital from other hospitals.
3.Contra-indication to the administration of TA - 
Previous history of thrombosis
Active thromboembolic disease (DVT,PE and cerebral thrombosis)
Other contraindication to the use of TA : 
Patients with acquired disturbances of colour vision
Patients with subarachnoid haemorrhage
Previous history of seizure
Creatinine clearance &lt; 30ml/min
Hypersensitivity to TA
4.Patients who are unable to provide informed consent.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment is done with the help of  central randomisation done by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based on 80% power to detect the minimum clinically important difference of 20% at a significant level of 0.05, 103 patients are required in each group. Allowing for 20% loss to follow up, we aim to recruit 125 patients. The minimum clinically important difference (MCID) of 20% we consider this difference to be necessary in order to justify the additional  cost of TA.
Intention to treat analysis will be performed in the primary analysis. A senior statistician will conduct all statistical analysis. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>29/03/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>250</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>15/04/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <postcode>2747 - Kingswood</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nepean Hospital (Nepean Blue Mountain Local Health District)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Nepean Hospital 
Derby Street
Kingswood, NSW, 2747</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Orthopaedic Department, Nepean Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Nepean Hospital 
Derby Street
Kingswood, NSW 2747</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose is to investigate the role of tranexamic acid (TA) in the setting of intra-capsular neck of femur fractures which is the type of broken hip. (TA) is a medicine (synthetic type of amino acid lysine) which is used to prevent excessive blood loss during surgery. (TA) is commonly used in elective joint replacement (Total hip and total knee replacement) and is recognized to reduce blood loss during surgery and the need of blood transfusion afterward. However we do not have as much evidence on its effect in the setting of broken bone in hip. We intend to explore the relationship between its use and blood loss after surgery and the need for blood transfusion.
If the patient agrees to participate in this study, they will be asked to sign the Person Responsible Consent Form. This study will be conducted over 1 to 2 years.
The treatment being investigated in this study is three doses of (TA) given intravenously at the time of surgery and 8 and 16 hours after surgery. 
 Study participants are put into two groups and given different treatments, and the results are compared to see whether one treatment is better. To ensure the groups are similar to start with, a computer allocates each study participant into a group randomly, Neither the doctor nor the study participant can decide which treatment the participant receives.
Once the patient agrees to participate in this trial, they will then be randomly allocated a number which decides whether they receive either 3 doses of (TA) (intervention group) or not. The first dose is given at the time of surgery and next two 8 and 16 hours post surgery.
Study hypothesis
  1.	Administration of intravenous TA in patients presenting with intra-capsular neck of femur fractures undergoing hemiarthroplasty or total hip arthroplasty reduces the rate of post-operative blood loss and blood transfusion. 
2.	The intravenous administration of TA is safe and is not associated with an increase in the rates of post-operative venous thromboembolic, cardiovascular or cerebrovascular events in this population.
Aims
This study aims to provide high quality evidence of the relative benefits and risks of the use of TA in the setting of emergency hemiarthroplasty or THA for the management of NOF fractures.  The results of this study will support and influence the future treatment of this common injury.
Primary outcome
1.	To determine the effect of administration of a three dose protocol of intravenous TA on the incidence of acute postoperative blood transfusion in patients presenting with intra capsular neck of femur fractures undergoing hemi or THA
Secondary outcomes
1.To assess the incidence of acute post-operative venous thromboembolic (deep vein thrombosis, pulmonary embolism), cardiovascular (acute myocardial infarction) and cerebrovascular events (stroke) in this study population
2.To assess whether the administration of TA in a three-dose intravenous protocol leads to a reduction in post-operative drop in Haemoglobin.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Nepean Blue Mountain Local Health District HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>NBMLHDHREC
Nepean Hospital
Derby Street
Kingswood, NSW 2747
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/02/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/Nepean 114 (Local reference 14/57)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yasser Khatib</name>
      <address>Orthopaedic Surgeon 
Nepean Hospital (NBMLHD)
2 Hope St
Penrith, NSW 2750
PO box 949, Penrith, NSW 2750</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4721 4434</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4732 3155</fax>
      <email>yasser@carefirstortho.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yasser Khatib</name>
      <address>Orthopaedic Surgeon 
Nepean Hospital (NBMLHD)
2 Hope St
Penrith, NSW 2750
PO box 949, Penrith, NSW 2750</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4721 4434</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4732 3155</fax>
      <email>yasser@carefirstortho.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yasser Khatib</name>
      <address>Orthopaedic Surgeon 
Nepean Hospital (NBMLHD)
2 Hope St
Penrith, NSW 2750
PO box 949, Penrith, NSW 2750</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4721 4434</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4732 3155</fax>
      <email>yasser@carefirstortho.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yasser Khatib</name>
      <address>2 Hope St
Penrith, NSW 2750
PO box 949, Penrith, NSW 2750</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4721 4434</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4732 3155</fax>
      <email>yasser@carefirstortho.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>