<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82342">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/10/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/10/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000558426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Home-based Physical Activity Program for Seniors</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Motivational interviewing to promote physical activity in older adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MOVES - Motivating Older adults to Value Exercise Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Adherence</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Body weight and composition</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Blood pressure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fitness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mental Health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study will evaluate the effects of two educational approaches, usual care and behavioural intervention and two motivational techniques, standard instruction and motivational interviewing. The intervention will be for an initial 6 months with a follow-up after a further 6 months during which participants will be asked to continue with their exercise but will not receive any further intervention. All participants will be asked to complete 150 minutes of moderate physical activity per week (3 X 50 minutes). All participants will attend a 2-hour workshop. One hour will outline the program, the safety aspects of exercise and participants will take part in a demonstration session. The other hour will be used to cover the specific intervention for each group.  
The behavioural intervention is based on the Stages of Change Model and consists of information and worksheets including topics such as goal setting, time management and overcoming barriers to exercise. The behavioural intervention will be included in a participant manual and will be briefly outlined (10-15 minutes) in part of the main workshop. 
The motivational interviewing will be delivered in a 45-minute workshop and will include worksheets included in the manual. It will be followed up with 4 phone calls one every 6 weeks over the initial 6 months, they will be of 10-15 minute duration and start at week 3.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care educational package and standard telephone follow-up.
The usual care education group will receive instruction (60 minutes) on what type of exercise they can do, when to do it and what resources are available in the community. They will receive a manual with community activities and a copy of booklets from 2 community groups, one on walking the other on activities for seniors.
The standard telephone instruction will consist of 4 phone calls one every 6 weeks over the initial 6 months, they will be of 10-15 minute duration and start at week 3. 
The participants will be asked about progress on their exercise and comments will be recorded. There will be no specific motivational talk and the content of the calls will be minimally discussed except in the case of where safety issues are raised.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood Pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body weight and body composition</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age 50-80 years, non smoking, healthy, but sedentary men and women.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>smokers, physically active, cardiovascular disease, diabetes, untreated hypertension, Body Mass Index (BMI)&gt;34, musculo-skeletal condition preventing moderate physical activity</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be telephoned screened  and if meeting the criteria will attend 2 screening visits. There will be a 4-6 week baseline and familiarisation period. Participants will be stratified and matched on gender and BMI and randomly assigned to the 4 treatment groups by a statistician using computer generated random numbers concealed from the study personnel. Allocation will be concealed by central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated random numbers.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/10/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/10/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2008</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>19/03/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Medicine and Pharmacology
GPO Box X2213 Perth
WA 6847</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Healthway WA</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Healthway
PO Box 1284
West Perth 6872</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Edith Cowan University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>100 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA.6027</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Edith Cowan University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>100 Joondalup Drive
Joondalup WA.6027</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim: 
The aim of this study is to assess the short and long-term efficacy of a behavioural change activity program and motivational interviewing to increase physical activity in older adults.
Hypothesis 1:
Participants who receive a tailored behavioural change program will have higher physical activity levels compared to those who receive a usual care education program.

Hypothesis 2:
Participants who undergo telephone counselling using motivational interviewing (MI) techniques will have higher physical activity levels compared to those who receive the same number of standard telephone contacts.

Hypothesis 3:
Participants who receive a tailored behavioural change program and telephone counselling with MI will have higher physical activity levels compared to those who received the other programs. 

Hypothesis 4:
Increased levels of physical activity will be associated with greater health benefits such as increased fitness, reduced blood pressure, body weight, depression, stress, anxiety and improved psychological well-being.

Hypothesis 5:
Self efficacy will mediate the change in physical activity behaviour.
METHODS

Healthy, non smoking, sedentary, 50-80 year old men and women will be recruited from the community. Participants will be assessed on physical activity, fitness, body weight, blood pressure and psycho-social aspects of mental health such as stress, depression anxiety and well being at baseline, 6 and 12 months. They will be randomly assigned to a usual care education program or a behavioural change education program.  Within each of these programs they will be further allocated to have standard telephone contacts or motivational interviewing (MI) telephone contacts. All participants will be asked to do 150 minutes/week of moderate physical activity for an initial 6 month intervention and a further 6 months of non contact.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Western Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>35 Stirling Hwy
Crawley WA 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/01/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/1/1679</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kay Cox</name>
      <address>School of Medicine and Pharmacology
GPO Box X2213 Perth
WA 6847</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92240237</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 92240243</fax>
      <email>kay.cox@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kay Cox</name>
      <address>University of Western Australia
School of Medicine and Pharmacology
GPO Box X2213 Perth
WA 6847</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92240237</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 92240243</fax>
      <email>kay.cox@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kay Cox</name>
      <address>School of Medicine and Pharmacology
GPO Box X2213 Perth
WA 6847</address>
      <phone>08 92240237</phone>
      <fax>08 92240243</fax>
      <email>kay.cox@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Kay Cox</name>
      <address>University of Western Australia School of Medicine and Pharmacology GPO Box X2213 Perth WA 6847 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 92240237</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kay.cox@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>