<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373160">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001086358p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study on the influence of obesity on the protection after influenza vaccination in children aged 11-17 years.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective pilot study investigating the impact of obesity on seroprotection after influenza vaccination in children aged 11-17 years.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1198-7227
</utrn>
    <trialacronym>FluTe</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity in children and adolescents</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Response to influenza vaccination</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the immune system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a pilot case control study to study the effect, if any, of obesity, on the immune response to the annual licensed quadrivalent influenza vaccination in Australian children aged 11-17 years.
Cases -  25 obese children (BMI &gt;=95th percentile for age and gender) aged 11-17 years.
Controls - 25 non-obese children (BMI 5th - &lt;95th percentile for age and gender) aged 11-17 years.
The dose of the influenza vaccine is 0.5 ml administered as a single dose IM injection. All vaccines will be administered by a qualified and experienced practitioners (medical officer or registered nurse) within the unit, according to current vaccination guidelines. 
All participants will have bloods samples collected by the recruiting medical officer before vaccination and at the follow-up visits at 1 and 6 months after vaccination.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group consists of 25 age and gender-matched non-obese children  (BMI 5th - &lt;95th percentile for age and gender) aged 11-17 years.
All participants, cases and control, will receive the same intervention. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The count and proportion in the case and control groups with seroprotective Haemagglutination Inhibition Assay (HIA)  titres (&gt;=40) at 1 and 6 months post vaccination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 1 month and 6 months after influenza vaccination. 



</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion in the case and control groups who achieve a four-fold rise in Haemagglutination Inhibition Assay (HIA) titres after influenza vaccination.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Comparison of the baseline with the 1 month and 6 month post-vaccination results.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Geometric mean Haemagglutination Inhibition Assay titres in the case and control groups.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Comparison of the baseline with the 1 month and 6 month post-vaccination results.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean geometric increase in Haemagglutination Inhibition Assay (HIA) titres in the case and control groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Comparison of the baseline with the 1 month and 6 month post-vaccination results.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All participants must satisfy ALL the following criteria at study entry:
1. Participants are healthy children aged between 11-17 years at the time of enrolment. 
2. Participants who, in the opinion of the study staff, can and will comply with the requirements of the protocol (eg return for follow-up visits, blood collection). 
3. Participants who can provide assent and have a parent willing to provide consent. 

Additional criteria specific to cases and controls include:
Cases -  Obese children (BMI &gt;=95th percentile for age and gender) aged 11-17 years. Total number to be enrolled is 25 cases. 
Controls - Non-obese children (BMI 5th - &lt;95th percentile for age and gender) aged 11-17 years. Total number to be enrolled is 25 controls. 


</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>11</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>17</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Presence of any of the following criteria will exclude the subject from receipt of influenza vaccination as part of the study:
1. History of serious medical conditions (eg cardiac, respiratory, renal, hepatic disorders, diabetes mellitus requiring treatment with insulin).
2. Any syndromal and/or endocrinological causes for obesity.
3. History of seasonal influenza vaccination within the last six months prior to enrolment. 
4. History of any immunosuppressive condition (eg HIV infection) or on immunosuppressing medication.
5. Any contraindication to influenza immunisation according to the Australian Immunisation Handbook.
6. Anaphylaxis following a previous dose of any influenza vaccine
7. Anaphylaxis following any vaccine component. 
8. History of egg allergy. 
9. History of Guillain Barre syndrome.
10. Bleeding diathesis or condition associated with prolonged bleeding that may contraindicate intramuscular injection or blood draw.
11. Any major illness that, in the investigators judgment, will substantially increase the risk associated with the subjects participation in the study, or interfere with the evaluation of the study objectives.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is a prospective clinical pilot study to assess the impact of obesity on the immune response to influenza vaccination in Australian children aged 11-17 years. A total of 50 children, which will include 25 non-obese (BMI 5th - &lt;95th percentile for age and gender) and 25 obese (BMI &gt;=95th percentile for age and gender) children, aged 11-17 years of age (N=50), will be recruited for the pilot study phase.  The data from this pilot study will be used as the basis to plan subsequent larger studies which will undergo a peer review process.

Primary outcomes: Influenza specific antibody concentrations and haemaggluttination inhibition assay (HIA) titres will be measured on blood samples from all three time-points following vaccination (0, 1 month and 6 months post-vaccination). A HIA titre of 1:40 is the established level of protection for influenza vaccination. Serum antibody concentrations will be log transformed to provide geometric mean concentrations (GMC). 

To examine the primary objective, continuous and categorical evaluations of immune response will be assessed between obese and non-obese cohorts. The percentage of participants within each group (obese or non-obese) with protective HIA titres will be evaluated using logistic regression models, with effects expressed as odds ratios with 95% CIs. Both unadjusted and adjusted analyses will be performed, with adjustment for biologically plausible potential confounders. Basic demographic data and other information collected will be correlated with GMC results for the obese and non-obese groups to identify the impact that the various data collected about participants, has on the immune response to influenza vaccination.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>15/10/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Womens and Childrens Hospital - North Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5006 - North Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Women's and Children's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>72 King William Road,
North Adelaide,
South Australia 5006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Women's and Children's Hospital Foundation, MS McLeod Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Research Secretariat,
Women's and Children's Health Network,
72 King William Road,
North Adelaide,
South Australia 5006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Influenza is a highly infectious respiratory virus that can affect people of all ages. Every year, influenza causes 35 million cases of severe disease worldwide including more than 250,000 deaths. The most effective method of protection from influenza infection is by vaccination. However vaccination is often not 100% effective, and various factors can influence the immune response achieved following vaccination. One such factor that may play an important role in altering the immune responses to influenza vaccination is obesity. Studies among adults have shown that significant obesity puts individuals at increased risk of more severe disease and a more prolonged disease course from influenza. In addition, the effectiveness of influenza vaccination may differ between obese and non-obese individuals. Studies among adults vaccinated with influenza vaccination showed that obese individuals developed significantly higher rates of influenza as compared to non-obese individuals suggesting that influenza vaccination may be less effective in obese than in non-obese adults. Other studies have shown that obese individuals had a reduced cell-mediated immune response to influenza vaccination as compared to non-obese individuals. Most of the studies exploring vaccine effectiveness in obese individuals have been conducted in adults and there are currently no published studies examining differences in immune responses between obese and non-obese children or adolescents in response to influenza vaccine. It is important to further explore and understand how the obese state alters immune function and response to influenza vaccination, and the impact that young age may have on these changes. Understanding mediators of lowered immune responses following vaccination is important for public health policy and programs, and will provide evidence which could be highly translatable to immunization policy and inform vaccination strategies for obese populations. This study will enrol 25 non-obese (BMI 5-&lt;95th percentile) and 25 obese (BMI &gt;=95th percentile) children aged 11-17 years of age (N=50) and include 3 study visits. Participants will receive a single dose of licensed quadrivalent influenza vaccine at visit 1. Blood samples will be collected at all 3 visits (visit 2 and 3 will occur 1 and 6 months post-vaccination). Influenza specific antibody concentrations and haemaggluttination inhibition assay (HIA) titres will be measured on blood samples from all three time-points. A HIA titre of 1:40 is the established level of protection for influenza vaccination. Serum antibody concentrations will be log transformed to provide geometric mean concentrations (GMC). The protective HIA titres and GMC will be compared between obese and non-obese cohorts using linear regression models with effects expressed as mean differences and 95% confidence intervals. Both unadjusted and adjusted analyses will be performed, with adjustment for biologically plausible potential confounders.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Women's and Children's Health Network (WCHN) Human Research Ethics Committee's (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Secretariat,
Level 2, Samuel Way Building,
72 King William Road,
North Adelaide,
South Australia 5006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Marshall</name>
      <address>Women's and Children's Health Network,
Department of Paediatrics,
Level 2, Clarence Rieger Building
72 King William Road,
North Adelaide,
SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81618115</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 81617031</fax>
      <email>helen.marshall@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Michelle Clarke</name>
      <address>Women's and Children's Health Network,
Department of Paediatrics,
Level 2, Clarence Rieger Building
72 King William Road,
North Adelaide,
SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81618115</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 81617031</fax>
      <email>michelle.clarke@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Marshall</name>
      <address>Women's and Children's Health Network,
Department of Paediatrics,
Level 2, Clarence Rieger Building
72 King William Road,
North Adelaide,
SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81618115</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 81617031</fax>
      <email>helen.marshall@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Michelle Clarke</name>
      <address>Women's and Children's Health Network,
Department of Paediatrics,
Level 2, Clarence Rieger Building
72 King William Road,
North Adelaide,
SA 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81618115</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 81617031</fax>
      <email>michelle.clarke@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>