<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363151">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001099819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An open trial of a guided internet-delivered cognitive behavioural therapy intervention to determine the benefits of the Mood Mechanic Course for young adults with symptoms of anxiety and depression</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open trial of guided internet-delivered cognitive behavioural therapy intervention to determine the benefits of the Mood Mechanic Course for adults aged 18-24 with symptoms of anxiety and depression</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MMOT1</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this open trial participants will receive access to a 5 week internet-delivered education course, the MoodMechanic Course, which teaches participants how to manage symptoms of anxiety, stress and low mood. All participants will have at least mild symptoms of anxiety or low mood (GAD-7 total score of &gt;4 or PHQ-9 total score of &gt;4).

The MoodMechanic Course comprises 4 online lessons, which describe evidence-based cognitive behavioural and interpersonal therapy strategies for managing cognitive, behavioural, and physical symptoms of anxiety and low mood. One lesson will be completed every 7 to 10 days. Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to read. Participants will also have access to summaries of each lesson, and will read anonymous stories about other people with anxiety and low mood, taking a further 20 minutes per week. All participants will also receive 10-20 automatic emails to promote adherence and engagement, and brief weekly (&lt;10minutes week) written or telephone contact from a therapist at the Macquarie University eCentreClinic. 

Study questionnaires will be administered at application, pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention. These will take about 20-30 minutes to complete. Additionally, there will be a brief 5 minute questionnaire at the start of each week of the Course.</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms and severity of depression is measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-intervention, at the beginning of each week of the Course, post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms of anxiety are measured by the Generalised Anxiety Disorder 7 Item Scale (GAD-7)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of psychological is measured by the Kessler 10-item  (K-10)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of disability is measured by the Sheehan Disability Scale (SDS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-intervention, post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Frequency of adaptive behaviours measured by the Things You Do Questionnaire (TYDQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-intervention, at the beginning of each week of the Course, post-intervention, and at 3-months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. 18+ years of age
2. GAD-7 score &gt; 4, and/or a PHQ9 score &gt; 4 indicating at least mild symptoms
3. Provides informed consent
4. Resident of Australia</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>24</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Severe depression (score of 23 or greater on PHQ-9)
2. Presenting problem not anxiety or depression
3. Suicidal intention or plan
4. Receiving CBT for target symptoms at same time as the present trial</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will self-refer to the Course. Potential participants will be assessed for risk by the eCentreClinic staff, and those at elevated risk will be encouraged to access face to face services (GP or primary physician, or emergency services as necessary).  Those who do not require urgent intervention and who report symptoms of stress, anxiety, or low mood will be informed about the aims of this study, and invited to apply. Those interested will provide Informed Consent and will complete an application which will consist of questionnaires of symptoms of depression and anxiety, the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 Item and Generalised Anxiety Disorder-7 item questionnaires, respectively. Applicants with scores too low or too high on these questionnaires will not be eligible but will be referred to other services by the eCentreClinic staff, while eligible applicants will be asked to provide demographic details. Participants who meet eligibility criteria will be given access codes to begin the intervention.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>22/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/12/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>18</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>eCentreClinic, Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>C3A 724
Macquarie University
North Ryde
NSW 2109</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>beyondblue: the national depression initiative</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 6100
Hawthorn West 
Victoria 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study tests the short and medium term efficacy of the online Mood Mechanic Course with adults aged 18-24 with symptoms of anxiety or low mood.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.ecentreclinic.org</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Dear BF, Titov N, Schwencke G, Andrews G, Johnston L, Craske MG, McEvoy P. (2011). An open trial of a brief transdiagnostic treatment for anxiety and depression. Behaviour Research and Therapy 49:830-837.

Johnston L, Titov N, Andrews G, Spence J, Dear BF. (2011). A randomized controlled trial of a transdiagnostic Internet-delivered treatment for anxiety disorders. PLoS ONE, 6(11): e28079. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0028079.

Titov N, Dear BF, Schwencke G, Andrews G, Johnston L, Craske M, McEvoy P. (2011). Transdiagnostic Internet treatment of anxiety and depression: A randomised controlled trial. Behaviour Research and Therapy 49:441-452.

Johnston, L., Dear, B. F., Gandy, M., Fogliati, V., Kayrouz, R., Sheehan, J., Rapee, R., &amp; Titov, N. (2014). Exploring the efficacy and acceptability of internet-delivered cognitive behavioural therapy for young adults with anxiety and depression: An open trial. Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry, 48, 819-827.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Macquarie University
North Ryde
NSW 2109</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5201200461</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Associate Professor Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>C3A 724
Macquarie University
North Ryde
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61298509901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Associate Professor Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>C3A 724
Macquarie University
North Ryde
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61298509901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nick Titov</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>61 2 9850 9901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>