<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370373">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000643471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of the probability of live birth after elective freezing of all embryos versus standard fresh embryo transfer in patients undergoing in-vitro fertilisation (IVF)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Fresh vs. Elective Frozen Embryo Transfer after IVF: a randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>FAST</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Subfertility</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fertility including in vitro fertilisation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Triggering of final oocyte maturation will be performed in the freeze-all arm with a bolus subcutaneous injection of 2 mg of leuprolide acetate when at least three follicles equal to or greater than 17mm in mean diameter are present at ultrasound. Oocyte retrieval will be performed at 34-36h after leuprolide administration.
Embryos will be cultured for 5 days using the standard protocol of each clinic. All day 5 embryos of top and good quality (at least at early blastocyst stage and of ICM/Trophectoderm: AA, AB, BA, BB) will be cryopreserved using the method of vitrification. If only one embryo is available, this embryo will be vitrified regardless of quality as long as full embryo compaction has occurred.  Delayed embryos will be allowed to be vitrified on day 6 as long as they fulfill the quality criteria (at least at early blastocyst stage and of ICM/Trophectoderm: AA, AB, BA, BB).
Prior to freezing of embryos the developmental stage and quality of the blastocysts will be recorded (based on the judgement of the embryologist). Each blastocyst will be frozen in its own straw. Based on the pre-vitrification morphological quality, the best blastocyst will be thawed for the next embryo transfer. If the blastocyst does not survive, the next best blastocyst (based again on the pre-vitrification morphological criteria) will be thawed. 
The maximum period of embryo cryopreservation is theoretically indefinite, however it rarely exceeds five years. For the primary outcome of this study, the embryo cryopreservation period is estimated between 20 days-3 months. Hence, thawing and embryo transfer is expected to occur within this timeframe. 
Vitrification will be performed according to established local laboratory protocols with the use of TGA approved Vitrification solutions (Vitrolife or Sage). Vitrification will be performed at either 37 degrees Celsius or room temperature. </interventions>
    <comparator>Triggering of final oocyte maturation will be performed in the fresh transfer arm with a bolus subcutaneous injection of 250 mcg of r-hCG when at least three follicles of equal to or greater than 17mm in mean diameter are present at ultrasound. Oocyte retrieval will be performed at 34-36h  after r-hCG administration.
Embryos will be cultured for 5 days using the standard protocol of each clinic. On day 5 of embryo culture the developmental stage and quality of the blastocysts will be recorded including ICM and Trophectoderm grading. The morphologically best day 5 embryo (according to the judgement of the embryologist) will be transferred. 
All remaining day 5 embryos of top and good quality (at least at early blastocyst stage and of ICM/Trophectoderm: AA, AB, BA, BB) will be cryopreserved using the method of vitrification. Delayed embryos will be allowed to be vitrified on day 6 as long as they fulfill the quality criteria (at least at early blastocyst stage and of ICM/Trophectoderm: AA, AB, BA, BB). 
Vitrification will be performed according to established local laboratory protocols with the use of TGA approved Vitrification solutions (Vitrolife or Sage). Vitrification will be performed at either 37 degrees Celsius or room temperature. 
The maximum period of embryo cryopreservation is theoretically indefinite, however it rarely exceeds five years. Usually, these embryos remain cryopreserved for future use, if fresh transfer does not result in a pregnancy or for future pregnancies after a live birth. However, the primary outcome measure of this study is live birth after the first embryo transfer (fresh vs. frozen-thawed). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Live Birth after the transfer of the first embryo by review of patients medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Delivery of a live baby after the 20th week of gestation </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ongoing pregnancy diagnosed by ultrasonography as presence of foetal heart activity at 10-12 weeks of gestation </outcome>
      <timepoint>Once at 10-12 weeks of gestation depending on the time of appointment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical pregnancy diagnosed by ultrasound as presence of foetal heart activity at 6-8 weeks of gestation</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6-8 weeks of gestation depending on time of appointment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemical pregnancy as assessed by blood serum b-hCG&gt;20 IU/L</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 11-16 days after embryo transfer depending on time of appointment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>First trimester miscarriage, defined as a biochemical pregnancy (assessed by serum hCG) at 11-16 days after embryo transfer but no foetal heart activity at 10-12 weeks of gestation as assessed by ultrasonography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Biochemical pregnancy diagnosed by serum hCG at 11-16 days following embryo transfer and ongoing pregnancy diagnosed by ultrasonography at 10-12 weeks gestation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occurrence of severe OHSS by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within the first 20 days after triggering final oocyte maturation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of cryopreserved embryos by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>7-8 days after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of cryopreserved embryos remaining after first embryo transfer by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>After first embryo transfer</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pre-term labour (defined as delivery &lt;37 weeks of gestation) by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>&lt;37 weeks of gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mode of delivery (normal vaginal delivery, assisted vaginal delivery, caesarean section) by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 42 weeks of gestation </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neonatal birthweight by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 42 weeks of gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stillbirth by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 42 weeks of gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neonatal mortality by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Death within the first 28 days of life</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intrauterine growth restriction by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 40 weeks of pregnancy</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hypertensive disorders of pregnancy (including gestational hypertension, pre-eclampsia, eclampsia) by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>Up to 42 weeks go gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gestational Diabetes Mellitus by review of medical records</outcome>
      <timepoint>From 20 weeks of gestation until delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1)	Indication for COS and IVF or ICSI with autologous gametes
2)	Age: 18-39 years 
3)	BMI: 18-32 kg/m2
4)	Presence of both ovaries
5)	Normal menstruating cycles: 21-35 days 
6)	Cycle where prevention of premature LH rise is achieved using a GnRH antagonist
7)	8-19 follicles equal to or greater than 10mm in mean diameter on the day of triggering</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>39</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1)	Endometriosis Stage&gt;II
2)	Indication for PGD/PGS
3)	History of OHSS
4)	Previous participation in the RCT
5)	&gt;3 previous unsuccessful stimulated cycles 
6)	History of hypothalamic dysfunction or history of inadequate pituitary response to GnRH agonist triggering  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be randomly allocated to one of the study groups on the day of triggering final oocyte maturation. This allocation will be performed centrally (web-based) using an online database specifically designed for that purpose. Prior to randomization, the nurse will have to enter patient data (unique identifier).  </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization will be performed with the use of a list of random numbers produced by dedicated software. Random permutation blocks stratified by each centre participating in this trial will be used. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Study Sample size and power calculations:	
Assuming a difference of 15% in live birth rates between the two treatments arms (35% vs. 50%), 183 patients in each group are required using a two-sided Fishers Exact test, with an alpha=0.05 and beta=0.20. To account for a ~10% drop-out rate, 200 patients in each group are planned to be randomized. 

Statistical Analysis:
Dichotomous data will be expressed as proportions and will be compared between groups with the use of Fishers Exact test. Continuous variables will be described with the use of the mean/standard deviation or the median/interquartile range, depending on the normality of the distribution. 
An adjusted analysis will also be performed with the use of logistic regression analyses, accounting for the different IVF clinics, the differences in age, BMI and indication for treatment. Exploratory analyses will be performed to assess the potential moderating effect of the quality of embryos on day 5 of embryo culture and levels of serum progesterone on the day of hCG of the stimulated cycle.  
Logistic regression analyses will be also employed to explore the potential moderating effect of patient or stimulation characteristics (e.g. endometrial thickness on the day of progesterone initiation in FRET cycles) on live birth rates. 
The main analysis will be performed according to the intention-to-treat principle. Per protocol analyses will also be performed.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>IVFAustralia Pty L.t.d.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>IVFAustralia
Level 3
176 Pacific Highway
Greenwich  NSW  2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>IVFAustralia Pty L.t.d.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>IVFAustralia
Level 3
176 Pacific Highway
Greenwich NSW 2065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Melbourne IVF</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>East Melbourne IVF
344 Victoria Parade,
Eas Melbourne VIC 3002</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Virtus Health Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3, 176 Pacific Highway
Greenwich NSW 2065, 
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Melbourne IVF </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>East Melbourne IVF
344 Victoria Parade, 
East Melbourne VIC 3002</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Virtus Health Limited</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 3, 176 Pacific Highway
Greenwich NSW 2065, 
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will test whether freezing all good or top quality day 5-6 embryos after IVF and subsequently thawing and transferring the best day 5-6 embryo into a natural or artificially prepared cycle leads to an increase in the probability of delivering a live baby from 35% to 50% as compared to the standard strategy of treatment which includes transferring the best quality day 5-6 embryo fresh and cryopreserving the remaining good or top quality embryos.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>IVFAustralia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>IVFAustralia
Level 3
176 Pacific Highway
Greenwich NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>117</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne IVF Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Melbourne IVF
Suite 13, Level 1
The Elgar Hill Building
28-32 Arnold Street
Box Hill VIC 3128</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>43/15-MIVF</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christos Venetis</name>
      <address>IVFAustralia Southern Sydney
Level 3, Suite 15
St George Private Hospital
Kogarah 2217 NSw </address>
      <phone>+61 2 8567 6955</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.venetis@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christos Venetis</name>
      <address>IVFAustralia Southern Sydney
Level 3, Suite 15
St George Private Hospital
Kogarah 2217 NSw </address>
      <phone>+61 2 8567 6955</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.venetis@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Christos Venetis</name>
      <address>IVFAustralia Southern Sydney
Level 3, Suite 15
St George Private Hospital
Kogarah 2217 NSw </address>
      <phone>+61 2 8567 6955</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.venetis@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>