<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364921">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001057774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pharmacokinetics of IPX203 </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>IPX203-B13-02:Pharmacokinetics of IPX203 and Levodopa formulations in healthy volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>IPX203 will be administered in a single-center, open-label, randomized, single-dose, 5-sequence, 5-treatment crossover study in healthy male adults. The treatment periods will be separated by a washout period of at least 7 days. All subjects will receive the following 5 treatments in a randomized sequence. All treatments will be administered with 240 mL of water to subjects in the fasted state. 
Treatment A comprises 3 capsules and 2 tablets: 1 capsule of investigational formulations C0017, C0019, C0022 and 2 tablets of carbidopa. 
Treatment B comprises 3 capsules and 2 tablets: 1 capsule of investigational formulations C0017, C0019, C0021 and 2 tablets of carbidopa. 
Treatment C comprises 3 capsules and 2 tablets: 1 capsule of investigational formulations C0017, C0020, C0021 and 2 tablets of carbidopa. 
Treatment D comprises 3 capsules: 1 capsule of investigational formulations C0013, C0016 and C0021.
Treatment E comprises 1 tablet of Stalevo 100. Treatment E comprises 1 tablet of Stalevo 100.
Treatment A regimen contains a total dose of 280mg  Levodopa, 250 mg Entacapone and 50 mg of Carbidopa.
Treatment B and C regimens each contain a total dose of 280mg equivalent Levodopa and 400 mg Entacapone formulated with different release characteristics, 50 mg of Carbidopa. 
Treatment D regimen contains a total dose of 256mg equivalent Levodopa, 400 mg Entacapone and 50 mg of Carbidopa. 
During each treatment period, subjects will remain at the clinical facility from the evening before dosing until approximately 8 h postdose for observation and PK sampling.
 </interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment E: 1 tablet of Stalevo 100, for a total dose of Levodopa 100 mg, Carbidopa 25 mg, and Entacapone 200 mg</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pharmacokinetics</outcome>
      <timepoint>Whole blood samples will be obtained within 1 hour predose and 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 4.5, 5, 5.5, 6, 6.5, and 8 hours postdose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety</outcome>
      <timepoint>Any AE that emerges from the time the subject signs the ICF until Study Exit will be recorded and reported.  Additional safety parameters (laboratory tests, 12-lead ECG, physical exams, and vital signs), and related information (demographics, concomitant medications) are to be recorded.

The more common adverse reactions seen with carbidopa/levodopa treatment include dyskinesias including, choreiform, dystonic and other involuntary movements, muscle twitching, eye twitching involuntary and nausea.
Other common reactions include mental changes, including paranoid ideation and psychotic episodes; depression, with or without development of suicidal tendencies; and cognitive dysfunction. The most frequent adverse reactions seen with entacapone treatment include nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, constipation and diarrhoea. Urine may be discoloured reddish-brown by entacapone but this is a harmless phenomenon. Entacapone in association with levodopa has been associated with isolated episodes of excessive daytime somnolence and sudden sleep onset. Isolated cases of rhabdomyolysis have been reported. As this study drug is new, it is unknown what all of the possible side effects may be and there may be unknown risks. For a more complete list of possible side effects please ask the study doctor.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy males between 18 years and 65 years of age inclusive at the time of informed consent.  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Presence of a clinically significant disorder involving bleeding or hematologic or cardiovascular system abnormalities, acute infections, respiratory, renal, gastrointestinal, immunologic, hepatic, reproductive, endocrine, or neurologic system(s), or psychiatric disease (as determined by the Investigator)
History of peptic ulcer disease or surgical procedure of the stomach, the small intestine, or the large intestine
History of glaucoma
Suspicious skin lesions or history of melanoma 
History of neuroleptic malignant syndrome (NMS) or nontraumatic rhabdomyolysis
Subject has smoked or used tobacco products or nicotine products (patches, gums, etc.) within 60 days prior to Period 1 dosing; subjects does not agree to abstain from tobacco or nicotine products throughout the study.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>5/12/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>5/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Impax Laboratories, Inc. Acting through its Impax Pharmaceuticals Division </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>31047 Genstar Road
Hayward, CA 94544
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Impax Laboratories, Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>30831 Huntwood Avenue,
Hayward, CA 94544</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of Study IPX203-B13-02 is to characterize the pharmacokinetics of IPX203 and levodopa formulations in healthy subjects.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>71 Anzac Highway
Ashford, SA 5035
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013-09-513</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sepehr Shakib</name>
      <address>CMAX, a division of IDT Australia  Limited
Level 5 East Wing
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA 5000
</address>
      <phone>+61 08 8222-4638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sepehr.shakib@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Cmax</name>
      <address>Level 5 East Wing Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide  SA  5000 
</address>
      <phone>1800 150 433</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cmax@cmax.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sepehr Shakib</name>
      <address>CMAX, a division of IDT Australia  Limited
Level 5 East Wing
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA 5000
</address>
      <phone>+61 08 8222-4638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sepehr.shakib@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>