<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367448">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/12/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000018516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does subcutaneous fat measured at 18­20 weeks predict difficulty inserting an epidural or adverse pregnancy  outcomes?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In pregnant women, does the abdominal subcutaneous fat measured by ultrasound at 18-22 weeks predict pregnancy outcomes or difficulty of insertion of neuraxial anaesthesia?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Adiposity measured by subcutaneous fat</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fetal medicine and complications of pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Abdominal subcutaneous fat measured by ultrasound at 18-22 weeks gestation, as a measure of central adiposity.

Part 1:  SCF measured at 18-22 weeks gestation will be analyzed against obesity-related pregnancy outcomes (maternal and fetal) to determine if it can be used to predict such outcomes.  The observation period will last from the time the measurement is taken until the week after the fetus has been delivered.

Part 2.  In women booked for elective caesarean section, the measurement of subcutaneous fat taken at 18-22 weeks gestation will be analysed against the anaesthetist's difficulty palpating landmarks, the number of insertion attempts and the US measurement of lumbar subcutaneous fat.  The aim is to determine if the SCF measurement can be used to predict these outcomes.  The observation period will last from the time of the SCF measurement, until the completion of the anaesthetic.</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal outcome
(pre-eclampsia, gestational diabetes, haemorrhage requiring transfusion, mode of delivery)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Antenatal (at 18-22 weeks gestation)
Post-natal (1 week after delivery of the fetus)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fetal Outcome 
Birth weight, length and head circumference, APGAR score at 5 minutes, hypoglycaemia, gestation, respiratory support, destination, 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>First 48 hours of life</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difficulty palpating lumbar landmarks
This will be rated by the treating anaesthetist at the time of palpation as easy (easily able to palpate lumbar spinous processes at multiple levels in sitting position with minimal/moderate compression of subcutaneous tissue), moderate (able to palpate L3/4 spinous process in sitting position with significant compression of subcutaneous tissues in optimal position) or hard (unable to palpate lumbar spinous process despite significant compression and optimal positioning)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of anaesthesia for elective caesarean section</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difficulty inserting neuraxial
Rated by the anaesthetist as easy, moderate or hard (definitions available)
Number of insertions of the needle through the skin, number of re-directions of the needle within the back</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of anaesthetic for elective caesarean section</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All participants must be pregnant (pregnancy is the "health condition" required for eligibility)
For part 1: all women presenting to the RBWH for an 18-22 week scan and do not opt-out.  
For part 2: Women booked for elective caesarean section (Category 4);
women who have had a SCF measurement taken at the RBWH on their 18-22 week USS; women who are reasonably expected to have regional anaesthesia for their caesarean section.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Part 1: For the purposes of analysis exclusion criteria will be:  referral to the alcohol and drugs service for significant drug or alcohol use; failure to attend at least one antenatal appointment.
Part 2:  Participants who do not have regional anaesthesia, or have an emergency caesarean section (category 1,2,3).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>For Part 1, the SCF will be measured for 12 months which should yield between 800-1000 measurements - statistical advice is that this will be sufficient.  The SCF measurement will be analysed according to the outcome data, to determine if there is a relationship between the SCF thickness and any of the outcome variables.  ANOVA, Chi square and multiple logistic regression will be used.   For Part 2, the sample size is currently being calculated from a pilot study but will be in the order of 100-200 (Part 1 will commence while this number is being finalised).  The number of attempts inserting the epidural and the difficulty palpating landmarks will be analysed against the SCF measurement using ANOVA and Chi-square.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/03/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>6/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>4006 - Herston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Butterfield St 
Herston, 4006
QLD</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Butterfield St 
Herston, 4006
QLD</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>St Lucia  
QLD 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>St Lucia  
QLD 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will test two hypotheses and consist of two parts:
1. Part 1.  The thickness of abdominal SCF, measured by ultrasound at 18-22 weeks gestation, predicts maternal outcomes (gestational diabetes, pregnancy-related hypertensive disorders, mode of delivery) and fetal outcomes (estimated fetal weight, birth outcome, gestational age, gender, weight, length, head circumference, large for gestational age, small for gestational age, intrauterine growth restriction).
2.  Part 2.  The thickness of abdominal SCF, measured by ultrasound at 18-22 weeks gestation, predicts the difficulty inserting an epidural, the difficulty palpating the landmarks of epidural insertion and the subcutaneous fat measured at lumbar interspace L3-4.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HREC of the Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7, Block 7.
Butterfield St
Herston 4006
QLD</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/QRBW/492</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Victoria Eley</name>
      <address>The Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital (RBWH)
Butterfield St
Herston 4006
QLD</address>
      <phone>+617 38127616</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>va_eley@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Victoria Eley</name>
      <address>RBWH
Butterfield St
Herston 4006
QLD</address>
      <phone>+61738127616</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>va_eley@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Victoria Eley</name>
      <address>RBWH
Butterfield St
Herston 4006
QLD</address>
      <phone>+617438127616</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>va_eley@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Victoria Eley</name>
      <address>RBWH
Butterfield St
Herston 4006
QLD</address>
      <phone>+61738127616</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>va_eley@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>