<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308132">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000613202</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Aspirin for the prevention of cognitive decline in the Elderly: a Neuro-Vascular Imaging Study (ENVIS-ion), a sub-study of ASPirin in Reducing Events in the Elderly (ASPREE)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A multi-centre, randomised, double-blind, placebo controlled trial of the effects of 100mg enteric-coated aspirin on rate of increase of magnetic resonance imaging(MRI)-based white matter hyperintensity (WMH) and silent brain infarction (SBI).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ENVIS-ion</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive decline in older adults</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Acetylsalicylic acid (aspirin) 100 mg; enteric coated unscored white tablet taken once per day for an average of 3 years</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo of acetylsalicylic acid; enteric coated unscored white tablet with identical appearance taken once per day for an average of 3 years enteric</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) including white matter hyper intensity (WMH) and silent brain infarction (SBI) volumes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years following randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in retinal vascular imaging (RVI) parameters, including quantitatively measured retinal arteriolar and venular calibre and the presence of retinal arteriolar pathology.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years following randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Death from any cause</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incident dementia (defined according to the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual for Mental Disorders 4th edition (DSM-IV) criteria)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Persistent physical disability (defined as the onset of a lot of difficulty to inability to perform any one of 6 Katz Activities of Daily Living)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatal and non-fatal cardiovascular events including: 
1. Coronary heart disease death 
2. Non-fatal myocardial infarction 
3. Fatal and non-fatal stroke 
4. Hospitalisation for heart failure</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatal and non-fatal cancer, excluding non-melanomatous skin cancer</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive decline as assessed by the following tests; Stoop test (Victoria version), Color Trails test, Digit Symbol Modalities (WAIS test), Modified Mini-Mental State Examination (3MS),  Center for Epidemiologic Studies?Depression questionnaire (CES-D), Digit Symbol Substitution Test (DSST), Hopkins Verbal Learning Test?Revised (HVLT-R), Single Letter Fluency Test (SLFT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major haemorrhagic events</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 years following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All subjects will be aged 70 years or more and capable of attending their usual family physician's clinic, providing informed consent and have no known contraindications to MRI.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>70</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. A history of cardiovascular morbidity defined as myocardial infarction, stroke, peripheral vascular disease, angina, transient ischaemic attack, greater than 50% carotid stenosis or previous carotid endarterectomy or stenting, coronary artery angioplasty or stenting, or coronary artery bypass grafting 
2. A serious intercurrent illness likely to cause death within the next 5 years 
3. A current or recurrent condition with a high risk of major bleeding e.g. cerebral aneurysm or cerebral arteriovenous (AV) malformation, any bleeding diathesis, gastrointestinal malignancy, peptic ulcer, liver disease, uraemia, aortic aneurysm or any other condition known to be associated with a high risk of serious bleeding 
4. Absolute contraindication or allergy to aspirin 
5. Current participation in a clinical trial 
6. Current continuous use of aspirin or other anti-platelet drug or anticoagulant 
7. A history of dementia 
8. In addition those who lie outside of tolerance levels of 8-104% during placebo run-in phase will not be randomised 
9. An inability to perform independently one of the 6 Katz Activities of Daily Living (walking, bathing, dressing, transferring from chair or bed, toileting, eating) 
10. Pill taking compliance below 80% on tablet count during a placebo run-in phase 
11. Absolute contraindications to undergo MRI</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Initially, the general practitioner (GP) is recruited into the study and with their consent their database is searched for possible participants. A mail-out database is created and letters are sent to all possible participants. Interested possible participants then phone the free-call ENVIS-ion telephone number and the trial nurse asks a set of telephone screening questions. Eligible participants then attend an initial screening visit (Visit 1) where consent is obtained and baseline measures are taken. Eligible participants are then asked to return to their GP for a GP screening visit. Within four weeks of Visit 1 eligible participants then attend a randomisation visit (Visit 2) where further baseline measures are collected and participants are randomised into one of the two treatment arms. Please note that until randomisation is complete participants may be excluded at anytime based on the exclusion criteria.
Following the completion of data collection at Visit 2, and if all inclusion criteria are satisfied, participants will be randomised to a treatment arm via the telephone or the internet. Telephone randomisation will be via a toll free 1800 Interactive Voice Response System (IVRS). For large clinical centers, randomisation will be achieved via the web portal. For both systems, password protected access is required for study personnel. Computer-generated medication numbers will be provided to trial sites through the IVRS or the web portal.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation list will be generated by an independent statistician. The randomisation list will be generated using the STATA “ralloc” procedure with randomisation stratified for site and age (&lt;80 yrs and &gt;=80 yrs). All staff remain blinded to treatment allocation through the randomisation procedure.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/06/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/04/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>3/04/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>600</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian National University (ANU)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>ANU Medical School
Frank Fenner Building 42
The Australian National University
Canberra ACT 0200</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) (ref: 471460)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Monash University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Research and Graduate Programs Office 
Faculty of Medicine, Nursing and Health Sciences 
PO Box 64 
Monash University
Victoria 3800</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Clinical Trials Unit, Canberra Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Building 1, Level 2
The Canberra Hospital
Po Box 11
Woden ACT 2606</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Centre for Eye Research Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The University of Melbourne
32 Gisborne Street
Melbourne, Victoria 3002</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Department of Radiology, The Alfred Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>P.O Box 315
Prahran. Victoria 3181</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The ENVIS-ion trial will examine whether low dose aspirin is effective in delaying the onset of declining abilities of thinking and memory in healthy older adults. Participants in the ENVIS-ion trial will be recruited from men and women who have agreed and consented to participate in the clinical trial of low dose aspirin (the ASPREE Trial ISRCTN83772183). The main features of the ENVIS-ion trial are additional measurement of brain and retinal structures by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and retinal photography in each participant before starting on the study drug and after treatment with aspirin or placebo for 3 years. As a part of the ASPREE study, mental functions are assessed every year by questionnaires administered by a trained researcher. For ENVIS-ion, participants will have extra questionnaires to further test their mental abilities. MRI of brain structure will detect markers of early worsening of thinking and memory abilities. Blood vessels of the retina share many features with vessels of the brain. We will compare whether aspirin lessens changes over time of features shown with brain MRI and retinal photography and compare these with the questionnaire measurements of mental function.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.med.monash.edu.au/epidemiology/cardiores/aspree-envision.html</trialwebsite>
    <publication>ENVIS-ion clinical trial: Aspirin for the prevention of cognitive decline in the Elderly: a Neuro-Vascular Imaging Study of ASPREE. Presented at the Canberra Regional Annual Scientific Meeting in Canberra, June 2009.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian National University (ANU)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics- Research Office   
Lower Ground Floor, Chancelry 10B
The Australian National University
Canberra ACT 0200</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/04/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008/115</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/04/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACT Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, 11 Moore St
Canberra City ACT 2601</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/02/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ETH.11/07.998</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>First Floor, Building 3e
Monash Research Office
Clayton Campus
Monash University VIC 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/05/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF08/1314 - 2008000648</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Second Floor, East Block
P.O Box 315
The Alfred Hospital
Prahran. Vic. 3181</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/04/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>79/08</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Walter Abhayaratna</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Unit, Building 1, Level 2 Canberra Hospital, Yamba Dr, Garran ACT 2605</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 3687</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 4647</fax>
      <email>walter.abhayaratna@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Ms Emily Wilford</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Unit
Building 1, Level 2
The Canberra Hospital
Po Box 11
Woden ACT 2606</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 3687</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 4647</fax>
      <email>emily.wilford@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Walter Abhayaratna</name>
      <address>Clinical Trials Unit, Building 1 Level 2 Canberra Hospital, Yamba Dr, GARRAN ACt 2605</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 3687</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 4647</fax>
      <email>walter.abhayaratna@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>