<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343355">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000883910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>School based program to promote lifestyle changes to prevent overweight in elementary school children.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomized school intervention to reduce BMI and prevent childhood obesity in Mexican elementary schools.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1123-1957</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity prevention</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Weight maintenance</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study was a quasi-experimental randomized cluster controlled trial during a period of 2 years. 
The intervention group (group1) was conformed by 1 public and 1 private school, with 7 class groups in total, the control group (group 2) was conformed by 1 public and 1 private school with 6 class groups in total. There were no statistical differences between the two groups in BMI, BMIz-score.
During the first phase, all components of the intervention were developed and implemented to the intervention group (group1).  
The studys intervention consisted of three components: 1) school board and teachers, 2) classroom curriculum, and 3) parent involvement. 
The intervention approach was based in the Bronfenbrenners Ecological Model. The educational component was designed to be interdisciplinary. Nutrition and physical activity professionals interacted with parents, children, and teachers.  Its purpose was to show how food choices and physical activity depend on personal behavior, individual health and school and family environment.
The classroom curricula for 2nd and 3rd grades were designed to promote healthful eating behaviors and to increase physical activity. One 30-min interactive lesson was delivered by nutrition graduate students each week for 8 weeks during the academic year. The objective of the interactive children sessions was to encourage children to increase fruit and vegetable consumption, to enroll in sports and play activities, to reduce the consumption of soda and snacks with a high fat and sugar content, and to lower the number of hours of TV viewing. This component also included the assessment of dietary intake and physical activity.
Four 60-minute sessions were delivered to school board and teachers by nutrition and PA professionals to discuss healthy lifestyles. Several meetings took place to discuss how to improve school meals and snacks offered in the cafeteria, and also on how to improve PA installations and offer PA activities during and after school.
The aim of the parents involvement component was to introduce them to the intervention program and to receive nutrition education and extend their knowledge on healthy lifestyle and eating behaviors. The parents component consisted of a 60-minute session delivered by nutrition professionals each month for 4 months during the academic year.
After the six months the control group Group 2 received the intervention program.
In phase 2 :For the intervention and control group a follow-up program was continued for another 18 and 12 months respectively. The follow-up program consisted in a 30 min weekly session for the semester with classroom activities to promote fruit and vegetable consumption and PA and decresease soda and non healthy snack consumption.</interventions>
    <comparator>For the control group (group 2) three 60-minute sessions were delivered to school board, teachers, and parents by medical professionals to discuss health issues (diabetes, hipertension, and blood lipid problems).
After the initial six month period, the control group received the intervention due to the benefits observed in the intervention group in the first six months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>BMI and z-score BMI changes between control and intervention groups and pre- and post-intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 6, 12, 18, 24 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in waist circumference (WC). The wast circunference will be measured using a flexible and retractable measuring tape (SECA) at the midpoint between the lower rib and the top of the iliac crest at the end of a gentle expiration.  Abdominal obesity was defined as WC&gt; 90th of NHANESIII.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12,and 24 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overweight and obesity prevalence.
 Height will be measured (without shoes) to the nearest 0.1 cm using a portable stadiometer (Model 214 Road Rod, Seca Corp, Hanover, MD, USA). Weight will be measured (in light clothing) to the nearest 0.1 kg using previously calibrated electronic scales (Model 2001; Tanita Corp. Tokyo, Japan). BMI (kg/m2) and z-scores will be calculated using the WHO (2007) LMS parameters for sex and age. Cut-off points for overweight are greater than 1DS, and obesity greater than 2 DS.
The percentage of children with overweight or obese will be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12, and 24 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>remission (percentage of children who were overweight or obese at baseline but were not overweight or obese at follow-up)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12, and 24 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>incidence (percentage of children with normal weight at baseline who became overweight or obese at follow-up).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12, and 24 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fruit and vegetables, soda and sweetened and high fat snack consumption and availability.
Dietary registry of food consumption: Children will be ask to complete a dietary registry on a randomly selected weekday. The registry will be analyzed based on portions of food groups targeted in the intervention: number of servings of cereals and grains, meat, milk, fruits, vegetables, sweetened beverages, candies and snacks. The dietary registry will be recorded with the support of trained teachers.
Food inventory: children will  complete a questionnaire on food inventory, which included number of portions of: fruits, vegetables, cookies, candies, snacks and sweetened beverages they had available in their homes or that they bought on the day of the inventory. The inventory will be recorded with the support of trained teachers, as a homework assignment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in physical activity and sedentary behavior.
Physical activity: A self-report questionnaire developed and validated in Chile (INTA PA questionnaire) will be used to assess physical activity levels in children. Children will complete the PA questionnaire with their teacher assistance and a trained student.
The reproducibility and validity, in a group of 45 children in this study, with an accelerometer ActiGraph was assessed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children of 2nd and 3rd grade from public and private elementary schools  of Tijuana</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>10</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Physical and mental disability</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>From four Elementary Schools (two public and two private) with13 class groups from 2nd and 3rd grade two groups were formed. Group 1: two schools (1 public and 1 private with 7 class groroups); group 2: and two schools (1 public and 1 private with 6 class groups from 2nd and 3rd grade). The composition of group 1 and 2 were put a sealed envelop with a label on it.</concealment>
    <sequence>A person not involved in the intervention label with number 1 or 2 on either side of a coin and tossed the coin.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <state>Baja California</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Montserrat Bacardi-Gascon</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Circuito Miraluna 1822A
Fracc. Altabrisa  CP 22390
Tijuana 
Baja California</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Mexico</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidad Autonoma de Baja California</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Julian Carrillo/Alvaro Obregon s/n
Colonia Nueva CP 21100
Mexicali
Baja California</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Mexico</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Colegio Familia School</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Avda de las Brisas s/n
Fracc. Altabrisa
Tijuana
Baja California</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Mexico</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Maria Eugenia Perez- Morales</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>14418 Avda Tecnologico
Parque Industrial Internacional
Mesa de Otay
Tijuana
Baja California</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Mexico</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Arturo Jimenez- Cruz</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>14418 Avda Tecnologico
Parque Industrial Internacional
Mesa de Otay
Tijuana
Baja California</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Mexico</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of this study, focused on parents and children to reduce sedentary behavior, consumption of soft drinks and high-fat containing snacks, and increase the consumption of fruits and vegetables, is to assess the effect of a six month intervention and an 18 months follow up on the body mass index, food consumption and physical activity of 2nd and 3rd grade elementary school children.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite de Etica de Ciencias de la Salud</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Facultad de Ciencias Quimicas e Ingenierias
14418 Avda Tecnologico
Parque Industrial Internacional
Tijuana
Baja california</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/09/0031</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/12/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Mexico</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Montserrat Bacardi-Gascon</name>
      <address>Facultad de Medicina y Psicologia
14418 Avda. Tecnologico
Edificio 4
Parque Industrial Internacional</address>
      <phone>52-6646821233</phone>
      <fax>52-6646821233</fax>
      <email>montserrat.bacardi@uabc.edu.mx</email>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Arturo Jimenez-Cruz</name>
      <address>Circuito Miraluna 1822
Altabrisa
Tijuana
BC</address>
      <phone>52-664-9736638</phone>
      <fax>52-664-6821233</fax>
      <email>arturojimenezc@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Montserrat Bacardi-Gascon</name>
      <address>Facultad de Medicina y Psicologia
14418 Avda. Tecnologico
Edificio 4
Parque Industrial Internacional</address>
      <phone>52-6646821233</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>montserrat.bacardi@uabc.edu.mx</email>
      <country>Mexico</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>