<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371573">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001485426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Ketamine, cognition and driving performance</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Effect of Three Stepwise Doses of Intravenously Administered Ketamine Infusions on Cognitive Functioning and Simulated Driving Performance.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Drugged driving</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will receive all three of the following  treatments during the experimental period:  
IV Ketamine infusion (low dose, Step 1), comprising 8mg/hour IV infusion 
Plus initial (one-off) 30mg bolus of ketamine solution. The one-off bolus is administered at the beginning of the infusion. 
IV Ketamine infusion (medium dose, Step 2), comprising 12mg/hour IV infusion  
IV Ketamine infusion (high dose, Step 3), comprising 20mg/hour IV infusion.
All infusions are timed for one hour. A five minute gap is timed between infusion steps. Adherence is monitored by electronically-timed infusion.   
 </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Associations between the treatment (ketamine infusion low, medium and high dose) and driving performance (day and night-time highway and city driving scenarios). 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>After administration of treatment (low medium and high ketamine treatment). Specifically, this will occur at baseline, 30 mins post each treatment step (each following low, medium and high treatment infusion), and 2 hours post-final treatment. This will be assessed using the Forum 8 driving simulator. Weaving of the car, expressed as standard deviation of the lateral position (SDLP), standard deviation of speed (SDS, km/h) and lapses will be assessed.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Associations between the treatment (ketamine infusion low, medium and high dose) and neurocognitive ability (CANTAB computerised battery). 
 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>After administration of treatment (low medium and high ketamine treatment). Specifically, this will occur at baseline, 30 mins post treatment (each following low, medium and high treatment), and 2 hours post-final treatment. This will be assessed using the CANTAB cognitive battery; where reaction time, spatial working memory and working memory will be assessed.  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Concentration of plasma levels of ketamine across time. This will be assessed by taking 5ml blood sample. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>After administration of treatment (low medium and high ketamine treatment). Specifically, this will occur at 30 mins post treatment (each following low, medium and high treatment), and 2 hours post-final treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Association between treatment plasma concentrations across time and cognitive performance. This will be assessed by blood samples and by the CANTAB computerised battery scores for reaction time, spatial working memory and working memory.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>After administration of treatment (low medium and high ketamine treatment). Specifically, this will occur at 30 mins post treatment (each following low, medium and high treatment), and 2 hours post-final treatment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of alertness over time as a function of treatment step. This will be assessed using subjective alertness questions which comprise part of the CANTAB battery. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After administration of treatment (low medium and high ketamine treatment). Specifically, this will occur at baseline, 30 mins post treatment (each following low, medium and high treatment), and 2 hours post-final treatment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Association between treatment plasma concentrations across time and driving simulator performance compared to baseline. This will be assessed using the Forum 8 driving simulator. Weaving of the car, expressed as standard deviation of the lateral position (SDLP), standard deviation of speed (SDS, km/h) and lapses will be assessed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After administration of treatment (low medium and high ketamine treatment). Specifically, this will occur at baseline, 30 mins post treatment (each following low, medium and high treatment), and 2 hours post-final treatment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relatedness to performance outcomes on the cognitive and driving simulator tasks.  This will be assessed by evaluating he predictive ability of performance on the CANTAB cognitive battery to performance on the driving simulator task.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After administration of treatment (low medium and high ketamine treatment). Specifically, this will occur at 30 mins post treatment (each following low, medium and high treatment), and 2 hours post-final treatment </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged between 21 and 45 years.  
Hold a full drivers licence (no P plates). 
No known allergic reaction to ketamine or other related opioids.   
Have no history of past substance abuse or current abuse of illicit drugs. 
Have no pre-existing physical or neurological conditions, no previous or current history of severe psychiatric, cardiac, endocrine, gastrointestinal, or bleeding disorders. 
Not currently pregnant or lactating  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability to speak or read English. 
Taking any form of medication within 5 days of admission (except for prophylactic antibiotics, contraceptive pill or other routine medications to treat benign conditions, such as antibiotics to treat acne) and agree not to take any medication throughout the study. 
Unable to participate in scheduled visit, treatment plan, tests and other trial procedures according to the protocol. 
Current participation in any other trials involving investigational or marketed products within 30 days prior to the screening visit. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>Non-randomised trial</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This study will employ a within subjects design, and will be open label. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Demographic data will be presented with summary statistics (number of participants, mean, standard deviation, median and range). The number and percentage of subjects will be presented for categorical variables.  
All statistical tests will be performed two tailed at the 5% significance level and performed using IBM SPSS statistical package. Z scores for the distribution will be calculated for each variable and displayed in histogram form. Out of range values will be recoded as missing values. 
Results for the driving simulator will be assessed using a within subjects one-way analysis of covariance (ANCOVA), with treatment step (Step 1, 2 or 3) as the within-subject variable and baseline score as the covariate.  
Results for the CANTAB cognitive battery will also be compared using a within subjects one-way analysis of covariance (ANCOVA), with treatment step (Step 1, 2 or 3) as the within-subject variable, and baseline score as the covariate.  
Correlations between CANTAB VAS scores and performance outcomes on CANTAB tasks and the driving simulator across time points as function of treatment will be conducted using Pearson product moment coefficient r. 
The relationship between ketamine plasma concentrations and VAS effects will be analysed by linear regression. 
Results for the Drugwipe 6S will be assessed as function of treatment and will be presented as a binary outcome (detection yes/no). A binary logistic regression model will be used, with detection status (present/absent) as the outcome, and treatment step (Step 1, 2 or 3) used as the categorical predictor variable. Baseline data and demographic information will be entered sequentially to assess for possible effect-modification.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>22/09/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>16/11/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>20</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash Medical Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton Victoria 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash Medical Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton Victoria 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The clinical utility of ketamine as demonstrated efficacy as a novel antidepressant and anti-anxiolytic, as well as a low-risk, effective tool to manage chronic pain among treatment resistant patients. Perhaps paradoxically, however, the associated cognitive, behavioural and attention impairments pose significant implications for driving ability and road safety. Despite this, no studies are currently available which explicitly assess the effect of sub-anaesthetic doses of ketamine on several facets of neurocognitive functioning related to driving performance, as well as explicit assessments of driving impairment. 
This study aims to  assess the effect of three doses of intravenously (IV) administered ketamine infusions delivered in an increasing step-dose manner on measures of higher-order cognitive processes and driving simulator performance. We will also assess the relatedness between the level of ketamine in the blood samples and over the 8 hour testing session in order to assess the relationship between ketamine blood concentration, cognitive function and driving ability. We also want to monitor the relationship between the treatment (ketamine infusion low, medium or high dose) and levels of subjective alertness over time, and how this relates to performance outcomes on the cognitive and driving tasks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/MonH/240</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Yahya Shehabi</name>
      <address>Program Director Critical Care 
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
Clayton Victoria 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9594 2730</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yahya.shehabi@monashhealth.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amie Hayley</name>
      <address>Mail H20 
Swinburne University of Technology, 
Faculty of Health, Arts and Design School of Health Sciences 
Centre for Human Psychopharmacology 
PO Box 218 
Hawthorn, 
Victoria, 3122 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9214 5585</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ahayley@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amie Hayley</name>
      <address>Mail H20 
Swinburne University of Technology, 
Faculty of Health, Arts and Design School of Health Sciences 
Centre for Human Psychopharmacology 
PO Box 218 
Hawthorn, 
Victoria, 3122 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9214 5585</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ahayley@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Amie Hayley</name>
      <address>Mail H20 
Swinburne University of Technology, 
Faculty of Health, Arts and Design School of Health Sciences 
Centre for Human Psychopharmacology 
PO Box 218 
Hawthorn, 
Victoria, 3122 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9214 5585</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ahayley@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>