<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335655">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000842066</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase 1/2 Study of Valproate in Combination with Interferon alpha in Relapsed, Recurrent or Progressive Neuroblastoma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1/2 Study to define the objective response rate of Paediatric Patients with Relapsed, Recurrent or Progressive Neuroblastoma to Valproate in Combination with Interferon alpha</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>ACCT003

Australian and New Zealand Children's Haematology and Oncology Group</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Relapsed, Recurrent or Progressive Neuroblastoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Other</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Course 1: Interferon: 3 MU/m2 subcutaneous (SC) given 3 times per week. Valproate: commence at 10 mg/kg/day, increase weekly until trough level reaches 525-700 micromoles/L.

Courses 2-12: Interferon: 3 MU/m2 SC given 3 times per week. Valproate: dose to maintain trough at 525-700 micromoles/L

Mode of administration: Valproate - oral, Interferon - subcutaneous injection

Treatment duration is 12 courses.  Due to the time required for dose escalation to reach desired concentration range, Course 1 may be significantly longer than 28 days.  Interferon therapy will continue throughout Course 1, whatever its length.  All subsequent treatment courses will be 28 days in duration.</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To define the objective response rate of relapsed/refractory neuroblastoma patients to the combination interferon alpha and valproic acid.

All imaging modalities that showed any abnormality at commencement of therapy will be repeated to evaluate response.  Imaging modalities include metaiodobenzylguanidine (MIBG) scan, computerised tomography (CT) scan / magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan, bone scane, bone marrow aspirate.  Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours (RECIST) will be used for patients with solid tumours.  Patients with bone marrow disease will be assessed on morphologic evidence of neuroblastoma by routine H and E staining. Patients who have a positive MIBG san at the start of therapy will be evaluable for MIBG response.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Interim analysis of response rate will be performed after 15 patients have been assessed for tumour response.  If at least 2 objective tumour responses are seen, a further 10 patients will be enrolled and response rate analysied for all 25 patients.
Patients will be re-evaluated for response every 8 weeks until disease progression. In addition to a baseline scan, confirmatory scans should also be obtained at least four weeks following initial documentation of objective response.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the toxicities of the combination treatment of interferon alpha and valproic acid.
The National Cancer Institute Common Toxicity Criteria (NCI-CTC) V3.0 will be used to classify and grade the intensity of adverse events and their relationship to study drug administration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All patients will be evaluable for toxicity from the time of their first treatment. 
Adverse events are to be recorded at every cycle during treatment and 30 days post last study drug administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the effects of the combination treatment on time to disease progression.
All imaging modalities that showed any abnormality at commencement of therapy will be repeated to evaluate response.  Imaging modalities include MIBG, CT/MRI, bone scane, bone marrow aspirate.  Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumours (RECIST) will be used for patients with solid tumours.  Patients with bone marrow disease will be assessed on morphologic evidence of neuroblastoma by routine H and E staining. Patients who have a positive MIBG san at the start of therapy will be evaluable for MIBG response.
Overall response will be defined using The International Neuroblastoma Response Criteria. The International Neuroblastoma Response Criteria were developed to define responses in patients being treated for neuroblastoma with frontline therapy.  These were utilized as a basis for the following response criteria, which integrate response at all sites defined as measurable in this study, including CT/MRI lesions which meet RECIST criteria, MIBG positive lesions, and bone marrow disease.  These criteria will be used to define the overall response for the patient in the statistical analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be re-evaluated for response every 8 weeks until disease progression.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the effects of combination treatment on overall survival.
Outcomes will be assessed at clinic visits.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be followed up after the completion of treatment to determine overall survival for up to 5 years following completion of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To measure the effect of interferon alpha and valproic acid on angiogenesis.
Blood will be sent to Professor Marshall's laboratory at the Children's Cancer Institute Australia (CCIA), prior to treatment, and prior to Cycle 3 for anti-angiogenic markers and endothelial cell inhibitory studies.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples are collected prior to treatment and prior to Cycle 3.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Target tumour is neuroblastoma.
Patient must have one of the following:
 - recurrent disease following aggressive multidrug frontline chemotherapy and autologous transplantation
- resistent/refractory disease during aggressive multidrug frontline chemotherapy
Patients must have measurable disease
Patients must have a performance level of 0, 1, or 2 using Karnofsky scale or Lansky scale
Patients must have a life expectancy of greater than or equatl to 8 weeks
Patients must have fully recovered from the actue toxic effects of all prior chemotherapy, immunotherapy, or radiotherapy prior to entering the study
Patients must have adequate organ function</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>21</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with recurrent or progressive benign lesions without viable malignant neuroblastoma
Patients do not meet concomitant medication restrictions
For female patients, pregnancy and breast feeding
Myeloplastic syndrome
Uncontrolled infection</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible patients will enrolled in 2 cohorts. Stage 1, 15 patients evaluable for toxicity will be accrued. Stage 2, an additional 10 patients will be accrued.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/06/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC,QLD,SA,WA</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian and New Zealand Children's Haematology and Oncology Group</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 5418 Clayton VIC 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study looks at the effectiveness of valproate in combination with interferon alpha in treating relapsed, recurrent or progressive neuroblastoma in children.

Who is it for?

You can join this study if you are 21 years or younger with relapsed or refractory (stubborn and resistant to treatment) neuroblastoma and you have no other effective treatment options available.

Participants will receive treatment with a specific combination of valproic acid and interferon.

Valproic acid is an anticonvulsant that has been shown to have an anti-cancer effect.  New data has shown that the combination of valproic acid and interferon has an anit-neuroblastoma effect.  The study aims to assess the effectiveness of this treatment, and monitor toxicity and side effects.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Alexandra Hospital for Children HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Children's Hospital at Westmead
PO Box 4001 Westmead NSW 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/02/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Ziegler</name>
      <address>Sydney Children's Hospital
High St
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+612 9382 1730</phone>
      <fax>+612 9382 1789</fax>
      <email>d.ziegler@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Helen Mueller</name>
      <address>Sydney Children's Hospital
High St
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+612 9382-1980</phone>
      <fax>+612 9382 1789</fax>
      <email>Helen.Mueller@SESIAHS.HEALTH.NSW.GOV.AU</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Robyn Strong</name>
      <address>27-31 Wright St
Clayton VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+613 9902 4852</phone>
      <fax>+613 9902 4810</fax>
      <email>acct@anzchog.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Ziegler</name>
      <address>Sydney Children's Hospital High St Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+612 9382 1730</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.ziegler@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>