<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371141">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000614392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Whakapai e Te Ara Ha: Asthma Self-Management Programme for the whanau of tamariki Maori with Asthma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Whakapai e Te Ara Ha: Asthma Self-Management Programme. A single-blinded, parallel group, randomised controlled trial of the impact of a culturally-relevant peer-support and self-management programme, on activation and quality of life among the parents/caregivers of Maori children aged 4-13 years old with asthma in New Zealand, and asthma control, quality of life and health-care utilisation among their children. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1183-1961 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Wheeze
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will receive a six-month holistic, culturally-based peer-support programme.   The intervention will comprise two phases: an initial 6-week intensive 'whakawhanaungatanga (relationship building) period and an awhi (support) maintenance period over the remainder of the 6 months.  

The 6-week initial intervention is an approved research derivative of the Stanford Chronic Disease Self-Management Program (CDSMP), it has been customised for our particular requirements (i.e. for the parent/caregiver of a child with asthma and culturally appropriate for Maori).  The programme consists of six 2-2.5 hour community-based, peer-led patient self-management education workshops which take place weekly over six weeks. Sessions include general topics about chronic disease management: e.g. exercise; use of cognitive symptom management techniques; nutrition; fatigue and sleep management; use of community resources; use of medications; dealing with emotions (anxiety, depression etc.); communication with health professionals; problem-solving; and decision-making. 

The informational materials and training requirements for the CDSMP programme are available here: http://patienteducation.stanford.edu/programs/cdsmp.html. The CDSMP derivative incorporates materials approved for use within a New Zealand context, specifically the Diabetes and Healthy Food Choices guide, published by Diabetes New Zealand, and all materials incorporate the use of Te Reo Maori. The Children and Asthma booklet published by the Asthma and Respiratory Foundation of New Zealand will be provided to all participants (both cases and controls) as it outlines relevant disease specific information.
 
The workshops will be led by Stanford approved peer-leaders who have been specifically trained in the research derivative of the CDSMP programme. Peer leaders (a combination of research staff and lay community members) all have lived-experience of long-term condition management with asthma. Programme fidelity is ensured by direct oversight of all peer leaders and workshops by two CDSMP Master Trainers in accordance with usual Stanford CDSMP programme fidelity requirements.

After the initial phase, research staff will maintain fortnightly telephone contact to check-in with whanau (families) (the awhi phase) to provide as-needed support with referrals, healthcare navigation, additional skill development. 

Participants in this group are able to access care from their GP as usual. This culturally-based approach differs from mainstream intensive asthma management programmes in that it is Te Ao Maori (Maori worldview)-centred.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual Care. Participants in the control group will receive appropriate educational resources (Children and Asthma Booklet) from the Asthma Foundation of NZ and be followed-up by their usual GP without limitation. All control group participants will be offered referral to a Maori health provider (or Asthma Society) of their preference at the end of the trial (i.e. 12-months following baseline). No restriction is placed on participation in other usual care pathways or disease-specific education.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent or caregiver activation, as measured by parent or caregiver Patient Activation Measure (PAM), a validated scale of activation.  This will be completed by the parent or caregiver.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>To be completed at baseline, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Asthma Control, as measured by the Child Asthma Control Test (C-ACT).  This will be completed by the child and the parent or caregiver.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Completed at baseline, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Healthcare Utilisation, expressed as the number of ED presentations or hospital admissions for asthma or wheeze over the previous 12 months, by interviewer administered questionnaire. The questionnaire was designed specifically for this study but derived in large part from the New Zealand Health Survey (Child Questionnaire) .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parents/Caregivers Quality of Life: 
Assessed via the Paediatric Asthma Caregiver Quality of Life Questionnaire (PACQLQ) and the EuroQol EQ-5D-Y (Proxy 1 Version) 

 </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at baseline, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child Quality of Life: 
Assessed via the Paediatric Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire (PAQLQ) and EuroQol EQ-5D-Y </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at baseline, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Healthcare Utilisation - Afterhours/Urgent GP visits
This data will be collected by interviewer-administered questionnaires from participants.
The questionnaire was designed specifically for this study but derived in large part from the New Zealand Health Survey (Child Questionnaire) .
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Economic Impact (Cost effectiveness &amp; Cost-utility)
Data collection for this outcome will include the detailed healthcare utilisation (as above), but additionally an assessment of direct medical costs (GP visits, prescriptions etc.) and indirect costs such as loss of productivity (e.g. days missed from school due to asthma, caregiver days missed from work due to asthma). Again, for the purposes of standardisation, these data will be obtained by interviewer-administered questionnaire using questions based on the New Zealand Health Survey.
The most appropriate economic evaluation method, given the data availability, is a cost effectiveness analysis in which the change in costs and health effects between those at baseline and study end are compared. In addition, however, we also aim to collect robust quality of life data, which will permit a cost utility study using the EQ5D-Y with New Zealand weights applied.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months. Reported at baseline vs 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative Assessment (Acceptability &amp; Effectiveness) 
A Phenomenological Approach will be used to analyse participant experiences.  Semi-structured interviews will be undertaken with a purposive sub-group of participants at the end of the intervention. Interviews will capture whanau experiences of the intervention, aspects that were successful, and areas requiring refinements or adaptations. Interviews will be recorded, transcribed verbatim, then organised and coded within NVivo (Trademark) software.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at completion of the intervention (6 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Parents/caregivers of children will be recruited prospectively through the Paediatric wards, Child Assessment Units, and Emergency Departments of participating District Health Boards (PROSPECTIVE). Additionally, invitations from eligible children with historic admissions/presentations to hospital or emergency departments from the same participating DHBs will supplement recruitment in batched reverse sequential order (RETROSPECTIVE). 

Parents/caregivers will be eligible to participate if their child is: 
a) between 4-13 years, 
b) identifies as NZ Maori ethnicity (prioritised, self/parental reported), 
c) has a doctor diagnosis of asthma, 
d) has a previous hospitalisation or Emergency Department presentation for asthma or wheeze (ICD-10-AM code: J45,J46 or R06.2), and 
e) usually resides within the geographical catchment area of the participating DHBs (District Health Boards).

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Parents/caregivers will be excluded from participating if their child: 
a) has previously been enrolled in the study;
 b) has a sibling on the study; 
c) does not reasonably expect to remain in the region for the duration of the intervention and follow-up or 
d) have other chronic respiratory comorbidities that may be deemed to interfere with the study (e.g. bronchiectasis).
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealed- central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Up to 315 participants will be recruited from participating district health boards. Allowing for a drop-out rate of 10% means this will provide 143 participants per group (treatment and control) for analysis. 

There are three primary outcomes for this study. Patient Activation, as measured by the PAM after the participants have completed the workshop (primarily evaluated at 12 weeks post baseline); the childhood asthma control test (C-ACT), (primarily evaluated at six months after baseline); and number of hospitalizations (admissions or ED presentations) per year, (primarily evaluated at one year post baseline).

143 participants per group will provide 80% power to detect, at the 0.05 level, an effect size d of 0.5, or a difference in mean PAM scores of 66 to 73 (G*Power 3.1.9.2). This size of difference was seen in Morrison et al (REF: Morrison D, Wyke S, Saunderson K, McConnachie A, Agur K, Chaudhuri R, Thomas M, Thomson NC, Yardley L, Mair FS, Findings from a pilot randomised trial of an asthma internet self-management intervention (RAISIN), BMJ Open, 2016; 6: e009254. DIO: 10.1136/bmjopen-2015-009254).

143 participants per group will provide 80% power to detect, at the 0.05 level, a difference in mean C-ACT of 20 to 22 between the two groups (G*Power 3.1.9.2). this is the same size of difference found by Piacentini et al (REF: Piacentini GL, Peroni DG, Bodini A, Bonafiglia E, Rigotti E, Baraldi E, Liu AH, and Boner AL, Childhood asthma control test and airway inflammation evaluation in asthmatic children, Allergy 2009; 64:1753-1757).

143 participants per group will provide 80% power to detect at the 0.05 level, a difference in admission/ ED presentation rates between 0.96 and 0.55, the difference observed by Greineder et al (REF: Greineder DK, Loane KC, Parks P, A randomized controlled trial of a 23 pediatric outreach program, J Allergy Clin Immunol, March 1999, pp 436-440). 
(https://www.statstodo.com/SSiz2Counts_Tab.php).

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>315</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/11/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago- Wellington</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>23a Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington
New Zealand
6021
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3 - ProCARE Building, Grafton Mews, at 110 Stanley Street,  Grafton, Auckland 1010

PO Box 5541, Wellesley Street, Auckland 1141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Asthma currently affects about 26% of NZ children, a rate that is amongst the highest in the world and the burden of asthma to these affected families is considerable. Forty-two percent of asthmatic children are uncontrolled, 12% miss school each month, and 14% attend an emergency department or are admitted to hospital with asthma each year. tamariki Maori (Maori children) suffer higher severity of asthma symptoms; have significantly higher rates of hospitalisation; are less likely to have a peak flow meter or asthma action plan; and fewer are prescribed regular inhaled corticosteroids. 

Health literacy has increasingly been recognised as an important modifiable determinant of health, especially for people with long-term conditions. Clear evidence demonstrates associations between parental literacy and health outcomes, particularly for young children. Health literacy also strongly correlates with poor asthma knowledge and improper inhaler use. We have previously shown that tamariki Maori with asthma face a significant knowledge burden, on-going challenges with chronic disease management, and often struggle with the complexities of navigating healthcare systems. Whanau expressed a clear aspiration for better asthma services which develop their asthma skills in a mana enhancing way while supporting their own capacities and resilience.  

This study will assess a whanau-centered, culturally tailored, health literacy based intervention, derived from a well validated and internationally recognised intervention programme. The Chronic Disease Self-Management Programme (CDSMP) has been widely demonstrated to lead to improved health outcomes for people with chronic illnesses such as asthma in adult populations.  We have adapted this programme for use within a Kaupapa Maori framework and for completion by the parents/caregivers of children with asthma. 

Participants in the intervention group will enter an initial 6 week phase involving peer-led
workshops. This will be followed by a 6 month support phase to foster the building of health literacy skills, activation (empowerment) and self-management in tamariki Maori with asthma and their parents/caregivers. The control group will receive usual care including asthma information resources and GP followup.

The study aims to assess the effectiveness of this intervention on patient activation, asthma control, health-related quality of life, cost effectiveness, and healthcare utilisation. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Postal address:
Ministry of Health
Health and Disability Ethics Committees
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6140

Street address:
133 Molesworth Street
Thorndon
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/NTB/95</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tristram Ingham</name>
      <address>University of Otago Wellington
23a Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington
New Zealand 6022

PO Box 7343
Wellington South
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+6449186842</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tristram.ingham@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Aldridge</name>
      <address>University of Otago Wellington
23a Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington
New Zealand 6022

PO Box 7343
Wellington South
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+6449186041</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>wtr@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tristram Ingham</name>
      <address>University of Otago Wellington
23a Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington
New Zealand 6022

PO Box 7343
Wellington South
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+6449186842</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tristram.ingham@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tristram Ingham</name>
      <address>University of Otago Wellington
23a Mein Street
Newtown
Wellington
New Zealand 6022

PO Box 7343
Wellington South
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+649186842</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tristram.ingham@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>