<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363100">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001051831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Intranasal white petrolatum versus chlorhexidine to reduce postoperative infections in dermatologic surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients scheduled for dermatologic surgery, is intranasal white petrolatum or chlorhexidine more effective than normal saline in reducing postoperative infections?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1135-3062</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Incidence of postoperative wound infections</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Prevalance of staphylococcus aureus carriage</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Skin Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Non melanoma skin cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Referrals to the Skin Centre for excision of skin cancers will be selected for possible inclusion by one of five participating Consultant Dermatologists. Eligible and consenting patients will at the time of consultation for surgery, fill in a short questionnaire for demographic data and have a nasal swab to assess staphylococcus aureus carriage. The patients will be randomised to either intranasal white petrolatum, 2% chlorhexidine or normal saline to the anterior nares. Five days prior to elective surgery, all patients will apply one of three treatments (depending on randomisation) to the anterior nares twice daily. In the chlorhexidine arm and the normal saline arm, this will be in the manner of a soaked cotton bud whereas in the white petrolatum arm, this will be in the manner of a cotton bud application.  All patients will have their wound assessed at the time of suture removal (expected range: 5  14 days depending on type of surgery) or if any clinical signs of wound infection occur outside this time frame (up to one month post-surgery). All infected wounds will be swabbed. The incidence of wound infection will be collected and a comparison will be made to the incidence of wound infection in patients being treated with intranasal white petrolatum, 2% chlorhexidine and individuals using intranasal normal saline.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo - Normal saline in anterior nares twice daily for five days prior to elective surgery.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the efficacy of intranasal application of white petrolatum or chlorhexidine for reducing wound infections. The incidence of wound infections in the group using white petrolatum or chlorhexidine in the anterior nares (nostrils) will be compared to the incidence of wound infections in the group using normal saline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the prevalance of nasal carriage of staphylococcus aureus. The number of nasal swabs being positive (positive culture for growth) for staphylococcus aureus amongst the entire study population will be reported.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine which patients would benefit most from this approach if proven to be effective. A subgroup analysis would be performed to determine if there are any patient related factors (eg. Age, recent hospitalisation etc) which would place the patient at high risk for intranasal staphylococcus aureus carriage or high risk of post-operative wound infections.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To prove the cost-effectiveness of this method to reduce wound infections. The cost of intranasal white petrolatum and 2% chlorhexidine would be compared against the cost of managing post-operative wound infection.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients scheduled for elective dermatologic surgery for removal of skin cancer.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current infection
Current antibiotic therapy
Antibiotic use in the last month
Failure to have intranasal swab to assess carriage of S. aureus prior to surgery</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer. Each enrolled patient would be allocated a number and central randomisation by a computer program will be utilised.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be performed using block randomisation where patients will be allocated to treatment of intranasal white petrolatum or intranasal normal saline per surgeon per time.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>16/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Bay of Plenty</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eugene Tan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Skin Cancer Institute
171 Cameron Road
Tauranga 3110</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Skin Cancer Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>171 Cameron Road
Tauranga 3110</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Paul Salmon</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Skin Cancer Institute
171 Cameron Road
Tauranga 3110</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Neil Mortimer</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Skin Cancer Institute
171 Cameron Road
Tauranga 3110</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Professor Marius Rademaker</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Waikato Hospital
Pembroke Street
Hamilton</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>New Zealand has the highest rate of skin cancers in the world which leads to a large number of skin excisions. About 30-40% of the population carry a bacterium known as Staphylococcus aureus. Carriage of this bacterium has been shown to increase the risk of surgical wound infections by up to eight times. Earlier studies have assessed the effectiveness of a topical antibiotic, mupirocin to eradicate carriage of Staphylococcus aureus. Unfortunately, this method has been complicated by bacterial resistance and allergic skin reactions. In this study, we want to see whether applying white petrolatum (Vaseline) or Chlorhexidine is effective for eradicating nasal carriage of staphylococcus aureus and reducing wound infections in dermatologic surgery. If proven to be effective, this simple method may be a safe and economic method to reduce the incidence of wound infections in dermatologic surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
1 the Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011
New Zealand</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/01/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/NTA/79</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/10/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr. Eugene Tan</name>
      <address>171 Cameron Road
Tauranga 3110</address>
      <phone>+64-7-5785788</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eugenederm@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr. Eugene Tan</name>
      <address>171 Cameron Road
Tauranga 3110</address>
      <phone>+64-7-5785788</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>spinothalamic@yahoo.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Eugene Tan</name>
      <address>171 Cameron Road
Tauranga 3110</address>
      <phone>+64-7-5785788</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eugenederm@gmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eugene Tan</name>
      <address>Skin Cancer Institute
171 Cameron Road
Tauranga 3110</address>
      <phone>+64-7-5785788</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>spinothalamic@yahoo.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>