<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336802">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/04/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000398909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Double blind, randomised, placebo controlled trial of Sativex for the management of cannabis withdrawal</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Double blind, randomised, placebo controlled trial of Sativex for the management of cannabis withdrawal</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1120-7086</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cannabis withdrawal</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Investigational drug: Sativex (1 spray: 2.7 mg THC and 2.5 mg CBD) in an alcohol and peppermint oil liquid administered as an oromucosal spray onto the inside of the mouth (but not intended to be swallowed and digested through the stomach - so some time (1 minute) should be taken after each single spray is administered to ensure absorption, before the next spray is administered). The patient cannot choose when they receive their 8 spray dose, they must have them all at the 6 hourly interval.

Dosage form/strength: maximum 800 uL every six hours (X8 sprays every six hours). Participants may not take partial doses (i.e. 6 sprays) but they can ask to miss up to two of the 6 hourly dose in a day. Patients are in hospital for 8 nights, discharging on day 9.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo spray - comprising alcohol and peppermint oil</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported measures of cannabis withdrawal using the Cannabis Withdrawal Scale (a modified version of the MWC (Budney et al., 1999)).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four times a day for 9 days (6am, 11 am, 6pm and 10pm)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment completion, defined as completing 9 days of inpatient treatment under protocol conditions (categorical yes/no); and number of days of inpatient treatment completed (range: 0-9).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Quantified once on day of patient discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events during the inpatient treatment period using a tailor made Adverse Events Checklist and administered by clinician/nurse/medical officer. Adverse events may include any of the following: Dizziness, Dry mouth, Tachycardia, Stomache ache, Slowed motor skills, slowed reaction time, anxiety, dysphoria, paranoia, oro-mucosal ulceration. Adverse events will be rated on a 0 - 3 scale, 0 being None, 1 being Mild, 2 being Moderate, 3 being Severe.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Once daily for the 9 days of inpatient stay</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported cannabis use with total days used cannabis (range 0-28) and longest period of continuous abstinence (range 0-28) during the one month follow-up period (quantifying rates of continuous and point prevalence abstinence from cannabis, time to relapse, levels of cannabis use, and cannabis related problems at follow up), using the Timeline Followback method</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (day 1 of entry into inpatient unit) for the previous 28 days, and at follow up (28 days after discharge from hospital)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urine Carboxy-THC: creatinine ratio using Gas Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (day 1 of entry into inpatient unit), daily during 9 day inpatient stay and at follow up (28 days after discharge from hospital)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood plasma profiles of cannabinoid metabolites (THC and its primary metabolite (THC-COOH) to CBD and its primary metabolite (CBD-7-oic acid))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 of intake to the inpatient unit(pre-sativex). And the same measures taken after Sativex has been administered to participants (taken on days 3 and 7).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cannabis Problems Questionnaire (Copeland, Gilmour, Gates, &amp; Swift, 2005)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Day 1) and Follow up (28 days after discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brief Treatment Outcome Measure-Social Functioning Scale (Lawrinson, Copeland, &amp; Indig, 2005)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Day 1) and Follow up (28 days after discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insomnia severity index (Bastien, Vallieres, &amp; Morin, 2001)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Day 1), Discharge (Day 9) and Follow up (28 days after discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cannabis Dependence using the Severity of Dependence Scale (SDS) (Martin, Copeland, Gates, &amp; Gilmour, 2006; Swift, Copeland, &amp; Hall, 1998)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Day 1), Discharge (Day 9) and Follow up (28 days after discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression, Anxiety and Stress measures using the 21 item version of the Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Day 1), Discharge (Day 9) and Follow up (28 days after discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life using the Sheehan Disability Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Day 1) and Follow up (28 days after discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self efficacy for Quitting Cannabis Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Day 1), Discharge (Day 9) and Follow up (28 days after discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety Sensitivity Index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Day 1) and Follow up (28 days after discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Distress tolerance Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (Day 1) and Follow up (28 days after discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Between 18-65 years of age (Both males and females)
2. Regular recent cannabis use (average of 5 times per week  self report)
3. Meet DSM-IV-TR 'Registered Trademark' criteria for cannabis dependence
4. Has made unsuccessful quit attempts in the past                 		
5. Desire to give up cannabis
6. Prepared to enter a hospital ward for 9 days

If NO to any (1 - 6) client is not eligible for SATIVEX trial phone screen, provide usual referral/treatment advice.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. More than twice weekly use of an illicit drug in the last 30 days (other than cannabis)
2. Dependence on a substance other than cannabis and tobacco
3. Pregnant or breastfeeding
4. Female of child bearing potential NOT using contraception
5. Evidence of severe medical impairment (e.g. chronic pain, severe hepatic impairment or cardiovascular disease)
6. Evidence of severe cognitive or psychiatric impairment (e.g. bipolar, schizophrenia, suicidal ideation)
7. Current (within past month) prescription for antipsychotic or mood stabilising medications   
8. Currently prescribed warfarin
9. Allergy to cannabinoids, propylene glycol, ethanol or peppermint oil
10. Not English literate
 11. Specialist substance use treatment in the last 30 days</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involves contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who was "off-site" or at central administration</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants receive either Sativex or Placebo - never both, and participants are anticipated to come into the study one at a time (at each of the two study sites)</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/07/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2000</postcode>
    <postcode>2300</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of New South Wales
SYDNEY
NSW 2052
AUSTRALIA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Belmont District Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Croudace Bay Road, Belmont NSW 2280</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Sydney &amp; Sydney Eye Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>GPO Box 1614, Sydney NSW 2001 Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective of the study is to examine the safety and efficacy of SATIVEX 'Registered Trademark (R)' in the inpatient management of cannabis withdrawal, in a double blinded randomised trial compared to placebo. Specifically, the study will compare withdrawal severity, detoxification completion and adverse events between the two conditions in an intention-to-treat analysis. Secondary objectives include 1-month post-withdrawal outcomes (including cannabis and other drug use and psychosocial outcomes), and to assess the relationship between the number, severity and duration of cannabis withdrawal symptoms and rates of continuous and point prevalence abstinence from cannabis, time to relapse, levels of cannabis use, and cannabis related problems at one month follow-up. The study will also explore the cognitive impact of withdrawing from cannabis, as well as the impact of SATIVEX on cognitive functioning, with an aim to assessing the real world safety profile of the drug ahead of larger outpatient studies. The study will also explore the pharmacokinetics and metabolites associated with SATIVEX (R) administration to develop a protocol for differentiating between SATIVEX(R) and illicit cannabis in blood or urine among those entering cannabis withdrawal treatment. This pharmacokinetic assay will prove useful for future large scale outpatient trials should the current trial prove successful. A final exploratory objective of the study is to determine whether there is evidence of an interaction with the efficacy of SATIVEX(R) and patient characteristics on admission (including demographics and cannabis and other use and psychosocial factors such as treatment expectancy) on reported severity of cannabis withdrawal and subsequent post-withdrawal outcomes (cannabis use, psychosocial outcomes, sleep disturbances and cannabis-related problems) to be fully tested in a larger community study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag No 1
New Lambton, NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/02/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10/12/15/3.02</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Jan Copeland</name>
      <address>National Cannabis Prevention and Information Centre, NDARC, UNSW, Sydney NSW, 2052, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2  9385 0208</phone>
      <fax>+61 2  9385 0201</fax>
      <email>j.copeland@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Jan Copeland</name>
      <address>National Cannabis Prevention and Information Centre, NDARC, UNSW, Sydney NSW, 2052, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2  9385 0208</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 0201</fax>
      <email>j.copeland@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr David Allsop</name>
      <address>National Cannabis Prevention and Information Centre, NDARC, UNSW, Sydney NSW, 2052, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2  9385 0448</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9385 0201</fax>
      <email>d.allsop@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>