<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336166">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000200987</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Menopausal transition and prospects of treatment</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Supplementation with alpha lipoic acid and hormone therapy with tibolone in menopausal transition: impact on oxidative stress, bone mass and quality of life.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1117-6294</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Protocol number 178/08 of Research Ethics Committee of Onofre Lopes University Hospital</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>CAAE number 294/08</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>climacteric syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>menopause</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Menstruation and menopause</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal metabolism and endocrine development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The trial was conducted as a prospective,
randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind. Eligible participants were randomized into four groups: 
The control group(G1) - consisting of 35 participants received capsules containing placebo - microcellulose capsule;
The Tibolone Group(G2) - consisting of 30 participants received capsules containing 2.5 mg tibolone per day(Reduclin (Registered Trademark) 2.5 mg, produced by Farmoquimica S/A, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, registered in the Ministry of health  science of Brazil number 1.0390.0136-001);
The alpha lipoic acid group(G3) - consisting of 32 participants received capsules containing 600 mg of alpha lipoic acid per day;
The tibolone and alpha lipoic group(G4) consisting of 32 participants received capsules containing 2.5 mg of tibolone per day and 600 mg of alpha lipoic acid per day.
This study  lasted 12 weeks. Participants were assessed at baseline, 4, 8 and 12 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Tibolone and  Alpha lipoic acid for twelve weeks with daily intake of 03 capsules all identical.The type of placebo used was microcellulose capsule.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Climacterics Symptoms</outcome>
      <timepoint>The Kupperman Index(IMK) and Greene Climacteric Scale was determined at each visit. They were detected before treatement(baseline), at weeks 4 and 8(during treatment)  and at week 12(end of treatment).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Activity of blood antioxidant enzymes: glutathione peroxidase, superoxide dismutase, catalase and thiobarbituric acid reactive substances.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Glutathione peroxidase activity was determined using quantitative and qualitative characterization of erythrocyte glutathione reductase. Superoxide dismutase activity  and catalase were determined spectrophotometrically. Serum thiobarbituric acid reactive substances levels were  calculated using a molar absorption coefficient.  They were detected before treatment(baseline) and at week 12(end of treatment).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life before and after treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Utian Quality of Life - Menopause - UQol. They were detected before treatment(baseline), at weeks 4 and 8 (during treatment) and at week 12(end of treatment).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemical and hematological parameters</outcome>
      <timepoint>alanine aminotransferases,  creatinine,  triglycerides, fasting glucose,  gamma-glutamyl transferase (GGT), iron,  urea, total protein, albumin and Hb and C-reactive protein analyzer will be measured in 50 RA Bayer, according to the methodology specified by the manufacturers (BioSystems Reagents &amp; Instruments). They were detected before treatment(baseline) and at week 12(end of treatment).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>anthropometric assessment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Body mass index: ratio of weight(Kg) to the square of height(m). 
Abdominal circumference(cms)
The triceps, biceps, subscapular and suprailiac be monitored by equipment Lange Skinfold Caliper, on the right side of the body.They were detected before treatment(baseline), at weeks 4 and 8 (during treatment) and at week 12(end of treatment).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hormone assays(follicle-stimulating hormone)</outcome>
      <timepoint>follicle-stimulating hormone(FSH) kits (Diagnostic Products Corporation, Los Angeles, CA).
The limits of quantification  FSH assays were
30 pg/ml. They were detected before treatment(baseline) and at week 12(end of treatment).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>bone mineral density (BMD)</outcome>
      <timepoint>BMD measurements at lumbar spine 
and proximal femur (femoral neck, Ward's triangle,
trochanter) were performed by dual-energy X-ray
absorptiometry (DEXA) using a scanner Brand LUNAR DPX-L Alpha Dual Energy X-Ray Bone Densitometer (Lunar Radiation Corporation, USA) and Lunar software v. 3.0. They were detected before treatment(baseline).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mammography</outcome>
      <timepoint>They were detected before treatment(baseline).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>transvaginal ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>Evaluate the endometrial echoes that must be below 15 mm in baseline and after 12 weeks of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Menstrual irregularity and/ or less than 12 months amenorrhea;;
Scoring less than 14 points in the Menopausal Index Blatt and Kupperman;
Serum concentrations of FSH &gt;30 IU/L</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a)prior hormone therapy(HT) ; b) amenorrhea for more than 12 months c) early menopause(before age 40 years) or surgical menopause(hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy) d)the presence of systemic diseases (cardiovascular disease, diabetes, hypertension, cerebrovascular disease, thromboembolic disease, hepatic, or renal failure); e)  the presence of osteoporosis; f) the presence of contraindications to HT (endometrial hyperplasia, malignant breast disease, endometrium cancer, undiagnosed vaginal bleeding); g) the presence of acute infection or chronic inflammatory disease; h)the use of drugs that could affect the metabolism (b-blockers, glucocorticoids, diuretics, lipid lowering drugs, antidiabetics, antiresorptives, anticoagulants); i) Smokers; j) the use of alcohol or drug abuse;  l)Body Mass Index&gt; 35 kg / m²;  m)endometrial thickness on transvaginal ultrasound&gt; 15 mm;  n)Results of Cytopathology oncotic previous or current diagnoses of atypia of undetermined significance , high grade intraepithelial lesions, microinvasive carcinoma and cervical cancer;  o)Presents some contraindication to therapy with tibolone; p) Medical conditions not listed but which may interfere with the climacteric; q) Fears, real or anticipated claims for treatment that might interfere with the objectives of the study; r)Simultaneous participation in another clinical trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects were recruited among women patients of
eight healthcare centers in the city of Parnamirim, State of Rio Grande do Norte, Brazil. The menopausal
status of the subjects was defined according to the
Stages of Reproductive Aging Workshop menstrual
criteria. This study was approved by the local Ethics
Committee (number  294/2008) and all the
women gave their informed consent prior to the inclusion in
the study. Subjects were given a short questionnaire to
obtain information about race, age, antecedents gynecological, smoking, alcohol consumption, physical exercise, previous HRT,and diagnosed diseases. The climacteric symptoms were assessed by screening the Blatt Menopausal Index (IMK). Women with case history of
alcoholism, smoking, diabetes, and  chronic disease
are excluded.</concealment>
    <sequence>The method used to create the random order for the allocation of subjects into different groups. Subjects were randomized in the ratio of 1:1, i.e.
the number of patients in the active groups was 
similar of the placebo group. Randomization was performed by a central randomization who obeyed the order of selection of volunteers  for input on trial.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Rio Grande do Norte</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Norte</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Street General  Gustavo Cordeiro de Farias, 112-  Petropolis - Natal - Rio Grande do Norte - 	59012-570
Programa de Pos- Graduacao do Centro de Ciencias da Saude</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>SEPN 507, quarto andar,  sala 402
CEP 70740-901 - Brasilia 
Telefone: 55 (61) 2108-9396</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Universidade Potiguar</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NIPEC - Nucleo Integrado de Ensino, Pesquisa, Extensao e Acao Comunitaria 
Avenue Aspirante Santos, 83- Santos Reis - 59.150-000 Parnamirim - RN</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prefeitura Municipal de Parnamirim</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Secretaria Municipal de Saude
Avenue Tenente Medeiros, 208 - Centro - 59.150-000 - Parnamirim - Rio Grande do Norte</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To value the impact of lipoic acid supplementation and treatment with Tibolone on the condition of oxidative stress, climateric symptoms and quality of life in  women in the menopausal transition.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethics Committe of the Federal University of Rio Grande do Norte</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Av Nilo Pecanha, 620 - Petropolis - Natal - 59012-300</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/04/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008/0294</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/04/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Maria Socorro Medeiros de Morais</name>
      <address>Avenue Governador Tarcisio de Vasconcelos Maia, 905 
59065-780 - Candelaria - Natal - RN</address>
      <phone>55 84 99816134</phone>
      <fax>55 84 32723054</fax>
      <email>moraissos@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Maria das Gracas Almeida</name>
      <address>Street General Cordeiro de Farias - Departamento de Farmacia - LABMULT - Laboratorio Multidisciplinar
Petropolis - 59012-570 - Natal - Rio Grande do Norte</address>
      <phone>55 84 99888158</phone>
      <fax>55 84 32154377</fax>
      <email>mgalmeida@digi.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rand Randhal Martins</name>
      <address>Rua General Cordeiro de Farias - Departamento de Farmacia - LABMULT - Laboratorio Multidisciplinar
Petropolis - 59012-570- Natal - Rio Grande do Norte</address>
      <phone>55 83 96304592</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>randmartins@yahoo.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>