<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368899">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000740594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pilot study to evaluate and compare the pharmacokinetic parameters of different doses of phenylephrine hydrochloride combined with paracetamol in 12 healthy adults under fasting conditions.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparative, randomized, single-dose, five period, cross-over open label, pilot study to evaluate the pharmacokinetic parameters of different doses of phenylephrine hydrochloride combined with paracetamol in 12 healthy adults under fasting conditions.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pain </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Nasal Congestion</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>12 healthy participants will be randomly allocated, in a five-way cross-over manner, to the following treatments:
Treatment A: 650 mg paracetamol and 5 mg phenylephrine hydrochloride
Treatment B: 650 mg paracetamol and 5.2 mg phenylephrine hydrochloride
Treatment C: 650 mg paracetamol and 5.4 mg phenylephrine hydrochloride
Treatment D: 650 mg paracetamol and 5.6 mg phenylephrine hydrochloride).
Treatment E: 650 mg paracetamol and 5.8 mg phenylephrine hydrochloride
Each of the treatment will be administered orally, as a single dose. The administration of the study drugs is done under the supervision of the study staff.
There will be a washout period of 7 days between each of the study treatments
Participants will be required to fast overnight (for at least 10 hours) before dosing and for 4 hours thereafter.</interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment A: 650 mg paracetamol and 5 mg phenylephrine hydrochloride</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine and compare the pharmacokinetic parameters (Cmax, AUCt, AUCinf, Tmax) of different doses of phenylephrine hydrochloride (5-5.8 mg) when taken in combination with 650 mg paracetamol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Plasma time concentrations will be determined from the blood samples collected at 5, 15, 30, 45 minutes and 1.00, 1.25, 1.50, 2.00, 3.00, 6.00, 8.00, 10.00 and 12.00 hours after each study drug administration. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To monitor the safety and tolerability of the different doses of phenylephrine hydrochloride (5-5.8 mg) when combined with 650 mg of paracetamol. This is a composite secondary outcome.

Safety will be assessed by assessing the frequency and percentage of adverse events.Changes from baseline (prior to dosing) of blood pressure and heart rate results will be compared between the treatment groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety will be evaluated during each study period and throughout the whole duration of the study
Vital signs will be measured pre-dosing and at 15, 30 minutes and at 1.00, 1.50, 2.00, 2.5, 3.0, 4.00, 8.00 and 12.00 hours after study drug administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy subjects, males and females aged 18 to 40 years of age. Females must be infertile or using adequate contraception. Participants must not have taken any prescription medications for at least 14 days or over-the-counter medications for at least 3 days before the start of each study phase, with the exception of oral contraceptives and the study medication.
All subjects must be deemed healthy on the basis of a medical history, physical exam, urinalysis, and blood biochemical and haematological examinations.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Women who are pregnant or nursing
- Women of childbearing potential who are unwilling to take adequate contraceptive precautions
 - Women of childbearing potential who are unwilling to undergo a urine pregnancy test
- Have any history of allergy or hypersensitivity to paracetamol and phenylephrine hydrochloride
- Have a history of drug abuse or positive test results for drug abuse during screening.
- Be able and willing to abstain from all prescription and over-the-counter medications (excluding the study drug and oral contraceptive) and herbal remedies for the duration of the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomization will occur once participant eligibility is confirmed. Participants will be randomly assigned to one of the five possible study drug treatment sequences in a fashion that ensures: that each individual receives each treatment, that for each study period at least 12 participants are allocated to each treatment and that first-order carry-over effects are minimized. Each successive participant will receive a unique study identification number.
Allocation is done by contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is located at the central administration site</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomization sequences</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Pharmacokinetic parameters will be summarized using standard descriptive statistics, including means, medians, geometric means, ranges, inter-quartile ranges, standard deviations and standard errors.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/11/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>3/10/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>12</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Jordan</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AFT Pharmaceuticals Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 1, 129 Hurstmere Rd, Takapuna, 0622, Auckland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AFT Pharmaceuticals Ltd.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 129 Hurstmere Rd, Takapuna 0622, Auckland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a Phase I pilot study designed to evaluate the pharmacokinetic profile of fixed dose combinations of paracetamol 325 mg, and phenylephrine hydrochloride at doses between 2.5 and 2.9 mg per tablet, when given as two tablets per dose. The results of this study will guide the selection of the further dose strength of phenylephrine hydrochloride to be used in a fixed dose combination with paracetamol 325 mg, which will be further evaluated in a larger confirmatory pharmacokinetic study.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>International Pharmaceuticals Research Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 Queen Rania Street
Sport City Circle
Amman 1196
Jordan</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/07/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Jordan</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Abdullah Hiyari</name>
      <address>International Pharmaceutical Research Centre
1 Queen Rania Street
Sport City Circle
Amman 1196
Jordan
</address>
      <phone>+962-6-5627648</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>iprc@iprc.com.jo</email>
      <country>Jordan</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hartley Atkinson</name>
      <address>AFT Pharmaceuticals Ltd. - Level 1, 129 Hurstmere Rd, Takapuna, 0622, Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 488 0232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hartley@aftpharm.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hartley Atkinson</name>
      <address>AFT Pharmaceuticals Ltd. - Level 1, 129 Hurstmere Rd, Takapuna, 0622, Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 488 0232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hartley@aftpharm.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>