<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320839">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/11/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/11/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609001015235</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Nephro-protective effects of L-amino acids in critically ill patients. A phase II multicentre randomised controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Nephro-protective effects of L-amino acids versus standard care/usual care in critically ill adult patients at risk of developing acute kidney injury. A phase II multi-centre randomised controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Critical Illness Intensive Care Unit (ICU) Patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Supplementary infusion of L-amino acids to achieve 2g/kg/day total protein intake on each day for the entire duration of Intensive Care Unit (ICU) stay</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard Care / Usual Care, which encompasses all aspects of standard/usual care delivered for the entire duration of Intensive Care Unit (ICU) stay</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of days of clinically significant renal dysfunction, assessed and defined using the Brussels Table standards (Bernard GR, Doig GS, Hudson LD et al. Quantification of organ failure for clinical trials and clinical practice. Am J Resp Crit Care Med 1995;151:A323).</outcome>
      <timepoint>During ICU stay</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of renal dysfunction, assessed and defined using the Acute Dialysis Quality Initiative's published criteria (Bellomo R, Ronco C, Kellum JA et al. Acute renal failure-definition, outcome measures, animal models, fluid therapy and information technology needs:The second International Consensus Conference of the Acute Dialysis Quality Initiative Group. Crit Care 2004;8:R204-212).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during ICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of days of renal replacement therapy (RRT) delivered. Assessed by prospectively observing and recording renal replacement therapy (RRT) delivered to enrolled patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during ICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dose of renal replacement therapy delivered. Assessed by prospectively observing and recording the mls/kg/hour of renal replacment therapy (RRT) delivered to enrolled patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during ICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life assessed using Short Form (SF)-36 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at day 90 post randomisation into the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Function measured using the physical function component of the Short Form (SF)-36 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at day 90 post randomisation into the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for Dialysis- i.e. is the patient receiving, or scheduled to receive, any form of dialysis (continuous haemodialysis, intermittent peritoneal dialysis etc) at day 90</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at day 90 post randomisation into the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of ICU and Hospital Stay. Assessed by prospectively observing and recording Intensive Care Unit (ICU) and Hospital Stay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at Intensive Care Unit (ICU) and Hospital Discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of Mechanical Ventilation. Assessed by prospectively observing and recording Mechanical Ventilation delivered to enrolled patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during ICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Days of antibiotic use.  Assessed by prospectively observing and recording Antibiotics delivered to enrolled patients on each day of Intensive Care Unit (ICU) stay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during ICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients will be screened for eligibility within 24hrs of admission to study Intensive Care Unit (ICU). Patients will be considered eligible for the trial if all of the following inclusion criteria are met at the time of screening: 1)Presence of a central venous access line through which the study intervention could be delivered; 2)Expected to remain in the ICU for at least 3 days; 3)At least 18yrs of age; 4)Admitted to the study ICU for less than 24hours</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be considered ineligible for the trial if any of the following exclusion criteria are met at the time of screening: 1)Receiving an non steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAID) with specific emphasis on COX-2 inhibitors; 2)Receiving a nitrous oxide (NO) inhibitor; 3)Receiving a diuretic that acts on the proximal tubule (Ex. acetazolaminde); 4)Pre-existing chronic kidney disease; 5)Pre-existing ongoing need for chronic dialysis; 6)Recent kidney transplant; 7)Intensive Care Unit (ICU) length of stay at the time of screening is greater than 24hrs; 8)Admitted to the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) for palliative care and is not expected to survive to hospital discharge; 9)Moribund and not expected to survive 24hrs; 10)Brain dead or suspected to be brain dead; 11)Admitted to the study Intensive Care Unit (ICU) directly from another ICU; 12)Documented contraindications to the study intervention (Intravenous (IV) L-amino acids), as listed on the Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA) product licensing document; or 13)Clinically significant acute kidney injury at the time of screening.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Centralised randomisation by computer using a password protected webserver. 
As in any centralised method, individual patient treatment assignment will not be revealed until the potential participant is determined to be truely eligible for the trial and patient identifiers are submitted over the web to the centralised computer. 
Persons recruiting patients into the trial will not be able to predict or influence treatment assignments, hence allocation is concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised (SAS)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>474</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/10/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Gordon Doig</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore (RNSH) Intensive Care Unit (ICU), Pacific Highway St Leonards, NSW 2065.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99268656</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gdoig@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Gordon Doig</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore (RNSH) Intensive Care Unit (ICU), Pacific Highway St Leonards, NSW 2065.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99268656</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gdoig@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>