<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373379">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/11/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001526369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of a new device for oxygen therapy with continuous positive airway pressure in healthy volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A new interface combining high flow oxygen through nasal cannula and continuous positive airway pressure: comparative assessment of physiological effects in healthy volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Oxygen therapy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention consists in the simultaneously application of HFNC and CPAP using a new device. 
We will invite to participate 14 healthy volunteers (7 male and 7 female), from our ICU staff.
After obtaining written informed consent, volunteers will be seated in upright position. 
After anesthetizing the nose with lidocaine, a 10 French suction catheter will be passed via the nose into the oropharynx. We visually confirmed that the manometry catheter tip was just below the uvula. We will also use end-tidal carbon dioxide monitoring to confirm correct placement and catheter patency. The catheter will be connected to a pressure transducer connected to a laptop computer interface. As necessary, the catheter will be adjusted or suctioned to obtain a clear reading.

We will test this new interface combing CPAP (PEEP 10 cmH2O and flow at 60 L/min) and HFNC at increasing flow rates (30, 40, 50 and 60 L/min), performed again with the volunteer's mouth open and closed. 
We will use two blenders taking gas flow from wall air and oxygen outlets (one for HFNC and one for CPAP). All trials will be run in room air oxygen concentration.
All pressure measurement will be taken after each flow rate will be established for 15 min, to allow the volunteer to become accustomed to the feeling of different interfaces and to allow the breathing pattern to settle. All recordings will be taken over one minute of quiet breathing. The approximate total duration of the intervention will be around 1 hour. The different flow rate will be consecutively applied.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Control treatments will be 1) HFNC and 2) CPAP.
1) HFNC
After a baseline assessment during spontaneous breathing in room air, the volunteer will start on HFNC (RT033/034 Optiflow nasal cannula, MR880 heated humidifier, and RT241 heated delivery tube, Fisher &amp; Paykel Healthcare, Auckland, New Zealand) once the system reached the set temperature (37°C). Measurements will be then performed with the volunteer's mouth open, and again with the mouth closed, at flows of 30, 40, 50 and 60 L/min. The duration of each flow rate will be 15 minutes, with an approximate overall intervention of 1 hour. The different flow rate will be consecutively applied.

2) CPAP
Afterwards, the volunteer will undergo to helmet CPAP set with a PEEP of 10 cmH2O and flow of 60 L/min, to avoid carbon dioxide re-breathing for 15 minutes. No heated humidification will be applied. Measurements will be then performed with the volunteer's mouth open, and again with the mouth closed. 

All trials will be conducted in room air.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess pressures applied to the airways during HFNC, CPAP and a new device combining HFNC and CPAP at varying of the gas flows.</outcome>
      <timepoint>All pressure measurements will be taken, through a dedicated catheter inserted in the oro-pharynx, after therapy will be established for 15 min, to allow the volunteer to become accustomed to the feeling of different interfaces and to allow the breathing pattern to settle. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the effects of different trials on the respiratory drive of the subjects</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measurements will be taken with the sonographic assessment of the diaphragm (i.e., cranio-caudal displacement) after therapy will be established for 15 min, to allow the volunteer to become accustomed to the feeling of different interfaces and to allow the breathing pattern to settle. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the effects of different interfaces and settings on the respiratory effort of the subjects</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measurements will be taken with the sonographic assessment of the diaphragm (i.e., thickening fraction) after therapy will be established for 15 min, to allow the volunteer to become accustomed to the feeling of different interfaces and to allow the breathing pattern to settle. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess subject's comfort with different devices and settings</outcome>
      <timepoint>Comfort evaluation will be taken through an 11-point Numeric Rating Scale (NRS) on an ICU-adapted large printed scale including numbers and descriptors after therapy will be established for 15 min. Before protocol initiation, all patients will receive a detailed explanation of the NRS. The patients will be asked to evaluate their comfort level, indicating a number between 0 (worst possible comfort) and 10 (best possible comfort).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>14 healthy volunteers (7 male and 7 female)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>contra-indications to pass a catheter into the pharynx (i.e., recent surgery or epistaxis)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All volunteers will undergo to all different devices and settings, applied in random order. The sequence will be hold in sealed, opaque numbered envelops. </concealment>
    <sequence>The sequence of device and settings application will be generated through a computer by an external statistician not involved in the study. The sequence will be hold in sealed, opaque numbered envelops. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The normal distribution will be ascertained by means of the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. Continuous data will be presented as mean (standard deviation) or median (interquartile range) depending on normality. The t-test or Kruskal-Wallis test will be used to compare pressures between open and closed mouth groups for inspiration and expiration and between genders. The analysis of variance on ranks for repeated measures (Friedman test) will be used to compare the evaluated continuous variables among different interventions. Pairwise multiple comparisons will be conducted with the post hoc Dunn's method. A p value &lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant. To evaluate the consistency among sonographic assessment by the investigators, we will use the interclass correlation coefficient.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/01/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>14</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/01/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Federico Longhini</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>SC Anestesia e Rianimazione, Ospedale Sant'Andrea, corso Abbiate 31, 13100 Vercelli</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Italy</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dipartimento di Scienze Mediche e Chirurgiche, Università Magna Graecia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Viale Europa - Loc. Germaneto 88100 Catanzaro</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Italy</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Paolo Navalesi</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dipartimento di Scienze Mediche e Chirurgiche, Università Magna Graecia
Viale Europa - Loc. Germaneto 88100, Catanzaro
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Italy</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>High flow oxygen therapy through nasal cannula (HFNC) is increasingly used in different clinical situation to assist patients with acute respiratory failure. HFNC is characterized by a low dilution of the administered gas with room air, a dead-space wash out of the upper respiratory airways and the application of a positive end-expiratory pressure (PEEP). 
However, PEEP is strictly limited to the during the expiration phase of the respiratory cycle, while during inspiration pharyngeal pressure drops to zero or even to negative values. This could be a limitation in case of hypoxemic acute respiratory failure (hARF), because recruitment of lung regions with atelectasis is not assured during the whole respiratory cycle. With continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP), the patients airway is maintained throughout the respiratory cycle at a selected constant pressure (PEEP), which is higher than the atmospheric pressure. 
Among the available interfaces, the helmet has been suggested to be effective in improving patient tolerance allowing more prolonged application of continuous CPAP. However, the heated humidification with helmet is problematic, difficult or almost or impossible because of condensation of water inside the interface ("fog" effect). We therefore designed a new interface joining HFNC with CPAP through helmet, to combine the physiological benefit of these two interfaces. 
We aim to assess airway pressures during the use of this new device with different gas flows and breathing conditions (primary endpoint). We will also assess the effects of different interfaces on the respiratory drive and effort of the subjects.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comitato Etico sezione Centro - Regione Calabria</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>A.O.U. Mater Domini in Via Tommaso Campanella, 115 Catanzaro</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/07/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Italy</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paolo Navalesi</name>
      <address>Dipartimento di Scienze Mediche e Chirurgiche, Università Magna Graecia
Viale Europa - Loc. Germaneto 88100, Catanzaro
</address>
      <phone>+393355321910</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pnavalesi@unicz.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Federico Longhini</name>
      <address>SC Anestesia e Rianimazione, Ospedale Sant'Andrea, corso Abbiate 31, 13100 Vercelli</address>
      <phone>+393475395967</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>longhini.federico@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Federico Longhini</name>
      <address>SC Anestesia e Rianimazione, Ospedale Sant'Andrea, corso Abbiate 31, 13100 Vercelli</address>
      <phone>+393475395967</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>longhini.federico@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Federico Longhini</name>
      <address>SC Anestesia e Rianimazione, Ospedale Sant'Andrea, corso Abbiate 31, 13100 Vercelli</address>
      <phone>+393475395967</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>longhini.federico@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>