<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362446">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/05/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000480886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study of treatment methods for undisplaced supracondylar humeral (elbow) fractures in children.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of three different types of external immobilisation methods comparing pain during application and functional outcome for children with undisplaced supracondylar humeral fractures.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1130-3360</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SUPE study (Study of undisplaced paediatric elbows)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute isolated Gartland Type 1 supracondylar humeral fracture confirmed on xray.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>To compare the effectiveness of different external immobilisation methods for the management of acute Gartland Type 1 supracondylar humeral fractures, patients will be randomly allocated to 1 of the following 3 treatment groups: 
Group 1 (control group) will have collar and cuff sling under clothing with elbow flexion at 120 degrees
Group 2 (low sling) will have collar and cuff sling under clothing with elbow flexion at 90 degrees
Group 3 (backslab) will have a posterior plaster of Paris backslab and collar and cuff sling over clothing with elbow flexion at 50 degrees

The patients in all groups will wear the external immobilisation for a total of 3 weeks. Patients in group 1 and 2 will wear the sling day and night. Patients in group 3 will have the posterior backslab insitu for 3 weeks day and night and will wear the sling during the day - the sling may be removed at night when sleeping.</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 1 (as above) as this is our current practice in the department. The collar and cuff sling will be worn under clothing day and night for a total of 3 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine optimal treatment of acute isolated Gartland Type 1 supracondylar humeral fractures in children with regard to pain during application of external immobilisation. Pain will be measured using the Faces Pain Scale-Revised and the Face, Legs, Activity, Cry, Consolability (FLACC) pain scale will be used for children who are unable to self report.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of application of external immobilsation in the Emergency Department.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Our secondary aim is to determine the functional outcome for each intervention. The Activities Scale for Kids will be used to measure this.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At subsequent Fracture Clinic visits at 1, 3 and 7 weeks after discharge from the Emergency Department.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children presenting to PMH ED aged between 3 and less than 9 years diagnosed with an acute isolated Gartland Type 1 supracondylar humeral fracture confirmed on xray.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>8</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children aged less than 3 years and 9 years or older
Supracondylar humeral fractures other than Gartland Type 1 and those which are not isolated fractures
Injury sustained more than 3 days ago (ie: not acute)
Neurovascular compromise
Open fractures
Multiple trauma patients
Head injury resulting in impaired judgement
No parent or legal guardian present who can give informed written consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be randomly allocated to one of three treatment groups. Computer generated block randomisation will be used and allocation concealed by sealed opaque envelopes which will be stored in the ED research office.</concealment>
    <sequence>Using computer generated block randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box D184 Perth, Western Australia, 6840</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box D184 Perth Western Australia 6840</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to determine the optimal treatment for uncomplicated elbow fractures (undisplaced supracondylar humeral fractures) in children by comparing three treatment methods. A supracondylar humeral fracture is a fracture or break to the bone immediately above the elbow. Children identified with an undisplaced supracondylar fracture will be randomly allocated to one of three treatment groups which will involve different methods of external immobilisation. Pain during application of these various methods and functional outcome will be measured.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Child and Adolescent Health Service Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box D184
Perth
Western Australia
6840</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/06/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jemma Bates-Smith</name>
      <address>GPO Box D184
Perth
Western Australia
6840</address>
      <phone>+61, 08, 9340 8222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jemma.Bates-Smith@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jemma Bates-Smith</name>
      <address>GPO Box D184
Perth
Western Australia
6840</address>
      <phone>+61, 08, 9340 8222</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Jemma.Bates-Smith@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>