<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336910">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/05/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000494932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study comparing the surgical and patient outcomes with different pre-surgery diet regimes with or without bowel preparation solution for laparoscopic gynaecological surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Single Blind Randomised Controlled Trial of Surgical and Patient Outcomes using Mechanical Bowel Preparation before Laparoscopic Gynaecological Surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>benign gynaecological pathology requiring laparoscopic surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1. Fasting only group - participants in this group have normal diet until the day before surgery (without fluid restriction) where they fast from midnight the night before surgery (including fluids)
2. Minimal residue diet group - 2 days of liquid diet before the surgery; 2 days before surgery - full liquid diet (milk shakes, pumpkin soup, orange juice etc), 1 day before surgery - clear liquod diet (eg apple juice, chicken broth, jelly etc), and fast from midnight the night before if the surgery is in the morning, or from 6am for afternoon surgery (including fluids)</interventions>
    <comparator>Minimal residue diet (as described above) for 2 days with mechanical bowel preparation solution (1 sachet of PicoPrep - 15.546g sodium picosulphate solution) where first sachet is taken no later than 3pm the day before the surgery, and second sachet taken 4 hours later.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>surgical visual field and bowel handling</outcome>
      <timepoint>at the time of surgery, using Visual analogue scale (VAS)and Verbal descriptor scale (VDS)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in patient symptomatology, using VAS and VDS on the symptoms of headache, nausea &amp; vomiting, thirst, weakness, tiredness and overall level of discomfort</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline (at the time of recruitment for the study- anytime before 2 days prior to surgery)
On the day of surgery, prior to the procedure
1 day after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in patient's bowel function, using a validated questionnaire (colorectal functional outcome questionnaire, as well as Hallbook &amp; Vaizey questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>basesline (time of recruitment of study)
1 week after surgery
1 month after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in patient's electrolyte and haematocrit, using meaurement of patient's serum EUC &amp; FBC level from blood sample</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline (time of recruitment of study)
on the day of surgery, prior to the procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Female aged 18 to 80 years

Fluent in spoken and written English

Capable of completing questions relating to pain

Able to understand implications of their involvement in the study

Consent to involvement in the study

Is a patient of the Department of Endo-Gynaecology, Royal Hospital for Women

Consented and scheduled to undergo a gynaecological laparoscopic procedure possibly involving the posterior pelvic compartment requiring mechanical bowel preparation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>May become distressed due to involvement in the study

Is currently involved in any other research project

Any intercurrent condition that, in the investigators opinion, precludes a patient from participating in the study

Known or suspected pregnancy

Suspected gynaecological malignancy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The allocation concealment will be achieved by telephone allocation by a  third party research assistant not involved in patient recruitment or data collection.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be  by computer generated sequence in balanced blocks</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/11/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>246</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>High St 
Sydney NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AGES (Australasian Gynaecological Endoscopy &amp; Surgery)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>282 Edinburgh Road
Castlecrag
 NSW 2068</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to compare the levels of discomfort a patient experiences, to compare the effects on blood components and to compare the surgical outcomes associated with different modes of bowel preparation before gynaecological laparoscopic surgery. Laparoscopic surgery is a minimally invasive surgical technique, for which you have already been admitted to this hospital. Prior to surgery, it is standard procedure in this department for patients to take mechanical bowel preparation.  This involves following a diet and then taking a proprietary drink to assist in emptying the bowels. Traditionally, the emptying of the bowels is believed to improve the visualisation of abdominal contents as well as potentially decrease complication rates involving the bowel, though there is not a lot of scientific proof that this is the case.  Recent research in gynaecological and bowel surgery has shown that mechanical bowel preparation may not be necessary.

In this study, patients will be randomly assigned to one of three groups: 
1.	Women in group one will only fast (not have anything to eat or drink) before their surgery
2.	Women in group two will fast and undertake a minimal residue diet 
3.	Women in group three will undertake a minimal residue diet and take mechanical bowel preparation as directed.

You will have a 33% chance of being in any of the three groups.  Neither the doctor nor the study participant can decide which bowel preparation the patient will undertake.  This study will be a single blind trial.  This means that the doctor will not know which bowel preparation the participant has taken. 

When you have been assigned to one group, we will provide a detailed outline of the bowel preparation you need to undertake.  A study team member will contact you before your surgery to ensure that you know which group you are in and to remind you of the procedures.  The knowledge gained from this study will allow us to estimate whether one type of bowel preparation is significantly better for patients, enabling us to provide a better quality of care for all women.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee - South Eastern Sydney Local Health Network (Northern Sector)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room G71, East Wing, Edmund Blacket Building 
Prince of Wales Hospital 
Barker St Randwick NSW
2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/11/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/08/0096</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/08/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr HaRyun Won</name>
      <address>Royal Hospital for Women
Barker St
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 6111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>haryun.won@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr HaRyun Won</name>
      <address>Royal Hospital for Women
Barker St
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 6111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>haryun.won@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>