<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364454">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000260628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Foot Orthosis versus Hip eXercises (FOHX) trial: Predicting success in patellofemoral pain patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective randomised single-blinded clinical trial in a community setting will evaluate the outcome of foot orthoses compared to hip strengthening exercises in people with patellofemoral pain. The FOHX trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1162-3936</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The FOHX trial: The Foot Orthosis versus Hip eXercises trial.</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patellofemoral Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Prefabricated foot orthoses. Orthoses will be adjusted to optimise participant comfort at the orthosis-foot interface, as well as to improve knee pain during physical tasks. Participants will use the orthoses during waking hours for 12 weeks. The orthoses will be fitted, reviewed and if required revised by a physiotherapist. In the first 6 weeks the participant will attend a physiotherapist clinic, 2 times a week for the first week and once a week for the remaining weeks with no sessions in the 5th week. These sessions will usually last approximately 30 minutes and no more than 45 minutes.

We aim to improve adherence to wearing these devices by (a) having the patient attend regular sessions with a physiotherapist over the first 6 weeks of the trial, (b) have the physiotherapist record in case file the level of adherence and any issues in this regard and strategies used in addressing these, and (c) patient recording in a diary over the last 6 weeks their level of wear of the devices as well as at exit by means of a questionnaire.</interventions>
    <comparator>Hip muscle strengthening exercises. The hip exercises will strengthen hip muscles that are reported weaker in people with patellofemoral pain than the pain free population. The hip exercises will be supervised by a physiotherapist in the clinic and done 3 times a week over a 4 week period. Each session will last approximately 45 minutes. There will be no home or self exercises done outside of the clinic. This will ensure adherence, but most importantly it will ensure optimal dosing (loading) of the muscles exercised. That is, the participants in the control group will not be required to continue doing the exercises outside of the 12 sessions in the clinic.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global Rating of Change (GROC): Participants will be asked to rate their overall change on a 7-point scale to indicate if they are better, same or worse (-3: Much worse, -2: Worse, -1: A little worse, 0: same, +1: A little better, +2: Better, +3: Much better).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 &amp; 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kujala Patellofemoral Scale (KPS): This questionnaire is made up of 13 specific questions related to patellofemoral pain that cover a range of knee function under varying loads. Participants answer by selecting the best response to each question. Each question is scored and collectively added together to give a maximum of 100 points. A change of 10 or more points indicates a clinically meaningful change in function. </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 &amp; 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Specific Functional Scale (PSFS):Participants choose up to five tasks that are affected by their knee pain. Each task is scored on an 11 point numerical rating scale to indicate the impact of their symptoms (0: unable to do the task at all, 10: capacity to do the task is unaffected)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 &amp; 12 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain Numerical Rating Scale (NRS): Participants will rate their average pain over the past 24hours, and worst pain over the past 7 days on an 11 point scale (0: no pain at all, 10: worst pain imaginable).</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 &amp; 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ): Participants will be required to document the amount of time (minutes or hours per day or alternatively days per week) they spend sitting, walking, moderate or vigorous exercise. </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 &amp; 12 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tampa Scale of Kinesphobia (TSK): The questionnaire comprises of 17 statements about perception of movement, and the participant selects the most appropriate response to each statement ("Strongly Disagree", "Disagree,", "Agree", "Strongly Agree")</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 &amp; 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS): Participants are required to select the most response to 14 statements about how they have felt over the past 7 days. Two subscales are intermingled within the 14 questions. </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 &amp; 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patellofemoral Osteoarthritis and Outcome Scale (PFOOS): The questionnaire is made up of 5 separate subscales that cover pain, symptoms, sports and recreational activities, activities of daily living and quality of life. Participants select the most appropriate response to each question within the subscales. </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 &amp; 12 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional movements: Participants will be required to step up a 25cm step repetitively at a pace of a metronome set to 96 beats per minute. Following this, participants will do repetitive step downs from a 25cm step. A repetitive squatting task will require participants, in standing, to squat down to touch ipsilateral malleoli and return to upright standing. Each functional movements will be stopped if there is: (a) onset of knee pain, or (b) an increase in knee pain, or (c) no pain after 25 repetitions. </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 &amp; 12 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Foot Posture Index (FPI):This index assesses 6 components of foot posture in relaxed standing. Each component is scored on a 5 point scale (-2 to +2) and then collectively summed to give an overall figure that denotes if the participants foot is classified as "Supinated", "Neutral" or "Pronated". </outcome>
      <timepoint>0 &amp; 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Foot mobility assessment: Participants will have static measures of foot width and dorsal arch height taken at 50% of foot length in a weight bearing and non-weight bearing posture. Navicular height will be measured with the subtalar joint in both a neutral and a relaxed posture. </outcome>
      <timepoint>0 &amp; 12 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hip Strength: Hip abduction, adduction and external rotation isometric muscle strength will be measured using a fixated hand held dynamometer.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 &amp; 12 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EQ-5D: The EuroQoL (EQ-5D) is a generalised health-related quality of life measure. The questionnaire comprises of a visual scale participant mark to indicate their own health as well as 5 written sections that cover mobility, personal care, usual activity, pain/discomfort and anxiety/ depression.  Participants select the statement that best describes their own health state. </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 &amp; 12 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain Catastrophizing Scale: This scale is a 13-item self-report scale to measure pain catastrophizing. The items are rated on a scale from 0-4 and has three different categories: Rumination, Magnification and Helplessness.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 &amp; 12 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction of treatment: This comprises of two questions 
1. Overall satisfaction of treatment  
2. Satisfaction to live with current symptoms. 

Participants will be require to answer from 5 point scale (Very Satisfied to Very Dissatisfied).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 &amp; 12 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Success of Treatment: Participants will be ask two questions related to their perception of the success of the treatment 
1. Participant's agreement that the treatment has been successful (Yes/ No)
2. Would the participant recommend the same treatment to a freind (Yes/ No)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 &amp; 12 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported Rate of Recovery: Participants will score how well they felt they have recovered from their knee pain on a scale ranging from 0% (meaning not at all) to 100% (meaning totally recovered).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 &amp; 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Acceptable Symptom State (PASS): Participants are asked in a statement if their current condition is satisfactory based on their general function and current pain. The answer will be yes or no. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 &amp; 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Single Assessment Numerical Evaluation (SANE): Participants will be asked to rate how normal they would rate their knee today on a scale of 0 to 100%. 100% normal is defined as having no problems at all with the knee. </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 6 &amp; 12 weeks. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patellofemoral pain of non-traumatic origin and greater than six weeks duration

2. Patellofemoral pain that is provoked by at least two of the following activities: squatting, jogging or running, hopping, jumping, stair ascending or descending.   

3. Patellofemoral pain over the previous week equal to or greater than 3 out of 10 on a numerical pain rating scale. 

4. Pain on palpation about the patella.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Concomitant injury or pathology of other knee structures (e.g. ligament, tendon or cartilage)

2. A history of knee surgery, patellofemoral dislocation or subluxation, Osgood-Schlatters disease, Sinding-Larsen-Johanssen Syndrome

3. A positive patella apprehension test or evidence of swelling at the knee

4. A foot condition that may preclude the use of foot orthoses

5. Pain at the hip, pelvis or low back 

6. Physiotherapy treatment of patellofemoral pain that included foot orthoses or hip exercises in the last 12 months 

6. Current use of anti-inflammatory or corticosteroid medication.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Volunteers will respond to advertisements calling for subjects to participate in the trial. 

Volunteers will pass through an interview and a physical examination/screen to assess eligibility for inclusion into the trial.

Those participants who are eligible will undertake baseline outcome measurements and then be randomly allocated to one of two interventions groups. Allocation will be concealed and generated by a computerised randomisation schedule developed by an off-site independent clinical trial unit (Clinical Trials &amp; Biostatistics Unit, QIMR Berghofer Medical Research Institute, Brisbane Australia).</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated radomisation schedule</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Single-blinded randomised controlled trial</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>At an alpha or 0.05 and 80% power with an allowance of 10% loss to follow up, a sample size of 220 will be required to detect a difference in proportion of success of 25% in the orthoses group with mobile feet from the hip exercise group assuming the latter have a success rate ranging from 30 to 50%. 

Analysis will be conducted blind to allocation by an independent clinical trial centre using appropriate regression and analytical procedures.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/05/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/05/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>16/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>220</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>218</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>17/03/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Denmark</country>
      <state>North Denmark: Aalborg</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Bill Vicenzino</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences
Therapies Building 84A
Therapies Road
University of Queensland
St Lucia 4072
Queensland</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council: Program grant Ref number 631717 </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Vionic Group LLC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>4040 Civic Center Drive ­ Suite 430
San Rafael CA 94903</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This trial will compare two commonly used treatments for patellofemoral pain, foot orthoses and hip strengthening exercises. There is evidence to support both approaches, and often debate revolves around counter-posing perspectives as to which may be more effective to use, yet the two treatment approaches have not directly compared before.

Previous foot orthoses trials have reported benefits on patient rated outcomes from use of foot orthoses over a flat shoe insert or adopting a wait-and-see approach in the treatment of patellofemoral pain. 

Recent trials implementing hip strengthening exercises have demonstrated reduced pain and improved ability to climb stairs after strength exercises for the hip, in people with patellofemoral pain. 

In the FOHX trial, participants will be randomly allocated into either wearing foot orthoses or performing hip muscle strengthening exercises. 

The clinical trial will compare the outcome of the two treatments, and also identify the baseline profile (physical measures and patient perceptions) that are associated with the greatest response to foot orthoses or hip strengthening exercises. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Queensland
Cumbrae-Stewart Building
Research Road
Brisbane Qld 4072 Australia
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013000981</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/07/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bill Vicenzino</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, 
Therapies Building 84A,
Therapies Road,
The University of Queensland,
St Lucia 4072
Brisbane QLD</address>
      <phone>+617 3365 2781 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.vicenzino@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bill Vicenzino</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, 
Therapies Building 84A,
Therapies Road,
The University of Queensland,
St Lucia 4072
Brisbane QLD</address>
      <phone>+617 3365 2781</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.vicenzino@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bill Vicenzino</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, 
Therapies Building 84A,
Therapies Road,
The University of Queensland,
St Lucia 4072
Brisbane QLD</address>
      <phone>+617 3365 2781 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>b.vicenzino@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mark Matthews</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, 
Therapies Building 84A,
Therapies Road,
The University of Queensland,
St Lucia 4072
Brisbane QLD</address>
      <phone>+61426899653</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.matthews3@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>