<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364633">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000862741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and safety of a colistin loading dose, population pharmacokinetic-pharmacodynamic profiles and bacterial clearance rate in critically ill patients with extensively drug-resistant Acinetobacter baumanii (XDRAb) infections</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In critically ill patients infected with extensively drug resistant Acinetobacter baumanii (XDRAb), does the use of colistin loading dose compared to the normal maintenance of colistin has better 30 day mortality outcome?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Infections with extensively drug resistant Acinetobacter baumanii </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Colistin in this study will be given intravenously to all the patients. 

The loading dose of colistin will be used in selected patient who will be randomised using a computer generated block. Colistin is a parenteral drug in the form of prodrug called colistimethate sodium (CMS). The generic drug is named colomycin.

We will use the Garonzik et. al. calculation method that was published in 2011, a study on colistin population PKPD. The maintenance will also be calculated using the formula from the paper that is dependent on the creatinine clearance.

We will provide the physicians and the investigators with the study protocol to ensure that there will be a systemic and 
planned review of each participants.

The loading dose is calculated based on weight in which the formula used will be, 2 x 2 x ideal body weight.
The dose will be in colistin based activity (CBA) in which the loading dose is given irrespective of the creatinine clearance

This loading dose will be given only once pre maintenance amongst subjects randomized into the the loading dose arm

The maintenance as per the formula will be calculated based on creatinine clearance. We will use the online CKD EPI calculator for the calculation of creatinine clearance. The formula will be, 2 (1.5 x creatinine clearance + 30). The sum will be expressed in CBA too. 

The subjects will be maintained on the maintenance dose for at 10 to 14 days depending on the clinical response and the type of infections. 

The subjects will be followed up till 30 days post commencement of antibiotic or till he/she is discharged (whichever comes first)</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be given maintenance of colistin without the loading dose using the same formula used to calculate the maintenance dose of loading arm.

We will provide the physicians and the investigators with the study protocol to ensure that there will be a systemic and planned review of each participants.

The maintenance dose calculated per day can be given in bd or tds dose depending on the physician jurisdiction. 
All the calculated dose will be given intravenously to the subjects </comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>30-day mortality rate. We will use crude mortality data rather than infection specific mortality data for the 30 day mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at the 30th day after treatment commencement </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ICU length of stay 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>We will review the patient medical record to ascertain the length of stay post colistin commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital length of stay
</outcome>
      <timepoint>We will review the patient medical record to ascertain the length of stay post colistin commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PKPD parameters attainment</outcome>
      <timepoint>For PKPD parameters: the blood will be collected on day 1 and day 3, and the modelling of colistin will be done to ascertain the serum levels of colistin in both the study arms. Liquid chromatography mass spectrometry machine will be used for this </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>bacterial clearance (using PCR technique)</outcome>
      <timepoint>For RT PCR bacterial clearance: Day 0,1,2,3 and the final day of the treatment. An RT PCR machine will be used for this</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1)	Age 18 and above 

2)	Patients with a first episode of culture proven XDRAb from blood, CSF, sputum and tracheal aspirate samples.

3)	Receive colistin treatment for more than 72 hours 

4)	Fulfill diagnostic criteria for ventilator-related pneumonia, hospital-acquired pneumonia, bacteremia (catheter- and non catheter-related), and meningitis or CSF infections, as defined in accordance with IDSA guidelines

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Pregnant
2) Breastfeeding
3) ALT/AST more than 8 times upper limit of normal
5) Allergy to colistin or its prodrug 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The patients who fulfilled the criteria and are admitted into ICU or neuro ICU will be invited to participate in the study. The treatment allocation in term of loading dose will be decided using a randomised block.

 However both the patients and the physicians will not be blinded of the treatment arms. Thus we will not be providing the concealment for both the arms post randomisation</concealment>
    <sequence>R program is used to generate a block of random numbers for the treatment allocation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We will use SPSS version 21 to assess the outcome between the 2 groups. Fisher exact test and X2 test will be used for categorical data, t test for parametric and Mann Whitney U test for non parametric continuous variables will be used.

Multivariable regression will be used to adjust for confounding factors and effect modification. Variables with a P value of less than 0.1 on bivariable analyses will be fitted into a multivariable logistic regression model in a forward stepwise selection manner and the adjusted odd ratios of 95% confidence intervals and P values will be determined 

The study is designed to identify an absolute mortality reduction of 30%. For sample size calculation, assuming raw 30-day mortality rate of 60% in the conventional (control group) arm, a 2-tailed significant level of 0.05, a power of 0.80, an allocation ratio of 1:1, and a drop out rate of 10%, 97 patients have to be enrolled.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Helmi B Sulaiman</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Medicine
Faculty of Medicine
University Malaya 
50603 
Kuala Lumpur
Malaysia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University Malaya
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University Malaya
50603 
Kuala Lumpur
Malaysia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Lo Yoke Lin</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University Malaya 
Department of Pharmacy
Faculty of Medicine
50603 
Kuala Lumpur
Malaysia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Malaysia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Nadia Atiya</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University Malaya
Department of Microbiology
Faculty of Medicine
University of Malaya
50603 
Kuala Lumpur
Malaysia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Malaysia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr. Wong Kang Kwong</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University Malaya
Department of Anaesthesiology 
Faculty of Medicine
University of Malaya
50603 
Kuala Lumpur</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Malaysia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr. Vineya Rai A/L Hakumat Rai</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University Malaya
Department of Anaesthesiology 
Faculty of Medicine
University of Malaya
50603 
Kuala Lumpur</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Malaysia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr. Mohd Shahnaz Bin Hasan</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University Malaya
Department of Anaesthesiology 
Faculty of Medicine
University of Malaya
50603 
Kuala Lumpur</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Malaysia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We aim to evaluate prospectively the efficacy and safety of a colistin loading dose, to determine the population pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic (PK/PD) profiles and the effect of initial rate of bacterial clearance on in-hospital in patients with infections of the lungs, blood, or CSF, caused by extensively drug-resistant Acinetobacter baumanii (XDRAb).


Objectives
The objectives of this study include:

1.	To determine, the effect of a loading dose and initial rate of bacterial clearance on 30-day mortality in patients with XDRAb infections 
2.	To assess the changes in renal function of patients receiving a loading dose of collision
3.	To estimate the pharmacokinetic parameters (such as clearance and volume of distribution) and pharmacodynamic parameters (such as ratios of Cmax/MIC, AUC/MIC or T greater than MIC) of colistin in patients with XDRAb infections in critically ill patients. 
4.	To evaluate whether the initial rate of bacterial clearance can be used to predict mortality.


Hypotheses to be investigated

1)	A colistin loading dose is no superior to no loading in 30-day mortality in critically ill patients having infections caused by XDRAb.
2)	A colistin loading dose is not associated with an increased risk of nephrotoxicity</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University Malaya Medical Centre Medical Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lembah Pantai,
59100
Kuala Lumpur Malaysia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>955.6</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/09/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Helmi B Sulaiman</name>
      <address>Infectious disease unit,
Department of Medicine
Faculty of Medicine
University of Malaya
50603
Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+60122327940</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>edenhelmi@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Helmi B Sulaiman</name>
      <address>Infectious disease unit,
Department of Medicine
Faculty of Medicine
University of Malaya
50603
Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+60122327940</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>edenhelmi@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Helmi B Sulaiman</name>
      <address>Infectious disease unit,
Department of Medicine
Faculty of Medicine
University of Malaya
50603
Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone>+60122327940</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>edenhelmi@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>