<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81778">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/12/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/01/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000030471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Identification of Susceptibility to Abacavir Hypersensitivity Reaction (HSR) in HIV-1 Infected Patients in Sydney, Australia and Development of Mechanisms for Risk Reduction</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Identification of Susceptibility to Abacavir Hypersensitivity Reaction (HSR) in HIV-1 Infected Patients in Sydney, Australia and Development of Mechanisms for Risk Reduction</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Abacavir Hypersensitivity Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Holdsworth House Medical Practice: ABV-HSR-01</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Human Immunodeficiency Virus Type-1 (HIV-1)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS / HIV)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Testing
 Strategy: sequence-specific primer (SSP) - amplify only intron 2 and exon 3 of a  limited subset of HLA types
 5 primer in intron 2  hybridises to all B*57 and B*58 sequences but not others 
 3 primer is a universal HLA-B primer
 If Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) negative: then not HLA-B*5701
 If PCR positive: then possibly HLA-B*57
 sequence PCR amplicon to distinguish HLA-B*57from HLA-B*58
 Use Single Nucleotide Polymorphism (SNPs) to determine HLA-B*5701 (or 06 or 08) or not 
 Can distinguish these alleles from other HLA-B*57alleles and from HLA-B*58

Condition being observed
1. Prevalence of HLA-B*5701 in abacavir-naïve HIV-1 participants
2. Prevalence of HLA-B*5701 in abacavir-experienced participants who has also had abacavir HSR


Duration of the Trial
January to June 2007

No.  HLA-B*5701 is a specific DNA sequence present in a small percentage of the total population.  This sequence is part of the immune system and is associated with hypersensitivity reaction when given the HIV drug treatment abacavir.</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator.</comparator>
    <control />
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the prevalence of HLA-B*5701 in a cohort of HIV-1 infected patients attending a high HIV-caseload primary care practice in Sydney, Australia

Effectively two visits in total:
Visit Number Visit Name Visit Length
Visit 1/Day 0 Baseline 30 min
Visit 2/Day 14 Result Visit 15 min

Baseline Visit 1 (Day 0, 30 min)
All patients agreeing to participate will be consented using HREC approved consent form. Consent will be taken for:
1. Participation in the HLA-B*5701 prevalence study, with separate consent for
2. Development of a model recording of results in patient records and abacavir HSR registry.

A 9ml EDTA sample collected from participants (with the exception of STEAL participants). The samples will be sent for laboratory testing in a de-identified manner with first 2 letters of patient name and surname and date of birth.

All prospective laboratory samples will be processed by Centre for Immunology, St Vincents Hospital, Victoria Street, Darlinghurst, NSW 2010 (NATA/RCPA accredited)

Result Visit 2 (Day 14, 15 min)
All study participants will have an appointment return for consultation with their treating doctor to discuss their HLA-B*5701 results and the implications. Those testing positive for HLA-B*5701 will be advised not to commence abacavir in their future treatment regimen.

HLA-*B5701 results will be entered into patient medical records for future access.

Those participants consenting will have results entered into created model Registry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At visit 1 (Day 0) and visit 2 (Day 14)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. To determine the prevalence of HLA-B*5701 in patients with a clinical diagnosis of abacavir HSR attending a high HIV caseload primary care practice in Sydney (approximately 35) 35 cases (patients).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. To develop a model for advising patients of testing results and recording the results in patient records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 3 months of enrollment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3. To develop a model for a secure web based registry of patient B*5701 and abacavir HSR for use by treating physicians as a model for application in Australia and elsewhere.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 3 months of enrollment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Documented HIV-1 infection. 2. Abacavir treatment naive or 3. Previous abacavir HSR. 4. Able to understand and willing to sign informed consent. 5. Able to return for discussion of B*5701 test results.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Previous abacavir exposure with no diagnosis of abacavir HSR 2. Patients unable to submit a blood sample 3. Unable to understand English where translator not available.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Holdsworth House Medical Practice</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>GlaxoSmithKline Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is being conducted in order to determine the proportion of HIV-1 patients attending Holdsworth House Medical Practice that may be susceptible to abacavir hypersensitivity reaction (HSR), which is associated with a genetic marker HLA-B*5701. 
Abacavir is a drug used in combination with other antiviral drugs, which is helpful in treating HIV infection. Abacavir is generally well tolerated, but 5-8% of patients develop an allergic reaction to the drug and the allergic reaction is much more common in those patients who have the genetic marker HLA-B*5701. 	Abacavir HSR is an allergic reaction characterised by respiratory and gastrointestinal symptoms that may be life threatening if abacavir dosing continues. Thus avoiding the use of abacavir in patients carrying this genetic marker will reduce the likelihood of developing a potentially serious allergic reaction. 
The study also aims to set up a model for a Registry where patient HLA-B*5701 results can be entered and made available to doctors who are licensed to prescribe HIV therapies in Australia via a secure password protected system. Ideally the Registry will be web-based, but if this is not feasible, it will be paper-based and managed by a recognised independent body already involved in the HIV field.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Holdsworth House Medical Practice</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Mark Bloch</name>
      <address>Holdsworth House Medical Practice
Suite 1 32A Oxford Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93317228</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93315705</fax>
      <email>mbloch@holdsworthhouse.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Mark Bloch</name>
      <address>Holdsworth House Medical Practice
Suite 1 32A Oxford Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93317228</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93315705</fax>
      <email>mbloch@holdsworthhouse.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>