<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362880">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000877886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving older patients safety in Western Australian
hospitals  reducing falls in rehabilitation units.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A cluster randomised controlled trial evaluating the effect of providing tailored multimedia patient education for cognitively intact older patients in addition to usual care in aged care rehabilitation units  on rates of falls compared to providing usual care alone.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1133-3825</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Accidental Falls</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients continue to receive their usual care. In addition to usual care, eligible patients admitted to the intervention wards will receive a multimedia falls prevention education package (DVD and workbook) with further face to face follow up education (including workbook completion and goal setting) with a health professional. The DVD will be shown to the patient at the bedside. Education session lengths will range between 15 and 35 minutes. The total number of sessions to deliver the entire educational content of the program is intended to occur within 4 sessions (range 1 to 4 sessions depending on the individual). The health professional delivering the intervention will have discretion over the frequency and duration of each follow up education session depending on individual patient and circumstance. However, the educational content is the same for all patients receiving the intervention. This flexibility in the frequency and duration of delivery is reflective of differences between and within individual patients' conditions such that on one day they may not feel well enough to participate in an education session, or only be able to manage a short duration of discussion, but on other days may tolerate longer sessions. Staff receive ongoing information about which patients have received the education and what the outcomes are for that individual patient, as well as any ward implications identified for that patient. There is not a maximum duration for the intervetion although it is expected that patients would receive a maximum of 5 sessions.
All wards commence in the control conditions at time 0. Two wards crossover into the intervention after 10 weeks and so on until all wards by 41 weeks have entered the intervention arm of the trial.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients admitted to wards who are receiving usual care will continue to receive the usual falls prevention practices. This is likely to consist of detailed falls risk screening, assessment and management of identified risk factors, ward level strategies including falls stickers and handover alerts, individual falls prevention treatment as each patient required and ongoing staff training in the area of falls prevention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of falls on all wards enrolled the trial (event rate of falls measured in events per time units) assessed by hospital data reporting numbers of patients on the trial wards, number of occupied bed days of all patients on the trial wards, and number of falls that occur on the wards during the observation period. Falls data also captured by hand searching of patient case notes throughout the obervation period of the trial.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These rates will be calculated at the conclusion of the trial observation period, that is at the  conclusion of 50 weeks.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of falls on individual sites Accidental falls (event rate of falls measured in events per time units)- assessed by hospital data reporting numbers of patients on the trial wards, number of occupied bed days of all patients on the trial wards, and number of falls that occur on the wards during the observation period. Falls data also captured by hand searching of patient case notes throughout the obervation period of the trial.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The falls rates for individual sites will be calculated at the end of the trial observation period, that is at the conclusion of 50 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Admission to ward enrolled in the trial - 8 aged care geriatric rehabilitation wards
Individual patients deemed eligible on ward to receive intervention -  The patient level inclusion criteria are that the patient must be over 60 years old, cognitively intact as defined by MMSE &gt;23/30 OR AMTS 7/10 AND final confirmation by the treating registrar that patient is cognitively intact. The patients projected admission must be longer 2 days on the ward.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of dementia or other cognitive impairment, presence of delirium diagnosed by registrar on ward</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Gatekeeper consent for ward participation in trial will be obtained from unit managers of the 8 wards prior to the commencement of the trial. The name of the ward allocated to each of the positions will be concealed in opaque envelopes numbered 1 to 8. Randomisation will occur at the ward level (cluster randomisation). All wards will start in the usual care condition for the first ten weeks. Each of the 8 wards will be randomised by project team member not directly involved in the running of these wards to enter the intervention condition at either week eleven, twenty-one, thirty-one or forty-one. Two wards will be randomised to enter the intervention condition at each of the aforementioned weeks. Once a ward has crossed over from the control condition to the intervention condition, that ward will remain in the intervention condition for the remainder of the trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised random number generation will be used to allocate each ward to crossover positions 1 through 8. Two wards will crossover from the usual care condition to the intervention condition at each ten week interval in order of their position allocation (i.e. wards allocated to crossover positions 1 and 2 will commence the intervention condition at week eleven, wards allocated to positions 3 and 4 will commence the intervention condition at week twenty-one etc.).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Wedge design - over 50 weeks 2 sites enter trial at 10 week intervals.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/01/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/12/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>27/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>8</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>8</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Notre Dame Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>19 Mouat Street, (PO Box 1225), Fremantle, WA 6959</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Health Western Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>189 Royal Street
East Perth WA 6004

PO Box 8172
Perth Business Centre
Perth WA 6849</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Nicholas Waldron</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Health Networks Branch
Department of Health, Western Australia
189 Royal Street, West Perth, Western Australia


Aged Care and Rehabilitation Department
Armadale Health Service
3056 Albany Highway, 
Armadale, Perth, WA 6112</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Professor Terry P. Haines</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Director, Allied Health Research Unit, Southern Health
Director of Research, 
Southern Physiotherapy Clinical School, 
Physiotherapy Department, Monash University
Victoria 3800 Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Christopher Etherton-Beer</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Medicine and Pharmacology, Royal Perth Hospital Unit
Principal researcher WA Centre for Health &amp; Ageing 
Level 6 Ainslie House
48 Murray Street Perth WA 6004
University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley WA 6009 Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Steven McPhail</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Senior Research Fellow
Centre for Functioning and Health Research, Queensland Health and Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation and School of Public Health,
Queensland University of Technology
c/o PO Box 6053
Buranda, QLD 4102 Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Katherine Ingram</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Geriatrician, Department of Health Western Australia
Institution: Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Department of Health, Western Australia
189 Royal Street, East Perth, WA 6004 Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Leon Flicker</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Professor Geriatric Medicine,
Director WA Centre for Health and Ageing 
The University of Western Australia
Level 6 Ainslie House
48 Murray Street Perth WA.
University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Highway
Crawley WA 6009 Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Falls are the most frequent adverse event reported in hospitals with over 30% of adverse events due to slips trips and falls.  Recently we tested a falls prevention patient education program in a large randomised trial and found it was effective in reducing falls for patients with no cognitive problems. We now plan to test this education in 8 wards within the realtime clinical setting.  The aims of the study are to evaluate the effect of providing patient education for cognitively intact older patients on the number of falls and also healthcare costs in aged care rehabilitation wards.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Hill, A.-M., Waldron, N., Etherton-Beer, C., McPhail, S. M., Ingram, K., Flicker, L., &amp; Haines, T. P. (2014). A stepped-wedge cluster randomised controlled trial for evaluating rates of falls among inpatients in aged care rehabilitation units receiving tailored multimedia education in addition to usual care: a trial protocol. BMJ Open, 4(1). doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2013-004195</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Notre Dame Australia HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee
 Research Office
The University of Notre Dame Australia PO Box 1225 Fremantle WA 6959</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>012069F</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee Office
SCGH
2nd Floor, A Block,
Hospital Avenue,
Nedlands WA 6009.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Metropolitan Area health Service HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>HREC Ethics Co-ordinator
Human Research Ethics Committee
G Block, Room G5.27B
Fremantle Hospital &amp; Health Service
PO Box 480, FREMANTLE WA 6959</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/11/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Anne-Marie Hill</name>
      <address>The University of Notre Dame Australia
School of Physiotherapy 
PO Box 1225 
19 Mouat St
Fremantle WA 6959</address>
      <phone>+61 8 94330239</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 94330210</fax>
      <email>Anne-Marie.Hill@nd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Anne-Marie Hill</name>
      <address>The University of Notre Dame Australia
School of Physiotherapy 
PO Box 1225 
19 Mouat St
Fremantle WA 6959</address>
      <phone>+61 8 94330239</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 94330210</fax>
      <email>Anne-Marie.Hill@nd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Anne-Marie Hill</name>
      <address>The University of Notre Dame Australia
School of Physiotherapy 
PO Box 1225 
19 Mouat St
Fremantle WA 6959</address>
      <phone>+61 8 94330239</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 94330210</fax>
      <email>Anne-Marie.Hill@nd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anne-Marie Hill</name>
      <address>The University of Notre Dame Australia School of Physiotherapy PO Box 1225 19 Mouat St Fremantle WA 6959</address>
      <phone>+61 8 94330239</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Anne-Marie.Hill@nd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>