<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363249">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001216808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comorbidities and Pre-operative Gastric Ultrasound Assessment</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Preoperative fasted surgical patients undergoing gastric ultrasound assessment to determine gastric fluid volume - do comorbitities influence these gastric volumes?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1136-7624</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CAPGU</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>gastric reflux</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Urgent, emergency surgery or trauma surgery</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Renal Dysfunction</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Ultrasound scan of gastric antrum . This involves placing ultrasound jelly on the epigastric area of the patient then placing a curvilinear ultrasound plastic probe on the epigastric area of the abdomen to produce a picture of the gastric antrum - this is done with the patient in the lateral decubitus position (on their side). The scan will take a duration of  circa 2 minutes which can approximate total gastric fluid volume using a validated formula</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ability to determine gastric volume in 243 patients using gastric antrum ultrasound (uses a previously validated formula which converts gastric antrum cross sectional area on ultrasound to total a total gastric volume</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each consented, fasted patient has the gastric antrum measured by ultrasound pre-operatively - duration circa 2 minutes only. The gastric antrum image is taken. The still image is then analysed by calipers and circumferential tracing which delivers a cm2 antral volume in the same instance (part of the two minutes). This figures is then fed into a formula on a database on a computer at the same time which delivers the final gastric fluid volume.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comorbidities - we will analyse the data from the primary outcome to determine whether or not comorbidities efffect gastric volumes in the fasted patient using the above technique. The source of this data is by medical records and by direct patient questioning.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post data collection analysis of groups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>ASA (american society of anaesthesiologists) grade 1-3
Starvation times more than 2 hours for clear fluids and 6 hours for food

Please see exclusion criteria... gastrointestinal abnormalities are excluded and also those who have had gastrointestinal surgery previously as this distorts the gastric antrum. All surgical specialities will be included aside from cardiothoracic patients.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous gastro-oesophageal surgery or abnormality of the gastrointestinal tract
Recent Pregnancy (within 3 months)
Age less than 18
Unable to give informed consent themselves
Hiatus Hernia
Patients who have not been starved for food fo 6 hours and clear fluids for more than 2 hours
Cognitive impairement/ mental disability
Those unable to lie still for ultrasound assessment
Cardiothoracic surgery</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/11/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>243</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr James Walker</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>C/o Department of Anaesthesia and Pain Medicine
Royal Perth Hospital
Wellington Street
Perth
WA
6000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Perth Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>197 Wellington Street
Perth
WA
6000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Tomas Corcoran</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>C/o Department of Anaesthesia and Pain Medicine
Royal Perth Hospital
Wellington Street
Perth
WA
6000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The inhalation of gastric (stomach) contents in to the lungs (pulmonary aspiration) has significant morbidity and mortality and can attribute to up to 9% of anaesthetic related deaths. [1] [2] In a large retrospective analysis, pulmonary aspiration occurs between 1:900 emergency patients and one in 3900 elective patients [3] A key risk factor for pulmonary aspiration is the volume of the aspirated gastric content. 

In certain subgroups of patients such as those with trauma, pulmonary aspiration can be as high has 34%. [4] Preoperative fasting guidelines aim to reduce the risk of pulmonary aspiration for the majority of patients undergoing anaesthesia. This is normally 6 hours for solid food and 2 hours for clear fluids in our institution (Royal Perth Hospital). Despite these guidelines there remain high risk groups in whom significant residual gastric volumes can remain despite adequate fasting - this is because they take longer to clear their gastric contents. These include patients with diabetes, liver or kidney dysfunction or pregnancy and trauma patients. [5] 
Previous methods for determining gastric content preoperatively have been invasive and lengthy procedures. Non-invasive gastric ultrasound however can now reliably estimate gastric volume and content. [5] [6] Ultrasound represents a convenient bedside portable tool that can be used to help guide anaesthetists managing the anaesthetic risk for these high risk groups.

This prospective cohort study aims to quantify the risk of aspiration by gastric volumes for those with renal dysfunction, emergency or urgent surgery, diabetes, gastro-oesophageal reflux disease (GORD) and obesity as indicated by preoperative gastric ultrasound using a standardised technique [1, 5] 
1.	Perlas, A., et al., Ultrasound assessment of gastric content and volume. Anesthesiology. 111(1): p. 82-9.
2.	Landreau, B., I. Odin, and N. Nathan, [Pulmonary aspiration: epidemiology and risk factors]. Ann Fr Anesth Reanim, 2009. 28(3): p. 206-10.
3.	Warner, M.A., M.E. Warner, and J.G. Weber, Clinical significance of pulmonary aspiration during the perioperative period. Anesthesiology. 1993. 78(1): p. 56-62.
4.	Lockey, D.J., T. Coats, and M.J. Parr, Aspiration in severe trauma: a prospective study. Anaesthesia. 54(11): p. 1097-8.
5.	Perlas, A., et al., Gastric sonography in the fasted surgical patient: a prospective descriptive study. Anesth Analg, 2011. 113(1): p. 93-7.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth Hospital Ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Office 
Level 5 Colonial House, 
Royal Perth Hospital, 
GPO Box X2213 Perth WA 6001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC 2012/162</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Corcoran</name>
      <address>C/O Anaesthetic Department
Royal Perth Hospital
Wellington Street
Perth
WA
6000</address>
      <phone>+610892241038</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tomas.corcoran@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>James Walker</name>
      <address>C/O Anaesthetic Department
Royal Perth Hospital
Wellington Street
Perth
WA
6000</address>
      <phone>+610892241038</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jameswalker50@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>