<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366066">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/07/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/07/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000740695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Oral Pacritinib Versus Best Available Therapy to Treat Myelofibrosis With Thrombocytopenia (PAC326)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomized Controlled Phase 3 Study of Oral Pacritinib Versus Best Available Therapy in Patients With Thrombocytopenia and Primary Myelofibrosis, Post-Polycythemia Vera Myelofibrosis, or Post-Essential Thrombocythemia Myelofibrosis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Persist-2</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NCT02055781</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Primary Myelofibrosis
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Myeloma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Pacritinib (oral) 400mg QD or BID daily for 24 weeks, PK (Pharmocokinetic)/PD (Pharmacodynamic) analysis and drug tablet return</interventions>
    <comparator>BAT (Best Available Treatment) varies from site to site cant be described as very different for each patient/treatment/site</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy [Baseline to Week 24]]
To compare the efficacy of two dose-schedule arms of pacritinib (pooled once-daily and twice-daily dosing arms) with that of Best Available Therapy in patients with thrombocytopenia and primary myelofibrosis, post-polycythemia vera myelofibrosis, or post-essential thrombocythemia myelofibrosis; the efficacy measure for this analysis is the proportion of patients achieving a greater than 35% reduction in spleen volume from baseline to week 24 by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) or computed tomography (CT) and the proportion of patients achieving a greater than 50% reduction in total symptom score from baseline to Week 24 as measured by the Myeloproliferative Neoplasm Symptom Assessment Form 2.0.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy [Baseline to Week 24]
To compare the efficacy of once-daily pacritinib with that of Best Available Therapy, as assessed by the proportion of patients achieving a greater than 35% reduction in spleen volume from baseline to Week 24 by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) or computed tomography (CT) and the proportion of patients achieving a greater than 50% reduction in the total symptom score from baseline to Week 24 on the Myeloproliferative Neoplasm Symptom Assessment Form 2.0.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Efficacy [Baseline to Week 24]
To compare the efficacy of twice-daily pacritinib with that of Best Available Therapy, as assessed by the proportion of patients achieving a greater than 35% reduction in spleen volume from baseline to Week 24 by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) or computed tomography (CT) and the proportion of patients achieving a greater than 50% reduction in the total symptom score from baseline to Week 24 on the myeloproliferate Neoplasm Symptom Assessment Form 2.0.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline to Week 24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Intermediate -1 or -2 or high-risk Myelofibrosis (per Passamonti et al 2010)
Thrombocytopenia (platelet count greater than 100,000/microlitre) at any time after signing informed consent
Palpable splenomegaly greater than 5 cm on physical examination
Total Symptom Score less than 13 on the MPN-SAF TSS 2.0, not including the inactivity question
Patients who are platelet or red blood cell transfusion-dependent are eligible
Adequate white blood cell counts (with low blast counts), liver function, and renal function
At least 6 months from prior splenic irradiation
At least 1-4 weeks since prior myelofibrosis therapy, including any erythropoietic or thrombopoietic agent
Not pregnant, not lactating, and agree to use effective birth control
Able and willing to undergo frequent MRI or CT assessments and complete symptom assessments using a patient-reported outcome instrument</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prior treatment with more than 2 JAK2 inhibitors or with pacritinib
More than 6 months of cumulative prior JAK2 inhibitor treatment
History of (or plans to undergo) spleen removal surgery or allogeneic stem cell transplant
Ongoing gastrointestinal medical condition such as Crohn's disease, Inflammatory bowel disease, chronic diarrhea, or constipation
Active bleeding that requires hospitalization during the screening period
Cardiovascular disease, including recent history or currently clinically symptomatic and uncontrolled: congestive heart failure, arrhythmia, angina, QTc prolongation or other QTc risk factors, myocardial infarction
Other malignancy within last 3 years other than certain limited skin, cervical, prostate, breast, or bladder cancers
Other ongoing, uncontrolled illnesses (including HIV infection and active hepatitis A, B, or C), psychiatric disorder, or social situation that would prevent good care on this study
Life expectancy &lt; 6 months</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Active Comparator: Best Available Therapy versus two doses of Pacritinib which will be randomised in a 1:1:1 ratio. Open Trial allocation not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/07/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hungary</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cell Therapeutics Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>3101 Western Avenue, Suite 600
Seattle, WA 98121</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cell Therapeutics Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>3101 Western Avenue, Suite 600
Seattle, WA 98121</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will compare the chemotherapy drug, Pacritinib, against the best available treatment for Thrombocytopenia and Myelofibrosis. You may be eligible to join this study if you aged 18 years or above and have been diagnosed with thrombocytopenia and/or myelofibrosis. Participants in this study are randomly allocated (by chance) to one of three groups. Participants in the first group will receive one dose of 400mg of oral Pacritinib for 24 weeks or until progression has occurred. Participants in the second group will receive two doses of 200mg of oral Pacritinib daily for up to 24 weeks or until progression occurs. Participants in the third group will receive best available treatment - which will be chosen by your treating physician. Participants will undergo magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) or computed tomography (CT) scans to determine spleen volume and will be assessed for total symptom score using the Myeloproliferative Neoplasm Symptom Assessment Form 2.0. These assessments will occur 12 weekly. Patients may crossover from the BAT (Best available treatment) arm to Pacritinib at the discretion of the Investigator.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.celltherapeutics.com/
</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road Eastwood South Australia 5063 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/06/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014-03-120 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Perkins</name>
      <address>Icon Cancer Care
PO Box 1879
MILTON QLD 4064</address>
      <phone>+61 07 3737 4883</phone>
      <fax>+61 07 3737 4873 </fax>
      <email>APerkins@iconcancercare.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Vince Holmes</name>
      <address>Ockham Oncology
The Logan Building, Roslin Biocentre, Edinburgh, EH25 9TT United Kingdom</address>
      <phone>+44 (0)238.032.1226</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vholmes@ockham.com</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Valentina Zhukova-Harrill, MD</name>
      <address>Ockham Oncology
8000 Regency Parkway, Suite 360, Cary, NC 27518 United States</address>
      <phone>+1 919 462 7566</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vzharrill@ockham.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Bennett Maxwell</name>
      <address>Ockham Australia Pty Ltd
c/o Blueprint Law Pty Ltd
Level 3, 2 Martin Place, 
Sydney, NSW 2000, 
Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61401817047</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bmaxwell@ockham.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>