<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372796">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000692336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study of the safety of a novel treatment (PVX108) for peanut allergy, conducted in peanut-allergic adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Phase I trial to assess the safety and tolerability of PVX108 in peanut allergic adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1195-9000 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peanut allergy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Allergies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>PVX108 comprises an equimolar solution of unmodified synthetic peptides representing T cell epitope sequences from major peanut allergens (Ara h 1 and Ara h 2).  It is administered by intradermal injection.

In Stage 1 of the trial, up to eight cohorts of six subjects will receive single injections of PVX108 or matched placebo (2:1).  The first cohort will receive a dose of 0.05nmol.  If the dose is well tolerated, the dose will be escalated in the next cohort up to a maximum of 150nmol in cohort 8.

In Stage 2 of the trial, 18 subjects will receive nine injections of PVX108 or matched placebo (2:1) at a frequency of one dose every 2 weeks.  Dosing will commence at the safe starting dose identified in Stage 1, and if well tolerated will be escalated up to a maximum of 150nmol.  The maximum total duration of treatment will be 16 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a double-blind, placebo-controlled study.  PVX108 placebo solution has the same composition as PVX108, but does not contain any active ingredients.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the safety and tolerability of single doses of PVX108 in peanut allergic adults, by assessment of adverse events monitored in clinic for at least 24 hours following administration, and then at home for 7 days.  Spirometry and peak expiratory flow will be used to assess affects of treatment on respiratory function whilst in the clinic.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety and tolerability will be monitored in clinic for at least 24 hours following administration, and adverse events assessed over 7 days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the safety and tolerability of multiple (n=9), escalating intradermal doses of PVX108 in peanut allergic adults, by assessment of adverse events monitored in clinic for at least 24 hours following the first administration, and in clinic monitoring for 8 hours following the subsequent administrations.  Adverse events occurring at home will be monitored for the duration of treatment.  Spirometry and peak expiratory flow will be used to assess affects of treatment on respiratory function whilst in the clinic.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety and tolerability will be monitored in clinic for at least 8 hours following each administration, and adverse events assessed over a 16 week duration of treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exploratory Outcome to investigate potential biomarkers of disease and blood borne signals of the effects of PVX108 therapy from blood samples collected prior to, during and after therapy.  Samples will be collected in both Stage 1 and Stage 2 of the trial in order to investigate the effects of single, and repeated administrations of PVX108, respectively. </outcome>
      <timepoint>In Stage 1, Blood samples will be collected prior to and a week after administration of PVX108.  In Stage 2, blood samples will be collected prior to, and approximately 28 days and 141 days following the commencement of PVX108 treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Males or females aged 18 to 65 years inclusive at the time of consent   
2.	Documented history of allergic reactivity to peanut regardless of severity 
3.	Positive response to peanut in a basophil activation test
4.	Peanut-specific serum immunoglobulin E (IgE) measured by ImmunoCAP (Registered Trademark) &gt;0.35 kUA/L
5.	Positive skin prick test (SPT) to peanut with a wheal diameter at least 3 mm, unless in the opinion of the investigator, it is unsafe to perform a SPT 
6.	Spirometry testing lung function within the normal range, Forced Expiratory Volume in 1 second (FEV1) at least 80% of predicted at Screening and Visit 1
7.	Bronchodilator reversibility test with change in FEV1 less than 12% and less than 200 mL   
8.	Female subjects must be:
a.	of non child-bearing potential [surgically sterilised or postmenopausal (12 months with no menses without alternative medical cause)] OR
b.	not pregnant, breast feeding or planning to become pregnant AND willing to comply with the medically acceptable contraceptive requirements of the study from Screening to at least 28 days after the last Investigational Medicinal Product (IMP) administration 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	History of or current clinically-significant gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal, cardiovascular, endocrine, oncological, immunological, neurological, ophthalmological, haematological, respiratory or psychiatric disorder or any other condition, which in the opinion of the investigator or sponsor would jeopardise the safety of the subject or the validity of the study results
2.	Random serum tryptase reading less than 11.4 ng/mL
3.	Severe or unstable asthma
4.	History of respiratory related life threatening events or life threatening anaphylaxis in the last 12 months
5.	Subjects with skin disorders that would hinder skin testing and/or its interpretation (eg severe generalised active atopic dermatitis)
6.	Subjects unable to receive beta-2-agonist or anticholinergics that could hinder treatment of an asthmatic response 
7.	Use of beta blockers, angiotensin converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors, angiotensin receptor blockers, systemic (oral or injectable) corticosteroids within 2 months prior to Day 1
8.	Prior participation in any interventional study aimed at desensitising peanut allergy within the last 5 years 
9.	Subject who received any specific immunotherapy for allergy during the past 12 months, or plans to receive during the course of the study
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A randomisation code is generated by an unblinded study statistician who is a staff member of the contracted CRO and has no involvement with site operations.  Study medication is labelled as "PVX108 Active or Placebo" with a randomisation and kit number, and packed by unblinded staff at the manufacturing facility according to the randomisation schedule generated by the study statistician.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Safety data will be summarised descriptively by treatment group at each available time point.
Categorical data will be summarised as frequency, and percentage; continuous data will be summarised as mean, standard deviation, minimum, median, and maximum as appropriate.
No formal hypothesis tests or statistical models are planned. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>10/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>19/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>66</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>9/05/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>CMAX Clinical Research Pty Ltd - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Nucleus Network - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Aravax Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 9, 31 Queens St, Melbourne, VIC 3000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Aravax Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 9, 31 Queens St, Melbourne, VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>PVX108 is a novel treatment being developed to treat the underlying cause of peanut allergy.  It is anticipated that PVX108 administered by intradermal injection every 2 or 4 weeks will produce immune tolerance to peanut proteins in patients with peanut allergy.  The product has been designed to have little or no capacity to induce acute allergic reactions, which is a significant risk with most, if not all other forms of allergen immunotherapy. Clinical trial AVX-001 is the first study of PVX108 to be conducted in humans.  Its objectives are to determine the maximum dose that can be safely administered as a single injection, and then also to assess the safety of 9 repeat, escalating doses, administered once every 2 weeks.  The study will therefore be conducted in 2 stages.

In Stage 1, up to 48 peanut-allergic subjects will receive a single dose of PVX108.  The first cohort of 6 subjects will receive the lowest dose of PVX108 (or placebo) and be monitored for 24 hours in clinic for adverse events and other clinical effects.  A safety review committee will review the results obtained in this cohort.  If the committee judges that it is safe to do so, dosing in the next cohort will progress at the next dose level.  Dose will be escalated in each cohort until the safety review committee determines that the maximum safe dose of PVX108 has been determined.

In Stage 2, up to 18 peanut-allergic subjects will commence the study at the maximum safe starting dose of PVX108.  If the dose is well tolerated, an increased dose will be administered 2 weeks later.  Subjects will receive a maximum of 9 administrations over a 16 week period.  Adverse events and other clinical effects will be monitored periodically during treatment and for 4 weeks after the last dose.  

A range of blood samples will be collected from subjects prior to, during and after treatment to address an exploratory objective to investigate potential biomarkers of disease and the effects of PVX108 therapy.   </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress> 129 Glen Osmond Road
Eastwood, South Australia 5063 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2017-03-176</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Office of ethics and research governance
55 Commercial rd
Melbourne VIC 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>127/17</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicholas Farinola</name>
      <address>CMAX Clinical Research.
Level 5, 18a North Terrace,
Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7088 7900 </phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7088 7999</fax>
      <email>Nicholas.Farinola@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Pascal Hickey</name>
      <address>Aravax Pty Ltd. Level 9, 31 Queens St. Melbourne VIC 3000 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9657 0700</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9657 0777</fax>
      <email>pascal.hickey@aravax.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sara Prickett</name>
      <address>Aravax Pty Ltd. Level 9, 31 Queens St. Melbourne VIC 3000 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9657 0700</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9657 0777</fax>
      <email>sara.prickett@aravax.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Pascal Hickey</name>
      <address>Aravax Pty Ltd. Level 9, 31 Queens St. Melbourne VIC 3000 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 9657 0700</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9657 0777</fax>
      <email>pascal.hickey@aravax.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>