<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343414">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000972921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Hunter Humira and Endothelial Function in Early Rheumatoid Arthritis Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An Investigator-Initiated Phase 2, Single Centre, Double-Blind, Randomised, Controlled Trial of the Effect of Adalimumab Upon Endothelial Function in Patients with Early and Established Anti-CCP Antibody Positive Rheumatoid Arthritis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1124-1715</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Hunter HEART Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Rheumatoid arthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>24 weeks of adalimumab (Humira) 40 mg sub-cutaneous injections 2nd weekly plus "usual care".</interventions>
    <comparator>24 weeks of placebo sub-cutaneous saline injections 2nd weekly plus "usual care".</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EndoPAT assessments of endothelial function</outcome>
      <timepoint>Minus 2 weeks, Baseline, 4 weeks, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of endothelial function by brachial artery flow-mediated dilation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Minus 2 weeks, Baseline, 4 weeks, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SphygmoCor assessments of arterial stiffness / compliance:
1. Carotid-femoral pulse wave velocity
2. Aortic augmentation index based upon radial artery pulse wave analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Minus 2 weeks, Baseline, 4 weeks, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease Activity Assessments - ESR, CRP, DAS28, DAS28 CRP, SDAI</outcome>
      <timepoint>Minus 2 weeks, Baseline, 4 weeks, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional assessment (Health Assessment Questionnaire score) and Work Instability Assessment (RA-WIS Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Minus 2 weeks, Baseline, 4 weeks, 12 weeks, 24 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Group 1: Early Rheumatoid Arthritis
Anti-CCP antibody positive rheumatoid arthritis of less than 6 months duration by onset of symptoms and age between 18 and 50 years. CRP &gt; 15 mg /L within 1 week of enrolment.

Group 2: Established Rheumatoid arthritis
Anti-CCP antibody positiverheumatoid arthritis of greater than 3 years duration,  age over 18 years and CRP &gt; 15 mg/L within 1 month of enrolment</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Disease Remission (ACR / EULAR 2010 Criteria) or CRP&lt;15 mg/L
2. Anti-CCP antibody test negative
3. Serious malignancy within the last 5 years 
4. Demyelinating Disease
5. Evidence of previous untreated TB infection</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential subjects will be identified by investigators in rheumatology outpatients and private practice and allocation will remain concealed to each individual patient until they have completed 24 weeks of saline placebo or 40 mg adalimumab injections or if they have dropped out of the study. 

Informed consent and enrolment will be performed by the research nurse / trial cordinator at the Royal Newcastle Centre. Subjects will be screened for safety and undergo two baseline assessments of vascular function, disease activity and functional / work assessments. They will then be randomly assigned to receive 24 weeks of 40 mg adalimumab or saline placebo 2nd weekly sub-cutaneous injections in addition to "usual care" for a period of 24 weeks. 

Adalimumab 40 and saline placebo pre-filled syringes will be prepared in and supplied by Abbott laboratories off-site and dispensed through the hospital pharmacy. The syringes will be labelled and dispensed in numbered containers so as to blind the investigators, research nurse / technician and patient to the contents of the syringe. A "randomisation table" will be provided to the hospital pharmacy to allow "unblinding" when each individual patient completes the study. 

Subjects will undergo further assessments of vascular function, disease activity and functional / work ability at 4, 12 and 24 weeks during the treatment period. 

After the 24 week assessment subjects and their treating rheumatologist will be informed as to whether they recieved adalimumab or placebo. They will continue to receive "usual care from their rheumatologist.</concealment>
    <sequence>Abbott laboraties will prepare syringes pre-filled with either placebo saline or 40 mg adalimumab off site The syringes will be delivered to and dispensed by the hospital pharmacy.

The randomised syringes will be presented in a numbered container for the purpose of blinding. Randomisation (50:50 ratio) will be performed at the company laboratories in batches of syringes for 10 patients (5 x 24 week courses of 40 mg adalimumab and 5 x 24-week courses of saline placebo injections) within each group (Early / Established) to ensure equal recruitment into the placebo / adalimumab arms within each group through the early phase of the study. 

The pre-filled syringes and randomisation table containing information regarding syringe contents will be delivered to and held by the John Hunter Hospital pharmacy. The pharmacy will provide the pre-filled syringes to study participants upon receipt of a study-specific prescription. The study participant, treating physician, research nurse, study technician and pharmacist will remain blinded to the contents of the pre-filled syringes until the indiviual patient has completed 24 weeks placebo / adalimumab or they have dropped out of the study.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/01/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2305</postcode>
    <postcode>2300</postcode>
    <postcode>2298</postcode>
    <postcode>2298</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Stephen Oakley</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rheumatology
Royal Newcastle Centre
Lookout Road
New Lambton
NSW
2305</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Abbott Pharmaceuticals</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>US Corporate Headquarters
Abbott Laboratories
Abbott Park, Illinois 60064-3500</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Newcastle Centre</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Lookout Road
New Lambton
NSW
2305</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Gabor Major</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Rheumatology
Royal Newcastle Centre
Lookout Road
New Lambton
NSW
2305</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr David Mathers</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Georgetown Arthritis
71 Georgetown Road
Geogetown
NSW 
2298</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr John van der Kallen</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Georgetown Arthritis
71 Georgetown Road
Geogetown
NSW 
2298</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Mark Collins</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Georgetown Arthritis
71 Georgetown Road
Geogetown
NSW 
2298</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Siva Ratnarajah</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>25 William Street 
Hamilton
NSW
2303</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr John Glass</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>50 Watt Street
Newcastle
NSW
2300</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Introduction

Rheumatoid arthritis is a severe destructive inflammatory arthritis that affects 1.5% of the population. The anti-CCP antibody positive subgroup experience a 50% increased risk of cardiovascular events that is directly related to the disease process although the mechanisms of this remain unclear. There is mounting evidence that a window of opportunity exists during which time treatment is more likely to achieve remission. It therefore seems possible that a similar window of opportunity might exist for the treatment of vascular disease in rheumatoid arthritis. 

New effective treatments for rheumatoid arthritis called the "Biologics" have become widely available over the last decade. This has resulted in dramatic improvements in the treatment of the arthritis. However, it remains unclear whether these treatments influence the risk of cardiovascular events. Pooled analyses of the large trials have not had sufficient power and are of insufficient duration to answer this question. Meta-analysis of the combined registry data found dramatic differences in the TNF-inhibitor treated group but these effects may be explained by confounding. 

Studies using assessments of pre-clinical vascular disease using imaging and physiological assessments of arterial stiffness seem more likely to show treatment effects but have thus far been inconclusive. Based upon studies in hypertension it is likely that studies utilising assessments of arterial stiffness and carotid artery wall thickness would require randomised controlled trials of considerable size and duration to detect treatment effects. Earlier pathological processes in vascular disease such as endothelial dysfunction are more likely to change quickly and detectably in response to treatment. However, studies have been inconclusive possibly due to the small sample sizes, insufficient study duration and because the studies evaluated subject with established and possibly irreversible disease. 

The Australian PBS funds Biologic drugs for patients with rheumatoid arthritis only after they have failed to respond to 6 months conventional DMARD therapy. This 6 month period presents an opportunity to evaluate the effects of TNF-inhibition (with adalimumab) upon vascular function in a randomised controlled trial while at the same time enhancing patient care. This phase 2, single-centre, double-blind randomised, placebo-controlled study will evaluate the effects of adalimumab upon endothelial function in early and established anti-CCP positive rheumatoid arthritis. 

Methods

Two groups will be studied in a randomised, controlled trial: 

1. 30 subjects with Early Anti-CCP Positive Rheumatoid Arthritis (&lt;6 months disease duration, age 18-50 years) and ;

2. 30 subjects with Established Anti-CCP Positive Rheumatoid Arthritis (&gt;3 years disease duration, age&gt;18 years)

Subjects within each group will be randomised 1:1 to receive adalimumab / placebo for 24 weeks in addition to "usual care. During the 24-week trial subjects will undergo assessments of vascular function, rheumatoid arthritis disease activity, functional impairment and work disability. Assessments will occur at minus 2 weeks, 0 (baseline), 4, 12 and 24 weeks. 

The primary response variable will be pripheral endothelial function as measured by EndoPAT. 
Secondary response variable will include:
1. Endothelial function (brachial artery flow-mediated dilation)
2. Arterial stiffness (Carotid-femoral pulse wave velocity, Central Aortic Augmentation Index as measured from the radial pulse wave analysis)
3. Disease activity (ESR, CRP, joint counts, DAS28, SDAI)
4. Functional Ability (HAQ Questionnaire)
5. Work Disability (RA-WIS Questionnaire)</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Not applicable</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Area Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Dr Nicole Gerrand
Manager, Research Ethics and Governance 
Research Ethics and Governance Unit
Locked bag 1, New Lambton, NSW, 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/09/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Stephen Oakley</name>
      <address>Rheumatology
Royal Newcastle Centre
Lookout Road
New Lambton
NSW
2305</address>
      <phone>+61 249 223 500</phone>
      <fax>+61 249 223 214</fax>
      <email>stephen.oakley@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Stephen Oakley</name>
      <address>Rheumatology
Royal Newcastle Centre
Lookout Road
New Lambton
NSW
2305</address>
      <phone>+61 249 223 500</phone>
      <fax>+61 249 223 214</fax>
      <email>stephen.oakley@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Stephen Oakley</name>
      <address>Rheumatology
Royal Newcastle Centre
Lookout Road
New Lambton
NSW
2305</address>
      <phone>+61 249 223 500</phone>
      <fax>+61 249 223 214</fax>
      <email>stephen.oakley@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>