<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365761">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000244606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Muscles activation in the movement pattern during hip joint extension.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Electromyographic analysis of the sequence of gluteus maximus and hamstring muscles activation in the movement pattern of hip extension in male and female young healthy adults: a prospective, crosssectional study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>muscle activation and movement pattern during active hip extension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of the study was to determine the order of muscle recruitment during the active hip joint extension in particular positions in young healthy adults during two different testing positions. 

First position  the subjects were asked to lie lateral on a therapeutic table with pelvis stabilization, the tested lower extremity at neutral position suspended in Universal Exercise Unit (UEU) in accordance with kinesiotherapeutic rules to exclude the force of gravity and to ensure a facilitation conditions. Second position  the subjects were asked to lie prone on therapeutic table with pelvis stabilization, feet shoulderwidth apart, arms at their sides and head was in mild line in standardized test position for prone hip extension testing. 

Subjects were instructed to perform hip extension at their natural speed, repeating five trials of each movement from starting position with 5s rest between every trial. Subjects were given a 5min rest period between the positions. All subjects presented rightleg dominance, defined according to which leg they used for kicking. 

The lower extremity subjected to measurement was chosen randomly as follows: 36 right and 28 left lower extremities were tested. We performed a onestage simple randomisation using a computergenerated random numbers, which were hidden in sequentially numbered envelopes and then selected by subjects. The researcher, who allocated the participants into the study, marking one of two cards with "X" for the left or with "Y" for the right lower extremity.

The measurement was performed by a dualchannel sEMG NeuroTrac MyoPlus device integrated with computer software for digital analysis and report creation. All electrodes were placed in pairs with distance of 1.52.0 cm from each other and parallel to the muscle fibers over the centre part of the GM and HMG muscles bellies according to recommendations of the Surface Electromyography for the Non-Invasive Assessment of Muscles (SENIAM) and International Society of Electrophysiology and Kinesiology (ISEK). 

Functional sEMG activity of the GM and HMG were recorded in realtime to analyse the order of muscle activation pattern. Recruitment time was considered necessary time to attain 75% value of the average muscle activation during hip extension in two positions. The mean onset of muscle activity for each set was calculated from the five trials within that set in both positions separately. Mean values of resting and functional GM and HMG muscles bioelectrical activity were given according to the Root Mean Square (RMS) algorithm expressed in microvolts.</interventions>
    <comparator>none</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The surface electromyography (sEMG) measurement of the average recruitment time (ART) required by the gluteus maximus (GM) and hamstring muscle group (HMG) to perform a movement of hip joint extension in two positions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Real-time sEMG measurements of the GM and HMG during the active hip joint extension in two positions.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The sEMG registration of resting and functional activity of the GM and HMG in two positions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Real-time sEMG measurements of the GM and HMG during the active hip joint extension in two positions.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of the results (resting and functional sEMG activity of the GM and HMG in two positions, as well as ART of the GM and HMG in two positions) obtained in the female and male groups in two positions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Real-time sEMG measurements of the GM and HMG during the active hip joint extension in two positions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of the correlations of functional sEMG activity of the GM and HMG with their ART during hip extension in both positions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Real-time sEMG measurements of the GM and HMG during the active hip joint extension in two positions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Lack of lower limb injuries;
2. Lack of lower back pain;
3. Correct hip joint function during testing; 
4. Normal muscle elasticity;
5. Lack of dysfunctions of the spine;
6. Normal pelvis position;
7. Lack of contraindications for sEMG measurement;
8. Age range of 18 to 25 yrs;
9. Signed agreement of participant.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Lower limb injuries;
2. Lower back pain;
3. Painful hip during testing;
4. Decreased muscle elasticity;
5. Scoliosis of the spine;
6. Pathological pelvis position;
7. Contraindications for sEMG measurement;
8. Age under 18 and/or over 25 yrs;
9. Non-agreement of participant.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The software applied in the statistical analysis was Statistica 10.0 (Stat Soft Inc., USA). Standard deviation, minimum and maximum values were calculated for measurable variables. All the variables analysed were checked through the Shapiro-Wilk test to establish a distribution type. The t-test was applied for independent samples to compare muscle recruitment time. For this pilot analyses included over 60 subjects the team had to use parametric tests (over 30 in each group). The level of p&lt;0.05 was established as statistically significant.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/01/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>64</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Opole</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Public Higher Medical Professional School</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Katowicka Street 68, 45-060 Opole</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Poland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Public Higher Medical Professional School</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Katowicka Street 68, 45-060 Opole</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Poland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Motor patterns (MP) are applied in numerous methods of modern physiotherapy as an element of diagnostics or therapy (i.e. functional diagnostics, manual therapy, PNF method). The aim of the study was to determine the order of muscle recruitment during hip joint extension in particular positions. The time recruitment of the hamstring and the gluteus maximus was assessed by the means of sEMG. The sequence of muscle recruitment in female and male group was also taken into consideration. The correct motor pattern of hip joint extension has been a subject matter of research, which stated the order of muscles activation in this movement. It is assumed that proper leg extension in the hip joint in a healthy person is initiated by the hamstring, then the gluteus maximus activates, and
at the end  erector spinae. The order of muscle activation in patients with different pathologies influencing the hip joint biomechanics should be also assessed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of Public Higher Medical Professional School</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Katowicka Street 68, 45-060 Opole</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tomasz Halski</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, Public Higher Professional School, Katowicka Street 68, 45-060 Opole</address>
      <phone>+48 774 423 524</phone>
      <fax>+48 774 423 524</fax>
      <email>halskit@wsm.opole.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tomasz Halski</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, Public Higher Professional School, Katowicka Street 68, 45-060 Opole</address>
      <phone>+48 774 423 524</phone>
      <fax>+48 774 423 524</fax>
      <email>halskit@wsm.opole.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tomasz Halski</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, Public Higher Professional School, Katowicka Street 68, 45-060 Opole</address>
      <phone>+48 774 423 524</phone>
      <fax>+48 774 423 524</fax>
      <email>halskit@wsm.opole.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Robert Dymarek</name>
      <address>Department of Nervous System Diseases, University of Medicine in Wroclaw, Bartla Street 5, 51-618 Wroclaw</address>
      <phone>+48 723 895 770</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.dymarek@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>