<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372271">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000191392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does the use of muscle relaxants during anaesthesia for hip arthroscopies influence the pressure on the perineum?
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Influence of deep muscle relaxation on the pudendal nerve by the perineal post of a traction table during hip arthroscopic surgery </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>pressure on the pudendal nerve </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anaesthesia for hip arthroscopic surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Muscle relaxation after induction of anaesthesia in patients undergoing hip arthroscopic surgery on a traction table. Relaxation will be achieved by intravenous administration of rocuronium 0.6 mg/kg (by the attending anaesthetist) approx. 5 minutes after traction has been applied to the operated leg. The pressure of the perineal post of the traction table on the patients' perineum will be measured by means of a pressure sensor mat build into the post before and 90 s after the muscle relaxant is applied. In addition, the width of the hip joint will be measured via xray before and after paralysis. In case the width of the hip joint increases after paralysis, the traction on the patient's leg will be decreased until the width of the joint is as before paralysis. At this stage, another pressure measurement at the pudendal nerve will be performed.</interventions>
    <comparator>no control group; patients act as own control (before and after administration of the muscle relaxant)</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pressures on the participants' perineum by the perineal post of a traction table by means of a pressure sensor mat built into the perineal post of the traction table.</outcome>
      <timepoint>intra-operatively; directly before and 90 seconds after intravenous administration of rocuronium 0.6 mg/kg, as well as after reducing traction on the leg (in order to reduce hip joint width to pre-paralysis status).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Width of the hip joint before and after neuromuscular paralysis in patients undergoing hip arthroscopic surgery on a traction table. The width of the joibt is measured via xrays taken during and after the traction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after paralysis at the begining of surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>none</outcome>
      <timepoint>none</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>40 patients (male and female), ASA 1-2, aged 18-60 years scheduled for elective hip arthroscopic surgery deemed appropriate (by attending anaesthetist) under relaxant general anaesthesia with propofol/opioid.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>allergy to rocuronium or sugammadex, neuromuscular disorder, severe peripheral neuropathy or anatomy excluding neuromuscular monitoring at the ulnar nerve, neuraxial anaesthesia or a femoral/sciatic nerve block prior to observation interval, age &lt; 18 &gt; 60 years, incapacity to consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>none</concealment>
    <sequence>n/a</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All data will be checked for normal distribution (Komogorov-Smirnov Test) and will be displayed as either mean (SD) or median (percentiles). Data comparing numerical values (i.e. pre- and post- paralysis pressures) will be compared using either students t-test or a non-parametric alternative, as appropriate. Relationships between categorical parameters may be explored using the chi-square or Fishers exact tests.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>20</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Joondalup Health Campus - Joondalup</hospital>
    <hospital>Glengarry Private Hospital - Duncraig</hospital>
    <postcode>6027 - Joondalup</postcode>
    <postcode>6023 - Duncraig</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof. Thomas Ledowski</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Perth Hospital
Medical REsearch Foundation
Level 2 RPH MRF Building
Rear 50 Murray Street
Perth WA 6000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Perth Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2 RPH MRF Building
Rear 50 Murray Street
Perth WA 6000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many types of surgery, such as some types of hip replacement surgery, hip arthroscopies or the re-alignment of femoral fractures need to be performed on a traction table. In order to not pull the patient off the operating table when pulling on the leg, a padded perineal post is used. However, once traction is applied, the patients pudendal nerve region is pressurized by the post and the nerve can subsequently be damaged. This can result in significant nerve dysfunction which may be short-lived, but can also last for years after surgery.
Sexual dysfunction after operations on a traction table is a long-known, but difficult to avoid problem (1-3). Mallet et al.(1) studied 168 patients after either operations on a traction table or a normal (non-traction) operating table. They found a 40.5% rate of erectile dysfunction (ED) in otherwise young, healthy males even years after operations on a traction table. Investigating potential influencing factors, the dose of the muscle relaxant administered during the anaesthetic was the only modifiable factor, with higher doses likely to prevent ED. The authors concluded that good relaxation leading to lower traction forces required and consequentially lower pressures on the pudendal nerve explained the superior outcome after deeper muscle relaxation (1).
Though this theory seems logical, it has actually never been proven.
Aim of this study is to determine the effect of deep muscle relaxation on the pressure on the perineum by the perineal post during operations on a traction table. Using an ultra-thin (approx.1 mm) pressure sensor foil embedded into the perineal post, we propose to measure the changes in pressures on the pudendal nerve after muscle relaxation. Fourty patients scheduled for elective hip arthroscopic surgery at Joondalup Health Campus and Glengarry Private Hospital will be included in this study. All patients will receive a standard general anaesthetic. After traction is applied on the operated leg, the resulting pressure on the perineum will be recorded. With the applied traction unchanged, the patient then receives a dose of the muscle relaxant rocuronium and the resulting change in pressure will be monitored. This concludes the study. The proposed project will close a significant gap of knowledge and, in a simple and risk-free approach, may lead to a change in anaesthesia practice. In addition, the joint width (hip) wil be measured before and after apralysis using portable xrays. If the joint width increases after the paralysis, the traction on the patients's leg will be reduced until the joint width is back to pre-paralysis status. At this stage the pressure on the pudendal nerve will be recorded again. 

References
1. Mallet R, et al. Urology. 2005;65(3):559-63.
2. Brumback RJ, et al. The Journal of bone and joint surgery American volume. 1992;74(10):1450-5.
3. Chan PT, et al.The Journal of trauma. 1999</summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication>none yet</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the Joondalup Health Campus </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Corner Grand Blvd and Shenton Ave
Joondalup WA 6919</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1628</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Thomas Ledowski</name>
      <address>Royal Perth Hospital
Medical Research Foundation
Level 2 RPH MRF Building
Rear 50 Murray Street
Perth WA 6000</address>
      <phone>+61892240210</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thomas.ledowski@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Thomas Ledowski</name>
      <address>Royal Perth Hospital
Medical Research Foundation
Level 2 RPH MRF Building
Rear 50 Murray Street
Perth WA 6000</address>
      <phone>+61892240210</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thomas.ledowski@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Thomas Ledowski</name>
      <address>Royal Perth Hospital
Medical Research Foundation
Level 2 RPH MRF Building
Rear 50 Murray Street
Perth WA 6000</address>
      <phone>+61892240210</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>thomas.ledowski@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>