<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370752">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000815460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Tell Your Story: An Online Intervention for Reducing Stigma in Traumatised Refugees </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Tell Your Story: An Online Intervention for Reducing Stigma in Traumatised Refugees </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1183-2978 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>STRIDE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>UNSW grant reference number: RG143112</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mental Health Stigma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Tell your Story online intervention comprises of twelve short interactive web-based modules, containing short videos, activities and integrated measurement tools. A minimum of two weeks is needed to completed the twelve sessions, access is granted for a maximum of 30 days. These sessions cover topics including psychoeducation about PTSD (Modules 1-4), self-stigma and concerns about seeking about seeking help (Modules 5-8) and potential benefits of help-seeking and help-seeking planning tasks (Modules 9-12). Each module takes between 1 and 10 minutes to complete. The intervention will be available in Tamil, Farsi and Arabic. Community consultants from refugee communities have been involved in the design of the intervention and study, and will continue to be consulted throughout the project. Intervention adherence is assessed by number of modules completed. Strategies to improve fidelity include automated reminder emails. </interventions>
    <comparator>Randomized allocation to waitlist or intervention group. After an eight week waiting period, waitlist group members will be reallocated to the intervention group and receive the intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stigma related to seeking treatment for mental health problems, assessed with the 'Self-Stigma for Seeking Help Scale'. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 4 and 8 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stigma related to PTSD, assessed with the 'Self-stigma for PTSD Scale' </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 4 and 8 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General help-seeking for mental health problems, assessed with the 'General Help-Seeking Questionnaire' </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 4 and 8 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Actual help-seeking for mental health problems, assessed with the 'Actual Help-Seeking Questionnaire' </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 4 and 8 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Personal feedback/evaluation of the online program, assessed using a 21 item measure specifically regarding the intervention, designed by the researchers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male,
Refugee, 
Speaks Arabic, Farsi or Tamil..
Subsyndromal Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD). Assessed via telephone screening process. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Actively suicidal. Assessed via telephone screening process. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central allocation by computer (online program) after eligibility determined and baseline completed</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants will be randomly assigned to either receive the intervention immediately (intervention condition) or will be placed on an 8 week waiting list (waitlist control condition), From eight weeks, when granted access to the intervention, participants in the waitlist control condition will go through the same procedures as the intervention group, </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Approximately 200 participants are expected to take part in this intervention, with a drop-out rate of 25%. Research studies of on-line interventions for traumatised samples report attrition rates of between 16-30%, accordingly, 25% attrition is a conservative estimate in this study. Based on this estimate, it is anticipated that 150 participants (75 in the intervention group and 75 in the waitlist control condition) will complete the intervention. We conservatively expect at least a medium effect size (d=0.50) when comparing the intervention and control groups. To detect an effect size of 0.5, with 80% power at a=0.05, we calculated a necessary sample size of 64 participants per condition, meaning that an overall sample size of 150 will be adequate.

Hierarchical linear modelling analyses will be used to compare change in key outcome variables from pre- to post-intervention and at follow-up between the control and and intervention groups. We will implement lower-level mediation techniques to examine the direction of influence between changes in self-stigma and key psychological, social and system-level variables. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>31/05/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/08/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>106</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Refugee Trauma &amp; Recovery Program, School of Psychology, UNSW Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Refugee Trauma and Recovery Program
UNSW School of Psychology
High Street,
UNSW AUSTRALIA
SYDNEY NSW 2052 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Beyondblue</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Beyondblue Head Office
PO Box 6100 Hawthorn West Victoria
Australia 3122. 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Movember Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Movember Head Office 
Movember Foundation, 
PO Box 60, East Melbourne, 
VIC 8002 Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Refugee men exhibit elevated rates of Post-traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD), an impairing psychological disorder. Refugee men are also highly vulnerable to the effects of self-stigma, which is associated with a range of negative outcomes, including unemployment and income loss, interpersonal difficulties, decreased self-esteem, and low treatment-seeking behaviour. This project proposes to test the efficacy of an evidence-based online intervention (Tell Your Story website) targeting self-stigma for refugee men with PTSD. Refugee men will be invited to take part in the study, recruited via caseworkers at refugee settlement agencies and advertisements within refugee networks,  with 200 men expected to enter the study following telephone eligibility screening, information and consent processes.  Participants will be randomly assigned to either receive the intervention immediately (intervention condition) or will be placed on an eight week waiting list (waitlist control condition), before access to the intervention is granted. From then on participants in the waitlist will go through the same procedure as the intervention group, The Tell your Story online intervention comprises of twelve short interactive web-based modules, containing short videos, activities and integrated measurement tools. It is available in Tamil, Farsi and Arabic. Community consultants from refugee communities have been involved in the design of the study and intervention and will continue to be consulted throughout the project. Participants will complete pre-intervention, post-intervention (4 weeks after commencing intervention) and follow-up (8 weeks after commencing intervention) measures of self-stigma, help-seeking intentions, help-seeking behaviours, PTSD symptoms and mental health-related quality of life online, with telephone support if required.  Please see attached document 'Procedure Diagram' for an overview of study flow. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.rtrp-research.com/tellyourstory</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UNSW Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)
The University of New South Wales
UNSW Sydney, NSW, Australia, 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC15351</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370752-370752-Study diagram - May update (1).pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Angela Nickerson</name>
      <address>Refugee Trauma and Recovery Program, School of Psychology, Mathews Building (F23), High Street, UNSW AUSTRALIA, Sydney 2052 
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 0538</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.nickerson@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Angela Nickerson</name>
      <address>Refugee Trauma and Recovery Program, School of Psychology, Mathews Building (F23), High Street, UNSW AUSTRALIA, Sydney 2052 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 0538</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.nickerson@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Angela Nickerson</name>
      <address>Refugee Trauma and Recovery Program, School of Psychology, Mathews Building (F23), High Street, UNSW AUSTRALIA, Sydney 2052 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 0538</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.nickerson@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Angela Nickerson</name>
      <address>Refugee Trauma and Recovery Program, School of Psychology, Mathews Building (F23), High Street, UNSW AUSTRALIA, Sydney 2052 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9385 0538</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.nickerson@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>