<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370095">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000443493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Accelerated Theta Burst Stimulation (TBS) in the Treatment of Depression</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Accelerated Theta Burst Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation in the Treatment of Depression</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1179-4083</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>It is a single blind randomised control trial where participants will receive either active daily repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (rTMS) (20 treatments over 4 weeks)  or active accelerated Theta Burst Stimulation (3 treatments per day on 7 treatment days over 4 weeks). The participant and the treater will be aware of the treatment condition however the person conducting weekly reviews will be blinded to the patient's treatment group.  Participants will also be asked to submit a sample saliva for genetic analysis of potential predictors of response to TMS. Provision of the sample is voluntary and refusal to provide a sample will not affect the participant's inclusion in other study procedures.

Both the rTMS and TBS treatments  involve the application of magnetic stimulation to the left side dorso-lateral-prefrontal cortex (DLPFC), During treatment patients will be reclined in a comfortable chair and will be alert and awake. The sensation associated with treatment is usually well tolerated with most people describing it as a tapping sensation. 

 rTMS the stimulation occurs at 10 Hz, with each pulse train lasting 4 seconds and there is intertrain interval of 15 seconds. There are 75 trains of stimulation and each treatment lasts approximately 24 minutes. TBS will be provided as  3-pulse 50 - Hz bursts applied at 5 Hz (ie  50 Hz burst of 3 pulses delivered every 200 msec). It will involve a 2 second train of TBS followed by an 8 second rest and will run for a total of 190 seconds. Thus each treatment takes a little over 3 minutes and there are 3 treatments on each treatment day with a minimum  15 minute break between treatments. The treatment intensity for both rTMS and TBS will be 120% of resting motor threshold which is measured by administering single pulse TMS to the muscle controlling area of the brain.

Adherence to the treatment schedule will be monitored by recording each treatment session on a participant's treatment sheet.</interventions>
    <comparator>The study aim is investigate whether accelerated TBS  is as efficacious as standard daily rTMS. rTMS is the control treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Montgomery Asperg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and weekly for 4 weeks. The week 4 review is to be conducted immediately after treatment completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptoms (QIDS - SR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and weekly for 4 weeks. The week 4 review is to be conducted immediately after treatment completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Global Impression - Improvement (CGI - I)

This is a 7 point scale completed by a reviewer blinded to the participant's treatment group and it assesses change in  the participant's depression relative to a baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and weekly for 4 weeks. The week 4 review is to be conducted immediately after treatment completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Clinical Global Impression - Severity (CGI - S)

This is a 7 point scale completed by a reviewer blinded to the participant's treatment group and it rates severity of depression at time of assessment. .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and weekly for 4 weeks. The week 4 review is to be conducted immediately after treatment completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (CSSR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and weekly for 4 weeks. The week 4 review is to be conducted immediately after treatment completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medical Outcomes Study Short Form - Quality of Life (SF - 12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and weekly for 4 weeks. The week 4 review is to be conducted immediately after treatment completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weschler Test of Adult Reading (WTAR). This and subsequent measures are cognitively based. Although the cognitive safety of rTMS has been repeatedly established a battery of cognitive tests have been included to explore whether there are any adverse cognitive effects of accelerated TBS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and immediately after completion of treatment course.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Digit Span - WMS III</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and immediately after completion of treatment course.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trail Making Test A and B which assesses visual attention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and immediately after completion of treatment course.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brief Visuospatial Memory Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and immediately after completion of treatment course.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and immediately after completion of treatment course.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>STROOP colour and word test (adult version) will be used to  measure:
-selective attention capacity
-processing speed ability</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and immediately after completion of treatment course.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- DSM-IV diagnosis of Major Depressive Disorder (MINI)
- HAMD score of &gt; 20 (moderate - severe depression)
- no increase or initiation of new antidepressant therapy in 4 weeks prior to screening
- have treatment resistant depression (stage II of Thase and Rush classification)
- have had no increase or initiation of new antidepressant therapy in the four weeks prior to screening 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- unstable medical condition, neurological disorder, history of seizure disorder, pregnant or lactating
-  metal in the head, except in mouth, which may interfer with the magnetic field
- current DSM-IV diagnosis of substance abuse or dependence disorder, a diagnosis of a personality disorder or another Axis 1 disorder</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The treatment group is determined by  a computer program that generates random numbers. The researcher with access to this program and who  is not involved in patient selection  securely provides the treatment group to a member of the treatment team by email or in a sealed envelope. The staff member in receipt of the treatment group is  not involved in assessing a patient's eligibility at the baseline assessment. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation to one of two treatment conditions will occur via the generation of a single computer number sequence (no stratification). </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>For the primary analysis we will compare the rate of change of depressive symptoms across the four weeks of  treatment with a mixed model approach where a time by group interaction will indicate a significantly different response. Depression scores will be compared using the PROC Mixed procedure in SAS (SAS Version 9.1 SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA). The covariance structure will be treated as unstructured using the MADRS as there are likely to be differing drop out rates across time. The PROC MIXED procedure does not delete missing values listwise, but rather handles missing values by treating them as being missing at random. The PROC MIXED procedure uses a restricted maximum likelihood algorithm that enables specific modeling of the within-patient covariance structure. Using the lowest Akaikes Information criteria as a guide to goodness of fit enables the most appropriate covariance structure to then be evaluated for each situation. 
In addition, we will compare the percentage of patients meeting response (50% MADRS reduction) and remission (HAMD score &lt;8) criteria at three and six weeks with chi squared analyses. Finally, we will compare change in baseline to end point cognitive performance between the groups with independent t-tests.

This sample size calculation was based on the acute treatment period (four week assessment), and was conducted assuming a standard deviation of 7.5 for change in MADRS scores (the standard deviation for MADRS scores varied between 4.8 and 9.9 at various study points in our largest rTMS trial to date). A difference of at least four points between the groups on the mean change in MADRS score would be clinically significant demonstrating a more rapid reduction in depression in the TBS group. With an alpha of 0.05, the study will have &gt;95% power to detect this difference allowing for a withdrawal rate of 8.3% (this is a conservative estimate based on the ongoing and previous trials) and a total analysable sample of 110 (55 per group).
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Paul Fitzgerald</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre
Level 4 - 607 St Kilda Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname> Monash University Central Clinical School </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 6, The Alfred Centre (Alfred Hospital)
99 Commercial Road
Melbourne Vic  3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>na</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>na</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this project is to investigate whether the use of a rapid form of transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS), called Theta Burst Stimulation (TBS), is a successful treatment for patients with treatment resistant depression compared to the standard form of TMS that has been used to date. 
TMS involves the application of magnetic stimulation to your head and, given repeatedly over time this stimulation has been shown to change the activity levels in the brain. Previous experience has shown that people with depression may have an imbalance in the excitability, or activity levels, of cells in the brain. TMS appears to work by changing how excitable the cells of the brain are, which may help reduce or alleviate depressive symptoms. We are conducting this study to see if we can speed up the response to TMS using a rapid form of TMS called Theta Burst Stimulation (TBS).  Theta burst stimulation (TBS) is a type of TMS where the magnetic pulses are applied in very short bursts (three pulses at a time) at a high frequency (30-50 pulses a second).  
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital's Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital
55 Commercial Rd, Prahran VIC 3181</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/01/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>577/15</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Fitzgerald</name>
      <address>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre
Level 4 - 607 St Kilda Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 6564 </phone>
      <fax>+613 9076 6588</fax>
      <email>paul.fitzgerald@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Elliot</name>
      <address>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre
Level 4 - 607 St Kilda Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 6595</phone>
      <fax>+613 9076 6588</fax>
      <email>tms-enquiry@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Fitzgerald</name>
      <address>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre
Level 4 - 607 St Kilda Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+613 9076 6564</phone>
      <fax>+613 9076 6588</fax>
      <email>paul.fitzgerald@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Elliot</name>
      <address>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre
Level 4 - 607 St Kilda Road
Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>613 9076 6595</phone>
      <fax>613 9076 6588</fax>
      <email>tms-enquiry@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>