<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373866">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/11/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001541392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessing the outcomes of patients who undergo spinal cord stimulation compared to patients who undergo spinal fusion surgery for the treatment of chronic low back pain.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessing the effectiveness of spinal cord stimulation versus spinal fusion surgery for the treatment of chronic low back pain: a prospective randomised study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1204-1725</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>FVS2016</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Low Back Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects will be randomised to either a spinal cord stimulation arm or a spinal fusion arm.
Spinal cord stimulation (SCS) arm: SCS uses a surgically implanted electrical device positioned near the spine that delivers a pulsed current to the spinal cord. The current then suppresses the pain signals being sent to the brain or replaces them with a sensation often described as a tingling, not unpleasant feeling (paraesthesia). A spinal cord stimulation trial is performed first. This involves a surgical procedure where trial (temporary) leads are placed near the spine and stimulation via an external device is performed for 7-10 days to ascertain whether or not pain relief is obtained. If greater than 50% pain relief is obtained, then a permanent implant will be offered which involves the placement of permanent leads and an implantable pulse generator. If pain relief is not obtained with a spinal cord trial, a subject will be withdrawn from the study and offered fusion. If the spinal cord implant does not maintain pain relief after 6 months, a spinal fusion will be offered. If the spinal fusion does not maintain pain relief after 6 months, reactivation of the SCS will be offered.
Spinal fusion arm: Spinal fusion is a surgical technique that stabilises the spinal vertebrae and the disc between the vertebrae. Lumbar fusion surgery has been in use for many decades and is designed to create solid bone between the adjoining vertebrae, eliminating any movement between the bones. The goal of the surgery is to reduce pain and nerve irritation. If spinal fusion does not maintain pain relief 6 months after surgery, a spinal cord stimulation will be offered. If greater than 50% pain relief is obtained from the trial, the subject will be offered a permanent spinal cord stimulation implant. A neurosurgeon will perform spinal fusion or spinal cord stimulation procedures and pain management doctors will perform spinal cord stimulation procedures.</interventions>
    <comparator>Two treatments will be compared in this study - spinal cord stimulation and spinal fusion.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary endpoint is the Numerical Pain Rating Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months except for patients randomised to the spinal cord stimulation treatment and fail the 7-10 day trial. For the 7-10 day trial spinal cord stimulation failure patients the primary endpoint is 7-10 days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of subjects who respond to SCS of fusion, where a responder is defined as greater than or equal to 50% pain relief.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post implant or spinal fusion procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient's belief of treatment efficacy as determined by Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post implant or spinal fusion procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient disability as measured by the Oswestry Disability Index (ODI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post implant or spinal fusion procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient depression, anxiety and stress as measure by the Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS21). This is a composite secondary outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post implant or spinal fusion procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health outcomes from baseline as determined by changes in the EuroQol five dimensions questionnaire (EQ-5D)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post implant or spinal fusion procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient functionality and activities of daily living (ADL) as determined by sitting, standing and walking tolerance times. This is a composite secondary outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post implant or spinal fusion procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events will be collected for all subjects. Possible adverse events  for spinal cord stimulation include:
	pain,
	potential risk of infection,
	bleeding or bruising,
	nerve damage,
	pain and inflammation at the surgical site,
	lead fractures, migrations or disconnections, and
	lack of response to treatment. 

Possible adverse events  for spinal fusion include:
	pain,
	potential risk of infection,
	bleeding or bruising,
	nerve damage,
	pain and inflammation at the surgical site,
	bone fusion failure, and
	lack of response to treatment.

These will be assessed by a study doctor.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be followed up for 18 months post the most recent procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>	Have been diagnosed with chronic low back pain that has persisted for at least 90 days
	Pain clinically suspected to be generated from single level lumbar disc disease as assessed by an investigator
	Be 18 years of age or older
	Have an average pain intensity of at least 6 out of 10 on the Numerical Pain Rating Scale at enrolment. 
	Willing and able to complete health questionnaires and pain scales as specified in the protocol 
	Willing and able to sign the study-specific Patient Informed Consent form
	Have private health insurance
	No previous open back surgery 
	No previous SCS treatment
	No RF treatment in past 12 months
	Be on stable pain medications, as determined by the Investigator, for at least 28 days prior to enrolling in this study.
	Be willing to not increase pain medication, until 6 months after SCS or fusion surgery. This excludes post and peri-operative analgesia administered as per the centres standard practice for up to 3 months following surgery. 
	Imaging, as per standard of care, to ensure suitability for spinal fusion surgery and SCS therapy (MRI +/- CT, +/- X-ray). 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	Have plans to enroll in another clinical study during their participation in this study, or are currently enrolled in an interventional clinical study that could interfere in participation in the trial or affect the scientific soundness of this study 
	Have a medical condition or pain in other area(s), not intended to be treated with SCS or fusion, that could interfere with study procedures, accurate pain reporting, and/or confound evaluation of study endpoints, as determined by the Investigator (such as primary headache diagnosis and fibromyalgia).
	Clinical back instability with surgically unstable spondylolisthesis as determined by the investigator
	Have evidence of an active disruptive psychological or psychiatric disorder or other known condition significant enough to impact perception of pain, compliance of intervention and/or ability to evaluate treatment outcome, as determined by a psychologist or the physician 
	Have a current diagnosis of a progressive neurological disease such as multiple sclerosis, chronic inflammatory demyelinating polyneuropathy, rapidly progressive arachnoiditis, rapidly progressive diabetic peripheral neuropathy, brain or spinal cord tumor, and/or central deafferentation syndrome. 
	Have a current diagnosis of a coagulation disorder, bleeding diathesis that would put patient at any increased risk of bleeding during SCS or fusion procedure, progressive peripheral vascular disease or uncontrolled diabetes mellitus. 
	Having any clinical evidence of mechanical instability or progressive neurologic pathology that warrants surgical intervention.  
	Any previous history of surgery on the posterior elements (laminectomy, posterior fusion) that would disrupt/obliterate the posterior epidural space.
	Have a condition currently requiring or likely to require the use of MRI or diathermy.
	Have metastatic malignant disease or active local malignant disease.
	Have a life expectancy of less than 1 year.
	Have an active systemic or local infection.
	Be pregnant (if female and sexually active, subject must be using a reliable form of birth control, be surgically sterile or be at least 2 years post-menopausal).
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Subjects will be assigned to a SCS arm or a fusion arm. Depending on the outcome of these treatments, the subjects could then follow other arms. There are 9 sub-arms within the study. These include:
1.1a Positive SCS trial and implant.
1.1b Positive SCS trial, negative SCS implant, positive fusion
1.1c Positive SCS trial, negative SCS implant, negative fusion, positive SCS reactivation.
1.1d Positive SCS trial, negative SCS implant, negative fusion, negative SCS reactivation
1.2 Failed SCS trial.
2a Positive fusion
2b Negative fusion, positive SCS trial, positive SCS implant.
2c Negative fusion, positive SCS trial, negative SCS implant.
2d Negative fusion, negative SCS trial.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>NRS back pain will be analysed with analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) with baseline as the covariate. The use of ANCOVA will reduce the standard deviation for NRS back pain relative to baseline SD, and relative to change in NRS SD. Therefore, based on the estimates for the standard deviation (1.6 and 3.0 ) a reasonable estimate for the standard deviation of NRS back pain at final analysis is 2.0.
For the sample size calculation the level of significance was set to 0.05 with a 2-sided test, the difference between mean NRS back pain for the SCS and Spinal Fusion groups was set to 1.5 with a common standard deviation of 2.0. With these settings a sample size of 29 patients per arm, so 58 in total, is required to achieve a power of 80%. 
The null hypothesis shall be that mean NRS for the SCS arm is equal to mean NRS for the Spinal Fusion arm. The alternative hypothesis shall be that the NRS means are not equal. The assumptions of the ANCOVA of Normality and constant variance will be assessed graphically with quantile-quantile plots and residual versus fitted plots. If necessary rectifying transformations will be applied. The continuous secondary efficacy variables will be analysed as per the primary efficacy variable analysis. 
Binary and categorical variables with greater than 2 outcomes will be reported as frequencies and percentages. 
Binary secondary efficacy variables, such as success or failure with respect to a 50% improvement in NRS, will be analysed with logistic regression. Odds-ratios and relative risks with 95% CI will be used as measures of the strength of the Treatment effect. The null hypothesis shall be appropriate for each binary variable. For example, for the secondary efficacy variable of the proportion of patients whose NRS improves by greater than or equal to 50% the null hypothesis shall be that the proportion of patients with greater than or equal to 50% in their NRS shall be equal for the SCS arm, and the Spinal fusion arm. The alternative hypothesis is that the 2 proportions are not equal. The hypothesis test will be conducted with the log-likelihood ratio statistic. 
Categorical secondary efficacy variables with greater than 2 outcomes, such as PGIC, will be analysed with a log-linear model. Odds-ratio with 95% CI will be used as measures of the strength of the Treatment effect. The null hypothesis shall be that there is no association between Treatment and the Categorical secondary efficacy variable. The alternative hypothesis shall be that there is an association. The hypothesis test will be conducted with the log-likelihood ratio statistic. 

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/01/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>20/01/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>58</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>20/07/2022</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - St Kilda Road Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash Clinical Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>271 Clayton Road, Clayton, Victoria, 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Boston Scientific</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Gaetano Martinolaan 50
6229 GS Maastricht
The Netherlands</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Netherlands</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The main purpose of this study is to determine whether or not patients that are treated by spinal cord stimulation have the same or different treatment outcomes as patients that undergo spinal fusion in a group of patients that have received no treatment in the past for chronic low back pain. The outcomes are measured by pain scores, depression, anxiety and stress scores, patient impression of change, patient functionality, health outcomes assessments and disability scores. The patients' belief in the efficacy of the treatment will also be collected. There is also an aspect of the study that will look at whether spinal cord stimulation in conjunction with spinal fusion leads to better patient outcomes. Eligible subjects will be randomised to either the spinal cord stimulation arm or the fusion arm. Subjects randomised to the spinal cord stimulation arm will undergo an initial spinal cord stimulation trial. If this trial is positive (relieves pain by at least 50%), the subject will then be offered a spinal cord implant. If the trial is not positive, the subject will be withdrawn from the study and offered spinal fusion. If the implant is positive (pain relief of at least 50% is maintained) 6 months post implant, a subject will be followed for a further 12 months. If the implant is negative, the subject will be offered spinal fusion. Outcomes of the fusion will be assessed 6 months after surgery. If the fusion is positive (pain relief of at least 50% is maintained), the subject will be followed for a further 12 months. If the fusion is negative, the subject will be offered reactivation of the spinal cord stimulator. The subject will then be followed for 18 months post reactivation. Subjects randomised to the spinal fusion arm will be assessed 6 months post procedure. If the spinal fusion is positive (pain relief of at least 50% is maintained) , subjects will be followed for a further 12 months. If the spinal fusion is negative, subjects will then be offered a spinal cord stimulation trial. If this trial is positive (at least 50% of pain relief is obtained), subjects will be offered a spinal cord stimulation implant. Subjects will be followed for 18 months post implant (whether positive or negative). If the spinal cord stimulation trial is negative, subjects will be followed for 18 months post the spinal fusion procedure. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road Eastwood South Australia 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/10/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-09-690</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Epworth Healthcare Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>89 Bridge Road, Richmond, Victoria, 3121</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bruce Mitchell</name>
      <address>Metro Pain Group
271 Clayton Road
Clayton 
Victoria 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9595 6111</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9595 6110</fax>
      <email>bmitchell@metropain.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Merylyn Ryan</name>
      <address>Monash Clinical Research
271 Clayton Road
Clayton 
Victoria 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9595 6111</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9595 6110</fax>
      <email>mryan@monashcr.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Merylyn Ryan</name>
      <address>Monash Clinical Research
271 Clayton Road
Clayton 
Victoria 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9595 6111</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9595 6110</fax>
      <email>mryan@monashcr.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Merylyn Ryan</name>
      <address>Monash Clinical Research
271 Clayton Road
Clayton 
Victoria 3168</address>
      <phone>03 9595 6111</phone>
      <fax>03 9595 6110</fax>
      <email>mryan@monashcr.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>