<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371388">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001422415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and safety of artemether-lumefantrine and artesunate-amodiaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum in Dolisie, Republic of Congo</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy and safety of artemether-lumefantrine and artesunate-amodiaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum in Dolisie, Republic of Congo</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malaria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The efficacy and safety of artemether-lumefantrine (twice daily doses for 3 days) and artesunate-amodiaquine (one daily dose for 3 days)  for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum malaria will be evaluated. For artemether-lumefantrine, each tablet contains 20 mg artemether and 120 mg lumefantrine, A total target dose ranges 5-24 mg/kg bw of artemether and 29-144 mg/kg bw of lumefantrine. Artemether+lumefantrine will be given by weight bands: 1 tablet for children 5 to less than 15kg, 2 tablets per dose for children 15 to less than 25kg, 3 tablets for children 25 to less than 35 kg. For artesunate+amodiaquine treatment, a daily dose of 4 mg of artesunate/kg body weight and 10 mg of amodiaquine base/kg body weight will be given. The treatment will be given orally in tablets. Eligible children will be treated for three days and followed up for 28 days. The daily doses of the study medicines will be administered under direct supervision by the study team. 

Patients will be enrolled sequentially. The first cohort of recruited patients will be treated with artesunate+amodiaquine. When 88 patients have been enrolled and treated with artesunate+amodiaquine, the recruitment of the second cohort will begin; patients in the second cohort will be treated with artemether+lumefantrine and recruitment will continue until the target number of patients was reached.
</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no comparison. Each drug will be studied separately in a cohort of patients. So for each drug it is one arm prospective study design</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent of treatment failures (early treatment failure + late clinical failure + late parasitological failure). This is a composite primary outcome.

Enrolled children will be evaluated for parasitological (using microscopy) and clinical responses. Treatment outcomes will be classified according to the WHO protocol 2009</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome (treatment failures) will be assessed on days 1, 3, 7, 14, 21 and 28 following treatment of artesunate+amodiaquin or artemether+lumefantrine </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent of adverse events

Known adverse events of the study drugs are:

1. Artemether-lumefantrine: Abdominal pain, asthenia, cough, diarrhoea, dizziness, fever, headache, joint and muscle pain, loss of appetite, rush, nausea, vomiting.
2.Artesunate-amodiaquine: abdominal pain, asthenia, cough, diarrhoea, dizziness, insomnia, loss of appetite, nausea, vomiting.

Parents/guardians of children enrolled in the study will be asked routinely about previous symptoms and about symptoms that have emerged since the previous follow-up visit. When clinically indicated, patients will be assessed and treated appropriately. All adverse events will be recorded on the case report form.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Secondary outcome (adverse events) will be assessed on days days 1, 3, 7, 14, 21 and 28 following treatment of artesunate+amodiaquin or artemether+lumefantrine </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of artemisinin resistance molecular markers (K13).

Parasite DNA extracted from the dried blood spots will be analyzed by PCR and sequencing for the presence of K13 (molecular marker for artemisinin resistance).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At day 0 (prior initiation of treatments)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	age between 6 months and 11 years.
2.	mono-infection with P. falciparum detected by microscopy;
3.	parasitaemia of 1000200000/microliter asexual forms;
4.	presence of axillary  temperature equal  to or greater than 37.5 degrees centigrade or history of fever during the past 24 h;
5.	ability to swallow oral medication;
6.	ability and willingness to comply with the study protocol for the duration of the study and to comply with the study visit schedule; 
7.	informed consent from the parent of children 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>11</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	presence of general danger signs in children aged under 5 years or signs of severe falciparum malaria according to the definitions of WHO (Appendix 1);
2.	weight under 5 kg;
3.	mixed or mono-infection with another Plasmodium species detected by microscopy;
4.	presence of severe malnutrition defined as a child aged 6-60 months who has a mid-upper arm circumference &lt; 115 mm;
5.	presence of febrile conditions due to diseases other than malaria (e.g. measles, acute lower respiratory tract infection, severe diarrhea with dehydration) or other known underlying chronic or severe diseases (e.g. cardiac, renal and hepatic diseases, HIV/AIDS);
6.	regular medication, which may interfere with antimalarial pharmacokinetics;
7.	history of hypersensitivity reactions or contraindications to any of the medicine(s) being tested or used as alternative treatment(s);
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment.  is not applicable as this is a single arm study,  
Patients aged between 6 month and 11 years with uncomplicated falciparum malaria who meet the study inclusion criteria will be recruited and treated on site with artemether-lumefantrine or artesunate-amodiaquine. Patients will enrolled sequentially: patients will be enrolled first in the artesunate-amodiaquine study and when the sample size of 88 is reached, the subsequent patients will be enrolled in the artemether/lumefantrine arm. Patient will be monitored for 28 days at a fixed schedule of check-up visits and corresponding clinical and laboratory examinations.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The treatment failure rate to artesunate+amodiaquine, and artemether-lumefantrine  in the study area is estimated to 5%. At a confidence level of 95% and a precision around the estimate of 5%, a minimum of 73 patients will be included. With a 20% increase to allow loss to follow-up and withdrawals during the28/42-day follow-up period, 88 patients per  per drug will be included in the study.

The WHO excel software programs will be used for data double entry and analysis. Data will be analysed using Kaplan-Meier method and per-protocol analysis. In addition to the other reasons for withdrawal, patients will be considered withdrawn from the analysis if the PCR results are unclassifiable or if the results of PCR indicate that the failure is due to reinfection with P. falciparum or P. vivax.

The final analysis will include:

1.	a description of all patients screened and the distribution of reasons for non-inclusion in the study;
2.	a description of all the patients included in the study;
3.	the proportion of adverse events and serious adverse events in all the patients included in the study;
4.	the proportion of patients lost to follow-up or withdrawn, with 95% confidence intervals and a list of reasons for withdrawal;
5.	the cumulative incidence of success and failure rates at day 28, PCR-uncorrected and PCR-corrected; and
6.	the proportion of early treatment failure, late clinical failure, late parasitological failure and adequate clinical and parasitological response at day 28, with 95% confidence intervals, PCR-uncorrected and PCR-corrected.

Guidelines on calculating the cumulative success or failure rate, the proportion of adequate clinical and parasitological response and treatment failure are given in the WHO protocol 2009.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>176</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/12/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Congo</country>
      <state>Niari</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ministry of Health and Population</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rue Lucien Fourneau 9, Centre-ville, BP 2101, Brazzaville</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Congo</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Health and Population of Congo</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rue Lucien Fourneau 9, Centre-ville, BP 2101, Brazzaville</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Congo</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Institute Pasteur du Cambodge, Phnom Penh</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>5 Blvd Monivong, BP 983
Phnom Penh</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Cambodia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Title: Efficacy and safety of artemether-lumefantrine, artesunate-amodiaquine and dihydroartemisinin+piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in Dolisie in Congo.

Objective: To assess the efficacy and safety artemether-lumefantrine and artesunate-amodiaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum malaria infections

Study Sites: study will be conducted in two public health facilities in Dolisie. 

Study Period: The study period will cover October to December 2016.

Study Design: Single arm prospective study for each drug.

Patient population: Febrile patients aged between 6 months and 11 years with confirmed uncomplicated P. falciparum infection.

Sample Size: 88 patients will be enrolled in each treatment arm.

Treatments and follow-up: artemether-lumefantrine (twice daily doses for 3 days) and artesunate-amodiaquine (daily dose for 3 days) will be given under direct supervision. Clinical and parasitological parameters will be monitored over a 28-day follow-up period to evaluate drug efficacy and safety.

Primary endpoints: The proportion of patients with early treatment failure, late clinical failure, late parasitological failure or an adequate clinical and parasitological response as indicators of efficacy. Recrudescence will be distinguished from re-infection by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) analysis. Day 3 malaria positivity rate will determined.

Secondary endpoints: 
1. The frequency of adverse events.
2. Frequency of molecular markers for artemisinin resistance (K13).
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>WHO ethics and research committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>20 Av. Appia, 
1211 Geneva 27 Switzerland
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ERC.0002769</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Switzerland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mathieu Ndounga</name>
      <address>Programme National de Lutte contre le Paludisme (PNLP)
Rue Lucien Fourneau 9, Centre ville, BP 2101, Brazzaville</address>
      <phone>+242 05 526 05 03 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ngoualandounga@yahoo.fr</email>
      <country>Congo</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mathieu Ndounga</name>
      <address>Programme National de Lutte contre le Paludisme (PNLP)
Rue Lucien Fourneau 9, Centre ville, BP 2101, Brazzaville</address>
      <phone>+242 05 526 05 03 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ngoualandounga@yahoo.fr</email>
      <country>Congo</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mathieu Ndounga</name>
      <address>Programme National de Lutte contre le Paludisme (PNLP)
Rue Lucien Fourneau 9, Centre ville, BP 2101, Brazzaville</address>
      <phone>+242 05 526 05 03 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ngoualandounga@yahoo.fr</email>
      <country>Congo</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marian Warsame</name>
      <address>Global Malaria Programme, World health Organization 
20 Av. Appia, 1211
Geneva 27 Switzerland</address>
      <phone>+41 22 791 5076</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>warsamem@who.int</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>