<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371220">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001103459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Disposable gastroscope for variceal screening and surveillance</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Ultra-thin disposable gastroscope for screening and surveillance of gastro-oesophageal varices in patients with liver cirrhosis: a prospective comparative study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1185-9724 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Liver cirrhosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Portal hypertension</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Gastro-oesophageal varices</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a pilot study that will prospectively evaluate the role of disposable thin endoscopy in screening and surveillance of gastro-oesohageal varices, compared to the current gold standard upper endoscopy. 

Consecutive patients with liver cirrhosis scheduled to undergo upper endoscopy in the Gastrointestinal Investigation Unit for variceal screening or surveillance will be screened for eligibility to participate in the study. Patients will undergo examination with thin disposable endoscopy and standard upper endoscopy on the same day or within 72 hours. These 2 examinations will be performed by different consultant gastroenterologist who will be blinded to the results of the other endoscopic examination.

Upper endoscopy with the disposable ultra-thin gastroscope will be performed unsedated after a minimum of four hour fast from solids and liquids. The patients will receive laryngeal/pharyngeal local anesthesia with lignocaine gargle or spray. The patient will be in the left lateral position for the upper endoscope. The approximate duration of the procedure will be 15 minutes. This will be followed by conventional gastroscopy which will be performed under sedation. The approximate duration of this examination will be 15 minutes

On endoscopic examination, the following will be documented:
Number and location of varices: upper, middle or lower oesophagus or stomach.
Size of varices: classified according to Baveno I consensus, small varices &lt; 5mm, large varices &gt;5mm.
Presence of red colour signs / red wale signs
</interventions>
    <comparator>Gold standard conventional gastroscopy</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Accuracy of new device to detect the presence of oesophageal varices compared with CG results</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of endoscopic evaulation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Accuracy  of the new device to detect the presence of high risk varices compared with CG results</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of endoscopic evaluation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>sensitivity for the detection of oesophageal varices and the presence of high risk varices compared with CG results</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of endoscopic evaluation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Specificity for the detection of oesophageal varices and the presence of high risk varices compared with CG results</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of endoscopic evaluation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety will be assessed with vital signs performed every 3 minutes and clinical assessment by the clinician during the procedure and the patient observed for 1 hour post procedure. A phone call will be made 24 hours after the procedure to document any late complications</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of endoscopic evaluation and upto 24 hours later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postive predictive value for the detection of oesophageal varices and the presence of high risk varices compared with CG results</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of endoscopic evaluation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Negative predictive value for the detection of oesophageal varices and the presence of high rish varices compared with CG results</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of endoscopic evaluation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Liver cirrhosis</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Active gastrointestinal bleeding
Inability to provide written informed consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size of 49 was caluclated for a specificity of 90%, with a prevalence of 0.3 in the target popultion and a margin of error of 0.10, with a 95% confidence interval.
Statistical analysis will be performed to calculate the sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value (PPV), negative predictive value (NPV) and accuracy of thin disposable gastroscopy (TDG) compared with gold standard conventional gastroscopy(CG). The agreement between the presence or absence of varices and the grading of varices between TDG and CG will be assessed with calculation of kappa statistics. Inter-observer agreement for the assessment of presence and grade of varices will be calculated between the endoscopist and independent validator. The Mann Whitney U test ill be used to compare patient tolerability pre- and post-procedure, p&lt;0.05 would be considered significant</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>2/09/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>28/11/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>49</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>48</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/11/2015</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>28/11/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Royal Adelaide Hosptial </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>North Terrace, Adelaide, SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Royal Adelaide Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>North Terrace, Adelaide, SA 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients with liver cirrhosis are at risk of having varices (dilated vessels) in their oesophagus and stomach. These varices can bleed and bleeding is associated with serious complications. It is recommended that all patients have their oesophagus examined with an endoscopy (flexible telescope / camera) to detect these varices. Currently these endoscopies are performed in the Gastrointestinal Investigation Unit using sedation (medication to make you drowsy). The purpose of this study is to evaluate the accuracy of a new endoscope in detecting dilated vessel in the oesophagus and stomach compared to standard the endoscopy. The newer scope is very thin, disposable and can be performed in a consultation room. The thinness of the scope allows the examination to be performed without sedation, using only local sedation. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>North Terrace, Adelaide, SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>130230</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/06/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dep Huynh</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5214 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dep.huynh@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dep Huynh</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5214 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dep.huynh@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dep Huynh</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology and Hepatology
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5214 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dep.huynh@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>