<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371508">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001410448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of short-term exposure to sound at very high and ultrasonic frequencies at subthreshold levels; a double-blind provocation study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects on sensitive and non-sensitive adults of short-term exposure to sound at very high and ultrasonic frequencies at subthreshold levels; a double-blind provocation study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pain or sensation of pressure in the ears</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Tinnitus</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dizziness or light-headedness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Nausea</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Headache or pain or pressure other than in the ears</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Inability to concentrate</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Ear</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other ear disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study comprises an initial screening session, a hearing threshold measurement session, and four test conditions.
== Asymptomatic participants ==
The following procedure applies to asymptomatic participants, as identified by questionnaire in the screening session
== Hearing threshold level measurement session ==
In the hearing-threshold measurement session, the hearing threshold level (HTL) of the participant at 20 kHz will be measured using standard psychoacoustic methods with very short bursts of ultrasound (&lt;0.5 sec per presentation). The HTL is required in order to ensure that an inaudible sound can be presented to the participant during the exposure conditions. The maximum sound pressure level used in this measurement will be 105 dB (re 20 microPa). The measurement will be performed in a sound-treated booth using earphones. The level of the sound is that measured at the reference microphone of the appropriate ear simulator according to IEC 60318.  The HTL will be re-measured after the test condition to ensure that it has not altered (for example due to changes in earphone placement).  If the HTL has reduced by 10 dB or more, then the test session will be deemed invalid, and will be repeated on another day.
== Test conditions ==
Four test conditions will be carried out.
Condition A, the Ultrasound ON condition: Ultrasound will be presented to the participant; the participant will be told that ultrasound may or may not be present.
Condition B, the Ultrasound OFF condition: Sham ultrasound (silence) will be presented to the participant; the participant will be told that ultrasound may or may not be present.
Condition X and Y; additional information will be displayed to the participant.
The comparison of conditions A and B will be used to estimate any genuine effect of ultrasound presence. The details of the four conditions are given below.
Condition A, the Ultrasound ON condition.
The participant will be seated in a sound proof booth with the earphones placed by the tester, and not removed for the duration of the test session (unless requested by the participant).  High-frequency sound will be presented to the participant at a frequency of 20 kHz and at a sound-pressure level that is either 88 dB (re 20 microPa) or is 15 dB below the participant's hearing threshold level at 20 kHz, whichever is the lower level. The participant will be exposed for a period of 20 minutes, during which time they will be asked to perform a computer-based visual recognition task, displayed to them via a small screen. Galvanic skin responses will be recorded from electrodes attached to the fingers. After the 20-minutes of exposure, the participant will asked to remain seated for a further 5-minute recovery period.
The participant will be asked to complete subjective ratings of the severity of their symptoms relating to the health conditions stated previously. Ratings are performed at three time points: pre-exposure (baseline), immediately following exposure, and at the end of the recovery period. Testing will be postponed if the participant scores higher than 0 (=no symptoms) on any of the health conditions in the baseline condition.

Condition B, the Ultrasound OFF condition.
This condition is identical to condition A in all respects except that silence is presented from the loudspeaker.
Condition X and Y: These conditions are identical to conditions A and/or B in all respects except that additional information will be displayed to the participant.
== Sequence and timing of test conditions ==
Participants will be randomly allocated to one of four arms, which determines the order in which the four conditions will be conducted:
Arm 1: A X B Y
Arm 2: A Y B X
Arm 3: B X A Y
Arm 4: B Y A X
Allocation will be by random selection without replacement in blocks of four participants to achieve a counterbalanced design.
There will be a maximum of two conditions per day, such that A and B will be separated by approximately 24 hours (at least), and X and Y will also be separated by approximately 24 hours. If two conditions are conducted on one day, there will be a minimum of 2 hours between the end of the first condition and the start of the second. A test condition will be postponed if the participant scores higher than 0 (=no symptoms) on any of the health conditions in the baseline condition.
== Conducting the test ==
For all conditions, the sound will be presented from a computer in an observation room adjacent to thesound-treated both. The tester has no influence on the sounds being presented, and no way of telling whether ultrasound is being presented or not in conditions A and B. After starting the software run, the tester inputs the participant number only. The software uses a random number generator to determine which arm the participant is allocated to, and thus whether genuine ultrasound or sham exposure (silence) is presented in any session. The key indicating which participant was allocated to which arm is stored in a coded computer file that is not opened until after the experimental phase of the study has finished, and the statistical analysis has been completed. Conditions X and Y are not blind to the tester as they are able to see the same display as the participant.

== Symptomatic participants ==
For symptomatic participants, the above procedure will be adapted as follows. They will be asked about the time course of the symptoms they have previously experienced. If the estimated onset and recovery time of these allows, then the exposure time and time between test conditions will be reduced. Additional repeats of the set of four conditions will also be conducted.</interventions>
    <comparator>For the primary research question, which is to determine whether the presence of ultrasound has an effect on health conditions, the comparator condition is the silent condition described above under "interventions" (condition B).

The participant will be seated in a sound-treated booth with the earphones in place. No sound will be presented but the participant will not know whether ultrasound is being presented or not. The participant will be exposed for a period of 20 minutes to this sham ultrasound, during which time they will be asked to perform a computer-based visual recognition task, displayed to them via a small screen. Galvanic skin responses will be recorded from electrodes attached to the fingers. After the 20-minutes of exposure, the participant will asked to remain seated for a further 5-minute recovery period.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure will be a composite obtained by summing the scores on a 7-item subjective rating scale.  The seven items are tinnitus, pain or fullness in the ear, Headache or pain or pressure somewhere other than my ears, nausea, dizziness or light headedness, anxiety, and inability to concentrate.  For each item, the participant will be asked to rate the severity of their symptoms on an 11-point scale running from 0 (No symptoms) to 10 Extreme severity.  The scale is administered via computer and does not allow fractional selections.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following each exposure condition (i.e. true or sham exposure)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance on a sustained attention task carried out during each of the four test conditions.  The task is the Conjunctive Continuous Performance Task (Kelip, J.G., Herrera, J., Stritzke, P., Cornblatt, B.A. [2003]. The continuous performance test, identical pairs version [CPT-IP]. III. Brain functioning during performance of numbers and shapes subtasks. Psychiatry Research, 74:35-45.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Performance is measured at the end of exposure condition  (i.e. true or sham exposure)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in mean galvanic skin response measured on the finger relative to the baseline reading.  This is a measure related to emotional stress or arousal.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Average is measured across the duration of exposure condition and compared to the value at baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ability to correctly state that ultrasound is present after prolonged exposure, despite the level of ultrasound being presenented below the hearing threshold of the participant at that frequency, as measured using detection of short stimuli (&lt; 0,5 sec).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after exposure condition (i.e. true or sham exposure).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Same as for the primary outcome measure, but with a different timepoint.</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of the 5-minute recovery period which immediately follows the exposure period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>For participants deemed "sensitive or symptomatic", the participant must have reported adverse reactions which they attribute to ultrasound exposure in the past.
For aysmptomatic participants, they must have hearing within normal limits at conventional audiometric frequencies (0,25 - 8 kHz).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>69</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Severe tinnitus as identified by screening questionnaire
2. Abnormality detected on otoscopy, such as discharge, inflammation, infection, or excessive wax.
3. Contraindications in screening questionnaire such as recent ear infection, current ear pain, or exposure to very loud sounds in the last 24-hours. 
4. Excessive intake of caffine in the two hours before the study (e.g. 2 cups of strong coffee)
5. Excessive intake of alcholol withing 24 hours of the study (e.g. more than 2 pints of beer, or two glasses of wine)
6. Colour blindness effecting participants ability to distinguish red, green and blue (which could affect outcomes on the sustained attention task used)
7. Epilepsy (which might be agrivated by the sustained attention task, which has flashing images)
8. Use of recreational drugs in the last week.
9. Strenuous physical or mental activity on the day of the experiment.
10 Hyperacusis experienced for sounds at "conventional" frequencies (&lt; 10 kHz).
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>computer with controls the stimulus generation (whether genuine or sham exposure) also randomly assigns participants to each arm (genuine or sham exposure first).  Key to allocation is stored on computer file, visible only after completion of the analysis.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization using computer generated sequence, counterbalanced over blocks.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>As well as conditions of genuine and sham exposure, where the participant is told ultrasound may or may not be present, the effect of informing that the ultrasound is definitely present or absent will be tested in two addional conditions using a display. These conditions will not be double blind.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>sample size:
For asymtomatic participants, the primary outcome measure is the difference in adverse ratings between genuine and sham exposure conditions, taken at the end of the exposure phase. An increase in rating of 3 points would be considered important, as it represents an increase from no noticeable effect to a clearly noticeable adverse effect.  A previous pilot study indicated that the measurement error (standard deviation of measurement in identical exposure conditions) to be typically &lt;1 point in asymptomatic participants who typically scored at the bottom of the rating scale (no symptoms) throughout the test.  However, this is likely to be an underestimate for cases where symptoms arise.  

The sample-size calculation is based the directional alternative hypothesis that the genuine effect of ultrasound will be &gt;= 3 points on the response scale.  The standard deviation is assumed to be 6 points.  For a type 1 error rate of 5%, and a power of 80%, for a paired t-test, the required sample size is 27.  Allowing for a requirement of an additional 15% in the sample size where non-parametric tests are required leads to a target sample size of 32.  
Recruitment will continue until 32 participants complete the study.  If participants withdraw early from the study due to high adverse symptoms following exposure, they will be included in the analysis.  Those withdrawing for other reasons will not be included in the analysis.

Statistical analysis.
The null hypothesis under test is that there will be no increase in subjective rating scores between conditions of genuine and sham exposure measured at the end of the exposure period.  Based on pilot studies, it is expected that the rating scores will be heavily positively skewed, with a preponderance of low scores.  Parametric statistical analysis using MANOVA is unlikely to be appropriate. Instead, generalized estimating equations using a gamma distribution will be used.  If these tests are judged inappropriate, then non-parametric tests such as Wilcoxon tests, corrected for familywise error will be used.

Fewer symptomatic participants are available for testing, and these will be tested using experiments customised to measure their specific symtpoms, and with many more repeats of the genuine and sham conditions to allow analysis  using a multiple repeated measures (n-of-1) design.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/02/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>27/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/06/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>40</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>12/05/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>2/06/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Hampshire</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Southampton</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Southampton,
Highfield
Hampshire
Southampton
SO17 1BJ
United Kingdom
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United Kingdom</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Colt Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>New Lane Havant
Hampshire
PO9 2LY
United Kingdom
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To measure subjective and objective responses to ultrasound at 20 kHz, at a level which is inaudible to the participant, and to compare these responses to sham exposure (i.e. silence). The participant is informed that ultrasound may or may not be present in each condition, but is unaware of whether ultrasound will be present or absent..

Two groups of participants will be tested. Those who have complained of adverse symptoms in the past which they attribute to high-frequency sound, and adults with no such history of adverse symptoms.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Southampton, Ethics Committee of the Faculty of Engineering and the Environment</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Southampton,
Highfield
Hampshire
Southampton
SO17 1BJ
United Kingdom
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>23716</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>United Kingdom</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Lineton</name>
      <address>University of Southampton,
Highfield
Hampshire
Southampton
SO17 1BJ
United Kingdom
</address>
      <phone>+44 23 8059 3467</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>B.Lineton@soton.ac.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mark Fletcher</name>
      <address>University of Southampton,
Highfield
Hampshire
Southampton
SO17 1BJ
United Kingdom
</address>
      <phone>+44 23 8059 3467</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>M.D.Fletcher@soton.ac.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Lineton</name>
      <address>University of Southampton,
Highfield
Hampshire
Southampton
SO17 1BJ
United Kingdom
</address>
      <phone>+44 23 8059 3467</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>B.Lineton@soton.ac.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ben Lineton</name>
      <address>University of Southampton,
Highfield
Hampshire
Southampton
SO17 1BJ
United Kingdom
</address>
      <phone>+44 23 8059 3467</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>B.Lineton@soton.ac.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>