<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83872">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/05/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000354280</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The efficacy of a specific tennis elbow brace (Go-Strap brace) compared to a standard counterforce brace in participants with tennis elbow</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparing the effects of a novel elbow brace, standard elbow brace and control intervention on elbow pain and function in patients with lateral epicondylalgia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1149-9753</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>lateral epicondylalgia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There will be two independent variables in the research design; treatment condition and time (pre-, post-application). Treatment condition will have three levels; Go-strap (trademark, Sportstek, Australia) brace, a standard counterforce brace and a control condition. Participants will experience each treatment condition in a random order over three separate sessions. Participants will attend at approximately the same time of day on three occasions, each separated by at least 24 hours in order to control for carry-over effects. Go-strap (trademark) brace: An experienced musculoskeletal physiotherapists will apply the brace to the affected elbow, following the manufacturer's instructions for application, in terms of orientation of the brace relative to the elbow and firmness of fit. The brace will be worn only for the time taken for post-intervention assessment (approximately 30 minutes). Hence, the only activities the participants will be performing whilst wearing the brace are the post-intervention outcome measures.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard counterforce brace (United Pacific Ltd, Australia): the same physiotherapist will apply this brace to the affected elbow, following the manufacturer's instructions for application, with respect to the orientation of the brace relative to the elbow and firmness of fit. The brace will be worn only for the time taken for post-intervention assessment (approximately 30 minutes). Hence, the only activities the participants will be performing whilst wearing the brace are the post-intervention outcome measures.
Control (no brace): The participant will be in the treatment room with the physiotherapist for the same length of time as the other two interventions, but no manual contact between the therapist and participant will take place.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain-free grip strength: measured using a Digital Analyser grip dynamometer (MIE Ltd, Leeds UK). Each participant will be positioned in supine lie with the upper limb to be measured in shoulder neutral, elbow extension and forearm pronation. They will be instructed to squeeze the dynamometer until pain is first provoked. The process will be repeated three times with an intervening 30-second rest interval, with the average of three measures calculated. Both affected and unaffected arms will be tested.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention and immediately post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wrist posture: Wrist joint angle will be measured simultaneously with pain-free grip strength using a MTx 3-dimensional sensor (Xsens, Netherlands) attached via velcro to the dorsal surface of the hand. The MTx sensor is an accurate motion tracking device that simultaneously measures angles in three dimensions (heading, roll and pitch). Therefore, measures of wrist flexion/extension and radial/ulna deviation will be simultaneously recorded and will be plotted against the pain-free grip data. The mean angle of three efforts with intervening 30-second rest intervals will be calculated, and the process repeated for the opposite side.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention and immediately post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pressure pain threshold: A quantitative measure of pain will be obtained by the use of pressure pain algometry, which has previously demonstrated good inter- and intra-rater correlation and reliability. The most sensitive point will be located over the lateral humeral epicondyle by manual palpation and marked with a permanent marker so that the same point can be used for pre- and post-condition application measures. Pressure pain threshold (kp/cm2) will then be measured with a pressure algometer (load cell, switch, data acquisition card and Labview software 8.6; National Instruments, Texas USA) over the site on the lateral elbow that was most tender to palpation. Pressure pain threshold is defined as the amount of pressure that provokes the first onset of pain and is expressed as a ratio of affected/unaffected arms. Three repeat measures with a 30-second rest period between each measurement will be recorded and averaged. Both affected and unaffected arms will be tested.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention and immediately post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Active joint position error: All testing will be carried out using a MTx 3-dimensional motion tracking sensor (Xsens, Netherlands), a slide sheet and board. For measurement of shoulder internal/external rotation and elbow flexion/extension, the MTx sensor will be placed on the dorsal aspect of the distal forearm using velcro. For wrist flexion/extension, the MTx sensor will be placed on the dorsal aspect of the hand and held in place with velcro. In all tests visual cues will be eliminated by a blindfold. Each participant will be asked to wear a no-sleeves or short-sleeved shirt.

Active elbow joint position error (flexion/extension).  Active elbow joint reposition error: Participants will be seated at a table with hips and knees flexed to 90 degrees, with their arm in 90 degrees shoulder elevation and neutral rotation. The upper arm will be stabilised against a fixed block using velcro, while the hand will be supported by a cloth doughnut on a low friction surface. Joint reposition sense will be measured by performing an ipsilateral matching activity at random target angles using active angle reproduction. The target positions will be randomly chosen by the investigator, within the range of 30-100 degrees of elbow flexion, as previous studies have suggested that cues from soft tissue stretch and apposition at the ends of range may influence the accuracy of joint position sense. Once the selected target angle has been reached, it will be held in that position for 5 seconds and the participant will be instructed to memorise the position. The limb will then be passively returned to the original starting position. After a pause of 5 seconds the participant will be asked to actively move the forearm back to the same target angle, and to activate a hand held stop button once they felt they had reached the target angle. The angle will be recorded using a customised Labview program (V8.6, National Instruments, Texas USA), this process will then be repeated ten times for each side. The absolute difference between the two measures will be recorded and the mean of ten repetitions will be calculated. 

Active shoulder joint position error (rotation).  The same procedure described above, will be used to measure joint position error in shoulder rotation. The patient will be seated with the upper arm resting by the participant's side and the forearm and elbow resting on a low-friction slide sheet and board. The humerus will be held against the participant's body by a velcro strap while the hand will be supported by a cloth doughnut on the low friction surface. Using the same protocol described above, the target positions will be randomly chosen by the investigator, within mid-range of internal/external rotation. Ten trials will be recorded and the mean absolute error will be calculated.

Active wrist joint position error (flexion/extension).  The participant will be seated with the upper arm resting by the participant's side and the forearm and elbow resting on a low-friction slide sheet and board. The forearm will be held against a fixed block by a velcro strap while the hand will be supported by a cloth doughnut on the low friction surface. Using the same protocol described above, the target positions will be randomly chosen by the investigator, within mid-range of wrist flexion/extension. Ten trials will be recorded and the mean absolute error will be calculated.
Both affected and unaffected arms will be tested for all measures of joint position error.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-intervention and immediately post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pain over the lateral elbow of a minimum six weeks duration which is increased on palpation of the lateral epicondyle, gripping, and resisted wrist or 2nd or 3rd finger extension.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any treatment of the elbow pain by a health care practitioner within the preceding three months, corticosteroid injection to the affected elbow within the last six months, bilateral elbow symptoms, cervical radiculopathy, any other elbow joint pathology or peripheral nerve involvement, previous surgery to the elbow or a past history of dislocation, fracture of the elbow or tendon ruptures, systemic or neurological disorders, and shoulder, wrist and/or hand pathology.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A research investigator will screen potential participants for eligibility, based on the inclusion/exclusion criteria, via an initial interview. Once informed consent is obtained, participants will receive all three intervention conditions in a random order. A computer-generated randomisation schedule will be drawn up with the order of intervention randomised and administered via concealed allocation (sealed opaque envelopes). This process will be carried out by a research investigator who is independent of the outcome assessments.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated randomisation schedule</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>A repeated-measures, crossover, placebo controlled, randomised design</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/06/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>28/05/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>35</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Griffith University
Gold Coast Campus
Qld 4222</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>United Pacific Industries</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>10 Eastspur Court
Kilsyth
Victoria 3137</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Leanne Bisset</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science
Griffith University
Gold Coast Campus
Qld 4222</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>An elbow brace is commonly used by patients to help manage the pain of tennis elbow, however good quality evidence to support the use of braces in the management of tennis elbow is scarce and the evidence is conflicting. The aim of this study is to compare the immediate effects of two tennis elbow braces; the Go-Strap brace and a standard counterforce brace, in people with tennis elbow. It is hypothesised that the 'Go-Strap' brace will reduce pain and increase function significantly more than either the counterforce brace or a control (no treatment).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Room 2.39, Bray Centre(N54) 
Nathan Campus
Griffith University
170 Kessels Road
Nathan Qld 4111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>PES/26/08/HREC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Leanne Bisset</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy &amp; Exercise Science,
Griffith University,
Gold Coast Campus. Qld 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 55527717</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 55528674</fax>
      <email>l.bisset@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Leanne Bisset</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy &amp; Exercise Science,
Griffith University,
Gold Coast Campus. Qld 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 55527717</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 55528674</fax>
      <email>l.bisset@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Leanne Bisset</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy &amp; Exercise Science,
Griffith University,
Gold Coast Campus. Qld 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 55527717</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 55528674</fax>
      <email>l.bisset@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Leanne Bisset</name>
      <address>School of Rehabilitation Sciences
Griffith University
Gold Coast Campus
Qld 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 55527717</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.bisset@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>