<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369317">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000148471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The evaluation of rehabilitation effects using exoskeleton EKSO GT in patients after stroke 
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The evaluation of rehabilitation effects using exoskeleton EKSO GT in patients after stroke 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>hemiparesis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>ambulation/gait limitations</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>mental health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>quality of life</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will recruit individuals who have experienced a stroke. It will be focused on evaluation of the efficacy of new technology, a lower body exoskeleton EKSO GT with Variable Assist software extension (EKSO Bionics, Richmond, CA, USA), that allows ambulation of patients with various neurological disorders. All measurement procedures will be performed by members of the research team on subjects, that have been qualified to EKSO training basing on inclusion and exclusion criteria provided by both  Ekso Bionics (in terms of safe use of the device) and the lead researcher (to maintain the coherence of the research group). The physical therapists conducting the training are certified EKSO Physical Therapist. Each training session will involve standing and walking in EKSO GT exosceleton. The intervention will be administrated on an individual one-on-one basis. 
The duration of each training session will depend on the patient capabilities to walking, but will not exceed 60 min each. The training of each evaluated individual will be made over the course of 4 weeks, 3-4 times a week. The frequency of sessions will be determined each time at the discretion of the treating therapist. Each training session in Ekso GT will be stored in exosceleton software and noted in patients personal medical documentation. Evaluation of the patients state will be made at baseline and after 4 weeks of treatment.</interventions>
    <comparator>The subjects in control group will recieve a standard rehabilitation typical for stroke survivors. It will include gait reeducation, neurorehabilitation with e.g  PNF or Bobath methods. The rehabilitation will be administrated  3-4 times a week. Evaluation of the patients state will be made at baseline and after 4 weeks of treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in quality of ambulation assessed by surface electromyography with foot-switch sensors, </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, after 4 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in functional abilities assessed by balance analysis -evaluated by baropodometric platform </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after 4 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in functional abilities assessed by muscles strength analysis - evaluated by isokinetic dynamometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after 4 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in gait progression assessed by walking time in EKSO, training mode type in EKSO, level of assists in EKSO, step count (composite secondary outcome) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, during every second training session and after 4 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in gait quality assessed by surface electromyography with footswitch sensors.  Analysis of muscle timing, recruitment over the gait phases, differences in activation between body sides and the changes over time
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after 4 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in balance and load distribution  assessed by  baropodometric platform. Stabilometric evaluation of quiet standing (eyes open/eyes closed), weight bearing during quiet standing and stand up from chair/sit down on chair tasks.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after 4 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in muscular strength assessed by isokinetic dynamometer during knee flexion-extension</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after 4 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiovascular effect of treatment assessed by heart rate and blood pressure measurements - evaluated by automatic sphygmomanometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, during every second training session and after 4 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impact of treatment on Spasticity assessed by Modified Ashworth Scale (MAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, during every second training session and after 4 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in bladder and bowel function assessed by medical staff evaluation-  (composite secondary outcome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, during every second training session and after 4 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in functional abilities assessed by Riverbed Mobility Index, Barthel Index and neurological evaluation (exteroceptive sensation  sensation of touch, vibration, squeeze, proprioception, mirror test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after 4 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life assessed by questionnaire - Stroke Speci c Quality of Life Scale (SS-QOL) and SF-36</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after 4 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subjects must be post stroke  1st ischaemic stroke incident
Subjects must be able to fit into device and have joint motion to allow ambulation in device</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Second or another stroke incident
Difference in lower limbs length bigger then 2 cm
Joint contractures of the hip, knee, or ankle that might limit normal ROM during ambulation
Medical issue that precludes full weight bearing and ambulation (e.g. orthopedic injuries, pain, severe osteoporosis, or severe spasticity)
History of significant problems with skin breakdown or current skin breakdown that would prevent subject from wearing the device
Cognitive and/or communicative disability (e.g. due to brain injury). Patients must be able to follow directions and demonstrate learning capability
Pregnancy
Untreated deep vein thrombosis (DVT)
Weight above 100 kg
Height lower then 150 cm or above 190 cm</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Enrolling by invitation</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>prof. Anna Mika</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Physical Education in Krakow
al. Jana Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Poland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Physical Education in Krakow</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>al. Jana Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Poland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Institute of Physical Education, State Higher Vocational School in Nowy Sacz, Poland</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>ul Kosciuszki 2 
33-300 Nowy Sacz </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Poland</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Limitations of independent walking after stroke and of functional status are serious problem for a growing group of patients. Restoration of walking abilities by various mechanical devices and locomotor training have been previously reported. Therapy for neurological recovery of walking may include locomotor training with the use of body weight supported treadmill training by either, a robotic training system or manual placement of the feet during the treadmill walking. The most technologically advanced devices for mechanical support of the gait are exoskeletons. An exoskeleton is a wearbale robot which support or, in some cases substitute for the users own movements.
The aim of this study is the evaluation of the quality of ambulation and functional status of stroke survivors while using the robotic exoscelaton. 
This study will recruit individuals who have experienced an ischemic stroke. It will be focused on evaluation of the efficacy of new technology, a lower body exoskeleton EKSO GT with Variable Assist software extension(EKSO Bionics, Richmond, CA, USA), that allows ambulation of patients with various neurological disorders. The Variable Assist software feature allows the patients with hemiparesis to be trained only on the affected side, whilst the non-affected side works as a non-motorized support frame only. The other feature is the ability of adaptation of the level of force support given to the lower limbs by EKSO drives independently to each limb. Those two features might significantly improve the therapy outcomes made with the use of the EKSO system.
Members of the research team will perform all of the evaluation listed in methods section on subjects, that have been qualified to EKSO training basing on inclusion and exclusion criteria provided by both  Ekso Bionics (in terms of safe use of the device) and the lead researcher (to maintain the coherence of the research group). The Physical therapists conducting the training are certified EKSO Physical Therapist. The training of each evaluated individual will be made over the course of 4 weeks, 3-4 times a week. The subjects in control group will recieve a standard rehabilitation typical for stroke survivors. It wil include gait reeducation, neurorehabilitation with e.g  PNF or Bobath methods. The rehabilitation will be administrated 3-4 times a week. Evaluation of the patients state will be made before the first training session and after last one.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Ethical Committee of Regional Medical Chamber in Krakow</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>ul. Krupnicza 11a
31-123 Krakow</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>77/KBL/OLI/2014</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Anna Mika</name>
      <address>University of Physical Education in Krakow
al. Jana Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</address>
      <phone>+48 12 6831134</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anna.mika@awf.krakow.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Anna Mika </name>
      <address>University of Physical Education in Krakow
al. Jana Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</address>
      <phone>+48 12 6831134</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anna.mika@awf.krakow.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Anna Mika</name>
      <address>University of Physical Education in Krakow
al. Jana Pawla II 78
31-571 Krakow</address>
      <phone>+48 12 6831134</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anna.mika@awf.krakow.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>