<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368695">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000827538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of rates of extravasation injuries and phlebitis between fixed duration use of peripheral intravenous cannula and standard practice in newborns infants.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of rates of extravasation injuries and phlebitis between fixed duration use of peripheral intravenous cannula and standard practice in newborns infants.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1171-0011</utrn>
    <trialacronym>RESITE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Extravasation injuries associated with peripheral intravenous cannula use in neonates</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Phlebitis associated with peripheral intravenous cannula use in neonates</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This research aims to study the rates of infiltration/extravasation injuries and phlebitis between infants who have an elective removal and re-site of their PIVC at 72 hours compared to those in whom the PIVC is changed due to clinical concerns only.  The study follows one episode of PIVC use per baby enrolled into the study. For babies randomised to the elective resite group, the babies will have his/her PIVC electively re-sited every 72 hours. The re-site will be performed by medical staff (neonatal registrar, fellow or consultant). 
All participants' PIVC site will be monitored by nursing staff for signs of infiltration and phlebitis injuries. The nursing staff are required to document presence or absence of these signs every shift (morning, afternoon or night). 
If the PIVC sites show clinical indication for replacement prior to 72 hours it will be re-sited.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator, which is the standard practice group in this project, is the group of babies whose peripheral intravenous cannulas will be monitored and re-sited if there were signs of complications.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of extravasation injury. This will be assessed by the presence of signs of extravasation injury identified by nursing and medical staff. These signs include: distress with flushing, swelling at site, skin blanching, delayed capillary refill time, blistering of skin, absent peripheral pulse. Nursing staff will be required to fill out an observation log to indicate if these signs occur during their shift. If signs occur, this will prompt the need for medical review to assess for need of PIVC re-site.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be monitored until the peripheral intravenous cannula is no longer required for that episode of intravenous therapy use. Duration of monitoring therefore depends on individual participant's situation. Rate of infiltration injury will be assessed at the end of study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of phlebitis. This will be assessed by the presence of signs of phlebitis injury identified by nursing and medical staff. These signs include: distress with flushing, erythema, induration, palpable venous cord, and pyrexia. Nursing staff will be required to fill out an observation log to indicate if these signs occur during their shift. If signs occur, this will prompt the need for medical review to assess for need of PIVC re-site.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be monitored until the peripheral intravenous cannula is no longer required for that episode of intravenous therapy use. Duration of monitoring therefore depends on individual participant's situation. Rate of phlebitis will be assessed at the end of study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate if gestational age of participant is associated with development of extravasation injury and phlebitis. The information on gestational age of the participant at birth will be collected at enrolment on our registration pro forma. The information will be used to see if there is link between gestational age and complication rates of peripheral IV cannula use.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at the end of study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate if birthweight of participant is associated with development of extravasation injury and phlebitis. The information on participant's birthweight will be collected at enrolment on our registration pro forma. The information will be used to see if there is link between gestational age and complication rates of peripheral IV cannula use.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at the end of study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate if the site of PIVC placement is associated with risk of developing extravasation injury and phlebitis. The information on where the site of PIVC insertion is will be collected on our participant registration pro forma. The information will be used to see if there is link between site of PIVC insertion and complication rates of peripheral IV cannula use.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at the end of study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate if the admission diagnosis of participant is associated with risk of developing extravasation injury and phlebitis. The information on participant's admission diagnosis will be collected at enrolment. The information will be collected on our participant registration pro forma. The information will be used to see if there is link between participants' medical condition(s) and complication rates of peripheral IV cannula use.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at the end of study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate if the type of infusate given is associated with risk of developing extravasation injury and phlebitis. The information on the type of infusate given will be collected at enrolment and also during use of PIVC through our participant registration pro forma and also our nursing observation log. The information will be used to see if there is link between use of different infusates and complication rates of peripheral IV cannula use.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at the end of study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Newborns who are born at least 32 weeks of gestation admitted into Neonatal Intensive Care Unit and Special Care Nursery who requires a peripheral intravenous cannula for treatment and management.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>1</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Babies who have concurrent use of intravenous access other than peripheral intravenous cannula</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is concealed via use of sealed opaque envelope for randomisation</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Assuming that the current rate of infiltration/extravasation injury is approximately 50%, we expect a 50% reduction with the intervention (i.e. a reduction to 25% incidence). We will need a sample size of 52 infants in each group to give the study a power of 80% and an alpha error of 0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/07/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>16/07/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>104</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>113</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>20/07/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Atul Malhotra</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Newborn, Southern Health, 246 Clayton Road, Clayton VIC 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Unfunded</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unfunded</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is to compare the rates of extravasation injury and phlebitis between newborn infants who have an elective re-site of their peripheral intravenous cannula (PIVC) at 72 hours compared to those in whom the PIVC is changed due to clinical concerns only. We hypothesise that the incidence rates of extravasation injury and phlebitis will reduce by half in our study group with the intervention.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, Monash Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Services, Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Road, Clayton VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/05/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15200A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/04/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Atul Malhotra</name>
      <address>Monash Newborn, Monash Medical Centre,
246 Clayton Road,
Clayton VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 95945191</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>atul.malhotra@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Atul Malhotra</name>
      <address>Monash Newborn, Monash Medical Centre,
246 Clayton Road,
Clayton VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 95945191</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>atul.malhotra@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Atul Malhotra</name>
      <address>Monash Newborn, Monash Medical Centre,
246 Clayton Road,
Clayton VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61 3 95945191</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>atul.malhotra@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>