<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365800">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000251628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cognitive Remediation Therapy (CRT): is it a feasible and acceptable psychological treatment for borderline personality disorder (BPD)?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In consumers with Borderline Personality Disorder, does Cognitive Remediation Therapy (CRT) improve cognitive and social functioning?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1153-3107 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Borderline Personality Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Cognitive Remediation Therapy (CRT) is a psychological treatment which aims to improve cognitive functioning and has shown to be effective in reducing cognitive dysfunction and improving social function mainly in people with a diagnosis of schizophrenia (McGurk et al, 2007). It is distinct from Cognitive Behavioural Therapy in targeting cognitive skills (e.g. working memory, long-term memory, cognitive flexibility, planning, organisational ability) rather than thoughts, beliefs, or affect. 

Reeder and colleagues (2012) have designed and completed initial feasibility testing for a computerised CRT package for Schizophrenia: CIRCuiTS (Computerised Interactive Remediation of Cognition  Training for Schizophrenia). This is a modular package including tasks of a wide range of cognitive functions (particularly executive function and memory), designed to allow therapy programmes to be flexibly designed to incorporate only relevant tasks. 

With the latter taken into consideration a new CIRCuiTS program will be developed to only include excercises known to target the cognitive deficits identified in consumers with BPD. The aim of the new CIRCuits program seeks to target the specific cognitive deficits found in consumers with BPD (from phase 1) to improve attention, memory, and planning.

The new (CRT) CIRCuiTS program will be piloted to 30 consumers to assess the acceptability and feasibility. Participation involves taking part in a group run CIRCuiTS program delivered by a trained advanced CRT practitioner.  The program involves 45 minutes working on a computer program that focuses on cognitive skills and 15 minutes discussing how these computer programs relate to thinking skills needed in day to day life.  Participants will be required to attend twice a week for around 20 weeks.
</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no control group within this study.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.To identify cognitive targets for intervention with CRT (a psychological therapy which aims to improve cognitive skills such as problem-solving and memory), by investigating associations between cognitive functions known to be frequently impaired in BPD and social functioning, symptoms and costs of care.  Participants will complete a pre-treatment battery of questionnaires that assess mental health diagnosis and symptoms, participants ability to reason, solve problems and remember items, assess perceptions about the way they think and solve problems, and participants' perceptions about their social functioning, and the costs of care associated living with a mental illness.  

The measures used to assess this outcome include:
1) Premorbid IQ: Test of Premorbid Functioning 
2) Executive function : Computerised neurocognitive tests from the Cambridge Neuropsychological Test Automated Battery (CANTAB).
3) Social function: Work and Social Adjustment Scale (Mundt et al, 2002); Global Assessment of Functioning (Endicott et al, 1976. Symptoms: BPD Severity Index (Arntz et al, 2003); Brief Symptom Inventory (Derogatis, 2001); The Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale- 21 Item (Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995); Impact of Events Scale  Revised (Weiss and Marmar, 1996); Barratt Impulsiveness Scale (Patton et al, 1996)
4) Costs of care: Client Service Receipt Inventory (Beecham and Knapp, 1992)


</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months Pre-treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2.	To investigate self-perception of cognitive performance in people with BPD and the perceived relevance and importance of a psychological treatment which aims to improve cognitive skills.

This outcome is assess as part of the pre-treatment battery of questionnaires and includes the use of:
1)The Self-perception of cognitive function: Subjective Scale to Investigate Cognition in Schizophrenia (SSTICS) (Stip et al, 2003) and,
2) A qualitative interview exploring participant's perceptions of the perceived relevance and importance of the CRT program. 
  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 Months Pre-treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3.	To adapt CIRCuiTS for people with BPD based on findings from Phase 1.

This outcome will be assessed utilising SPSS statistical software to determine the frequency and severity of cognitive deficits identified in consumers with BPD. The CIRCuiTS program will be be adapted to specifically target the cognitive deficits identified from the findings. 
 </outcome>
      <timepoint>1 Month Pre-Treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4. To pilot a new computerised CRT programme (CIRCuiTS), specifically adapted for BPD with nine individual cases, to assess (a) acceptability and (b) feasibility.   

The outcome will be assessed on and case by case basis using qualitative information from participant feedback and conducted interviews. Paired samples t-tests will be utilised to compare pre-treatment and post-treatment  data to establish whether the CIRCuits program is a feasible and effective treatment for improving cognitive skills in BPD consumers.   </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post preliminary assessment/screening (treatment) and 1 month post completion of the 20 week intervention  (post-treatment follow-up). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients aged 18-65, who are attending/being treated by Metro South Addiction and Mental Health Services. Inclusion criterion requires a confirmed diagnosis of BPD according to the McLean Screening Instrument for BPD (Zanarini et al, 2003). </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criterion includes evidence of an organic brain disorder, or head injury.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited from the Mood ACU of Addiction and Mental Health Services at Metro South, Queensland Health. Potential participants will be identified by treating teams within this service, and advised of the study. The treating teams will be requested to arrange a convenient time for the participant to meet with the Associate Investigator. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The design of the proposed research is a mixed-method within-subjects repeated measures design. 

</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be analysed using SPSS v19 statistical package. Variables will be examined to determine the normality of distributions, missing information, and outliers.   

1. Pearsons correlations and linear regression will be used to investigate the extent to which cognitive functioning can be used to predict a) social functioning, b) symptoms, and c) costs of care. Cognitive variables with high correlations will be incorporated into the CIRCuiTS for people with BPD. 

2. Paired samples t-tests will be utilised to compare data collected pre-treatment/ post-treatment to establish whether the CIRCuits program is a feasible and effective treatment for improving cognitive skills in BPD consumers.    


</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>6/06/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Metro South Addiction and Mental Health Services
519 Kessel Rd, MacGregor QLD, 4109</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aims: The proposed research aims to (i) identify cognitive targets for intervention with Cognitive Remediation Therapy (CRT) in people with Borderline Personality Disorder (BPD), and (ii) to investigate self-perceptions of cognitive performance, and the perceived relevance and importance of a psychological treatment that aims to improve cognitive skills. In addition, the proposed research aims to (iii) adapt CIRCuiTS for people with BPD based on the established cognitive targets and (iv) to pilot the new CRT (CIRCuiTS) program to assess the acceptability, and feasibility. 

Method: The design of the proposed research is a within groups study.  Participants will be 30 BPD patients aged 18-65, who are attending/being treated by Metro South Addiction and Mental Health Services. Inclusion criterion requires a confirmed diagnosis of BPD according to the McLean Screening Instrument for BPD (Zanarini et al, 2003). Exclusion criterion includes evidence of an organic brain disorder, or head injury. All participants will be give an information letter, and written informed consent to take part. If participants do not have the capacity to consent but wish to participate, their guardian will be asked to consent to the patients participation in the study. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Health Service District Human Research Committee (EC00167)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Centres for Health Research, level 7
Translational Research Institute Building
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Road, Woolloongabba,  Qld 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Frances Dark</name>
      <address>Metro South Addiction and Mental Health Services
519 Kessel Rd, MacGregor QLD, 4109
</address>
      <phone>+61731678430</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>frances.dark@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Frances Dark</name>
      <address>Metro South Addiction and Mental Health Services
519 Kessel Rd, MacGregor QLD, 4109
</address>
      <phone>+61731678430</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>frances.dark@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Frances Dark</name>
      <address>Metro South Addiction and Mental Health Services
519 Kessel Rd, MacGregor QLD, 4109
</address>
      <phone>+61731678430</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>frances.dark@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Frances Dark</name>
      <address>Metro South Addiction and Mental Health Services
519 Kessel Rd, MacGregor QLD, 4109
</address>
      <phone>+61731678430</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>frances.dark@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>