<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369818">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001571460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of cows milk infant formula on neurodevelopment and growth in infants</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of 12-month supplementation of infant and follow-on formula with complex milk lipids on neurodevelopment and growth in healthy term infants</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1177-9120</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CLING</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Infant nutrition

</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Brain Development in term infants</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention products are infant formula for 0-6 month-old infants and follow-on formula for 6-12 month-old infants. All products comply with GB standard for nutritional composition. Healthy term infants in group 1 receive a infant formula and follow-on formula enriched in complex milk lipids to match the upper end of breast milk levels. 
Composition of the infant formula products for group 1 per 100 mL of reconstituted powder formula (67 kcal/100 mL):
Protein 1.7 g, fat 3.4 g, carbohydrate (lactose) 7.4 g, linoleic acid 400 mg, a-linolenic acid 45 mg, prebiotic, probiotic, vitamins and minerals.
Composition of the follow-on formula products for group 1 per 100 kcal of reconstituted powder formula (68 kcal/100 mL):
Protein 2.2 g, fat 3.2 g, carbohydrate (lactose) 7.8 g, linoleic acid 360 mg, prebiotic, probiotic, vitamins and minerals.
Up to 2 weeks of age, infants will be fed 7-8 times 60 mL of formula by their parent or caregiver at home.
Up to 4 weeks of age, infants will be fed 7-8 times 90 mL of formula by their parent or caregiver at home.
Up to 2 months of age, infants will be fed 6-7 times 120 mL of formula by their parent or caregiver at home.
Up to 4 months of age, infants will be fed 5-6 times 150 mL of formula by their parent or caregiver at home.
Up to 6 months of age, infants will be fed 5-6 times 180 mL of formula by their parent or caregiver at home.
Between 6 and 12 months of age, infants will be fed 3-4 times 210 mL of formula by their parent or caregiver at home.
It is expected that weaning foods will be introduced from 6 months.
All infant feeding will be monitored by every scheduled visit, we also will collect and record number of empty cans of formula milk from each infants parent throughout the trial.     


</interventions>
    <comparator>Healthy term infants in group 2 receive an infant formula and follow-on formula with the same volume, energy level, macronutrients and micronutrients as in group 1 but not enriched in complex milk lipids to match lower end of breast milk levels .This formula is on on par with China formulas currently on the market. Recommended volume consumption of formula in group 2 are identical. Similarly, it is expected that weaning foods will be introduced from 6 months.
Group 1 infants will receive an infant formula and follow-on formula containing rich complex milk lipids.  Group 2 infants will receive an infant formula and follow on formula with the same volume, energy levels, macronutrients and micronutrients as in the group 1, but not enriched in complex milk lipids, but the complex milk lipids levels in group 2 infant formula and follow-on formula match the lower level of breast milk, e.g human mature milk  12 months. 
Linoleic acid and a-linoleic acid are present in both infant formula and follow-on formula for both intervention and control products. All products meet FSANZ and GB standard requirements for infant and follow-on formula, including fatty acid profile.
All empty formula packaging will be returned to the sites. Feeding questionnaires are filled by parents.

Infants will be allocated to the breast-fed group if their mother is able or willing to breast feed exclusively. If the mother cannot or decide not to breast feed, then the infants will be randomly allocated to one of the 2 formula-fed groups to receive either the intervention formula product or the control formula product. The breast-fed group (breast-feeding exclusively for at least 4-6 months) will act as a reference standard group.
Therefore, there are three groups in total. 2 x control groups (1 breastfed group and 1 control formula group) plus 1 x experimental formula group</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neurodevelopment
The Bayley Scales of Infant and Toddler Development (Bayley II or III) will be used to test neurodeveloping and cognitive function ability of infants. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12 months of age</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neurodevelopment

The Bayley Scales of Infant and Toddler Development (Bayley II or III) will be used to test neurodeveloping and cognitive function ability of infants. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months of age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Growth assessed by anthropometry measurements </outcome>
      <timepoint>At birth, 42 days, 4 months, 6 months, 8 months and 12 months of age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gut microbiota, assessed by faecal sample metagenomic sequencing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 42 days and 4 months of age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Short term memory (Chinese version) 

The Bayley Scales of Infant and Toddler Development (Bayley II or III) will be used to test neurodeveloping and cognitive function ability of infants. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months of age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>formula tolerance assessed by feeding survey. This survey was designed for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>42 days, 4 months, 6 months, 8 months and 12 months of age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy full term infants, born at gestational age between 35 and 41 weeks and with a birth body weight between 2500 and 4000 g

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Days</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Days</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Neonates with Apgar score &lt;7
Neonates with a major birth defect or evidence of genetic disease
Preterm infants (less than 35 weeks)
Term infants born less than 2500 g or more than 4000 g.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation) 
Infants exclusively breast-fed for at least 4-6 months will be the reference group. It is expected that weaning foods will be introduced from 6 months in this group.
The 1st group of infants will be allocated to the breast-fed group if their mother is able or willing to breast feed exclusively. If the mother cannot or decide not to breast feed, then the infants will be randomly allocated to one of the 2 formula-fed groups to receive either the intervention formula product or the control formula product.
This is a randomized, controlled, double blind clinical trial stratified for gender, of 2 parallel groups; one formula fed experimental group (n=120) and one formula fed control  group (n=120). We do not know which group would be enriched in complex milk lipids until the end of study.  Therefore we only know the infants who are breast-fed or formula-fed. 

</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Power calculation is included and is based on the design of a similar recent study by Timby et al 2014.. The power calculation assumes an effect-size of 4 points (increase) and a standard deviation of 9 points on the Bayley's III test with a power of 90% and significance of 5%, and a dropout rate of 25%. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>27/01/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>5/10/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>423</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/10/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Fujian Province</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Charles Sturt University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Boorooma Street,
North Wagga Wagga
NSW
2650
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Charles Sturt University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Boorooma Street,
North Wagga Wagga
NSW
2650
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Fonterra</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Private Bag 11029, Palmerston North 4442, Dairy Farm Road, Fitzherbert, Palmerston North, New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>N/A</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Xiamen University </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>No 422, Siming South Road, Xiamen, Fujian, China. 361005 </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>China</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Complex milk lipids are present in human breast milk and are thought to play an important role in neonatal development. Infant formula based on vegetable oils has lower complex lipid content than breast milk. The proposed study will test if enrichment of infant formula and follow-on formula using dairy ingredients with enhanced levels of complex milk lipids to match the upper end of breast milk levels will have a positive impact on neonatal growth and development.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Ethic Committee, Xiamen University </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>No 422, Siming South Road, Xiamen, Fujian, China. 361005 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/08/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bing Wang</name>
      <address>Charles Sturt University
Locked Bag 588
Boorooma Street
NSW 2678
Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 69334549</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 69332991</fax>
      <email>biwang@csu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bing Wang</name>
      <address>Charles Sturt University
Locked Bag 588
Boorooma Street
NSW 2678
Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 69334549</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>biwang@csu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Bing Wang</name>
      <address>Charles Sturt University
Locked Bag 588
Boorooma Street
NSW 2678
Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 69334549</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 69332991</fax>
      <email>biwang@csu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Kristie-Lee Addyman</name>
      <address>Charles Sturt University
Locked Bag 588
Boorooma Street
NSW 2678
Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61269334556</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kaddyman@csu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>