<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371806">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001553460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised Controlled Trial to compare initiation of peritoneal dialysis at one or two weeks post radiological catheter insertion</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised Controlled Trial to compare initiation of peritoneal dialysis at one or two weeks post radiological catheter insertion</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RadCath Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Peritoneal Dialysis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Kidney Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1 - Participants will have peritoneal dialysis initiated at 1 (+/- 2 days) week post catheter insertion
Arm 2 - Participants will have peritoneal dialysis initiated at 2 (+/- 2 days) weeks post catheter insertion
The intervention will be delivered in the renal unit under trained nursing staff. 
The progress will be reviewed on a regular basis during the dialysis sessions and at clinic appointments.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group is arm 2 which will have their dialysis commenced at the standard time of 2 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peritoneal Fluid Leaks will be assessed by physical exam</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 180 days of peritoneal dialysis catheter insertion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PD related infection - Exit site and/or tunnel and/or peritonitis will be assessed by physical exam, skin swab, blood cultures and or peritoneal fluid microscopy/culture/stain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 180 days of peritoneal dialysis catheter insertion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite of all PD catheter related complications and Haemodialysis (HD) requirements and associated complications. PD catheter related complications include fluid leaks, infection, cuff erosion, cuff extrusion, failure to establish PD successfully (may be due to blockage, fibrin plug or outflow obstruction), delayed wound healing, haematoma, catheter revision or replacement, conversion to HD, HD related events, allergic reactions, hospitalisation for any reason with cause recorded as related to either surgery or start-up of dialysis, and death during the study period.  The secondary outcomes will be assessed by physical exam and review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be recorded for 180 days post PD catheter insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	End Stage Kidney Disease
2.	Patients in whom PD is the dialysis modality of preference
3.	Patients already on haemodialysis and/or require dialysis initiation within 2 weeks of PD catheter insertion 
4.	Age &gt;18
5.	Able to give informed consent 
6.     Participants must be scheduled for radiological Tenckhoff catheter insertion</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Patients with a history of psychological illness or condition which interferes with their ability to understand or comply with the requirements of the study.
2.	Recent (within 1 month) acute infection.
3.	Patients in whom PD is contraindicated or not desired.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>224</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Butterfield St &amp; Bowen Bridge Rd, Herston QLD 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Butterfield St &amp; Bowen Bridge Rd, Herston QLD 4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Dialysis is the artificial replacement of a patients non-functioning kidney which has been damaged due to medical disease. There are two main techniques, peritoneal dialysis (PD) and haemodialysis (HD). PD requires the insertion of a catheter into the patients abdomen prior to use. Historically this has been done surgically, however a new technique is for it to be inserted radiologically, which appears to have several benefits including decreased waiting times, inpatient admissions and hospital expenses. The main purpose of this trial is to determine the optimal time to use these catheters post radiological insertion which no study has previously investigated.
The most appropriate time to initiate dialysis after radiological insertion of Tenckhoff catheters is not clear in the literature. There is the possibility of peritoneal dialysis (PD) complications such as leakage and infection if dialysis is started too soon after insertion. However, much morbidity and expense could be saved by reducing dependency on haemodialysis (HD) by earlier initiation of PD post catheter insertion. Previous studies are observational and mostly compare surgically inserted catheters and their immediate or delayed use. The primary objective is to determine the safest and shortest time interval between radiological placement of a Tenckhoff catheter and starting PD.
The goal is to compare initiation of PD at one and two weeks post radiological Tenckhoff catheter insertion. This will be done by measuring the incidence of PD complications in a period post PD commencement as well as the HD associated problems during the same period if bridging HD is performed.
This is a randomised controlled trial of patients who will start PD after radiological insertion of a Tenckhoff catheter at Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital (RBWH) and who meet the inclusion criteria. The patients will be randomised to one of two treatment groups. Group 1 will start PD 7 +/-2 days after Tenckhoff catheter insertion and group 2 at 14 +/-2 days. Nurses and physicians will be blinded to the randomised allocation. The primary end point is the complication rate (leaks and infection) after initiation of PD.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Butterfield St &amp; Bowen Bridge Rd, Herston QLD 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QRBW/19</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nigel Mott</name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield St &amp; Bowen Bridge Rd, Herston QLD 4029 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 407657121 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Nigel.Mott@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dwarakanathan Ranganathan</name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield St &amp; Bowen Bridge Rd, Herston QLD 4029 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36468576</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dwarakanathan.ranganathan@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dwarakanathan Ranganathan</name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield St &amp; Bowen Bridge Rd, Herston QLD 4029 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36468576</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dwarakanathan.ranganathan@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James Lee</name>
      <address>Redcliffe Hospital, Anzac Avenue, Redcliffe, QLD, Australia 4020</address>
      <phone>+61 450006561</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jamesaaronslee@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>