<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368372">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/04/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000392561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical trial of a take-home rehabilitation device for vestibular patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Incremental vestibular rehabilitation training in patients with partial peripheral vestibular dysfunction: balance function outcomes compared between current and proposed rehabilitation techniques.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1168-9612</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Reduced vestibulo-ocular reflex response (due to peripheral vestibular dysfunction only).</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Ear</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other ear disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We have designed and built a small, non-invasive, safe, battery-driven, portable, head-mounted programmable device that patients will use to train at home (i.e., with the dosage / compliance recorded). Both control and intervention groups will be asked to perform current best practice rehabilitation, which are home-based exercises 5 times daily for a total of 30-40 min per day, with changes in exercises from week to week. After these exercises, both groups will perform the device or placebo intervention for 15 minutes. Patient's will be asked to continue current best practice and intervention exercises for at least the minimum duration of the study, i.e., 12 months. 

The intervention exercise consists of the patient rapidly turning their head leftwards by a small angle (i.e., a 5-10 degree turn), then slowly returning the head back to neutral, followed by a similarly rapid rotation rightwards. The patients task will be to visually track a moving laser dot target on the wall in front of them while they keep turning their head. The basis of incremental adaptation training is that tracking the target starts off easy and gradually gets harder for the patient. This approach has been shown to be more effective at increasing the vestibulo-ocular reflex response compared to tracking a stationary target while turning the head, i.e., a difficult task for vestibular patients. Patients will be educated by one of the researchers listed on our protocol to use the the device during their first (baseline) session at our laboratory,   

In the test group, subjects will use the rehabilitation device at home for 15 minutes once daily performing the new incremental adaptation technique we developed. In the control group, subjects will also use the rehabilitation device at home for 15 minutes once daily; however, the device will project a stationary visual target, so that the training is identical to one of the exercises performed in current best practice.

A log is automatically maintained on the device to record compliance, whereas patients must manually record their compliance to current best practice via diary. Patients will be asked to bring their diary with them to each monthly visit to our laboratory.     </interventions>
    <comparator>The rehabilitation device is set in a mode that results in training identical to current best practice.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vestibulo-ocular reflex (VOR) gain

Head impulse Test (HIT): A head impulse consists of a manual, passive, unpredictable, head rotation with peak-acceleration 3000deg/s/s. For this test eye movements will be measured using either the scleral search coil or video-oculography technique.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: at baseline and once per month for at least 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dizziness Handicap Inventory (DHI) Score
Questionnaire: Activities of Daily Living</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: at baseline and once per month for at least 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait Stability scores

Using an established method (Menz et al., 2003ab), linear accelerations and rotations of the body and head will be measured along three orthogonal axes (vertical, antero-posterior and medio-lateral) using two tri-axial accelerometers and gyroscopes while subjects walk a 30 m path with eyes open and eyes shut. Acceleration levels (RMS), acceleration variability, step timing variability, and harmonic ratio (indicates smoothness and rhythm of body and head) are the key measures of posture and balance control during locomotion. Gait velocity, cadence are included as covariates in these analyses.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: at baseline and once per month for at least 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dynamic Visual Acuity (DVA) score

Dynamic Visual Acuity Test (DVAT): The DVAT works on a similar principle to the HIT. Head impulses are delivered to the subject. However, here the subjects task is to identify the orientation (up, down, left, right) of an optotype (the letter E) presented at different visual acuity levels. The DVAT measures the impact of vestibular hypofunction on visual acuity. An improvement in visual acuity, with no underlying change in vestibular function, would indicate that other oculomotor mechanisms (e.g., the saccadic or smooth pursuit system) are contributing to gaze stabilisation. This improvement could be due to vestibular rehabilitation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: at baseline and once per month for at least 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rotary Chair scores

Rotary Chair Testing (RCT): The rotary chair test is used to measure low-frequency vestibular function without input from the neck muscles. The rotary chair provides a well-controlled rotary stimulus that would be difficult to perform manually.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: at baseline and once per month for at least 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Falls Risk

A physiological screen of function related to balance control that is associated with falls (Lord et al., 2003) will be applied. The five tests are:
1. Visual Contrast Sensitivity assessed using the Melbourne Edge Test. 
2. Proprioception measured with a lower limb-matching task. 
3. Quadriceps strength measured isometrically in the dominant leg while seated with the hip and knee at 90 deg flexion. 
4. Simple reaction time measured using a light stimulus and a finger-press as the response. 
5. Postural sway standing on foam with eyes open: this is measured as a component of the comprehensive balance tests.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: at baseline and once per month for at least 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Standing Balance scores

Postural sway and Centre of Pressure excursions will be measured using a CODA motion analysis system integrated with two Kistler force plates. RMS and peak-to-peak in the antero-posterior and lateral directions (markers at pelvis, C7 and head) will be obtained while participants stand for 30 s, each on rigid floor and foam rubber, each with eyes open and shut. These combinations will provide markers of visual, proprioceptive and vestibular contributions to sway stabilisation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point: at baseline and once per month for at least 12 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must have a well-defined, isolated, peripheral, vestibular lesion, but are otherwise healthy. These lesions could be due to: Menieres disease, vestibular neuritis, labyrinthitis, vestibular neurectomy, semicircular canal plugging, superior canal dehiscence and post-intratympanic gentamicin treatment. Participants can have complete or incomplete unilateral lesions, or incomplete bilateral lesions, i.e., they must have some residual peripheral vestibular function. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People not fluent in English are unsuitable for these studies and will not be recruited.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients seen at Royal North Shore Medical Centre (RNSMC) (Dr. Cremer’s private practice), Prince of Wales Private Hospital (POWPH) or Blacktown Neurology (Dr. Watson’s private practices) with a well-defined, isolated, peripheral vestibular lesion, but otherwise healthy, may participate in this study.

Prior to seeing their treating physician (Drs Cremer or Watson) potential patient participants, as determined by the physician support staff, will be handed a flyer with my laboratory contact details. ONLY if the patient initiates a discussion about the study will the treating physician discuss the study with their patient. ONLY if the patient makes first contact with my laboratory will the other personnel listed on our protocol discuss the study with them.

We will offer to email/mail the potential participant a copy of the Participation Information Sheet and Consent Form. Prior to the first laboratory test session one of the personnel listed on our protocol will obtain consent, including: explaining the tests and risks involved, making clear that the participant can withdraw at any time from the study, answer questions, and witness the participant signature.  

Participants will be randomly allocated to one of two treatment groups. The person involved in programming the rehabilitation device for each patient will also be responsible for running the group randomization software and maintaining the confidential patient group list. The patient and the researchers recruiting, performing the testing and processing the data will be blinded as to whether the patient is in the control or test group. Thus, allocation involves contacting the holder of the allocation schedule, i.e., the rehabilitation device programmer, who is at the central administration site and does not interact with the participants.   </concealment>
    <sequence>The randomized controlled trial will conform to CONSORT guidelines. We will implement permuted block randomization using software. Randomization will be stratified to create 4 equal-sized groups: control and test groups (i.e., 2 groups), unilateral injury and bilateral injury sub-groups (i.e., 2 sub-groups) (2 x 2 = 4 groups in total).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Between groups comparisons of in-between and final test performance for the continuously-scored primary and secondary outcome measures will be made using General Linear Models (ANCOVA) controlling for pre-rehabilitation performance and other potential confounders. All analyses will be by intention to treat and Bonferroni corrections will be made to adjust for multiple statistical testing. The effect of our rehabilitation technique on each outcome measure will be established using multivariate modelling techniques including multiple linear and logistic regression analyses. This analysis will determine whether our rehabilitation technique will provide significant, objective, short- and long-term benefits to patients.

Power analysis indicates that 15 subjects per group allows us to detect a 15% VOR response (gain) increase due to vestibular adaptation training (mean1= 0.5, mean2 = 0.575, standard deviation = 0.1, a = 0.05, power = 0.9, 2-sided test). From previous experience we foresee that most patients (~75%) will participate for the duration of study. However, as a contingency for dropout, we will enrol 20 subjects per group ([control or incremental] x [unilateral or bilateral], so 4 groups of 20). To fully determine functional changes due to vestibular rehabilitation complete data sets from 40 patients with unilateral and 40 patients with bilateral peripheral vestibular hypofunction will be needed. So we estimate a total of 80 subjects will be required. However, we would like to recruit up to 120 participants in case our 75% continuing participation rate is an underestimation. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/09/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/04/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2148 - Blacktown</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Neuroscience Research Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>139 Barker St, 
Randwick, 2031, NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council of Australia (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A randomized controlled trial will be conducted in 120 people with injury to their balance organ and/or balance nerve. We have developed a safe, non-invasive, incremental rehabilitation technique that after a single 15 minute session increases the vestibular (balance) response many times more than current best practice, which takes 6-8 weeks to see any increase. We have shown that the technique can be successfully administered using a small portable device under a controlled setting. This project will determine the longterm (minimum of 12 months) changes in vestibulo-ocular reflex (VOR), balance and gait function in vestibular patients that train once daily (i.e., fixed dosage).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Peer-reviewed papers:
1.	Migliaccio AA, Schubert MC. Pilot study of a new rehabilitation tool: Improved unilateral short-term adaptation of the human angular vestibulo-ocular reflex. Otol. Neurotol. 2014 Dec;35(10): e310-6.
2.	Migliaccio AA, Schubert MC. Unilateral adaptation of the human angular vestibulo-ocular reflex. J Assoc Res Otolaryngol. 2013 Feb;14(1):29-36.]

Conference Talks:
1.	Migliaccio AA Vestibulo-ocular reflex adaptation and compensation mechanisms. Federation of European Neuroscience Societies (FENS) satelite meeting, Como, Italy 2014. (Invited keynote speaker, all fees waived, July 2014)
2.	Migliaccio AA The effect of retinal image error update rate on human vestibulo-ocular reflex gain adaptation. Barany, Buenos Aires, Argentina 2014.(May 2014)
3.	Migliaccio AA Functional vestibular rehabilitation using a promising new technique. Sydney Alliance for Healthcare, Research and Teaching (SAHRT), Sydney, Australia 2013 (Invited symposium speaker)
4.	Migliaccio AA A new technique to increase the human vestibulo-ocular reflex gain that has potential for vestibular rehabilitation. Neuro-otology society of Australia (NOTSA) conference, Sydney, Australia, 2014. (Invited speaker, all fees waived.)
5.	Migliaccio AA Unilateral incremental adaptation of the vestibulo-ocular reflex: A promising method for improving gaze stability after a unilateral vestibular lesion. Neuro-otology society of Australia (NOTSA) conference, Newcastle, Australia 2011.

Conference Posters:
1.	C Todd, P Hubner, P Hubner, M Schubert and A Migliaccio (Presenting). Unilateral Incremental Vestibulo-ocular Reflex Adaptation Training in Normal Subjects. Poster at the FENS Satelite Meeting, Como, Italy 2014. 
2.	C Todd, P Hubner, A Migliaccio (Presenting) and M Schubert. Incremental Vestibulo-ocular Reflex Adaptation Training in Patients with Peripheral Vestibular Hypofunction. Poster at the FENS Satelite Meeting, Como, Italy 2014.
3.	C Todd, P Hubner, P Hubner, M Schubert and A Migliaccio. Dynamic Visual Acuity before and after Unilateral Incremental Vestibulo-ocular Reflex Adaptation Training in Normal Subjects. Poster at the Barany Main Meeting, Beunos Aires, Argentina 2014. 
4.	C Todd, P Hubner, A Migliaccio and M Schubert. Dynamic Visual Acuity before and after Incremental Vestibulo-ocular Reflex Adaptation Training in Patients with Peripheral Vestibular Hypofunction. Poster at the Barany Main Meeting, Beunos Aires, Argentina 2014.
5.	AA Migliaccio (presenting) and MC Schubert. Unilateral adaptation of the human angular vestibulo-ocular reflex. Poster at the Association for Research in Otololaryngology Midwinter Meeting, Baltimore, USA 2013.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW Research Ethics &amp; Compliance Support
Level 3, Rupert Myers Building (South)
The University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/05/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC14319</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Americo Migliaccio</name>
      <address>Balance and Vision Laboratory
Neuroscience Research Australia
139 Barker St
Randwick, 2031, NSW
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93991030</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.migliaccio@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Americo Migliaccio</name>
      <address>Balance and Vision Laboratory
Neuroscience Research Australia
139 Barker St
Randwick, 2031, NSW
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93991030</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.migliaccio@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Americo Migliaccio</name>
      <address>Balance and Vision Laboratory
Neuroscience Research Australia
139 Barker St
Randwick, 2031, NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93991030</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.migliaccio@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>