<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372124">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000205336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can an increase in consumption of dietary fibre improve gut flora profile, bowel habit and sense of wellbeing in healthy adults? </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparing the effects of diets low and moderate in natural prebiotic fibre on gut flora profile, laxation and sense of wellbeing in healthy Australian adults. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>CF14/2904- 2014001593</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>D.MHN.0617</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>gut health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>sense of wellbeing</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>25 healthy volunteers (no pre-existing gastrointestinal disorders) will be recruited into a single-blinded, randomised, cross-over design study of 12 weeks in duration. They will each follow the following three dietary treatments for 3 weeks with a 1 week break between each treatment and 1 week baseline period prior to commencing the first study diet . The three treatments will be consistent with the Australian Dietary Guidelines in terms of recommended foods and serves of foods and will differ only in relation to the types of carbohydrate containing foods (including grains, legumes, fruits and vegetables) provided to modify intake of naturally occurring indigestible oligosaccharides (which have known prebiotic effects), in the following amounts: 

1. Low prebiotic diet (~4g oligosaccharides/day) 
2. Moderate prebiotic diet (~8g oligosaccharides/day) 
3. High prebiotic diet (~12g oligosaccharides/day) 

The majority of food will be provided to participants for this study and will be prepared in Monash University's commercial kitchen by their research chef. Menu planning will include beef and lamb as recommended in the 'Australian Dietary Guidelines' i.e. 130g every second day (200g uncooked meat). 

Sample study meal plan for one day: 
Low prebiotic diet- 
Breakfast: Cereal (flakes of corn, puffed oats, puffed rice, rice bran, dried cranberries, almonds, sunflower seeds) with milk + tea and/or coffee + orange juice + yoghurt. 
Snack: Banana 
Lunch: Sourdough spelt bread sandwich with ham, cheese and salad + tea and/or coffee + yoghurt with strawberries
Snack: Mix of macadamia, Brazil nuts and pecans 
Dinner: Beef curry (with small amount of onion and garlic) served with rice, vegetables and pita bread. 

Moderate prebiotic diet- 
Breakfast: Cereal (flakes of wheat, rolled oats, dried apple, wheat bran, cashews, sunflower seeds) with milk + tea and/or coffee + apple juice + yoghurt. 
Snack: Nectarine
Lunch: Wholemeal bread sandwich with ham, cheese and salad (including beetroot) + tea and/or coffee + yoghurt with peaches
Snack: Mix of cashew nuts and almonds
Dinner: Beef curry (with moderate amounts of onion and garlic) served with lentil curry, rice, vegetables and pita bread. 

High prebiotic diet- 
Breakfast: Cereal (flakes of amaranth, lupin flakes, wheat bran, dried mango, pistachio nuts) with milk + tea and/or coffee + apple juice + yoghurt. 
Snack: Watermelon
Lunch: Rye bread sandwich with ham, cheese and salad (including beetroot and asparagus) + tea and/or coffee + yoghurt with mango
Snack: Mix of cashew and pistachio nuts
Dinner: Beef curry (with large amounts of onion and garlic) served with lentil curry, rice, vegetables and naan bread. 

Evaluation of dietary adherence: 
This will be checked via direct questioning, via daily diaries into which any food consumed in addition to that supplied will be entered and via assessment of uneaten food. 
Breath hydrogen/methane testing will also evaluate adherence. Hourly breath samples for hydrogen and methane testing will be collected over a one-day period to assess the degree of fermentation occurring with each diet. 



</interventions>
    <comparator>As this is a cross-over study design, participants act as their own control. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Detection and characterisation of gut microbial changes as reflected in collected faecal samples. Analysis will include use of real-time PCR to compare the absolute and relative abundance of bacteria. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Faecal samples collected on three consecutive days during the baseline week and three consecutive days during the third week of each dietary intervention period. In addition, an aliquot from one faecal sample will be taken by participants on the second (or third) day of each faecal collection period using a sampling kit containing a specialised microbial preservative. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in regional gut transit time and luminal pH from mouth to anus measured using a SmartPill device. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Device swallowed on the last day of the second week (day 14) of each dietary intervention period. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in faecal water content measured by weighing faecal sample before and after freeze-drying. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Faecal samples collected on three consecutive days during the baseline week and three consecutive days during the third week of each dietary intervention period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in faecal levels of short chain fatty acids, including butyrate measured using gas-liquid chromatography. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Faecal samples collected on three consecutive days during the baseline week and three consecutive days during the third week of each dietary intervention period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in levels of faecal ammonia and phenols measured by high-performance liquid chromatography. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Faecal samples collected on three consecutive days during the baseline week and three consecutive days during the third week of each dietary intervention period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Changes in faecal calprotectin concentration measured by commercially available ELISA (Buhlman) as a quantitative marker of intestinal inflammation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Faecal samples collected on three consecutive days during the baseline week and three consecutive days during the third week of each dietary intervention period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in gastrointestinal symptoms (including bloating, wind, abdominal pain and fatigue) assessed using a 100mm visual analogue scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily throughout the baseline and dietary intervention periods.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in stool frequency/consistency assessed using the Bristol stool chart and recorded on a 4-point (frequency) and 7-point (consistency) likert scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily during baseline and dietary intervention periods. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in breath hydrogen and methane levels as assessed using a QuinTron breath track Analyser instrument. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Samples collected during one 12-hour testing period on the second last day of the second week (day 13) of each dietary intervention period. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in cognitive function assessed by Subtle Cognitive Impairment Test (SCIT). </outcome>
      <timepoint>On final day of each dietary intervention period. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in psychological state assessed using the 80 item State-Trait-Personality Inventory (STPI) and 21 item Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (DASS 21). </outcome>
      <timepoint>On final day of baseline and each dietary intervention period. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in levels of fatigue measured using the 40 item Daily Fatigue Impact Scale (D-FIS). </outcome>
      <timepoint>On final day of baseline and dietary intervention periods. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Generally healthy adults with no pre-existing gastrointestinal conditions (e.g. Irritable bowel syndrome, coeliac disease, Crohn's disease or Ulcerative colitis) 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Currently or recently (last 4 weeks) been taking antibiotics, probiotics or prebiotics as supplements or added into food types 
- Being treated with medication known to affect intestinal transit (such as laxatives or hypomotility agents) 
- They have any gastrointestinal disease (e.g. Irritable bowel syndrome, coeliac disease, Crohn's disease or Ulcerative colitis) 
- They suffer from an eating disorder 
- Are pregnant or planning a pregnancy 
- Vegetarian </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The power calculations for this study were based on the smallest effect size of bacterial abundance (R. torques) and the most conservative statistical procedures that could be used: a linear mixed model analysis for crossover designs with one repeated measure. The alpha (or p) value is set at at 0.001 to allow for Bonferroni corrections for multiple comparisons.  On the basis of linear mixed model analysis for crossover designs, with an alpha level of 0.001, a desired power level of 0.95 and a Cohen's d effect size measure of 1.095, the minimum sample required to complete this study is 24. Assuming a drop-out rate of around 20% this means that ~ 29 people will need to be recruited. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>12/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3004 - St Kilda Road Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wellington Road 
Clayton, VIC 
3800</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Meat &amp; Livestock Australia Limited </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
40 Mount Street 
North Sydney 
NSW, 2060</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to discover new understanding regarding whether an increase in dietary fibre will improve the profile of gut flora (i.e., the micro-organisms that aid digestion), bowel habit and sense of wellbeing. There is strong evidence suggesting dietary fibre is essential for good health. This project aims to understand better the fibre-health relationship.   </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Note: A pilot of this study was conducted in 9 participants using the aforementioned protocol. Due to participants experiencing uncomfortable gastrointestinal side effects on the high prebiotic (~12g/day) diet, this study arm was discontinued and a 2-arm version of the trial continued with only the low and moderate prebiotic dietary interventions. All other aspects of the protocol remained unchanged, however the study length was subsequently reduced from 12 to to 8 weeks in duration. </publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash University
Wellington Road, 
Clayton, VIC 
3800 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF14/2904- 2014001593</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/09/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jane Muir</name>
      <address>Monash University Department of Gastroenterology 
Level 6, The Alfred centre 
99 Commercial Rd 
Melbourne, VIC 
3004 
</address>
      <phone>+610399030274</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jane.muir@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Lyndal McNamara </name>
      <address>Monash University Department of Gastroenterology 
Level 6, The Alfred centre 
99 Commercial Rd 
Melbourne, VIC 
3004 
</address>
      <phone>+610399030269</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lyndal.mcnamara@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jane Muir </name>
      <address>Monash University Department of Gastroenterology 
Level 6, The Alfred centre 
99 Commercial Rd 
Melbourne, VIC 
3004 </address>
      <phone>+610399030274</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jane.muir@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Lyndal McNamara </name>
      <address>Monash University Department of Gastroenterology 
Level 6, The Alfred centre 
99 Commercial Rd 
Melbourne, VIC 
3004 </address>
      <phone>+610399030269</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lyndal.mcnamara@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>