<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371116">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000085370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Treating working memory and decision-making deficits in children following traumatic brain injury.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Treating attention, speed of processing, decision-making, and working memory deficits in children following traumatic brain injury: Implementation of an attention and working memory intervention to improve adaptability and functional outcomes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1185-9761 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acquired Brain Injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Cogmed (RM version) is an adaptive working memory training program designed for children aged 7-15 years.The program involves 25 sessions carried out over approximately 5 weeks. Each session runs for 40- 50 minutes and comprises 8 different games. For the first five days, children train on the same games. On day 6 and every 5th day after this a new game is introduced, replacing one of the existing games.

The treatment group will be administered Cogmed (RM version). 
- During the initial program appointment the coach provide an information statement to set up the program on the participants' home computer or ipad.  At this meeting they will also assign each participant a unique ID number corresponding to the intervention and instruct the parent how to log into  the online video conference platform.
- The coach will provide one weekly support every week of the training, to ensure that the training is progressing well and answer any questions from the families through any one of online video-conferencing platforms. The online video-conference would be scheduled in the initial start- up session with the families and would last for approximately 30 minutes. The coach can monitor the training and compliance by logging into a secure server.  Program compliance can be assessed as the number of sessions completed by each child, and time spent per session will be recorded. 
- The participants' parents will be their Cogmed Aide at home. 
- The intervention will be delivered online. 
- The intervention will include 25 sessions over a period of 5 weeks (i.e. 5 sessions each week). Each session will run for 40-50 minutes. 
- The intervention will run in participants' home under the supervision of their parents.</interventions>
    <comparator>The active control group will be administered Lexia(Registered Trademark) Reading, a program designed to target phonological awareness and phonics skills in reading but has no memory training component.  Children will complete the program at home, and parents are asked to sit with their child during training to encourage task engagement and minimise environmental distractions.  The program runs for 30 minutes per day, 5 days per week over the 8 week intervention period.  

-The active control program will be administered online. 
-The Coach will monitor child's adherence to the program by monitoring the training and compliance by logging into a secure server of the program.
-The Coach will provide weekly support, to ensure that the training is progressing well and answer any questions from the families through any one of online video-conferencing platforms. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decision-Making .

Problem-Solving/Decision-Making Task ( Klayman, 1985). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, immediately post-intervention and at 6 months post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Working Memory 

 Automated Working Memory Assessment: Short-Form (AWMA: Alloway, 2012)</outcome>
      <timepoint>AWMA: Screening(2 sub tests), pre-intervention (remaining 2 sub tests), immediately post-intervention and at 6 months post-intervention. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Academic performance

Wide Range Achievement Test 4 (WRAT-4 : Wilkinson &amp; Robertson, 2006)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, immediately post-intervention and at 6months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adaptive Behaviour 

Brief Rating Inventory of Executive Function (BRIEF: Gioia et al., 2000)


D. </outcome>
      <timepoint>BRIEF: Screening, Pre- intervention, Immediately post-intervention and at 6months post intervention.



</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life

Paediatric Quality of Life Inventory - Parent version (Peds QL : Varni, 1999)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, immediately post-intervention and at 6months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social Skills 

Social Skills Improvement System Rating Scales- Teacher (SSIS Rating Scale-Teacher: Gresham &amp; Elliott, 2008).

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, immediately post-intervention and at 6-months follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adaptive Behaviour 

Child Behaviour Checklist (CBCL:Achenbach et al., 2001)</outcome>
      <timepoint>CBCL : Pre-intervention, immediately post-intervention and at 6 months post-intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adaptive Behavior

Teacher Rating Form (TRF: Achenbach et al., 2001)</outcome>
      <timepoint>TRF : Pre-intervention, immediately post-intervention and at 6 months post-intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Working Memory: Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children V: Working Memory sub tests (WISC-V: Wechsler, 2016)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention and at 6 months post-intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decision-Making : The Beads Task (Huq et al., 1988)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-intervention, immediately post-intervention, and at 6 month post-intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) attend primary and secondary school and be between the ages of 7-15 at the time of the intervention; 
(2) sustained an TBI where there was head trauma associated with a) altered consciousness, as defined by Glasgow Coma Score and/or post traumatic amnesia, or b) intra-cranial abnormalities on brain scan, and, 
(3) injury from acute stage onwards;and,
(4) evidence of  reduced working memory or executive dysfunction at screening (1 SD below the mean)
(5) IQ&gt;70</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) non-fluency in English; 
(2) IQ below 70 at screening 
(3) other previously documented neurological or learning difficulties diagnosis; 
(4) severe sensory or physical impairment that affects their capacity to attend mainstream school and complete the training program: and,
(5) families and/or primary caregivers who are unable to support/assist their child through to the completion of the intervention program. This will be determined through discussions with primary caregivers/parents during the recruitment phase.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>For each intervention program, planned comparisons, using the SPSS General Linear Model procedure will compare pre- and post-intervention performance on the outcome measures and will examine age and sex effects. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/05/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>74</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/01/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cathy Catroppa</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Psychologist/Senior Research Fellow
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
Royal Childrens Hospital
50, Flemington RD, Parkville Victoria, 3052
Australia.
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Collier Charitable Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>31/570 Bourke St, 
Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Vicki Anderson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Head of Psychology, RCH Mental Health
Theme Director, Clinical Sciences Research, MCRI
The Royal Children's Hospital Melbourne
50 Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Celia Godfrey</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Psychologist/Research Fellow
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
Royal Childrens Hospital
50 Flemington Rd, Parkville Victoria, 3052 
Australia.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Nikita Tuli</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PhD Candidate
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
Royal Childrens Hospital
50 Flemington Rd, Parkville Victoria, 3052
Australia.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In children, acquired brain injury (ABI), and in particular traumatic brain injury (TBI), represents a common interruption to the course of normal development, with both international and local statistics citing an annual rate of 250300 per 100,000 children (Kraus, 1995). 

Working memory refers to the capacity to temporarily store information for use in everyday activities (Alloway et al., 2006). Decision-Making is conceived as a complex interplay of high-level cold cognitive processes such as working memory, information processing, problem-solving, and hot emotional processes (Cassotti et al., 2011;  Reimann and Bechara, 2010). Efficient  working memory and decision-making abilities are  essential as they underpin ones performance in functional skill areas such as academic, adaptive, behavioural and social domains (Catroppa &amp; Anderson, 2006; Ganesalingam et al, 2011; Gathercole et al., 2006; Mandalis et al, 2007; Muscara et al., 2008). 

Using a prospective, longitudinal design, adaptive abilities, behaviour, educational progress and everyday memory skills were investigated acutely post-injury and again at 12 and 30 months post-injury.  Results suggested a strong association between injury severity and outcomes across all domains.With regard to social outcomes following childhood brain injury, deficits have been reported in many areas of social functioning and communication style, often resulting in low self-esteem, isolation, high rates of psychiatric disorder, criminal behaviour, and unemployment, and therefore poor integration into society (Anderson et al., 2009)

The overall aim of the proposed study is to enhance working memory and decision-making abilities and therefore potentially strengthen academic, social, behavioural and  improving quality of life for children and adolescents post traumatic brain injury (TBI).  

To achieve this aim, the objectives of the proposed study are:
(i) To evaluate the effectiveness of Cogmed using a randomized controlled trial (RCT) to investigate improvements in  working memory and decision-making, in children post-TBI, compared to children in an active control group.
(ii) To determine whether these improvements in working memory and decision-making generalise into other areas of function and so also improve academic,social, behavioural, and quality of life outcomes.

It is hypothesized that 
(i) Compared to children in the active control group, those children receiving Cogmed will display better  working memory and decision-making skills immediately post-intervention and at 6 months post-intervention.
(ii) Improvements in working memory and decision-making will result in improvements in functional areas such as academic, social, behavioural and quality of life outcomes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> Research Ethics &amp; Governance. The Royal Children's Hospital. Melbourne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics &amp; Governance
The Royal Children's Hospital Melbourne
50 Flemington Road, Parkville,  
3052, Victoria
Australia

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>35181F</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/04/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371116-35181F Amendment Approval_Ethics and Governance (11.04.2017).pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Cathy Catroppa</name>
      <address>Psychologist/Research Fellow
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road, Parkville, Victoria, 3052
Australia. </address>
      <phone>+61 03 99366638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathy.catroppa@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nikita Tuli</name>
      <address>PhD Candidate
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road, Parkville, Victoria, 3052
Australia. </address>
      <phone>+61 03 99366395</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nikita.tuli@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Cathy Catroppa </name>
      <address>Psychologist/Research Fellow
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road, Parkville, Victoria, 3052
Australia. </address>
      <phone>+61 03 99366638</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cathy.catroppa@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nikita Tuli</name>
      <address>PhD Candidate
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Road, Parkville, Victoria, 3052
Australia. </address>
      <phone>+61 03 99366395</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nikita.tuli@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>