<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368465">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000607572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cabrini Scribe Trial - a pilot study of the relationship between emergency department scribes and emergency physician productivity using locally trained, Australian scribes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study of the relationship between Australian trained emergency department scribes and emergency physicians productivity</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1169-8051</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>emergency physician efficiency
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>medical scribe training costs</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A scribe or scribes will be trained on a 25-30 hour web-based, American training program in August 2015 ("The ultimate medical scribe handbook and training course - Aaron Thompson"), followed by working as a trainee medical scribe at Cabrini Emergency Department with an Emergency Physician Trainer. They will take notes as directed and will assist the physician with clerical tasks as directed. Once they achieve competency they will work with an Emergency physician or physicians at Cabrini Emergency Department. They will work with the trainer from September 1st 2015 to November 30th 2015 and with the physicians from December 1st 2015 to May 31st 2016.</interventions>
    <comparator>The same emergency physician trainer will carry out their usual work without the assistance of a scribe which includes their usual note taking and clerical duties from January 1st 2015 to May 31st 2016. (including all shifts worked without a scribe - they will work some scribed shifts and some un-scribed shifts during the scribe trial period)

There will be another control group which is the emergency physicians not enrolled in the study group who work at Cabrini permanently and are not authors of the study or administrators from January 1st 2015 to May 31st 2016.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Data on trainer physician and physician patients seen per hour in similar circumstances at the same Emergency Department in close time proximity to the intervention sampling.
Mean and standard deviation of the number of patients seen by each physician per hour.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intervention:
Trainer physician: September 1st to november 30th 2015
Physician/s: December 1st 2015 to May 31st 2016
Control: January 1st to August 31st 2015</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of shifts required for the scribe to be able to work independently, measured using a learner competency scale after each trainee shift, assessed by the physician trainer</outcome>
      <timepoint>September 1st to november 30th 2015
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the cost of training a scribe - measured by the cost of educational tools and the cost in reduced productivity in terms of patients per hour for the physician trainer and billings per hour for the physician trainer</outcome>
      <timepoint>August 1st to november 30th 2015
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean billing rates per patient - measured by including medicare fee rates for consultations and procedures in the ED: facility fees excluded, consumables excluded, gap fees excluded, pathology and radiology fees excluded, ED admission fees excluded</outcome>
      <timepoint>september 1st 2015 to May 2016</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>staff and patient satisfaction regarding the scribe - measured informally by spontaneous and requested feedback
</outcome>
      <timepoint>September 1st 2015 to May 30th 2016</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>patient wait times</outcome>
      <timepoint>door-to-doc, from Sept 1st 2015 to May 30th 2015</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>total patient time in the Emergency Department</outcome>
      <timepoint>door-to-discharge time, from Sept 1st 2015 to May 30th 2015</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>time per shift that the Emergency Department is on ambulance bypass/diversion</outcome>
      <timepoint>total bypass time / total shift time in minutes, from Sept 1st 2015 to May 30th 2015</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>complaints - any written or verbal complaints received about the scribe/scribe program</outcome>
      <timepoint>from Sept 1st 2015 to May 30th 2015</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patient encounters:
All patients seen during scribed shifts and scribed patient encounters during the trial period including any where the scribe was supposed to be present but wasn't. If the scribe was asked to leave an encounter by the patient or physician the encounter will be included in the analysis.

Scribe:
The scribe/s enrolled to participate will be all those hired to train and work as scribes at Cabrini ED during the study period.

Physicians:
FACEMs working on a permanent full-time or part-time contract at Cabrini Emergency Department</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>FACEMs unwilling to work with a scribe or unwilling to consent to the study
FACEMs working less than 1 shift per week
Primary investigator of the study
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Phase 1 of the study - training the scribes, will remain unchanged. When the scribes reach competency (defined by a modified Anghoff scale grading after each shift - receiving 3 competent shift gradings in a row) they will be randomly allocated to physicians who are eligible enrolment. 

Blocks of time, chosen in advance for containing at least 2 eligible physicians per block are allocated a scribe (e.g. Monday late shift). The same trained scribe regularly works this shift. The physician the scribe is allocated to each shift is chosen randomly (blinded random allocation by computer program) (e.g. next Monday late shift - 3 eligible physicians are rostered to work, the computer allocates the scribe to physician B).

All physicians eligible for the study will be asked to consent to participate.
Those choosing to participate will be required to complete a 1-2 hour on-line training module in how to use a scribe effectively. Physicians will then be asked to dial-in to a training session to offer them the opportunity to ask questions about how to use a scribe prior to proceeding to randomisation.

Participating physicians will then all be included in the intervention group. The intervention group will be allocated scribes for some of their shifts. Two control groups will be formed. 
1. Participating physicians working shifts without being allocated a scribe. 
2. Ineligible physicians (for this study) who work at the study institution other than those that declined to give permission for their data to be analysed.

All physician productivity data will then be collected.
Three final groups will be analysed.
1. control group not receiving a scribe
2. intervention group with a scribe
3. intervention group working shifts without a scribe</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The scribe will be allocated to an emergency physician working at Cabrini ED. The physicians that don't receive a scribe will form the control group for the same time period.
The scribe will work allocated shifts with the physician they have been paired with. This may be a proportion of the total shifts worked by that physician or it may be all the shifts worked by that physician. This will depend on the availability and compatibility of the rosters and total work time of the physician and the scribe.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>we will look for a minimum effect size of 15% rather than 20%, all else will remain unchanged</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>24/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>150</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/06/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Cabrini Hospital - Malvern - Malvern</hospital>
    <postcode>3144 - Malvern</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Katie Walker</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Emergency Department
Cabrini Hospital
183 Wattletree Rd
Malvern
3144 
VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Equity Trustees Limited
(AFSL No. 240975)
funds administered by equity trustees on behalf of several donors
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 575 Bourke Street 
Melbourne Victoria 3000 Australia </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Michael Ben-Meir</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Emergency Department
Cabrini Hospital
183 Wattletree Rd
Malvern
3144 
VIC</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Margaret Staples</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Monash Department of Clinical Epidemiology
Cabrini Hospital
Department of Epidemiology and Preventative medicine
183 Wattletree Rd
malvern 
VIC 3144</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr David Phillips</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Finance Department
Cabrini Hospital
183 Wattletree Rd
Malvern
3144 
VIC</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mr Matthew Johnson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Cabrini Institute
Department of Education
154 Wattletree Rd
Malvern
3144 VIC</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Hamish Rodda</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Emergency Department
Cabrini
183 Wattletree Rd
Malvern 
3144
VIC</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Diana Egerton-Warburton</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Emergency Department
Monash medical centre
246 Clayton Rd
Clayton
3168</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ian Turner</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Cabrini ED
183 Wattletree Rd
Malvern
3144
vic</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Prof Danny Liew</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Epidemiology and Preventative Medicine
Monash University
The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Rd
Melbourne
VIC
3004
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is a rising medical cost base in emergency medicine. There is a rising seniority of medical staff required to safely perform the role of physician in an emergency department. The currently accepted productivity of a FACEM is one patient per hour. Much of this time is spent writing and printing notes, faxing documents and contacting physicians. None of this work requires the skill set of an emergency physician and there is opportunity for work substitution, performed by a well-trained medical scribe or secretary. 

A pilot Cabrini ED study using an American trained and experienced scribe showed emergency physician productivity improvements of around 30%. A second larger Cabrini ED study, again using an American trained and experienced scribe showed variable improvements, overall an 18% productivity improvement (submitted for publication currently). There were no major safety/quality/risk issues with the use of these scribes.

This offers emergency physicians the opportunity to increase productivity without compromising quality. The next step in using scribes is to establish whether it is possible to train local Australian scribes to perform the same role with the same level of competence as their USA counterparts and what the cost of this training will be.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Publications:
An economic evaluation of the costs of training a medical scribe to work in Emergency Medicine, Emerg Med J, Walker K et al, June 28th 2016
10.1136/emermed-2016-205934</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>cabrini HREC, initial submission May 11th 2015</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Cabrini Institute 
154 Wattletree Rd
malvern 
3144
VIC</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Cabrini HREC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katie Walker</name>
      <address>Emergency Department
Cabrini Hospital
183 Wattletree Rd
Malvern
3144, VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 431 272 262</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9508 1501</fax>
      <email>katie_walker01@yahoo.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katie Walker</name>
      <address>Emergency Department
Cabrini hospital
183 Wattletree Rd
Malvern
3144, VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 431 272 262</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9508 1501</fax>
      <email>katie_walker01@yahoo.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katie Walker</name>
      <address>Emergency Department
Cabrini hospital
183 Wattletree Rd
Malvern
3144, VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 431 272 262</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9508 1501</fax>
      <email>katie_walker01@yahoo.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Katie Walker</name>
      <address>Emergency Department
Cabrini Hospital
183 Wattletree Rd
Malvern
3144, VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 431 272 262</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9508 1501</fax>
      <email>katie_walker01@yahoo.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>