<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="307974">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/05/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000452099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessment of lung derecruitment resulting from suction of the endotracheal tube in ventilated preterm infants</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of endotracheal tube suction on lung derecruitment in ventilated preterm infants</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ventilated preterm infants</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention  consists of removal of the flow sensor followed by suctioning via a Bodai suction port using a 6-F catheter in infants on conventional ventilation.  Each suction procedure will consist of approximately and will consist of 2 suction passes and conclude with re-insertion of the flow sensor back into the ventilatory circuit. Only one suction intervention will be measured and the entire procedure will take a maximum of 10 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ventilation distribution using electrical impedance tomography (EIT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>EIT measurements will be taken for 60 seconds before suction, and at 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90 105, 120 minutes post suction. 
A 10 minute EIT measurement will be taken during suction.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physiological parameters such as heart rate (HR), respiratory rate (RR), oxygen saturation (SpO2), blood pressure (BP).
Ventilator parameters using the Draegar ventview program will be downloaded from the ventilator Oxygenation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Ventilator parameters and physiological variables will be downloaded continuously from before suction and continue until 2 hours post suction.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Gestation less than 32 weeks gestation  (i.e. up to and including 31 weeks 6 days gestation)
Less than 7 days of age at onset of endotracheal ventilation
Birth weight of more than 750 grams
Duration of ventilation at enrolment of at least 12 hours
Expected to continue to receive mechanical ventilation before and after at least one episode of airway suction after enrolment
Satisfactory endotracheal tube position has been determined by chest radiograph
Arterial sampling line in situ (umbilical or extremity) 
Parent(s) able and willing to provide informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>7</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Days</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Air leak syndrome (e.g. pneumothorax, pneumomediastinum, pulmonary interstitial emphysema
Lung or cardiovascular anomaly that would substantially affect oxygenation, lung recruitment or regional ventilation, e.g;
o	 cyanotic or other major congenital heart disease (not including Patent Ductus Arteriosus)
o	tracheo-oesphageal fistula
o	space occupying thoracic lesion such as diaphragmatic hernia or eventration, or cystic adenomatoid malformation
Substantial leak around endotracheal tube (e.g.. &gt;50%) precluding accurate non-invasive measurement of respiratory function 
Significant hemodynamic instability  (untreated shock, hypovolemia, hypotension)
Poor skin integrity precluding the use of adhesive electrocardiogram (ECG) electrodes.
Survival considered unlikely (death considered imminent or inevitable).
Both parents of baby under 18 years of age due to the complexities of obtaining consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/11/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/11/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>9/09/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>20</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Judy Hough</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Physiotherapy Department
Mater Health Services
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
Queensland
4101</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australia and New Zealand (ANZ) Trustees Childrens Medical Research Establishment Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 389D
Melbourne 
Victoria
3001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Infants on ventilatory support in neonatal intensive care regularly require suction to clear their airways of secretions. This process entails the introduction of a catheter into the endotracheal tube through which the infant is ventilated to suction the secretions. There are two brief episodes of disconnection from the ventilator (to remove then reinsert the flow measurement device, or pneumotachograph) before and after the suctioning. Although this is a necessary process, some infants experience a reduction in oxygenation possibly due to lung collapse from this procedure. In the past we did not have any good monitoring tool to assess the changes occurring in lung volume during and after suction in ventilated newborn infants. Electrical impedance tomography (EIT) is a new non-invasive lung volume monitoring tool, which is well suited to this purpose. Our study group has shown that EIT measures ventilation distribution highly accurately and gives information on the level of lung inflation in preterm infants. The purpose of the study is to attempt to examine the effect of endotracheal suction on ventilation distribution and lung de-recruitment in preterm infants.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Hough JL, Shearman AD, Liley H, Grant CA, Schibler A. (2014) Lung recruitment after endotracheal suction in ventilated preterm infants measured with EIT. Journal of Paediatrics and Child Health. 50 (11): 884  889. Published online June 2014. doi:10.1111/jpc.12661

Hough JL, Shearman AD, Liley HG, Grant CA, Schibler A (2011) Endotracheal suction procedure leads to transient lung derecruitment in ventilated preterm infants. Oral presentation at the Australian Physiotherapy Conference, Brisbane

Hough J, Shearman A, Liley H, Grant C, Schibler A (2010) Lung derecruitment related to endotracheal suction in ventilated preterm infants. European Respiratory Society, Barcelona Poster 2705</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Health Services</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
QLD
4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/08/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1209M</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
QLD 
4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Judy Hough</name>
      <address>Paediatric Critical Care Research Group
Mater Health Services
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
Queensland
4101
Principal Investigator</address>
      <phone>+61 422404369</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 31631642</fax>
      <email>judyhough@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Judy Hough</name>
      <address>Paediatric Critical Care Research Group
Mater Health Services
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
Queensland
4101
Principal Investigator</address>
      <phone>+61 422404369</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 31631642</fax>
      <email>judyhough@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Judith Hough</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Mater Health Services
Raymond Terrace
South Brisbane
QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>61 422404369</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>judyhough@optusnet.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>