<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372807">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000708358p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>CLinical Evaluation of the FluidVision Mongoose X Accommodating Intraocular Lens for Accommodation Restoration
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Clinical Evaluation of the FluidVision Mongoose X Accommodating Intraocular Lens for Accommodation Restoration in Adults with Cataract</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1192-5993 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>CLEAR</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cataract</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients diagnosed with cataracts in both eyes, who require bilateral cataract extraction by phacoemulsification and are eligible for bilateral IOL implantation.

The study is a prospective, randomized, bilateral, multicenter, subject and assessor-blinded, parallel-control design. In the randomized arm, a 1:1 ratio will be employed for subjects to receive either the investigational AIOL or a commercially available trifocal IOL (active control). The trifocal lens restores vision at more than one distance, by splitting or stretching the light entering the eye. The investigational AIOL is designed to use the eyes natural forces to change the shape and power of the lens, producing an change in lens power when needed. In addition, there is a non-randomized parallel control arm, where the subjects will receive a monofocal IOL. The monofocal lens is a standard replacement lens, which focuses at one distance only, usually set for distance vision. Patients usually must wear glasses or contact lenses after surgery in order to see clearly things that are close to them, such as a newspaper. All arms of the study will enroll the same number of subjects. The parallel control arm will include subjects who fail to satisfy the extra screening criteria that apply only to the randomized arm or who choose not to be randomized. 

Based on the subject biometry, the sponsor will assign each subject a lens that is best suited for the subject to provide optimal results for them. Each intervention provider will be provided in-person hands on implant/explant training and an Instructions for Use document prior to implanting any device at their affiliated clinic/hospital. In addition, each procedure will be attended by a Sponsor appointed proctor.

The intervention is intended to be a single visit outpatient surgery with follow-up visits, also at their affiliated clinic(s), at 1 day, 1 week, 1 month, 3, 6, and 12 months post-surgery, for each treated eye. The study team member assigned to perform visual acuity assessments at each follow-up visit will be masked to the type of IOL that the subject receives. The subject will also be masked to the type of IOL implant used during surgery if the subject is in the randomized arm of the study. The implanting investigator performing the procedure will not be masked to the treatment assignment.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The study is a prospective, randomized, bilateral, multicenter, subject and assessor-blinded, parallel-control design. In the randomized arm, a 1:1 ratio will be employed for subjects to receive either the investigational AIOL or a commercially available trifocal IOL (active control). In addition, there is a non-randomized parallel control arm, where the subjects will receive a monofocal IOL. All arms of the study will enroll the same number of subjects. The parallel control arm will include subjects who fail to satisfy the extra screening criteria that apply only to the randomized arm or who choose not to be randomized. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Monocular Corrected Distance Visual Acuity (CDVA) at 4m (comparison between FluidVision lens and monofocal control lens at 100% contrast) as assessed with the M&amp;S Technologies Clinical Trial Suite System (electronic ETDRS charts).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1, Month 1, Month 3, Month 6, Month 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Monocular Distance Corrected Near Visual Acuity (DCNVA) at 40cm (comparison between FluidVision lens and trifocal control lens), as assessed with the M&amp;S Technologies Clinical Trial Suite System (electronic ETDRS charts).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Month 1, Month 3, Month 6, Month 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CDVA at 4 meters (comparison between FluidVision lens and monofocal control at 10% contrast), as assessed with the M&amp;S Technologies Clinical Trial Suite System (electronic ETDRS charts).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1, Month 1, Month 3, Month 6, Month 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DCIVA at 66cm (comparison between FluidVision lens and trifocal control lens), as assessed with the M&amp;S Technologies Clinical Trial Suite System (electronic ETDRS charts).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Month 3, Month 6, Month 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Monocular DCIVA at 66cm (comparison between FluidVision lens and trifocal control lens) as assessed with the M&amp;S Technologies Clinical Trial Suite System (electronic ETDRS charts).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Month 3, Month 6, Month 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Monocular DCIVA at 66 cm (comparison between with the FluidVision lens and the trifocal control lens at 10% contrast) as assessed with the M&amp;S Technologies Clinical Trial Suite System (electronic ETDRS charts).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Month 3, Month 6, Month 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Monocular DCNVA at 40cm (comparison between the FluidVision lens and the trifocal control lens at 10% contrast) as assessed with the M&amp;S Technologies Clinical Trial Suite System (electronic ETDRS charts).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Month 1, Month 3, Month 6, Month 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Monocular DCNVA at 40cm (comparison between the FluidVision lens and the monofocal control lens) as assessed with the M&amp;S Technologies Clinical Trial Suite System (electronic ETDRS charts).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Month 1, Month 3, Month 6, Month 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Refractive outcomes (comparison between the FluidVision lens and the monofocal control)  as assessed with the M&amp;S Technologies Clinical Trial Suite System (electronic ETDRS charts).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1, Month 1, Month 3, Month 6, Month 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Range of vision between 4m and 40cm (comparison between the FluidVision lens (binocular, as measured by defocus, and the trifocal control lens) as assessed with the M&amp;S Technologies Clinical Trial Suite System (electronic ETDRS charts).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Month 1, Month 3, Month 6, Month 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. At least 50 years of age;
2. Willing and able to comply with schedule for follow-up visits;
3. Subject has read, understood and signed the informed consent form;
4. Subject can read and write English and/or Afrikaans;
5. Eligible for primary intraocular lens implantation for the correction of aphakia following cataract extraction;
6. Corrected distance visual acuity worse than 20/40 in each eye with or without a glare source present OR presence of visually significant lens opacity;
7. Predicted corrected distance visual acuity in both eyes to be 20/32 or better after cataract removal and IOL implantation as determined by potential acuity meter (PAM) or other potential vision tests;
8. Less than or equal to 1.0 diopter (D) of preoperative or predicted post-operative corneal astigmatism;
9. Clear intraocular media other than cataract;
10. Preoperative central endothelial cell density of 2200 cells/mm2 or more;
11. Lens appropriate for the patient is available for the relevant device;
12. Eligible for laser eye corrective procedure (this criterion does not apply to the monofocal arm)
13. Able to undergo second eye surgery 7-80 days after the first eye surgery.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Subject is a member of a vulnerable population as defined in ISO 14155;
2. Current use of medications that may affect accommodation;
3. Current or historic use of systemic medications that may confound the outcome or increase the risk to the subject;
4. Sensitivity to planned study medications;
5. Pregnant, lactating during the course of the investigation, or has another condition with associated fluctuation of hormones that could lead to refractive changes;
6. Has systemic disease that could increase the operative risk or confound the outcome;
7. Ocular conditions that may predispose for future complications;
8. Previous intraocular or corneal surgery in either eye;
9. Diagnosed degenerative visual disorders that are predicted to cause future corrected distance visual acuity worse than 20/32;
10. Conditions that increase the risk of zonular rupture during cataract extraction procedure;
11. Simultaneous participation in other ophthalmic drug or device clinical trial;
12. Pre-operative Anterior Chamber Depth (ACD) less than 2.8 mm (this criterion does not apply to the monofocal arm);
13. Grade 4 cataract in either eye, as assessed according to the Quick Reference Guide (QRG)-8 published by the American Optometric Association.
Intraoperative Exclusion Criteria
14. Do not have an intact capsulorhexis and posterior capsule at the time of cataract extraction and lens implantation;
15. Floppy/weak zonules, incomplete zonules or zonular rupture during cataract extraction;
16. Decentered capsulorhexis of &gt;1.0 mm in relation to the limbus;
17. Posterior capsular opacity observed after cataract extraction;
18. Complicated cataract surgery that prevents attempted implantation of the (A)IOL.
Additional Intraoperative Exclusion Criteria for the FluidVision AIOL
19. Unable to attain and maintain a dilated pupil size greater than or equal to 7 mm in diameter;
20. Capsulorhexis size of less than 5.5 mm or greater than 6.0 mm.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Up to 55 subjects will be enrolled in the parallel-control arm, comprised of subjects who do not pass screening criteria for the randomized arm or who choose not to be randomized. The parallel control arm will receive an Acrysof IQ Monofocal IOL (Model SN60WF). Subjects will be enrolled at up to 15 study sites located in Australia, New Zealand and South Africa. Each study site is expected to enroll an equal number of fully qualified subjects in each of the three (3) cohorts, up to a maximum of 21 subjects.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>165</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>South Africa</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>PowerVision</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>298 Harbor Blvd
Belmont, CA 94002</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>PowerVision, Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>298 Harbor Blvd
Belmont, CA 94002</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this investigation is to compare the safety and effectiveness of the investigational FluidVision MX Accommodating Intraocular Lens (AIOL) to the approved monofocal IOL and trifocal IOL in patients undergoing bilateral cataract extraction and bilateral intraocular lens implantation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
133 Molesworth Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Liited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road Eastwood 
South Australia 5063 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Lawless</name>
      <address>Vision Eye Institute
Level 3, 270 Victoria Avenue,
Chatswood, NSW 2067</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8318 3802</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ashah@powervisionlens.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Bettina Kohler</name>
      <address>PowerVision
298 Harbor Boulevard
Belmont, CA 94002</address>
      <phone>+1 6506209948</phone>
      <fax>+1 6506204607</fax>
      <email>info@powervisionlens.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Bettina Kohler</name>
      <address>PowerVision
298 Harbor Boulevard
Belmont, CA 94002</address>
      <phone>+1 6506209948</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>info@powervisionlens.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>