<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368116">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000353594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Short-Term Effect of Kinesio Taping on The Temperature Distribution at The Site of Application. A Randomized Clinical Trial. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Short-Term Effect of Kinesio Taping on The Temperature Distribution at The Site of Application in healthy volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1167-8773</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Potential lumbar muscular strain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Sixty healthy students of the Medical University of Warsaw will be randomly selected and divided into one of two groups. 
Arm1 will be consisted of 30 participants both sexes with aged 18 to 25 years. In this group, Kinesio Tape ( K-Active Tape produced by Nitto Denko) will be applied over the insertions of the paraspinal multifidus muscles to the L1-L5 spinous processes using the I shape application technique. Tape will be applied without tension during maximal lumbar spinal flexion in a standing position.No tension means applying the tape directly to the skin as it comes off the paper backing

Arm2 will be consisted of 30participants both sexes  with aged 18-25 years. In this group, Matopat Classic adhesive tape, produced by TZMO SA, will be used in a similar fashion.  

The I-strips will be applied in the same manner as in the arm1 on both sides of lumbar region  (l1-l5). All taping applications will be applied in both groups by a certified KT physiotherapist. Nevertheless, the tape applications in experimental (Arm1) and placebo groups (Arm2) will be looked very similar. Only one difference will be color of the tape, blue in the Arm1 and white in the Arm2. The tapes  will be left on the patients skin for the next four days.

The two study groups will be comparable in terms of BMI and age. Only participants with a body mass index below 24 kg/m2 will be excluded in the study to eliminate thermal distortions caused by excess adipose tissue. 

To ensure accurate thermal readings, certain study constraints and conditions will be maintained. European Association o Thermology guidelines  for thermal imaging, preparation of the study protocol, recording and archiving data will be  followed to ensure proper testing conditions. 

Prior to infrared thermal measurements, participants will not ingest any food, drugs, or hot liquids and did not take part in strenuous physical activities. 

</interventions>
    <comparator>In this group, Matopat Classic  non elastic adhesive tape, produced by TZMO SA(Poland) will be applied. The I-strips will be applied in the same manner as in the arm1. on both sides of lumbar region. Only one difference will be color of the tape, blue in the Arm1 and white in the Arm2</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be changes the skin temperature at the site of application tape will be recorded at baseline and after trial. 

Thermograms will be taken three times: prior to application of the tape (1st day), immediately after removal (4th day), and one hour after removal of the tape. Readings will be consistently taken between 10:00 am - 11:00 am to account for changes in body temperature associated with the circadian rhythm. Prior to each reading, participants will be acclimated to the room for around 15 minutes (ambient temperature of 22-25°C with 40-50% humidity). Then, participants will be asked to stand with their upper extremities abducted at 45-90 degrees. The MobIR M8 thermal imaging camera will be positioned 2 meters away from the participant at a perpendicular angle to the lumbar region.
Skin emissivity will set at 0.98</outcome>
      <timepoint> Baseline, and at 4 days after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>none</outcome>
      <timepoint>none</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>healthy volunteers </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>age &lt;18,low back pain accompanied by radicular symptoms, body mass index over 24 kg/m2, wounds and  trauma (l1-l5 area), menstruation cycle ,pregnancy, cold, intolerability of or allergy to kinesio tape  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The experimental (Arm1) and placebo group (Arm2)) allocations will be determined according to randomized codes. 
Main coordinator who will allocate the participants to groups will have 60 opaque, sealed envelopes, each will be contained   a piece of paper marked with code 1 or code 2</concealment>
    <sequence>The experimental  group (Arm1) will receive  code1 and code 2 for placebo  group (Arm2). The participants would select and open an envelope in the presence of a physiotherapist to see the symbol and would then direct the patient to the corresponding group. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size has been computed as follows. We assumed the effect size d=0.90, a err prob = 0.05 and minimum power (1-ß err prob) = 0.92. For the computation of the effect size we took empirical values of mean and standard deviation (SD) for ..t1...... based on the previous studies [1] - value of mean = 33.34 and SD = 1.2 for the t2... group and value of mean = 34.60 and SD = 1.00 for the control group. 
We assumed that the ratio of the t1 group to the control group (allocation ratio) should be 1.0. Computations made with the G*Power 3.0.10 software resulted in the minimum sample size for the treatment group equal to 29 and for the control group equal to 29. In fact the final sample size was 30 and 30 individuals for the t1 and t2 control groups, respectively.

statistical assumptions prepared based on the previous studies [1]"Assessment of the thermal effects of kinesilogy tape application." Fizjoterapia Polska 2008; 8(3):310-316 
t1,t2-temperature
 </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>21/09/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>21/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>95</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>25/09/2015</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>25/09/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Warsaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bartosz Slomka</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Physiotherapy, Rehabilitation Division, II Faculty of Medicine, Medical University of Warsaw,Zwirki i Wigury 61, 02-091 Warsaw,Poland.
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Poland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Witold Rongies</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Physiotherapy, Rehabilitation Division, II Faculty of Medicine, MedicalUniversity of Warsaw, Zwirki i Wigury 61, 02-091 Warsaw,Poland.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Poland</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Janusz Sierdzinski </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Medical Information Technology and Telemedicine Medical University of Warsaw, Banacha 1a, 02-097 Warsaw, Poland;</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Poland</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dorota Laskowska</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Physiotherapy, Rehabilitation Division, II Faculty of Medicine, MedicalUniversity of Warsaw, Poland.
PhD Medical University of Warsaw, Poland.
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Poland</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Pawel Ruszczuk</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Neurosurgery, II Faculty of Medicine, Medical University of Warsaw, Poland
PhD Medical University of Warsaw, Poland</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Poland</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Marta E Worwag </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>II Faculty of Medicine, Medical University of Warsaw, Poland</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Poland</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Sebastian Zdunski</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>AVI Medical Centre, LUX MED Group, Warsaw, Poland</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Poland</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To analyze the effect of Kinesio Taping on the distribution of body heat along the paraspinal multifidus muscles and the area between them at the L1-L5 level when applied to individuals without lower back pain symptoms, as compared to a sham tape application using thermography.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bioethics Committee of the Medical University of Warsaw</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Zwirki i Wigury 61, 02-091 Warsaw, Poland</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>KB/52/2014</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368116-Approval_Bioethics Committee of the Medical University of Warsaw.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Bartosz Slomka</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, Rehabilitation Division, II Faculty of Medicine, MedicalUniversity of Warsaw
PhD Medical University of Warsaw,Zwirki i Wigury 61, 02-091 Warsaw, Poland
</address>
      <phone>+48 022 57 20 920 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>slomka.bartosz@interia.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Bartosz Slomka</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, Rehabilitation Division, II Faculty of Medicine, MedicalUniversity of Warsaw
PhD Medical University of Warsaw,Zwirki i Wigury 61, 02-091 Warsaw, Poland</address>
      <phone>+48 022 57 20 920 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>slomka.bartosz@interia.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Witold Rongies</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy and Rehabilitation
Medical University of Warsaw
</address>
      <phone>+48 604 538 380</phone>
      <fax>+48  22 599 15 63</fax>
      <email>Rongies@interia.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Bartosz Slomka</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy, Rehabilitation Division, II Faculty of Medicine, MedicalUniversity of Warsaw
PhD Medical University of Warsaw,Zwirki i Wigury 61, 02-091 Warsaw, Poland</address>
      <phone>+48 022 57 20 920</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>slomka.bartosz@interia.pl</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>