<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368915">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001002572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot trial of topical St Johns Wort in the treatment of post-herpetic neuralgia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot randomised controlled trial of topical St Johns Wort in the treatment of post-herpetic neuralgia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1172-0635</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>post-herpetic neuralgia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Herbal remedies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: A topical olive oil extraction of St John's Wort (Hypericum perforatum). 

Dose: 1mL of 0.23mg/mL fresh plant tincture olive oil extraction, administered three times daily.

Duration of use: 4 weeks

Design: 1 week with all participants on placebo, then 4 weeks on intervention/control, then 4 weeks on crossover intervention/control. No washout period between 4 week intervention/control periods. 

Mode of administration: topical application will be applied to the area affected by PHN

Strategies used to monitor adherence: empty lotion bottle return and bottle measurement open completion. </interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo - olive oil with red food colouring</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effectiveness of a herbal treatment on clinical pain measures of post-herpetic neuralgia as measured by Visual Analogue (Pain) Scale (VAS); </outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 - end of initial placebo
Weeks 5, 9 - indicate end of each 4 week intervention period (active/control)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effectiveness of a herbal treatment on clinical quality of life measures of post-herpetic neuralgia as measured by SF-36 </outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 - end of initial placebo
Weeks 5, 9 - indicate end of each 4 week intervention period (active/control)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability of a herbal treatment in PHN (adverse events)

Examples of unlikely, but potential (known) adverse reactions include skin photosensitivity and irritation. Some adverse events and drug interaction are known to occur with internal use (though not topical use), and patients have been issued with a safety sheet asking them to report to study coordinator should these symtpoms (e.g. weight loss, nausea, headache).  

Assessed via self-reported outcomes by patients in diary</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 1 - end of initial placebo
Weeks 5, 9 - indicate end of each 4 week intervention period (active/control)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Any person male or female aged 18-65 presenting with a confirmed diagnosis of herpetic neuralgia.

- Willingness to give written informed consent and willingness to participate to and comply with the study (and who do not meet exclusion criteria  see below).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Other infectious skin diseases 

- Diagnosed hepato-bilary disease/inflammation 

- Current or &lt; 6 month substance abuse disorder including alcohol 

- Current or &lt; 12 month use of St. Johns wort

- Current or &lt; 1 month of therapeutic agents with narrow therapeutic windows (e.g. warfarin, anti-retroviral mediciations) 

- Previous reaction to St. Johns wort 

- Medications that maybe pharmacokinetically altered via St. Johns wort including: amitriptyline, anti-coagulants e.g. phenprocoumon, warfarin, anti-fugals e.g. voriconazole, anti-histamines e.g. fexofenadine, benzodiazepines e.g. alprazolam, Chemotherapeutics e.g. irinotecan, digoxin, HIV medication (anti-retrovirals), Immunosuppressants e.g. cyclosporine, methadone, OCP, statins e.g. simvastatin, warfarin (Henderson 2002; Izzo 2004). However this interactions are based on case studies and theoretical interactions and are regarded to be induced by hyperforin (a constituent of St. Johns wort); low or non-standardised hyperforin preparations are regarded to not induce drug interactions as little induction of P-glycoprotein and CYP P450 enzymes occurs (Madabushi et al. 2006). 

- Non-English speakers. 

- More than 6 months since the onset of acute herpetic rash</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study will be blinded by using active and controls with reference numbers allocated by the manufacturer. These will only be revealed at the end of the trial, when the reference number is matched to participants reference number.</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will be randomised in sequence according to the reference numbers provided, using computerised sequence generation (simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software). These will only be revealed at the end of the trial, when the reference number is matched to participants reference number. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Technology Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Health, 235-253 Jones St, Ultimo, NSW 2007</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Technology Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Faculty of Health, 235-253 Jones St, Ultimo, NSW 2007</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Description: Post-herpetic neuralgia (PHN) is a condition in which there are few effective therapies, and most of those which do show some efficacy have an unfavourable side effect
profile. This study will explore whether a widely used clinical complementary therapy may have a role in the treatment of PHN. In addition to confirming whether SJW is effective in PHN, this research will help to build an evidence base for complementary therapies. Despite being widely
used, most complementary therapies remain unstudied. This research will help to uncover the effectiveness, or lack thereof, of SJW in PHN.

Objectives: Primary  The effectiveness of a herbal treatment on clinical measures of post-herpetic neuralgia. 
Secondary  Tolerability of a herbal medicine treatment in the treatment of post-herpetic neuralgia

Study design: Double-blind randomised cross-over clinical trial

Planned sample size: 40-60 (pilot)

Selection criteria: Persons with a confirmed diagnosis of herpetic neuralgia.

Study procedures: The design of the study is a randomised, placebo controlled pilot trial recruiting 40-45 adults (18-65) with post-herpetic neuralgia (PHN). The clinical trial will be conducted over 9 weeks in 3 phases. All the participants will receive placebo application for the 1st phase (washout-placebo phase - 1 week), then group 1 (determined via randomisation) will continue to take placebo for 4 weeks, while group 2 will receive the active St. Johns Wort topical application (SJW). The next phase involves both groups 1 and 2 crossing over for 4 weeks. The topical application will be applied to the area affected by PHN twice daily, this will differ depending on the severity and extent of PHN in individual patients.

Statistical considerations: As a pilot study of a treatment in common clinical use, but with no data to calculate effect size, a pilot trial of 40-60 persons will be conducted.

Study duration: 4 weeks (participant). Recruitment will last for 1 year (12 months)</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Technology Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Faculty of Health, 235-253 Jones St, Ultimo NSW 2007</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014000104</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jon Wardle</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health, University of Technology Sydney, 235-253 Jones St, Ultimo, NSW 2007</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4813</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jon.wardle@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jon Wardle</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health, University of Technology Sydney, 235-253 Jones St, Ultimo, NSW 2007</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4813</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jon.wardle@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jon Wardle</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health, University of Technology Sydney, 235-253 Jones St, Ultimo, NSW 2007</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4813</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jon.wardle@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jon Wardle</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health, University of Technology Sydney, 235-253 Jones St, Ultimo, NSW 2007</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9514 4813</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jon.wardle@uts.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>