<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363600">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000125729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Primary prevention of gestational diabetes for women who are overweight and obese: a randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing the effectiveness of a telephone based behavioural change program to usual care   in reducing the incidence of gestational diabetes in overweight and obese women. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gestational Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Gestational weight gain</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Large for gestational age infants</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Self efficacy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight/obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>From recruitment in the first trimester until childbirth, women in the intervention group will receive a telephone based program informed by the Theory of Self-efficacy and employing Motivational Interviewing. Brief ( less than 5 minute) phone contact will alternate each week with a text message/email and this contact will involve goal setting, behaviour change reinforcement with weekly self weighing and charting, and the provision of health information. The intervention does not involve clinical care.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual pregnancy care will vary with respect to advice provided to women on lifestyle modifications and referrals to other health professionals such as dieticians. Women in both the intervention and control group will receive two commonly available information booklets one following recruitment and on at 36 weeks. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of women diagnosed with Gestation Diabetes on Oral Glucose Tolerance Test. Both the criteria for  the  Australian Diabetes in Pregnancy Society management guidelines and the International Association of Diabetes and Pregnancy Study Groups criteria will be used and reported separately.</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 - 28 weeks gestation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of women with a gestational weight gain within the Institute of Medicine's guidelines. Measured as the difference between the woman's booking in weight and the last recorded weight in her pregnancy record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From 36 weeks gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Large for gestational age infants
The differences in the proportions of babies that are LGA will be compared.  LGA infants will be defined as a birth weight &gt; /=90th centile for gender and gestation, as well as a birth weight &gt; 4000 grams. These data will be obtained from a review of medical records and will be reported using both criteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy related to healthy lifestyle changes in diet and exercise will be measured and the mean differences between groups will be compared. The Weight Efficacy Life-Style Questionnaire and the Self-Efficacy for Exercise Scale will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Self reported using questionnaire at 36 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety will be measured using the short version of the Speilberger State-Trait anxiety inventory (STAI-State). Mean scores will compared. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Self reported using questionnaire at 36 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression will be measured using the Beck Depression Inventory II. The mean differences between groups will be compared. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Self reported using questionnaire at 36 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pregnant with gestation less than 14 weeks
Singelton pregnancy
Body Mass Index =/&gt; 25 
Able to give informed consent in English</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pre-exisiting diabetes
History of gestational diabetes
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Women who meet the selection criteria will be offered information on the study by their General Practitioner or Practice Nurse.Women interersted in participating will provide written informed consent and an enrolment form will be completed. The attending clinicians are not part of the research team.
The consent and enrolment form will be faxed/emailed to the research office. Women will be randomly allocated to the intervention or control group by an individual who is independent to the study team, drawing a sealed numbered opaque envelope indicating "intervention" or "control". Envelopes are numbered and will be drawn consecutively.  
</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated randomisation sequence will be used to achieve block randomisation by recruitment site.  </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Initial analysis will examine baseline characteristics of all women, as an indication that the treatment groups were comparable for selected variables including, age, parity and BMI category.  Primary and secondary outcomes will be analysed on an "intention to treat" basis. Differences between trial arms will use the Chi-squared statistic for categorical outcomes and Students t-test for continuous outcomes and 95% confidence intervals will be reported. Appropriate regression models will be employed controlling for co-variates. The fidelity of the intervention will be assessed and reported and the feasibility of the intervention will be considered in the process evaluation that will include the experience of participants and General Practioners /Practice Nurses. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/02/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>370</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3220 - Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>3250 - Colac</postcode>
    <postcode>3280 - Warrnambool</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Cate Nagle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 20000
School of Nursing and Midwifery
Waterfront campus
Geelong
Victoria
3220</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Deakin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 20000
School of Nursing and Midwifery
Geelong
Victoria
3220</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Gestational Diabetes Mellitus (GDM) has well recognised adverse health implications for the mother and her newborn that are both short and long term. Obesity is a significant risk factor for developing GDM and the prevalence of obesity is increasing globally. It is a matter of public health importance that clinicians have evidence based strategies to inform practice and currently there is insufficient evidence regarding the impact of dietary and lifestyle interventions on improving maternal and newborn outcomes. The primary aim of this study is to measure the impact of a telephone based intervention that promotes positive lifestyle modifications on the incidence of GDM.  Secondary aims include: the impact on gestational weight gain; large for gestational age babies; differences in blood glucose levels taken at the Oral Glucose Tolerance Test (OGTT) and selected factors relating to self-efficacy and psychological wellbeing.    
A  randomised controlled trial (RCT) will be conducted involving  pregnant women who are overweight (BMI &gt;25 to 29.9 kg/m^2) or obese (BMI &gt;30kg/m^2),  less than 14 weeks gestation and recruited from the Barwon South West  region of Victoria, Australia. From recruitment until birth, women in the intervention group will receive a program informed by the Theory of Self-efficacy and employing Motivational Interviewing. Brief (less than 5 minute) phone contact will alternate each week with a text message/email and will involve goal setting, behaviour change reinforcement with weekly weighing and charting, and the provision of health information. Those in the control group will receive usual care. Data for primary and secondary outcomes will be collected from medical record review and a questionnaire at 36 weeks gestation.    
Evidence based strategies that reduce the incidence of GDM are a priority for contemporary maternity care. Changing health behaviours is a complex undertaking and trialling a composite intervention that can be adopted in various primary health settings is required so women can be accessed as early in pregnancy as possible. Using a sound theoretical base to inform such an intervention will add depth to our understanding of this approach and to the interpretation of results, contributing to the evidence base for practice and policy.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Barwon Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research
P0 Box 281
Ryrie St
Geelong
Vic
3220</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/108</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cate Nagle</name>
      <address>Deakin University
School of Nursing and Midwifery 
Waterfont Campus
1 Gheringhap St
Geelong
Victoria
3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5227 8401</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5227 8411</fax>
      <email>cate.nagle@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cate Nagle</name>
      <address>Deakin University
School of Nursing and Midwifery 
Waterfont Campus
1 Gheringhap St
Geelong
Victoria
3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5227 8401</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5227 8411</fax>
      <email>cate.nagle@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Cate Nagle</name>
      <address>Deakin University
School of Nursing and Midwifery 
Waterfont Campus
1 Gheringhap St
Geelong
Victoria
3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5227 8401</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5227 8411</fax>
      <email>cate.nagle@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cate Nagle</name>
      <address>Deakin University
School of Nursing and Midwifery 
Waterfont Campus
1 Gheringhap St
Geelong
Victoria
3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 5227 8401</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 5227 8411</fax>
      <email>cate.nagle@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>