<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372815">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001347358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of a dietary ketone on immunity, tolerability and performance in well-trained, healthy male cyclists. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of 1,3-butanediol on immunity, tolerability and performance in well-trained, healthy male cyclists. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U111-1192-4543</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Exercise-Induced immunosuppression
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Gastrointestinal distress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Systemic symptoms (e.g. dizziness, nausea)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Pre-experimental tests: Participants will arrive at the laboratory at a time of convenience and having abstained from caffeine, alcohol and strenuous exercise for the previous 24 h.  Participants will be required to fast for at least 4 hours prior to arrival. Participants will be asked to void their bladder before their body mass (shorts only), height and sum of 8 skinfolds are measured by an International Society for the Advancement of Kinanthropometry Level 1 Accredited Anthropometrist. To determine VO2max, participants complete a continuous incremental cycling protocol originally described by Achten and colleagues (2002) (1) and adapted by Achten and colleagues (2003) (2), requiring participants to start cycling at 95W with increments of 35W every 3 min until either; 1) volitional exhaustion or 2) cadence cannot be maintained &gt;60 RPM. After 20 min of rest, participants will cycle to exhaustion at 110% of their final power output of the preceding incremental cycling test as recommended by Poole and colleagues (2017) (3) to confirm VO2max. Pre-experimental, familiarisation and experimental tests will be completed on an electromagnetically braked cycle ergometer (Lode Excalibur Sport, Groningen, Netherlands). The expired gas will be collected and analysed continuously using a computerised metabolic system with mixing chamber (Parvo Medics TrueOne 2400, Salt Lake City, Utah, USA). 

Ventilatory thresholds (VT1 and VT2) will be estimated during the continuous incremental cycling protocol. VT1 will be inferred by the criteria of the first marked increase in VE/VO2  with no concomitant increase in VE/VCO2. VT2 will be inferred by the criteria of an increase in both VE/VO2 and VE/VCO2 and a decrease in PETCO2. (4). Ratings of perceived exertion (RPE) (Borg scale (5)) will be noted for each stage and heart rate will be continuously measured using short-range telemetry. The work rate equivalent to 85% VT2 will be inferred for use in the experimental procedures for performance trials. If participants VO2max is &gt;60ml/kg/min they will be considered eligible for the study. Maximal power output (Wmax) will be calculated according to the formula

Wmax = Wfinal + (t/T) x Winc

Where Wfinal is the power output (W) of the final completed stage, t is the time achieved in the final uncompleted stage (s), T is the duration of each stage (180 s) and Winc is the workload increment (35 W).

Familiarisation testing: Three to seven days after the pre-experimental test, participants will return to the laboratory between 07:00 and 08:00h having fasted from 23:00 h the previous day. Participants will we be asked to consume a high carbohydrate diet (6g/kg) during the previous 24 hours to standardise nutritional status prior to arrival. Participants will be provided with dietary guidelines and asked to record their intake via written and photographic documentation. If certified, participants will be asked to repeat their dietary protocol prior to each subsequent experimental procedure. Participants will be advised to consume 500 ml of water upon wakening to standardise hydration status. They will then provide a saliva sample (practice sample). Participants will mount the cycle ergometer and cycle for 85 min at the power output equivalent to 85% of their VT2 as determined in the pre-experimental test. Every 20 min, participants will have a ventilatory mask fitted for 3 min for gas analysis. Following completion, they will then be allowed 5 min to rest and use the lavatory. Participants will re-mount the cycle ergometer, which will be switched from hyperbolic mode to linear mode, and precisely on 5 min of rest they will commence a time trial equivalent to 7kJ/kg (~25-35 min). 

Compared to hyperbolic mode, which allows the cycle ergometer to produce a set power output independent of cadence, the power output in linear mode is cadence dependant, with power (W) calculated according to the formula:

W = L x (RPM)2

Where RPM is the cadence and L is a (constant) linear factor. L will be calculated to elicit a power output of 70% Wmax at an RPM of 90. 

Participants will be able to consume water ad-libitum throughout the familiarisation test. Participants will then provide a saliva sample (practice sample), after which, they will be reminded of the requirements of the experimental tests. 

Experimental procedure: Five to ten days after the familiarisation test, participants will arrive at the laboratory between 07:00 and 08:00 h having fasted from 23:00 h the previous day and refrained from caffeine and alcohol for the previous 24 hours and strenuous exercise for the previous 48 h. Participants will be advised to consume 500 ml of water upon waking to standardise hydration status. Upon arrival at the lab, participants will rest quietly for ~10 min prior to initial blood and saliva samples, ketone levels and tolerability (i.e. gastrointestinal and systemic symptom) scores being collected (baseline measures). Participants will be asked to void their bladder before their body mass (shorts only) measured.

Participants will then consume a citrus flavoured drink (2ml/kg) immediately after (i.e. 30 min before commencing exercise). The drink will be formulated to provide either 0.7g/kg of 1,3-butanediol (1,3-BD) or placebo.  Participants will be blinded to the dose of 1,3-BD in a single-blinded randomised crossover design. Twenty-five minutes following the intake of 1,3-BD and immediately prior to commencing exercise, blood and saliva samples, ketone and lactate levels, and tolerability (i.e. gastrointestinal and systemic symptom) scores  will be collected. Participants will then mount the cycle ergometer and cycle 85 min 85% VT2 power output. Every 20 min, participants will have a ventilatory mask fitted for 3 min for gas analysis and RPE will be recorded. They will then be allowed 5 min to rest. During this time, blood samples, ketone and lactate will be collected. Precisely on 5 min, participants will re-mount the cycle ergometer, which will be switched from hyperbolic mode to linear mode, and they will complete a time trial equivalent to 7kJ/kg (~25-35 min) from a stationary start. Participants will be restricted to 2ml/kg of fluid every 15 min during exercise. Before leaving the cycle ergometer, blood samples, blood ketone and lactate levels will be collected.  

Immediately afterwards, saliva samples, and tolerability and tolerability (i.e. gastrointestinal and systemic symptoms) scores will be collected. Participants will then remove wet clothing, towel dry themselves and have their body mass measured (shorts only) to estimate fluid loss. Participants will then be provided with 5ml/kg of water and asked to rest until 1 h post time trial when blood and saliva samples and ketone levels will be collected. Following completion of the trial, participants will be provided with 400ml of a carbohydrate drink and recommended to return to their normal dietary patterns and asked to return to the laboratory 5  10 days later to repeat the protocol with the alternative dietary intervention (i.e. placebo or 1,3-BD).

Safety monitoring: Participant tolerability, side-effects and abnormal haematological values will be immediately reported to a medical doctor. This study will be immediately terminated when advised by the medical doctor or following intractable symptoms after 1,3-BD consumption in 2 trial arms (i.e. 10% of trials). Participants will be followed up 3 days and 1 week after the consumption of 1,3-BD to ascertain if any adverse effects occurred. Participants will also be encouraged to report any symptoms following consumption of 1,3-BD by email, phone or text. 

All exercise tests, blood and saliva collection protocols and body composition assessment will be performed by the lead researcher, who is a trained phlebotomist and level 1 ISAK accredited. 

Capillary blood samples for ketone and lactate monitoring: Samples will be collected from participants fingers using standardised techniques. The site of puncture will be cleaned with an alcohol swab then allowed to air dry. Skin puncture will occur in one quick, deliberate strike of the lancet. The first drop of blood will be wiped away, then subsequent accumulation of blood will be used in analysis. Afterwards, pressure and/or a plaster will be applied to stop further bleeding. Blood beta hydroxybutyrate (ketone) will be measured using Freestyle Optium Neo (Abbott Diabetes Care, Victoria, Australia) and blood lactate will be measured using the Lactate 2 Pro (Akray, Japan). 

Tolerability questionnaire: The questionnaire is organised in three sections as previously described by Pfeiffer et al. (2009) and adapted to include additional symptoms. Section 1 addresses upper abdominal problems; Section 2, lower abdominal problems; and Section 3, systemic problems. Each participant will be assessed on the 29 items on a 10-point scale ranging from 0, no problem at all, to 9, the worst it has ever been.

Salivary sampling and analysis: Unstimulated saliva samples will be collected. Participants will be instructed to be in a seated position, leaning forward with their head tilted down and asked to empty their mouth of any residual saliva before the timed sample collection begins. Each saliva collection will last 3 min, during which time participants will be requested to minimise orofacial movement and passively dribble into a pre-weighed vial. Samples will be weighed to estimate saliva volume (the density will be assumed to be 1g/ml and micro-centrifuged to remove cells and insoluble matter before storing at -20oC for later analysis. The saliva flow rate (mlmin-1) will be determined by dividing the volume of saliva by collection time. Saliva samples will be analysed for salivary immunoglobulin A using a commercially available ELISA kit (DRG, Germany). 

Blood sampling: All blood samples will be collected via cannulation of the antecubital vein into three evacuated vacutainers, two containing tripotassium ethylene diamine tetraacetic acid (K3EDTA) and one containing no additive to obtain serum. All vacutainers will be centrifuged for 10 min at 1500 x g and 4oC. Plasma and serum will be aliquoted and stored at -80oC for later analysis. 

Blood cell counts: Blood collected into the K3EDTA vacutainer will be used to analyse for total and differential leukocyte counts, haematocrit and haemoglobin contents using a haematology analyser (AC.TTM 5diff analyser, Beckman Coulter, UK).  All cell counts will be adjusted for plasma volume changes, with changes being estimated from haemoglobin and haematocrit values according to Dill &amp; Costill (1974). 

Whole blood culture: 2ml of whole blood obtained from an K3EDTA vacutainer will be added to 2 ml of RPMI medium with no added stimulant (unstimulated) or stimulant (stimulated) at a concentration designed to elicit maximal lymphocyte response (final stimulant concentration will be determined with prior titration work). The stimulant that will be used will be Staphylococcal enterotoxin B from Staphylococcus aureus. The whole blood cultures will then be incubated for 24 h at 37 °C, 5 % CO2 (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, Massachusetts, USA). 

Unstimulated and antigen-stimulated lymphocyte subset cell counts and activation: Whole blood cultures will be used to analyse lymphocyte cell subsets and their activation (CD69+) according to their cell surface markers CD4+, CD8+ CD25+ (T cells) via the Muse (Millipore, Darmstadt, Germany). 

Unstimulated and antigen-stimulated whole blood cytokine production: Blood cultures will be centrifuged for 4 min at 13,000g in a microcentrifuge. Supernatants will be collected and stored frozen at -80 °C until analysis.  Cytokines interleukin (IL)-1, IL-1ra, IL-2, IL-4, IL-8, IL-10, interferon (IFN)-? and tumour necrosis factor (TNF)-a) will be determined using a multiplex kit (Millipore, NZ) on the MAGPIX. 

Unstimulated and antigen-stimulated peripheral blood mononuclear cells IFN- ?, IL-4 and IL-10 gene expression: A gene expression assay will be used to measure the expression of genes coding for IFN-y, IL-4 and IL-10 in peripheral blood mononuclear cells. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) will be isolated from the whole blood culture and total RNA will be extracted. PBMC RNA will be treated with DNase to remove contaminated genomic DNA.  Purified RNA will be reversed transcribed by a one-step real time PCR assay (Roche Light Cycler instruments (2.0 &amp; 480)) to generate cDNA and specific PCR products for IFN-y, IL-4 and IL-10 genes. In addition to these genes, a reference gene will be used to normalize results.

Plasma cortisol: Plasma concentrations of cortisol will be measured using ELISA kits (DRG, Germany). 

Blood glucose: Blood glucose will be measured using the COBAS analyser. 

Substrate utilisation calculations: The application of indirect calorimetry (stoichiometry) will be used to estimate in vivo substrate utilisation (respiratory quotient (RQ)) from gaseous exchange measurements (respiratory exchange ratio (RER)). The stoichiometric equations (see below) originally published by Frayn and colleagues (1983), which assumes the contribution of protein is negligible, has been validated at exercise intensities up to 80-85% VO2max where a steady state has been achieved. 

CHO oxidation (g/min-1) = 4.585 VCO2  3.226 VO2
Fat oxidation (g/min-1) = 1.695 VO2  1.701 VCO2
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will act as their own control by consuming a placebo (i.e. drink containing no 1,3-butanediol) in a single-blinded randomised crossover design.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>T-cell mediated immune response (i.e. peripheral blood T-cell subset count and balance, and stimulated cytokine production) using the Muse, RT-PCR, Magpix. T-cells will be stimulated using Staphylococcal enterotoxin B within a whole blood culture.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 30, 150 and 210 minutes after consumption of 1,3-butanediol (i.e. immediately before ingesting 1,3-BD,  immediately before exercise, immediately after sub maximal exercise, immediately after time-trial and 60 minutes after exercise). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Salivary flow rate (i.e. volume of unstimulated saliva drool collected divided by collection time)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 30, 150 and 210 minutes after consumption of 1,3-butanediol (i.e. immediately before ingesting 1,3-BD,  immediately before exercise,  immediately after time trial and 60 minutes after exercise). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Salivary immunoglobulin A concentration and secretion rate (i.e. amount of salivary immunoglobulin A collected divided by collection time). sIgA will be measured an using in-house ELISA method.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 30, 150 and 210 minutes after consumption of 1,3-butanediol (i.e. immediately before ingesting 1,3-BD,  immediately before exercise,  immediately after time trial and 60 minutes after exercise). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pre-loaded time trial (time to complete the workload equivalent to 7kJ/kg following 85 minutes of cycling at 85% of the power output equivalent to their secondary ventilatory threshold). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Exercise completion </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability (i.e. gastrointestinal and systemic symptoms) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 30 and 150 minutes after consumption of 1,3-butanediol (i.e. immediately before ingesting 1,3-BD,  immediately before exercise,  immediately after time trial). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lactate (capillary blood)</outcome>
      <timepoint>30, 120 and 150 minutes after consumption of 1,3-butanediol (i.e. immediately before exercise, between sub-maximal exercise and time trial and immediately after time trial)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ketones (capillary blood beta-hydroxybutyrate)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 30, 120, 150 and 210 minutes after consumption of 1,3-butanediol (i.e. immediately before exercise, between sub-maximal exercise and time trial, immediately after time trial and 1 hour after time trial)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gaseous exchange analysis </outcome>
      <timepoint>Every twenty minutes during exercise for 3 minutes (no gas analysis will occur during the time trial). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body weight and composition </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weight and skinfolds will be measured during the screening process. Weight will also be measured immediately pre and post exercise. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse effects and safety </outcome>
      <timepoint>All adverse effects will either be communicated to the lead researcher via the tolerability questionnaire at designated time points or orally when symptoms arise. Participants will also be prompted following the completing of the sub maximal exercise and time trial to ascertain 'how they feel'. As previously described, all adverse effects and safety issues will immediately reported to the sports doctor. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Endurance-trained male cyclists; VO2max &gt;60mlkg/min; 18  35 years; history of competition; training for &gt;2 years; train &gt;6 hours per week; habitually consuming a mixed diet for at least 1 year; weight stable for &gt;1 month. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Possess cardiovascular, metabolic, neurological, immunological or autoimmune disorders; baseline haematological values (leukocytes and erythrocyte counts) outside of normal range; experienced illness and/or upper respiratory symptoms within the previous 4 weeks; experienced GI symptoms within the previous 4 weeks or has a history of GI symptomology; consumed medications or supplements known to effect immunity within previous 2 weeks; smoker or previously smoked; family member has died before the age of 50 due to a heart condition. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be allocated to citrus flavoured drink containing either 0.7g/kg of 1,3-butanediol or placebo in a randomised order following their inclusion into the study. The primary researcher will not know the order of treatment for the participant during the participant screening process. Each trial will be allocated a number (i.e. 1 or 2). The day prior to the participant arriving, the investigator will generate a number (via random number generator) from 1 - 2 that will specify what drink will be used. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive statistics will be used to determine the centrality and spread of the data. The normality of each data set will be assessed prior to further statistical analysis. Datasets that defy the assumptions of normality will be log-transformed prior to analysis or analysed using non-parametric analysis. A Repeated Measures Anova will be used to identify whether within-group differences occurred. If significance is found, a paired t-test will be used to determine where the effect occurred. Differences between groups will be assessed using an unpaired t-test. Effects sizes will be determined using Cohens d effect size statistics; &gt;0.2 (small), &gt;0.5 (moderate) and &gt;0.8 (large). Differences between group means will be analysed using an unpaired t-test. All analysis will be undertaken using the statistical package SPSS (Version 21, SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL), with significance accepted at P &lt; 0.05. Below P = 0.01, P values will be reported as P &lt; 0.01. 

Data will be further analysed for clinical significance using magnitude-based inferences. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>17/01/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/01/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland </state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Auckland University of Technology </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>17 Antares Place, Rosedale, Auckland, 0632</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Auckland University of Technology </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>17 Antares Place, Rosedale, Auckland, 0632</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Athletes are constantly searching for novel dietary strategies to enhance performance and health. The use of 1,3-butanediol (1,3-BD), a dietary ketone precurser, has been suggested to influence endurance performance, with both positive and negative effects. The consumption of this ketone can increase blood ketone concentration to levels similar of a low carbohydrate, ketogenic diet, without the burden of drastic dietary change. The presence of ketones in the blood provides an additional energy source to muscle and the brain, and influences how the body uses its carbohydrate and fat stores. In some athlete circles, 1,3-BD is being used, however, its effects on immunity and tolerability (i.e. gastrointestinal and systemic symptoms) in male endurance athletes is not known. Considering endurance athletes are at a higher risk of illness and gastrointestinal distress, this study is important to provide an initial insight into the effect of 1,3-BD on these health markers.  Local competitive, male cyclists, aged 18 - 35 will be recruited and will have to undertake a strenuous exercise protocol following the consumption of 1,3-butanediol (1,3-BD) (within a flavoured drink) or placebo in a randomised, crossover trial, with blood and saliva samples collected before and following exercise. These samples will be analysed for the defining immune markers of T-cell mediated immunity (blood) and mucosal immunity (saliva). providing a comprehensive depiction of the dynamic changes to the immune system.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern B Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health 133 Molesworth Street, Wellington, 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>17/NTB/39</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Shaw</name>
      <address>17 Antares Place, Second Level, Sports Performance Research Institute of NZ (SPRINZ), Rosedale, Auckland, 0632</address>
      <phone>+64 21 0827 6137</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nutrition@daveshaw.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Shaw</name>
      <address>17 Antares Place, Second Level, Sports Performance Research Institute of NZ (SPRINZ), Rosedale, Auckland, 0632</address>
      <phone>+64 21 0827 6137</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nutrition@daveshaw.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Shaw</name>
      <address>17 Antares Place, Second Level, Sports Performance Research Institute of NZ (SPRINZ), Rosedale, Auckland, 0632</address>
      <phone>+64 21 0827 6137</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nutrition@daveshaw.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>David Shaw</name>
      <address>17 Antares Place, Second Level, Sports Performance Research Institute of NZ (SPRINZ), Rosedale, Auckland, 0632</address>
      <phone>+64 21 0827 6137</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nutrition@daveshaw.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>