<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367467">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000921482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of intranasal dexmedetomidine versus intranasal ketamine on emergence agitation after sevoflurane anesthesia in myringotomy patients: a randomized  clinical trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>  Intranasal dexmedetomidine versus intranasal ketamine for prevention of emergence agitation after sevoflurane anesthesia in pediatric patients undergoing myringotomy : a randomized clinical trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1181-5880</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Emergence agitation after sevoflurane anesthesia in children</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Preoperatively, all patients will be assessed by detailed medical and surgical history, complete clinical examination and routine laboratory investigations and will be allocated randomly into two groups; Group I (intranasal ketamine group = 45 children): Children of this group will receive ketamine intranasal in a dose 5 mg/kg.
Group II (Intranasal dexmedetomidine group = 45 children): Children of this group will receive dexmedetomidine intranasal in a dose 1 microgram/kg.
   A preoperative fasting period of 6 hours. No  premedication  will be  taken. 
Induction of general anesthesia will done 15 minutes after study drug administration with sevoflurane which will be titrated with increments of 1% at each breath up to 8% in oxygen 100%. Once an appropriate depth of anesthesia will be obtained an IV cannula and a suitable laryngeal mask will be inserted (its position will be confirmed by capnography) and sevoflurane concentration will be reduced to an end tidal concentration of 3% in 100% oxygen. Spontaneous breathing will be allowed provided ETCO2 remained below 50 mm Hg; if ETCO2 exceeded 50 mm Hg, the patient will be excluded from the study and ventilation will be assisted. No muscle relaxant or narcotic will be administered during the procedure. The patients will be monitored continuously for heart rate, oxygen saturation, respiratory rate, end tidal CO2 and mean arterial blood pressure. Sevoflurane will be discontinued immediately after insertion of the T-tube, and the laryngeal mask will be removed  60 seconds later and the patient will be transported to the post-anesthesia care unit (PACU) in a quiet and warm environment without any stimulus. Parents will be allowed to be at the childs bedside in the PACU. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Group II (Intranasal dexmedetomidine group = 45 children): is the active control group, Children of this group will receive dexmedetomidine intranasal in a dose of 1 micro-gram/kg.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	The incidence of EA was evaluated using Aono's four point scale  1= calm;  2=  not calm but could be easily consoled;  3=  moderately agitated or restless and not easily calmed; 4= combative, excited, or disoriented, thrashing around. Scores of three and four will be considered as presence of EA, while one and two as absence of EA.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 minutes after awakening</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The pediatric anesthesia emergence delirium (PAED) scale will be used to evaluate the severity of  EA , a five-point rating scale (eye contact, purposeful actions, awareness of surroundings, restlessness and consolability), with five grades(0 to 4) for each item. The total  score (20) is the sum of the scores of the individual items. The severity of EA increases proportional to the total score. A score = 10 will be considered agitated, and will be treated with i.v propofol 1 mg/kg as rescue medication. A score = 15 reflects severe agitation  while, scores less than 10 means no agitation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The severity of EA will be evaluated  at Time 0 , 5, 10, 15 and 30 min after  awakening . </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Duration of emergence in minutes </outcome>
      <timepoint>The time interval from switching off sevoflurane to spontaneous eye opening, the ability to obey commands after and purposeful movements .</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Occurrence of complications: e.g. nausea, vomiting, bradycardia, Cough, laryngospasm, or desaturation (SpO2 below 95%), or any other complication will be treated , recorded and cleared to the ethical committee on time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>from the time of drug administration till 30 minutes after awakening</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	The response to parental separation will be assessed using parental separation anxiety scale; excellent (1):child cooperative, unafraid or asleep. Good (2): the child is slightly afraid/crying and quiet with reassurance. Fair (3):  the child is moderately afraid and no response to reassurance. Poor (4): the child is crying and needs restraint .</outcome>
      <timepoint>15 minutes after drug administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The response to face mask induction will be evaluated using the mask acceptance scale; 1= combative, crying, 2= not easily calmed, moderate fear of mask, 3 = cooperative with reassurance, 4 = cooperative and calm .</outcome>
      <timepoint>at the time of induction of anesthesia</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>  Patients prepared to unilateral or bilateral myringotomy	
  Both sexes, age from 3 to 6 years old.
  ASA physical status I or II. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	a -Parent's refusal. 
	b- Preoperative agitation (e.g.  cerebral palsy, agitationetc).
	c - Children with allergy to ketamine, dexmedetomidine. 
	d - Aberrant nasal deformity or nasal trauma. 
	e - Acute (e.g. running nose or upper respiratory tract infection) or chronic nasal                  problems.
       f -Mental retardation, physical developmental delay, or neuromuscular disease.
       g - Patients under treatment with sedatives or anticonvulsants.
       h - Respiratory and cardiovascular diseases.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>	sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>2/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>26/05/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>90</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>26/05/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state>Tanta, Elgharbia governorate</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hoda Alsaid Ahmed Ezz </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress> El Geesh street, Department of Anesthesia and surgical ICU, Tanta University Hospital, faculty of Medicine,Tanta University, Tanta, Elgharbia Governorate, Egypt. 
The postal code:31257 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Tanta University Hospital.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress> El Geesh street, Department of Anesthesia and surgical ICU, Tanta University Hospital,faculty of Medicine,Tanta University, Tanta, Elgharbia  Governorate, Egypt. 
The postal code:31257 

</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this prospective randomized study is to compare the effect of intranasal dexmedetomidine and intranasal ketamine for prevention of emergence agitation after sevoflurane anesthesia in pediatric patients scheduled for myringotomy operations.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The research Ethics Committee of the Faulty of Medicine ,Tanta University, Egypt. </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>El Geesh street, Faulty of medicine ,Tanta University, Egypt. 
Postal code: 31257 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>30758/02/16</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Hoda Alsaid Ahmed Ezz</name>
      <address>El Geesh street, Department of Anesthesia and surgical ICU, Tanta University Hospital, faculty of Medicine,Tanta University, Tanta, Elgharbia  Governorate, Egypt. 
The postal code:31257 
</address>
      <phone>+20 1222768250 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hoda.ezz@med.tanta.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Abd El Raheem M. Dowidar </name>
      <address>El Geesh street, Department of Anesthesia and surgical ICU, Tanta  University Hospital, faculty of Medicine,Tanta University, Tanta, Elgharbia Governorate, Egypt. 
The postal code:31257 </address>
      <phone>+20 12223195015 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dr.dowidar47@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Abd El Raheem M. Dowidar </name>
      <address>El Geesh street, Department of Anesthesia and surgical ICU, Tanta  University Hospital, faculty of Medicine,Tanta University, Tanta, Elgharbia Governorate, Egypt. 
The postal code:31257 </address>
      <phone>+20 12223195015 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dr.dowidar@med.tanta.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Hoda Alsaid Ahmed Ezz</name>
      <address>El Geesh street, Department of Anesthesia and surgical ICU, Tanta  University Hospital, faculty of Medicine,Tanta University, Tanta, Elgharbia Governorate, Egypt. 
The postal code:31257 </address>
      <phone>+20 1222768250 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hodaezz714@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>