<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373438">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001189314p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Suprascapular block with infraclavicular block in shoulder surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Suprascapular block with infraclavicular block as an alternative to interscalene block for analgesia in shoulder surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>shoulder pathology</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Combined suprascapular and infraclavicular regional block

Written informed consent obtained.  Patients will be randomized to one of the two groups (Group I or Group C).  Blocks and anaesthesia will be performed prior to commencement of shoulder surgery when the surgeon is not in the room.

All patients will receive pre medication with 1.5g of oral paracetamol (1g if &lt;50kg), then enter theatre and be positioned on shoulder table.  Standard anaesthetic monitoring will be attached (non invasive blood pressure (NIBP), electrocardiography (ECG), pulse oximetry).  IV access will be obtained in the contralateral upper limb.
50mcg fentanyl administered IV along with TIVA (Marsh model) target plasma concentration 0.5-1mcg/ml.  Intra operative tramadol will be avoided.
Head turned to contralateral side.
Chlorhexidine/alcohol skin prep from mastoid to acromion, nipple and midline anteriorly,  and above spine of scapula posteriorly (skin prep will be the same in both groups to maintain surgeon blinding).
Ultrasound guidance used to identify interscalene landmarks (C5/6 roots, anterior and middle scalene muscles).

Group I:
Place interscalene catheter under ultrasound guidance (high frequence linear probe) out of plane with 51mm eCath.  Catheter tip aimed beside the C5/6 root, adjacent to middle scalene.  Inject 20ml Ropivacaine 0.375%.  Readjust needle tip as required to obtain adequate spread of LA.  Secure catheter with Friars balsam, tegaderm dressing and medipore tape.
Induction of general anaesthesia and positioning for surgery (see details below).
Make small skin punctures with 18G needle as for infraclavicular and suprascapular block.
At end of procedure operating surgeon infiltrates up to 20ml 0.25% plain bupivacaine around the port sites.



Group C:
Place interscalene catheter as above using 20ml NaCl 0.9% instead of ropivicaine and position catheter tip as above to obtain adequate spread.  Secure catheter with Friars balsam, tegaderm dressing and medipore tape.
Induction of general anaesthesia (see details below).
Site infraclavicular block with 100mm 18G sonoplex needle.  In plane approach. Aim to position tip inferior to subclavian artery.  Inject 15ml 0.375% ropivacaine to surround subclavian artery. 
Position patient in semi sitting position and scan suprascapular fossa.  Place needle tip on floor of suprascapular fossa beside suprascapular artery.  Inject 10ml 0.375% Ropivacaine just above floor of suprascapular fossa.
At end of procedure operating surgeon infiltrates up to 20ml 0.25% plain marcain around the port sites.


General Anaesthesia Induction:
100% Oxygen via facemask.  Increase TCI Propofol to adequate level as judged by anaesthetist and depth of anaesthesia monitoring. (usually 3-6mcg/ml).  Commence Remifentanil infusion (TCI Minto effect site concentration 2ng/ml)
Insert supraglottic airway device.  PCV with PEEP 5cm H20 to obtain tidal volume of 6ml/kg and ETCO2 40-50mmHg.
Use phenylephrine as required to maintain MAP &gt; 80% of baseline on the ward.
Use glycopyrrolate/atropine as required to maintain HR &gt; 40
Parecoxib 40mg IV given to all patients prior to skin incision.
Additional monitoring  temperature (nasopharyngeal) and Bispectral Index(BIS)/Entropy to maintain &lt; 60.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Interscalene regional block

Please see description of Group C in "Description of intervention" field in ANZCTR registration form.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>change in lung function measured using Micro Medical Micro Lab Spirometer (FVC and FEV1) </outcome>
      <timepoint>comparison from pre-operatively and prior to discharge from PACU </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>a comparison of the maximum visual analogue pain scores in PACU</outcome>
      <timepoint>maximum VAS score while in PACU, measured once post operatively at approximately 1-2 hours</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>complication rates - presence or absence of symptomatic haematoma, pneumothorax, persistence of block effect (all assessed clinically by examination)</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 24 hrs-2 wks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>patient satisfaction at 24hrs post operatively (using a 2 question survey conducted via a phone call)</outcome>
      <timepoint>24hrs post operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>opioid use in PACU (in mg as recored in post operative medication charts)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-2 hours post operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>block failure as assessed clinically by anaesthetist - insufficient pain relief with absence of sensory or motor block</outcome>
      <timepoint>1-2 hours post operatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>age &gt;=18 years up to 70 years; ASA physical status 1-3 , all patients will be scheduled for arthroscopic shoulder surgery by Ilia Elkinson</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>known pulmonary disease except well controlled asthma; diaphragmatic dysfunction or phrenic nerve palsy; allergy to local anaesthetics or other drugs used in study protocol; pre-existing neuropathy; pre-existing coagulopathy; any chronic pain syndrome or chronic opioid use (including regular tramadol use); patients undergoing bone graft harvesting from another body site; recreational drug users; BMI greater than 35</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>envelope and blinding to all but the anaesthetist administering the block</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using envelopes with 50/50 each group allocation being picked from a box on day of surgery</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Non inferiority analysis for pain relief
Superiority analysis for lung function</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/02/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>12/02/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Wellington Regional Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Riddiford St
Newtown
Wellington 6021</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Capital and Coast District Health Board</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Wellington Regional Hospital
Riddiford St
Newtown
Wellington 6021</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The rationale for this project lies in identifying an alternative form of regional anaesthesia to the interscalene block for use in shoulder surgery.  The interscalene block is associated with a significant rate of phrenic nerve palsy and subsequent respiratory impairment.  The objective is to compare the suprascapular and infraclavicular block combination with the interscalene block in terms of analgesia and effect on lung function.  Patients undergoing shoulder surgery will be randomized to one of two groups and have pre- and post-operative analgesia and lung function assessed.  Based on anatomical knowledge and previous studies we hypothesise that the combined infraclavicular and suprascapular blocks would result in similar analgesia but less impairment of lung function when compared with the interscalene block, for patients having shoulder surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HDEC New Zealand</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ilia Elkinson</name>
      <address>Wellington Regional Hospital
Riddiford St
Newtown
Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 385 5999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ilia.Elkinson@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Bond</name>
      <address>Wellington Regional Hospital
Riddiford St
Newtown
Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 385 5999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Elizabeth.Bond@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Bond</name>
      <address>Wellington Regional Hospital
Riddiford St
Newtown
Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 385 5999</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Elizabeth.Bond@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>