<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363610">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000159752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Videolaryngoscopy for Intubation in Neonates: an Evaluation a randomized controlled study (The Vine study)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to evaluate the effect of videolaryngoscopy and verbal assistance on the rate of successful intubation in neonates 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The VINE study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Intubation of the neonatal trachea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Infants in the intervention group will be intubated orally by a neonatal trainee using a videolaryngoscope. The attached monitor will be displaying real time images that are visible to a supervisor who is in attendance, supervising and assisting with the intubation attempt. The intervention is the verbal assistance offered during the intubation attempt by the supervisor on seeing what the intubator can see. </interventions>
    <comparator>The infants in the control group will also be intubated orally by a neonatal trainee and the laryngoscope used will also be the videolaryngoscope. However, the attached monitor screen will remain covered during the intubation attempt and the images therefore not be visible to the attending supervisor. The supervisor can still offer verbal guidance and assistance, as is standard current practice. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The rate of successful intubation on first attempt. An attempted intubation will be defined as the insertion of the laryngoscope into the infants mouth.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The duration of the intubation attempt
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time taken for the intubation attempt</outcome>
      <timepoint>The time taken is defined by the time difference between when the laryngoscope is inserted and subsequently removed from the patients mouth. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The lowest oxygen saturation and heart rate during the procedure. The oxygen saturation will be read from the attached pulsoximeter and the heart rate read either from the pulseoximeter or the infants electrocardiograph recording if attached.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The duration of the intubation attempt</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The rate of endotracheal tube adjustment following chest x-ray evaluation</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 hours following the intubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative data will be obtained from the registrars about their experience of the intubation attempt</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded as soon as possible after the intubation attempt</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Infants in the delivery room, operating theatre or in the Newborn Intensive and Special Care (NISC) unit of The Royal Womens Hospital, Melbourne who require oral endotracheal intubation will be eligible for entry to this study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Hours</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>4</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Infants will be not be recruited if they are in extremis requiring immediate intubation by a senior experienced operator who will use his/her own preferred method. 
Infants who will be intubated nasally will not be included as this technique is generally not taught to registrars.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque, sequentially numbered envelopes will contain the allocation. Once the decision is made to intubate, the infant will be enrolled. Just before the intubation attempt commences, an envelope will be opened revealling the allocation.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation will be stratified according to whether or not the clinical team prescribe premedication. Variable block randomisation will be used within each stratification group. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>In a trial performed at the Royal Womens Hospital recently - A Randomized Trial of Stylets for Intubating Newborn Infants, 228 intubations by registrars were examined of which 115 were successful on first attempt (50%). Assuming a success rate of 50% in the control group, a sample size of 103 and 103 for the two groups would have a power of 80% to detect a 20% absolute difference in success rates between the groups (50% versus 70%).
The data will be presented as mean (standard deviation) for normally distributed variables and median (interquartile range) when the distribution is skewed. The clinical characteristics and outcome variables will be analysed by using the Student t test for parametric and Mann-Whitney U test for nonparametric comparisons of continuous variables and Chi squared for categorical variables. P values will be 2-sided and P values of less than 0.05 will be considered statistically significant. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/02/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>210</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Peter Davis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Newborn Research,
The Royal Women's Hospital,
Locked Bag 300,
Corner of Grattan Street and Flemmington Road,
Parkville,
VIC 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council Program Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is looking at methods used to intubate (insert a breathing tube that connects to a ventilator) sick infants. The standard method, which has been used internationally for many years, involves the doctor first inserting a laryngoscope into the infants mouth. This is an L-shaped device with a light at the tip.  When it is manipulated correctly, it moves the infants tongue and jaw allowing a view of the infants airway. The doctor can then insert the breathing tube through the voice-box into the airway. This is a difficult procedure for doctors to learn and more than one attempt is often required to insert the breathing tube correctly. A more senior supervising doctor is usually present to assist during the procedure but is limited by the fact that he/she cannot see in the infants mouth. 
The devise being examined in this study is a videolaryngoscope. This is structurally the same as a traditional laryngoscope but displays real time images on to a nearby monitor. This essentially means that the assisting doctor can now see what the intubating doctor sees and can therefore potentially offer improved guidance and assistance. 
This is a randomised controlled trial and any infant at the Royal Womens Hospital, Melbourne, who requires intubation, is eligible for inclusion. If the infant is very sick and needs urgent intubation, they are excluded. All intubations in the study will be performed by neonatal registrars, who are junior doctors in training. The enrolled infants will be allocated randomly into the intervention group or the control group. In the intervention group, the registrar will attempt to intubate the infant using the videolaryngoscope and standard breathing tubes. A supervising doctor will be present and view the videolaryngoscope screen. They will offer instruction to the registrar based on the images they see. In the control group, the registrar will attempt to intubate using the videolaryngoscope and standard breathing tubes. However this time, the monitor will remain covered during the intubation attempt. The registrar will still be offered verbal guidance, as would be standard current practice. In both groups it will be recorded if the first attempt resulted in correct placement of the breathing tube. The main result of the study will be a comparison of the rate of correct tube placement between the two groups. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Women's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Women's Hospital,
Locked Bag 300,
Grattan St and Flemmington Road,
Parkville
VIC 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/05</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joyce O'Shea</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Research
Royal Women's Hospital,
Corner of Grattan St and Flemmington Road,
Parkville,
VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61383453775</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>joyce.oshea@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joyce O'Shea</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Research
Royal Women's Hospital,
Corner of Grattan St and Flemmington Road,
Parkville,
VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61383453775</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>joyce.oshea@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joyce O'Shea</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Research
Royal Women's Hospital,
Corner of Grattan St and Flemmington Road,
Parkville,
VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61383453775</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>joyce.oshea@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joyce O'Shea</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Research
Royal Women's Hospital,
Corner of Grattan St and Flemmington Road,
Parkville,
VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61383453775</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>joyce.oshea@thewomens.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>