<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320809">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/11/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/11/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000984291</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cough testing after stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Identifying Aspiration and Reducing Pneumonia in Stroke Patients using Cough Reflex Testing</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Health Research Council NZ 09/658</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dysphagia in stroke patients</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Identifying Aspiration and Reducing Pneumonia in Stroke Patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>For participants in the experimental group, the standard swallowing evaluation will be completed with the inclusion of cough reflex testing.  This will occur as a one -off intervention at the time of inital assessment.  Initially a placebo (0.9% Sodium choride (NaCl)) dose without citric acid will be presented to coach the participant on task completion.
The PulmoMate Compressor/Nebuliser by deVilbiss (model 4650I) with a predetermined flow output of 8 litres per minute will be turned on for a period of 15 sec.  
Presence of absence of cough during the period of administration will be documented. 
This test will be repeated three times with the same concentration at 30 sec intervals, with a 30 second interval between each inhalation to prevent tachyphylaxis. 
Cough reflex will be identified as present when participants cough on at least two out of the three inhalations. 
If patients cough readily on all three presentations of the lower concentration, the clinician will ask the patient to try to suppress the cough at this level. 
Participants will be asked to try to suppress the cough as much as they can. 
The suppressed cough threshold will be reached when participants cough at least two out of three inhalations. 

For patients assigned to the experimental condition, the cough reflex test will be administered using a face mask method which was recently  evaluated to establish normative data in New Zealand (NZ). These data, which have established the citric acid concentrations at which healthy individuals in two age groups (equal gender representation) produce a spontaneous cough and a suppressed cough, will be shortly available:
Monroe, M., Huckabee, M.L., Robb, M.P. (in progress). Citric-Acid Inhalation Cough Challenge  Establishing Normative Data. University of Canterbury, Swallowing Rehabilitation Research Laboratory at the Van der Veer Institute.</interventions>
    <comparator>For those in the standard evaluation group, clinical swallowing assessment will be executed as is defined by the clinical protocols of the Counties Manukau District Health Board (CMDHB) and Auckland District Health Board (ADHB) Speech and Language Therapy Departments. Management of swallowing impairment will proceed as per existing protocols based on recommendations from the clinical examination.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure will be the proportion of patents who are prescribed antibiotics for suspected or confimed chest symptomotology during the 3 months post discharge</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be assessed via chart review at 3 months post discharge by a clinical researcher</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of acute hospital stay in days</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be assessed via chart review at 3 months post discharge by a clinical researcher</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of patients with completed videofluoroscopic swallowing study or fibreoptic endoscopic evaluation of swallowing during acute admission or 3 month post acute period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be assessed via chart review at 3 months post discharge by a clinical researcher</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Route of intake at discharge (oral vs non-oral)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be assessed via chart review at 3 months post discharge by a clinical researcher</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diet restriction at discharge (thin vs thickened liquids; altered diet texture)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be assessed via chart review at 3 months post discharge by a clinical researcher</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of patients with bounce-back admissions for chest infection within 3 months post discharge from acute hospitalisation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcomes will be assessed via chart review at 3 months post discharge by a clinical researcher</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All stroke patients referred for clinical or diagnostic swallowing assessment from the two hospital sites will potentially be included in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients on mechanical ventilation for respiratory support will be excluded from the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Consenting participants will be randomly assigned to either a 1) standard evaluation group or 2) standard evaluation with inclusion of cough reflex testing. The group allocation was based on a computer-generated random numbers list. The randomisation schedule is held in the office of a researcher, remote from the study environments</concealment>
    <sequence>The group allocation is based on a computer-generated random numbers list.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Clinical Research and Effective Practice (CCRep)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Clinical Research 
and Effective Practice (CCRep)
PO Box 93311
Otahuhu, Auckland.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Health Research Council of New Zealand
Te Kaunihera Rangahau Hauora o Aotearoa
PO Box 5541 Wellesley Street, Auckland, New Zealand 1141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We propose to evaluate the usefulness of cough testing for reducing chest infection in patients with stroke. All inpatients referred to stroke services team and referred for swallowing evaluation in a 9 month period will be approached for participation in the study. Those participants who agree to participate will be randomly assigned to either a 1) standard evaluation group or 2) standard evaluation with inclusion of cough testing. For those in the experimental group, citric acid in a mist will be inhaled through a face mask to assess cough response. These results will contribute to usual clinical decision making. Outcomes for both groups will be measured by chest infection rates by 3 months post discharge and other clinical indicators of swallowing impairment. If successful in reducing complications associated with stroke, this test can be easily implemented without significant cost or resources and consequently reduce the impact of stroke on health status and quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Y Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>3rd floor, BNZ building 
354 Victoria St
PO Box 1031
Hamilton</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/11/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Maggie -Lee Huckabee</name>
      <address>Van der Veer Institute for Parkinson's and Brain Research
66 Stewart Street
Christchurch 
New Zealand  8011</address>
      <phone>64 (3) 378-6070; lab 64 (3) 378-6094;</phone>
      <fax>64 (3) 364-2760</fax>
      <email>maggie-lee.huckabee@canterbury.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Helen McLauchlan</name>
      <address>Professional Leader
Speech Language Therapy 
Counties Manukau District Health Board
Middlemore Hospital 
Private Bag 93311, Otahuhu
Auckland 1640</address>
      <phone>0064 9 2760044 x 5006</phone>
      <fax>0064 9 2704733</fax>
      <email>mclauch@middlemore.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>