<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308293">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/08/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000717257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can an acute dosage of Bacopa Monniera (brahmi) improve cognition, cardiovascular function and stress in a healthy older population</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Acute cognitive, cardiovascular and stress effects of Bacopa Monniera on healthy older human participants.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive function in healthy older individuals</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular function in healthy older individuals</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stress</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Herbal remedies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>2 X 150mg capsules Bacopa Monniera

Participants consume oral capsules after baseline testing on one day only (to test the acute effects)

Intervention and Placebo are administered in a randomised order with 1 week between treatments.</interventions>
    <comparator>2 X 150mg Avicel microcrystalline cellulose Participants consume 2 X150mg oral capsules after baseline testing on one day only. Intervention and Placebo are administered in a randomised order with 1 week between treatments.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive Function using Cognitive Drug Research (CDR) battery, Swinburne University Computerised Cognitive aging Battery (SUCCAB) battery</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 hours post dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiovascular function using transcranial doppler ultrasound and arterial stiffness measure (using sphygmocor system)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 hrs post dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stress/mood using multitasking battery to induce stress and mood questionnaires before and after stress task</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 2 hrs post dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Free from psychiatric disorders
- No neurological diseases
- Not suffering from endocrine, gastrointestinal or bleeding disorders
- No history of chronic illness/infection
- Not currently pregnant or lactating
- Must not be taking anticoagulants, antidepressants, antipsychotics, anxiolytics, acetylcholine esterase (AChE) inhibitors, anti-Parkinsons medication, illicit drugs or any cognitive enhancing drugs
- Must have corrected to normal vision
- Non smoker</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Smokers
- Psychiatric disorder
- Neurological diseases
- Suffering from endocrine, gastrointestinal or bleeding disorders
- A history of chronic illness/infection
- Pregnant or lactating
- Taking anticoagulants, antidepressants, antipsychotics, anxiolytics, AChE inhibitors, anti-Parkinsons medication, illicit drugs or any cognitive enhancing drugs
- Vision that is not normal or corrected to normal</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited through advertising and word of mouth. After successfully completing the phone screen, medical screen and practice session, they will be randomly allocated to receive either treatment A or B on their first testing day. This will be done by a randomised computer number sequence generator. On their second testing day, they will receive the other treatment. A disinterested third party will be responsible for the blinding procedure.</concealment>
    <sequence>A disinterested third party will generate the randomisation sequence using a computerised sequence generator</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Swinburne University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>400 Burwood Rd
Hawthorn VIC 3122</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Swinburne University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>400 Burwood Rd
Hawthorn VIC 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Bacopa Monnieri (BM) was first defined as a phytochemical brain tonic and touted to have the ability to improve memory, learning, and concentration for 3000 years (Zhou et al., 2007). Bacopa of late has had the statistical backing to support its cognitive enhancing capabilities (Calabrese et al., 2008) and since these findings BM has been trialled in a number of different settings offering new insights to its cognitive and physiological benefits. Investigations using BM on the response of elderly subjects uncovered significant cognitive improvements and a complete tolerability of the herb over a 12-week study (Calabrese et al. 2008). Elderly participants significantly improved their performance on learning tests and stroop tasks and showed decreases in Center for Epidemiologic Studies Short Depression Scale (CESD-10) depression scores and State-Trait Anxiety Indicator scores (STAI) scores. These studies allow us to hypothesize that cognitive improvements with the use of BM made after the age of 65 indicate its possible effectiveness on age related disorder (Calabrese et al. 2008; Barbhaiya et al.'s 2008).  No study has reported any adverse events that werent also experienced by placebo groups, indicating a high tolerability of the drug among healthy human subjects.

Furthermore using animal models, BM has been implicated in the amelioration of vascular dysfunction (Dar and Channa 1997), the decreased accumulation of beta-amyloid-42  (Holcomb et al. 2006) and acetylcholinesterase (Das et al. 2002), decreased levels of cholesterol (Anbarasi et al., 2005), and increased the activity of free radicals (Bhattacharya et al. 2000; Dhanasekaran et al. 2007) lessening the impact of oxidative stress associated with ageing and Alzheimers Dementia.

The study will be an acute double blind, placebo controlled, crossover design investigating stress levels, cardiovascular effects, aortic elasticity, and cognitive function in an older adult population. Participants are required to attend testing sessions on three occasions; one practice day and two subsequent testing days separated by a seven day washout period. On the first of the testing days the participants will be randomly assigned to either placebo or treatment group and will then crossover groups on the second testing day. Each testing day will consist of a battery of tests, followed by the administration of the drug and a two hour wait period, followed by a second round of battery testing. The results of both pre-treatment and post-treatment testing will be compared using a repeated measures analysis of variance contrasting both groups in each condition over several testing periods.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Swinburne University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 218
Hawthorn VIC 3122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>SUHREC 2009/136</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Con Stough</name>
      <address>400 Burwood Rd
Hawthorn VIC 3122</address>
      <phone>613 9214 8167</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cstough@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marni Kras</name>
      <address>400 Burwood Rd
Hawthorn VIC 3122</address>
      <phone>613 9214 5094</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nutra@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>