<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365480">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000013662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Do Treatment Interventions for Obstructive Sleep Apnoea Reduce Depressive Symptoms in Patients with Comorbid Depression?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) Treatment for Obstructive Sleep Apnoea improve Depression?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>COSAD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnoea</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>CPAP therapy. CPAP treatment involves wearing a mask that is attached to a pump that forces air into the airway to hold the airway open during sleep. The dosage will be individually determined during an in-laboratory CPAP implementation sleep study at the start of the trial. This treatment should be used every night, for 12 months for the CPAP group, or 8 months for the wait-list group. Usage data is recorded automatically by the device and can be downloaded by the researchers at each visit. The CPAP group will be provided with a 1-hour CPAP and sleep education session by a sleep scientist or psychologist (either one-on-one or in small groups), a CPAP information booklet,  and follow up phone call from a sleep scientist after night 1 and night 7 at home to troubleshoot any problems (~5 minutes duration). The treatment as usual (TAU) group will receive CPAP without additional follow up procedures or education.</interventions>
    <comparator>Wait-list for 4 months, after which this group will receive the CPAP treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression score - (Center for Epidemiology - Depression scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 2, 4 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daytime Sleepiness (Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 2, 4 and 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotional Reactivity Scale and Difficulties in Emotional Regulation Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 2, 4, 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Untreated OSA patients who have been recommended to start CPAP therapy; English fluency; not pregnant or possibility of being pregnant; CES-D score &gt;16. Patients with a current clinical diagnosis of depression, and who are on antidepressants will also be included.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>History of or current psychiatric or medical condition (except depression) including epilepsy, recent stroke, myocardial infarction (in last 6 months); excessive daytime sleepiness (ESS&gt;16); head injury with loss of consciousness &gt;15 mins; learning disability; alcohol or drug dependence; shiftwork; and any neurological disorder or inability to complete the trial at the judgment of the clinician investigator. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be stratified by depression and daytime sleepiness score, and randomized into one of three conditions:  a new CPAP treatment group (CBT), the current CPAP treatment group (TAU) or a wait-list group. Group allocation is concealed between the TAU and CBT groups. Allocation is conducted via centralized randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>After each subject has been assessed for depression and sleepiness, they will be assigned a random number using an on-line number generator program into the CPAP, TAU or wait-list group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Partial cross-over - CPAP group will not cross over to waitlist.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>An intention-to-treat principle will be employed. Statistical analysis will be in the form of a repeated measures ANCOVA model with CES-D score, memory sensitivity and sleepiness as the primary outcome measures, with baseline depression score as a covariate. Treatment group (CPAP vs TAU vs. wait list) and time (1, 2, 4 and 12 months) will be included in the model as independent variables. Secondary analyses will be performed to evaluate effect modification across levels of the depression stratification factor (MDD vs. mild-no depression) to examine a potential interaction between treatment group and baseline depression category. Regression analyses will be conducted to determine whether quality of relationship, personality and/or depression scores at baseline differ between those participants who continue CPAP and those who stop treatment. 

We plan to recruit 120 OSA patients. This sample size is calculated assuming an SD of 8 for change in CES-D score over 3 months as estimated using individual patient data (Baron, Smith et al. 2008). A change in CES-D score of 5 or more constitutes a clinically significant change (Jacobson and Truax 1991). Therefore, we need a total 33 patients in each group to detect an effect size of 5, assuming an SD of 8, Beta = 0.80 and alpha less than or equal to 0.05. We estimate 20% attrition; therefore we will recruit 40 participants in each group.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/01/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>19/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Redmond Barry Building
Level 12
Parkville, Vic, 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Redmond Barry Building
Level 12
Parkville, Vic, 3010
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Austin Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Austin Health
145 - 163 Studley Rd
Heidelberg 3084 VIC</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Austin Health</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Studley Rd Heidelberg, Vic, 3084</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obstructive Sleep Apnoea (OSA) is a common respiratory disease, caused by collapse of the airway during sleep, which produces oxygen desaturations and sleep disruption. OSA is associated with cognitive deficits, reduced quality of life, and depressed mood. The prevalence of both depressive symptoms and major depressive disorder (MDD) are significantly higher in OSA patients compared to the general community. Currently there is little clinical evidence to support whether treatment of OSA improves depressive symptoms in OSA patients with comorbid depressive symptoms or MDD. The aim of this study is to determine whether CPAP treatment improves depressive symptoms and cognitive functioning over the short and long term. This project is a prospective, randomised controlled trial of an  enhanced CPAP treatment program for OSA patients with comorbid MDD and depressive symptoms, compared to a wait list control group, and treatment as usual. This study will provide much-needed clinical evidence of the efficacy of CPAP therapy for improving both depression and cognitive functioning in OSA.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Studley Rd Heidelberg, Vic, 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>05076</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Melinda Jackson</name>
      <address>RMIT University
School of Health Sciences
RMIT University
P.O. Box 71 
Bundoora, VIC 3083</address>
      <phone>+61399257564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>melinda.jackson@rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Melinda Jackson</name>
      <address>RMIT University
School of Health Sciences
RMIT University
P.O. Box 71 
Bundoora, VIC 3083</address>
      <phone>+61399257564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>melinda.jackson@rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Melinda Jackson</name>
      <address>RMIT University
School of Health Sciences
RMIT University
P.O. Box 71 
Bundoora, VIC 3083</address>
      <phone>+61399257564</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>melinda.jackson@rmit.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>