<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362026">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000145808</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A comparison of two commercially-available eye drops on corneal epithelial cell shedding when eye drops are used in one eye for two weeks in healthy participants</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective, randomised validation of corneal epithelial cell-counting with two instruments after 4 hours of bilateral contact lens wear and a prospective, randomised, masked, parallel group comparison of two commercially-available tear supplements utilising different preservatives, on corneal epithelial cell shedding when tear supplements are used unilaterally for two weeks</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Corneal epithelium cell shedding</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is divided into two stages. Participants can complete just one stage or both stages. 
Stage 1: Five participants will undergo a baseline visit and three further scheduled visits (visits 1, 2, and 3). At each visit, visual acuity will be measured and the ocular surface will be assessed. 
-Baseline: The corneal surface of each eye will be gently washed with a saline rinse and shed corneal epithelial cells are collected in the retained solution. This procedure is performed to familiarise the participant to the eye wash procedure.
-Visit 1: Following a 48 hour wash-out (no use of contact lenses or ocular eye drops) participants will have the corneal surface of each eye gently washed with a saline rinse and shed corneal epithelial cells are collected in the retained solution. These corneal epithelial cells will be counted using two instruments, the confocal microscopy (manual cell count) and the flow-cytometer (semi-automated cell count), with instrument allocated for each eye by randomisation.
-Visit 2: Following a 48 hour wash-out (no use of contact lenses or ocular eye drops) plano (lens with no power)PureVision [Registered trade mark] contact lenses soaked overnight in renu [Registered trade mark] fresh [Trade mark] solution are inserted bilaterally.
-Visit 3: Lenses are removed four hours after insertion and the corneal surface of each eye will be gently washed with a saline rinse and shed corneal epithelial cells are collected in the retained solution. These corneal epithelial cells will be counted using two instruments, the confocal microscope (manual cell count) and the flow-cytometer (semi-automated cell count), with instrument allocated for each eye by randomisation.
Stage 2: Twenty participants will undergo a baseline visit and two further scheduled visits (visits 1 and 2). At each visit, visual acuity will be measured and the ocular surface will be assessed.
-Baseline: The corneal surface of each eye will be gently washed with a saline rinse and shed corneal epithelial cells are collected in the retained solution. This procedure is performed to familiarise the participant to the eye wash procedure. If participant has completed stage 1, this procedure is not repeated. Participants are randomly allocated either Revital Eyes [Registered trade mark] (preservative- BAK) or Refresh Tears Plus [Registered trade mark] (preservative-purite), lubricating eye drops. These will be used four times per day for two weeks unilaterally (in one eye only), with the eye designated for eye drop use randomly allocated.
-Visit 1: After 7 days of unilateral eye drop use, the corneal surface of each eye will be gently washed with a saline rinse and shed corneal epithelial cells are collected in the retained solution. These corneal epithelial cells for eye will be counted using flow-cytometry.
-Visit 2: After 14 days of unilateral eye drop use, the corneal surface of each eye will be gently washed with a saline rinse and shed corneal epithelial cells are collected in the retained solution. These corneal epithelial cells for eye will be counted using flow-cytometry.</interventions>
    <comparator>Stage 1: The manual method of cell counting will be the control. Comparisons will be made between the two instruments.

Stage 2: The number of cells shed in the eye not using lubricating eye drops will be the control. Comparisons will be made for each eye drop between the control and also between eye drops.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if there is a difference in corneal epithelial cell shedding between eyes exposed to tear-supplements preserved with either BAK or Purite. Epithelial cells shed in the retained solution from the ocular saline wash will be passed through the Attune Acoustic focussing Flow cytometer and cells will be counted using Attune Flow cytometer software</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 7 and 14 days of lubricating eye drop use</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To validate the flow-cytometer as a method of counting collected human corneal epithelial cells</outcome>
      <timepoint>After 4 hours of contact lens wear</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent.
-Be at least 18 years old, male or female.
-Willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the Investigator.
-Have ocular health findings considered to be normal and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses.
-Be an experienced contact lens wearer (but willing to not wear contact lenses for the duration of the trial, except, during stage visits 2-3) or a non lens wearer (but willing to wear plano lenses for approximately four hours on one day during stage 1 visits 2-3).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including infection or disease) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses.
-Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves disease, and auto immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjögrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosus.  Conditions such as systemic hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants.
-Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication at enrolment and/or during the clinical trial.
-Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings / are known to affect a participants ocular health / physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse or beneficial manner at enrolment and/or during the clinical trial. 
NB: Systemic antihistamines are allowed on an as needed basis, provided they are not used prophylactically during the trial and at least 24 hours before the clinical trial product is used.
-Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial.
-Previous corneal refractive surgery.
-Known allergy or intolerance to ingredients in any of the clinical trial products.
-Currently enrolled in another clinical trial.
-Participation in a clinical trial within the previous 2 weeks for dispensing studies and 48 hours between in-house studies.
-Not willing to not wear contact lenses for the duration of the clinical trial.
-Pregnancy* (either at enrolment or during the course of the trial). Formal testing of pregnancy is not required. A participants verbal report is sufficient
-The Investigator may, at his / her discretion, exclude anyone who they believe may not be able to fulfil the clinical trial requirements or it is believed to be in the participants best interests.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/02/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Allergan, Inc</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>2525 Dupont Drive, Irvine, 
CA 92612-1599</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building Gate 14, Barker
Street University of New South Wales, NSW
2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>this trial will investigate the effect of preservatives in comfort eye-drops on corneal epithelial cells</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker
Street,
The University of New South Wales
SYDNEY NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 6165</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker
Street,
The University of New South Wales
SYDNEY NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 6165</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker
Street,
The University of New South Wales
SYDNEY NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 6165</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>