<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335579">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000999033</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of pneumococcal conjugate vaccine in preventing acquisition and carriage of pneumococcal vaccine serotypes in Tanzanian children with human immunodeficiency virus/ acquired immunodeficiency syndrome  (HIV/AIDS)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of pneumococcal conjugate vaccine in preventing acquisition and carriage of pneumococcal vaccine serotypes in Tanzanian children withhuman immunodeficiency virus/ acquired immunodeficiency syndrome  (HIV/AIDS)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1115-4400</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pneumococcal disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>HIV/AIDS</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Pneumococcal vaccination 
1
a) containing two microgram of Pneumococcal polysaccharide
serotypes 4, 9V, 14, 18C, 19F, 23F, and four micrograms of pneumococcal polysaccharide serotype 6B. It also contains sodium chloride and water for injections.
b) two identical vaccines will be administered three months apart. 
c) administered as a intramuscular injection
2
At the fourth visit to the clinic children will be given the first dose of the vaccine they have not yet received. That is children will be given four vaccinations over nine months. Firstly two doses of either control or intervention vaccine then two doses of the other vaccine in succession. There is three months between the final dose of the first type of vaccine and the first dose of the second, there is not usually a wash out in these studies.  Children will be randomly allocated to receive control or treatment vaccine first. All children in the study will receive both vaccines only the order will vary.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control vaccine Haemophilus influenzae (Hib) (Act-HIB(registered trademark)- Aventis Pasteur
Quadrace)
1
a) contains Pertussis Vaccine Combined with Diphtheria and Tetanus Toxoids combinedwith Inactivated Poliomyelitis Vaccine, the solution contains 0.6% +/- 0.1%2-phenoxyethanol as preservative
b) two identical vaccines will be administered three months apart. 
c) administered as a intramuscular injection
2
At the fourth visit to the clinic children will be given the first dose of the vaccine they have not yet received. That is children will be given four vaccinations over nine months. Firstly two doses of either control or intervention vaccine then two doses of the other vaccine. Children will be randomly allocated to receive control or treatment vaccine first. All children in the study will receive both vaccines only the order will vary.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nasopharyngeal carriage of vaccine serotypes. 

A nasopharyngeal swab will be obtained at the 0, 3, 6 and 9-month visit, prior to administration of the vaccine dose. Samples will be collected and processed according to the WHO working group standard methods for detecting upper respiratory carriage of S. pneumoniae and the WHO Laboratory Manual for the Diagnosis of Meningitis Caused by Neisseria meningitidis, S. pneumoniae, and H. influenzae. A paediatric calcium alginate tipped aluminium swab will be inserted through the nose into the nasopharynx, and rotated gently through 180 degrees. The swab will be placed into 1ml of Skim milk tryptone-glucose-glycerin (STGG) transport medium, made according to WHO methods.

Swabs will then be taken directly to the laboratory where they will be frozen at minus 70C until culture.  Culturing will take place on 5g/ml gentamicin in sheeps blood agar. 

20l of the sample will be streaked onto a plate, incubated at 35C in CO2 for two days, using a candle jar, as pneumococcus grows best under anaerobic conditions. Any samples that showing growth will then be subcultured up to four times, depending on how many colonies are present.  Samples are then subcultured onto blood agar.

Facilities for serotyping are currently not available in Tanzania.  Samples will be serotyped at the Kenya Medical Research Institute (KMRI) in Kilifi in Kenya by Quellung reaction. PCR serotyping at Westmead Hospital in Australia, will give us information on multiple serotype carriage.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6 and 9 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Antibody response to vaccination If blood has been taken for other serologic tests then any sera left over, with the permission of the patient and parents, will be placed in EDTA tubes and frozen at -20 degrees Celsius. It will be transferred to CIDM laboratories at Westmead hospital for enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay tests to measure antibody response to the vaccine.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 3, 6 and 9 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>HIV positive children aged 1-14 years old</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous vaccination</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>HIV-positive children will be recruited when they present for routine follow-up to the clinic (usually every 1 to 3 months) and also when presenting with an illness. During each visit to The Diana Centre, they will be assessed for their need of treatment. Medical care will be provided according to national guidelines. Patients with severe disease or requiring urgent care will be transferred to the appropriate area in the hospital where this will be provided. 
The following procedures will be performed:
ascertain participant eligibility,
explain the purpose of the study,
obtain written informed consent for study participation
complete the case report form 
obtain and process a nasopharyngeal swab,
vaccinate the participant,
record epidemiological and treatment information from notes. 
Only children with a written informed consent form, signed/thumb-printed by parents/guardians will be screened.
 
Participant eligibility will be ascertained through a checklist. Then the parent/guardian of the child will be requested to read the Kiswahili (local language) information sheet and informed consent form or these will be read to them. If informed consent to participate is provided, data will be collected through interview and from the patient’s medical notes. Information will be recorded in a standardised Case Report Form (CRF). The CRF is designed to investigate baseline data, such as presenting symptoms, HIV-history, socio-economic status and prophylactic and therapeutic medications. Height and weight will be measured by standard methods using calibrated scales.

As participants are recruited they will be allocated to the infant group (less than five years) or the school aged group (greater than or equal to five years). Random numbers will be generated via Excel these will then be put into brown security envelopes and stored in a file. An envelope will be taken from the file. Depending on whether this contains odd or an even number they will be assigned to receiving PCV or Hib as the first 2 doses.</concealment>
    <sequence>As participants are recruited they will be allocated to the infant group (less than five years) or the school aged group (greater than or equal to five years). Random numbers will be generated via specific statistical software these will then be put into brown security envelopes and stored in a file. An envelope will be taken from the file. Depending on whether this contains odd or an even number they will be assigned to receiving pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV) or Hib as the first 2 doses.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>216</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Tanzania, United Republic Of</country>
      <state>Muheza</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Robert Booy</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Centre for Immunisation Research and Surveillance of Vaccine Preventable Diseases (NCIRS)
The Children's Hospital at Westmead Cnr Hawkesbury Rd &amp; Hainsworth St, Westmead
Post: Locked Bag 4001, Westmead NSW 2145, Australia
T: +61 2 9845 1433
F: +61 2 9845 1418</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Prof Robert Booy</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Centre for Immunisation Research and Surveillance of Vaccine Preventable Diseases (NCIRS)
The Children's Hospital at Westmead Cnr Hawkesbury Rd &amp; Hainsworth St, Westmead
Post: Locked Bag 4001, Westmead NSW 2145, Australia
T: +61 2 9845 1433
F: +61 2 9845 1418</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a randomised controlled trial of a pneumococcal conjugate vaccine  to examine the efficacy of this vaccine in preventing the nasopharyngeal acquisition and carriage of vaccine serotypes of pneumococcus, among Tanzanian children with HIV/AIDS. Prevention of nasopharyngeal carriage can be used as a surrogate for vaccine protective efficacy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/05/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof Robert Booy</name>
      <address>National Centre for Immunisation Research and Surveillance of Vaccine Preventable Diseases
The Children's Hospital at Westmead Cnr Hawkesbury Rd &amp; Hainsworth St, Westmead
Post: Locked Bag 4001, Westmead NSW 2145, Australia

T: +61 2 9845 1433
F: +61 2 9845 1418</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 1415</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>RobertB2@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof Robert Booy</name>
      <address>National Centre for Immunisation Research and Surveillance of Vaccine Preventable Diseases
The Children's Hospital at Westmead Cnr Hawkesbury Rd &amp; Hainsworth St, Westmead
Post: Locked Bag 4001, Westmead NSW 2145, Australia

T: +61 2 9845 1433
F: +61 2 9845 1418</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 1415</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>RobertB2@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof Robert Booy</name>
      <address>National Centre for Immunisation Research and Surveillance of Vaccine Preventable Diseases
The Children's Hospital at Westmead Cnr Hawkesbury Rd &amp; Hainsworth St, Westmead
Post: Locked Bag 4001, Westmead NSW 2145, Australia

T: +61 2 9845 1433
F: +61 2 9845 1418</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 1415</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>RobertB2@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>