<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369729">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000133437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Increasing toddlers' vegetable consumption through interactive shared reading of a vegetable-promoting picture book and puppetry.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Promoting toddlers vegetable consumption through interactive shared reading and puppetry.
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Vegetable consumption</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Overweight</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>STUDY DESIGN:
The intervention used in this experimental study consisted of shared reading a picture book about a rabbit that loves to eat carrots. The study had a 2 (reading style: passive vs. interactive) x 2 (puppet use: without vs. with hand puppet) between-subjects design. Toddlers (2-3 years old) were randomly assigned to one of these four conditions. During the interactive reading sessions, children were asked questions about the story, whereas no questions were asked during the passive reading sessions. Both types of shared reading were either performed with a puppet resembling the main book character (rabbit) or without a puppet.

PROCEDURE:
Reading sessions were conducted in a quiet room within the nursery school during one week. Because Dutch nursery schools are closed on Wednesday afternoon, the readings took place on Monday, Tuesday, Thursday, and Friday (thus, the intervention ran for one week only, with children participating in four reading sessions in total). The reading sessions took about ten minutes, each consisting of approximately four toddlers. Since there were no attendance requirements at the schools, the composition of shared reading groups could differ within the same condition. Toddlers were given name stickers, which facilitated observers to fill out a checklist of childrens behaviors shown during the reading sessions. Moreover, name stickers facilitated the storyteller to ask questions to the children during interactive shared reading. After the fourth reading session (on Friday), the dependent variable was measured with an eating task, in which toddlers could freely eat snacks for five minutes. 
For the reading sessions, four young females with a pedagogical background were recruited and trained in the different reading styles and puppetry. These storytellers were teamed up with four female experimenters who observed the toddlers during the readings. The observers were trained in filling out the checklist, and observed the children from a distance to prevent session disruptions.</interventions>
    <comparator>The group in which children were read passively without the puppet was compared to all the other conditions, and thus considered as control group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CARROT CONSUMPTION:
Toddlers were presented with 4 equal-sized bowls, each containing 4 pieces of a different snack. They could choose from 2 healthy snacks (carrots &amp; cucumber), and 2 unhealthy snacks (cheese &amp; salted sticks). It was counted how many pieces of each product toddlers had eaten after the maximum 5 minutes had elapsed. The proportion of consumed carrots was calculated by dividing the pieces of carrots the child had eaten by the total amount of pieces of foods the child had eaten.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After exposure to the intervention (i.e., after 4 days of reading)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CHARACTER IMITATION:
Observers registered the poses that toddlers physically imitated from the book characters during reading (e.g., eating carrots, being strong). The number of poses demonstrated were summed to create a single measure of character imitation, with a higher score indicating more character imitation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Observed during each reading, thus 4 times, on Monday, Tuesday, Thursday, and Friday.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Boys and girls aged 2-3 years without food allergies.
- From nursery schools without formal fruit and vegetable programs, with children from mostly low-SES households.
- Nursary schools provided active consent, and parents provided passive consent for their children. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>3</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nursery schools with formal fruit and vegetable programs, children with food allergies.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Each nursery group was randomly assigned to the condition 'without puppet' or 'with puppet'.  Within each group, children were randomly assigned to the condition 'interactive reading' or 'passive reading'.  The independent researcher focused on having an equal amount of children within each experimental condition.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The targeted sample size was based on previous studies that demonstrated effects of picture books on young children's consumption (i.e., around 100 - 150). We targeted 200 children, and were able to recruit 199, with a drop-out of 36 toddlers. Thus, total sample was 163, still higher than the average sample size within this research domain. 
The analyses used were: univariate analysis of variances (ANOVA's) with Eta-squared (?2) to determine effect sizes, Pearson's correlations, and mediation analyses according to the specifications set out by Hayes PROCESS for SPSS (using 95% bias-corrected bootstrap confidence intervals).
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>16/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>27/03/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>199</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Radboud University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Address for visitors: 
Thomas van Aquinostraat 8
6525 GD Nijmegen

Postal address: 
P.O. Box 9104
6500 HE Nijmegen</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Netherlands</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dutch Ministry of Health, Welfare and Sport (VWS)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Address for visitors:
Parnassusplein 5 
2511 VX Den Haag

Postal address:
P.O. Box 20350 
2500 EJ The Hague</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Netherlands</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Worldwide the number of overweight children is still rising. While vegetable consumption before the age of 7 has shown to be an important prevention factor, children are not eating the required amount. To make healthy eating more fun, picture books with engaging characters are being used to promote vegetable consumption. These types of books have shown to increase the vegetable consumption of preschoolers (aged 4-6 years) when read interactively, meaning that questions about the story are asked to the child during reading. With governments increasingly focusing on younger audiences, the current study investigated whether interactive shared reading of a vegetable-promoting picture book also increases the vegetable consumption of toddlers (aged 2-3 years) or whether a hand puppet as additional tool is needed. 
The impact of vegetable-promoting picture books was tested with a book about a rabbit that is able to rescue his friend only after eating carrots to make him strong. In addition, a hand puppet was developed resembling the main book character. The study had a 2 (reading style: passive vs. interactive) x 2 (puppet use: no vs. yes) between-subjects design. In the interactive reading condition children were asked questions about the story, whereas no questions were asked in the passive condition. Both types of shared reading were either performed with a puppet resembling the main book character (rabbit) or without a puppet. In the puppet condition, the storyteller would have the puppet listen to the story, pointing out pictures in the book, imitating the movements shown in the pictures, and speak the characters lines from the book. 163 Toddlers in nursery schools were randomly assigned to the conditions. They were read to in small groups and observed on 4 consecutive days. During the observations, narrative involvement and character imitation was registered. On the last day, carrot consumption was measured with an eating task, in which toddlers could freely eat snacks for 5 minutes. The results of the study will be published in a scientific journal. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>De Droog, S. M., Govers, M., Van Nee, R., &amp; Buijzen M. (2015, February). Promoting toddlers vegetable consumption through interactive shared reading and puppetry. Paper presented at the annual convention of the Netherlands School of Communication Research, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee Social Sciences of Radboud University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Montessorilaan 3
6525 HP Nijmegen</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/01/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/01/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Netherlands</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Simone M. de Droog</name>
      <address>Radboud University
Communication Science
P.O. Box 9104
6500 HE Nijmegen</address>
      <phone>+(31)(0)243612372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.dedroog@maw.ru.nl</email>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Simone M. de Droog</name>
      <address>Radboud University
Communication Science
P.O. Box 9104
6500 HE Nijmegen</address>
      <phone>+(31)(0)243612372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.dedroog@maw.ru.nl</email>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Simone M. de Droog</name>
      <address>Radboud University
Communication Science
P.O. Box 9104
6500 HE Nijmegen</address>
      <phone>+(31)(0)243612372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.dedroog@maw.ru.nl</email>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Simone M. de Droog</name>
      <address>Radboud University
Communication Science
P.O. Box 9104
6500 HE Nijmegen</address>
      <phone>+(31)(0)243612372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.dedroog@maw.ru.nl</email>
      <country>Netherlands</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>