<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364885">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000994785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Is walking really the best therapy for walking recovery after stroke?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is the recovery of walking velocity and symmetry after stroke enhanced more by balance strength and coordination training than by treadmill training?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Walking recovery after stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Walking rehabilitation using individualised balance, strength and coordination training conducted by a physiotherapist during 12 x 30-minute sessions over 4-weeks.
Simple equipment such as Therabands, chairs, and balls will be used for this training. The therapy will include both upper and lower limb tasks. Since each training session for each patient is conducted by a physiotherapist adherence will be inherent.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Walking rehabilitation using treadmill walking training supervised by a physiotherapist during 12 x 30-minute sessions over 4-weeks. The highest treadmill velocity each patient can safely maintain over a 20-30 minute period will be chosen. 
Since each training session for each patient is conducted by a physiotherapist adherence will be inherent. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fast self-selected walking speed using the 10 m walk test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At two-month followup visit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depth of reciprocal inhibition between ankle effectors using 1 ms pulse-width suprathreshold electrical stimulation of an antagonist's mixed peripheral nerve on EMG recorded from weak tonic contraction of the agonist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two-month followup visit.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stroke Specific Quality of Life Scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Two-month followup visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spatiotemporal gait measures will be measured using a 5 m long GaitRite instrumented mat.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two-month followup visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>TMS-conditioned H-reflexes measure the strength of conductivity between motor cortex and spinal circuits. Transcranial magnetic stimulation is delivered to the lower limb motor cortex at a point in time that allows the descending volley to arrive at the spinal cord circuitry when an H-reflex is being generated at the spinal cord level. H-reflexes are elicited in the soleus muscle using electrical stimulation of the posterior tibial nerve. The extent of modulation of the TMS conditioned H-reflex can be taken as a measure of cortex to spinal cord conductivity.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Two-month followup visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Between 3 months and 2 years post-stroke
Overground gait velocity between 0.6 and 1.0 m/s 

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Less than 3 months or greater than 2 years post-stroke
Patient receiving other walking therapy
Brain stem stroke
Orthopaedic conditions that would affect gait patterns 
Co-morbidities that would restrict walking such as cardio-pulmonary disease and morbid obesity
Vision deficits, apraxia, or neglect that would be a barrier to training
Mini-Mental State Exam score &lt; 20
Cognitive or communication deficits that preclude informed consent and study engagement
Contraindications to TMS</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The blinded assessing physiotherapist will randomise and minimise subjects into two groups using custom-written software. This allocation concealment process removes any bias to group randomisation and automates the balancing of independent variables. 
Minimisation of the following variables will be achieved: 
Gender
Age
Time-since-stroke (months)
Dichotomised self-selected overground walking velocity
Lower extremity Fugl-Meyer score</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated minimisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A power analysis was conducted using a minimal clinically important difference in gait velocity of 0.16 m/s and a reported variance of 0.2 from the LEAPS study. With an alpha of 0.05 and a sample size of 20, the power was 0.95. Recruiting 25 for each group will allow for some dropout. 
Data will first be assessed for normality using Kolmogorov-Smirnov tests. Baseline data (A1, A2, A3) will be assessed for significant pre-intervention group differences. Pre-intervention baseline data (A1, A2, A3) will be analysed with two-way mixed effects analyses of variance (time and group), and main effects will be investigated using Tukeys HSD post hoc tests. Pre- to post-intervention and retention period data (A3, A4, A5, A6) will be analysed with mixed-effects analyses of variance (time and group). Main effects will be investigated using Tukeys HSD post hoc tests. If baseline data do not reveal an effect of time, data will be collapsed across all three time-points, otherwise only the last baseline data will be used in the analysis of variance. Data that are not normally distributed will be analysed with Friedman tests for effects of time, and Mann-Whitney U tests for effects of group. A significance level of 0.5 will be adopted for all analyses.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>27/05/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Applications pending to the Neurological Foundation of NZ</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>66 Grafton Road, Grafton
PO Box 110022, Auckland Hospital
Auckland 1148</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Regaining independence is a prized goal for stroke survivors. Crucial to independence is an ability to walk safely in the community. It is therefore important to identify the most effective components of walking therapy. It is equally important that we understand the way the nervous system drives walking recovery after stroke. The study will test the hypothesis that balance, strength and coordination training is as effective, or more effective, than treadmill walking alone. Changes in nervous system activity associated with walking recovery will also be assessed. Study outcomes are expected to inform therapy design and the distribution of clinical resources. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/10/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James Stinear</name>
      <address>University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737599 ext 82378</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.stinear@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James Stinear</name>
      <address>University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737599 ext 82378</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.stinear@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James Stinear</name>
      <address>University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737599 ext 82378</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.stinear@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James Stinear</name>
      <address>University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737599 ext 82378</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.stinear@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>