<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368728">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/12/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001701415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing the effect of Nasal High Flow (NHF) therapy with Non-invasive ventilation (NIV) on carbon dioxide levels in Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) patients with chronic respiratory failure</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparing the effect of Nasal High Flow (NHF) therapy with Non-invasive ventilation (NIV) on PaCO2 in COPD patients with chronic respiratory failure</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1188-6144</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Nasal high flow (NHF) therapy, via the myAIRVO 2 device at 45 Litres per minute, 37 degrees for 60 minutes at the Medical Research Institute of New Zealand Respiratory Physiology Lab. This involves breathing heated and humidified room air (and oxygen if required)  through the nasal interface (nasal prongs which sit inside both nostrils). Oxygen, if required, will be administered through the device and titrated by the investigator to maintain saturations 88-92%. 

There will be a 30 minute wash-in period before starting Intervention 1 where oxygen will be administered, if required, and titrated by the investigator to maintain saturations of 88-92%. The oxygen flow at the end of this wash-in will be used at the start of Intervention 1.

There will be a 15 minute washout period between interventions and recordings will continue during this time. The washout will be extended until the PtCO2 returns to within 4mmHg of t=0 recording of intervention 1. </interventions>
    <comparator>Non-invasive ventilation, via Bi-level Positive Airways Pressure at 15cmH2O inspiratory positive airways pressure (IPAP) and 4 cmH2O expiratory positive airways pressure, for 60 minutes at the Medical Research Institute of New Zealand Respiratory Physiology Lab . This involves breathing room air (and oxygen if required)  through the mask interface. Oxygen, if required, will be administered through the device and titrated by the investigator to maintain saturations 88-92%. IPAP setting may be altered, down to a minimum of 10cmH2O if not tolerable at 15 cmH2O.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Transcutaneous partial pressure of carbon dioxide (PtCO2)  at 60 minutes adjusted for baseline. Nb: Baseline is the measurement taken at t=0 at the start of each intervention. Intervention number 2 will have a baseline +/- 4mmHg from baseline for Intervention 1. This will be measured on a Sentec transcutaneous monitor. </outcome>
      <timepoint>60 minutes</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PtCO2 at 5 minute intervals during the intervention, adjusted for baseline. Note: Baseline is the measurement taken at t=0 at the start of each intervention. Intervention number 2 will have a baseline +/- 4mmHg from baseline for Intervention 1. This will be measured on a Sentec transcutaneous monitor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 minute intervals (t=5, t=10, t=15 up to t=60) and at the end of the subsequent 15 minute washout period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients that have a decrease in PtCO2 by greater than or equal to 4mmHg  compared to baseline. This will be measured on a Sentec transcutaneous monitor. 
Note: Baseline is the measurement taken at t=0 at the start of each intervention. Intervention 2 will have a baseline +/- 4mmHg from baseline for Intervention 1. </outcome>
      <timepoint>60 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxygen saturation at 5 minute intervals during the intervention, adjusted for baseline*.
* Baseline is the measurement taken at t=0 at the start of each intervention. Intervention number 2 will have a baseline +/- 4mmHg from baseline for Intervention 1. This will be measured on a Sentec transcutaneous monitor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 minute intervals (t=5, t=10, t=15 up to and including t=60) and at the end of the subsequent 15 minute washout period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate at 5 minute intervals during the intervention, adjusted for baseline*.
* Baseline is the measurement taken at t=0 at the start of each intervention. Intervention number 2 will have a baseline +/- 4mmHg from baseline for Intervention 1. This will be measured on a Sentec transcutaneous monitor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 minute intervals (t=5, t=10, t=15 up to and including t=60) and at the end of the subsequent 15 minute washout period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory rate at 5 minute intervals during the intervention, adjusted for baseline*.
* Baseline is the measurement taken at t=0 at the start of each intervention. Intervention number 2 will have a baseline +/- 4mmHg from baseline for Intervention 1. This will be counted by the Unblinded investigator over the preceding 1 minute before each 5 minute time-point.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 minute intervals (t=5, t=10, t=15 up to and including t=60) and at the end of the subsequent 15 minute washout period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants who withdrew from the interventions before completion. </outcome>
      <timepoint>60 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tolerability questionnaire (designed for the study)  results </outcome>
      <timepoint>Tolerability questionnaires will be administered at the end of each intervention in the washout period. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>BORG dyspnoea score results</outcome>
      <timepoint>BORG dyspnoea score will be measured immediately prior and immediately after each intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients that have a decrease in PtCO2 by greater than or equal to 8mmHg  compared to baseline. This will be measured on a Sentec transcutaneous monitor. 
Note: Baseline is the measurement taken at t=0 at the start of each intervention. Intervention 2 will have a baseline +/- 4mmHg from baseline for Intervention 1. </outcome>
      <timepoint>60 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	A doctors diagnosis of COPD
2.	 PcapCO2 &gt;45mmHg on Capillary blood gas, at point of randomisation
3.	Age greater than or equal to 40 years old. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Smoking pack year history &lt;10 years
2.	FEV1/FVC greater than or equal to 70%
3.	Body mass index &gt;35
4.	Hypercapnea believed to be primarily due to Obesity Hypoventilation syndrome and/or Obstructive Sleep Apnoea
5.	Any condition which makes NIV contra-indicated as per BTS guidelines.
6.	Requiring greater than or equal to 4 L/min through standard nasal cannulae during the wash-in period to maintain oxygen saturations 88-92%.
7.	COPD not deemed to be stable:
a.	Current exacerbation requiring acute treatment with a short course of antibiotics/oral steroids within the last 2 weeks.
b.	Hospital admission for an acute exacerbation of COPD in the last 6 weeks.
8.	Nasal conditions such as deviated septum, chronic rhinitis, current cold/flu which, in the evaluation by the investigator, could impair nasal breathing.
9.	Any other condition, which at the investigators discretion, is believed may present a safety risk or impact the feasibility of the study or study results.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be considered enrolled and part of the study population at the time the Consent Form has been filled in by both the Participant and Study Investigator. The Blinded Investigator responsible for documenting PtCO2, heart rate and oxygen saturations, will be blinded to which  intervention the participant is receiving by a screen. A second Unblinded Investigator will be responsible for opening an opaque envelope containing the randomised treatment, applying, administering the randomised treatment, recording respiratory rate and administering the questionnaires. The participant will not be told the order they receive the different interventions. We will ask them not to divulge any detected differences in flow to the investigators due to risk of un-blinding the Blinded Investigator.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation code will be pre-generated by the study statistician
by computer and stored in a sealed opaque envelope which will be
opened by the Un-Blinded Investigator at randomisation (immediately
prior to the first intervention).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Randomised controlled 2-way crossover trial. Two investigators will carry out each study visit: one of these will be blinded to the treatment allocation and one unblinded. Participants will not be told in which order they will receive the interventions.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size of 24 has 80% power, type I error rate 5%, to detect a difference of 2.4 mmHg. This is half the difference found in a study of participants with obesity hypoventilation syndrome which reported a mean (standard deviation) paired difference of 5 (4) mmHg (Wijesinghe et al, CHEST 2011; 139(5):10181024).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/12/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>21/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>21/06/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 7 CSB
Wellington Regional Hospital
Riddiford Street
Newtown 
Wellington 6021</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3 - ProCARE Building, Grafton Mews, at 110 Stanley Street, Auckland 1141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 7 CSB
Wellington Regional Hospital
Riddiford Street
Newtown 
Wellington 6021</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will compare the effect of Nasal High Flow therapy and Non-invasive ventilation on the blood levels of carbon dioxide (PaCO2) in participants with chronic respiratory failure associated with stable chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). Acute exacerbations of this condition cause a build-up of carbon dioxide in the blood which can require ventilation and increase risk of death. Acute exacerbations of COPD lead to 12000 hospital admissions in New Zealand every year. NHF therapy has a potential role in lowering carbon dioxide levels in COPD patients and we therefore wish to study the effects further and compare it to the gold standard of NIV. Participants will undergo an informed consent process, gathering of personal/medical information and lung function testing. They will then be randomised to the order they receive the 2 interventions for 60 minutes at a time and a washout period of 15 minutes after each. There will be a 30 minute 'wash in' period whereby supplemental oxygen will be given, if required, to maintain oxygen saturations of 88-92%. This oxygen flow will be used at the start of intervention 1 and continuously titrated through either the NHF or NIV to maintain oxygen saturations of 88-92%.  The participant will be asked to complete a tolerability questionnaire following each 60 minute intervention. and will be asked about their breathlessness, on the BORG dyspnoea score, before and after each intervention..
The primary aim of the study is to identify whether the NHF device has an equivalent impact on PaCO2 levels, compared to NIV  in participants. Secondary outcomes include how well participants tolerate the 2 devices and other physical parameters such as respiratory rate, oxygen saturations,and heart rate.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern B Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
133 Molesworth Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/11/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/NTB/207</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James Fingleton</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand Level 7 CSB Wellington
Regional Hospital Riddiford Street Newtown Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0247</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>james.fingleton@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Steven McKinstry</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand Level 7 CSB Wellington
Regional Hospital Riddiford Street Newtown Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0261</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Steve.mckinstry@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Steven McKinstry</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand Level 7 CSB Wellington
Regional Hospital Riddiford Street Newtown Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0261</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Steve.mckinstry@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Steven McKinstry</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand Level 7 CSB Wellington
Regional Hospital Riddiford Street Newtown Wellington 6021</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0261</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Steve.mckinstry@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>