<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336428">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/02/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000166976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Sedation Practice in Intensive Care in Australia and New Zealand- A Pilot Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of  a sedative regimen that utilises dexmedetomidine as the primary agent and minimises the use of midazolam compared with current sedation practice in intensive care patients on outcomes of mortality, cognitive function and Health Related Quality of Life.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1119-1020</utrn>
    <trialacronym>SPICE Pilot.</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sedation in intensive care patients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1
Known as Grp DexP-sedation regime with dexmedetomidine as the primary agent.
Dexmedetomidine up to 1 to 1.5 mcg/kg/hour to achieve desired sedation level. Given via infusion as required for up to a max of 30 days.
Arm 2
Grp Std care- standard care sedation as per site's normal practice. Given via infusion as required.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator arm of this trial is standard care sedative regime as per the sites usual practice.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>a comparison of the cumulative and daily dose of administered dexmedetomidine and midazolam in the intervention and the control groups.
This will be assessed via data collected from the medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge from intensive care.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The cumulative and daily dose of propofol, ketamine, fentanyl, morphine, diazepam, clonazepam and other sedatives.
This will be assessed via data collected from the medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge from intensive care.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients in RASS categories -3 to -5, -2 to +1 and +2 to +4, assessed every day in ventilated patients still receiving sedative infusions.
This will be assessed via data collected from the medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At cessation from mechanical ventilation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients with a positive CAM-ICU and the number of days for which the CAM-ICU is positive
This will be assessed via data collected from the medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge from intensive care.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of mechanical ventilation, ICU and hospital length of stay, mechanical ventilation and ICU free days at day 28.
This will be assessed via data collected from the medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vital status.
This will be assessed via data collected from the medical record and also patient follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at hospital discharge and at 90 days after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite of death or full time institutional dependency (rehabilitation hospital or nursing home).
This will be assessed via data collected from the medical record and also patient follow up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 180 day after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of the rate of recruitment of eligible subjects: 
a.	Proportion of screened and eligible patients who were recruited.
b.	Proportion of enrolled patients who were intubated for longer than 24 hours.
c.	Duration from time of intubation to time of randomisation and time from randomisation to time of commencement of study medications.
This will be assessed via data collected from the medical record.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At study completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients eligible for the study must meet these 2 criteria:
The patient is mechanically ventilated via an endotracheal tube and has been intubated, (excluding time spent intubated within an operating or procedural theatre), for less than 12 hours, and the treating clinician believes that:
1.	The patient requires immediate AND ongoing sedative medication for comfort, safety, and to facilitate the delivery of life support measures.
2.	The choice of the sedative medications needs to be determined now
3.	There is uncertainty whether a sedative regimen using dexmedetomidine as the primary agent or the clinicians usual choice of sedative regimen for this patient is superior, AND
4.	The patient is expected to remain intubated the day after tomorrow.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded from the study if any of the following criteria apply:	
- Age less than 18 years,
- Patient is pregnant and/or lactating. 
- Patient has a proven or suspected acute primary brain lesion that may result in global impairment of conscious level or cognition, such as traumatic brain injury, intracranial haemorrhage, stroke, or hypoxic brain injury.
- Patient has a proven or suspected cervical spinal cord injury or pathology that may result in permanent or prolonged weakness of upper and lower limbs.
-  Patient has proven or suspected primary neurological pathology associated with prolonged weakness, such as Guillain-Barre syndrome 
-  Patient has been admitted as a consequence of a drug overdose
- Patient has burn injuries
- Patient is receiving or expected to need ongoing neuromuscular blockade
- Patient has allergy to propofol or dexmedetomidine
-  Patients mean arterial blood (MAP) pressure is less than 55 mmHg despite resuscitation and vasopressor therapy
-  Patient has a heart rate (HR) less than 55/min unless being treated with a beta blocker 
-  Patient has a high grade atrio-ventricular block in the absence of a functioning pacemaker
- Patient has end stage liver failure or acute fulminant hepatic failure
- Patient does not speak English
- Death is deemed imminent and inevitable 
-Patient is a nursing home resident
- Patient has an underlying disease that makes survival to 90 days unlikely.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A pilot study where patients are allocated to study arm via concealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be done in permuted blocks, in a 1:1 ratio to either the dexmedetomidine arm or standard care arm.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/04/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>ANZIC-research centre, Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial road
Melbourne Victoria 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hospira Inc</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>275 North Field Drive, Lake Forest, Illinois 60045</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>ANZIC-research centre, Monash University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial road
Melbourne Victoria 3004</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the SPICE Pilot RCT is to obtain preliminary data on the feasibility of conducting a large phase III RCT. The hypothesis of the proposed RCT is that a sedation regimen based on dexmedetomidine as the primary sedative agent, and in which benzodiazepine use is minimised, will lead to improved patient centred outcomes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/02/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Yahya Shehabi</name>
      <address>Associate Professor, University of New South Wales
Clinical School of Medicine
Prince of Wales Hospital, Barker Street, Randwick, NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 4721</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9382 4870</fax>
      <email>y.shehabi@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Belinda Howe</name>
      <address>ANZIC-research centre, DEPM, Monash University
The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0340</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9903 0152</fax>
      <email>belinda.howe@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Belinda Howe</name>
      <address>ANZIC-research centre, DEPM, Monash University
The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Melbourne Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0340</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 99030152</fax>
      <email>belinda.howe@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>