<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335003">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/02/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/03/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000182099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Double blind, randomised, placebo controlled trial of lithium carbonate for the management of cannabis withdrawal in adult humans</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In cannabis dependent adults does lithium carbonate, compared to placebo, assist in the management of cannabis withdrawal?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cannabis dependence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This project aims to explore the safety and effectiveness of lithium carbonate in reducing the severity of withdrawal that often occurs on cessation of dependent cannabis use. The trial will utilise a double-blind, randomised, placebo controlled design. Participants will be admitted to an inpatient drug treatment unit for 7 days and will be randomly assigned to receive either lithium or placebo. Participants randomised to the treatment condition will be administered two capsules containing 250mg lithium carbonate twice a day (i.e., 1000mg per day) for 6 days.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomised to the placebo condition will be administered placebo medication on the same dosing schedule as participants in the treatment condition (i.e., two capsules twice a day for six days in inpatient setting). Placebo capsules will be an exact match to lithium capsules in terms of shape, size, colour and degree of opaqueness.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The efficacy of lithium carbonate compared to placebo in reducing the severity of cannabis withdrawal among dependent cannabis users abstaining from cannabis use.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Severity of cannabis withdrawal will be measured using a modified version on the Marijuana Withdrawal Checklist, a 32-item self-report measure with reference to previous 24 hours.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Detoxification completion rates among participants randomised to lithium carbonate compared to placebo.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Treatment completion, defined as completing 7 days of inpatient treatment under protocol conditions (categorical yes/no); and number of days of inpatient treatment completed (range: 0-7).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of adverse events (e.g., nausea, vomiting, loss of appetite, fatigue, diarrhea) during detoxification in the two randomised groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse events during the inpatient treatment period. This will be assessed daily by a self-report adverse effects checklist administered by a clinician (developed for the previous open-label trial conducted by Winstock et al., 2009), and by clinician assessment. Serum lithium levels at day 4 and day 7 will determine whether trough serum lithium levels are in the therapeutic range (0.5-1.5 mmol/L) on day 4 and day 7.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine whether the provision of lithium carbonate for the management of cannabis withdrawal is associated with reduced levels of cannabis use during a 3-month follow-up period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Self-reported cannabis use with total days used cannabis (range 0-90) and longest period of continuous abstinence (range 0-90) during the follow-up period. Cannabis use will be assessed at each follow-up point (days 14, 30 and 90 after discharge from inpatient unit) using the Timeline Followback Method (TLFB) (Sobell et al., 1996). Self-reported cannabis use will be corroborated with serial urinalysis of carboxy-tetrhydrocannabinol (THC): creatinine ratio using Gas Chromatography/Mass Spectrometry (GC/MS), saliva and blood tests at 30 and 90 day follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Examination of the potential role of oxytocin in mediating the effects of lithium on cannabis withdrawal.</outcome>
      <timepoint>In order to determine whether there is an association between lithium administration and oxytocin levels, plasma oxytocin levels will be assayed on day 1 (baseline), day 4 and day 7 of the inpatient admission.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine whether baseline patient characteristics (including demographics, substance use and psychosocial parameters) predict the severity of cannabis withdrawal and subsequent post-withdrawal outcomes (cannabis use, psychosocial outcomes, sleep disturbances and cannabis-related problems).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Self-reported measures of cannabis-related problems assessed at study entry and at each follow-up point (days 14, 30 and 90 after discharge for inpatient unit) using the Cannabis Problems Questionnaire (CPQ).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the relationship between the attainment and maintenance of abstinence from cannabis and changes in measures of psychological functioning (assessed using the Depression, Anxiety, Stress Scale (DASS) 21, the Social Interaction Anxiety Scale (SAIS) and the Social and Occupational Functioning Assessment Scale), neuropsychological functioning (assessed using the Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test, the Rey Complex Figure Test, the Trail Making Test, the Wechsler Test of Adult Reading, the Wechsler Memory Scale IV (WMS-IV) Logical Memory, Digit Span, and Spatial working memory using CANTAB), social cognition (assessed using Movie Stills Task and Reading the Mind in the Eyes), functioning and disability (assessed using the Short Form Health Survey (SF-12), World Health Organisation Disability Assessment Schedule II, and World Health Organisation Quality of Life) ? BREF, sleep disturbance (using the Athens Insomnia Scale), other substance use, and cannabis-related problems (using the CPQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Psychological and neuropsychological functioning, social cognition, functioning and disability, sleep disturbance, other substance use and cannabis-related problems will be measured on day 1 and day 7 of inpatient admission, and at 30- and 90 -day follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine whether certain single nucleotide polymorphisms (genetic variants) are over-represented in heavy cannabis users relative to the overall Australian population. This might include (but is not limited to) single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in genes such as cannabinoid receptor 1, catechol-o-methy transferase and adenosine-triphosphate (ATP)-binding cassette (ABC) transporters.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples taken at study admission will be used to assess whether certain single nucleotide polymorphisms (genetic variants) are over-represented in heavy cannabis users relative to a normative sample collected at the Brain and Mind Institute, University of Sydney. This might include (but is not limited to) SNPs in genes such as cannabinoid receptor 1, catechol-o-methy transferase and ABC transporters.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* At least (=) 18 years of age.
* Meet Diagnostic Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM)-IV-TR criteria for cannabis dependence.
* Have identified withdrawal symptoms as a barrier to achieving abstinence from cannabis.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* People who are alcohol dependent. This will be assessed by clinical assessment 
* People who use drugs other than cannabis, caffeine and tobacco more than twice weekly, or inject drugs more than once per week (on average) in the 30 days prior to recruitment. 
* People on methadone or buprenorphine treatment for opioid dependence.
* People with documented lactose intolerance.
* People with a documented intolerance of lithium.
* People with a history of schizophrenia, bipolar affective disorder or recent psychosis (within preceding 3 months); or admission to mental health unit within the 3 months prior to recruitment.
* People assessed as being at significant risk of suicide.
* People with renal or thyroid function outside the normal range. People with severe liver disease (as identified by clinical assessment and liver function tests (Gamma Glutamyl Transpeptidase (GGT), Aspartate Transaminase (AST) and Alanine Transaminase (ALT) levels 3-fold above the normal range). This will be assessed prior to study entry.
* People with significant cardiovascular disease (myocardial infarction in past 6 months, cardiomyopathy, significant hypertension (&gt; 180/120), major arrhythmias). Assessed clinically and by electrocardiography (ECG) in those &gt;45 years of age.
* People with current prescriptions (within past month) for mood stabilising medications (e.g., Valproate and Carbamazepine).
* People with current prescriptions (within past month) for antidepressant and/or antipsychotic medications assessed as clinically unstable.
* Females who are breastfeeding or pregnant at recruitment (screened using blood test for human chorionic gonadotropin (hCG) in women of child bearing potential), or planning on becoming pregnant or not using adequate contraception in the month following study entry.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/04/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/12/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/08/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Brain &amp; Mind Research Institute (BMRI), University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>BMRI, University of Sydney
100 Mallett St
Camperdown NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to explore the safety and effectiveness of lithium carbonate in reducing the severity of withdrawal that often occurs with the cessation of dependent cannabis use. Participants will be admitted to an inpatient drug treatment unit for 7 days and will be randomly assigned to receive either lithium or placebo.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydeny South West Area Health Service (SSWAHS) Ethics Review Committee - Royal Prince Alfred Hospital (RHAH) Zone</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
RPAH
Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/08/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Associate Professor Nicholas Lintzeris</name>
      <address>The Langton Centre
591 South Dowling Street
Surry Hills, NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9332 8777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nicholas.lintzeris@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Jennifer Johnston</name>
      <address>care of
Riverlands Drug and Alcohol Centre
Locked Bag 11
Lismore, NSW 2480</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6688 2391</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennifer.johnston@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Lintzeris</name>
      <address>The Langton Centre
591 South Dowling Street
Surry Hills NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9332 8777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Nicholas.Lintzeris@SESIAHS.HEALTH.NSW.GOV.AU</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>