<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363251">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001187831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exploring Dialectical Behaviour Therapy vs Conversational Model in the treatment of Borderline Personality Disorder: A randomised clinical trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised clinical trial of Dialectical Behaviour Therapy compared to Conversational Model in the treatment of Borderline Personality Disorder in reducing parasuicidal behaviour and depression.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Borderline Personality Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention A: Dialectical Behaviour Therapy (DBT)
The participants will take part in a manualised treatment that combines treatment strategies from behavioural, cognitive and supportive psychotherapies.  It will include weekly individual therapy for two months, followed by concurrent weekly individual and group therapy for 12 months.  The individual DBT therapy session will be for approximately one hour per week and apply directive, problem-orientated techniques (including behavioural skill training, contingency management, and cognitive modification) balanced with supportive techniques such as reflection, and acceptance.  The emphasis is on teaching participants how to manage emotional experiences. 
The group therapy will meet once each week for two and a half hours and follow a psycho-educational format.  Behavioural skills in three main areas will be taught in three modules as follows: interpersonal effectiveness, distress tolerance, and emotion regulation skills.  Each module will be preceded by a two-week focus on Mindfulness, which is the core skill taught over the entire group.  The group will include the teaching and application of skills, and the practice of them between classes.

Intervention B: Conversational Model (CM)
The participants will have twice weekly individual therapy for fourteen months. The individual therapy will be for approximately one hour per session and will be nondirective. The focus will be on understanding the patients emotional experience and actively describing that back to the patient. The therapist actively looks for subtle signs of emotionally misunderstanding the patient, leading to mutual self-reflection and repair of the moment of disconnection in the therapeutic relationship. High value is placed on the patients real experience (as against socially acceptable experience) and the development of an authentic personal narrative. The patient is encouraged to find links between the maladaptive relationship patterns they have developed in their current social world and the relationship pattern they have with the therapist (and possibly, but not necessarily, the links with their childhood relationships).</interventions>
    <comparator>DBT &amp; CM are both active treatments and are both considered to have equal weight in the study for comparator purposes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2: Depression scores as measured by Beck Depression Inventory II (BDI-II)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, 7 months (mid-treatment), 14 months (post-treatment), 26 months (1 year follow-up), 38 months (2 year follow-up) and 74 months (5 year follow-up).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: Parasuicidal behaviour (including suicide attempts and non-suicidal self-injury) as measured by information from the following measures: 
a.     Suicide Attempt Self-Injury Interview Count (SASII)
b.     Borderline Personality Disorder Severity Index (BPDSI) 
c.      Structured Clinical Interview for Axis II Disorders (SCID-II)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, 7 months (mid-treatment), 14 months (post-treatment), 26 months (1 year follow-up), 38 months (2 year follow-up) and 74 months (5 year follow-up).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 1: Number and severity of BPD symptoms as measured by Borderline Personality Disorder Severity Index (BPDSI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, 14 months (post-treatment), 26 months (1 year follow-up), 38 months (2 year follow-up) and 74 months (5 year follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 2: Interpersonal problems as measured by the Inventory of Interpersonal Problems (IIP)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, 7 months (mid-treatment), 14 months (post-treatment), 26 months (1 year follow-up), 38 months (2 year follow-up) and 74 months (5 year follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 3: Mindfulness skills as measured by the Kentucky Inventory of Mindfulness Scale (KIMS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, 7 months (mid-treatment), 14 months (post-treatment), 26 months (1 year follow-up), 38 months (2 year follow-up) and 74 months (5 year follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 4: Dissociation as measured by the Dissociative Experiences Scale (DES)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, 7 months (mid-treatment), 14 months (post-treatment), 26 months (1 year follow-up), 38 months (2 year follow-up) and 74 months (5 year follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 5: Emotion regulation as measured by the Difficulties in Emotion Regulation Scale (DERS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, 7 months (mid-treatment), 14 months (post-treatment), 26 months (1 year follow-up), 38 months (2 year follow-up) and 74 months (5 year follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Outcome 6: Sense of self as measured by the Sense of Self Inventory (SSI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, 7 months (mid-treatment), 14 months (post-treatment), 26 months (1 year follow-up), 38 months (2 year follow-up) and 74 months (5 year follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Meet the diagnostic criteria for BPD as measured by SCID-II interview
Minimum of three episodes of parasuicidal behaviour in the past 12 months 
Between 18-65 years of age
Fluent in English
Live within an hours drive of the treatment centre</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Disabling organic conditions
Acute psychotic illness
Antisocial behaviour that poses a significant threat to staff
Developmental disability
Living more than one hour's drive from Newcastle 
Unable to speak or read English 
Prior treatment with DBT or Conversational Model
Drug or Alcohol dependence (eligible for entry once no longer meet criteria for dependence)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be assessed by a psychiatrist to determine whether they meet criteria for BPD. If they meet criteria, they will be invited to talk with the Research Assistant who will explain the study and ask whether they would like to participate. If they provide consent, they will complete the baseline assessment and then receive a sealed, opaque envelope with their randomisation status. It will be explained to the participants why the assessor needs to be blind and they will be asked not to discuss the type of treatment they receive with the assessor.</concealment>
    <sequence>Blocked and stratified randomisation using randomisation created by computer software. Stratified by gender and anti-depressant use.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/04/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>162</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hunter New England Local Health District</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 833
Newcastle
NSW
2300</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Centre for Translational Neuroscience and Mental Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Translational Neuroscience and Mental Health
HNELHD &amp; University of Newcastle
PO Box 833
Newcastle
NSW
2300</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Approximately 11% of all psychiatric outpatients and 19% of psychiatric inpatients meet the criteria for Borderline Personality Disorder (BPD). People with this disorder are high utilisers of mental health services and medical services as their condition often involves problems with interpersonal relationships, impulsivity in self-damaging areas such as substance abuse and reckless driving, recurrent suicidal threats and self-harming or self-mutilating behaviours.  Approximately 9% of all individuals with BPD commit suicide. 

DBT has become the gold standard of psychotherapeutic treatment of BPD. Results across a number of trials have consistently shown significant reductions in suicidal and self-mutilating behaviours as well as improvement in quality of life. To date, there have been very few RCTs comparing DBT to other active treatments and very few trials conducted in real world settings. This trial compares DBT with CM, a psychodynamic model, developed specifically for treatment of BPD that has some empirical support, but has not been evaluated against another active treatment. It is hypothesised that DBT will be more effective at reducing self-harm and suicidal behaviour than CM, but less effective at reducing depression.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee
Hunter New England Health
Locked Bag 1
New Lambton   NSW   2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/12/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06/12/13/5.11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Carla Walton</name>
      <address>Centre for Psychotherapy, 
Hunter New England Mental Health Service
PO Box 833, 
Newcastle NSW 2300</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4924 6820</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4924 6801</fax>
      <email>Carla.Walton@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Carla Walton</name>
      <address>Centre for Psychotherapy, 
Hunter New England Mental Health Service
PO Box 833, 
Newcastle NSW 2300</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4924 6820</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4924 6801</fax>
      <email>Carla.Walton@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Carla Walton</name>
      <address>Centre for Psychotherapy, 
Hunter New England Mental Health Service
PO Box 833, 
Newcastle NSW 2300</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4924 6820</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4924 6801</fax>
      <email>Carla.Walton@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>