<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373871">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/11/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001527358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Use of exciteBCI for technology assisted stroke rehabilitation: Usability and
acceptability for physiotherapists and people with stroke.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Use of exciteBCI for technology assisted stroke rehabilitation: Usability and
acceptability for physiotherapists and people with stroke.
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1204-1845 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>exciteBCI is a wearable rehabilitation device that is novel paired associative stimulation intervention that utilises a brain computer interface (BCI) that aims to promote neural plasticity and improve walking ability in people with stroke. The exciteBCI device augments standard rehabilitation programme. Participants wear an electroencephalography headset and an electrical muscle stimulator over the dorsiflexor or plantar flexor muscles of the ankle, or the quadriceps or hamstring muscles of the thigh depending on the nature of the task and which muscles are prime movers for the task. An application on an ipad controls the device and provides a muscle stimulation timed with the intention to move.
Part one of study: Participants are asked to attend one 90 minute session to explore the usability and acceptability of exciteBCI. Potential users of the exciteBCI will be asked to perform a number of tasks using the exciteBCI whilst engaging in a think-aloud process. This involves verbalising their thinking, observations and opinions whilst interacting with the exciteBCI. During the session observational and video recordings are made. The participants also take part in a short semi structured interview after the usability trial. The researcher will ask questions regarding the tasks, design features, pros and cons, and suggested improvements.
Part two of study: Intervention. Following the incorporation of usability feedback two participants with stroke will volunteer to participate in a standard rehabilitation programme augmented by the exciteBCI. The rehabilitation programme will be based on current evidence based practice as recommended in the NZ stroke guidelines and will include task specific training of locomotor skills supervised by a New Zealand registered physiotherapist with clinical experience in stroke rehabilitation. The task specific training will involve an increase in the task complexity over the eight 1-hour sessions over a 3-week period based on principles of motor learning. The rehabilitation workload will be progressed based on the perceived difficulty of each task. The participant will use the exciteBCI throughout the rehabilitation programme. The rehabilitation sessions will be video recorded.  Following completion of the rehabilitation programme the person with stroke and the physiotherapist will take part in separate 60-90 minute semi-structured interviews. The rehabilitation programme and interviews will be carried out at AUT University.
</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional measurement: Change in walking speed - 10 metre walk test </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention and 3 days post completion of the 3-week intervention </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional measurement: Change in walking endurance - Six minute walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention and 3 days post completion of the 3-week intervention </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional measurement: Sit to stand spped - Change in Chair stand Test </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention and 3 days post completion of the 3-week intervention </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dynamic balance measurement: Change in 4 Square Step Test </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention and 3 days post completion of the 3-week intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Strength Measurement: Changes in maximum voluntary contraction of the ankle dorsiflexors,  using a force gage. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention and 3 days post completion of the 3-week intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Interviews to determine the usability and acceptability of exciteBCI : Physiotherapists </outcome>
      <timepoint>Study part one: For the usability trial Interview will take place immediately after the participant has interacted with the exciteBCI and the usability tasks have been completed. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Interviews to determine the usability and acceptability of exciteBCI : People with stroke.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Study part one: For the usability trial Interview will take place immediately after the participant has interacted with the exciteBCI and the usability tasks have been completed. 
Study part two: Immediately after the 3 week intervention is completed.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Strength Measurement: Changes in maximum voluntary contraction of the knee extensors using a force gage</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention and 3 days post completion of the 3-week intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Strength Measurement: Changes in maximum voluntary contraction of the hip flexors using a force gage</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention and 3 days post completion of the 3-week intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety monitored by recording any medical/physical changes at the beginning of each session, and any changes during the session. Unrelated events such as illness will be recorded and may result in a session being missed. Possible related events include superficial skin irritation related to electrode placement, or a headache due to wearing the EEG headset. Both of which are considered low risk. Any adverse events requiring the participant to seek medical attention from a health professional will be recorded on an adverse events form.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Stroke participants who meet the following inclusion criteria will be considered:
 Aged 18 years or more
 Stroke with hemiparesis affecting their ability to move their ankle
Physiotherapist participants in the usability trial (part 1) will be included if:
 They have 5 years experience in neurological rehabilitation
 Are able to attend a data collection session at AUT University</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Stroke Participants will be excluded if they:
 are unable to engage in the testing due to significant cognitive, perceptual or communication deficits
 have had a cerebellar stroke
 have another medical condition that may impact the testing or results</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Part one of study (precedes intervention): Participants are asked to attend one 90 minute session to explore the usability and acceptability of exciteBCI. Potential users of the exciteBCI will be asked to perform a number of tasks using the exciteBCI whilst engaging in a think-aloud process. This involves verbalising their thinking, observations and opinions whilst interacting with the exciteBCI. During the session observational and video recordings are made. The participants also take part in a short semi structured interview after the usability trial. The researcher will ask questions regarding the tasks, design features, pros and cons, and suggested improvements.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Qualitative descriptive data from the think-aloud protocol and interviews will be analysed using descriptive content analysis. This will provide a rich description of participants experiences and opinions of the devices usability and acceptability rather than an interpretation. Data form each of the quantitative measures for the two participants with stroke that participate in the 3-week intervention will be analysed using descriptive statistics.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/02/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Auckland University of Technology </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Health and Rehabilitation Research Institute, Faculty of Health and Environmental Science, AUT University,
Private Bag 92006,
Auckland 1142.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Auckland University of technology </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Health and Rehabilitation Research Institute, Faculty of Health and Environmental Science, AUT University,
Private Bag 92006,
Auckland 1142.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>MedTech CoRE</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Auckland Bioengineering Institute 
University of Auckland 
Uni Services House, 
Level, 6/70 Symonds St,
 Grafton, 
Auckland 1010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Callaghan Innovation C-Prize</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 31310
Lower Hutt
Wellington
 5040
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Exsurgo Rehab Limited</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>11J Piermark Drive 
Albany 
Auckland
0623</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this research is to investigate the usability and acceptability of exciteBCI a wearable rehabilitation device that is in a development and refinement phase, which aims to improve walking ability in people with stroke. The intervention has been tested previously and shown to be safe and effective when delivered using laboratory based equipment. We are making a smaller, lighter, portable version of the laboratory device, which can be used in clinical settings. We want to observe people with stroke and therapists while they use the device, and then interview them to find out what they think about the exciteBCI and how it could be made better. We will use these findings to modify the device to improve its usability and acceptability to clinicians and people with stroke. Following the incorporation of usability feedback, two stroke participants will take part in a 3 week physiotherapy intervention in which standard physiotherapy exercises will be supplemented with the exciteBCI.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
133 Molesworth Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/10/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>17/NTA/177</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Denise Taylor</name>
      <address>Health and Rehabilitation Research Institute, Faculty of Health and Environmental Science, AUT University,
Private Bag 92006,
Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9680</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>denise.taylor@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Gemma Alder </name>
      <address>Health and Rehabilitation Research Institute, Faculty of Health and Environmental Science, AUT University,
Private Bag 92006,
Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9999 ext 7815</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>galder@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Gemma Alder</name>
      <address>Health and Rehabilitation Research Institute, Faculty of Health and Environmental Science, AUT University,
Private Bag 92006,
Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9999 ext 7815</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>galder@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Gemma Alder</name>
      <address>Health and Rehabilitation Research Institute, Faculty of Health and Environmental Science, AUT University,
Private Bag 92006,
Auckland 1142.</address>
      <phone>+64 9 921 9999 ext 7815</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>galder@aut.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>