<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82779">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/04/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/04/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000218392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of different diets on gestational diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can a low glycemic index (GI) diet during pregnancy reduce prevalence of large for gestation age (LGA) amongst women with gestational diabetes (GDM)?  a randomized, controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>GIBABY1</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gestational Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other reproductive health and childbirth disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Low glycemic index diet - with a daily dietary GI less than 50, carbohydrate choices include low/lower GI alternatives, e.g. pasta, lower GI rice, multigrain bread, low GI breakfast cereals, sweet potatoes, etc. from diagnosis of gestational diabetes (at 26 - 30 weeks) till 36 weeks of gestation.
Participants in this diet group would receive 1 dietary education session fortnightly for at least 5 weeks to educate them how to follow a low GI diet. Phone reviews will be conducted in between the face-to-face sessions. The sessions will be given by the PhD student who is also an Accredited Practising Dietitian. Low/lower GI food samples baskets will be provided to the participants on a fortnightly basis, and a range of low/lower GI foods would be suggested and encouraged during the education sessions. Participants will be provided sample meal plans which are specially formulated to have a GI less than 50, and a 24 hour recall at the 2nd face-to-face dietary education session would assess their compliance.</interventions>
    <comparator>Wholegrain high fibre - with a GI of around 60, carbohydrate choices include moderate to high GI but high fibre and/or wholegrain foods, e.g. wholemeal bread, wholegrain breakfast cereals, brown rice, potatoes, etc. from diagnosis of gestational diabetes (at 26 - 30 weeks) till 36 weeks of gestation.
Participants in this diet group would receive 1 dietary education session fortnightly for at least 5 weeks (i.e. at least 3 sessions) to educate them how to follow a wholegrain high fibre diet. Phone reviews will be conducted in between the face-to-face sessions. The sessions will be given by the PhD student who is also an Accredited Practising Dietitian. Wholegrain high fibre food samples baskets will be provided to the participants on a fortnightly basis, and a range of wholegrain high fibre foods would be suggested and encouraged during the education sessions. Participants will be provided sample meal plans which are specially formulated to have a GI approximately 60 (the GI of the usual Australian diet), and a 24 hour recall at the 2nd face-to-face dietary education session would assess their compliance.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>birth weight z-score</outcome>
      <timepoint>birth of infant</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ponderal index (weight/cube of length)</outcome>
      <timepoint>birth of infant</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>need for insulin to control blood glucose level during gestation (Yes or No).
Doctors/diabetes educators will determine whether the gravidas requires insulin for optimal blood glucose control or not, based on their home blood glucose monitoring readings.
results presented as a group percentage</outcome>
      <timepoint>from the start of the study till the birth of infant,
determined during their routine antenatal visits, which is fortnightly.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>otherwise healthy pregnancy, singleton gestation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnancy achieved via assited reproduction, pregnancy complicated with conditions other than gestational diabetes</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is concealed via central randomization. A stratified random number list (with blocking) will be maintained by a personel not involved in the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>subjects will be randomized by computer generated random numbers</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/09/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/10/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>4/11/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2050</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Research Office
A14 Quadrangle Building
Camperdown Campus
Parramatta Rd
Sydney NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Research Office
A14 Quadrangle Building
Camperdown Campus
Parramatta Rd
Sydney NSW 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Diabetes Centre, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 6 West Wing
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to investigate the efficacy of a low glycemic index diet (GI) in reducing the prevalence of large-for-gestion-age (LGA) babies amongst gravidas with gestational diabetes (GDM). Study participants will be pregnant women diagnosed with GDM at ~26-30 week gestation. They will be randomized into two study groups, one receiving dietary education on how to follow a wholegrain high fibre diet for GDM, whereas the other group will receive education on how to follow a macronutrient and energy matched low GI diet. We hypothesize, based on our previous pilot study on healthy gravidas, gravidas with GDM following a low GI diet will have a lower risk of giving birth to LGA infant than those following a wholegrain high fibre diet. The size of the infants (as birth weight z-score) will be measured as the primary outcome.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Primary publication

Louie JC, Markovic TP, Perera N, Foote D, Petocz P, Ross GP, Brand-Miller JC. A randomized controlled trial investigating the effects of a low-glycemic index diet on pregnancy outcomes in gestational diabetes mellitus. Diabetes Care. 2011 Nov;34(11):2341-6. doi: 10.2337/dc11-0985. Epub 2011 Sep 6.

Secondary publications

Louie JC, Markovic TP, Ross GP, Foote D, Brand-Miller JC. Effect of a low glycaemic index diet in gestational diabetes mellitus on post-natal outcomes after 3 months of birth: a pilot follow-up study. Matern Child Nutr. 2013 May 3. doi: 10.1111/mcn.12039. [Epub ahead of print]

Louie JC, Markovic TP, Ross GP, Foote D, Brand-Miller JC. Higher glycemic load diet is associated with poorer nutrient intake in women with gestational diabetes mellitus.
Nutr Res. 2013 Apr;33(4):259-65. doi: 10.1016/j.nutres.2013.02.008. Epub 2013 Mar 26.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South West Areath Health Service Human research Ethics Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Level 8, Building 14
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/06/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/RPAH/208</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/04/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jennie Brand-Miller</name>
      <address>Room 476, Human Nutrition Unit,
G08 School of Molecular and Microbial Biosciences,
Cnr Butlin Ave and Maze Cres.
University of Sydney
Camperdown, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 3759</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9351 6022</fax>
      <email>j.brandmiller@mmb.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jimmy Chun Yu Louie</name>
      <address>Room 453, Human Nutrition Unit,
G08 School of Molecular and Microbial Biosciences,
Cnr Butlin Ave and Maze Cres.
University of Sydney
Camperdown, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 433 538 424</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jimmy.louie@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jimmy Chun Yu Louie</name>
      <address>Room 453, Human Nutrition Unit,
G08 School of Molecular and Microbial Biosciences,
G08 School of Molecular and Microbial Biosciences,
Cnr Butlin Ave and Maze Cres.
University of Sydney
Camperdown, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 433 538 424</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jimmy.louie@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jennie C Brand-Miller</name>
      <address>G08 School of Molecular Bioscience
The University of Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61293513759</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennie.brandmiller@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>