<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308047">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000532202</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Tamoxifen and Exemestane Trial Bone Substudy - A substudy to Amendment 2 of the IBCSG 25-02 / BIG 3-02: Tamoxifen and Exemestane Trial (ACTRN12605000418673) hereby referred to as TEXT-2, which evaluates the effects of exemestane plus Gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) analogue as adjuvant therapy for premenopausal women with endocrine responsive breast cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>IBCSG 25-02 / BIG 3-02: Tamoxifen and Exemestane Trial (TEXT) - A phase III trial evaluating the role of exemestane plus Gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH)analogue as adjuvant therapy for premenopausal women with endocrine responsive breast cancer.

The TEXT-Bone Substudy evaluates serial bone markers for bone remodelling, serial growth factors, and bone mineral density for patients randomized to TEXT-2.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TEXT-Bone</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>IBCSG 25-02/BIG 3-02 TEXT-Bone</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Effects of adjuvant endocrine therapies on bone mineral density in pre-menopausal breast cancer patients.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Prior to registration in the TEXT-Bone Substudy, patients must be randomised to the TEXT-2 parent trial (Protocol Amendment 2 of IBCSG 25-02 / BIG 3-02 Tamoxifen and Exemestane Trial - TEXT). TEXT-2 re-starts recruitment.

The TEXT trial will evaluate the worth of ovarian function suppression (achieved by long-term use of Gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) analogue (Triptorelin) 3.75mg by intramuscular injection every 28 days for 5 years from randomisation) plus exemestane 25mg orally daily until 5 years from date of randomisation (Exemestane should start after adjuvant chemotherapy has been completed or approximately six to eight weeks after the initiation of Gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) analogue (Triptorelin) whichever is later) compared with Gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) analogue (Triptorelin) 3.75mg by intramuscular injection every 28 days for 5 years from randomisation plus tamoxifen 20mg orally daily until 5 years from date of randomisation (Tamoxifen should start after adjuvant chemotherapy has been completed or approximatley six weeks to eight weeks after the initiation of Gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH) analogue (Triptorelin), whichever is later) for premenopausal women with steroid hormone receptor positive early invasive breast cancer. Patients may either receive no chemotherapy or commence chemotherapy at the same time that Gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH)analogue is initiated.

Women will be randomised in a 2-arm design to receive one of the following:

a. Ovarian Function Suppression (triptorelin) + Tamoxifen
b. Ovarian Function Suppression (triptorelin) + Exemestane


All treatment will be for 5 years.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm A - Tamoxifen as the control treatment: 20mg given orally daily until 5yrs from date of randomisation, unless relapse or intolerance should occur earlier. Triptorelin 3.75mg given by intramuscular injection every 28 days for 5 years from randomisation, unless relapse or intolerance should occur earlier or surgical oophorectomy or ovarian irradiation is subsequently performed.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate changes in bone mineral density (BMD) among pre-menopausal women randomized to TEXT-2 to receive either: A) triptorelin (GnRH analogue) for 5 years plus tamoxifen for 5 years; or B) triptorelin (GnRH analogue) for 5 years plus the steroidal aromatase inhibitor exemestane for 5 years.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Bone Mineral Density (BMD) measured by Dual energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) in L1-L4 (postero-anterior, PA) region of the spine and hip is required as baseline, 12, 36, 60, and 72 month visits.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate serial serum markers for bone remodelling (C-telopeptide, osteocalcin, bone-specific alkaline phosphatase) and investigate their correlation with BMD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Morning fasting blood samples for serum are required as baseline, 12, 36, 60, and 72 month visits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate serial serum growth factors Insulin-like growth factor (IGF-1) and Insulin-like growth factor binding protein-3 (IGFBP-3) and investigate whether their time course correlates with bone mineral density (BMD).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Morning fasting blood samples for serum are required as baseline, 12, 36, 60, and 72 month visits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Explore the role of serum Insulin-like growth factor (IGF-1) and Insulin-like growth factor binding protein-3 (IGFBP-3) FBP-3 as biomarkers of disease outcome (disease-free survival).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Morning fasting blood samples for serum are required as baseline, 12, 36, 60, and 72 month visits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients must be eligible and enrolled in the TEXT-2 trial prior to enrollment in TEXT-Bone. Patients must have given informed consent for the TEXT-Bone substudy. the informed consent form must be signed and dated by the patient and her clinician.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who have received bisphosphonate therapy (or other bone therapies such as Parathyroid hormone (PTH) or Strontium) within the previous 6 months or who are currently receiving therapy. Concomitant calcium and Vitamin D supplements are permitted and strongly recommended.
Patients who in the previous 6 months have had a bone fracture which in the investigator's judgement could be related to bone fragility.
Patients who have used a glucocorticoid (&gt;5mg prednidone or equivalent) for more than one month in the previous 6 months.
Patients taking anticonvulsants within the previous 12 months.
Patients with clinical or biochemical malabsorption syndrome, or known vitamin D deficiency, active hyper- or hypoparathyroidism, or Paget's disease.
Uncontrolled thyroid disease, Cushing's disease or other pituitary diseases.
Any other bone disease (including osteomalacia, osteogenesis imperfecta).
Patients for whom serial BMD measuerment within the same institution is ompossible.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The Statistical Centre at the National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) Clinical Trials Centre, University of Sydney will provide a central randomisation service by fax for all Australian and New Zealand institutions. At the time of study entry all participants will be allocated a treatment code via a web-based randomization system and study drug will be supplied in accordance with the treatment code. </concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated stratified blocks</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Patients will be randomised to the parent TEXT-2 trial via computer generated stratified blocks. TEXT-2 patients opting to participate in the TEXT-Bone substudy will then be registered to participate in the trial.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/12/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>118</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2298</postcode>
    <postcode>2170</postcode>
    <postcode>2560</postcode>
    <postcode>3135</postcode>
    <postcode>3081</postcode>
    <postcode>8006</postcode>
    <postcode>4029</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Breast Cancer Trials</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 283
The Junction NSW 2291</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Breast Cancer Trials</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 283
The Junction NSW 2291</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>International Breast Cancer Study Group (IBCSG)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>International Breast Cancer Study Group (IBCSG)  Coordinating Centre
Effingerstrasse 40 CH-3008 BERN</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>International Breast Cancer Study Group</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>International Breast Cancer Study Group (IBCSG)  Coordinating Centre
Effingerstrasse 40 CH-3008 BERN</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Switzerland</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this research is to compare the effect of the treatments (Tamoxifen and Exemestane) used in the main trial (TEXT-2) on bones. This will provide researchers and doctors with information as to whether these drugs are safe in terms of bone health and if there are increased or decreased risks of osteoporosis with the treatments.

Approximately 200 patient's will be enrolled in this sub-study worldwide. Every patient will be in the sub-study for an average period of six years. However, participation in the study could be shorter depending on the response to the treatment on the main study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.breastcancertrials.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Breast Cancer Trials formerly known as the Australia &amp; New Zealand Breast Cancer Trials Group.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee
Butterfield Street
HERSTON QLD 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/05/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2004/098</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Prue Francis</name>
      <address>Medical Oncology Department 
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
Locked Bag 1
A'Beckett Street
MELBOURNE      VIC   8006</address>
      <phone>+61 (03) 8559-7902</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Prue.Francis@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Corinna Beckmore</name>
      <address>BCT
PO Box 283
The Junction NSW 2291</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4925 5235</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4925 3068</fax>
      <email>enquiries@bctrials.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Prue Francis</name>
      <address>Medical Oncology Department 
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
Locked Bag 1
A'Beckett Street
MELBOURNE      VIC   8006</address>
      <phone>+61 (03) 8559-7902</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Prue.Francis@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>