<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366883">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000908639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised Trial of Circle of Security as a Parenting Support Program for Multiproblem Families</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of Circle of Security Parenting Training (DVD) to improve parent and child outcomes in multiproblem families, compared to a supportive waitlist</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parental sensitivity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Child internalizing symptoms</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Child externalizing symptoms</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Parenting stress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Parental reflective functioning</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Parental attachment and interpersonal style</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Parental depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Parental bonding</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Parenting practices</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will be the 8-week Circle of Security Parent DVD Program. 

This program provides parents with psychoeducation based on attachment theory, using the training DVD. Parents will attend sessions with a psychologist, where they will watch the training DVD and relate the content to their own family. The DVD includes short videos and built-in moments to facilitate reflective dialogue. The program will be conducted in one-on-one sessions each taking around 1 hour, once per week for eight weeks. Only one parent is required to attend. Parents will be asked to reflect on the content between sessions. 

Master and Doctoral level psychologists trained in the Circle of Security Parent DVD Training will conduct the sessions. Regular peer supervision will be held, to assist with adherence to the program. </interventions>
    <comparator>Participants allocated to the 8-week Waitlist will be contacted weekly by phone by their allocated therapist, for brief conversations regarding family and other concerns. At the end of the 8 weeks, families will be offered the Circle of Security Parent DVD Program. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parental sensitivity will be assessed by coding recorded parent-child interactions within a 10-minute free-play session. The measure of parent sensitivity was developed by modifying one subscale of the Emotional Availability Scales (Biringen, Robinson, &amp; Emde, 2000). Parents will be rated from 1 (highly insensitive) to 9 (highly sensitive). Coding will include consideration of the parents affect, ability to respond to the childs signals, flexibility, and accessibility to the child.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At treatment completion (8 weeks after randomization), and at 3 month post treatment completion (20 weeks after randomization)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent stress will be assessed using The Parenting Stress Inventory, Third Edition (PSI-3; Abidin, 1990).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At treatment completion (8 weeks after randomization), and at 3 month post treatment completion (20 weeks after randomization)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The 21-item Beck Depression Inventory II (BDI; Beck, Steer &amp; Brown, 1996) will be used to assess parental depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At treatment completion (8 weeks after randomization), and at 3 month post treatment completion (20 weeks after randomization)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The parent report Behavior Assessment System for Children (BASC-2; Reynolds &amp; Kamphaus) will be used to assess child internalizing symptoms. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At treatment completion (8 weeks after randomization), and at 3 month post treatment completion (20 weeks after randomization)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The parent report Behavior Assessment System for Children (BASC-2; Reynolds &amp; Kamphaus) will be used to assess child externalizing symptoms. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At treatment completion (8 weeks after randomization), and at 3 month post treatment completion (20 weeks after randomization)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Parents of children aged 1 to 6 years, experiencing relationship difficulties. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomization of participant ID codes to treatment or supported waitlist was conducted using a coin flip process on www.random.org, prior to recruitment. Thus, participants are assigned an ID code (and corresponding treatment or waitlist group) according to the order in which they enroll in the program. Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Sequential participant ID codes were formed (e.g., 1, 2, 3). Using coin flipper on www.random.org, where heads corresponded to treatment, and tails to waitlist, each ID code was allocated to treatment or waitlist, then participants were assigned an ID code according to the order in which they enroll the program. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Different groups of participants receive different interventions during the same time span of the study, however supported waitlist participants are also offered the intervention after they have completed the waitlist. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We plan on conducting a series of mixed ANOVAs to evaluate whether change in outcome measures from pre- to post-assessment differs between the treatment and waitlist control groups. 

Based on results obtained in a previous RCT we have conducted, using similar measures in a comparable population, we calculate that we will require 80 participants (40 in each group). Specifically, at 80% power and .05 (two-sided) significance level, we calculated that we will require between 60 and 80 participants to obtain differences in measures that we obtained in our previous trial.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>23/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Parklands Drive, Southport, QLD, 4222</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>QLD Government, Department of Communities, Child Safety
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>111 George St, Brisbane QLD 4000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Circle of Security parent DVD training is an 8-week relationship-based group program designed to enhance
the parent-child relationship and attachment. We aim to examine the effectiveness of the DVD-based program for enhancing the parent-child relationship with multiproblem families, as well as improve other symptoms, such as parental mental health, and child internalizing and externalizing symptoms. Given the suggestion that group-based interventions may not be suitable for at risk families, we will examine the suitability of modifying the DVD protocol for use on an individual basis. Participants will be parents with a child aged 12-months to 6-years. Parents will be randomly assigned to one of two groups: (1) Circle of Security intervention or (2) supported waitlist control. The intervention group will complete the 8-week COS protocol involving one weekly 1-1.5 hour session with a trained Circle of Security facilitator. Parents in the waitlist control group will receive weekly supportive phone contact.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport QLD 4222</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>PSY/10/14/HREC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Melanie Zimmer-Gembeck</name>
      <address>Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport QLD 4222
</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)7 5678 9085</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.zimmer-gembeck@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Elbina Avdagic</name>
      <address>Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)7 5678 9105</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.avdagic@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Haley Webb</name>
      <address>Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)7 5678 9105</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.webb@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Haley Webb</name>
      <address>Griffith University
Parklands Drive
Southport QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)7 5678 9105</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>h.webb@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>