<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372744">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000579392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A drug interaction study of DUR-928 and Midozolam</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Drug Interaction Study to Evaluate the Effect of DUR-928 on the Pharmacokinetics of a Single Oral Dose of Midazolam in healthy participants.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>C928-018</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Liver Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The proposed study is an open label, single sequence, dosing study in 18 healthy male and female subjects, to obtain 15 evaluable subjects.
Subjects will be screened to determine eligibility within 14 days prior to dosing.  Subjects will be admitted to the clinical unit on Day -1 for baseline assessments.  On Day 1, subjects will receive an oral solution of midazolam 3mg.  On Days 3, 4 and 5, subjects will receive an oral suspension of DUR-928 50 mg daily. On Day 6, subjects will receive an oral solution of midazolam 3mg as well as an oral suspension  of DUR-928 50mg. On Day 8 subjects will receive DUR-928 (150 mg) as intravenous infusion over 2 hours immediately followed by an oral solution of midazolam 3 mg. 
All study treatments will be administered after an overnight fast of at least 10 hours.  Subjects will continue to fast for 4 hours after the study drug administration. During fasting no fluids will be allowed except water; however water will not be allowed from 1 hour before dosing to 1 hour after dosing (except for 240 mL of water required to swallow DUR-928 or midazolam).  Subjects will be confined in the study unit from Day -1 through Day 9 procedures and return to the clinic on Day 14 for trial completion procedures.
DUR-928 oral dose: 50 mg of DUR-928 drug substance powder in a 60 cc wide mouth, amber glass bottle with a child-resistant screw cap.  At the time of administration, 60 mL of a commercially available flavored, sugar-free, vehicle (ORA-Blend SF) is added to the bottle of DUR-928 powder to suspend the drug substance, and the entire bottle content is orally dosed, followed by two rinses with water.
Study staff will administer all doses.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Midazolam (drug interaction).  This is a drug interaction study between study drug and CYP3A4 substrate.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the effect of DUR-928 when administered as an oral dose or as IV infusion on the pharmacokinetics of midazolam. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The following PK parameters will be assessed - Cmax, Tmax, Terminal elimination rate constant, AUC0-last, AUCinf, %AUCexp, T1/2, Vz, CL.
Blood samples will be collected for analysis of plasma concentrations of midazolam, 1-OH midazolam up to 26 hours after study drug administration.  The samples will be collected as follows: Day 1: pre-dose, 0.25, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12 and 24 hours post dose. Day 6: pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12 and 24 hours post-dose. Day 8 : pre-dose 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.25, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 10, 14 and 26 hours post-dose.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the effect of oral midazolam on the pharmacokinetics of an oral dose of DUR-928 in plasma.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The following PK parameters will be assessed - Cmax, Tmax, Terminal elimination rate constant, AUC0-last, AUCinf, %AUCexp, T1/2, Vz, CL.
Blood samples will be collected for analysis of plasma concentrations of DUR-928 and 25 hydroxycholesterol (25-HC) up to 26 hours after study drug administration. Day 3, Day 5 and Day 6: pre-dose, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12 and 24 hours post-dose.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety of DUR-928 and midazolam in healthy subjects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Common adverse reactions observed with oral doses of midazolam include: slowed or impaired breathing, decreased blood pressure, fast or slow heart rate, drowsiness, lightheadedness, nausea and vomiting, and impaired motor skills. Subjects will be monitored closely by frequent assessments of vital signs and adverse events.
Routine vital sign measurements (blood pressure [BP], heart rate [HR] and respiratory rate [RR]) will be measured at screening, Day -1, pre-dose, and 0.25 (RR  only), 0.5, 0.75 (RR only),1, 1.25 (RR only), 2, 3, 4, 6, 12, and 24 hours post-dose of each study treatment, and at trial completion (Day 14). 
Continuous pulse oximetry will be obtained with an alarmed monitor maintained for 4 hours from start of Midazolam dosing on Days 1, 6 and 8.  Readings will be recorded at pre-dose (immediately prior to administration of midazolam), 15 and 30 min, 1, 2 and 4 hours after dosing.
Physical examination will be performed at screening, Day -1, and at trial completion (Day 14). The physical exam done on Day -1 will be abbreviated.
Safety Laboratory tests (Chemistry, Hematology, Gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase (GGT), and Urinalysis) will be drawn at screening, Day  1, pre-dose and 24 hours post-dose of each study treatment, and at trial completion (Day 14).
All adverse events will be collected from Day -1 and continues through to trial completion (Day 14).
Twelve-lead ECGs will be obtained from subjects at screening, Day -1, pre-dose, and at approximately 1 and 24 hours post-dose on Days 1,3,4,5,6, and pre-dose and 2, 3 and 26 hours post-dose at Day 8. Additional ECGs may be obtained if clinically indicated.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Be in good health as determined by medical history, physical examination, 12 lead ECG and clinical laboratory evaluations at screening.
Weight at least 50kg and BMI between 18.0 kg/m2 and 30.0 kg/m2, inclusive.
Male subjects must agree to use a medically acceptable method of contraception/birth control throughout the study duration and for 90 days after the study is completed.
Female subjects must be of non-childbearing potential. 
Willing and be able to be admitted to the clinical study unit for 9 nights and 9 days.
Able to abstain from alcohol and tobacco use during the trial.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>19</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Significant blood loss or donated blood in the 30 days prior to study participation.
Participation in an investigational drug study within 30 days prior to dosing.
History of drug or alcohol abuse.  
Use of any medications, including OTC and herbal or nutritional supplements within 2 weeks prior to study drug dosing, and for the study duration.
Use of grapefruit or grapefruit juice, apple or orange juice, vegetables from mustard green family (e.g. kale, watercress, collard greens, brussels sprouts, mustard) and charbroiled (grilled) meats within 1 week prior to study drug dosing, and for the study duration.
Positive tests for HIV, hepatitis B/C, drugs of abuse or alcohol breath-test. 
Clinically significant abnormalities.
Tobacco users who have used tobacco within the last 30 days  prior to screening
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is an open label, single sequence, dosing study in 18 healthy male and female subjects. Subjects will complete a Screening Phase, Treatment, and an End of Study Visit.  The Screening phase will be conducted on an outpatient basis within 14 days prior to the start of dosing. Subjects will be confined in-house for 9 nights during study Treatment from Day -1 through 26 hours post-dose of Day 8.  They will be discharged from the clinic and will return, for the End of Study Visit, at Day 14.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Fixed sequence drug interaction Study</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Comparison of AUC and Cmax of between treatments will be done using an analysis of variance (ANOVA) on the ratios of the least squares means (LSM) using linear mixed effects modeling to yield point estimates (geometric means) with 90% confidence intervals (CI).  
18 subjects will be enrolled to achieve 15 evaluable subjects. A sample size of 15 subjects will provide greater than 80% power for the 90% confidence interval of the geometric mean ratio to fall within the specified no-effect boundary of 0.8 and 1.25.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/06/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>8/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>9/06/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>18</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>17</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>22/06/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>22/06/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>INC Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>159 Port Rd, Hindmarsh South Australia, 5007 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>DURECT Corporation </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>10260 Bubb Road
Cupertino, CA  95014, USA
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research project is being conducted to look at the pharmacokinetics of both DUR-928 and Midazolam; this is done by measuring the amount of DUR-928  and Midazolam in the blood at different times throughout the dosing periods. Data from this study will allow us to evaluate how DUR-928 is handled by the body (for example how quickly it gets into the blood stream) and it will allow us to determine the impact of DUR-928 on how Midazolam is handled by the body. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>OFFICE OF ETHICS &amp; RESEARCH GOVERNANCE,
Ground Floor, Linay Pavilion, 
The Alfred Hospital,
Commercial Road,
Melbourne 
VIC 3004
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Project No: 137/17</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jason Lickliter</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network
5th Floor, Burnet Tower, AMREP Precinct
89 Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, 3004
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9076 8960</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 3 9076 8911</fax>
      <email>j.lickliter@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Elaine Wong</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network
5th Floor, Burnet Tower, AMREP Precinct
89 Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, 3004</address>
      <phone>+ 61 402 329 162</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 3 9076 8911</fax>
      <email>E.Wong@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jemma Lawson</name>
      <address>INC Research
159 Port Road, 
Hindmarsh, SA 5007, Australia 
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7202 1500</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7202 1599 </fax>
      <email>jemma.lawson@incresearch.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jemma Lawson</name>
      <address>INC Research
159 Port Road, 
Hindmarsh, SA 5007, Australia 
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7202 1500</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7202 1599 </fax>
      <email>jemma.lawson@incresearch.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>