<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83743">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/03/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000427279</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pharmacist Prescribing in a Sexual Health and Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) Outpatient Clinic</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Evaluation of the Impacts of a Doctor  Pharmacist Collaborative Prescribing Model on the Management of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) Infected Patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Human Immunodefiency Virus (HIV)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS / HIV)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Management of previously diagnosed and stable HIV patients, under an agreed care plan between consultant sexual health physician, pharmacist and patient
Patient appointments are approximately half an hour, and scheduled routinely every 3 months. The intervention will run until all patients in the intervention arm have been seen twice by the pharmacist after the production of the initial care plan, so for approximately 6 months after care plan production for each patient.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care, control patients will be seen by their usual sexual health physician for the duration of the study
Patient appointments are approximately half an hour, and scheduled routinely every 3 months.
Usual care for the purposes as a control will be administered for the same time period as the intervention runs for, namely Appointment 1 is informed consent and randomisation, appointment 2 is production of a care plan for intervention patients and usual care for control, appointment 3 is being seen by the pharmacist for intervention patients and usual care for control and appointment 4 is being seen by the pharmacist for the second time for intervention patients and usual care for control. So from recruitment to end of 4th appointment is 9 months</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The effective ongoing management of previously diagnosed and stable HIV patients by the pharmacist prescriber.
An audio recording of all doctor and pharmacist consultations with patients will be made. The recordings will be transcribed and analysed using Leximancer. The completeness of information gathered to enable ongoing treatment decisions to be made will be assessed using the Medication Related Consultation Framework.
Leximancer text analysis software extracts concepts from text independent of coder biases. A thesaurus is built from the dataset containing concepts derived from the document(s) according to the proximity and frequency of word co-occurrences in the text. Leximancer produces a two dimensional pictorial representation of a multidimensional matrix.  The size of the dot associated with a concept represents its frequency in the analysed text. The proximity of the concepts on the map indicates the co-occurrence proximity with other concepts in the text analysed. Automatic coding can process large amounts of text, and provides coding standardization which has been validated against standard tests and manual coding software.

Evaluation of Process of Care

Case files will be compiled for a selection of patients throughout the study and 50% from each arm will be randomly selected and assessed by an independent, multi-disciplinary panel at the end of the study.
A panel will be convened that ideally consists of 2 independent sexual health physicians, 2 independent HIV/sexual health pharmacists and 2 independent HIV/sexual health nurses.
Using consensus methods, the panel will assess the appropriateness of the patient's ongoing management and degree of care plan compliance, including:

-disease progress and control 
-symptoms and management
-management of side effects 
-appropriateness of dose adjustments
-appropriateness of medication changes
-appropriateness of referrals

Evaluation of Patient Adherence with Medication

Patients' level of adherence with medication regimens will be assessed via three different methods:
-viral load and CD4 counts
-from dispensing records and frequency of medication collection
-via a self-reported adherence questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>6. 9 and 12 months following recruitment of the patient into the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A reduction in the burden on medical staff within the clinic with regards to patient access
Sexual health physician appointments throughout the study will be timed, using the recording made on the MP3 player , and averaged out to assess how much physician time may be released as a result of the pharmacist seeing patients under an agreed care plan.
Any change in waiting list time to access an appointment at the clinic to see a prescriber will also be assessed as a measure of increased access for patients to medical staff.
The average length of time from ringing for an appointment to obtaining an appointment can be obtained from the electronic appointment system in the clinic. Data will be assessed for a month within the project, August 2009, and compared to the same month of the previous year, August 2008.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6, 9 and 12 months following recruitment of the patient into the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Previously diagnosed and stable HIV patients, as determined by their usual sexual health physician</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>New patients to the clinic, without a diagnosis.
Transient patients visiting the clinic from outside of the health district. 
Patients currently participating in clinical drug trials. 
Patients having prescriptions dispensed interstate
Patients having pathology testing performed by private laboratories</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients with a diagnosis of HIV infection, who have had a prior medical assessment and are stable in terms of disease, will be considered for participation in the study.

Patients identified as suitable for participation will be seen by their usual sexual health physician at their next regular appointment and be provided with an information leaflet about the study and given the opportunity to ask any questions. If patients are happy to participate, they will be asked to provide written and informed consent.

Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization using randomization created by a computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/03/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Medication Services Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>RBWH, 
Block 7, Level 13,
Herston Road
Herston,
Brisbane,
Queensland
4006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medication Services Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Brisbane and Womens' Hospital (RBWH) 
Block 7, Level 13,
Herston Road,
Herston,
Brisbane
Queensland,
4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Office of the Chief Health Officer, Qld Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Qld Health Building,
147-163 Charlotte Street, 
Brisbane,
Queensland
4001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to develop a doctor - pharmacist collaborative prescribing model and to consider alternative workforce models to better utilize clinical skills within the multi-disciplinary team to release medical staff time for diagnosis or more complex patients. The hypothesis of the project is that the collaborative doctor - pharmacist prescribing model provides at least as high a quality of care as usual care.

Patients who have a diagnosis of HIV, have been previously medically assessed and are stable with regards to their disease will be considered for participation in the project. At their next appropriate appointment, the patient will be seen by their usual sexual health physician, given a patient information leaflet, and given the opportunity to participate in the study and provide written, informed consent.

Patients will be randomised into one of two arms, to be either:
-seen by their usual doctor and for their care to be managed in the usual way, or
-seen by their usual doctor and the prescribing pharmacist with the aim of producing an agreed care plan, and for their subsequent appointments during the project to be managed by the prescribing pharmacist.

The efficiencies of having the pharmacist responsible, under an agreed patient care plan, for all medication management aspects of the patients' appointment will be evaluated as follows.

All patient consultations with the doctor or pharmacist will be audio-taped and assessed using the Medication Related Consultation Framework, for completeness of information gathered in the consultation.

Patient's adherence to medications will be assessed using 3 methods, including:
-pathology results (CD4 counts, viral load)
-pharmacy records to establish dispensing frequency of medications 
-patient self-report adherence assessment tool.

The completeness and legality of all prescriptions will be analysed.

At the end of the study an independent, multidisciplinary panel, including doctors, pharmacists and nurses will review a random sample (50%) of patients. The panel will assess appropriateness of management and degree of concordance with the care plan.

Patient satisfaction will be assessed using self-completion questionnaires.

The multidisciplinary team within the clinic will be surveyed to assess their views and satisfaction on the pharmacy service before and after the project.

Potential doctor time released as a result of the new model will be evaluated, as will increased access of patients to a prescriber.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Gold Coast Health Service District Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>District Executive Offices
Gold Coast Hospital
108 Nerang Street, Southport
Qld, 4215</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/01/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>200895</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ian Coombes</name>
      <address>MSQ,
RBWH, Block 7, Level 13,
Herston Road,
Herston,
Brisbane,
Queensland,
4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36366251</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36369098</fax>
      <email>ian_coombes@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andrew Hale</name>
      <address>Medication Services Queensland (MSQ),
RBWH, Block 7, Level 13,
Herston Road,
Herston,
Brisbane,
Queensland,
4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36368782</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36369098</fax>
      <email>andrew_hale@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andrew Hale</name>
      <address>RBWH, Block 7, Level 13,
Herston Road,
Herston,
Brisbane,
Queensland,
4006</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36368782</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36369098</fax>
      <email>andrew_hale@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>