<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336261">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/11/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000054910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigating Magnetic Seizure Therapy in Major Depressive Disorder.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of Magnetic Seizure Therapy for the treatment of Major Depressive Disorder</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Project 363/10</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Treatment Resistant Major Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Magnetic Seizure Therapy (MST).

MST uses magnetic stimulation to induce a seizure for therapeutic purposes.  Magnetic stimulation is a non invasive technique for stimulating neural tissue.  A rapid change in magnetic field induces a current in the neural tissue.  If the current is of sufficient amplitude and duration it will excite nerve tissues.

All patients will undergo a dose titration procedure to establish their convulsive stimulation threshold using 10 second trains at 100Hz.  Stimulation will then be provided at 120% of seizure threshold.  Patients will undergo a maximum of 15 treatment sessions over approximately 5 weeks.

Stimulation is applied using the Magstim Magnetic Seziure Therapy device.  Treatment duration is between 20-30 mins.</interventions>
    <comparator>Electroconvulsive Therapy (ECT).

ECT uses electrical stimulation to induce a therapeutic seizure.

ECT treatment will be based on seizure threshold which will be determined at the first ECT session. In the majority of subjects we will use right unilateral ECT at three times seizure threshold. Only those patients who have a history of no response to an effective course of unilateral ECT will commence with bilateral ECT at 1.5 times seizure threshold

Patients will undergo a maximum of 15 treatment sessions over approximately 5 weeks.

Stimulation is applied using the Thymatron device.  Treatment duration is between 20-30 mins.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Antidepressant effect.

Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS)

Response is defined as a reduction of at least 50% from baseline.</outcome>
      <timepoint>MADRS will be assessed at baseline, weekly during treatment, at treatment end, and for responders at 2, 4 and 6 months following treament end.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive side effects.

A comprehensive cogntive battery will be administered. The battery will include the Autobiographical Memory Interview, Rey Verbal Auditory Learning Test , Verbal Paired Associates (WMS-R), Logical Memory (WMS-III), and the Brief Visual Spatial Memory Test.  We will also include a number of assessments of information processing, i.e. Digit Span, Digit Symbol Coding, and Trail Making Test.  Finally, we will look at general intellectual functioning (Wechsler Test of Adult Reading), as well as aspects of executive functioning and language (Rey Complex Figure Test, Stroop, Verbal Fluency and Boston Naming Test). 

Post treatment Orientation will also be assessed.  Patients will be repeatedly asked to provide their name, date of birth, age, place and day of week. Orientation will be considered to be present when the patient provides correct answers to 4 of these questions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The Cognitive battery will be administered at baseline, endpoint and at 6 months follow up.

Post MST / ECT orientation will be assessed immediately following the first, fourth and ninth treatments.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age 18-75 and a DSM-IV diagnosis of a major depressive episode (uni or bipolar depression) (diagnosis made using the standard structured clinical interview for the DSM-IV (SCID I) instrument). 

Patients with psychotic symptoms as part of their mood episode will not be excluded if able to give informed consent.

Are referred for or are otherwise suitable for a course of ECT as determined by their treating psychiatrist 

Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (17 item version) score of &gt; 18 (moderate  severe depression): note  some authors have defined moderate depression on the 17 item HAMD as &gt;14. We have selected a higher cut off to ensure all patients clearly have depression of substantial clinical severity. It is likely that most patients will have scores in the severe or extremely severe ranges. 

Score greater than 23 on the Mini Mental State Examination 

Have treatment resistant depression at Stage II of the Thase and Rush classification. This requires failure to respond to adequate courses of several courses of antidepressants. 

Demonstrated capacity to give informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who are too unwell to undergo general anesthetic.  

Patients with metallic implants in the head, cardiac pacemakers, cochlear implants or other implanted  electronic devices

Treatment with ECT in the last three months 

Presence of another DSM-IV Axis I psychiatric disorder (on SCID I) other than bipolar disorder

Presence of substance abuse or dependence during the last six months (on SCID I)

Current pregnancy

Past history of stroke, neurodegenerative disorder or other major neurological illness</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment occurs through central randomisation by computer. </concealment>
    <sequence>Individuals are randomized (single non stratified sequence) via a  computer-generated list</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/03/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>8/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>40</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Paul Fitzgerald</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Monash Alfred Psychiatry Research Centre (MAPrc): Level 4, St Kilda Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Alfred Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>55 Commercial Road
PO Box 315 Prahran
Victoria 3181 Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Electro convulsive therapy (ECT) remains the only established treatment for the large percentage of patients with depression who fail to respond to standard therapies. It is commonly used (with 10 to 15% of inpatients with depression receiving ECT) but has substantial problems including the occurrence of cognitive side effects that are often highly distressing for patients. ECT is associated with both short term and long term cognitive side effects. The short term effects include anterograde and retrograde memory loss and post treatment disorientation which can be distressing, dangerous and significantly slow treatment progress. In the longer term, ECT can affect autobiographical memory which can be very distressing to patients. The development of a new treatment with similar efficacy but which minimises these side effects would have great clinical value. 

A highly promising possibility is magnetic seizure therapy (MST). MST involves replacing the electrical stimulation used in ECT with a magnetic stimulus. This appears to be able to produce similar clinical effects but without the disabling cognitive side effects related to ECT. However, substantive trials using the newest MST equipment are required. Due to the rarity of the equipment available so far, these studies are only being undertaken in a handful of places internationally and no research with MST has occurred.

Building on a pilot study conducted by the applicants, we propose to undertake a substantive head-to-head trial of MST versus ECT. There will be a total of 60 patients in the study undertaking a treatment course of between 9 and 15 treatments.  Baseline and endpoint assessments will be undertaking to investigate efficacy, these will include clinical assessments, cognitive assessments and neurophysiological assessment

If MST proves to be as efficacious as ECT, but with fewer side effects, we anticipate that it could be rapidly adopted in clinical practice. All of the facilities are available for the provision of MST in every substantive mental health service in the country (in current ECT suites / facilities); all that would be required would be the replacement of the ECT machine with MST equipment for seizure induction. Fewer cognitive side effects will enhance patient outcomes and improve treatment acceptability and hence access. In addition, a reduced duration of post treatment disorientation will shorten the period of post treatment observation required enhancing capacity for convulsive therapy to be provided on an outpatient basis, lessening demand on inpatient psychiatric services.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research &amp; Ethics Unit
Linay Pavilion

55 Commercial Road
PO Box 315 Prahran
Victoria 3181 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/10/0363</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/11/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Fitzgerald</name>
      <address>MAPrc Level 4, St Kilda Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9076 6552</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.fitzgerald@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Fitzgerald</name>
      <address>MAPrc Level 4, St Kilda Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9076 6552</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.fitzgerald@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Fitzgerald</name>
      <address>MAPrc Level 4, St Kilda Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9076 6552</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.fitzgerald@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>