<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362024">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000147886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Body, Brain, Life Program a prevention trial to reduce risk of Alzheimer's Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Body, Brain, Life Program -Evaluation of a multi-domain, online lifestyle intervention in middle-aged adults at risk of Alzheimers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1125-8325</utrn>
    <trialacronym>BBL</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alzheimer's disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive decline</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Neurodegenerative diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The BBL program is an online, theoretically-driven, multi-domain intervention comprising seven modules (Dementia literacy, Risk factors literacy, engagement in physical, cognitive, and social lifestyles, nutrition, and health monitoring and management). All modules were designed in a manner reflective of current theoretical models of health behaviour change, and with the exception of the first two modules which are primarily educational in nature, will be delivered in an individually-tailored manner.  

The BBL program was designed to be delivered over 12 weeks, starting with the delivery of the seven modules once per week in a fixed order, and continuing with associated goal-related sessions in the remaining weeks. Participants in the intervention arms will be required to complete online activities 1 hour per week. They will be, however, encouraged to engage with the online material more frequently than that.  

Arm1; This group will complete the online BBL program as described above over 12 weeks (one hour per week). 

Arm2: This group will also complete the online BBL program over 12 weeks. However, this group will also participate in weekly face-to-face sessions to evaluate any additional effects of face-to-face contact, over and beyond the effects of the online trial only. Small face-to-face group sessions will be facilitated by a psychologist. The content of these sessions will largely echo the respective online modules. They will include discussion of the various risk factors, and will use motivational techniques to elicit group-level behavioural change dynamics. The small group element will be conducted weekly for 7 weeks with each week focusing on the topic of one of the online modules.]These face-to-face sessions will be of approximately one hour in duration.</interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment as usual. This group will have no contact with the researchers other than for the baseline and follow-up assessments. At present, dementia risk is not routinely screened or flagged, and no standard form of care exists in relation to prevention/risk reduction. Hence, the control group will not receive any dementia-related information and lifestyle intervention as part of this trial. They may nevertheless explore dementia and risk-reduction strategies outside of the study context. They will be, however, advised not to enrol in a different trial of dementia prevention during the BBL trial period, or they will be exlcluded from follow-up analyses. The contents of the BBL program will be provided to the control participants in the form of a booklet at the conclusion of the trial.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alzheimer's disease risk: The primary outcome measure of the trial will be reduction of risk of Alzheimer's disease in the intervention arms post-intervention and following a delay, as measured using the Australian National University Alzheimer's Disease Risk Index (ANU-ADRI). The ANU-ADRI was developed by the research group to assess risk of Alzheimer's disease based on self-reported measures of risk factors. Relative-risk algorithms for the ANU-ADRI were developed from a comprehensive meta-analysis and synthesis of risk factors from the literature. The ANU-ADRI provides an overall risk score, as well as domain- specific scores in respect to: a) Age b) Education, c) Body-Mass Index, d) Diabetes, e) Depression, f) high cholesterol, g) Traumatic Brain injury, h) Smoking, i) Alcohol intake, j) Social engagement k) physical activity, l) cognitive activity, m) Fish intake, n) Exposure to occupational pesticide. The ANU-ADRI was validated using data from three external longitudinal cohort studies: 1) Cardiovascular Health Study (CVHS): This large cohort study followed more than 5000 older persons from four US cities for 5 years to explore the association between cardiovascular health and the risk of incident AD. 2) The Rush Memory and Aging Project (MAP): Beginning in 1995, this is an ongoing longitudinal study involving more than 1000 non-demented community dwelling persons who agree to be follow-up to death and to donate their brain for histopathological examination. The study explores various risks for AD. 3) The Kungsholmen Project: A large longitudinal study in Sweden concerned with the identification of risk and protective factors for AD and in which community dwellers were followed from 1987 to 2000.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The ANU-ADRI will be used to assess risk for Alzheimer's disease at baseline, at 13 weeks (upon completion of the intervention), and at 26 weeks post baseline (three months post0intervention).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological determinants of behaviour. A secondary outcome of the trial will be the extent to which any changes in lifestyle behaviours following the intervention will be underpinned by changes in the main determinants of behaviour as reflected in specific psychological questionnaires designed for each module. These questionnaires measure the main psychological determinants of behaviour, and were developed using contemporary models of health behaviour-change.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The behaviour specific questionnaires will be administered at the start of the respective behaviour change module as part of the intervention. The questionnaires will then be re-administered during the 26 weeks follow up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Management of chronic medical conditions including hypertension, hypercholesterolemia, diabetes mellitus and depression. Evaluation of the degree of management of medical conditions will achieved by examination of blood and functional biomarkers (Blood pressure readings, HBA1C, serum cholesterol levels). Depressive symptoms will be assessed using Centre for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D). Consistent with the literature using this measure, a cut-off of 16 will be used to identify individuals with symptoms in the clinical range of severity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 26 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The impact of the intervention on performance on cognitive measures of speed and attention. Participants will undergo a cognitive evaluation including established pen-and-paper tests, as well as new or adapted online measures, including Symbol-Digit Matching Test, Trail Making Test, and Face-Name Learning Test. Participants will be given the option to complete a cognitive training package as part the intervention module.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and  at the 26 week follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Persons aged 50 to 60, showing 3-4 AD modifiable risk factors on the ANU-ADRI, and who live in the ACT area. All participants will be required to have internet access at home, and they will need to agree to attend the Centre for Research on Aging, Health, and Wellbeing for two face-to-face assessments (baseline and 26 weeks)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A diagnosis of any dementia, mild cognitive impairment, or cognitive impairment of any cause (MMSE&lt;26).
History of neurological conditions likely to affect cognition (e.g., parkinsonism, traumatic brain injury, significant stroke)
Significant functional disabilities, for example due to hearing loss, vision impairment, or other medical events or procedures. 
Significant psychological illness, for example due to psychosis, schizophrenia, or bipolar disorder. 
No internet access at home,
Not fluent in English</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants who meet all inclusion and no exclusion criteria will be invited for the baseline evaluation at the Centre for Research on Aging, Health, and Wellbeing. Following the baseline assessment, participants will be randomised to one of the 3 groups using a computer program. Group allocation will then be concealed using sealed envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>The trial will involve simple randomization using a randomization table created by computer software: computer sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/03/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>176</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2580</postcode>
    <postcode>2600- 2620</postcode>
    <postcode>2900-2914</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Kaarin J anstey</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Research on Aging, Health, and Wellbeing 
63 Eggleston Rd. Acton
The Australian National University 
Canberra 0200
ACT</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dementia Collaborative Research Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>63 Eggleston Rd., Acton
Canberra, 
ACT 0200</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Alex Bahar-Fuchs</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Research on Aging, Health, and Wellbeing 
63 Eggleston Rd. Acton
The Australian National University 
Canberra 0200
ACT</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor George Rebok</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>John Hopkins School of Public Health, 624 N. Broadwa, 8 Fl, Baltimore, MD 21205</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project is a randomised control trial of an online program that aims to reduce risk for Alzheimers disease (AD) by intervening in modifiable risk factors. The sample will be healthy but have several modifiable risk factors for AD. Hence this is classified as an indicated prevention trial. The intervention will educate individuals about AD and risks for AD. The intervention itself is tailored to individuals based on their readiness for change and level of risk in particular domains. There will be three groups; a control group who receives a pre and post assessment, an online only intervention group and an online plus small face-to-face intervention group. The trial involves 7 modules (one per week). Level of risk for AD will be assessed at baseline, 13 weeks and 26 weeks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Anstey K J, Cherbuin N, Herath PM. National Dementia Research Forum, Interventions to prevent or delay the onset of dementia: Review 2011, 22-23 Sept. 2011, Sydney, Australia.

Herath PM, Anstey K J, Cherbuin N, National Dementia Research Forum, Development of ANU-Dementia Risk Index (ANU-DRI): Evidence based risk calculations for dementia, 22-23 Sept. 2011, Sydney, Australia.

Anstey K J, Cherbuin N, Herath PM. 1st International Conference in Translational Medicine (13th Frank and Bobbie Fenner Conference), PROACTA an online risk assessment tool for dementia and an evidence based intervention, 1-4 November 2010, Canberra, Australia</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2011/609</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/12/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prof Kaarin J Anstey</name>
      <address>Centre for Research on Aging, Health, and Wellbeing. Building 63, Eggleston Rd.,
Australian National University, 
Acton, ACT 0200</address>
      <phone>+61 2 61258410</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 61250733</fax>
      <email>kaarin.anstey@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Alex Bahar-Fuchs</name>
      <address>Centre for Research on Aging, Health, and Wellbeing. Building 63, Eggleston Rd., 
Australian National University, Acton, 
ACT 0200</address>
      <phone>+61 2 61259705</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 61250733</fax>
      <email>alex.baharfuchs@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Alex Bahar-Fuchs</name>
      <address>Centre for Research on Aging, Health, and Wellbeing. Building 63, Eggleston Rd., Australian National University, 
Acton, ACT 0200</address>
      <phone>+61 2 61259705</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 61250733</fax>
      <email>alex.baharfuchs@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Kaarin Anstey</name>
      <address>Centre for Research on Ageing, Health, and Wellbeing
54 Mills Rd.
Acton
The Australian National University
ACT 0200 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 61258410</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kaarin.anstey@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>