<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1452">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/07/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/07/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000306516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Monotherapy Phase II Dose Ranging Study of DAC HYP in Relapsing Remitting Multiple Sclerosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Multicenter, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Dose-Ranging Study to Determine the Safety and Efficacy of Daclizumab HYP (DAC HYP) as a Monotherapy Treatment in Subjects with Relapsing Remitting Multiple Sclerosis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>European Agency for the Evaluation of Medicinal Products (EMEA) European Clinical Trials (EUDRACT): EMEA EUDRACT No: 2006-001161-42 </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Daclizumab HYP (high yield process) 25mg, 100mg or 200mg, administered by subcutaneous injection every 4 weeks, for a duration of 12 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo subcutaneous injection every 4 weeks, for a duration of 12 months.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of this study is to determine the relationship between 3 different doses of daclizumab high yield process (DAC HYP) on brain lesion activity as measured by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) in subjects with relapsing-remitting MS when compared to placebo. The primary endpoint is the total number of gadolinium (Gd) enhancing lesions over 5 brain MRI scans.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Weeks 4, 8, 12, 16, and 20 (calculated as the sum of these 5 MRIs).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) The number of new or newly-enlarging T2 hyperintense lesions </outcome>
      <timepoint>At Week 20 compared to baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2) The volume of new T1 hypointense lesions </outcome>
      <timepoint>At Week 20 compared to baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3) The change in total lesion volume of new and newly enlarging T2 hyperintense lesions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Week 20 compared to baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosed with relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis (according to McDonald criteria #1-4, Section 22), with a baseline Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS) between 0.0 and 5.0, and who either have experienced at least 1 relapse within the 12 months prior to randomization with a cranial MRI demonstrating lesion(s) consistent with MS or show evidence of Gd-enhancing lesions of the brain on an MRI performed within the 6 weeks prior to randomization.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Diagnosis of primary progressive, secondary progressive, or progressive relapsing MS2. History of malignancy; however, subjects with a history of excised or treated basal cell carcinoma or fewer than 3 squamous sell carcinomas are eligible to participate in this study.3. History of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions or known drug hypersensitivity.4. History of abnormal laboratory results that, in the opinion of the investigator, are indicative of any significant cardiac, endocrinologic, hematologic, hepatic, immunologic, metabolic, urologic, pulmonary, gastrointestinal, dermatologic, psychiatric, renal, neurologic (other than MS), and/or other major disease that would preclude administration of DAC HYP.5. History of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or other immunodeficient conditions.6. History of drug or alcohol abuse (as defined by the Investigator) within the 2 years prior to randomization.7. An MS relapse that has occurred within the 50 days prior to randomization AND/OR the subject has not stabilized from a previous relapse prior to randomization.8. Positive for hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibody and/or positive for hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) at Screening.9. Varicella or herpes zoster virus infection or any severe viral infection within 6 weeks before Screening.10. Exposure to varicella zoster virus within 21 days before Screening.11. Any of the following abnormal blood tests at Screening:i.Hemoglobin &lt; or = 9.0 g/dLii.Platelets &lt; or = 100 x 109/Liii.Lymphocytes &lt; or = 1.0 x 109/Liv.Neutrophils &lt; or = 1.5 x 109/L12. Any previous treatment with DAC HYP or Zenapax®.13. Any of the following types of live virus vaccine from 4 weeks before randomization: measles/mumps/rubella vaccine, varicella zoster virus vaccine, oral polio vaccine, and nasal influenza vaccine.  Use of these vaccines, however, by other members of the subjects household does not affect the eligibility of patients to enroll or continue in the study.14. Infection (viral, fungal, bacterial) requiring hospitalization or intravenous (IV) antibiotics within 8 weeks before randomization.15. Elective surgery performed from 2 weeks prior to randomization or scheduled through the end of the study.16. Prior treatment with the any of the following:· total lymphoid irradiation· cladribine· mitoxantrone· T-cell or T-cell receptor vaccination· any therapeutic monoclonal antibody, except natalizumab or rituximab17. Prior treatment with cyclophosphamide or rituximab within 1 year prior to randomization.18. Prior treatment with any of the following medications or procedures within the 6 months prior to randomization:· natalizumab· cyclosporine· azathioprine· methotrexate· intravenous immunoglobulin  (IVIg)· plasmapheresis or cytapheresis19. Prior treatment with any of the following within the 3 months prior to randomization:·SC or oral glatiramer acetate·IFN-alpha·IFN-beta (subjects who are positive for neutralizing antibodies to IFN beta may receive IFN-beta treatment up to 2 weeks prior to randomization)20. Treatment with any of the following medications within the 30 days prior to randomization:·IV corticosteroid treatment·oral corticosteroid treatment·4-aminopyridine or related products21. Female subjects considering becoming pregnant while in the study.22. Female subjects who are currently pregnant or breastfeeding.23. Previous participation in this study.24. Subjects, for whom MRI is contraindicated, i.e., have pacemakers or other contraindicated implanted metal devices, are allergic to gadolinium, or have claustrophobia that cannot be medically managed.25. Current enrollment in any other investigational drug study or participation in any other investigational study within 6 months prior to randomization.26.Unwillingness or inability to comply with the requirements of the protocol, including the presence of any condition (physical, mental, or social) that is likely to affect the subjects ability to comply with the protocol.27. Other unspecified reasons that, in the opinion of the Investigator and/or Biogen Idec, make the subject unsuitable for enrollment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone/fax/computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Patients assigned to placebo or 25mg DAC HYP will switch to 100 mg DAC HYP in part 2 of the study (week 20 thorugh 52) after experiencing a confirmed relapse</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/07/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>264</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Biogen Idec</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Biogen Idec</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of the study is to determine whether or not 3 different doses of DAC HYP are effective in decreasing the number of abnormal spots (lesions) on brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scans and in delaying the progression of MS, and to test the safety of DAC HYP in patients with relapsing-remitting MS.
This is a double blind, parallel group study where subjects will receive either placebo, or Dac HYP 25mg, 100 mg or 200 mg every 4 weeks by subcutaneous injection for 52 weeks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Melbourne Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Suite 30, 4th Floor, Royal Melbourne Hospital, Gratten Street, Parkeville VIC 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Department of Medicine, University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Department of Medicine, Room 479, 4th Floor, Blackburn Building, University of Sydney, NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>
      </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>207 Melbourne Street, North Adelaide   SA   5006 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincents Medical Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincents Medical Centre Level 4, Suite 1, 55 Victoria Parade, Fitzroy  VIC   3065  </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Department of Neurology, Austin Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Department of Neurology, 6 North, Austin Tow, Austin Health,  145 Studley Road, Heidelberg Vic 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lynn Sartori</name>
      <address>Suite 2 Level 4  123 Epping Road
North Ryde NSW 2113
PO Box 380  North Ryde BC NSW 1670</address>
      <phone>(61) (0)2 8875 3907</phone>
      <fax>Fax: (61) (0)2 9889 1162</fax>
      <email>Lynn.Sartori@BiogenIdec.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lynn Sartori</name>
      <address>Suite 2, Level 4, 123 Epping Road
North Ryde NSW 2113
PO Box 380, North Ryde BC NSW 1670</address>
      <phone>(61) (0)2 8875 3907</phone>
      <fax>Fax: (61) (0)2 9889 1162</fax>
      <email>Lynn.Sartori@BiogenIdec.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>