<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81684">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/12/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/01/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000009415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Impact of Inpatient Weight Restoration in Adoelscent Anorexia Nervosa</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does inpatient weight restoration prior to outpatient family therapy improve psychological and physical outcomes in adolescent anorexia nervosa</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>EDRCT</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Adolescent Anorexia Nervosa</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Eating disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study examines the effect of length of hospital admission for refeeding, prior to manualised outpatient family therapy on outcomes for patients with AN.  Subjects will include 72 children and adolescents aged 10 to 18 years admitted for medical management of AN of less than 3 years duration. This study aims to randomly allocate and compare outcomes between individuals with AN admitted for medical stabilisation, approximately 2 to 3 weeks, followed by 20 one hour sessions of outpatient family therapy over a 12 month period versus those admitted for full weight restoration, approximately 9 to 12 weeks also followed by 20 one hour sessions of outpatient family therapy.  Physical and psychological outcomes will be measured at admission, at discharge from hospital, completion of outpatient treatment and at 6 and 12 months following outpatient treatment.

Medical Compromise
Medical compromise will be defined by the presence of one or more of the following:
 Heart rate of less than 50 beats per minute
 Blood pressure below 80mm Hg diastolic and 40 systolic mm Hg
 A postural blood pressure drop of greater than 10mm of Hg
 The presence of cardiac arrhythmias on electrocardiograph
 A temperature below 35.5 C
 Electrolyte abnormalities
A weight below 75% of predicted IBW 
 
Medical Stability
Medical stability will be defined as the absence of any of the aforementioned indicators for a period of 72 hours.

Minimum Healthy Weight
Minimum healthy weight will be defined as reaching 90% of predicted IBW

Manualised Family-Based Treatment 
Family-based treatment will be conducted using a three phase model as defined in Treatment Manual for Anorexia Nervosa: A Family-Based Approach. Each family will attend 20 one hour sessions, over a 12 month period. Family-based treatment will commence one week after discharge from hospital. The Maudsley Model of family treatment was developed by Dare and colleagues at the Maudsley hospital in London in the early 1980s as an out-patient treatment for AN and was subsequently manualised by Lock and colleagues in the United States in 2002. The treatment is of one year duration and consists 20 one hour  face to face therapy sessions grouped into three phases. Therapy sessions involve the young person with anorexia nervosa and all members of their family being seen by a family therapist.  The model incoorporates aspects of structural and narrative therapy. In the first phase AN is externalised and parents mobilised to refeed their child in the home setting. Parents are seen as a central resource in the process of recovery and notions of familial aetiology are rejected. Siblings are allied with the patient to assist with distress arising as a result of parental control. Phase 1 consists of weekly family thearpy sessions for 12 weeks. Phase two is instigated once the child has reached 90% Ideal Body Weight (IBW) and a transition is made from parental to adolescent control of eating. Sessions during phase 2 are held fortnightly.  Once full weight restoration and menstruation is achieved phase three commences which aims to assist the family to restart the normal adolescent life-cycle transition that has been stalled since the onset of the illness. Sessions during phase 3 are held on a monthly basis.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in the core psychopathology of anorexia nervosa (AN)</outcome>
      <timepoint>There will be five major assessment points (imediately before treatment, 24 hours prior to discharge from hospital at the completion of hospital based treatment, at the completion of family therapy on the day of the final family therapy session and 6 and 12 months after the completion of treatment).  The assessment will involve standardised research interviews and questionnaires, physical examination and clinical laboratory investigations.  Psychological assessments will be conducted by a research assistant trained in their administration and scoring.  This assistant will not be involved in patient treatment.  Physical examination will be carried out by an experienced adolescent physician and clinical investigations will be carried through the Departments of Pathology and Radiology at The Childrens Hospital at Westmead.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in weight as measured by percentage ideal body weight (%IBW).</outcome>
      <timepoint>There will be five major assessment points (imediately before treatment, 24 hours prior to discharge from hospital at the completion of hospital based treatment, at the completion of family therapy on the day of the final family therapy session and 6 and 12 months after the completion of treatment).  The assessment will involve standardised research interviews and questionnaires, physical examination and clinical laboratory investigations.  Psychological assessments will be conducted by a research assistant trained in their administration and scoring.  This assistant will not be involved in patient treatment.  Physical examination will be carried out by an experienced adolescent physician and clinical investigations will be carried through the Departments of Pathology and Radiology at The Childrens Hospital at Westmead.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary measures will include rates of readmission, treatment completion, patient and family satisfaction with treatment, return to school and measures of self-esteem, depression and anxiety. Further measures of medical well-being will include menstrual status, measures of bone health and body composition measured by Dual X-Ray Absorptiometry (DXA), and hormonal levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>There will be five major assessment points (imediately before treatment, 24 hours prior to discharge at the completion of hospital based treatment, at the completion of family therapy on the day of the finally family therapy session and 6 and 12 months after the completion of treatment).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subjects will meet criteria for DSM-IV  (Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 4th edition (DSM-IV)) AN, be medically unstable, have a duration of illness of less than 3 years. All subjects and their families will have provided informed consent prior to their inclusion in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects will be excluded from the study if they show evidence of psychosis, mania, substance abuse, are currently engaged in psychotherapy or have significant current medical illnesses with the exception of nutrition related complications of AN.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed Tamper Proof Envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised in clusters of using a fixed block size to receive one of two treatment regimens using  a randomisation table created by computer sequence generation by The Clinical Epidemiology Unit at The Children’s Hospital, Westmead.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Therapists, assessor and data analyst will be blind to treatment allocation</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/06/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Departments of Psychological Medicine and Adolescent Medicine at The Children's Hospital at Westmead and the Department of Adolescent Medicine at Westmead Hospital.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Children's Hospital at Westmead Locked Bag 4001 Westmead NSW 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Department of Psychology, The University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology
Brennan MacCallum Building (A18)
University of Sydney NSW 2006
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Simple Description of the Project
This study examines the effect of length of hospital admission for refeeding, prior to manualised outpatient family therapy on outcomes for patients with AN.  Subjects will include 72 children and adolescents aged 10 to 18 years admitted for medical management of AN of less than 3 years duration. This study aims to randomly allocate and compare outcomes between individuals with AN admitted for medical stabilisation, approximately 2 to 3 weeks, followed by 20 one hour sessions of outpatient family therapy over a 12 month period versus those admitted for full weight restoration, approximately 9 to 12 weeks also followed by 20 one hour sessions of outpatient family therapy.  Physical and psychological outcomes will be measured at admission, at discharge from hospital, completion of outpatient treatment and at 6 and 12 months following outpatient treatment.  
Interpretation of Results 
If hospitalisation to a minimum healthy weight produces equivalent outcomes this has the potential to reduce the standard length of current hospital treatment for AN in adolescents from approximately 9 to 12 weeks to 2 to 3 weeks, resulting in benefits including savings of hospital based resources and reductions in the disruptions to schooling, peer and family relationships, adolescent development and family life.  Should this not be the case this would support this would support the need for increased periods of hospitalisation with the possible benefits including reduced hospital readmission rates, decreased length of illness, decreased medical complications from malnutrition and lower levels of family and patient distress.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Children's Hospital at Westmead</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/12/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2006/114</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Sloane Madden</name>
      <address>The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Locked Bag 4001
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 98452005</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 98452009</fax>
      <email>sloanem@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jane Miskovic</name>
      <address>The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Locked Bag 4001
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 1284</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 98452009</fax>
      <email>janem6@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jane Miskovic</name>
      <address>The Children's Hospital at Westmead Locked Bag 4001 Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 1284</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9845 2009</fax>
      <email>janem6@chw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>