<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83084">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/08/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/03/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000144213</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Abdominal Binder effect on breathing, speech and blood pressure in spinal cord injuries.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is breathing, speech and blood pressure improved with the use of an abdominal binder in people who have suffered an acute spinal cord injury?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Spinal Cord Injury</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects will all wear an abdominal binder throughout the study period (there will NOT be two groups with one wearing the AB and one group not). However, testing with and without the abdominal binder will be randomised in order of testing for each time point according to a computer generated randomisation order list of binder on/off. An elastic binder is an elastic garment that wraps around a patients abdomen extending from the bottom of the ribs to just above the hip. It is used when a patient assumes an upright position. Patients are provided with an abdominal binder when they first commence sitting up in a wheelchair after acute injury. Patients are advised to continue the use of an abdominal binder if they have no motor activation of the abdominal muscles. Outcome measures will be collected over 4 points in time during the subjects first 12 months after a spinal cord injury.</interventions>
    <comparator>No abdominal binder</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory function- 
Vital capacity (VC), forced vital capacity in one second (FEV1), Peak expiratory flow (PEF) will be measured using a handheld SpiroPro machine.
 
Maximum expiratory pressure (MEP)and maximum inspiratory pressure (MIP) will be measured using a Micro Medical MicroRPM machine</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks after mobilization, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Speech function - Sustained phonation, loudness range, conversational speech quality will be measured using the Edirol device. Data analysis will be carried out by trained blinded Speech Pathologists.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks after mobilization, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean arterial pressure will be calculated from blood pressure recording taken using the portable OMRON IA2</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks after mobilization, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Acute spinal cord injury above T12, Amercian Spinal Injuries Association (ASIA) classification system of ASIA classification A or B which indicates complete motor dennervation below level.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pressure sore of stage 2 or greater, active respiratory disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Within subject design, Subjects will have outcomes collected with and without abdominal binder in place when seated.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Ipswich Rd,
Woolloongabba 4102
Brisbane</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Health Allied Health Research Scholarship</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Rd, Woolloongabba 4102
QLD</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Rehabilitation and Health Sciences
Sir Fred Schonnell Drive
St Lucia
Brisbane 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients who experience spinal cord injury loose normal function of respiratory muscles leaving them particularly vulnerable to respiratory complications, loss of optimal speech function and potential development of secondary postural deformities.  Gravity, in conjunction with increased abdominal muscle compliance, pulls downward on the diaphragm resulting in flattening of the diaphragm, which reduces its ability to drive respiration.  Abdominal binders limit abdominal wall distension when against gravity (sitting in wheelchair) by replacing the non-functioning abdominal muscle (innervated T5-T12) role.  The restoration of diaphragm position may assist with improved respiration, speech and blood pressure when a patient is sitting in his/her wheelchair.
This study will investigate the effect of an abdominal binder on breathing, speech and blood pressure in newly injured patients admitted to the Spinal Injuries Unit of Princess Alexandra Hospital.  Those patients that have suffered an injury resulting in damage to T12 level or above and presenting as a complete injury will be approached.  

The current practice in the Spinal Injuries Unit is to wean the abdominal binder once the cardiovascular system has adapted and postural hypotension is no longer a concern. However, the abdominal binder has been shown to have an effect on respiratory function.

Respiratory, speech and blood pressure measurements will be taken with and without the binder on in sitting at 6weeks post initial mobilizing,12 weeks,24weeks ,and 48 weeks after this point.  The results of this study will be analyzed to determine the effect of binder use on outcomes collected.  These results will direct further practice and use of the abdominal binder.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Wadsworth BM, Haines TP, Cornwell PL, Paratz JD. Abdominal binder use in people with spinal cord injuries: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Spinal Cord advance online publication, 21st October 2008;doi:10.1038/sc.2008.126</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ipswich Rd, Woolloongabba. Brisbane 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/02/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2005/079</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Brooke Wadsworth</name>
      <address>QSCIS
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Rd, Woolloongabba 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 32402089</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 32402009</fax>
      <email>painsolutions@bigpond.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Brooke Wadsworth</name>
      <address>QSCIS
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Rd, Woolloongabba 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 32402089</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 32402009</fax>
      <email>painsolutions@bigpond.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Brooke Wadsworth</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>painsolutions@bigpond.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>