<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365901">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000332628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of a soft-tissue technique on shoulder functional profile in nonprofessional tennis players</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Influence of an osteopathic soft-tissue technique on the glenohumeral range of motion and shoulder rotator muscle strength in nonprofessional competitive tennis players: Immediate effects and after 3 weeks.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>shoulder sport-specific adaptations</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Osteopathic soft-tissue technique on the dominant shoulder will be applied once for 10 minutes. 
The player will sit on the table, he will put the dominant hand on the non dominant shoulder, keeping the arm in a horizontal plane. The therapist will be behind the player, he will stabilize the player's trunk with his thorax. With the first corner of the internal hand, he immobilizes the scapula and the collarbone of player's dominant shoulder. With the first corner of the external hand, he seizes the axillary crease.
The technic will be composed of three phases :
1. Exaggeration:
The player will low the elbow downward until the therapist will feel the tension in the first corner of the internal hand. The player will make a deep costal inspiration followed by an apnea, the therapist will wait then for the soft-tissue relaxation. The therapist could meet several barriers which he will exceed gradually during the time of exaggeration.
2. Correction :
The player will make a light rotation of trunk to non dominant side and the therapist will make a counter strain with the external hand, putting in tension glenohumeral elastic tissues. The patient will raise the elbow until the therapist feels tension, player will then make a deep costal expiration followed by an apnea. The therapist will wait for the soft-tissue relaxation and will progress in the same way towards the internal rotation by exceeding the tissular barriers.
3. Consolidation :
The previous parameters will be kept, the subject will make a deep costal inspiration followed by an apnea, the therapist will wait for the soft-tissue relaxation and he will put off his hands on a costal inspiration of the patient.

</interventions>
    <comparator>The player will sit on the table, the therapist will be behind him with the internal hand on the dominant shoulder, he will take the player's dominant hand with his external hand. The therapist will apply passive movements in adduction (once), external circumduction (three times) and maximal internal rotation (twice).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glenohumeral internal/external range of motion will be measured using a standard manual goniometer, in the supine position with the arm abducted 90 degrees.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, after the osetopathic soft-tissue intervention, and after 3 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Shoulder external and internal rotator muscle strength will be measured using a hand-held dynamometer, in the supine position with the arm abducted 90 degrees.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, after the osteophatic soft-tissue technique, after 3 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>healthy nonprofessional competitive tennis players</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>dominant shoulder pain or injury</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The tennis players will be contacted by phone
Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>The block random allocation will be applied </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The mean and standard deviation of each outcome parameter will be calculated. Then inferential statistical tests will be performed, in particular Analysis of Variance with one independant factor (two groups) and three repeated measurements. Following the osteopathic intervention, we attempt to find an increase by 5 +/- 5 degrees of the glenohumeral internal rotation. Based on 20 subjects, the a priori statistical power will be equal to 99% and the effect size would be equal to 1.0.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>rhone</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universite Claude Bernard Lyon 1</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>UFRSTAPS - Centre de Recherche et d'Innovation sur le Sport - EA 647
27-29, boulevard du 11 novembre 1918 
69622 VILLEURBANNE cedex
France</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>France</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>UFRSTAPS - Centre de Recherche et d'Innovation sur le Sport - EA 647
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>27-29, boulevard du 11 novembre 1918
69622 VILLEURBANNE Cedex</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>France</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The tennis practice is known to limit the glenohumeral internal rotation range of motion, and to develop the internal rotator muscle strength at the dominant shoulder. The aim of this study is to investigate the effects of a osteopathic intervention on the shoulder flexibility and strength. Forty nonprofessional tennis players will be recruited to participate in this study. Two groups will be defined: a first group will receive an osteopathic soft-tissue intervention, while the second group will receive a placebo osteopathic soft-tissue intervention. The glenohumeral internal and external range of motion of the dominant shoulder will be measured using a manual goniometer. The shoulder internal and external rotator muscle strength will be evaluated using a handle dynamometer. These measurements will be made before the intervention, immediately after the intervention and after three weeks. We hypothesize that the osteopathic intervention will limit the shoulder tennis-specific adaptations immediatly after its application, and these effects will be still observable after three weeks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite de Protection des Personnes SUD EST II</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hopital Edouard Herriot
Batiment 12 - 1er etage
5 place d'Arsonval
69437 LYON CEDEX 03</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>France</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>ROGOWSKI Isabelle</name>
      <address>UCB Lyon 1 - UFRSTAPS
Centre de Recherche et d'Innovation sur Sport - EA 647
27-29, bd du  11 novembre 1918
69622 VILLEURBANNE Cedex</address>
      <phone>+33 4 72 43 28 48</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>isabelle.rogowski@univ-lyon1.fr</email>
      <country>France</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>CREVEAUX Cecile</name>
      <address>Isosteo
13 Chemin du Petit Bois 
69130 ECULLY</address>
      <phone>+33 6 10 87 13 47</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cecile.creveaux.osteo@gmail.com</email>
      <country>France</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>ROGOWSKI Isabelle</name>
      <address>UCB Lyon 1 - UFRSTAPS
Centre de Recherche et d'Innovation sur Sport - EA 647
27-29, bd du  11 novembre 1918
69622 VILLEURBANNE Cedex</address>
      <phone>+33 4 72 43 28 48</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>isabelle.rogowski@univ-lyon1.fr</email>
      <country>France</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>CREVEAUX Cecile</name>
      <address>Isosteo
13 Chemin du Petit Bois 
69130 ECULLY</address>
      <phone>+33 6 10 87 13 47</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cecile.creveaux.osteo@gmail.com</email>
      <country>France</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>