<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364869">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001012763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Voice disorders in very preterm children: responsiveness to treatment.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, controlled trial of behavioural voice therapy in very preterm children with moderate to severe voice difficulties: effects on voice quality.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dysphonia.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Intubation injury.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hyperfunctional voice use.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Very preterm birth.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be offered 8 sessions of behavioural voice therapy, either immediately (experimental group) or following an 8 week delay (comparison group).

Behavioural voice therapy will target vocal hygiene information and counselling, indirect voice therapy targeting abdominal breathing and laryngeal relaxation, and direct voice therapy targeting easy onset phonation and resonant voice therapy.

Behavioural voice therapy will be administered one-on-one by a speech pathologist, in the presence of a caregiver to promote without session carryover of the therapy tasks.

Sessions will last for one hour and be administered once per week for eight weeks. In the event of cancellations and postponements, the therapy period will be extended to ensure that each participant receives the entire therapy over eight sessions.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparison group will not be provided with treatment during the intervention window for the experimental group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dysphonia severity as measured by the Consensus Auditory Perceptual Evaluation of Voice rating scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For the experimental group, immediately after randomisation prior to commencement of intervention and after 8 weeks (at completion of treatment).

For the control group, on initial assessment (Phase I of study), 8 weeks after randomisation (period of no treatment) prior to commencement of intervention, and after a further 8 weeks (completion of treatment).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Influence of voice on quality of life as measured by the Pediatric Voice Handicap Index rating scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For the experimental group, immediately after randomisation prior to commencement of intervention and after 8 weeks (at completion of treatment).

For the control group, on initial assessment (Phase I of study),  8 weeks after randomisation(period of no treatment) prior to commencement of intervention, and after a further 8 weeks (completion of treatment).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dysphonia severity as measured by the Acoustic Voice Quality Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For the experimental group, immediately after randomisation prior to commencement of intervention and after 8 weeks (at completion of treatment).

For the control group, on initial assessment (Phase I of study), 8 weeks after randomisation (period of no treatment) prior to commencement of intervention, and after a further 8 weeks (completion of treatment).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Voice quality, as measured by the GRBAS (Grade, Roughness, Breathiness, Aesthenia and Strain scale).</outcome>
      <timepoint>For the experimental group, immediately after randomisation prior to commencement of intervention and after 8 weeks (at completion of treatment).

For the control group, on initial assessment (Phase I of study), 8 weeks after randomisation (period of no treatment) prior to commencement of intervention, and after a further 8 weeks (completion of treatment).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Birth at less than 32 weeks gestation and admitted to the NICU at a single tertiary centre at birth.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known disability likely to preclude compliance with assessment tasks.
Residence &gt;200km from the study centre.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants for this trial will be recruited from Phase I - Clinical voice assessment (quasirandomised recruitment) and Phase II - Fribeoptic Endoscopic Evaluation of Laryngeal Function (self-selection) and then randomised to either the experimental or control groups.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>All participants will receive intervention. The experimental group will commence intervention immediately after randomisation, and the control group will receive therapy 8 weeks after randomisation to allow comparison of voice quality with and without intervention.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/10/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/11/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Women and Infant's Research Foundation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>C/O Carson House
Bagot Road
SUBIACO  WA  6008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Telethon Trust, administered by the Women and Infant's Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>C/O Carson House
Bagot Road
SUBIACO  WA  6008</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Greater numbers of children now survive preterm birth. Dysphonia is a newly-recognised long-term complication of extremely preterm birth, yet remains a relatively little-researched entity. Voice outcomes have been associated with gestational age, birthweight and cardiac surgery. However, the strongest association found has been with intubation in the neonatal period. Thus, there is a need to investigate voice quality of all who may be intubated.

Laryngeal pathology of very preterm children has not been systematically documented in the literature. Yet knowledge of laryngeal pathology is essential for intervention planning. Laryngeal pathology is investigated jointly by the Ear, Nose and Throat medical speciality and the Speech Pathology Voice allied health speciality. 

Further, there has been no investigation of treatment effects in preterm voice disorders. Having identified that dysphonia is a long-term voice outcome for some preterm children, treatment options should be investigated.

Finally, many preterm children participate in paediatrician follow-up programmes to maximise medical and developmental outcomes. As dysphonia can now be considered a possible long-term complication for some preterm children, a screening tool for voice difficulties could be incorporated into existing follow-up programmes. The ideal measure would have: i) diagnostic accuracy to correctly identify the presence of dysphonia; ii) sensitivity to change in voice quality due to therapy; and iii) be quick and simple to administer to minimise cost.

This study consists of three phases: an observational study of voice quality and its impact on quality of life in 200 children born at less than 32 weeks gestation; assessment of the nature and extent of laryngeal pathology visualised in those children with moderate to severe dysphonia; and a quasi-randomised, non-blinded, controlled trial of behavioural voice therapy in the children with moderate to severe dysphonia.  Additionally, the sensitivity to therapeutic change of an objective voice assessment, the Acoustic Voice Quality Index, validated by our laboratory as a measure of dysphonia severity in children, is being measured. 

This registration pertains to Phase III Intervention.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Roberts Road
SUBIACO WA  6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1995EP</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Western Australia Human Research Ethics Office</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Western Australia
Hackett Drive
CRAWLEY  WA  6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/1/5633</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Noel French</name>
      <address>King Edward Memorial Hospital
Bagot Rd
SUBIACO WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 1260</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>noel.french@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Victoria Reynolds</name>
      <address>University of Western Australia
School of Paediatrics and Child Health
M561
Hackett Drive
Crawley WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 438 749 005</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>victoria.reynolds@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Victoria Reynolds</name>
      <address>University of Western Australia
School of Paediatrics and Child Health
M561
Hackett Drive
Crawley WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 438 749 005</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>victoria.reynolds@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>