<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367749">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000260527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of mesenchymal stem cells in the treatment of hip osteoarthritis  prospective case series data collection</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The evaluation of autologous adipose derived mesenchymal stem cells as treatment for symptomatic hip osteoarthritis on pain, function and cartilage volume in osteoarthritis patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1166-1016</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will look to prospectively assess the response of symptomatic hip osteoarthritis to mesenchymal stem cell therapy using the following protocol :
- Intra-articular injection of 20million stem cells at 0 and 6 months (total of 40million cells).

This will be a single treatment group uncontrolled case series.

Autologous adipose derived mesenchymal stem cells will be used due to the ease of harvest (liposuction) and safety.</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hip Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score - 
consists of 5 subscales being pain, other symptoms, function in daily living, function in sport and recreation and knee related quality of life. It is reliable and valid for the population of people with osteoarthritis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at 0,1,3,6 and 12months post commencement of study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>0-10 Numerical Pain Rating Scale (NPRS) - The NPRS has been validated for use in people with hip osteoarthritis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at 0,1,3,6 and 12months post commencement of study.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>MRI quantitative data including mapping of cartilage volume.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at commencement of study and again at 12months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global perceived effect scale. Measures of global effect are a recommended outcome measure for clinical trials</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at 1,3,6 and 12months post commencement of study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain Treatment Satisfaction Scale - a validated questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at 1,3,6 and 12months post commencement of study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Orebro Musculoskeletal Pain Questionnaire will also be completed. This questionnaire has been to shown to be reliable and valid for detecting individuals at risk of developing persistent pain. This questionnaire will be used in the current study to assess the potential impact of psychosocial factors on participants outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at commencement of study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion Criteria :
1.	Radiological diagnosis of hip osteoarthritis using the American College of Rheumatology criteria (Altman, 1986).
2.	Primary OA treatment already undertaken defined as: analgesia/anti-inflammatory medication, supplements approved by the treating clinician (eg glucosamine sulphate), an attempted exercise program prescribed by a physiotherapist or medical practitioner for at least 8 weeks (Petrella 2000), weight loss and nutritional management as prescribed by a dietitian or medical practitioner for at least 8 weeks, and biomechanical management including bracing if appropriate as prescribed by a physiotherapist, podiatrist or medical practitioner.  Autologous MSC is an invasive treatment and guidelines recommend trialling conservative measures as the first line of treatment in OA (Thompson, Gordon et al. 2009).
3.	Sufficient English skills to complete the questionnaires required for the study, as well as to understand the instructions given by the study doctors. This is required as no funding is available for translation or interpreters, and the outcome questionnaires to be used have only been validated in English language. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria:
1.	Age &lt;18yrs.  OA does not commonly occur in people under 18.
2.	Pregnancy (accepted contra-indication as no safety data on this population). 
3.	Breastfeeding (accepted contra-indication as no safety data on this population). 
4.	Have other causes of their hip symptoms suspected to be due to serious pathology such as tumour or referral from the hip or lumbar spine.  These conditions are not under investigation within the current project.
5.	Blood disorder (accepted contra-indication as no safety data on this population)
6.	Anti-coagulant therapy that cannot safely be ceased.
7.	History of cancer. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The trial will be advertised to both allied health and medical groups. Google ads will also be used to gather attention within the general community. 

After direct enquiry from a possible participant and after an initial phone based screen, participants will be invited to attend for a formal assessment to ascertain their suitability for treatment and involvement in this prospective case series. If suitable they will be invited to enrol in the study and then complete a formal informed consent. </concealment>
    <sequence>Case series</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data analysis will focus on change in pain, function and quantitative MRI measures  (with 95% confidence intervals) at each of the follow-up points (1-month, 3-months, 6-months and 12-months). Analyses will be conducted using SPSS Version 21, with alpha set at 0.05 using a two-tailed hypothesis. Continuous data will be analysed using linear mixed models. These were chosen for their strength in analysing longitudinal biological data and accounting for correlations associated with repeated measurement. The mixed models will adjust for the baseline score of the outcome of interest as recommended by the revised CONSORT statement. Ordinal data will be analysed using the Mann Whitney U test.
At each follow-up point, participants will be dichotomised according to whether they achieved the minimum clinically important difference of the outcome or not, and then the risk ratio, risk difference and number needed to treat will be calculated along with 95% confidence intervals. Statistical significance will be evaluated using Chi square analysis. For these purposes, the minimum clinically important difference will be defined as 10/100 for the KOOS, 2/10 for the NRS pain scales, at least much improved on the global rating of change scale and very satisfied on the treatment satisfaction scales. It has been argued that these values for minimum clinically important difference may be too low in some contexts, hence we will repeat this analysis using a threshold of 50% reduction in KOOS scores and NRS pain scores based on empirical validation studies suggesting that this may be a more suitable threshold for important differences.
All participants who withdraw from treatment for any reason will continue to be contacted for follow-up assessments and informed that their data are still required. Missing data will be handled via restricted maximum likelihood estimation within the linear mixed models. Given the popularity of simple data imputation methods we will undertake a secondary sensitivity analysis to determine whether the results would differ if missing data were replaced using the last observation carried forward method.

There is insufficient data published to date on the effects of autologous MSC on hip osteoarthritis.  As such sample size calculations are not possible. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/01/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>1/01/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>50</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Magellan Stem Cells</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 2, 116-118 Thames St
Box Hill Nth 3128
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Melbourne Stem Cell Centre</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 2, 116-118 Thames St
Box Hill Nth 3128
Victoria</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Osteoarthritis is a major cause of pain and disability world wide. This study aims to explore the effectiveness of autologous mesenchymal stem cell (MSC) injections in treating hip OA. This study involves the use of autologous MSC, autologous meaning that the cells are taken from and injected back into the same person. Based on previous animal studies and initial human patients, these MSCs are expected reduce pain and assist in bone and cartilage tissue repair, supporting their potential in the treatment of hip osteoarthritis.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.melbournestemcellcentre.com/research/</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Humam Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics
Monash Research Office
Monash University
Level 1, Building 3e, Clayton Campus
Wellington Rd
Clayton VIC 3800, Australia </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF14/2229 - 2014001174</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/367749-Hp Case Series Explanatory Statement.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard Boyd</name>
      <address>Department of Anatomy and Developmental Biology, School of Biological Sciences Monash University Clayton, Victoria 3800 Australia</address>
      <phone>+6139905 0630</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.boyd@monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Julien Freitag</name>
      <address>Melbourne Stem Cell Centre Level 2, 116-118 Thames St Box Hill Nth Victoria 3128</address>
      <phone>+61392708000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julien.freitag@mscc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard Boyd</name>
      <address>Department of Anatomy and Developmental Biology, School of Biological Sciences Monash University Clayton, Victoria 3800 Australia</address>
      <phone>+6139905 0630</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.boyd@monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Julien Freitag</name>
      <address>Melbourne Stem Cell Centre Level 2, 116-118 Thames St Box Hill Nth Victoria 3128</address>
      <phone>+61392708000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julien.freitag@mscc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>