<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1162">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/03/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/03/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000098538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The management of acute low-back pain in general practice</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Implementing a clinical practice guideline for acute low-back pain evidence-based management in general practice: a cluster randomised controlled trial of the effectiveness of a tailored implementation strategy on patient low-back pain disability and x-ray referral</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>IMPLEMENT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute (duration &lt;3 months) non-specific low-back pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: tailored implementation strategy (face-to-face education sessions, printed educational materials and patient education) for a clinical practice guideline. Delivered over a two month time period.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control: dissemination only of the clinical practice guideline. Delivered at a single time point.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>None</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General practitioner (GP) level #1: measurement of behavioural constructs measured by a questionnaire developed by our research team for this trial. Questionnaire items were designed by considering constructs relevant to behaviour (drawn from the Theoretical Domains Framework and the Theory of Planned Behaviour)
Michie S, Johnston M, Abraham C, Lawton R, Parker D, et al. (2005) Making psychological theory useful for implementing evidence based practice: a consensus approach. Quality &amp; Safety in Health Care 14: 26-33.
Ajzen I (1991) The theory of planned behavior. Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes 50: 179-211
Francis J, Eccles M, Johnston M, Walker A, Grimshaw J, et al. Constructing questionnaires based on the theory of planned behaviour. A manual for health services researchers, 2004. Centre for Health Services Research, University of Newcastle</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months after intervention/control delivery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP level #2: Behavioural simulation outcomes (clinical decision in response to vignettes)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after intervention/control delivery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP level #3: Referral rates for plain x-ray and CT scan (Administrative data outcomes)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after intervention/control delivery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP level #4: GPs' fear avoidance beliefs about low back pain were measured via a modified version of the Fear-Avoidance Beliefs Questionnaire (FAB-Q) physical activity subscale adapted for the GP participants.
Waddell G, Newton M, Henderson I, Somerville D, Main CJ (1993) A Fear-Avoidance Beliefs Questionnaire (FABQ) and the role of fear-avoidance beliefs in chronic low back pain and disability. Pain 52: 157-168.
Coudeyre E, Rannou F, Tubach F, Baron G, Coriat F, et al. (2006) General practitioners' fear-avoidance beliefs influence their management of patients with low back pain. Pain 124: 330-337</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>General practices will be included if:1. The practice manager agrees to the practice being involved in the C-RCT.2. At least one GP, and no objection from the remaining GPs, within the practice provide written informed consent.3. Practice GPs do not work in more than one practice.4. Practice support staff are willing to facilitate patient recruitment. Patients will be included if:1. They attend the participating practices for acute non-specific LBP (duration of less than three months).2. Provide written informed consent.3. Are able to write and understand English.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>General practices will be excluded if:1. Any of the GPs at the practice participated in focus groups during part one of this study.Patients will be excluded if:1. Radicular pain is present.2. They have had previous spinal surgery.3. Red flags are present, alerting the possibility of serious conditions such as malignancy, infection and fracture.4. Pregnancy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A statistician independent of the study and located at a central administration location will implement the randomisation. Allocation will involve contacting the statistician via phone/email and providing them only with general practice codes and strata variables which will be used in the randomisation. The statistician will then provide the allocation of the general practices.</concealment>
    <sequence>Restricted randomisation will be employed. Computer generated random numbers will be used to randomly select permutations.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>2300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Institute of Health Services Research, Monash University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>43-51 Kanooka Grove
Clayton, VIC 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC,Primary Health Care Project Grant 334060</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, 20 Allara Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Department of General Practice, Monash University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Building 1, Omnico Business Park
270 Ferntree Gully Rd
Notting Hill  VIC  3168</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The recently released NHMRC-endorsed evidence-based clinical practice guideline for acute low-back pain management provides an opportunity to assess the effects of a tailored implementation strategy for use in general medical practice. This trial will assess the effectiveness of the implementation strategy both at the general practitioner and patient level and also assess the cost effectiveness of the strategy. Successful implementation of these guidelines will reduce the morbidity and cost of acute low-back pain. The trial will contribute to our knowledge about implementation strategies attempting to change clinical practice behaviour.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.cochrane.org.au/projects/implement.php</trialwebsite>
    <publication>McKenzie J, French S, O'Connor D, Grimshaw J, Mortimer D, Michie S, Francis F, Spike N, Schattner P, Kent P, Buchbinder R &amp; Green S (2008). IMPLEmenting a clinical practice guideline for acute low back pain evidence-based manageMENT in general practice (IMPLEMENT): cluster randomised controlled trial study protocol. Implementation Science 3: 11

Mortimer D, French S, McKenzie J, O'Connor D &amp; Green S (2008). Protocol for economic evaluation alongside the IMPLEMENT cluster randomised controlled trial. Implementation Science 3: 12

Page MJ, French SD, McKenzie JE, O'Connor DA, Green SE (2011) Recruitment difficulties in a primary care cluster randomised trial: investigating factors contributing to general practitioners' recruitment of patients. BMC Med Res Methodol 11: 35

French SD, Green SE, O'Connor DA, McKenzie JE, Francis JJ, et al. (2012) Developing theory-informed behaviour change interventions to implement evidence into practice: a systematic approach using the Theoretical Domains Framework. Implement Sci 7: 38</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Standing Committee on Ethics in Research Involving Humans</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2006/047</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sally Green</name>
      <address>School of Public Health and Preventive Medicine
Level 6, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99030366</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sally.green@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Simon French</name>
      <address>Centre for Health, Exercise and Sports Medicine
The University of Melbourne
200 Berkeley St
Carlton, Victoria 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83445536</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.french@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>