<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362579">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000603819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A 12 month randomised controlled trial to determine biomarkers from the gut microbiota as management tools for overweight and obesity</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A 12 month randomised controlled trial to determine biomarkers from the gut microbiota as management tools for overweight and obesity</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Overweight and obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects are randomised to either a standardised high protein, Mediterranean, or low fat (low GI) diet. Subjects will meet the study dietitian for advice on their allocated diet and prescribed the diet for weight loss i.e. based on the Harris Benedict Equation for estimating energy requirements with an energy deficit of 500 calories daily. Each of the diets will be followed daily over a six month period. Subjects will then be followed up for a further six months (up to month 12). Each of the diets will be costed relatively the same so that there is no extra cost for the participant depending on their randomisation group. For those randomised to the high protein diet, strategies for cutting cost will be educated to participants at the baseline and follow up visits. For example, recipes for budget cuts of meat will be provided, as well as focusing their diets on cheaper sources of protein including canned fish, eggs, milk and yoghurt. Home brand alternatives of similar nutritional quality with also be encouraged. This will also be applicable to those in the Mediterranean diet when including fish and olive oil products. The low GI diet will be based on foods endorsed by the glycemic index foundation with the latest GI values for popular foods explained to subjects.</interventions>
    <comparator>All three diets are an intervention. There is no control comparison.  In this study we aim to identify microbial signals in stool samples that will allow clinicians to predict which diets will give successful weight loss outcomes (thus avoiding the frustration of diet failures) and also to test how to improve and change a persons microbiota to a healthy composition.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. To develop rapid methods based on microbial biomarkers by which clinicians can predict:
(i) Those who will achieve weight loss in any given lifestyle program and;
(ii) Those who will be maintain their weight loss.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Month 1, Month 3, Month 6, and Month 12.
Subjects will provide stool samples at these clinic visits for molecular biology processing (PCR, flow cytometry and DGGE) and sequencing.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. To test the hypothesis that homeostatic control of the microbiota constrains weight loss outcomes in lifestyle programs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Month 1, Month 3, Month 6, Month 12. 
Subjects will provide stool samples at these clinic visits for molecular biology processing (PCR, flow cytometry and DGGE) and sequencing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. To examine the differences in weight loss between groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Month 6, Month 12.
Subjects will be weighed at clinic visits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3. To investigate changes in a number of indicators of metabolic disease between groups - fasting blood glucose, lipid profile, liver function, and inflammatory markers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Month 6, Month 12.
Fasting bloods will be taken at clinic visits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4. To investigate the change in appetite hormones with changes in microbiota.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Month 3, Month 6, Month 12.
Fasting bloods will be taken at clinic visits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 18 years or older
BMI 25  35 kg/m2</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Recent diagnosis of diabetes (&lt; 3 months)
Unstable angina or recent onset of cardiovascular disease
Serious hepatic or renal disease
- serum transaminases (ALT or AST) &gt; 2.5 times upper limit of normal
- serum creatinine &gt; 1.5 times upper limit of normal or urinary microalbumin &gt;40 mg/L or eGFR &lt; 60ml/min/1.73m2
Alcohol or illicit drug abuse
Pregnant, breastfeeding, or planning pregnancy during the study
Treatment for an eating disorder, weight loss medications and other drugs that affect body weight e.g. anti-psychotics, anti-depressants, or corticosteroids
Hypothyroidism defined by elevated thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) and low free thyroxine (fT4), or current hyperthyroidism under treatment
Participation in another weight loss clinical trial within past 3 months
Individuals who have lost &gt;10% weight within past 3 months
Inability to read and write English
Subjects who frequently change smoking habits or who have stopped smoking within 6 months prior to screening. Those who wish to take on the advice of a 'Quit' smoking program at the time of screening will be eligible to start the trial after 3 months.
Subjects not willing to participate in all of the specimen collection.
Individuals with known penicillin and/or cephalosporin hypersensitivity will not be eligible for randomisation to the antibiotic treatment, however will still be eligible for entry into the trial</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All participants will come into the clinic for a screening visit. Once a participant is deemed eligible for randomisation, they will be allocated to a treatment group (i.e. High protein diet, Mediterranean diet, low fat (low GI) diet). Random group allocation will be performed by the study database upon entry of the participant’s details and determination of eligibility. The person who determines if a subject is eligible for inclusion in the trial is unaware, when the allocation is made, to which group the subject would be allocated. It will not be possible to override this allocation. Allocation is to be done by central randomisation with a computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation process will be completed by computer using a FileMaker Pro database that is password protected by The University of Sydney server. The process essentially works the same as ‘lotto’. The computer effectively picks a ball which is then taken out of the total allotment number (in this case n=108). This ensures that at the end of the randomisations, all 108 slots have been filled and there is no imbalance between groups.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>108</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Microbes influence how much energy we extract from our diet, how we regulate the storage of this as fat, and also on glucose regulation. There are both good and bad microbes.  We have found that in overweight or obese persons undergoing weight loss diets not everyone is successful and significantly those who fail to lose weight are also those who fail to change their microbial community composition. In this study we aim to identify microbial signals in stool samples that will allow clinicians to predict which diets will give successful weight loss outcomes (thus avoiding the frustration of diet failures) and also to test how to improve and change a persons microbiota to a healthy composition.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://sydney.edu.au/medicine/research/units/boden/index.php</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)
Level 6
Jane Foss Russell Building 
The University of Sydney NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/06/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14547</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andrew Holmes</name>
      <address>G08 - Biochemistry Building
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006 Australia</address>
      <phone>+61293512530</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.holmes@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nicholas Fuller</name>
      <address>92-94 Parramatta Road, 
Medical Foundation Building K25
The University of Sydney,
Camperdown, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61290363468</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.fuller@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nicholas Fuller</name>
      <address>92-94 Parramatta Road, 
Medical Foundation Building K25
The University of Sydney,
Camperdown, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61290363468</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.fuller@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>