<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335532">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/12/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001105033</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of stretching on muscle performance and functionality of institutionalized elderly women</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of stretching on muscle performance and functionality of institutionalized elderly women</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1115-1115</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Effects of stretching on muscle performance and functionality of institutionalized elderly women</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Initially, 142 women were contacted via the administration of a long term care facility. Sixty-one women were excluded from the study as they presented limited mobility condition (use of wheel chair, cane or other walking devices), 10 were found to experience health problems and 52 subjects presented restrictions to the practice of physical activities. Thus,  nineteen elderly women were divided into 2 groups at random: Control Group (CG, n=09) participated in enjoyable-cultural activities as playing with balloons or balls, the chair dance and movements of the upper and lower limbs; The Stretching Group (SG, n=07) performed active stretching of hamstrings, 4 bouts of 1 min each. Both groups were supervised 3 times per week over a period of 8 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>After recruited, subjects were randomly assigned in the control group (CG; n=9), which received educative talks about health habits and cultural activities or in the second group- The Stretching Group (SG, n=07) performed active stretching of hamstrings, 4 bouts of 1 min each. Both groups were supervised 3 times per week over a period of 8 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak torque was assessed by an isokinetic.  Both groups were evaluated by The Photogrammetric Method to assess muscle-tendon length of uni- and biarticular hip flexors and hamstring flexibility.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Both groups (control-GC and Stretching-SG) were evaluated before and 8 weeks later.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible criteria were present non-limited physical and cognitive conditions evaluated by the following: Mini Mental State Exam-MMSE, Barthel Index and Lysholm Scoring Scale. The MMSE questionnaire was conducted to determine the cognitive ability of the subjects according to education level and it had to be more than 13, while the Barthel Index to establish the activities of daily living (ADL) had also to be more than 13 and the Lysholm Scoring Scale was applied to assess knee functional status which had to set up at 84.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The procedure for enrolling a subject and allocating the treatment (allocation concealment procedures) was done using a central randomisation by computer. Nineteen institutionalized female elderly nursing home residents were randomized to the Stretching Group (SG, n=10) or to the Control Group (CG, n=09). The total number of participants that completed the study is shown (n=17).  To be included the participants were submitted to The MMSE questionnaire to determine their cognitive ability according to education level and it had to be more than 13, also the Barthel Index to establish the activities of daily living (ADL) which should reach more than 13 and the Lysholm Scoring Scale was applied to assess knee functional status which had to set up at 84.</concealment>
    <sequence>For randomization was used random number table
2. Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>17</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Parana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sao Vicente de Paulo long-stay Institution, Curitiba, Parana, Brazil.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Barao dos Campos Gerais, 970
Curitiba - PR
CEP: 80.030-400</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Physical Education, Federal University of Parana, Curitiba, Parana, Brazil</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Coracao de Maria, 92
Jardim Botanico Curitiba - Parana
 80215-370</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Knee Clinic, Curitiba, Parana, Brazil.</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Getulio Vargas, 3066
Agua Verde - Curitiba - PR
CEP 80610-010</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Objective: Evaluate the chronic effects of stretching on the muscle strength, flexibility and functionality in institutionalized elderly women. Design: Randomized Controlled Trial. Setting: Sao Vicente de Paulo Nursing home. Participants: Elderly women (N=19; 67 years) 
Interventions: Control Group (CG, n=09) received educational lectures and enjoyable-cultural activities; Stretching Group (SG, n=07), Active stretching of hamstrings, 4 bouts of 1 min, both 3 sessions/week, during 8 weeks.  Main Outcome Measures: Assessment of isokinetic strength, range of motion (ROM) of knee flexor and extensor muscles were performed before and after 8 weeks. Functionality was analyzed by Barthel. Results: Flexibility of hamstrings increased in SG when compared to pre-training (59.5 degrees vs 76.5 degrees) and CG (76.5 degrees vs 64.0 degrees) the CG decreased ROM of the hip bi-articular flexor muscles (118.3 degrees vs 124 degrees) and eccentric knee extensor peak torque, compared to pre test (-60.5 Nm degrees vs -49.4 Nm degrees). 
Conclusion: Stretching program was effective to increase ROM of knee flexor muscles. A lack of stretching can cause flexibility losses and muscle strength reduction.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the Parana Federal University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Committee of the Parana Federal University
Padre Camargo, 280- Alto da Gloria
CEP: 80060-240
Parana, Curitiba-PR</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/04/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CAAE-0003.0.91.000-09</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Anna Raquel Silveira Gomes</name>
      <address>R. Jaguariaiva, 512
Caioba
Matinhos-Parana
Brasil
CEP: 83260-000</address>
      <phone>+55 (41) 8406-1100</phone>
      <fax>+ 55 (41) 35118300</fax>
      <email>annaraquelsg@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Daniela Gallon</name>
      <address>Av Presidente Kennedy, 1823 apto 13, Bairro: Agua Verde, CEP: 80610-010, Parana, Curitiba (PR), Brazil.</address>
      <phone>+55 (41) 99469611</phone>
      <fax>+55 (41) 35118300</fax>
      <email>danigallon@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Daniela Gallon</name>
      <address>Presidente Kennedy, 1823 apto 13, Bairro: Agua Verde. Curitiba. Parana. Brazil
 CEP 80610-010</address>
      <phone>+55 41 33339883</phone>
      <fax>+55 41 33339883</fax>
      <email>danigallon@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>