<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83848">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/04/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000301268</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving the Psychosocial Health of People with Cancer and their Carers: A Community Based Approach</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Improving the Psychosocial Health and Distress Levels of People with Cancer and their Carers through therapist-delivered or self-managed support intervention: A Community Based Approach</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Beating the Blues After Cancer</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Psychosocial health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Distress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Economic evaluation of support interventions to determine its economic efficiency</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This project is a randomised controlled trial comparing minimal contact self help self management materials versus a tele-based psychologist delivered cognitive behavioural intervention. Group 1: The self-managed support arm will consist of an initial single 30-minute telephone support and education session with a nurse counsellor who will provide feedback to the participant about his/her levels of distress and instruction in evidence based strategies to improve adjustment. A resource package will also be provided as in kind support that will include a range of already developed audio and written patient education materials produced by The Cancer Council Queensland. The duration of the self-managed intervention for Group 1 will dictated by the participants utilisation of their resource material after the initial telephone contact by the nurse counsellor. Group 2: For the individualised cognitive behavioural intervention (therapist delivered), five one-hour sessions of tele-based counselling from a clinical psychologist will be delivered that include psycho-education, skills in stress reduction, problem-solving, cognitive challenging and enhancing relationship support. The individualised counselling sessions will include assigned behavioural homework that will be supported by work and tip sheets. It is anticipated that the 5 therapist delivered sessions for Group 2 will be conducted at regular intervals after randomisation and completed before follow-up assessment at 3 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>On the ethical basis that these participants have demonstrated elevated psychological distress we will not utilise a no treatment control group. This project is a randomised controlled trial comparing minimal contact self help self management materials versus a tele-based psychologist delivered cognitive behavioural intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 1: Psychological Distress will be assessed through self report measures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 2: Cancer specific distress will be assessed through self report measures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 3: Unmet Psychological Supportive Care Needs will be assessed through self report measures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Seconday outcome 1: Positive adjustment  will be assessed through self report measures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Seconday outcome 2: Quality of life will be assessed through self report measures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 3: A trial-based economic evaluation will be conducted that integrates the efficacy and quality of life outcomes data with comparative cost data on the intervention options. The various distress indicators and the unmet needs data will be built in incremental cost-effectiveness analysis (CEA), while the quality of life data will be used in cost-utility analysis (CUA) using the Brazier algorithm. The feasibility of adding a modelled economic evaluation (to broaden the target population; lengthen the time horizon beyond that of the trial; and estimate cost offsets) will also be carefully assessed, having regard to trial results and the strength of evidence in the literature to underpin key modelling assumptions. 
Costs and outcomes will be assessed from a health sector perspective, but with a focus on government as 3rd party funder. Cost impacts that fall on patients and their carers/families will be reported to the extent they can be assessed from the activity data; but this collection will not be complete. Pathway analysis and patient flowcharts (incorporating decision tree analysis) will be used to clearly identify and cost the activity components for each arm of the trial. Standard discounting will be applied to both costs and outcomes, together with detailed sensitivity testing (using @RISK probabilistic software).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients suffering from any form of cancer or carers of those suffering from any form of cancer who contact the Cancer Helpline in both Queensland and New South Wales, have a score of 4 or over on the Brief Distress Thermometer at the time of Helpline contact, be able to read and speak English, be an adult aged 18 years or over and have no previous history of head injury, dementia or psychiatric illness.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A caller to the Cancer Helpline who is not a patient or carer, a score under 4 on the Brief Distress Thermometer at time of Helpline contact, under the age of 18 years, unable to read and speak English, a previous history of head injury, dementia or psychiatric illness</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Cancer Helpline staff will identify potential participants who meet study inclusion criteria and will invite participation into the study. Verbal permission to be contacted by the research team will be obtained and 
information sheet and consent forms posted. Project staff will telephone potential participants within a couple of days of initial contact to discuss the information sheet and ensure study eligibility. The initial contact is designed to explain the research in more detail, assess the person's interest in participating, determine eligibility and where appropriate to conduct the baseline
assessment. Following baseline assessment participants will be randomly allocated to an intervention group. Intervention allocation will be via central randomisation by a computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be stratified by patient/carer and state (QLD vs NSW) and will occur in blocks. Simple randomisation will be achieved by using a random number generator (within Stata SE 10.1) based on the Uniform distribution. This sequence will be undertaken by the project manager and concealed from investigators.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Two group randomised controlled trial: self-managed support; therapist-delivered support intervention</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/09/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>3/08/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>560</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4006</postcode>
    <postcode>2011</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cancer Council Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 201, Spring Hill, Qld, 4004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 1201
Dickson
CANBERRA
ACT 2602</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>beyondblue</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 6100
Hawthorn West
VIC 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Centre for Health Research &amp; Psycho-oncology (CHeRP), The University of Newcastle</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Newcastle
Room 230A
Level 2
David Maddison Building
Callaghan  
NSW  2308</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Cancer Council NSW</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 572
Kings Cross NSW 1340</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Griffith University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychology
Room 4.09
Psychology Building (M24)
Griffith University
176 Messines Ridge Road
Mt Gravatt Qld 4122</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cancer is the leading cause of burden of disease and injury in Australia, accounting for nearly one-fifth of the total disease burden. The diagnosis and treatment of cancer is a major life stress that is followed by a range of well described psychological, social, physical and spiritual difficulties. Approximately 35% of patients will experience persistent clinically significant distress and carers often experience even higher distress than patients. The aim of the proposed study is to assess the efficacy and cost-effectiveness of accessible and affordable psychological interventions for distressed cancer patients and carers who contact community based Cancer Helplines. The study comprises a randomised controlled trial with patients and carers who have elevated psychological distress, comparing minimal contact self management with an individualised tele-based cognitive behavioural intervention.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
Room 2.39, Bray Centre(N54) 
Nathan Campus
Griffith University
170 Kessels Road
Nathan, Qld 4111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/04/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>PSY/19/09/HREC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/03/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Suzanne Chambers</name>
      <address>Griffith Health Institute GO5 Health Sciences, Room 2.13 Gold Coast Campus Griffith University QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5678 0008</phone>
      <fax>N/A</fax>
      <email>suzanne.chambers@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Suzanne Chambers</name>
      <address>Griffith Health Institute GO5 Health Sciences, Room 2.13 Gold Coast Campus Griffith University QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5678 0008</phone>
      <fax>N/A</fax>
      <email>suzanne.chambers@griffith.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bronwyn Morris</name>
      <address>Cancer Council Queensland
PO Box 201
Spring Hill
QLD
4004</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3634 5370</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 7 3259 8527</fax>
      <email>bronwynmorris@cancerqld.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Suzanne Chambers</name>
      <address>Griffith Health Institute GO5 Health Sciences, Room 2.13 Gold Coast Campus Griffith University QLD 4222 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 5678 0008</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>suzanne.chambers@griffith.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>