<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365174">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001174774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Online treatment for depression in people with osteoarthritis: a randomised controlled trial
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing Internet based cognitive behaviour therapy (iCBT) for depression in patients with osteoarthritis vs. treatment as usual on depression symptoms. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All intervention participants will separately complete 6 lessons of Internet based cognitive behavioural therapy (iCBT) about the management of symptoms of depression over 10 weeks. One lesson will be completed every 7 to 14 days (it will become available after the preceding lesson has been completed, with a minimum of 7 days between lessons and a maximum of 14 days). Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to complete. Participants will have access to summaries of each lesson, homework exercises, extra resources, email contact from the Clinician (Registered Psychologist) after completion of the first two lessons, then as required. The participant is also able to email or phone the clinician at any point during the trial as required. The participant completes a measure of psychological distress before each lesson and if their scores increase by one or more standard deviations the clinician is automatically alerted and contact with the participant either by phone or email is initiated. 

Strategies used to improved adherence to intervention protocols and procedures for monitoring adherence include: automated email reminders, monitoring the downloading of homework, collection of data on how long participants spent reading lessons and practising skills.</interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment as usual (TAU) waitlist control group. These participants remain on the waitlist and receive their usual treatment for osteoarthritis until the treatment groups have completed their treatment and 3-month follow-up (24 weeks). At that time (24 weeks) the waitlist control group will be offered the same iCBT program for depression.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reductions in the Patient Health Questionnaire  9-Item (PHQ-9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (week 4), 1 week post-treatment (week 11), and 3 months after post-treatment (week 24).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reductions in psychological distress according to the Kessler-10 (K10).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, mid-treatment (week 4), 1 week post-treatment (week 11), and 3 months after post-treatment (week 24).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reductions in the SF-12  a 12 item validated measure of functional health and wellbeing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 week post-treatment (week 11), and 3 months after post-treatment (week 24).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reductions in the Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-Item (GAD-7).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 week post-treatment (week 11), and 3 months after post-treatment (week 24).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the Pain Catastrophising Scale  (PCS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 week post-treatment (week 11), and 3 months after post-treatment (week 24).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the Arthritis Self Efficacy Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 week post-treatment (week 11), and 3 months after post-treatment (week 24).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the Western Ontario and McMaster (WOMAC) Osteoarthritis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 week post-treatment (week 11), and 3 months after post-treatment (week 24).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PainDetect Questionnaire (PD-Q). </outcome>
      <timepoint>The PD-Q will be used to assess the relationship between depressive symptoms severity and neuropathic pain measured at baseline. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment Credibility/Expectancy Questionnaire (CEQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of current Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) based on the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview Version 5.0.0.

Diagnosis of symptomatic Osteoarthritis based upon radiographic criteria and pain on most days. The recruitment pathway ensures all potential participants (i.e., those who are informed about the study) meet this eligibility criterion.


Age 50+

Prepared to provide name, phone number and address, and to provide the name and address of a local general practitioner, and to provide informed consent. 

English language skills equivalent to a School Certificate level. 

Have access to a phone and a computer with regular Internet access and a printer. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Severe depression (PHQ-9 &gt;23) and/ or current suicidality (PHQ-9 Q9=2 or 3).

If taking medication for anxiety or depression, has been taking the same dose for less than 1 month or intended to change the dose during the course of the program.

Currently receiving CBT for depression or completed an iCBT or CBT program for depression in the past 6 months or intention to commence CBT for depression. 

Psychosis, bipolar disorder, substance abuse or dependence. 

Taking antipsychotics or benzodiazepines.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants apply online, followed by a telephone interview to confirm diagnosis via the Mini-International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI), a structured clinical interview. </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomized using a list generated prior to the study.

Allocation concealment will occur in the following way: A staff member not involved in the clinical trial will generate the sequence using computer software and place each choice in a sequentially numbered, opaque sealed and stapled envelope. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based on previous results, we anticipate the iCBT group to improve more than the TAU Control group by an ES of 0.8.  

Assuming a more conservative ES of .60 for the secondary OA-specific outcome measures we will recruit 50 participants in each group (allowing for at least 20% potential attrition). Sample size is powered to have an 80% chance of detecting differences at p&lt;.05. 

Analyses will be undertaken using mixed-model repeated measures (MMRM) ANOVA with measurement occasion as a within-groups factor and intervention as a between-groups factor. Relationships between observations at different occasions will be modelled with an unstructured covariance
matrix. For each experimental group, planned contrasts will be used to compare changes from baseline to post-intervention and 3- month follow-up.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>26/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>6/10/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>77</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St Vincent's Hospital
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Gavin Andrews</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aims of the current study are to evaluate the efficacy of a validated internet-based cognitive behavioural therapy
(iCBT) program (CRUfAD's Sadness Program) for depression when delivered to individuals who meet criteria for a
major depressive episode comorbid with osteoarthritis (OA).

This study will recruit 100 people with depression and OA and randomly allocate them to 1 of 2 conditions: OA
treatment as usual (TAU) + iCBT for depression or OA TAU + delayed iCBT for depression (TAU waitlist control).

The primary outcomes will be to determine the impact of online CBT for MDD on depression symptoms and remission rates, as well as on OA-specific outcomes. 

We will also measure adherence to the course material and satisfaction with the intervention generally.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Trial publications pending</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincent's Hospital
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/SVH/292</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression 390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1405</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression 390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1405</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression 390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1405</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jessica Smith</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression 390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8382 1434</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jessica.smith@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>