<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336949">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/05/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000548932</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Kava Anxiety-Lowering Medication (KALM) Project 
Acute Kava Mood, Anxiety and Cognition Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of administration of kava on driving ability, cognition, mood and anxiety measures in comparison to oxazepam and placebo in adults aged 18-65 presenting with current mild to moderate levels of anxiety.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>KALM acute</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mood</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly allocated to one of three treatments at each session during the study (A,B,C). At the end of the study they will have taken all of the interventions individually. The trial treatments are kava, oxazepam and placebo. Participants must take the four tablets simultaneously once during each of the testing session. Randomised to either: 

A)Oxazepam treatment  - 1 oxazepam tablet (30mg) and 3 kava placebo (0mg) 
B) Kava treatment - 1 oxazepam placebo tablet (0mg) and 3 kava (60mg each = 180mg) tablets
C)Placebo treatment - 1 oxazepam  placebo tablet (0mg) and 3 kava placebo tablets (0mg)

This is a crossover study with a one week washout period between each session.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo tablet is a sugar pill, identical in taste and appearance but without the active ingredient (Kava and oxazepam)

Treatment C which consists of 1 oxazepam  placebo tablet (0mg) and 3 kava placebo tablets (0mg) is the placebo condition</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Driving via driving simulator (indoor on the computer) assessing driving ability</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collection will occur during week 0 at baseline and at sessions 1, 2 and 3 which will be 3-5 days apart</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood and Anxiety via The State-Trait Anxiety Inventory, 
The State-Trait-Cheerfulness-Inventory (STCI) and  
Bond-Lader Visual Analogue Scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collection will occur during week 0 at baseline and at sessions 1, 2 and 3 which will be 3-5 days apart</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognition via computerised cognitive assessment battery exploring effects on quality of memory, speed and accuracy of attention and working memory and a brief pencil and paper memory recall task</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collection will occur during week 0 at baseline and at sessions 1, 2 and 3 which will be 3-5 days apart</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess any differences between responders or non-responders to Kava due to genetic differences (liver enzyme or neurochemical polymorphisms). This will be done via bloods tests analysed by pathology labs.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collection will occur during week 0 at baseline and at the last testing session</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be eligible into the study if they have elevated stable levels of stress and anxiety and are not diagnosed with major depressive disorder or bipolar disorder. As there is evidence that kava can interfere with other herbal remedies, prescription medications and over the counter products that share CYP450 metabolism (Singh 2005), enrolled participants will be screened for drugs, alcohol and current medication use. As this is a randomized trial there will be equal probability of the control (placebo) and active (kava/oxazepam) groups to have the same numbers of participants who are currently on medication. 


Specific inclusion criteria:
1.Males and females aged between 18-65 years of age 
2.Must be currently presenting with mild to moderate levels of anxiety (HAM-A 14 to 25)
3.Fluent in English
4.Participant must provide a signed copy of consent form</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Diagnosis of Psychotic or Bipolar illness, or Major Depressive Disorder
2.Significant suicidal ideation in the previous 6 months
3.Current use of the following medications: antidepressants, mood stabilisers, antipsychotics, opiod, analgesics, St Johns wort, HIV, anti-tumoral/cancer, blood pressure, warfarin, Parkinsons, epileptic, migraine or anti-ulcer medications 
4.Diagnosed hepato-biliary disease/inflammation
5.Substance abuse or dependency disorder including alcohol in the previous 6 months 
6.Previous adverse reaction to kava or benzodiazepines
7.Current smoker (more than one day per week)
8.Regular use of kava or benzodiazepines in the previous 12 months
9.No more than one occasion of benzodiazepine or kava use each week over the past month
10.Pregnancy, trying to conceive, or those who could be pregnant
11.Lack of facility in written or spoken English</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A disinterested third party generated the randomisation list using a computerised random number sequence generator. Allocation involved contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is off-site</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be contacted via avertisements in health clinics and on community notice boards. Participants will be screened to ensure they pass the inclusion/exclusion criteria and allocated a participant number and treatment condition. 

Eligible recruited participants will be assigned a participant number. The treatment number that has been placed next to the participant’s number will be the allocated treatment for that individual.

Blinding will be achieved by enlisting a person outside of the project to code the treatments, and maintain the key to this code until data collection is completed. An emergency code break envelope will be provided to the principle investigator which will only be opened in case of emergency. If this occurs, the sponsor and the ethics committee will be informed. The codes will only be broken in an emergency, such as an SAE that requires knowledge of the treatment being taken in order to manage a participant’s condition.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/02/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/03/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>6/08/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>22</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3022</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Integria</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 1, 8
Clunies Ross Court, Eight Mile Plains Qld 4300</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Integria</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 8
Clunies Ross Court, Eight Mile Plains Qld 4300</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of this trial is to examine the effects of administration of kava (a plant medicine) on driving ability, cognition, mood and anxiety measures in comparison to oxazepam (a synthetic anti-anxiety drug) and placebo in adults aged 18-65 presenting with current mild to moderate levels of anxiety.
Participants will be randomly allocated to one of three treatments at each session during the study (A,B,C). At the end of the study they will have taken all of the interventions individually. The treatments consist of kava, oxazepam, or placebo tablets consumed orally.
A. Kava (180mg)  3 X 60mg tablets taken in one session. 
B. Oxazepam (30mg tablet) - 1 tablet taken in one session. 
C. Oxazepam placebo 1 tablet taken in one session, or kava placebo 3tablets taken in one session</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>J. Sarris , E. LaPorte , A. Scholey , R. King , A. Pipingas , I. Schweitzer
&amp; C. Stough (2013) Does a Medicinal Dose of Kava Impair Driving? A Randomized,
Placebo-Controlled, Double-Blind Study, Traffic Injury Prevention, 14:1, 13-17, DOI:
10.1080/15389588.2012.682233</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Swinburne's Human Research Ethics Committee (SUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 218
Hawthorn VIC 3122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/01/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2010/210</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/09/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jerome Sarris</name>
      <address>The Melbourne Clinic 

130 Church St, Richmond 

Victoria, 3121</address>
      <phone>+613 9420 9350</phone>
      <fax>na</fax>
      <email>jsarris@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jerome Sarris</name>
      <address>The Melbourne Clinic 

130 Church St, Richmond 

Victoria, 3121</address>
      <phone>+613 9420 9350</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jsarris@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rebecca King</name>
      <address>Swinburne University of Technology
Advanced Technologies Centre
Burwood Rd, Hawthorn,VIC 3122</address>
      <phone>613 9214 5087</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rking@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jerome Sarris</name>
      <address>The Melbourne Clinic 130 Church St, Richmond Victoria, 3121</address>
      <phone>+613 9420 9350</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jsarris@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>