<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368490">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000859482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The efficacy of mangosteen pericarp fruit extract for the treatment of schizophrenia.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The efficacy of adjunctive Garcinia mangostana Linn. (mangosteen) pericarp for the treatment of schizophrenia: A 24-week double blind randomised placebo controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MANGO SZ/CADENCE-M</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Schizophrenia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Total daily dose of 1000mg of Garcinia mangostana L. (mangosteen dried fruit pericarp encapsulated in gelatine capsules): 500mg 2 capsules once a day with food.
Duration of treatment: 24 weeks
Participants will be instructed to return unused medication which will be calculated and documented to determine medication adherence. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Total daily dose of 1000mg of rice flour weighted gelatine capsules: 500mg 2 capsules once a day with food.
Duration of treatment: 24 weeks</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome will be the change in schizophrenia symptom severity on PANSS total score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4,8,12,16,20, primary endpoint week 24, post-discontinuation week 28.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in PANSS Positive subscale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4,8,12,16,20, primary endpoint week 24, post-discontinuation week 28.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in depressive symptoms using MADRS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4,8,12,16,20, primary endpoint week 24, post discontinuation week 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in participant life satisfaction rated on the self-reporting scale (Q-LES-Q)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 4,12,16,20, primary endpoint week 24 and post-discontinuation week 28.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in functioning measures using the Global Assessment of Functioning Scale (GAF)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4,8,12,16,20, primary endpoint week 24 and post-discontinuation week 28.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in functioning measures using the LIFE-RIFT scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 4,8,12,16,20, primary outcome week 24 and post-discontinuation week 28.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in participant perception using the Patient Global Impression Scale (PGI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 4,8,12,16,20, primary endpoint week 24 and post-discontinuation week 28.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in participant cognition using Cogstate computerised cognitive testing (Cogstate).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in tobacco use will be recorded using the Opiate Treatment Index (OTI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood samples are being collected at baseline and the end of the treatment phase (week 24).  We expect to explore oxidative stress factors, including cytokines, thiobarbituric acid reactive substances and total antioxidant capacity. However, as the field of biological psychiatry is rapidly moving, these will be exploratory investigations for which the targets may change by the end of the trial.  Participants are providing blood samples as an optional extra to the trial and have signed unspecified consent to allow all relevant and unforeseen investigations to occur at the completion of the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in PANSS Negative subscale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4,8,12,16,20, primary endpoint week 24, post-discontinuation week 28.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in PANSS General Psychopathology subscale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4,8,12,16,20, primary endpoint week 24, post-discontinuation week 28.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in alcohol use will be recorded using the Opiate Treatment Index (OTI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in heroin use will be recorded using the Opiate Treatment Index (OTI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in other opiates use will be recorded using the Opiate Treatment Index (OTI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in cannabis use will be recorded using the Opiate Treatment Index (OTI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in amphetamine use will be recorded using the Opiate Treatment Index (OTI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in cocaine use will be recorded using the Opiate Treatment Index (OTI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in (illicit) benzodiazepine use will be recorded using the Opiate Treatment Index (OTI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in barbiturates use will be recorded using the Opiate Treatment Index (OTI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in hallucinogens use will be recorded using the Opiate Treatment Index (OTI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in inhalants use will be recorded using the Opiate Treatment Index (OTI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in synthetic drugs use will be recorded using the Opiate Treatment Index (OTI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in the occurence of tardive dyskinesia using the Abnormal Involuntary Movement Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4,8,12,16,20, primary endpoint week 24, post-discontinuation week 28.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in overall illness severity, improvement or change and therapeutic response using  the Clinical Global Impression</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4,8,12,16,20, primary endpoint week 24, post-discontinuation week 28.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in alcohol use using the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The changes in level of nicotine dependence using the Fagerstrom Test for Nicotine Dependence</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and primary endpoint week 24.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Global Impressions (CGI)  - Severity scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4,8,12,16,20, primary endpoint week 24, post-discontinuation week 28.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CGI - Improvement scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, weeks 4,8,12,16,20, primary endpoint week 24, post-discontinuation week 28.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Being 18 years or older
2. Have a DSM-V diagnosis of schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder.
3. Score greater than or equal to 54 on the PANSS total score or have a CGI-S score of greater than or equal to 3.
4. Participants currently under therapy for schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder will need to have been on that primary therapy for at least four weeks prior to randomization.
5. Have the capacity to consent to the study and comply with the procedures.
6. Be using effective contraception if female, sexually active and childbearing age.
7. Be able to speak, read, write and understand English language.
8. Participants will be required to nominate a current treating physician and will not be eligible to enter the study until one is identified.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Participants with a known or suspected active systemic medical disorder.
2. Individuals who are pregnant or lactating.
3. Participants currently enrolled in any other intervention study.
4. Individuals who are intolerant, allergic to or have had an anaphylactic reaction to any of the components of the preparation.
5. Inability to comply with either the requirements of informed consent or treatment protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited through various recruitment avenues including advertisements through local newspapers, flyers in medical waiting rooms, pharmacies and university campuses. Direct contact will be made with potential referral sources consisting of general practitioners, community mental health teams, the disability support sector, support groups, private psychiatrists and local psychiatric inpatient unit.
Trial clinicians will contact all participants referred to the trial to schedule an initial face-to-face screening interview to establish written consent, that inclusion criteria are satisfied and confirm the DSM-V diagnosis of schizophrenia or scizoaffective disorder with a PANSS total score of greater than or equal to 54 or CGI greater than or equal to 3. Participants will be randomised in the Garcinia mangostana Linn group or placebo group and will be allocated a study number for trial identification purposes. Packs will be allocated sequentially and bottles are identical so as to conceal treatment allocation and blinding. To facilitate the double-blinding process, the trial medications will be dispensed by an independent pharmacist in identical numbers and capsule forms in sealed containers. The trial statistician and trial clinicians will be blinded to the group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation to treatment arm will be randomly assigned using 1:1 ratio (active to placebo) using permutated block randomisation. An independent researcher will develop the computer-generated randomisation plan. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The statistical method used will be a likelihood based mixed-effect model and repeated measures approach (MMRM). The MMRM model includes the fixed, categorical effects of treatment-by-visit interaction, as well as the continuous, fixed covariates of baseline score and baseline score-visit interaction. Results from the analysis of dichotomous data will be presented as proportions, with 95% confidence interval and Fisher's exact p-value where appropriate. Non-parametric statistics will be used when assumptions for parametric methods are violated. Effect sizes will be calculated using Cohen's guidelines. All tests of treatment effects will be conducted using two-sided alpha level of 0.05 and 95% confidence intervals. Change scores in symptoms and biological markers will be derived. Pearson Product Moment Correlations will be used to examine the relationships between the change scores for symptoms and the change scores for biological markers in two groups. Using Fisher's z transformation, we will test whether the correlations obtained for each group are statistically different in terms of strength.  Sample size: Pilot study data indicated that effect sizes depicting treatment group differences in change between baseline to endpoint, ranged from moderate (e.g., GAF, Cohens d=0.59), to large (PANSS Total, Cohens d=1.41). Power and sample size calculations for the proposed study were conservative and based on the smallest effect observed in the pilot study (i.e. medium effect for GAF). With power (1-ß) set at 0.90, alpha (a) at the 0.05 level, a sample size of 50 per group is required. As effect sizes are typically smaller in follow up studies and to allow for attrition, total sample size was increased to 150, to enable confident detection of PANSS Total group differences. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/07/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>101</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Ipswich Hospital - Ipswich</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>Logan Hospital - Meadowbrook</hospital>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Barwon Health - Geelong Hospital campus - Geelong</hospital>
    <hospital>The Geelong Clinic - St Albans Park</hospital>
    <postcode>3220 - Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>4305 - Ipswich</postcode>
    <postcode>4006 - Herston</postcode>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <postcode>4122 - Upper Mount Gravatt</postcode>
    <postcode>4131 - Meadowbrook</postcode>
    <postcode>3219 - St Albans Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3214 - Corio</postcode>
    <postcode>3215 - Bell Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3228 - Torquay</postcode>
    <postcode>3216 - Belmont</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University Hospital-Barwon Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>P.O. Box 281 
Geelong VIC 3220</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Stanley Medical Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>8401 Connecticut Avenue, Suite 200
Chevy Chase, MD 20815</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Queensland,  Queensland Brain Institute </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The University of Queensland
QBI Building 79, University of Queensland, 
St Lucia QLD 4072
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is evidence of anomalies in redox biology in schizophrenia; (i) the presence of oxidative stress (where the levels of antioxidants are decreased or the levels of free radicals are increased to a point that is damaging to the function of the cell, increasing inflammation) particularly implicating the glutathione system ; (ii) changes in oxidative status with treatment; and (iii) evidence that other glutathione and redox active agents have therapeutic value.
Garcinia mangostana Linn, known colloquially as mangosteen, is a tropical evergreen fruit tree originating from Indonesia. Its rind or pericarp contains an exudate containing a large number of bioactive compounds called xanthones that have robust effects on the glutathione system and many other pathways germane to schizophrenia. Motivated by the results of the first pilot randomised, double blind placebo trial of adjunctive Garcinia mangostana Linn for the treatment of schizophrenia we speculate that this research may uncover a new class of agents for the treatment of the disorder, and uncover novel pathophysiological pathways.
The trial involves 150 participants aged 18 years or older with a DSM-V diagnosis of schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder. Participants referred to the trial will have an initial faceto-face screening interview. All randomised participants will receive two 500mg mangosteen pericarp capsules once a day to a total dose of 1000mg daily or placebo, in addition to treatment as usual, for 24 weeks. Assessment will occur at regular 4 weekly intervals throughout the 24 weeks and 1 month after completion of the study. The primary outcome will be the change in schiaophrenia symptom severity using the PANSS total scale at the end of the 24-week treatment phase. The secondary outcomes will include changes in depressive symptoms, quality of life, functioning and life satisfaction which will be measured using the PANSS subscales, Q-LES-Q scale, GAF, LIFE-RIFT, PGI and Cogstate. Blood biomarkers will also be analysed. Blood samples will be obtained at baseline and week 24.  Blood will be analysed for relevant markers based on preclinical evidence including markers of antioxidant defence, oxidative stress and markers of inflammation. The research will have immediate and direct translational benefits. The safety and tolerability of Garcinia mangostana Linn, its affordability and accessibility and that the general public are accepting of plant-derived compounds, raise its attraction as a potential therapeutic agent.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Barwon Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Office
University Hospital-Barwon Health
P.O.Box 281
Geelong, Victoria
3220</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/26</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/06/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Metro South HREC Office
PAH Centres for Health Research
Level 7, Translational Research Institute
37 Kent Street
Woolloongabba QLD 4102
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QPAH/15 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368490-MANGO S StudyProtocol-V1-12-5-15-update.doc</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Berk</name>
      <address>IMPACT Strategic Research Centre
Swanston Centre
University Hospital-Barwon Health
P.O.Box 281
Geelong
Victoria 3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 42153330</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 42153491</fax>
      <email>mikebe@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Berk</name>
      <address>IMPACT Strategic Research Centre
Swanston Centre
University Hospital-Barwon Health
P.O.Box 281
Geelong
Victoria 3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 42153330</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 42153491</fax>
      <email>mikebe@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Berk</name>
      <address>IMPACT Strategic Research Centre
Swanston Centre
University Hospital-Barwon Health
P.O.Box 281
Geelong
Victoria 3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 42153330</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 42153491</fax>
      <email>mikebe@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Olivia Dean</name>
      <address>Level 1 Kitchener House
P.O Box 281
Geelong
Victoria 3220</address>
      <phone>+61 3 42153300</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 42153491</fax>
      <email>oliviad@barwonhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>