<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336039">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000890033</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can pain words hurt? A randomised trial comparing comfort versus pain scores following caesarean section</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pain versus Comfort scores after caesarean section: a randomised trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pain after caesarean section</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>On the post-anaesthetic ward round within 10-36 hours after caesarean section, eligible women will be randomised to one of two groups. One group will be asked questions specifically about their level of comfort (Group C). The other group will be asked questions specifically about their level of pain (Group P). Overall, every participant will be asked the same questions, however the questions may be asked in a different order, depending on the Group. Participants will be interviewed by one of three researcher anaesthetists, medical students or midwives.

After a greeting and introduction, women in Group C will be asked Are you comfortable?. If the woman says that they are not comfortable, they will be asked why they are not comfortable. They will then be asked for a Verbal Numerical Rating Score (VNRS) for comfort. More specifically they will be asked: With regard to your healing caesarean wound, can you please rate your comfort level at rest, where 10 is most comfortable and zero is least comfortable and then When you move, how would you rate your level of comfort where 10 is most comfortable and zero is least comfortable?. Women will then be asked Is the healing wound bothering you?, and then, How much is the healing wound bothering you, where zero is least bothersome and 10 is most bothersome?, and then Would you like any additional medication to get you more comfortable?. Women will then be asked to indicate how comfortable they are feeling, at rest and on movement, on a 100mm sliding Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) for comfort. Patient will then be asked Do you have any pain? and then will be asked for a VNRS for pain at rest and on movement, and their VAS for pain at rest and on movement. Women will then be asked Would you prefer to be asked about your comfort level or your pain level or do you have no preference?. If the woman reported that she was comfortable earlier in the interview, she will be asked Earlier in this interview when you said that you were comfortable, did you have any pain at that exact moment in time. If the woman reported that she was comfortable, and then later said she was in pain, she will then be asked Why did you say you were comfortable even though later you said you were in pain?. And finally, women will be asked whether their pain is an unpleasant experience or something that is not unpleasant.</interventions>
    <comparator>As in Group C, Group P women will be interviewed within 10-36 hours after caesarean by one of three researchers. Following a greeting and introduction, Group P will be asked Do you have any pain? They will then be asked Can you please rate your pain level at rest, where 10 is most painful and zero is least painful? and then When you move, how would you rate your pain where 10 is most painful and zero is least painful Women will then be asked Does the pain bother you? and then Would you like additional pain relief?.  Women will then be asked to indicate how much pain they have, at rest and on movement, on a 100mm sliding VAS for pain. Then women will be asked Although that you have said that you have pain, would you say that you are comfortable? Then they will be asked for a VNRS and a VAS for comfort at rest and on movement, whether they would prefer to be asked about their comfort level or pain level, and whether their pain is unpleasant or not unpleasant, as in Group C.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain severity as measured by a zero to ten point Verbal Numerical Rating Score (VNRS) for pain and the VNRS for comfort.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 10-36 hours after caesarean section women will be randomised to one of the two groups. They will be interviewed within 5 minutes of randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain severity as measured by 100mm Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) for comfort and VAS for pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 10-36hours after caesarean section women will be randomised to one of the two groups. They will be interviewed within 5 minutes of randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether or not the pain is bothersome when asked "Is the healing wound bothering you?" in Group C, or "Does the pain bother you?" in Group P. This outcome is dichotomous - either yes or no.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 10-36 hours after caesarean section women will be randomised to one of the two groups. They will be interviewed within 5 minutes of randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether or not the patient would like additional analgesia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 10-36hours after caesarean section women will be randomised to one of the two groups. They will be interviewed within 5 minutes of randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether the patient prefers to be asked about their comfort level, or their pain level, or they do not have a preference</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 10-36hours after caesarean section women will be randomised to one of the two groups. They will be interviewed within 5 minutes of randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether the patient considers their pain as unpleasant or not unpleasant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 10-36hours after caesarean section women will be randomised to one of the two groups. They will be interviewed within 5 minutes of randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All English speaking women who are scheduled for post-anaesthesia review following caesarean section.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women will be excluded if they need an interpreter, are deaf, have an intellectual disability, or have a history of chronic pain or opioid abuse.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Women will be interviewed between 10-36 hours after caesarean section. Eligibility will be assessed by case note review and then eligible women will be randomised to one of the two study groups immediately before the interview. Allcoation concealment is achieved by consecutively numbered opaque sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>5006</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Women’s &amp; Children’s Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>72 King William Road,
Adelaide, S.A. 5006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine if the use of the word pain when asking for pain scores in the post-anaesthesia review after caesarean section results in higher scores than if the word comfort is used instead.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Child Youth and Women's Health Service (CYWHS) Women's and Children's Hospital (WCH) Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>72 King William Rd
Adelaide, SA 5006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/06/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00197</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Allan M Cyna</name>
      <address>Department of Womens Anaesthesia
Womens &amp; Childrens Hospital,
72 King William Road,
Adelaide, S.A. 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81617630</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 81617020</fax>
      <email>allan.cyna@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Allan M Cyna</name>
      <address>Department of Womens Anaesthesia
Womens &amp; Childrens Hospital,
72 King William Road,
Adelaide, S.A. 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81617630</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 81617020</fax>
      <email>allan.cyna@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Allan M Cyna</name>
      <address>Department of Womens Anaesthesia
Womens &amp; Childrens Hospital,
72 King William Road,
Adelaide, S.A. 5006</address>
      <phone>+61 8 81617630</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 81617020</fax>
      <email>allan.cyna@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>