<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367267">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/11/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001162606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can early active repetitive motor training prevent development of upper limb contracture after stroke? A randomised trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does early active repetitive motor training for inpatient stroke survivors with upper limb hemiplegia prevent loss of passive range of motion in the upper limb more than standard upper limb rehabilitation?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1162-9542</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Upper limb hemiplegia following stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Upper limb contracture following stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Early active repetitive motor training for a maximum of 1 hour per day, in addition to usual upper limb therapy programs, 5 days a week for 5 weeks. Early active repetitive motor training will be delivered using the SMART Arm device. The SMART Arm is a non-robotic device which enables intensive and repetitive reaching practice by patients with severe upper limb weakness. Training using the SMART Arm will involve repeatedly practicing a reaching task by pushing the arm along a track to reach a goal e.g. to reach to a goal line or grasp an object. to help the participant achieve the movement, electrical stimulation may be applied to one or more muscles which straighten the arm or open the hand. Training may be progressed by increasing the number of repetitions and speed, adding weight, elevating the work surface and including a number of grasping tasks.
There will be no minimum amount of training time or repetitions. Compliance to the intervention will be monitored daily using SMART Arm training record sheets by the treating therapists. Data collected will include time spent training, number of repetitions &amp; amount of supervision for each session.
Physiotherapists, Occupational Therapists and Allied health assistants who are trained in use of the SMART Arm device, will administer the training.
The amount of supervision required for SMART Arm training will vary, and it is envisioned that many patients will be able to use the device with minimal supervision once set up.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual upper limb therapy program only, 5 days a week for 5 weeks. 
The duration of "Usual upper limb therapy" will not be prescribed in this trial. Daily data will be collected for each participant regarding the amount of "usual upper limb therapy" in terms of time, and usual therapy will be categorised as active or passive interventions.
Usual upper limb therapy will be provided by physiotherapists, occupational therapists and therapy assistants as would normally occur in both study sites, and may include one to one therapy, semi-supervised or group practice sessions.
Usual therapy will not be prescribed, but normally consists of task specific training of upper limb tasks. Usual upper limb training will be quantified in terms of time and categorised.
 </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Passive range of motion of wrist extension. Torque controlled measures of passive wrist extension in degrees will be obtained using the procedure and measurement device described by Harvey et al (1994). Measurements using a standardized protocol will be used to decrease variability. The procedure has been used in previous research investigating contracture following stroke (Lannin et al 2003, Lannin et al 2007, Horsley et al 2007).</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Passive range of motion of shoulder flexion. Passive range of shoulder flexion will be measured using the HALO digital goniometer, using a standardised procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Passive range of motion of elbow extension.Torque controlled passive range of elbow extension will be measured with the HALO digital goniometer using a standardized procedure. Intra and inter-rater reliability of the HALO digital goniometer has been demonstrated by previous research conducted by the University of Western Australia. </outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Passive range of motion of shoulder external rotation. Passive range of shoulder external rotation will be measured with the HALO digital goniometer, using a standardised procedure.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain at rest. Pain at rest will be measured using a 10cm vertical visual analogue scale (McCaffery and Pasero 1999).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arm function using the Motor Assessment Scale (MAS). A composite of the three upper limb items of the Motor Assessment scale (Carr et al 1985, Lannin 2004) will be used to score upper limb function between 0 points (no function) and 18 points (best possible score/good functional ability). </outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Passive range of motion of wrist. Torque controlled measures of passive wrist extension in degrees will be obtained using the procedure and measurement device described by Harvey et al (1994). Measurements using a standardized protocol will be used to decrease variability. The procedure has been used in previous research investigating contracture following stroke (Lannin et al 2003, Lannin et al 2007, Horsley et al 2007).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow up at 7 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pasive range of motion of shoulder flexion. Passive range of shoulder flexion will be measured using the HALO digital goniometer, using a standardised procedure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up at 7 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Passive range of motion of elbow extension. Torque controlled passive range of elbow extension will be measured with the HALO digital goniometer using a standardized procedure. Intra and inter-rater reliability of the HALO digital goniometer has been demonstrated by previous research conducted by the University of Western Australia.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up at 7 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Passive range of motion of shoulder external rotation will be measured with the HALO digital goniometer, using a standardised procedure. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up at 7 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain at rest. Pain at rest will be measured using a 10cm vertical visual analogue scale (McCaffery and Pasero 1999). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up at 7 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arm function (MAS).A composite of the three upper limb items of the Motor Assessment scale (Carr et al 1985, Lannin 2004) will be used to score upper limb function between 0 points (no function) and 18 points (best possible score/good functional ability).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Follow-up at 7 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant's perceptions of upper limb rehabilitation, using semi-structured interviews with 10 participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the 5 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain during movement. Pain on movement (during upper limb range of motion measures) will be measured using a 10cm vertical visual analogue scale (McCaffery and Pasero 1999). </outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impact of pain on sleep.The effect of pain on ability to sleep at night will be assessed using the relevant question contained in the DASH (Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand) questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>5 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain during arm movement. Pain on movement (during upper limb range of motion measures) will be measured using a 10cm vertical visual analogue scale (McCaffery and Pasero 1999).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>7 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effect of pain on sleep. The effect of pain on ability to sleep at night will be assessed using the relevant question contained in the DASH (Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand) questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>7 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>At least 10 days and no more than 6 months post stroke or stroke-like brain injury, unable to extend the affected wrist past neutral or flex the affected shoulder to greater than 90 degrees with the elbow extended.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Language, comprehension or cognitive problems which prevent informed consent and/or participation in the study. Co-existing upper limb problems which directly affect movement. Cannot participate in rehabilitation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients admitted with stroke or stroke like brain injury will be screened. Eligible patients will be informed about the study &amp; invited to participate. Written informed consent will be obtained from all participants.
Baseline measures will be collected prior to participants being randomized into either the experimental or the control group. Once a potential participant has provided informed consent, one of the investigators will telephone an off-site administrator who will advise the investigator of that participant’s allocation. This process ensures concealment of the allocation schedule from potential participants and staff recruiting participants.
</concealment>
    <sequence>The allocation schedule will be generated by a person who is not otherwise involved in the day-to-day conduct of the trial.  The “ralloc” user-written routine in Stata will be used for this purpose. The allocation schedule will be blocked. Allocation will be in random permuted blocks.
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>
    </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis
The expected (mean) effect of the experimental intervention will be estimated from the difference between the mean outcomes of the experimental and control groups. The primary analyses will be an intention to treat analysis. The focus will be on estimation of effects rather than hypothesis testing.

The primary analysis will estimate the mean difference in passive wrist and finger extension, elbow extension and shoulder external rotation range of motion between the experimental and control groups at 5 weeks.  Confidence intervals will be constructed using the t-distribution.

Secondary analyses will estimate the mean difference in each of the secondary outcomes between the experimental and Control groups.  Confidence intervals will be constructed using the t-distribution.

Sample size
The sample size of 50 is designed to give a 90% power to detect a 10 degree effect on each of the primary outcome variables. This assumes a SD of 10 degrees and a two-tailed alpha of 0.05. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sally Horsley</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Caloundra Hospital, SCHHS.
West Terrace,
Caloundra. QLD. 4551</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Wishlist Sunshine Coast Health Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 2610, Nambour West, QLD.4560</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of this study is to investigate whether five weeks of up to one hour daily of early, active, repetitive motor training in addition to usual upper limb therapy can prevent upper limb contractures after stroke or other types of ABI. Secondary aims are to determine the effect of this intervention on upper limb function and upper limb pain, and to investigate patients perspectives of the intervention. 
The study will be a parallel group, randomized controlled trial, with blinding of assessors and concealed randomization. Pre-intervention outcome measures will be taken prior to participants being randomized into either the experimental or the control group. Participants in the experimental group will receive a maximum of 1 hour a day of early active repetitive motor training using the SMART Arm device plus usual upper limb therapy, five days a week, for five weeks, in addition to the usual upper limb therapy. Participants in the control group will receive usual upper limb therapy only. The intervention will cease at the end of 5 weeks and outcome measures for both groups will be collected at that time. Follow-up outcome measures will be collected at 7 weeks. Qualitative interviews with ten participants from the experimental group will be undertaken at the end of the intervention period.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.ANZCTR.org.au/ACTRN12614001162606.aspx</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Townsville Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>HREC, Townsville Hospital &amp; Health Service, IMB 52, PO Box 670, Townsville. QLD. 4810.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/QTHS/124</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sally Horsley</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation and Assessment Unit
The Caloundra Hospital, SCHHS
West Terrace
Caloundra. QLD. 4551</address>
      <phone>+61 0427853573</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sally.horsley@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sally Horsley</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation and Assessment Unit
The Caloundra Hospital, SCHHS
West Terrace
Caloundra. QLD. 4551</address>
      <phone>+61 0427853573</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sally.horsley@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sally Horsley</name>
      <address>Rehabilitation and Assessment Unit
The Caloundra Hospital, SCHHS
West Terrace
Caloundra. QLD. 4551</address>
      <phone>+61 0427853573</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sally.horsley@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sally Horsley</name>
      <address>2/7 Lexie Street, Marcoola. QLD. 4564</address>
      <phone>+61 0427853573</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sally.horsley@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>