<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370903">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001325493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of cognitive and cognitive-motor training on falls in older people</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial on the effect of cognitive-only and cognitive-motor training on falls in older people: understanding physical, neuropsychological and neural mechanisms</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>smart+/-step</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NHMRC 1086804</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>accidental falls</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention involves home-based cognitive or motor+cognitive training in community dwelling older people. Participants will be randomised to one of 3 arms for a 12-month intervention duration. Arm 1 involves  cognitive training (seated computer games) for 120 minutes per week . Arm 2 involves cognitive-motor training (playing computer games with the feet while standing and stepping) for 120 minutes per week. Arm 3 is the no-intervention control. 

The training interventions (arms 1 and 2) involve home-based training with a custom built system of software (user interface and games), operating on a supplied personal computer and response device (touch pad for arm 1 or stepping mat for arm 2). Following a 1-hour session of instruction and safety check with a trained research assistant, participants will be asked to undertake training unsupervised in their home. Participants will receive a follow-up home visit at 4 weeks (~1 hour) to ensure safe use and progression of training and discuss any issues related to using the program. 

Upon trial commencement, arm 1 and 2 participants will be instructed to  gradually increase their training dose from 40 min per week (week 1,2), to 60 min (week 3,4), 80 min (week 5,6), 100 min (week 7, 8) and 120 min from week 9 onwards. 

The training will be recommended to be split over 3 or 4 sessions during the week and compliance will be monitored via data transfer to a web application. Participants not engaging in the minimum weekly training dose (80 mins) for 2 consecutive weeks will be contacted by telephone to discuss any issues and to encourage adherence.

Intensity and progression of intensity of training will be adjusted as performance improves and the participant moves through the inbuilt game levels.  Support will be provided by telephone and additional home visits from the research staff may be requested for those experiencing difficulty. 

Intervention group participants will also receive a custom-designed 10-page booklet containing health-related information relevant to older adults (e.g. healthy eating, exercise, hydration, mental health, bone and joint health).
</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group participants will receive a custom-designed 10-page booklet containing health-related information relevant to older adults (e.g. healthy eating, exercise, hydration, mental health, bone and joint health). The control group will receive telephone calls instead of home visits.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of fallers in each group: Falls will be monitored with supplied monthly fall diaries returned via mail.</outcome>
      <timepoint>monthly from baseline to 12 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The rate of falling in each group: Falls will be monitored with supplied monthly fall diaries returned via mail.</outcome>
      <timepoint>monthly from baseline to 12 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Standing balance (postural sway) will be measured in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group), while standing on on a foam rubber mat, using a swaymeter that records displacements of the body at the level of the pelvis for 30 seconds, </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stepping performance (speed and errors) using the choice stepping reaction time test in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait velocity will be measured in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group), with a GAITRite mat (CIR Systems Inc. Clifton, NJ) under single- and dual-task conditions. </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Timed Up &amp; Go test of mobility in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group). </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Simple hand reaction time will be measured in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group), seated using a light as the stimulus and a finger-press as the response.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Leaning balance will be measured in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group), using the maximal balance range and coordinated stability test</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trail Making Test of executive function in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stroop test, a composite measure of attention and response inhibition, will be assessed in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Controlled Oral Word Association Test of semantic/verbal fluency in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Digit Span test of working memory in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Wisconsin Card Sorting Test of set shifting will be undertaken in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Addenbrooke's Cognitive Examination Revised test of global cognition in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brain structural plasticity assessed via structural MRI in a subsample of 105 participants (35 per group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>White matter plasticity determined with Diffusion Tractography Imaging in a subsample of 105 participants (35 per group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brain functional network plasticity assessed using resting state fMRI in a subsample of 105 participants (35 per group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brain neurometabolic changes assessed with 1H-Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy in a subsample of 105 participants (35 per group). </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Concern about falling will be assessed with the icon-FES mobile application</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LOGOS: an automated test of episodic verbal memory in a random subsample of 105 participants (35 per group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pattern separation memory test in a random subsample of 105 participants (35 per group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life assessed using the EuroQol EQ-5D</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 and 12 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost-effectiveness of the intervention measured by intervention and medical costs </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait variability will be measured in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group), with a GAITRite mat (CIR Systems Inc. Clifton, NJ) under single- and dual-task conditions in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group). </outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Short Physical Performance Battery in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait step length will be measured in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group), with a GAITRite mat (CIR Systems Inc. Clifton, NJ) under single- and dual-task conditions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment in </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait double support time will be measured in a random subsample of 300 participants (100 per group), with a GAITRite mat (CIR Systems Inc. Clifton, NJ) under single- and dual-task conditions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after baseline assessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Aged 65 years and older
- Community-dwelling
- Independent in activities of daily living;
- English-speaking
- Able to walk 10m without the use of a walking aid
- Willingness to give informed consent and comply with the study protocol</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Cognitive impairment (Pfeiffer Short Portable Mental Status Questionnaire; score &lt;8)
- Acute psychiatric condition with psychosis
- Progressive neurological condition (such as Parkinsons disease, Multiple Sclerosis)
- Unstable medical condition that would preclude safe participation 
- Unable to read a computer screen
- Currently participating in a fall prevention research trial</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Volunteers will be screened for eligibility over the phone. Eligible participants will proceed to perform the baseline assessment. Following the baseline assessment, the participants will be randomly allocated to one of three groups (two intervention groups and one control group) using a web-based randomisation service.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a computer generated random number schedule available from an external web-based randomisation service. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>3-arm trial</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be analysed with an intention-to-treat approach. The number of falls per person-year will be analysed using negative binomial regression to estimate the difference in fall rates between comparison groups. The proportion of fallers between groups will be compared using the relative risk statistic. General linear models will be used to assess the effect of group allocation on the continuously scored secondary outcome measures. 

Sample size calculation (with significance levels of 0.05, power of 0.9, baseline falling rate of 45%, 20% loss to followup) revealed that 750 eligible subjects would need to be recruited initially (250/group) for a significant reduction by 34% in the number of fallers in the intervention group.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2020</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>750</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/09/2021</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Daina Sturnieks</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Neuroscience Research Australia
Margarete Ainsworth Building
Barker Street
Randwick NSW 2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GHD Building Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke St
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Stephen Lord</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Neuroscience Research Australia
Margarete Ainsworth Building
Barker Street
Randwick NSW 2031</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Jasmine Menant</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Neuroscience Research Australia
Margarete Ainsworth Building
Barker Street
Randwick NSW 2031</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Kim Delbaere</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Neuroscience Research Australia
Margarete Ainsworth Building
Barker Street
Randwick NSW 2031</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Michael Valenzuela</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Regenerative Neuroscience Group
Level 4, Building K
Brain and Mind Research Institute
94 Mallet St Camperdown
Sydney NSW 2050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>No studies have examined the potential for cognitive or cognitive-motor training to prevent falls in older people, despite good evidence of fall-related cognitive and physical improvements following both intervention types. We have developed and validated a home-based computerised training intervention that can be delivered identically, either while seated (cognitive) or while standing and undertaking balance exercises (cognitive+motor). This unique design will allow us to assess whether cognitive and cognitive+motor training can prevent falls, as well as the neural, physiological, physical and neuropsychological mechanisms behind the intervention effects. We will conduct a randomised controlled trial of 750 older people, to determine the effects of cognitive and cognitive+motor training, compared with a no-intervention control group, in preventing falls and related physical, cognitive and neurological measures in older people. We hypothesise both interventions will significantly prevent falls and fall-related measures of physical and cognitive functions. Any differential effects of the interventions will provide valuable insights into the intervention components required for efficacious fall prevention, and those required for neural, neuropsychological and physical benefits.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW Grants Management Office
Rupert Myers Building, Level 3, South Wing
University of New South Wales
NSW
2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/09/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15203</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/04/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Daina Sturnieks</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Barker St
Randwick 
NSW
2031 
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1062</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9399 1204</fax>
      <email>d.sturnieks@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Daina Sturnieks</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Barker St
Randwick 
NSW
2031 
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1062</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9399 1204</fax>
      <email>d.sturnieks@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Daina Sturnieks</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Barker St
Randwick 
NSW
2031 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1062</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9399 1204</fax>
      <email>d.sturnieks@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Daina Sturnieks</name>
      <address>Neuroscience Research Australia
Barker St
Randwick 
NSW
2031 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 9399 1062</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9399 1204</fax>
      <email>d.sturnieks@neura.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>