<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362133">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000959875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Inhibition of Fructosamine Oxidase in Diabetic Nephropathy (INFO-Renal) Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Study to assess whether treatment with GC811007 would arrest the decline in renal function and the associated progression of diabetic retinopathy, peripheral neuropathy and autonomic neuropathy in patients with Type 2 diabetes mellitus.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>INFO-RENAL</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients with type 2 diabetic nephropathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This was a randomized, double-blind, Placebo-controlled study in adult patients with diabetic nephropathy. Upon completion of screening, Enrolment and a 3-week Placebo-run-in period, patients were randomized to treatment with 1200 mg/day, GC811007 (taken as two 300-mg capsules twice daily, BID, before meals) or Placebo, administered as 2 identical 300-mg capsules taken orally twice daily (BID) before meals for 6 months. Patients underwent safety and efficacy assessments during clinic visits at Months 0, 2, 4, and 6. Telephone follow-up interviews were conducted 2 weeks after the final clinic visit.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo: The Placebo formulation was matched to the active drug in appearance and capsule weight dosage, and was supplied as microcrystalline cellulose (Vivapur type 102) in opaque Capsugel gelatin capsules.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of decline from Baseline to Month 6 in renal function as measured by glomerular filtration rate using 3 calculation methods for creatinine clearance: (i) measured serum and urine creatinine; (ii) Cockcroft-Gault equation based on actual body weight, (iii) Cockcroft-Gault equation based on ideal body weight.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Safety and efficacy assessments during clinic visits at Months 0, 2, 4, and 6 when urine collection occurred, for creatinine analysis</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in rate of progression of diabetic retinopathy and/or diabetic maculopathy over a 6 month period, as measured by non-mydriatic retinal photography</outcome>
      <timepoint>During clinic visits at Months 0, 2, 4, and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in rate of progression of peripheral neuropathy over a 6 month period, as measured by change in severity assessed by the Michigan Peripheral Neuropathy Screening Instrument</outcome>
      <timepoint>During clinic visits at Months 0, 2, 4, and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in severity of autonomic neuropathy as assessed by heart rate variation with deep breathing, upon standing, and during Valsalva manoeuver, as well as postural fall in systolic blood pressure</outcome>
      <timepoint>During clinic visits at Months 0, 2, 4, and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Men and women between 30 to 70 years of age with poor blood glucose control, retinopathy and nephropathy resulting from Type 2 diabetes mellitus.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Healthy volunteers excluded, and those with with poor blood glucose control, retinopathy and nephropathy resulting from Type 2 diabetes mellitus, but outside of the age range above</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This was a randomized, double-blind, Placebo-controlled study in adult patients with diabetic nephropathy. Upon completion of screening, Enrolment and a 3-week Placebo-run-in period, patients were randomized to treatment with 1200 mg/day GC811007 or Placebo, administered as 2 identical 300-mg capsules taken orally twice daily (BID) before meals for 6 months.</concealment>
    <sequence>A variable block randomisation schedule was used where a random number was assigned to each drug treatment pack and each pack sequentially assigned to blocks of varying sizes. Within each block, the drug treatment packs were sorted by random number and packs associated with the lower half of the random number set were assigned placebo, and those associated with the higher half were assigned active treatment. Assignment within blocks ensured that the number of active and placebo packs was equal once each block was full, to attain a balanced design in the event of early termination. The variable block size was a protection against unblinding.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/11/2001</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Protemix Corporation, Ltd.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 28, IAG House
151 Queen Street,
Auckland 1010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Protemix Corporation Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 28, IAG House
151 Queen Street,
Auckland 1010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This pilot study was designed to assess whether treatment with GC811007 would arrest the decline in renal function and the associated progression of diabetic retinopathy, peripheral neuropathy and autonomic neuropathy in patients with Type 2 diabetes mellitus. The safety and tolerability of GC811007 also were assessed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Auckland Health &amp; Disabilities Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>650 Great South Road, Penrose, Auckland 1051, New Zealand</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/12/2000</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>99/147</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/08/2000</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Garth Cooper</name>
      <address>School of Biological Sciences
University of Auckland
Privvate Bag 92 019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 (9) 373 7599 Ext 87239</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>g.cooper@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Sally Poppitt</name>
      <address>School of Biological Sciences
University of Auckland
Privvate Bag 92 019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 (9) 630 5160</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.poppitt@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>