<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362057">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000222842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An Antenatal Resilience and Optimism Workshop on Postnatal Depressive Symptoms</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Pregnant women in Indonesia, attending an Antenatal Resilience and Optimism Workshop,  to reduce postnatal depression symptoms?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1126-5428</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Resilience &amp; Optimism Workshop (ROW)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Postnatal Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Resilience and Optimism Workshop (ROW).

This intervention is a 2-day consecutive workshop, each day starts at 8.30am - 4pm with 1 hour lunch break and two 15 minute coffee breaks in the morning and afternoon. 

The workshop will be facilitated by a clinical psychologist who is the author of the ROW intervention (Josephine Ratna). Josephine is an experienced clinical psychologist who speaks English and Bahasa Indonesia. The intervention will include group disscussion, activities, role play and brain storming activities for pregnant women who are at least in their second trimester of pregnancy. Topics cover empowerment, resilience, and optimistic thinking will be developed in consultation with a clinical psychologst, Obstetrician/ Gynaecologist, a nurse and a psychiatrist, taking into account suggestions from previous studies and relevant programs, as well as specific cultural issues and myths. 

The workshop will use examples and hypothetical situations that are common but specifically challenging for pregnant women e.g. what if they deliver a child who has a developmental delay; what if their husband or close family member can not attend the birth; what to do if the child is struggling when do you intervene to get help rather than watch and wait a child that is struggling, what actions can be taken to gather extra support while the family is trying to meet the needs of a difficult child. ROW will be specifically designed for the purpose of preventing postnatal depressive symptoms, emphasising efforts to increase individual resilience in the mother and the family, and optimism based activities based on previous research studies and activity outcomes. 

Participants will receive a booklet which describes key themes (pregnancy, changes, depression, protective and risk factors, attributions - optimism vs pessimism, resilience, support systems and cultural aspects of childbirth and caring and caring for a new baby). There will be sections for critical reflection, individual and group learning activities (including possible implementations in a personal context) to complete and inspirational quotations.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard Control Group. The control participants will receive the active ROW intervention 6 weeks after the intervention group has completed their intervention. At this time the control group will be appoximately 4.5 - 7 months pregnant.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Score on Attributional Style Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, post-intervention, 6-weeks after intervention, 6 months after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Score on Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, post-intervention, at 6 weeks and 6 months after intervention completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Score on Edinburg Postnatal Depression Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Score on Connor-Davidson Resilience Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, post-intervention, 6-weeks after intervention, 6 months after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Score on Self-Report Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, post-intervention, 6-weeks after intervention, 6 months after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Score on Quality of Life Enjoyment and Satisfaction Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, post-intervention, 6-weeks after intervention, 6 months after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women at least in their second trimester of pregnancy who agree to participate fully in antenatal and postnatal activities, complete the consent form, are not in high risk pregnancy condition (evaluation made by the Obstetrician/ Gynecologist), do not indicate clinical psychopathologies (anxiety, depression and psychosis) and deliver life born babies.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>59</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pre-eclampsia, potential miscarriage due to frequent bleeding, or recurrent pregnancy loss and clinical depression/anxiety and psychosis as per latest antenatal check-up</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Pregnant women attending antenatal care at 8 primary health care clinics in Surabaya (East Java) - will be recruited. After completing the pre-tests, clinics will be randomly allocated to one of two groups. The random allocation will be performed by our statistician who will be blind to the identity (intervention or control) of the two groups.</concealment>
    <sequence>After completing the pre-tests, clinics (rather than participants) will be randomly allocated to either an intervention or a wait-list control group with the proviso that there are four clinics from each city in each group. The online randomizer at http://www.randomizer.org/form.htm will be used to accomplish this.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <state>N/A</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <state>East Java</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AusAID - using the Australian Leaderhip Awards (ALA) Study Enrichment Allowance</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>c.o. Curtin University. International Sponsored Student Unit
Curtin international, building 103
GPO Box U1987
Perth Western Australia 6845</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Josephine Ratna</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Kent St.
GPO Box U1987
Curtin University
Bentley WA 6845</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>AusAID using the Australian Leadership Award (ALA) Study Enrichment Allowance</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Curtin University 
International Sponsored Student Unit
Curtin international, building 103
GPO Box U1987
Perth Western Australia 6845</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Josephine M J Ratna</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>27 North Lake Road, Alfred Cove, Western Australia 6154</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will investigate the efficacy of a Resilience and Optimism Workshop (ROW) given to pregnant women as part of their antenatal care. It will involve Primary Health Care in East Java (Surabaya) Indonesia. Eight Primary Health Care (PHC) clinics will be randomly assigned to either an intervention or a wait-list (WL) control group conditions. Eight to twelve pregnant women from each clinic will participate, in total 64 - 96 participants. Pregnant women from clinics receiving the intervention will attend a two day workshop. For the intervention and control groups, measures of depression, anxiety, stress, attributional style, resilience and quality of life will be taken at pre-test, post-test, 6-week follow-up, and 6-month follow-up. The control group will be assessed with the same measures, but will not get the intervention until after the 6-week follow-up. It is hypothesized that, the intervention group will show significant therapeutic changes in outcomes from pre-test to post-test and these changes will be maintained at the 6-week and 6-month follow-ups. If ROW is effective it will be recommended as a regular antenatal care program in Indonesia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>/- Office of Research and Development, Curtin University, GPO Box U1987, Perth, WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/01/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR164/2011</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee - Ministry of Health Indonesia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Komisi Etik 
Badan Penelitian dan Pengembangan Kesehatan
Jl. Percetakan Negara 29
Jakarta 10560</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>KE.01.02/EC/057/2012</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Indonesia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Clare Roberts</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology 
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987, Perth, WA 6845</address>
      <phone>+61892667992</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.roberts@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Josephine M J Ratna</name>
      <address>27 North Lake Road, Alfred Cove, WA 6154</address>
      <phone>+61451997812</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ratna.josephine@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Josephine M J Ratna</name>
      <address>27 North Lake Road, Alfred Cove, WA 6154</address>
      <phone>+61451997812</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ratna.josephine@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>