<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369782">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000717459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A feasibility study to assess the safety and efficacy of JenaValve for patients with severe aortic stenosis (AS).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Feasibility Study to Assess Safety and Efficacy of the Transapical and Transfemoral JenaValve Pericardial TAVR (Transcatheter Aortic Valve Replacement) System in the Treatment of Patients with Symptomatic Severe Aortic Stenosis (AS)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Aortic Stenosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will examine the use of TAVR (Transcatheter Aortic Valve Replacement), which is a minimally invasive procedure designed to replace the aortic valve inside the heart.  The JenaValve Pericardial TAVR System will be examined in this clinical study for aortic valve replacement.  The TAVR procedure is performed by a heart surgeon and a cardiologist.  The TAVR device may be implanted transapical, which is placed through your chest wall, or transfemoral, which is placed though an artery in your groin. The choice of which which approach is used is at the clinical discretion of the study physicians..  The TAVR procedure typically takes 1-2 hours to complete.  The JenaValve TAVR device, once implanted, is designed to remain permanently in place.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Nil- single-arm study</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All-cause mortality (adjudicated)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post-index procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Event rate of VARC-2 individual safety endpoints, including:
- All-cause mortality (assessed by review of medical records)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 month, 6 months, 1 year, and 2 years post-index procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Myocardial infarction (assessed by review of medical records)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 month, 6 months, 1 year, and 2 years post-index procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Neurologic complications- all cause stroke and transient ischemic attack (TIA) (assessed by review of medical records)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 month, 6 months, 1 year, and 2 years post-index procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Bleeding complications (assessed by review of medical records)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 month, 6 months, 1 year, and 2 years post-index procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Acute kidney injury (AKIN classification) (assessed by review of medical records)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 7 days post-index procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Vascular complications (Major, minor, closure device failure) (assessed by review of medical records)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 month, 6 months, 1 year, and 2 years post-index procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Conduction disturbances and arrhythmias (assessed by review of medical records)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 month, 6 months, 1 year, and 2 years post-index procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- TAVR-related complications (assessed by review of medical records)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 month, 6 months, 1 year, and 2 years post-index procedure.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional classification assessed using the New York Heart Association (NYHA) functional class. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 month, 6 months, 1 year, and 2 years post-index procedure, as compared to baseline. 

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical outcome assessed using the 6 Minute Walk Test (6MWT). </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months, 1 year, and 2 years post-index procedure, as compared to baseline. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical outcome assessed using the Kansas City Cardiomyopathy Questionnaire (KCCQ). </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 year and 2 years post-index procedure, as compared to baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Patient with severe degenerative native aortic stenosis (AS)
2.	Patient at high risk for open surgical valve replacement
3.	Patient symptomatic according to NYHA functional class II or higher
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Congenital uni- or bicuspid aortic valve morphology
2.	Previous prosthetic aortic valve (bioprosthesis or mechanical) implant
3.	Endocarditis or other active infection
4.	Need for urgent or emergent TAVR procedure for any reason
5.	Cardiogenic shock or hemodynamic instability requiring inotropic support or ventricular assist device
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This study is a single-arm, multi-center, prospective feasibility study that is exploratory in nature.  It is anticipated that a maximum of 30 mITT (modified intention to treat) subjects will be included to initially assess the safety and feasibility of the procedure and investigational device.
Continuous outcome variables will be presented as means and standard deviations, as well as medians and ranges. For categorical outcome variables, relative frequencies will be provided. Descriptive tables will be produced for baseline characteristics.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>17/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>17/02/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Suspended</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland, Waikato</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>JenaValve Technology, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>7545 Irvine Center Drive
Suite 100
Irvine, CA 92618</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>JenaValve Technology, Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>7545 Irvine Center Drive
Suite 100
Irvine, CA 92618</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this research study is to collect information about a new treatment for severe aortic stenosis, which affects the aortic valve in the heart.  Aortic stenosis is a narrowing of the aortic valve opening, which decreases blood flow from the heart and causes symptoms such as chest pain, fainting and shortness of breath. The preferred treatment for severe aortic stenosis is aortic valve replacement surgery. A less invasive surgical approach called TAVR (also known as TAVI) is offered to those patients who are high risk for undergoing open heart surgery to replace the aortic valve.  In this study, TAVR will be performed using the JenaValve Pericardial TAVR System, which is intended to help treat severe aortic stenosis. The JenaValve replacement valve is placed inside the aortic valve by using the JenaValve delivery system.  The JenaValve replacement valve may be implanted in one of two ways: (1) transapical - where the valve is implanted through the chest wall, and (2) transfemoral  where the valve is implanted through an artery in the groin. The choice of which implant method will be used is decided by the doctor.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health, Freyberg Building, 20 Aitken Street, PO Box 5013, Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mark Webster</name>
      <address>Green Lane Cardiovascular Service
Auckland City Hospital
2 Park Road, Grafton
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 3074949</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mwebster@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Robin Clarke</name>
      <address>Interventional Cardiology Trial Coordinator
Auckland City Hospital
2 Park Road, Grafton
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+ 64 9 3074949 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robinc@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Barbara Lindsay</name>
      <address>JVT Research and Development Corp.
7545 Irvine Center Drive, Suite 100
Irvine, CA 92618 
</address>
      <phone>+ 1 (949) 396-7500</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lindsay@jenavalve.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Gita Ghadimi</name>
      <address>JenaValve Technology, Inc.
7545 Irvine Center Drive, Suite 100
Irvine, CA  92618
</address>
      <phone>+1 949 396-7513</phone>
      <fax>+1 949 396-7559</fax>
      <email>ghadimi@jenavalve.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>