<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362410">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000458831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Reflux in obstructive sleep apnea</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Mechanisms of gastroesophageal reflux in obstructive sleep apnoea</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym>None</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive sleep apnoea</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Gastroesophageal reflux</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The proposed research will investigate the underlying reason for the presence of increased gastroesophageal reflux (GOR) in individuals with obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA). 
Each participant will undergo a 24 hour pH-impedance study for assessment of reflux severity, two overnight sleep studies and a full body dual energy x-ray absorptiometry scan.  One of these nights will be conducted on continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) therapy, one will be without therapy.  The two sleep studies will be conducted on consecutive nights.  On the treatment night, CPAP will be delivered at 10cmH20 for 8 hours.  The order of these nights will be randomised.
Each participant will be enrolled in the study for approximately 2 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Four groups of participants will be studied and compared against one another: obese individuals without sleep apnoea, obese individuals with moderate/severe sleep apnoea, non-obese individuals without sleep apnea and non-obese individuals with moderate/severe sleep apnoea.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparisons will be made for presence and severity of GOR assessed by pH/impedance testing (variables assessed will include: acid contact time, number of acidic and non-acidic reflux events, longest event and number of events &gt; 5 mins). Comparisons between the obese (BMI &gt;30kg.m-2) group and non-obese (BMI &lt;30kg.m-2) groups as a whole, and between the obese and non-obese subgroups with differing OSA severities will be conducted using two-way ANOVA. Multivariate regression modelling will also be used to assess the role of OSA severity and obesity in predicting the risk of GOR.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be assessed over a 24 hour period at the beginning of the study (the 24-hour pH/impedance test is one of the first assessments to be made).
In addition, the pH/impedance parameters will be assessed over the 8 hour sleep study after both sleep studies.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LOS and oesophageal function will be assessed using a high resolution manometry catheter during water and viscous swallows.  Comparisons will be made for LOS function (baseline LOS pressure, residual LOS pressure during a swallow) and oesophageal function (peristaltic amplitude and duration and bolus transit). Comparisons between the obese group and non-obese groups as a whole, and between the obese and non-obese subgroups with differing OSA severities will be conducted using two-way ANOVA. Multivariate regression modelling will be used to determine the role of OSA severity and obesity in predicting the risk of LOS dysfunction.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be assessed over 10 swallows of water and 10 swallows of viscous solution performed during wakefulness.
These assessments will be made before both sleep studies.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparisons will be made between groups (obese and non-obese) and within these groups (OSA severity - none vs moderate/severe) for intragastric pressure (assessed using high resolution manometry catheter) and measures of body morphology (assessed by DEXA scan) including ratio of central to peripheral fat and abdominal fat mass. Analyses will include two-way ANOVA to compare variables between groups and multivariate regression modelling to determine the role of OSA severity and body fat distribution in predicting the relative risks for GOR.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intrgastric pressure will be assessed during a 5 minute period of quiet breathing prior to the 10 water and 10 viscous swallows.  This assessment will be made before both sleep studies.

Body morphology will be assessed after a 7 minute full body DEXA scan.  The DEXA scan will be assessed only once, prior to the first sleep study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We also intend to conduct post-hoc analyses to determine if the presence and severity of hiatal hernia influences the effect of CPAP on GOR and the LOS.  Presence and severity of hiatal hernia will be assessed using the high resolution manometry catheter.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Presence and severity of hiatal hernia will be assessed using the high resolution manometry catheter during the 10 water and 10 viscous swallows.
These assessments will be made before both sleep studies.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjects will undergo full laboratory polysomnography including monitoring of: electroencephalogram, electrooculogram, submental electromyogram, oxygen saturation, nasal/oral pressure, thoracic and abdominal movements and leg movements.  In addition to the polysomnography, they will simultaneously undergo oesophageal pH/impedance monitoring.  Based on these assessments, comparisons will be made between groups (obese and non-obese) and within these groups (OSA severity) for the nights on and off CPAP for GOR characteristics including number of apnoeic/hypopnoeic events, number of arousals and relationship of each arousal to reflux and respiratory events, proportion of acidic and non-acidic events, length of events, degree of proximal migration of events, manometric measures to define underlying mechanisms of each event (e.g. strain, TSLER, swallow, hypotonic LOS) and their manometric characteristics (e.g. nadir pressure, duration of relaxation). The principal analyses for these comparisons will be two-way ANOVA.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be assessed after both 8 hour sleep studies.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All groups will be 18-70 years of age of mixed gender.

Inclusion criteria for the 4 subject groups are as follows:
Group 1.
Non-obese without OSA: BMI&lt;30kg.m-2, AHI&lt;5 events per hour
Group 2. 
Non-obese with moderate/severe OSA: BMI&lt;30kg.m-2, AHI &gt;15 events per hour
Group 3. 
Obese without OSA: BMI&gt;30kg.m-2, AHI&lt;5 events per hour
Group 4.
Obese with moderate/severe OSA; BMI&gt;30kg.m-2, AHI&gt;15 events per hour</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Uncontrolled hypertension, ischaemic heart disease, type I diabetes or depression.
Previous oesophageal or gastric surgery
Gastroesophageal disorders such as lupus, coeliac disease or ulcerative colitis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Each subject will undergo two conditions - one night of no CPAP and one night of CPAP in a randomised fashion.  Therefore there is no need for a procedure for allocating treatment.</concealment>
    <sequence>The order of treatment/no treatment will be determined by simple randomisation using a coin-toss.  The allocation will not be concealed.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>35 Stirling Highway
Crawley WA 6009
Perth, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Hospital Avenue, Nedlands WA 6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research will define the mechanisms underlying the presence of gastroesophageal reflux (GOR) in individuals with obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA). Both are common conditions with OSA affecting 1 in 20 individuals and GOR affecting approximately 1 in 12 individuals in the community. Continuous positive airways pressure (CPAP), the most common and effective treatment for OSA has also been found to treat GOR.

GOR symptoms are more common in OSA than the general population (14% vs 5%) and increase with increasing OSA severity. Nighttime GOR is a particular worry in individuals with OSA with 1 in 3 OSA patients reporting overnight symptoms. Despite this increased risk for GOR, we do not know the underlying reason for the link between OSA and GOR.

Background
GOR has significant negative health effects in individuals with OSA including painful symptoms and an increase in cancer risk. Identification of the reasons for the increased incidence of reflux in OSA may assist in improving prevention and/or treatment of GOR in individuals with OSA as well as increasing quality of life in these patients.
Aims
The overall aim of the proposed research is to determine the underlying reason for the presence of
gastroesophageal reflux (GOR) in individuals with obstructive sleep apnoea (OSA), including the role of obesity.
Methods
80 individuals will be recruited: 40 obese (20 with no OSA and 20 with moderate-severe OSA); and 40 non-obese (20 with no OSA and 20 with moderate-severe OSA). Each participant will undergo a 24 hour pH-impedance study for assessment of reflux severity, two overnight sleep studies including monitoring of oesophageal pH/impedance and oesophageal and lower oesophageal sphincter pressures, and a DXA scan to assess obesity and fat distribution.  The two sleep studies on CPAP therapy and one sleep study off CPAP therapy in a randomised, cross-over fashion.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Group Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>2nd Floor A Block (Mailbox 26)
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Ave
Nedlands, WA
6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2012-058</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/03/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kelly Shepherd</name>
      <address>Department of Pulmonary Physiology and Sleep Medicine
Internal Mailbox 201
Queen Elizabeth II Medical Centre
Hospital Ave
Nedlands
Western Australia 
6009</address>
      <phone>+61 (08)9346 3056</phone>
      <fax>+61 (08)9346 2034</fax>
      <email>Kelly.Shepherd@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Kelly Shepherd</name>
      <address>Department of Pulmonary Physiology and Sleep Medicine
Internal Mailbox 201
Queen Elizabeth II Medical Centre
Hospital Ave
Nedlands
Western Australia 
6009</address>
      <phone>+61 (08)9346 3056</phone>
      <fax>+61 (08)9346 2034</fax>
      <email>Kelly.Shepherd@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>