<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370954">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000847415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>N-acetyl cysteine (NAC) augmentation in Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder (OCD): A 24-week, randomized, double blind placebo controlled trial </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>N-acetyl cysteine (NAC) augmentation in Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder (OCD): A 24-week, randomized, double blind placebo controlled trial </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>NAC-OCD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The amino acid N-acetyl cysteine (500mg capsules, taken orally) versus placebo, used adjunctive to stable medication (minimum 8-weeks at consistent dosages) for the individuals OCD for 20 weeks (and an additional 4-week placebo run-out from week-20 to week-24 for all participants). 

Randomised participants will take 2 capsules, twice per day (equating to 2,000mg NAC or placebo per day) for the first 8-weeks of the study. In cases of non-response (&lt;35% reduction in baseline score of primary outcome measure: Y-BOCS), participants will increase their dose by an additional 1,000mg per day from week-8 and remain on this dose for the subsequent 4-weeks. The maximum dose permitted in this study will be 4,000mg (4 capsules twice daily), however, participants will only be permitted to increase their dose by 1,000mg at a time and must remain on this dose for a minimum of 4-weeks before a further titration can occur. Titration will occur at week-8, week-12, week-16 and week-20 in cases of non response. 

All participants will receive placebo (single-blinded, participants remain blinded) for the final 4-weeks of the study (week-20 to week-24). They will continue on the same amount of capsules (however, will be placebo) from the previous 4-weeks OR  in cases of non-response (determined at week-20 after completing Y-BOCS), will increase their dose by an additional 1,000mg (maximum 4,000mg IP per day, 4 capsules bid).

Participants will be asked to return all remaining capsules in their containers at each study follow-up visit. Remaining capsules will be counted by a 3rd party to determine participant compliance. </interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo capsules containing microcellulose</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Yale-Brown Obsessive-Compulsive Scale (Y-BOCS), clinician administrated </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week-4, Week-8, Week-12, Week-16, Week-20, Week-24</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Structured Interview Guide for the Hamilton Depression Rating Scale (HAM-D; 17-item), clinician administrated </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week-4, Week-8, Week-12, Week-16, Week-20, Week-24 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Obsessional Belief Questionnaire-44 item (OBQ-44), self-reported</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week-8, Week-20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brown Assessment of Beliefs Scale (BABS), clinician administrated </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week-4, Week-8, Week-12, Week-16, Week-20, Week-24 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dimensional Y-BOCS, clinician administrated</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week-8, Week-20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI), self-reported</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week-4, Week-8, Week-12, Week-16, Week-20, Week-24 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sheehan Disability Scale (SDS), self-reported</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week-4, Week-8, Week-12, Week-16, Week-20, Week-24 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>World Health Organisation Quality of Life Brief (WHOQOL-bref), self-reported</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week-4, Week-8, Week-12, Week-16, Week-20, Week-24 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Global Impression Scale (CGI), clinician administrated </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week-4, Week-8, Week-12, Week-16, Week-20, Week-24 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant Global Impression scale (PGI), self-reported</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week-4, Week-8, Week-12, Week-16, Week-20, Week-24 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Barratt Impulsivity Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline only, used as a predictor of response/non-response</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary Questionnaire for Epidemiological Studies version 3.2</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline only</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Systematic Assessment for Treatment Emergent Events (SAFTEE), self reported. 

NAC may induce gastrointestinal side effects including mild abdominal pain or discomfort, heartburn, diarrhea, flatulence, nausea and cramps. Headaches and skin rashes have also been reported in previous clinical studies. However, specific to psychiatric research studies, only a small minority of participants have withdrawn due to side effects of NAC including a skin rash (n = 1), aggression (n = 1), severe heartburn (n = 1), neutropenia with 6 grams of NAC which resolved when dose reduced to 2.4g, (n = 1) and sensorineural deafness (n = 1) (Slattery et al., 2015). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Week-4, Week-8, Week-12, Week-16, Week-20, Week-24</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OCD Family Functioning Scale, two sections. First section completed by participant. Second component completed by a consenting informant (family member)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Week-8, Week-20</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Primary diagnosis of OCD as per the Structured Interview Guide for the DSM-5 (SCID)
Adults between the age of 18-70 who have the desire and capacity to consent to the study and follow its procedures
Minimum score of 16 on the Y-BOCS at time of entry into the study, but no greater than 31
Currently taking medication for their OCD which has been stable for the past 8-weeks 
Stable psychological treatment (if employing), minimum eight weeks (an 8-week wash-out period will be required if participants have just completed an intensive in-patient CBT program for their OCD)

 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Bipolar disorder
*Psychotic disorders
*Primary diagnosis of Obsessive-compulsive spectrum disorders including hoarding, body dysmorphic disorder, trichotillomania (secondary diagnosis permitted)
*Severe depression (as defined by HAM-D score equal to or greater than 24
*Alcohol/substance abuse
*Y-BOCS score equal to or greater than 32 
*Treatment resistant OCD (3 or more trials of first line medications for their OCD at therapeutic doses for minimum of 12-weeks each, at least one augmentation strategy, for example, anti psychotic medication as well as exposure response prevention therapy minimum 20 hours)
*Medications with known or suspected negative interactions with NAC (activated charcoal, nitro glycerine, insulin replacement therapies, Aralen, anti-coagulant medications excluding aspirin and NSAIDS)  
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>Randomisation of participants to treatment groups (for the first 20-weeks of the study) will be determined by computerised random allocation. Recruited eligible participants will be assigned a participant number and provided capsules according to a corresponding investigational product (IP) number. Participant numbers are provided sequentially and the randomisation code is set up in a 2 by 2 block design, with no group identifying them (to avoid potentially unblinding researcher’s if participants were randomised to medication bottles labelled A or B).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants will be randomised into either NAC or placebo for the first 20-weeks of the study in a double  blind manner. For the last 4-weeks of the study, all participants will receive placebo in a single blinded manner (researchers unblinded). The purpose of including a 4-week, placebo-run out is to asses any withdraw effects and/or sustained response of the NAC.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A sample size of 200 participants (100 participants in each arm) are to be recruited and intention-to-treat principles will be applied to all data. A large sample of 200 participants is powered to detect a potential small to moderate effect size (f = 0.15) difference between NAC and placebo beyond treatment as usual, approximating a clinically significant 3 point reduction on the Y-BOCS (using all post-baseline data via intention-to-treat analysis). Based on an ANOVA model over seven time-points, a two tailed analysis with alpha = 0.05, beta = 0.80, and a critical F of 3.78; 200 participants (not including drop-outs) are required to detect a small to moderate effect size difference in Y-BOCS scale score between treatment and placebo.       

The primary efficacy analysis will assess mean treatment group differences for the primary outcome measure (Y-BOCS) using a mixed-effects model, repeated measures approach (MMRM). Results from the analysis of dichotomous data (e.g. demographics data) will be presented as proportions with 95% confidence interval, and Fishers Exact p-value where appropriate. Analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) will also be used to compare differences between treatment means in changes from baseline to week 20 last observation carried forward (LOCF) endpoint. The ANCOVA model will assess confounding covariates including intervention type (medication or psychological care), as well as age, gender, weight, physical activity levels, smoking and alcohol consumption. 

Non-parametric statistics will be used when assumptions for parametric methods are violated. Effect sizes will be calculated using Cohens d. All tests of treatment effects will be conducted using a two-tailed alpha level of 0.05 and 95% confidence intervals. Data will be analysed via SPSS 23.0. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/12/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Melbourne Clinic - Richmond</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>3121 - Richmond</postcode>
    <postcode>4001 - Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>2560 - Campbelltown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Parkville, 
Melbourne VIC
Australia, 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The National Heath and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>St Lucia 
QLD 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Western Sydney University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>192 Narellan Rd, 
Campbelltown 
NSW 2560</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study seeks to elucidate the benefits of NAC augmentation (2-4 grams/day) compared to placebo in the treatment of OCD, in a 20-week, multi-centre, randomized, double-blind, placebo controlled trial, with an additional 4-week, single blinded placebo run-out. The purpose of including a 4-week, placebo-run out is to asses any withdraw effects and/or sustained response of the NAC.  It is hypothesized that NAC will be superior over placebo for improving OCD symptoms as measured by a reduction in Y-BOCS scores from baseline against each subsequent time point (W4, W8, W12, W16, W20 and W24). Additional benefits are anticipated for relieving anxiety as well as improving mood, functioning and overall quality of life. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>Currently under construction</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Melbourne Clinic Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>2 Salisbury St, 
Richmond
Melbourne
VIC     3121</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Sydney University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Penrith Campus
Great Western Highway
Werrington 
NSW 2747
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00380</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UQ Medical Research Ethics Committee (MREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Queensland (UQ)
Level 3, Brian Wilson Chancellery
The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016001720</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jerome Sarris</name>
      <address>The Melbourne Clinic Professorial Unit
2 Salisbury St, 
Richmond 
Melbourne VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94874748 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jsarris@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Georgina Oliver</name>
      <address>The Melbourne Clinic Professorial Unit
2 Salisbury St, 
Richmond 
Melbourne VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94874748 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>georgina.oliver@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Georgina Oliver</name>
      <address>The Melbourne Clinic Professorial Unit
2 Salisbury St, 
Richmond 
Melbourne VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94874748 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>georgina.oliver@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Georgina Oliver</name>
      <address>The Melbourne Clinic Professorial Unit
2 Salisbury St, 
Richmond 
Melbourne VIC 3121</address>
      <phone>+61 3 94874659 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>georgina.oliver@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>