<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362821">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000898853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Increasing adherence to Obstructive Sleep Apnea treatment with a coaching intervention.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Increasing adherence to Obstructive Sleep Apnea treatment with a coaching intervention.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1133-2492</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Low self-efficacy in patients with Obstructive Sleep Apnea (OSA)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomised to either the current Treatment As Usual group (TAU) or a Coaching Group (C).  Both TAU and C groups will undergo a psycho-education and mask fitting session (1.5 - 2 hours), a CPAP Titration study night, a 1 hour CPAP set-up session, and 4 CPAP data usage download sessions (each 1 hour in length).  In addition, the C group will also receive four, one hour one-to-one coaching sessions  three face-to-face and one by phone. 

The psycho-education  is a group session of a standardised slide presentation containing information about normal sleep, daytime and night-time health consequences of untreated OSA , and the effectiveness of CPAP treatment. Side-effects encountered when using CPAP will be highlighted and discussed. All participants will have a trial of CPAP at a pressure of 4cm H20 in a supine position and will be encouraged to handle the equipment. Participants will also be encouraged to seek help and support for any mechanical difficulties throughout the study period.

During the CPAP titration night, subjects will undergo an in-laboratory manual titration of their CPAP pressure with polysomnography (PSG). CPAP-therapy pressure will be titrated to treat apnea, hypopnea, and flow limitation, with a therapy target of AHI&lt;5 per hour of sleep. A prescription for an appropriate CPAP pressure and well sealing mask will be provided for participants. 

The coaching sessions  involve: Coaching Session 1 (immediately after the psycho-education and mask fitting session):  to develop a collaborative relationship between coach and participant, help the participant develop personally meaningful coaching goals and explore how CPAP treatment can be incorporated into their lifestyle. Coaching Session 2 (immediately after the CPAP set-up session): This session will review and evaluate actions and progress to date. Participant generated goals will be set and action plans developed. The key focus will be on identifying areas of success thus far and coaching the participant to capitalise on these, although barriers to change will also be explored where relevant. Coaching Sessions 3 &amp; 4:  to help the participant prepare for longer-term use of the CPAP equipment, exploring ways to consolidate change and building self-efficacy, confidence and motivation levels. Session 3 will be between the 1st and 2nd download sessions and Session 4 will be immediately after the 3rd download session.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment as Usual - psycho-education session and mask fitting</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence as measured by CPAP download (mean hours per night)
All participants will be provided with a CPAP device (provided by Air Liquide) with data-storage which allows for usage data to be directly downloaded from the machine or via a memory key. The data card/key records run time while the mask is on the patient's face and includes information about air leaks and apneas/hypopneas (complete or partial airway closures).  The returned data will be downloaded by a CPAP therapist from Air Liquide and automatically analyzed using software provided by the device manufacturers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After the following number of weeks of CPAP usage: 2 weeks, 5 weeks, 8 weeks, 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sleepiness and sleep related quality of life.  Measured by: Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS)
Functional Outcomes Sleep Questionnaire (FOSQ)
Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)]</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood and Wellbeing.  Measured by: 
Depression, Anxiety and Stress Scale 21 items (DASS-21)
Newark Cognitive Hardness Scale
Multidimensional Quality of Life Inventory</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 3 months, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy &amp; related Variables.  Measured by: 
Social Cognitive Theory Questionnaire 
SEMSA
Newark Cognitive Hardness Scale (resilience)
Solution-focussed thinking inventory</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 1 week, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Any patient (over 18 years) with untreated OSA and a low self-efficacy score (4 or lower)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous use of CPAP
Individuals not fluent in written and oral English</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will have undergone a Sleep Study and diagnosed with Obstructive Sleep Apnea.  At the follow-up visit with their Sleep physician they will be asked to complete a Self-efficacy questionnaire.  Any patient with a self-efficacy score of 4 or less will be contacted for participation in this study.  Once recruited participants will be randomised to a 1:1 ratio (treatment as usual or health coaching). The randomisation sequence will be prepared by a party independent of the trial, with randomly permuted block sizes. Allocation concealment will be ensured by use of sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence will be prepared by a party independent of the trial, with randomly permuted block sizes.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>7/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>55</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>21/12/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2037 - Glebe</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Missenden Road</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Air Liquide Healthcare</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Unit 5, 476 Gardeners Road, Alexandria, NSW, 2015
(Locked Bag 1008, Rosebery NSW, 1445)</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Air Liquide Healthcare</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 5, 476 Gardeners Road, Alexandria, NSW, 2015
(Locked Bag 1008, Rosebery NSW, 1445)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to (1) assess the effectiveness of a coaching intervention (C) in increasing adherence to CPAP compared with an enhanced education or treatment as usual (TAU) intervention; (2) to identify individuals with low self-efficacy scores who are at risk of stopping treatment and (3) to examine the role of mood, quality of life and well-being in the treatment response. The hypothesis is that the C intervention will increase uptake and adherence to CPAP and will improve low baseline self-efficacy scores as individuals feel they can perceive themselves using CPAP effectively. By using CPAP on a nightly basis for most of the night, mood and well-being, sleepiness and sleep related quality of life and self-efficacy will also be improved. A total of 60 individuals diagnosed with OSA will be recruited into the study on the basis of being naive to CPAP treatment and having low self-efficacy scores (&lt;4). Participants will be randomised to either the current treatment as usual group (TAU) which consists of psycho-education and mask fitting (1.5 - 2 hours) before the CPAP titration night or a coaching group (C). The C group will undergo the psycho-education and mask fitting but will also undertake 4 individual coaching sessions at baseline (3 face-to-face session and 1 by telephone).  All participants will be asked attend 4 CPAP data usage download sessions and to complete questionnaires at baseline, 1 week after starting CPAP, 1 month after starting CPAP, 12 weeks after starting CPAP and 3 months after study end.  All participants will receive a CPAP machine and tubing free of charge for the duration of the study.  Past CPAP research has found that self-efficacy predicts CPAP adherence, and as SF/CBC has been found to enhance self-efficacy and goal attainment and adherence, thus advancing knowledge and practice in CPAP and contributing to the broader emerging area of health coaching. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Research Development Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/RPAH/442</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/08/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Associate Professor Delwyn Bartlett</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
431 Glebe Point Road
Glebe
NSW
2037</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0460</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 9114 0014</fax>
      <email>delwyn.bartlett@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Associate Professor Delwyn Bartlett</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
431 Glebe Point Road
Glebe
NSW
2037</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0460</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 9114 0014</fax>
      <email>delwyn.bartlett@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Hannah Openshaw</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
431 Glebe Point Road
Glebe
NSW
2037</address>
      <phone>+61 2 91140499</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 9114 0014</fax>
      <email>hannah.openshaw@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Delwyn Bartlett</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research 431 Glebe Point Road Glebe NSW 2037</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0460</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 9114 0014</fax>
      <email>delwyn.bartlett@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>