<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81560">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/08/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/09/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000413527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Treatment Evaluation of Alcohol and Mood</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A double blind placebo controlled trial of citalopram for the treatment of coexisting alcohol dependence and major depressive syndrome for patients receiving naltrexone and clinical casemanagement: impact on drinking and mood symptomotology</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TEAM</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alcoholism</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Investigate the effectiveness of 12 weeks treatment of oral citalopram (20mg daily for week one, 40mg daily during weeks 2-12, with the option to increase to 60mg daily at week six) in a group of patients being treated over the same period of time with naltrexone (25mg daily for week one, 50mg daily during weeks 2-12, with the option to increase to 100mg at week six). All patients will attend clinical case management appointments at weeks 1, 2, and 3 with appointments then every three weeks until week 24.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (equivalent dosage protocol)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure for alcohol use will be the percent days abstinent</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured every three weeks during the trial, with primary outcome measures at pharmacotherapy termination, and then 12 weeks and 12 months post-pharmacotherapy.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure for depressive symptoms will be scores on the Montgomery and Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured every three weeks during the trial, with primary outcome measures at pharmacotherapy termination, and then 12 weeks and 12 months post-pharmacotherapy.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome drinking measures will be based on sessional drinking data and will include mean drinks per drinking day and percentage of heavy drinking days during the follow-up period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be measured every three weeks during the trial, with primary ouctome measures at pharmacotherapy termination, and then 12 weeks and 12 months post-pharmacotherapy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary depression outcome measures will be based on MADRS scores and Symptoms Checklist-90 (SCL-90) data, and will include catergorisation of responders and non-responders using a criterion of a MADRS score of 10 or less.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be measured every three weeks during the trial, with primary ouctome measures at pharmacotherapy termination, and then 12 weeks and 12 months post-pharmacotherapy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Currently meets the DSM-IV (APA 1994) criteria for alcohol dependence (i.e. the presence of at least 3/7 DSM-IV criteria for alcohol dependence in the month prior to presentation; -currently meets the the DSM-IV criteria for major depression (i.e. the presence of at least 5/9 DSM-IV criteria for major depression in month prior to presentation and has no history of manic episodes);-has a MADRS score of 20 plus at presentation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>17</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any history of daily or nearly daily intravenous drug use for more than 2 weeks, or use of any opioid drugs in the previous 4 weeks; -a history of psychosis of any sort;-a clear history of mania or hypomania based on the DSM-IV criteria;-signifcant current risk of suicide or homicide;-severe psychiatric symptoms requiring hospitalisation;-evidence of any significant cerebral, renal, thyroid or cardiac disease;-taken disulfiram, calcium carbimide, naltrexone, or antidepressant medication during the past 4 weeks;-a history of alcoholic liver disease;-if premenopausal female: pregnancy, nursing or refusing to use a reliable method of birth control;-in prison or on home detention at any time during the past 4 weeks.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment by central randomisation (by phone). All participants are assigned a unique research number.  An administrator will be responsible for applying a random list to the unique research number and then randomising patients in a double-blind fashion to receive 12 weeks of citalopram or placebo in addition to naltrexone.</concealment>
    <sequence>Stratified allocation by gender and primary versus secondary depression status, in blocks.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Patients, research clinicians, senior medical officers, and investigators will all be blinded to treatment allocation. (Note: research clinicians are responsible for recruitment, assessment, casemanagement and followup).</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>220</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Doug Sellman</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Karen de Zwart</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The combination of alcohol dependence and depression is very common in people presenting to alcohol and drug services. Pharmacotherapy offers a significant step forward in treatment.  Effective antidepressant medications have been available for a number of decades, but medications which assist with relapse prevention in alcohol dependence (antidipsotropics), other than the long-established disulfiram, have only been developed more recently.  There have been no published randomised controlled trials investigating the combination of these medications in people with both problems.  This study will investigate the effectiveness of 12 weeks treatment of citalopram (an antidepressant) compared with placebo in a group of patients presenting to one of five alcohol and drug treatment clinics in New Zealand, who are all being treated over the same time period with naltrexone (an antidipsotropic) and clinical case management. They will all have both alcohol dependence and major depression. All participants will receive standard clinical case management, which will cover the initial 12 weeks of combined pharmacotherapy, followed by a further 12 weeks of active monitoring and support.  This study will make an important contribution to evaluating the place of antidepressants in clinical practice for patients with co-occurring alcohol dependence and depression.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northland District Health Board (Community Alcohol and Drug Service - Whangarei);</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/04/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MEC/05/12/170</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Waitemata District Health Board (Community Alcohol and Drug Service - Auckland);</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/04/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MEC/05/12/170</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Waikato District Health Board (Community Alcohol and Drug Service - Hamilton);</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/04/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MEC/05/12/170</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Canterbury District Health Board (Community Alcohol and Drug Service - Christchurch);</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/04/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MEC/05/12/170</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Otago District Health Board (Community Alcohol and Drug Service - Dunedin).</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/04/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MEC/05/12/170</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Doug Sellman</name>
      <address>TEAM Principal Investigator
National Addiction Centre
Department of Psychological Medicine
Christchurch School of Medicine &amp; Health Sciences
University of Otago
4 Oxford Terrace
PO Box 4345
Christchurch
http://www.addiction.org.nz</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3640480</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 3641225</fax>
      <email>doug.sellman@chmeds.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Karen de Zwart</name>
      <address>TEAM Study Co-Ordinator
National Addiction Centre
Department of Psychological Medicine
Christchurch School of Medicine &amp; Health Sciences
University of Otago
4 Oxford Terrace
PO Box 4345
Christchurch
http://www.addiction.org.nz</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3640480</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 3641225</fax>
      <email>karen.dezwart@chmeds.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>