<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82419">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/12/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/12/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000643471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to evaluate the effectiveness of exercise in the treatment of cervical dystonia.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized controlled trial to determine the effectiveness of a programme of active and passive exercies in the treatment of idiopathic cervical dystonia.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CD_EXS</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Idiopathic Cervical Dystonia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Active exercise group. This group will attend  8 treatment sessions (of approximately 30 minutes duration) over 12 weeks with a physiotherapist.  During these sessions participants will perform initially some passive exercises, and then mostly active exercises including cervical spine retraction, flexion, rotation and lateral flexion. Participants will be trained to perform these exercises in a variety of positions for example in lying, sitting, standing and walking. Relaxation will also be taught to participants, and advice will be given on managing their dystonic neck movements.  Participants will continue these exercises at home, and will record their practice in a diary.</interventions>
    <comparator>Passive exercise group.  This group will attend  8 treatment sessions (of approximately 30 minutes duration) over 12 weeks with a physiotherapist.  During these sessions participants will perform relaxation only.  Participants will continue this relaxation at home, and will record their practice in a diary.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Toronto Western Spasmodic Torticollis Rating Scale (TWSTRS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at 6, 12 and 16 weeks after commencement of treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cervical Dystonia Questionnaire (CDQ-24)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at 6, 12 and 16 weeks after commencement of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Beck depression inventory</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at 6, 12 and 16 weeks after commencement of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cervical spine active range of motion in the directions of flexion, extension, left and right rotation and lateral flexion, and suboccipital flexion and extension.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, at 6, 12 and 16 weeks after commencement of treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of cervical dystonia for at least 6 months, committment to maintain any other medications for cervical dystonia at the same dose for the duration of the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any concurrent severe cervical spine condition (eg. severe arthritis).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation will be done by someone not involved in recruitment or assessment and will occur offsite.  Therefore, recruitment staff will be unable to predict any participant's group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer will be used to generate randomisation tables. Block randomisation will be used to allocate participants to treatment groups.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/10/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2145</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Westmead Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hawkesbury Rd, Westmead, NSW, 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NSW Physiotherapy Registration Board</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Foveaux St Haymarket, NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Faculty of Health Sciences
PO Box 170, Lidcombe, NSW, 1825</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will assess the effects of an active and passive exercise programme for participants with idiopathic cervical dystonia.  Participants will be randomly allocated into either the active or passive exercise group, and will receive 8 treatment sessions with a physiotherapist over 12 weeks. Participants in the active exercise group will also receive advice on controlling their dystonia. The primary outcome measure is the Toronto Western Spasmodic Torticollis Rating Scale (TWSTRS) which includes assessment of active neck movements, neck control, pain and disability.  Secondary outcome measures include active range of motion of all neck movements, quality of life and depression questionnaires.  All measures will be conducted prior to commencement of treatment, half way through treatment, at the end of treatment and 1 month after the completion of treatment. The study aims to determine if active exercises are more beneficial in improving neck control, reducing pain, range of movement, quality of life, and than passive exercises. Participants will be given a home exercise programme to be continued throughout the study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney West Area Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Westmead Hospital, Hawkesbury Rd, Westmead, NSW, 2145.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/11/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC2005/11/4.11(2233)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2005</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Human Reseach Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Sydney, NSW, 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/03/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>8991</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/02/2006</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Colleen Canning</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy Faculty of health Sciences, The University of Sydney, PO Box 170, Lidcombe, 1825</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93519263</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.canning@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Melani Boyce</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department Westmead Hospital Hawkesbury Rd, Westmead, NSW, 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 6500</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>robbo_mel@bigpond.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Melani Boyce</name>
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>