<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364129">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000502730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing Internet based cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) versus a cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) self help book versus a meditation self help book versus a waitlist control condition for adults with depression on severity of symptoms and depression.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial comparing an Internet based Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT) treatment versus a Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT) self help book versus a meditation self help book versus a waitlist control condition for Adults with Depression on severity of symptoms of depression.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Major depressive disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of four groups: 1) Treatment with clinician-assisted Internet based Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (iCBT) for depression, 2) CBT self help book for depression, 3) Meditation self help book, or 4) Waitlist control (treatment as usual). All participants will meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 4th Edition (DSM-IV) criteria for Major depressive disorder. 

All group 1 participants will separately complete 6 lessons of Internet based treatment about the management of symptoms of depression. One lesson will be completed every 7 to 14 days (it will become available after the preceding lesson has been completed, with a minimum of 7 days between lessons and a maximum of 14 days). Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to complete. Group 1 participants will have access to summaries of each lesson, homework exercises, extra resources, weekly reminder emails, and one-on-one contact with the Clinician (Clinical Psychologist) by telephone or email in the first 2 weeks, then as required. Weve found that people who get the most out of our programs spend about 3-4 hours a week completing the homework tasks and applying the new skills theyre learning on a daily basis. The treatment materials are based on cognitive behavioural techniques. 

The CBT self help book group (Group 2) will have 12 chapters to read over the 12 week period. This leading Australian book designed to help people with depression and will be given free to the people in this group. They will be asked to work through each of the 12 chapters over the given time. The book is self-guiding in describing specialised ways of looking at your thoughts and what you do when youre feeling low. The 12 chapters are arranged in an organised manner beginning with Understanding Depression and working through multiple topics including Our Thinking Habits and Looking After Your Needs. We recommend approximately 1 hour per week reading the chapters (total approximately 12 hours). There are various activities for participants to complete throughout the book, varying from Chapter to Chapter. We recommend participants spend 3-4 hours a week completing the homework tasks and applying the new skills theyre learning on a daily basis. 

The Meditation self help book group (Group 3) will have 7 sections (including 13 chapters) to read over the 12 week period. This leading Australian book designed to help people improve their mental health will be given free to the people in this group. They will be asked to work through each of the 13 chapters over the given time. The book is self-guiding in describing an approach to meditation called mental silence. The chapters are arranged in an organised manner, working through multiple topics including How to Meditate: How to begin and Stress  the noise in the mind. We recommend approximately 1 hour per week reading the chapters (total approximately 12 hours). There are various activities for participants to complete throughout the book, varying from chapter to chapter. We recommend participants spend 3-4 hours a week applying the new skills theyre learning on a daily basis. 

The duration of the program is 12 weeks, but participants will be contacted 3 months post program and asked to complete follow-up questionnaires. Study questionnaires will be administered at application, pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, at 3 months post-treatment, and the K10 pre-each lesson for those in group 1 (iCBT group). These will take about 20 minutes to complete. 

Strategies used to improved adherence to intervention protocols and procedures for monitoring adherence include: Group 1 - receive automated email reminders, monitor downloading of homework, collect data on how long participants spent reading lessons and practising skills;  Groups 2, 3 receive mid term email reminders, collect data on how long participants spent reading the books and practising new skills.</interventions>
    <comparator>Waitlist control group (receiving treatment as usual). These participants remain on the waitlist until the treatment groups have completed their treatment (12 weeks). At that time (12 weeks) the waitlist group will be offered the choice of whichever treatment they would like after being advised which mode appears to be better. The person will be given free access to either the CBT book, the meditation book, or the computer course.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms and severity of depression is measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at application, pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress is measured by the Kessler-10 (K-10).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment. Also administered pre each lesson for group 1 (iCBT).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generalised Anxiety Disorder is measured by the Generalized Anxiety Disorder - 7 Item (GAD-7) questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rumination is measured with the RTQ: The Repetitive Thinking Questionnaire - 10 items</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rumination is also measured by the Beliefs about Thinking Scale 18 item </outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Distress Tolerance is measure by the DTS - Distress Tolerance Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Service use and days out of role are measure by the SUDOR questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3 months post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Credibility/Expectancy Questionnaire (CEQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment and post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of the American Psychiatric Association-4th Edition (DSM-IV) criteria for Major Depressive Disorder, Internet access + printer access, Australian citizen.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current substance abuse/dependence, Psychotic mental illness (Bipolar or Schizophrenia), change of psychological treatment in last month, change in medications during last 1 month, use of Benzodiazepines, Suicidal.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The sealed opaque envelope (described in the next section) will be taken at the beginning of the phone call and opened after the informed consent is received and after the patient meets criteria on the MINI diagnostic interview completed by the research staff.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomization to four groups will be generated by www.random.org and each choice will be placed in a sealed opaque envelope by staff not involved in the research study. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All analyses will be undertaken using mixed-model repeated measures (MMRM) ANOVA with measurement occasion as a within-groups factor and intervention as a between-groups factor. Relationships between observations at different occasions will be modelled with an unstructured covariance matrix. For each experimental group, planned contrasts will be used to compare changes from baseline to post-test and 3 month follow-up. At each measurement occasion, participants will be asked whether they are currently undertaking any adjunctive treatment for their depression, and this variable will be included as a covariate in the regression models. 
How number of participants needed to achieve study objectives was determined: 100 subjects in each cell had an 80% chance or showing a significance p&lt; 0.5 if the difference between the iCBT and the books was greater than 0.4 SD or the difference between the books and waitlist control (treatment as usual) was greater than 0.4 SD.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/05/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>26/02/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>400</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>270</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Private Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many people with depression do not access treatment. Internet-based therapies are proven in efficacy and effectiveness. Bibliotherapy may provide an easier way to deliver self-guided treatment, but efficacy is rarely established. A trial comparing internet CBT, CBT via a self help book, and meditation via a self help book has not been performed to our knowledge. This research will allow the community to make a more informed choice about what form of readily available treatment to choose from for depression. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.virtualclinic.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincent's Hospital HREC
390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/SVH/29</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney 390 Victoria St Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1400</phone>
      <fax>+612 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney 390 Victoria St Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1400</phone>
      <fax>+612 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney 390 Victoria St Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1400</phone>
      <fax>+612 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>gavina@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jessica Smith</name>
      <address>St Vincent's Hospital, Sydney 390 Victoria St Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1400</phone>
      <fax>+612 8382 1401</fax>
      <email>jessica.smith@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>