<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81874">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/02/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/03/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000155493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Is Dornase alfa (Pulmozyme ) effective if administered at night, in relation to airways clearance techniques? A multi centre, crossover, randomised controlled trial for people with cystic fibrosis.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is Dornase alfa (Pulmozyme ) effective if administered at night, in relation to airways clearance techniques? A multi centre, crossover, randomised controlled trial for people with cystic fibrosis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cystic Fibrosis (CF)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cystic fibrosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Following randomisation to determine morning or evening Dornase alfa (rhDNase, [Pulmozyme]) administration as commencement intervention, paediatric and adult CF outpatients were studied over a six week period: 14 day regimes of morning or evening rhDNase administration, with 14 days washout between the two regimes. These regimes resulted in alteration of the interval time between rhDNase nebulisation and chest physiotherapy. The subjects usual routine for chest physiotherapy and exercise were unaltered. Outcomes were measured at start and end of each regime when participants attended four study visits (each approximately 30-60 minutes duration).  The subjects were all current users of nebulised rhDNase (2.5mg unit dose ampoule nebulised once daily via Pari LC+ nebuliser; duration approximately 10 minutes); the study protocol required alteration of the time of day or night at which rhDNase was administered to alter the in-situ dwell time of rhDNase in relation to chest physiotherapy. 
Usual timing of rhDNase administration in relation to chest physiotherapy is highly variable, with "short" intervals in some users (eg 15 minutes prior to physiotherapy) and others having a "long" interval (eg 8-10 hours if rhDNase is taken at night). Patients acted as their own control, using their "usual" timing during the washout period of 14 days, and data was analysed with consideration of "usual" in-situ dwell time of rhDNase compared to longer or shorter intervals caused by the study protocol.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spirometry: Forced Expiratory Volume in one second (FEV1).  The washout period was day 15 to 28 in all participants, during which they returned to their "usual" timing of rhDNase nebulisation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 14 days, 28 days, and 42 days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spirometry: Forced Vital Capacity (FVC). The washout period was day 15 to 28 in all participants, during which they returned to their "usual" timing of rhDNase nebulisation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 14 days, 28 days, and 42 days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spirometry: Forced expiratory Flow Rate between 25 and 75% of FVC (FEF25-75%). The washout period was day 15 to 28 in all participants, during which they returned to their "usual" timing of rhDNase nebulisation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 14 days, 28 days, and 42 days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spirometry: Sputum weight (gm) collected from the preceding day's chest physiotherapy session/s. The washout period was day 15 to 28 in all participants, during which they returned to their "usual" timing of rhDNase nebulisation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 14 days, 28 days, and 42 days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spirometry: CF-specific quality of life via cystic fibrosis questionnaire-revised (CFQ-R).  The washout period was day 15 to 28 in all participants, during which they returned to their "usual" timing of rhDNase nebulisation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 14 days, 28 days, and 42 days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Additional outcomes were subjective cough score via Verbal Category Descriptive Score(VCD) and medication adherence (returned empty rhDNase nebules).</outcome>
      <timepoint>All outcomes were measured at baseline, 14 days, 28 days, and 42 days. The washout period was day 15 to 28 in all participants, during which they returned to their "usual" timing of rhDNase nebulisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>With CF attending outpatient clinics; using rhDNase (Pulmozyme); able to perform spirometry; with stable lung disease as assessed by physician at the time of the study; not currently participating in another clinical trial. Stable lung disease was defined as no deterioration in symptoms and no change in chest management for one month (Henry et al, 1998). Patients were excluded if they were currently enrolled in another study or had significant comorbidities (eg unstable diabetes).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria />
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment (sealed opaque envelopes)</concealment>
    <sequence>Random number tables on Excel</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The physiotherapist and research assistant assessing outcomes were blinded to the time of day at which the subject was receiving nebulised rhDNase. After all data had been collected, the randomisation envelope was opened to allow analysis based on timing at each 14 day block of the study.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/05/2003</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>46</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Children's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Roche Products Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Anne Chang</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study was to investigate if a longer time interval between rhDNase nebulisation and chest physiotherapy improves clinical outcomes of subjects with CF.  

METHODS: A single-blind randomised cross-over trial was conducted on subjects with CF from outpatients of 4 hospitals. Subjects were in stable health and studied over 6-weeks (utilising 14-day blocks of morning or evening rhDNase administration with 14-days washout). Usual regimes for physiotherapy and exercise were unaltered. Thus changing the times altered the dwell time of rhDNase prior to physiotherapy. Long interval was defined as dwell time of &gt;6-hours and short as &lt;6-hours. Outcomes were measured at pre and post each regime.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital Brisbane</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/02/2003</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Adult Hospital Brisbane</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/04/2003</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>566A,</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Gold Coast Hospital, Southport</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/07/2003</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>200334</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Prince Charles Hospital Brisbane</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/11/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC2460</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christine Wilson</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
Brisbane  QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36368506</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36365181</fax>
      <email>christine_wilson@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christine Wilson</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Royal Children's Hospital
Herston Rd
Brisbane  QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 36368506</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 36365181</fax>
      <email>christine_wilson@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>