<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82407">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/11/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/02/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000094370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Vocational Recovery in Young People With First Episode Psychosis.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Controlled Trial of Individual Placement and Support versus treatment as usual in young people with first episode psychosis. Predictors of outcome and health, social, employment and economic outcomes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Unemployment in first episode psychosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will be an employment intervention called Individual Placement and Support which is a well defined version of Supported Employment. Individual Placement and Support has six key principles: it is focussed on competitive employment (i.e. jobs which are not set aside but open to anyone with the appropriate skills or qualifications to apply for) as an outcome; IPS is open to any person with mental illness who chooses to look for work and that acceptance into the program is not determined by measures of work-readiness or illness variables; job searching commences directly on entry into the program; the IPS program is integrated with the mental health treatment team; potential jobs are chosen based on consumer preference; and the support provided in the program is time-unlimited, continuing after employment is obtained, and is adapted to the needs of the individual. A seventh principle is also sometimes considered as part of the model of IPS which is benefits counselling as there are often disincentives to be negotiated in transitioning from a welfare benefit to paid employment. These can include loss of concessions for transport and utilities, high effective marginal tax rates and loss of public health access (especially in USA). Those in the intervention group will receive service from one of two employment consultants who will follow the principles of the IPS model described above. These consultants are people who have worked in and are familiar with the Department of Employment and Workplace Relations (DEWR) system, but are not subject to the contractual conditions of DEWR services in their current role. Their job will be to meet with participants as required, begin job searching immediately, support the job seeking process and support those who find work in their position for the duration of the intervention. They may also work with participants to achieve an educational outcome such as enrolment in a course where this is the most appropriate outcome for the individual. Those in the intervention group will have access to all normal Early Psychosis Prevention and Intervention Centre (EPPIC) services. In intervention the consultant liaises with the participants case manager, and clinical care is continued throughout. The intervention will last for a period of 6 months. The employment sought will be in the open labour market.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator will be treatment as usual which in the case of employment consists of case manager determined referral to external employment agencies.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Employment</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months (end of intervention) 12 &amp; 18 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptomotology</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months (end of intervention) 12 &amp; 18 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social participation</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months (end of intervention) 12 &amp; 18 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Economic participation</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months (end of intervention) 12 &amp; 18 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Economic evaluation of intervention</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months (end of intervention) 12 &amp; 18 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported health service usage</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months (end of intervention) 12 &amp; 18 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patrients of a first episode psychosis service aged between 15 and 25 years who have a stated desire to seek employment</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Lack of sufficient english fluency to participate in assessments</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrolling will be conducted by the project manager after referral to the study from case managers of the Early Psychosis Prevention and Intervention Centre (EPPIC). Allocation will be conducted by a statistician independent of the study but located at the same centre who will then inform the employment consultant which clients to see. The research assistant who will conduct assessments will remain blind to the allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation will be conducted by a statistician using a computer programme with random blocks.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/04/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>8/04/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>146</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>7/10/2012</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Eoin Killackey</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>ORYGEN Research Centre
35 Poplar Road
Parkville, 3052
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Rotary Health Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Australian Rotary Health Research Fund
Floor 2
Rotary Down Under House
43 Hunter Street
PARRAMATTA NSW 2150</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ORYGEN Research Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>35 Poplar Road
Parkville, 3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Unemployment is the most significant non-illness disability that people with mental illness face. Despite much effort being put into employment systems in the community, they remain the single most unemployed disability group despite being able to, and wanting to work. In this study we will trial a form of employment intervention known as Individual Placement and Support with a group of young people with first episode psychosis who are interested in finding work. Our primary aim is to see if this intervention is superior to currently normal treatment. Secondly we are interested in seeing if employment has positive effects on symptoms and medication management. Finally we will be examining the economics of this intervention to establish if the benefit (if there is one) exceeds the cost of providing this type of intervention.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Killackey, E., et al. (2013). "A randomized controlled trial of vocational intervention for young people with first-episode psychosis: method." Early Intervention in Psychiatry 7(3): 329-337.

Arnold, C., et al. (2015). "Neurocognitive and social cognitive predictors of cannabis use in first-episode psychosis." Schizophrenia Research 168: 231-237.
	
Caruana, E., et al. (2015). "The Relationship between Cognition, Job Complexity and Employment Duration in First-Episode Psychosis." Psychiatric rehabilitation journal 38(3): 210-217.

Reser, M. P., et al. (2015). "Exploring cognitive heterogeneity in first-episode psychosis: What cluster analysis can reveal." Psychiatry Research 229(3): 819-827.

On, Z. X., et al. (In Press). "Relationship between duration of untreated psychosis and neurocognition and social cognition in first-episode psychosi." Schizophrenia Research.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>North Western Mental Health Human Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/11/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/12/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Eoin Killackey</name>
      <address>ORYGEN Research Centre
35 Poplar Road
Parkville, 3052
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 2900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eoin@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Eoin Killackey</name>
      <address>ORYGEN Research Centre
35 Poplar Road
Parkville, 3052
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 2900</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>eoin@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>