<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320836">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/11/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/11/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609001008213</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>ABRACADABRA (ABRA) Improving Literacy through Technology
A Multisite Randomised Control Trial Examining the Impact of a Web-Based Early Literacy program on Student Literacy in the Northern Territory (NT)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The impact of ABRACADABRA (ABRA) web-based literacy instruction as compared to standard literacy instruction on the phonemic awareness and word reading of Northern Territory (NT) students in Transition, Year 1 and Year 2 classrooms.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>ABRACADABRA</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Low student literacy in the Northern Territory</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Students will receive ABRACADABRA (ABRA) instruction for one semester (Semester 1, 2010) for a minimum of 30 minutes per day, 4 days per week up to a maximum of 1 hour per day, 5 days per week
.

Developed by a team of literacy and classroom technology experts at Concordia University, ABRA takes a balanced and flexible approach to reading instruction. ABRA includes 32 instructional activities embedded in 17 stories and provides instruc-tion in alphabetics, fluency, comprehension, writing and associated sub-skills (Hipps, Abrami, Savage, Cerna &amp; Jorgenson, 2005). ABRA instruction begins by introducing the main characters and then reading age-appropriate stories. Story associated activities, such as rhyming, are then selected and students can work individually or in groups of varying sizes to answer questions. The ABRA tool is available at no cost at http://abralite.concordia.ca.

The ABRA intervention will be delivered  by one of six trained registered teachers.  Treatment students will leave their classrooms to attend ABRA lessons in separate rooms. The delivery medium will depend upon the schools available technologies, and may include interactive White Boards, computer labs and/or laptops.  The registered teachers will be trained and intensively supported by a researcher during bi-weekly site visits to deliver ABRA according to best practice.  The six ABRA teachers will collaborate on lesson design in order to ensure they are providing the same quality and type of instruction.</interventions>
    <comparator>For the 30-45 minute daily ABRA lessons, students in the control group will receive lit-eracy instruction from their classroom teachers. Currently in the NT most students are taught literacy through three school-based approaches Accelerated Literacy (NALP, 2009), First Steps (2009) and Walking Talking Text (Murray, 1995).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Group Reading and Diagnostic Assessment and Evaluation (GRADE) K Phonological Awareness and Word Reading subscale posttest ability score (combined).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1)  Pretest, weeks 3-4, Semester 1, 2010 : One to two weeks prior to the initiation of ABRACADABRA (ABRA) instruction and 2) Posttest, weeks 19-20, Semester 1, 2010:  one to two weeks after ABRA instruction.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GRADE K phoneme-grapheme correspondence and early literacy skills subtest posttest ability scores.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1)  Pretest, weeks 3-4, Semester 1, 2010 : One to two weeks prior to the initiation of ABRACADABRA (ABRA) instruction and 2) Posttest, weeks 19-20, Semester 1, 2010:  one to two weeks after ABRA instruction.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance Indicators in Primary Schools (PIPS) reading posttest ability score</outcome>
      <timepoint>1)  Pretest, weeks 3-4, Semester 1, 2010 : One to two weeks prior to the initiation of ABRACADABRA (ABRA) instruction and 2) Posttest, weeks 19-20, Semester 1, 2010:  one to two weeks after ABRA instruction.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance Indicators in Primary Schools (PIPS) phonics posttest ability score</outcome>
      <timepoint>1)  Pretest, weeks 3-4, Semester 1, 2010 : One to two weeks prior to the initiation of ABRACADABRA (ABRA) instruction and 2) Posttest, weeks 19-20, Semester 1, 2010:  one to two weeks after ABRA instruction.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Performance Indicators in Primary Schools (PIPS) math posttest ability score</outcome>
      <timepoint>1)  Pretest, weeks 3-4, Semester 1, 2010 : One to two weeks prior to the initiation of ABRACADABRA (ABRA) instruction and 2) Posttest, weeks 19-20, Semester 1, 2010:  one to two weeks after ABRA instruction.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Raw scores on all GRADE K and PIPS total and subscale tests</outcome>
      <timepoint>1)  Pretest, weeks 3-4, Semester 1, 2010 : One to two weeks prior to the initiation of ABRACADABRA (ABRA) instruction and 2) Posttest, weeks 19-20, Semester 1, 2010:  one to two weeks after ABRA instruction.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Standard score change for all GRADE K and PIPS total and subscale tests per hour of intervention (response to intervention)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1)  Pretest, weeks 3-4, Semester 1, 2010 : One to two weeks prior to the initiation of ABRACADABRA (ABRA) instruction, 2) Posttest, weeks 19-20, Semester 1, 2010:  one to two weeks after ABRA instruction, 3) daily attendance will be used to calculate hours of exposure to ABRA instruction.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Students enrolled in Transition, Grade 1 or Grade 2 classrooms (or combination thereof)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>4</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>8</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Lack of reliable internet access within the students school

Schools with fewer than 60 students in Transition, Grade 1 and 2 classrooms

Schools with less than 30% Indigenous students

Students identified by the school as being non-testable due to severe cognitive impairment or unable to complete pretest assessment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Pre-randomisation
Schools will be asked to identify two to four classrooms to participate in the study so that the total number of students eligible for randomisation totals at least 60.  Schools will be responsible for distributing consent forms to the parents of eligible study students. During the pre-randomisation phase schools will provide demographic information on the study students (gender, date of birth, Indigenous status, English as a Second Language (ESL) status, student ID and student name).  This demographic information will be entered in a student database.  During the pretesting period (weeks 3 and 4 of Semester 1) volunteer testers and research staff will assess the students on the phonological awareness, word reading, phoneme-grapheme correspondence and early literacy skills subscale of the GRADE K and the PIPS assessments.  Students who do not complete pretests will be removed from the student database and excluded from randomisation.

Randomisation will use permuted blocks, stratified by school, class and class level within a class.  A list of all eligible students and classrooms will be supplied to the Menzies School for Health Research for randomisation by classroom during week 4.  Allocation will be concealed by 1) randomising after eligibility is determined and 2) supplying the student lists to the holder of the allocation schedule (Menzies School for Health Research) who is 'off-site' to create the allocation list. By week 5, schools will be informed which students will receive ABRA during Semester 1 and ABRA instruction will begin.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will use permuted blocks, stratified by school, class and class level within a class.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Assessors will be blind to student assignment.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Charles Darwin University -- School for Social and Policy Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>39 Ellengowan Drive
Building Yellow 1
Charles Darwin University
Darwin NT 0909</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 6022 
Parliament House
Canberra, ACT 2600</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Telstra Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 31
242 Exhibition Street
Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Menzies School of Health Research</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Building 58
Royal Darwin Hospital
Tiwi NT 0810</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Concordia University -- Centre for the Study of Learning and Performance</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>CSLP, LB-581
Concordia University,
1455 De Maisonneuve Blvd. West, 
Montreal, Quebec
H3G 1M8</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Canada</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>National Health and Medical Research Council Clinical Trials Centre</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown NSW 1450</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine whether literacy instruction using the ABRACADABRA (ABRA) program 30 minutes per day, 4 days per week for one Semester improves student literacy in the Northern Territory (NT) moreso than traditional literacy instruction.  ABRACADABRA (ABRA) is an online web-based early literacy program designed by Concordia University in Canada according to best practices in literacy instruction. The study tests the hypothesis that students who receive ABRA instruction will have higher scores than students who do not receive ABRA instruction on two measures of foundational skills for future reading:  1) phonemic awareness (recognition of the sounds in the English language) and individual word reading.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Charles Darwin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ellengowan Drive
Orange Building 1, Level 2, Room 21
Charles Darwin University
Darwin NT 0909</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jennifer Wolgemuth</name>
      <address>School for Social and Policy Research
39 Ellengowan Drive
Yellow Building 1, Level 2
Darwin NT 0909</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8946 6963</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jenni.wolgemuth@cdu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Helen Harper</name>
      <address>School for Social and Policy Research
39 Ellengowan Drive
Yellow Building 1, Level 2
Darwin NT 0909</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8946 6963</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Helen.harper@cdu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Christine Bottrell</name>
      <address>School for Social and Policy Research
39 Ellengowan Drive
Yellow Building 1, Level 2
Darwin NT 0909</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8946 6963</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.bottrell@cdu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>