<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336030">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000925044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A comparison of ultrasound guided and nerve stimulator assisted popliteal nerve blocks for foot surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients undergoing popliteal nerve blocks for foot surgery, is ultrasound guided administration of the block as good as or better than a nerve stimulator for providing intraoperative and postoperative pain relief?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pain relief during and after foot surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Ultrasound  nerve localization with a Sonosite Nanomaxx ultrasound system using an L38n ultrasound probe in the 5-10MHz range or 

Once the nerves have been adequately localized in the transverse plane below the level of the bifurcation. A double injection -  a block  of the Common Peroneal nerve  and Posterior Tibial nerve is performed, the saphenous nerve is also blocked at the level of the knee

The local anaesthetic agent used is 20ml of Ropivicaine 0.75% 
The block is inserted prior to prepping and draping</interventions>
    <comparator>Lateral popliteal block using Nerve stimulation using a Stimuplex A nerve stimulator with a 22G 50mm insulated needle.
A double injection technique to the posterior tibial then the common peroneal is performed after approriate evoked motor response is obtained and the stimulator is reduced to 0.5mA. A sapheneous nerve block at the knee is also performed
20ml of 0.75% Ropivicaine is used</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post procedure analgesic requirements. The analgesic and dose will be recorded on a form by the anaesthetist intraoperatively and by nursing staff in recovery and then on the ward</outcome>
      <timepoint>recorded during operation, at 2 hours, 4 hours and 16 hours post block</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Speed to perform block</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured intraoperatively</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to onset before 4 hours</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessment of the completeness of the block at 4 hours to be made by the nursing staff</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction</outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be asked by the nursing staff on discharge if they were satisfied with the block and analgesia that it provided. This will be recorded on a form</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Residual neurological deficit at 8 weeks</outcome>
      <timepoint>At a clinic review at 8 weeks a detailed motor and sensory examination will be recorded on a form to assess any deficit whihc may be block related.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Foot Surgery which will last &lt;90 mins and require an overnight stay.
Calf tourniquet 
&gt;18 yrs
American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) score I - III</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known neuropathies
Diabetics with a neuropathy
Patients receiving muscle relaxant
Coagulopathy or on Anticoagulants
Infection / Skin problems precluding injection of block
Previous surgery in the popliteal region
Allergy to local anaesthetic
Patients on opioids for chronic analgesic therapy
Patients with a known Chronic regional pain syndrome (CRPS) / neuroma
Renal / liver failure where post operative analgesia can not be used</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The patients who meet inclusion criteria at teh time of booking for suregery will be given an information and consent form and asked to participate. 
On teh day of surgery a sealed envelope  will randomise the patient to either recieve the popliteal block using ultrasound or nerve stimulation assistance.</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/02/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mr Harvinder Bedi</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Orthosport
Suite 61  Level 6
Epworth Eastern Hospital
1 Arnold Street
Boxhill
Melbourne
VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mr Harvinder Bedi</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Orthosport
Suite 61  Level 6
Epworth Eastern Hospital
1 Arnold Street
Boxhill
Melbourne
VIC 3128</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project has been designed to investigate whether one particular method of administering local anaesthetic around the knee in order to provide pain relief for patients undergoing foot surgery is better than the other.
A routine part of anaesthesia for foot surgery performed in our unit is to perform a popliteal block. This involves injecting local anaesthetic around the nerves behind the knee to numb the foot and provide pain relief both during and after the operation. This block is performed either using an ultrasound machine to visualise the nerves or a nerve stimulator which stimulates the nerve. Both allow the anaesthetist to know the correct position to inject the local anaesthetic.
We are planning to randomly allocate patients undergoing foot surgery to receive the block either with the ultrasound machine or with the nerve stimulator.
We will then use a form to collect information about pain and pain relief requirements whilst the patient is in hospital to assess the efficacy of the block. We will also collect information about the length time to perform each block and patient satisfaction.
Patients will be seen at routine follow up at 8 weeks and assessed to see if there are any ongoing problems related to the nerve block.
We will analyse the data to see if one technique is superior to the other and modify our practise as appropriate.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincents Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/A -155/10</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mr Hamish Curry</name>
      <address>Orthosport
Suite 61  Level 6
Epworth Eastern Hospital
1 Arnold Street
Boxhill
Melbourne
VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9890 0494</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hamishcurry@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mr Hamish Curry</name>
      <address>Orthosport
Suite 61  Level 6
Epworth Eastern Hospital
1 Arnold Street
Boxhill
Melbourne
VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9890 0494</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hamishcurry@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Harvinder Bedi</name>
      <address>Orthosport Suite 61 Level 6 Epworth Eastern Hospital 1 Arnold Street Boxhill Melbourne VIC 3128</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9890 0494</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hsbedi1@bigpond.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>