<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372728">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000596303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Pilot Study of CXCR-4 (68Ga-CPCR4-2) PET (Positron Emission Tomography) scanning in operable rectal cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Pilot Study evaluating the accuracy of CXCR-4 (68Ga-CPCR4-2) PET scanning in operable rectal cancer.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Rectal Adenocarcinoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>As part of the clinical trail participants with biopsy proven, newly diagnosed rectal adenocarcinoma, of all clinical stages, will undergo a 68Ga-CPCR4-2 PET scan with a, non contrast, low dose CT (68Ga-CPCR4-2 PET/CT) in one session, at the Herston Imaging Research facility (HIRF). 
The PET/CT scan will take approximately 45 mins.
As part of the clinical trial participants will be required to have an extra scan (68Ga-CPCR4-2 PET/CT) on top of the required standard diagnostic evaluations.  

A qualified Nuclear Medicine Technologist will administer the 68Ga-CPCR4-2 intravenously and perform the scan and a qualified Nuclear Medicine Physician will interpret the results.

The clinical trial scan will be undertaken when post diagnosis, prior to surgery or any other treatment commencing.  

</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard work up/investigations for this population include a contrast enhanced Pelvic MRI and CT chest, abdomen and pelvis and will have been undertaken as per normal standard of care prior to clinical trial involvement.  

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sensitivity and specificity of 68Ga-CPCR4-2 PET in detecting the spread of primary rectal adencarcinomas, assess by comparison to standard imaging studies (contrast enhanced Pelvic MRI and CT Chest, abdomen and pelvis).

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following the completion of index test (68Ga-CPCR4-2) </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>a)	To measure the uptake of the 68Ga-CPCR4-2 PET/CT tracer, (measured by SUV) in primary rectal adenocarcinomas and loco-regional nodal or any distant metastases;



</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of 68Ga-CPCR4-2 PET/CT tracer scan.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>b)	 To compare the uptake seen of primary rectal tumours and any metastases on 68Ga-CPCR4-2 PET/CT with the findings on standard imaging studies (contrast enhanced Pelvic MRI and CT chest, abdomen and pelvis);
Standard SUV measurement tools used in Nuclear Medicine Reporting will be used to assess uptake.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following 68Ga-CPCR4-2 PET/CT tracer scan</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>c)	To correlate findings on the 68Ga-CPCR4-2 PET/CT with the histopathology stage of the subsequent surgical specimen;</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following surgical removal of primary rectal adenocarcinomas and loco-regional nodal or any distant metastases.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>d) Monitor adverse events of participants receiving 68Ga-CPCR4-2 PET/CT.

The PET/CT procedure:
Common risks and complications include:
1. Minor pain and bruising
Less common risks and complications include:
1.  Infection from an intravenous cannula site that may require treatment with antibiotics
2.  An allergy to injected drugs may occur, requiring further treatment
Rare risks and complications include:
1. Death as a result of this procedure is very rare

All adverse events reported by the subject/or in response to questioning or observation by the Principal Investigator will be recorded from the time of consent, during the scanning session and for 30 days after the PET scan or until the time of treatment initiation whichever comes first. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of and for 30 days following (or until treatment initiation) the 68Ga-CPCR4-2 PET/CT tracer scan.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria

1)	 Biopsy proven newly diagnosed rectal adenocarcinoma (of any subtype)

2)	 Tumour must lie within 15 cm of the anal verge and be below the peritoneal reflection.

3)	 Age &gt; 18 years

4)	 Written informed consent

5)	 All women of child bearing age must have a pregnancy test before enrolment
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion Criteria

1)	 Rectal cancer of any other histopathology eg: neuroendocrine, small cell, squamous cell etc.

2)	 Any other diagnosis of cancer that the investigating team feel might complicate the interpretation of the PET findings. 

3)	 Locally recurrent rectal cancer.

4)	 Unable to undergo a PET scan, in the opinion of the investigators, for any reason.

5)	 Pregnant or breast feeding
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Metro North Hospital and Health Service
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston QLD 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Herston Imaging Research Facility Seed Funding</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Metro North Hospital and Health Service
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston QLD 4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will compare the accuracy of an investigative imaging technique (known as 68Ga-CPCR4-2 (68Ga-Pentixafor) PET/CT imaging) with conventional staging (contrast enhanced Pelvic MRI and CT chest, abdomen and pelvis) at initial diagnosis of rectal cancer.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or above, and have biopsy proven, newly diagnosed rectal adenocarcinoma (of any subtype).

Study details
All participants in this study will undergo a 68Ga-CPCR4-2 (68Ga-Pentixafor) PET scan together with a contemporaneous, non contrast, low dose CT for anatomical correlation, in one session, at the Herston Imaging Research facility (HIRF).  A qualified Nuclear Medicine Technologist will insert a tube into a vein in your arm and give you an injection of a radioactive substance called 68Ga-Pentixafor.  You will then be required to wait for 1 hour, called the uptake time, before emptying your bladder and proceeding to have your scan.  The scan involves lying flat with knees supported and arms resting above your head.  You will be scanned from head to mid-thigh.  The scan time for the 68Ga-Pentixafor PET/CT will be approximately 45 minutes.  

We will monitor all participants for adverse events for 30 days after the PET scan or until the time of treatment initiation whichever comes first. We will also measure the level of tracer uptake by the cancer . If results of this study are promising, we hope to further explore the impact of the PET tracer on management decisions, diagnostic accuracy, as well as the prognostic impact of the uptake of this tracer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7 Block 7
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston QLD 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Burge</name>
      <address>Cancer Care Services
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matthew.burge@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Annette Cubitt</name>
      <address>Cancer Care Services
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street 
Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>annette.cubitt@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Burge</name>
      <address>Cancer Care Services
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>matthew.burge@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>