<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335669">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/07/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000570088</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Brighten Your Mood Program: A randomized controlled trial of internet based treatment of depression for Chinese Australians</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized controlled trial of Internet based treatment for depression for Chinese Australians comparing immediate treatment vs. delayed treatment on symptoms of major depressive disorder.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Major Depressive Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two groups: 1) an immediate treatment group, or; 2) a delayed treatment group also known as a waitlist control group (beginnning the program 9 weeks after the immediate treatment group begin). All participants will meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 4th Edition (DSM-IV) criteria for depression. All participants will complete 6 lessons of Internet based treatment about management of symptoms of depression. One lesson will be completed every 7 to 10 days. Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to complete. Participants will also have access to summaries of each lesson, and will read anonymous stories about other people with depression, taking a further 20 minutes per summary. All participants will also receive automatic email and weekly reminder phone calls by a research assistant. The duration of the reminder emails/phone calls is expected to be 5-10 minutes per week. The duration of the program is 8weeks, but participants in the immediate treatment group will be contacted 3 months post program and asked to complete follow-up questionnaires. Study questionnaires will be administered at application, pre-education, post-education, and at 3-months post-education. These will take about 20-30 minutes to complete. The treatment materials are based on the Sadness Programs, which apply cognitive behavioural techniques such as psychoeducation about the symptoms and treatment of depression, behavioural activation, cognitive restructuring, graded exposure, behavioural experiments, and relapse prevention.</interventions>
    <comparator>The delayed treatment group (beginnning the program 9 weeks after the immediate treatment group begins). This is a wait-list control group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression is measured by the Chinese Patient Health Questionnaire 9-item (Chinese-PHQ-9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3-months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression is measured by the Chinese Beck Depression Inventory (Chinese-BDI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3-months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General levels of depression, anxiety and stress is measured by the Chinese 21-item Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (Chinese-DASS-21)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3-months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability is measured by the Chinese version of the Sheehan Disability Scale (Chinese-SDS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3-months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress is measured by the Chinese Kessler 10-item scale (Chinese-K-10)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at pre-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3-months post-treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Meet DSM-IV criteria for major depressive disorder
- Can speak fluent Cantonese or Mandarin
- Internet access + printer access
- Australian resident
- Be of Chinese origin</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Current substance abuse/dependence 
- Psychotic disorder or severe depression
- Current or planned psychological treatment during study duration 
- Change in medications during last 1 month or intended change during study duration 
- Suicidal</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants apply online, followed by a telephone interview to confirm diagnosis via structured diagnostic interview using the Chinese version of the Major Depressive Episode section of the Mini Neuropsychiatric Interview Schedule (MINI 5.0.0). Allocation concealment will occur by providing allocation details for each successive participant in a sealed envelope, which recruitment staff are required to open serially.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomized using a list generated prior to the study via a software program (www.random.org), at another site, in another country. The list will then be transcribed and details transferred to sealed envelopes.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression (CRUfAD), School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>299 Forbes Street Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>BeyondBlue</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>40 Burwood Road, Hawthorn West, Victoria 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Stephen Li</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Core Pathology Services at the Institute of Clinical Pathology and Medical Research (ICPMR), Westmead Hospital, Westmead NSW 2145</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current study aims to reduce the practical and cultural barriers to mental health treatment for Chinese Australians by developing an Internet-based cognitive behavior therapy (ICBT) program for depression, based on the Sadness Program developed by Perini, Titov &amp; Andrews (2009; www.virtualclinic.org.au) that is culturally sensitive and appropriate. A randomized controlled trial will compare the enhanced Chinese ICBT program for depression (the Brighten Your Mood Program) with telephone support to a waitlist control group. The project will examine the efficacy of the Internet Program in reducing symptoms of depression and disability in Chinese Australians, as well as its acceptability.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.virtualclinic.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, Jane Foss Russell Building - G02
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/05/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12436</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Caroline Hunt</name>
      <address>School of Psychology Transient Building  F12 The University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 5446</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caroline.hunt@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Caroline Hunt</name>
      <address>School of Psychology Transient Building  F12 The University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 5446</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caroline.hunt@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Caroline Hunt</name>
      <address>School of Psychology Transient Building  F12 The University of Sydney, Camperdown, NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 5446</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caroline.hunt@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>