<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371212">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001059459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of extended exposure to lixisenatide on gastric emptying and postprandial glycaemia in patients with type 2 diabetes treated with metformin</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of extended exposure to lixisenatide on gastric emptying and postprandial glycaemia in patients with type 2 diabetes treated with metformin</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will consist of 56 days treatment with either lixisenatide or placebo (saline). Dosing of lixisenatide will be stepped up according to the following schedule: 
-	5 mcg subcut, once daily on days 1-7, 10 mcg subcut, once daily on days 8-14, and 20 mcg subcut, once daily on days 15-56
-  Patients will have a diary and will need to sign each time an injection was given. 
- Patients self administer their injections</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo = normal saline</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in gastric half-emptying time as assessed by scintigraphy ( a meal will be given while the subject sits against a gamma camera, consisting of  300ml 25% dextrose labelled with 20MBq 99mTc-calcium phytate, and also containing 1.5g [U-13C] glucose, and 1000mg paracetamol to measure gastric emptying simultaneously by the paracetamol absorption test) from baseline to day 56, for lixisenatide versus placebo</outcome>
      <timepoint>Gastric emptying will be assessed from the time of ingestion of the meal and for 240 min afterwards. We will then review any change in gastric emptying at day 56 at the final gastric emptying study. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Postprandial glycaemia (incremental area under the curve) for blood glucose concentration between t = 0 and 240 min, Change from baseline to Day 56. . </outcome>
      <timepoint>Venous blood (~3 mL) will be sampled at t= -210, -20, -10, 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 and 240 min for subsequent analysis of blood glucose and plasma glucose tracer concentrations. Change from baseline to Day 56.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HbA1c by serum assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>A further sample (5 mL) will be collected at t = -210 min to measure HbA1C. Change from baseline to Day 56. .  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of exogenous glucose appearance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Venous blood (~3 mL) will be sampled at t= -210, -20, -10, 0 (meal given), 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 and 240 min for subsequent analysis of d plasma glucose tracer concentrations. Change from baseline to Day 56. . </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Insulin</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples at t = -210, -30, 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 and 240 min, for measurement of plasma insulin, Change from baseline to Day 56. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fructosamine - serum assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>A further sample (5 mL) will be collected at t = -210 min to measure Fructosamine. Change from baseline to Day 56. .  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of endogenous glucose production</outcome>
      <timepoint>Venous blood (~3 mL) will be sampled at t= -210, -20, -10, 0 (meal given), 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 and 240 min for subsequent analysis of d plasma glucose tracer concentrations</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma C-Peptide
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples at t = -210, -30, 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 and 240 min, for measurement of plasma C-Peptide, Change from baseline to Day 56. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Glucagon. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples at t = -210, -30, 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 and 240 min, for measurement of plasma glucagon, Change from baseline to Day 56. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Beta cell function (evaluated from insulin secretion rates as determined by deconvolution analysis of postprandial C-peptide concentrations)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples at t = -210, -30, 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 and 240 min, for measurement of plasma C-Peptide and insulin as above, Change from baseline to Day 56. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Paracetamol</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples at at t (min)= -20, -10, 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90, 120, 150, 180, 210, 240 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Males or females aged greater than 40 years
If females are premenopausal they must have had either a tubal ligation or hysterectomy i.e. are not fertile.
Type 2 diabetes treated with metformin for greater than or equal to 3 months
HbA1c between 6.5 and 9%
Duration of known diabetes greater than or equal to 2 years
Haemoglobin above the lower limit of the normal range (i.e. greater than 135 g/L for men and 115 g/L for women), and ferritin above the lower limit of normal (i.e. greater than 10 mcg/L)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Evidence of renal, hepatic or cardiovascular disease, pancreatitis, gastric surgery, or known gastroparesis. Renal disease: creatinine clearance (mL/min) will be calculated using the Cockcroft-Gault equation. Subjects will be excluded if creatinine clearance is estimated at less than 30 mL/min. Hepatic disease: subjects will be excluded if there is documented cirrhosis or transaminases or alkaline phosphatase elevated more than 2 times the upper limit of normal.  Cardiovascular disease: admission to hospital with heart failure, myocardial infarction or stroke within previous 6 months.
Previous exposure to GLP-1 receptor agonists
Use of drugs potentially affecting gastrointestinal motility (opiates, anticholinergics, levodopa, clonidine, nitrates, , phosphodiesterase type 5 inhibitors, sumatriptan, metoclopramide, domperidone, cisapride, tegaserod, or erythromycin)
Use of any agent other than metformin for control of glycaemia
Premenopausal females, unless they have had a tubal ligation or hysterectomy
Presence of definite autonomic nerve damage (as assessed by standardised cardiovascular reflex tests)
Participation in any research studies involving exposure to ionising radiation within the previous 12 months
Vegetarian diet
Intake of  greater than 20 g alcohol on a daily basis, or cigarette smoking
Volunteers who have donated blood in the preceding 3 months
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Yes allocation concealment. Blinding and randomization by central randomization by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (Research Randomizer - https://www.randomizer.org/) </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We have previously established a mean half-emptying time for 150 mL 10% dextrose when consumed with 100g minced beef, as measured by scintigraphy, of 34 min with a standard deviation of 19 min in a group of patients with longstanding diabetes. Therefore, 20 subjects in each group will provide 80% power to detect a 50% increase in the gastric half-emptying time by lixisenatide compared to placebo at 8 weeks (Day 56).
Analysis will be undertaken on a per-protocol basis. Analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) will be used to compare changes in gastric emptying in each group at 8 weeks, adjusting for baseline values. Secondary endpoints will be analysed in similar fashion. Relationships between reduction in postprandial glycaemia and change in gastric emptying, between reduction in postprandial glycaemia and baseline rate of gastric emptying, and between reduction in postprandial glycaemia and beta cell function will be examined</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/05/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname> Central Adelaide Local Health Network </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress> Level 4, Women's Health Centre
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace,
Adelaide 5000
South Australia 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sanofi</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Talavera Corporate Centre, Building D,
12-24 Talavera Rd, Macquarie Park NSW 2113
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The trial will follow a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled parallel group design.

After providing written, informed consent, each subject will attend the Nuclear Medicine Department in the morning (0800) after an overnight fast under baseline conditions (day 0). If the subject is normally prescribed metformin, this will be held while fasting and will be taken with the first meal following gastric emptying study. The investigators will confirm the prescribed metformin dose and check that this remains stable at each visit. A standardised meal will be provided the evening before the study. An intravenous cannula will be inserted in each forearm, one for blood sampling and the other for IV infusion of glucose tracer (initial bolus of 28 micromol.kg-1 6,6-2H2 glucose, followed by continuous infusion at a rate of 0.28 micromol.min-1.kg-1 from t = -210 until t = 240 min). At t = -5min, a meal will be given while the subject sits against a gamma camera, consisting of  300ml 25% dextrose labelled with 20MBq 99mTc-calcium phytate, and also containing 1.5g [U-13C] glucose, and 1000mg paracetamol to measure gastric emptying simultaneously by the paracetamol absorption test. The meal will be consumed within 5 minutes. Gastric emptying will be assessed from the time of ingestion of the meal and for 240 min afterwards. Venous blood (~3 mL) will be sampled at t= -210, -20, -10, 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 and 240 min for subsequent analysis of blood glucose and plasma glucose tracer concentrations, and additional samples (~10 ml volume) at t = -210, -30, 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180 and 240 min, for measurement of plasma insulin, C-peptide, and glucagon. A further sample (5 mL) will be collected at t = -210 min to measure HbA1C and fructosamine. Heart rate and blood pressure will be monitored every 3 minutes between t = -60 min and t =240 min using an automated recording device ((DINAMAP ProCare 100, GE Medical Systems, Milwaukee, WI, USA). At the conclusion of the study, subjects will be offered a light meal before they leave the laboratory.

On the following day (day 1), each subject will then commence a 56 day (8 week) intervention consisting of lixisenatide or matching placebo (saline) administered subcutaneously once daily, 30 min before breakfast, as detailed below. On the final day (day 56), he or she will return to the department for a second gastric emptying study that will be identical to the study protocol for day 0, other than for administration of the final dose of lixisenatide or placebo 30 min before meal ingestion.

Intervention
The intervention will consist of 56 days treatment with either lixisenatide or placebo (saline). Dosing of lixisenatide will be stepped up according to the following schedule:
- 5 mcg days 1-7, 10 mcg days 8-14, 20 mcg days 15-56</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, Womens Health Centre
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, South Australia, 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/01/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC Reference No: HREC/15/RAH/520</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Chris Rayner</name>
      <address>University of Adelaide 
Discipline of Medicine, 
Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Rd, Adelaide, South Australia 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82222916</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chris.rayner@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Chris Rayner</name>
      <address>University of Adelaide 
Discipline of Medicine, 
Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Rd, Adelaide, South Australia 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82222916</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chris.rayner@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Chris Rayner</name>
      <address>University of Adelaide 
Discipline of Medicine, 
Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Rd, Adelaide, South Australia  5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82222916</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chris.rayner@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Linda Watson</name>
      <address>University of Adelaide 
Discipline of Medicine, 
Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building
Frome Rd, Adelaide, South Australia 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82222915</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>linda.watson@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>