<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365696">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000118606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating Sensory Perception in Cervical Dystonia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluating Sensory Perception in Cervical Dystonia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1152-5351 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>ESP CD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cervical Dystonia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Observational study- Sensory testing including Quantitative Sensory analysis and nerve conduction studies.
Quantitative Sensory Analysis (QST) will be performed testing pressure, temperature and pain perception. These tests take 2-3 hours to complete.
Control subjects will undergo this testing on a single occasion. Subjects with Cervical Dystonia will undergo this testing on two separate occasions 6 weeks apart. </interventions>
    <comparator>Control subjects without neurological disease</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>comparison between sensory testing outcomes in people with cervical dystonia and control subjects</outcome>
      <timepoint>Comparison between groups ( Cervical dystonia compared with healthy controls)  will be conducted after all participants have completed their initial visit.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>comparison between sensory testing before and after botulinum toxin injection treatment for cervical dystonia </outcome>
      <timepoint>Comparison between sensory testing before and after botulinum toxin injection treatment for cervical dystoniarequires two tests to be performed in each subject with cervical dystonia. 
Each participant with cervical dystonia will under go the testing on two separate occasions, with the second testing session taking place after the administration of the participant's next botulinum toxin injection for the treatment of cervical dystonia;  testing sessions will be at least 6 weeks apart.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>variability in sensory testing outcomes across affected and non affected body parts in cervical dystonia</outcome>
      <timepoint>this information will be collected during the first testing session in subjects with cervical dystonia</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Two groups:
1. Cervical dystonia
Cervical dystonia as diagnosed by a movement disorders neurologist, aged &gt; 18 years, capable of providing informed consent. The first visit will be held at the end of the botulinum toxin injection cycle, 12 weeks since last injection. 
2. control subjects without known neurological disease or chronic pain syndrome</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Complex dystonia phenotype or familial dystonia
2.Presence of neuropathy (including risk factors as detailed below)
a.Diabetes
b.Carpal tunnel syndrome
c.Major cardiac/respiratory/renal impairment
d.Deranged thyroid function
e.Significant B12 deficiency
f.Autoimmune disease
g. Past history of multiple myeloma, chemotherapy 
h.Cervical spine pathology/radiculopathy
i.Co-existing neurological disease or other movement disorder
j.Pregnancy
k. Drug and alcohol abuse
l.HepB/HepC/HIV
3.Inability to speak English to sufficient degree to provide appropriate consent
4.Clinically diagnosed dementia 
5.Clinically significant generalised pain disorders including
a.Migraine
b.Back pain
c.Fibromyalgia
d.Bruxism/TMJ dysfunction
e.CRPS
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Data found to be normally distributed is presented as mean and standard deviation, with comparison between groups made using the independent groups t-test. Data found not to adhere to a normal distribution is presented as median and interquartile range, and differences between groups compared using a Mann-Whitney U-test.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Alfred</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Commercial road
Prahran
Victoria 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Alfred
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Commercial road
Prahran
Victoria 3004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Dystonia is a movement disorder characterised by involuntary twisting movements and abnormal postures of the body. Cervical dystonia is the most common focal dystonia of younger adults, producing abnormal neck postures, twisting, shaking and turning movements of the neck, and pain in the neck and shoulders.  How dystonia develops is not known.  Treatment for cervical dystonia is predominantly with Botulinum toxin. There is compelling evidence for its benefit in reducing symptoms of head posturing and pain, however it requires repeated injections and does not always provide satisfactory outcomes. Botulinum toxin is known to interrupt neuro-muscular interaction, producing focal muscle weakness, however evidence for its use in migraine headache has implicated a direct effect on pain perception. Whether improvement in dystonia  with botulinum toxin is related only to motor effects or has a longer term benefit on modulating the dystonia itself is not known. The experience of pain can alter sensory and motor processing related to direct interference with neuroplastic processes or compromised motor performance. Sensory testing has shown decreased sensory function in the affected compared with unaffected hand in people with hand dystonia. This type of sensory testing has not been performed in people with cervical dystonia.  It is likely all dystonia arises from abnormal sensorimotor integration processes, though this process is currently incompletely understood. 
This project aims to measure peripheral sensory perception objectively in patients with cervical dystonia to determine if their sensation is abnormal, if this is a generalised or focal situation, and to determine if this sensation is altered by the administration of botulinum toxin which is effective in reducing the severity of the movements. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital 
Commercial road
Prahran
Victoria 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/01/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Bertram</name>
      <address>Neurosciences
Alfred Hospital
Commercial road
Prahran
Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.bertram@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Hewer</name>
      <address>Neurosciences
Alfred Hospital
Commercial road
Prahran
Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.hewer@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Bertram</name>
      <address>Neurosciences
Alfred Hospital
Commercial road
Prahran
Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.bertram@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kelly Bertram</name>
      <address>Neurosciences
Alfred Hospital
Commercial road
Prahran
Victoria 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.bertram@alfred.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>