<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83148">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/09/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000472370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>'Songs for Life': Group music therapy for serious and enduring mental illness (SEMI) -  a randomised control trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of a group music therapy program on quality of life in people living with severe and enduring mental illness (SEMI) in the community</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>'Songs for Life'</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Severe and enduring mental illness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Schizophrenia and other psychotic disorders</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Bipolar disorder and major depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Schizophrenia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A group music therapy intervention comprising the following (4) treatment components: singing preferred and familiar songs; percussive improvisation; writing an original song; recording an original song. The intervention will be a 13-week group music therapy progam, delivered by a registared music therapist (RMT). The program comprises one Introductory Session, and 12 group music therapy sessions, with session length of one hour. The original song will be recorded in a professional recording studio and a CD will be given to participants at the end of the program. Music therapy is a recognised psychosocial intervention that involves a wide range of musical applications, including improvisation, instrument playing, singing/vocalising, composition, song/lyric writing, music and movement, listening, performance and music imagery. Music therapy interventions are selected according to the unique needs of particular individuals or groups, and offer participants the opportunity to interact musically and socially in the context of a therapeutic relationship. The effectiveness of music therapy, especially active music-making, for people with SEMI has been demonstrated (Gold, Heldal, Dahle &amp; Wigram, 2005).</interventions>
    <comparator>The control condition will be a waitlist control in which all participants will receive group music therapy, either immediately after randomisation, or following a 3-month waiting period.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Statistically significant changes in Quality of Life, as measured by the Quality of Life Enjoyment and Satisfaction Questionniare (Q-LES-Q-18; Ritsner, Kurs, Gibel, Ratner &amp; Endicott, 2005). The Q-LES-Q-18 is an 18-item self-report inventory that assesses quality of life in four domains: social relationships, physical health, subjective feelings, and leisure-time activities. The instrument represents a parsimonious subset of items that maintains the validity and psychometric properties of the longer 60-item version. The Q-LES-Q-18 is suitable for the evaluation of quality of life outcomes in clinical trials involving participants with schizophrenia, shizoaffective, and mood disorders.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants randomised to the music condition will be assessed at three points: pre-treatment (immediately following randomisation), Week 13 (post-treatment) and follow-up (3 months after post-treatment assessment).
Participants randomised to the wailtlist condition will be assessed at four timepoints: Beginning of waitlist (3 months before intervention), pre-treatment, Week 13 (post-treatment), and follow-up (3 months after post-treatment assessment).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Statistically significant changes in perceived social support, as measured by the ENRICHD Social Support Instrument (ESSI; Barefoot et al., 2003). The ESSI is a 7-item self-report inventory that has demonstrated utility in assessing the role of social support in health outcomes (Vaglio et al, 2004).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants randomised to the music condition will be assessed at three points: pre-treatment (immediately following randomisation), Week 13 (post-treatment) and follow-up (3 months after post-treatment assessment).
Participants randomised to the wailtlist condition will be assessed at four timepoints: Beginning of waitlist (3 months before intervention), pre-treatment, Week 13 (post-treatment), and follow-up (3 months after post-treatment assessment).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Statistically significant changes in self-esteem, as measured by the Rosenberg Self-Esteem Scale (RSES; Rosenberg, 1965). The RSES is a widely used 10-item self-report inventory for evaluating individual self-esteem.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants randomised to the music condition will be assessed at three points: pre-treatment (immediately following randomisation), Week 13 (post-treatment) and follow-up (3 months after post-treatment assessment).
Participants randomised to the wailtlist condition will be assessed at four timepoints: Beginning of waitlist (3 months before intervention), pre-treatment, Week 13 (post-treatment), and follow-up (3 months after post-treatment assessment).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Statistically significant changes in spirituality, as measured by the Functional Assessment of Chronic Illness Therapy-Spiritual Well-being Scale (FACIT-Sp; Peterman et al., 2002). The FACIT-Sp is a popular 12-item self-report measure of the religious/spiritual (R/S) components of quality of life (QoL) in patients with cancer (Carmody et al., 2008). Qualitative analysis of song lyrics in the pilot study for this project revealed strong religious and meaning-related themes. Thus, the inclusion of a quantitative outcome measure of spirituality.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants randomised to the music condition will be assessed at three points: pre-treatment (immediately following randomisation), Week 13 (post-treatment) and follow-up (3 months after post-treatment assessment).
Participants randomised to the wailtlist condition will be assessed at four timepoints: Beginning of waitlist (3 months before intervention), pre-treatment, Week 13 (post-treatment), and follow-up (3 months after post-treatment assessment).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychiatric symptoms, as measured by the Brief Symtpom Inventory (BSI; Derogatis, 1993). The BSI is 53-item brief self-report inventory that reflects psychopathology and psychological distress in nine symptom dimensions and three global indices. This instrument is appropriate for a broad range of diagnoses and is useful in evaluating treatment outcome. We are expecting that psychiatric symptoms will remain unchanged  pre- and post-intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants randomised to the music condition will be assessed at three points: pre-treatment (immediately following randomisation), Week 13 (post-treatment) and follow-up (3 months after post-treatment assessment).
Participants randomised to the wailtlist condition will be assessed at four timepoints: Beginning of waitlist (3 months before intervention), pre-treatment, Week 13 (post-treatment), and follow-up (3 months after post-treatment assessment).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinically significant and self-reported meaningful change in quality of life, perceived social support, self-esteem, and spirituality (sense of meaning and purpose) as measured by focus group interview.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-intervention assessment (Week 13)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The inclusion criteria are not diagnosis-specific, such that people living with a broad range of mental illnesses can participate. Musical experience or ability is not necessary. 

Specific inclusion criteria: 1) a diagnosed severe and enduring mental illness (e.g., schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, major depression) that has been present for a least two years; 2) living independently in the community; 3) currently linked with a mental health professionial, case manager, or primary care physician; 3) ability to participate in a group for 1.5 hours.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Behavioural issues that may be disruptive to a group process. Inability to speak english or give informed consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment will occur via in-servicing and advertisement at mental health centres and through case managers. Potential participants will be assessed for suitability via screening interview and/or discussion with case manager. After participants give consent, baseline assessment will be undertaken by the research assistant (RA). Participants will then be individually randomised to either the treatment (music therapy) or control (waitlist) condition using central randomisation by email or computer. Participants, therapists, and the RA will all be aware of the treatment allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation using a computer generated sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Late in the trial small numbers of recruited participants could not be randomized to groups. Thus the design was amended to facilitate a non-randomized arm. These participants were assigned to Group Music Therapy, followed by standard care. Their data was collected at the same time points as the randomized participants.  </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Test power was calculated for the primary out- come. We expected a sample size of 120 to be real- istic to achieve and expected about 20% loss to follow-up, leading to an available sample size of 96. In line with previous systematic reviews, we expected a medium effect size (d = 0.50), but con- sidered that this effect size could be somewhat reduced due to clustering. In a two-sided paired t-test, the target sample size would still have 80% power if the effect size was as low as 0.29 (and near 100% for d = 0.50; calculated with R function power.t.test).
An independent statistician carried out all statistical analyses, using R version 3.0.1. All statistical tests were two-tailed with a 5% significance level. Baseline characteristics were compared between groups using Welch t-tests for continuous variables and Fishers exact tests for categorical variables.  Effects of GMT were evaluated based on paired t-tests comparing the change scores between conditions (i.e. the change during GMT vs. the change during SC; excluding the second SC period in those randomized to SC-GMT-SC). In addition, effect sizes (Cohens d) were calculated. Because the aim of the effect size calculations was to facilitate clinical interpretation, we divided mean differences as well as their confidence limits by baseline standard deviations. 
Effects were analyzed on an intention-to-treat basis in the main analysis. This means that all available data were analyzed, and no participants were excluded if they failed to attend sessions. Listwise deletion of missing values was used in the main analysis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/04/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>29/03/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>The Melbourne Clinic - Richmond</hospital>
    <hospital>Albert Road Clinic - Melbourne</hospital>
    <postcode>3022</postcode>
    <postcode>3123</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Parkville, 3010, Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council Discovery Projects</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1st Floor, 8 Brindabella Circuit
Brindabella Business Park
Canberra Airport ACT 2609</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>St Vincent's Mental Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>46 Nicholson St, Fitzroy, 3065</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Severe and enduring mental illness (SEMI) impacts detrimentally on the ability to work and form relationships, thus reducing quality of life. People with SEMI living in the community are particularly vulnerable. The importance of psychosocial interventions, in conjunction with medication, to improve quality of life or people with SEMI is increasingly being acknowledged. 

Music therapy is a recognised psychosocial intervention that can promote social support through musical and personal interaction. A recent Cochrane review analysed four outcome studies of music therapy and mental illness (Gold, Heldal, Dahle &amp; Wigram, 2005). Methods included active music making (mostly improvisation), and listening to music with discussion. A meta-analysis of results concluded that music therapy, when compared with standard care, improved global state, mental state and social functioning. 

The Songs for Life project aims to extend current knowledge about the benefits of music therapy for chronic psychiatric illness. The study will examine the effect of a music therapy intervention (involving singing, percussive improvisation and writing and recording an original song) on quality of life, self-esteem, social support, and sense of meaning and purpose in people with SEMI living in the community.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Grocke, D., Bloch, S., Castle, D. (2009). The effect of group music therapy on quality of life for participants living with a severe and enduring mental illness. Journal of Music Therapy; 46:90-104.

Grocke D, Bloch S, Castle D, Thompson G, Newton R, Stewart S, Gold C. Group music therapy for severe mental illness: a randomized embedded-experimental mixed methods study. Acta Psychiatr Scand 2013: 110. DOI: 10.1111/acps.12224
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health Sciences Human Ethics Sub-Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Melbourne Research Office
The University of Melbourne
Victoria, 3010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/02/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0722802</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Health and Research Ethics Committee-A</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>27 Victoria Pde, Fitzroy, 3065, Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/09/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Prof Denise Grocke</name>
      <address>Melbourne Conservatorium of Music
151 Barry Street
University of Melbourne 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83445259</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.grocke@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Denise Grocke</name>
      <address>Melbourne Conservatorium of Music
151 Barry Street
University of Melbourne 3010</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 8344 5259</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.grocke@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Denise Grocke</name>
      <address>University of Melbourne
Victoria, 3010</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 8344 5259</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.grocke@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Denise Grocke</name>
      <address>Melbourne Conservatorium of Music
151 Barry Street
University of Melbourne 3010</address>
      <phone>+61-3-8344-5259</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.grocke@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>