<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335450">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/05/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000376044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Contribution of the level of protein load and duration, to the effects of small intestinal protein, on gut motility, gut hormone release and sensations of appetite.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Contribution of the level of protein load and duration, to the effects of intraduodenal protein, on antropyloroduodenal motility, gut hormone release and sensations of appetite in lean and obese males.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A single 60 minute intraduodenal infusion at 4mL/min of: 
a) 0 kcal/min (control of saline solution ) 
b) 0.5 kcal/min (Whey Protein Hydrolysate) 
c) 1.5 kcal/min (Whey Protein Hydrolysate) 
d) 3.0 kcal/min (Whey Protein Hydrolysate)

Appetite sensation questionnaires in the form of a Visual Analogue Scale (VAS), blood samples. 

A buffet meal will be provided at the end of infusion and the participant has 30 minutes to eat until comfortably full. The buffet meal consists of 300ml orange juice, 600ml water, 375ml iced coffee, 4 slices white bread, 4 slices brown bread, 100g deli leg ham, 100g virginian chicken, 4 slices cheese, 100g tomato, 100g cucumber, 100g lettuce, 2 portions mayonnaise, 2 portions margarine, 1 medium apple, 1 medium banana, 200g chocolate custard, 150g fruit salad, 200g strawberry yoghurt, and a 14g milky way chocolate bar. 

Each volunteer will receive one of each infusion solutions on each of the 4 study days. Each study visit will be separated by no less than 3 days. Each study visit will last approximately 3-6 hours.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo: A single, 60 minute, 0kcal/min intaduodenal infusion of saline solution.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Appetite sensations using a Visual Analogue Scale (VAS) (satiety, hunger, fullness, thirst, desire to eat and amount of food desired to eat)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intubation occurs on subject arrival.
 
At t= -10 until 0, a baseline of the gastrointestinal (GI) tract motility is recorded. 

Infusion starts at t= 0 until 60 minutes.

Extubation and buffet meal presented at 60 minutes and subject allowed to consume freely, until comfortably full, for 30 minutes (until t= 90).

Blood samples and VAS questionnaire are taken at t= -10, 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, &amp; 90 minutes.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gut Hormone release: cholecyctokinin (CCK), glucagon-like peptide-1 (GLP-1), peptide YY (PYY), and Ghrelin.

Gut hormone release will be assessed by Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELIZA) from the blood samples taken.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intubation occurs on subject arrival.
 
At t= -10 until 0, a baseline of GI tract motility is recorded. 

Infusion starts at t= 0 until 60 minutes.

Extubation and buffet meal presented at 60 minutes and subject allowed to consume freely, until comfortably full, for 30 minutes (until t= 90).

Blood samples and VAS questionnaire are taken at t= -10, 0, 15, 30, 45, 60, &amp; 90 minutes.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Antropyloroduodenal Motility (antropyloroduodenal pressures, number of antral, duodenal and isolated pyloric pressure waves, and basal pyloric pressure) assessed by Manometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From intubation until 60 minutes end of infusion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Macronutrient and total energy intake at the buffet meal will be analysed using the FoodWorks software program.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Buffet meal will be presented at 60 minutes when the infusion ends and the subject will be allowed to freely consume food until comfortably full for 30 minutes (until t=90 minutes).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>non-obese with a Body Mass Index (BMI) of 18-25kg/m2 and obese with a BMI of 27-35kg/m2

Weight stable (&lt;5% fluctuation in body weight in previous 3 months)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Significant gastrointestinal symptoms, disease or surgery. Use of prescribed or non-prescribed medications (including vitamins and herbal suppliments) which may effect energy metabolism, gastrointestinal function, body weight or appetite (eg domperidone and cisapride, anticholinergic drugs (eg atropine), metoclopramide, erythromycin, hyoscine, orlistat, green tea extracts, astragalus, St Johns Wort etc)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Volunteers are asked to visit the clinic for a 30 minute screening visit. A questionnaire is answered by the volunteer, based on the inclusion/exclusion criteria and eligibilty is determined. A signed informed consent form is obtained and study dates are established. Eligible volunteers are assigned a subject number and randomised into a treatment for each study visit, using a randomisation table which was created on an excel spreadsheet. Randomisation involved contacting the holder (study assistant) of the randomisation table to inform them of the next subject's details and study dates. The unblinded study assistant is therefore responsible for allocating a random treatment to the subject and preparing the solution on each study day.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation table was generated using Microsoft Office Excel.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/01/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>5000</postcode>
    <postcode>5043</postcode>
    <postcode>5061</postcode>
    <postcode>5038</postcode>
    <postcode>5037</postcode>
    <postcode>5045</postcode>
    <postcode>5008</postcode>
    <postcode>5006</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Natalie Luscombe-Marsh</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6 Eleanor Harrald Building,
Frome Road, 
Adelaide, South Australia 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1 16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Adelaide</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>North Terrace
Adelaide, SA 5005</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study has been designed to investigate how the load and duration of Whey Protein Hydrolysate effects gut motility, gut hormones, and appetite sensations. 

Volunteers are required to visit the clinic on 4 occassions no less than 3 days apart. Visits will last for approximately 5 hours. 

A long felxible tube will be inserted through an anaethetised nostril and passed through into the small intestine to monitor stomach and small intestinal contractions. Through this tube, a whey protein or saline solution will be infused over a 60 minute period (4mL/min). Blood samples will be taken (through a cannula, which is a long flexible tube inserted into a vein) and questionnaires on appetite sensations will be completed every 15 minutes. 

At the end of the 60 minute infusion, a buffet meal will be provided. This meal will be consumed over 30 minutes until the volunteer is comfortably full.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, Hanson Institute, North Terrace,
Adelaide, South Australia, 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/01/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>081012e</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/10/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Natalie Luscombe-Marsh</name>
      <address>Level 6 Eleanor Harrald Building,
Frome Road,
Adelaide, South Australia 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5038</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.luscombe@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Natalie Luscombe-Marsh</name>
      <address>Level 6 Eleanor Harrald Building,
Frome Road,
Adelaide, South Australia 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5038</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>natalie.luscombe@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Penelope Fitzgerald</name>
      <address>Level 6 Eleanor Harrald Building,
Frome Road,
Adelaide, South Australia 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 4130</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>penelope.fitzgerald@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>