<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82037">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/05/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/06/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000323426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of fish oil containing eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) on weight loss and cachexia in pancreatic cancer patients undergoing cancer chemotherapy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of fish oil containing eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) on weight loss and cachexia in pancreatic cancer patients undergoing cancer chemotherapy.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Weight loss.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cachexia.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pancreatic cancer chemotherapy.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Changes in body composition.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pancreatic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a double-blind, randomised, placebo controlled clinical trial. All patients will be receiving the same standard chemotherapy regimen of Gemcitabine (1000mg/m2 iv D1, 8, 15, Q4 weekly). Treatment/placebo administration will be carried out during the first 16 weeks of the chemotherapy.
Body composition measurements, anthropometry and QL measurements will be carried out prior to chemotherapy and then at 4, 8, 12 and 16 weeks post-chemotherapy.</interventions>
    <comparator>EPA (2.7g/day) / placebo will be given orally as soft gel capsules for 16 weeks commencing on the first day of chemotherapy.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective of the trial is to assess the changes in body composition and the effects of EPA in pancreatic cancer patients undergoing cancer chemotherapy. It is hypothesised that the EPA will reduce weight loss and cachexia in this group of patients. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Body composition measurements will be carried out at 0 (baseline), 4, 8, 12, and 16 weeks post-chemotherapy to assess any changes in weight and the components of weight (ie fat, water, and protein).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The daily administration of EPA may also have possible improvement in Quality of Life and survival.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The quality of life is assessed using the EORTC QLQ-C30 and PAN-26 quality of life questionnaires at 0 (base-line), 4, 8, 12, and 16 weeks post-chemotherapy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The daily administration of EPA may reduce chemotherapy-induced toxicities.</outcome>
      <timepoint> Similarly, the chemotherapy induced toxicity (white blood cell and neutrophil counts) will be measured at 0 (base-line), 4, 8, 12, and 16 weeks post-chemotherapy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.Patients with a pathologic diagnosis of pancreas cancer that is locally advanced and unresectable, partially resected or metastatic;2.Signed informed consent.3.Patients with the ability to understand the nature of the project and to provide informed consent;4.Patients with ECOG performance status of less than or equal to 2, as determined by the referring physician;5.Patients who are greater than 4 weeks post-operative or post radiotherapy.6.Adequate haematologic and biochemical functioning, including liver function tests, permitting suitability for Gemcitabine chemotherapy.7.Life expectancy of 12 weeks.8.Ability to complete the scheduled body composition measures.9.Ability to complete the QL questionnaire.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Patients who have received and/or are receiving chemotherapy for pancreatic cancer;2.Progressing or untreated brain metastases.3.Pregnant and lactating women;4.Serious intercurrent medical illness or psychological, familial, sociological, geographical, or other concomitant conditions that do not permit adequate follow-up and compliance with the study protocol.5.Participation in clinical trials of other experimental agents within 30 days of study entry.6.Pregnant or lactating women or women of childbearing potential not using effective contraception.7.Radiotherapy within 4 weeks.8.Surgery within 6 weeks.Both male and female patients will be recruited for this trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation will take place centrally at Royal North Shore Hospital's Department of Medical Oncology by computer at a 1:1 ratio to receive Gemcitabine alone (plus placebo) or combined with EPA. Eligible patients will be stratified at inclusion according to age (&gt;=70 and &lt;70 years), ECOG performance status (0,1,2), and locally advanced or metastatic. After having checked the patient’s eligibility criteria, the investigators will request patient randomisation by phone or fax.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomisation logs will be used for each stratum. Patients will be allocated to his/her stratum and will be randomly assigned to the therapeutic arm according to the next consecutive number in the stratum log.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The patients, all investigators, and all staff (medical and non-medical) looking after the patients are blinded to the trial. Only the oncology data manger randomising the patients and the pharmacist dispensing the capsules are not blinded in this trial.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/08/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>35</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Ross C Smith</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>CanSur Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mr A Aslani</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Fish oils containing eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA) have been shown to prevent and reverse cancer-induced weight loss and cachexia by maintaining lean body mass. However, there have not been direct measurements of the components of weight loss nor the changes in body composition during and after the reversal. In addition, the reversal of weight loss and cachexia has not been investigated in patients with pancreatic cancer during chemotherapy. The RNS Hospital has the unique facilities to be able to directly, accurately and non-invasively measure these changes. We believe that the positive effects of EPA during chemotherapy will reduce weight loss, improve the quality of life as well as reducing chemotherapy-induced toxicities.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal North Shore Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/06/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0303-067M</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Ross C Smith</name>
      <address>Suite 5
Level 5
North Shore Private Hospital
Westbourne Street
St Leonards NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>02-84253554</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rsmith@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Ross C Smith</name>
      <address>Suite 5, Level 5
North Shore Private Hospital
Westbourne Street
St Leonards, NSW 2065</address>
      <phone>02-84253554</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rsmith@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>