<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82896">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/06/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/07/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000314325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The analgesic efficacy of ultrasound guided transversus abdominis plane (TAP) block after laparascopic appendicectomy in children: a prospective randomised trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The analgesic efficacy of ultrasound guided transversus abdominis plane (TAP) block after laparascopic appendicectomy in children: a prospective randomised trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Post-operative pain after laparscopic appendicectomy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients will receive a standardised general anaesthetic. This will involve a rapid sequence induction with propofol (3 mg/kg) by an intravenous injection and suxamethonium (1.5-2 mg/kg) by an intravenous injection and continued paralysis with atracurium (initially 0.5 mg/kg intravenous followed by 0.2 mg/kg intravenous at approximately 30 minute intervals).  Anaesthesia will be further maintained with nitrous oxide 70 % in O2 and sevoflurane (titrated to effect). All patients will receive intravenous (IV) fentanyl (1 mcg/kg) at the commencement of surgery and ondansetron (200 mcg/kg) to a maximum of 4 mg IV towards the end of the procedure. Standard monitoring including electrocardiogram, non-invasive arterial blood pressure, arterial oxygen saturation and end tidal carbon dioxide monitoring will be used throughout. The surgical technique will also be standardised.  All patients will have laparoscopy port sites infiltrated by the surgeons as per routine practice with 0.5 ml/kg of 0.2% Ropivacaine (1 mg/kg total ropivacaine).

Technique for Ultrasound guided TAP block.
Laparascopic appendicectomy requires that the TAP block be placed bilaterally.  A 38 mm linear array Ultrasound probe transducer (Sonosite Micromaxx (Registered)  SonoSite, Inc. 21919 30th Drive SE Bothell, WA) is placed in either flank with the probe orientated on a line joining the umbilicus and the 3rd / 4th lumbar vertebrae.  A needle is advanced under aseptic conditions from an injection point on the antero-lateral abdominal wall, at about the level of the umbilicus, in the plane of the ultrasound.  The needle is advanced until the tip lies between the transversus abdominus and the internal oblique muscles. A total of 1 ml/kg of 0.2% ropivacaine (2 mg/kg total ropivacaine) is drawn up. Half of this volume is injected on the left hand side and the other half on the Right hand side.  A remaining 0.5 ml/kg or 0.2 % ropivacaine (1 mg/kg total ropivacaine) will be available to the surgeons for infiltration of port sites.

Total dose of ropivacaine will be restricted to 3 mg / kg in according with published dose recommendations.  
  

Post-operatively each patient will be prescribed intravenous Patient Controlled analgesia with morphine as per the Sydney Childrens Hospital protocol and regular paracetamol 15 mg/kg Per Orum every 4 hours.  The Sydney Children's Hospital protocol is to draw up 750 microg / kg of morphine into a 50 ml syringe and dilute to 50 ml with normal saline.  The patient will be prescribed 1 ml intravenous boluses as required with a machine lockout period of 5 minutes.  This will mean that each bolus of intravenous morphine will be 15 microg/kg. There must be no background infusion on the Patient controlled analgesia (PCA). No other analgesics are to be prescribed during the first 16 hours post-operatively unless commenced by the Acute Pain Service.  Patients must also be prescribed post-operatively ondansetron 200 microg/kg intravenous (to a maximum of 4 mg) every 8 hours when necessary.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard care (Standard General anaesthesia with no TAP block).  No placebo</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome: Reduced PCA morphine consumption in the first 16 hours from the completion of anaesthesia.</outcome>
      <timepoint>First 16 hours post-operative.  PCA morphine consumption will be considered for both the first 8 hours from the completion of anaesthesia, the second 8 hours and the total morphine consumption in the firsts 16 hours from the completion of anaesthesia</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increased time to first supplemental analgesia from the completion of anaesthesia</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time at which any form of analgesia is administered after the completion of anaesthesia</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced PCA morphine consumption in the first 8 hours after the completion of anaesthesia</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of anaesthesia to 8 hours after the end of anaesthesia</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced morphine PCA consumption from 8 hours after the completion of anaesthesia to 16 hours after the completion of anaesthesia</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 hours from completion of anaesthesia to 16 hours after the completion of anaesthesia</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increased time from the completion of anaesthesia to the first dose of PCA morphine</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of first PCA button push</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced Pain measured by Visual analogue scale at 6 to 8 hours after the completion of anaesthesia</outcome>
      <timepoint>VAS at 6 to 8 hours after the completion of anaesthesia</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced Pain measured by Visual analogue scale at 10 to 12 hours after the completion of anaesthesia</outcome>
      <timepoint>VAS at 10 to 12 hours after the completion of anaesthesia</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced time to Hospital discharge</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from completion of anaesthesia to time of discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced Pain in the recovery ward measured by VAS at the time of recovery ward discharge</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of recovery ward discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced sedation scores at the time of recovery ward discharge</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of recovery ward discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced Postoperative vomiting and nausea measured by number of antiemtic administrations in the first 16 hours following completion of anaesthesia</outcome>
      <timepoint>From completion of anaesthesia to 16 hours after the completion of anaesthesia</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Any consented patient aged 7-16 years who is scheduled for laparoscopic appendicectomy.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The study exclusion criteria will include intolerance to morphine, unavailability of a Approved Healthcare interpreter in patients with a poor grasp of English, an inability to use a PCA device or the need to convert from laparascopic to open procedure.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Consent as per the inclusion and exclusion criteria and allocated by independent investigator:  Participants will be enrolled into the study and then randomised using a central computer generated sequence.  The randomisation code will be generated and kept by an identified randomisation officer who will be contacted prior to each individual case by the procedural anaesthetist in order to provide an instruction concerning allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be achieved using an online, computer generated sequence (http://www.randomizer.org/index.htm).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Bandaids placed on injection and potential injection points for both arms of the study</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/06/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/07/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>16/12/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr David Sandeman</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Anaesthesia, Sydney Children's Hospital, High St Randwick NSW 2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sydney Children's Hospital Department of Anaesthesia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Dept Anaesthesia, Sydney Children's Hospital, High St Randwick NSW 2031</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Anthony Dilley</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Dept Surgery:  Sydney Children's Hospital, High St Randwick NSW 2031</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Adam Perzcuk</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Dept Anaesthesia, Sydney Children's Hospital, Avoca St Randwick NSW 2031</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Assoc Prof Michael Bennett</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Hyperbaric Medicine
Prince Of Wales Hospital 
Randwick NSW 2034</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Siv Ein Lim</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Anaesthesia
Prince Of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2034</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Keith Kelly</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Anaesthesia
Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2034</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Safe and effective regional anaesthesia requires local anaesthetics to be placed in close proximity to nerves without injury to the target nerves or adjacent structures. A promising approach to the provision of postoperative analgesia after abdominal surgery is to block the sensory nerve supply to the anterior abdominal wall. Ultrasound guidance allows accurate identification of target tissue planes whilst avoiding adjacent structures.  Ultrasound guidance also allows spread of local anaesthetic to be monitored in real time during the injection.  We therefore anticipate improved safety and efficacy when utilising ultrasound guided TAP block when compared to standard care.

Standard care for laparascopic appendicectomy involves general anaesthesia and endotracheal intubation, intravenous opiate and local anaesthetic infiltration of laparascopic port sites by the surgeon.  In this study we will add to standard care bilateral ultrasound guided TAP block.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney and Illawarra Area Health service Northern Sector</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Prince of Wales Hospital, High St Randwick NSW 2031 Australia (phone 9382 3587, fax 9382 2813</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/06/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/002</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/12/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr David Sandeman</name>
      <address>29 Oxley St Matraville 2036 NSW</address>
      <phone>0416161046</phone>
      <fax>0296611203</fax>
      <email>david.sandeman@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr David Sandeman</name>
      <address>49 Oxley St Matraville NSW</address>
      <phone>0416161046</phone>
      <fax>0296611203</fax>
      <email>david.sandeman@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr David Sandeman</name>
      <address>49 Oxley st Matraville 2036 NSW</address>
      <phone>0416161046</phone>
      <fax>0296611203</fax>
      <email>david.sandeman@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr David Sandeman</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia 
Sydney Children's Hospital
High St
Randwick NSW 2031
Australia</address>
      <phone>0416161046</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.sandeman@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>