<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335663">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/06/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000531011</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of local anaesthetic type on injection-related pain levels intra and post operatively</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients undergoing bilateral hallux blocks for partial nail avulsion, is mepivacaine a more effective local anaesthetic than lignocaine for reducing injection-related pain levels.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>N/A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Partial Nail Avulsion</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A total of 2ml of 3% mepivacaine plain will be injected in the hallux (with 5ml syringe and a .25 gauge, 25mm in length) prior to the partial nail avulsion procedure.  The subject will receive 1ml of mepivacaine into the soft tissue on the lateral (1st injection) and medial (2nd injection) aspects of the proximal phalanx.  The partial nail avulsion will only be performed once the anaesthetic has taken effect.  If anaesthesia has not been achieved then a top up injection will be performed.

The allocation of which hallux, right or left that receives lignocaine or mepivacaine will be randomised.

Immediately after the injections into the medal and lateral aspects of the toe the subject will complete a visual analogue pain scale, if further injections are required then the visual analogue scale will be completed after the first (lateral aspect) and second injection (medial aspect).   Crossover will be achieved by the randomly selected hallux will receive lignocaine or mepivacaine and the opposite hallux will be injected immediately after the subject has completed the visual analogue scale.</interventions>
    <comparator>A total of 2ml of 2% lignocaine plain will be injected in the hallux (with 5ml syringe and a .25 gauge, 25mm in length) prior to the partial nail avulsion  procedure.  The subject will receive 1ml of lignocaine into the soft tissue on the lateral (1st injection) and medial (2nd injection) aspects of the proximal phalanx.  The partial nail avulsion will only be performed once the anaesthetic has taken effect.  If anaesthesia has not been achieved then a top up injection will be performed.

The allocation of which hallux, right or left that receives lignocaine or mepivacaine will be randomised.

Immediately after the injections the subject will complete a visual analogue pain scale.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain measured by Visual Analogue Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after each toe has been injected</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain measured by Visual Analogue Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>24 hours after the time of the injections</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients eligible for and undergoing bilateral hallux partial nail avultion surgery (in accordance with the University of Newcastle  Podiatry criteria)

Minimum weight of 70kg

Able to safely receive the local anaesthetic agents used (in accordance with the University of Newcastle Podiatry criteria)

Over 18 yrs of age

Proficient in English to give Informed Consent and follow post-operative care instructions</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Proficient in English to give Informed Consent and follow post-operative care instructions

Patients not meeting the inclusion criteria

Patients with medical conditions which contraindicate local anaesthetic use

Patients on medications which contraindicate local anaesthetic use

Patients with a known allergy to amide-type local anaesthetics</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A convenience sample will be identified by student practitioners and supervisors working at the podiaty clinic, suitably identified participants will then be assessed by Ms Eleanor Turvey for their inclusion in the study.

This is a double blinded clinical trial, with blinding of both the patient and the administrating practitioner to the anaesthetic type. The blinding will occur through use of equal amounts of both anaesthetics (2ml’s) and the administration of the local anaesthetic in needles and syringes of the same size (.25 gauge and 5ml respectively). Each syringe will be labeled A or B, according to its contents, by the data collector who will be independent of the practitioner to track which anaesthetic is used for each toe and which VAS refers to which anaesthetic type.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation of which toe left or right will recieve lignocaine or mepivacaine.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/08/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mr Priten Solanki</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Podiatry 
Faculty of Health 
School of Health Sciences
PO Box 127
Ourimbah
New South Wales 2258</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Newcastle</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Podiatry 
Faculty of Health 
School of Health Sciences
PO Box 127
Ourimbah
New South Wales 2258</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Vivienne Chuter</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Podiatry 
Faculty of Health 
School of Health Sciences
PO Box 127
Ourimbah
New South Wales 2258</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A double blind trial designed to assess the pain associated with the injection of lignocaine (Xylocaine) and mepivacaine (Scandonest) two local anaesthetics commonly used in podiatric practice.  So, is mepiviacaine a less painful anaesthetic to be injected into a toe than lignocaine.

Subjects will be selected from the University of Newcastle Podiatry Clinic, the subjects have been selected would require nail surgery of both big toes.  The practitioner and the subject will be blinded to which anaesthetic has been used in each of the toes.  After each injection the subject will be asked to complete a visual analog pain scale.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Priten Solanki</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
Faculty of Health 
School of Health Sciences
PO Box 127
Ourimbah
New South Wales 2258</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4349 4655</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4349 4538</fax>
      <email>priten.solanki@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Priten Solanki</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
Faculty of Health 
School of Health Sciences
PO Box 127
Ourimbah
New South Wales 2258</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4349 4655</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4349 4538</fax>
      <email>priten.solanki@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>