<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368261">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000717550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study to evaluate the safety and tolerability of RepaiRx in donor site healing</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can deer antler extract improve tissue healing of a skin graft donor site?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>UTN1111-1166-5084</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Wound healing</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Burns</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>RepaiRx (10ml or 5ml, depending on the donor site size) will be applied as a gel. It is spread directly onto the surface of the wound using a sterile flat-bladed instrument by the burns surgeon in the operating theatre. RepaiRx is applied as a thick gel to one of the donor sites as per the randomisation code and covered with Mepitel film. It is expected that this will remain in place until removed for Day 4 assessments; if needed additional external bandaging can be applied to hold the study dressings in place. After that the site normal management of donor site wounds will be applied.

RepaiRx is a biological product reproducibly produced via controlled extraction of New Zealand red deer velvet antler using the proprietary process developed by VARNZ.It is a complex biological mixture of peptides/polypeptides (these predominantly having molecular weights less than 10 kDa), 9.1% W/W amino acids, mineral salts and other water-soluble components of deer velvet tissue. The exact nature of the active ingredients is thus not well defined.</interventions>
    <comparator>The same volume of Control (carrier medium minus RepaiRx) will be applied to the remaining donor site as per the randomisation directive. The carrier medium is a gel containing Poloxamer 407, which is marketed by BASF under the  trade name Kolliphor P 407 (formerly Lutrol F 127) (CAS No. 9003-11-6).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective is to assess the safety and tolerability of RepaiRx in terms of the nature, relatedness, severity and incidence of adverse events reported in the course of the study. This is the first in man study of RepaiRx so the possible adverse events are not known but may include allergic reactions and wound infections. </outcome>
      <timepoint>From Screening and at each site visit to Month 6 (i.e. Days 0, 4, 5, 7, 10, 14, 28 and Months 3 and 6). Participants will be asked if they have experienced any adverse effects at each study visit. The patients will have physical exams and the wounds will be examined for signs of infection. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Donor site evidence of infection, as assessed by a masked sub-investigator, requiring antibiotic treatment </outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 4, 5, 7, 10, 14 and 28, and at Months 3 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trans-Epidermal Water Loss (TEWL) measurements using a specialised TEWL machine (DermaLab Series, SkinLab Combo).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 4, 5, 7, 10, 14 and 28, and at Months 3 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Donor site appearance to be estimated visually (1) in situ by a masked sub-investigator and (2) by a masked independent assessor's sight of photographs: Healing assessments - VAS of wound healing </outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 4, 5, 7, 10, 14 and 28, and at Months 3 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Scar assessment using POSAS [Patient and Observer Scar Assessment Scale" for POSAS] (i.e. by participants and by a masked sub-investigator)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28, at 3 and 6 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Donor site appearance to be estimated visually (1) in situ by a masked sub-investigator and (2) by a masked independent assessor's sight of photographs - VAS of colour match and pigment match
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 4, 5, 7, 10, 14 and 28, and at Months 3 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Donor site appearance to be estimated visually (1) in situ by a masked sub-investigator and (2) by a masked independent assessor's sight of photographs: Opinion of which site is better healed</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 4, 5, 7, 10, 14 and 28, and at Months 3 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Donor site appearance to be estimated visually by a masked sub-investigator and by masked independent assessor using photographs: Healing assessments - level of healing and blistering by choosing one of 4 options listed for each of the two donor sites</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 4, 5, 7, 10, 14 and 28, and at Months 3 and 6</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Males and females aged at least 18 years requiring split thickness skin grafts for reasons of burn therapy, trauma or scar revision. The area requiring skin grafting is to be greater than or equal to 1% and no more than 20% of the total body surface area. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pre-existing infection or condition or taking medication that may interfere with wound healing; airway burn; renal failure requiring dialysis; participation in other clinical trial/s; known allergy to deer products, poloxamer gel or mepitel film;history of skin disorders</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After obtaining consent and confirming eligibility, the participant will be enrolled in the study. Randomisation will occur prior to administration of Investigational Product (IP) on Day 0. As two donor sites will be demarcated on each participant, the participant acts as their own control.  Randomisation of the IP application to the donor sites (A and B) will be generated by the study statistician who will provide an individual randomisation envelope for each participant randomisation number. The randomisation envelope will be opened by the pharmacy delegate preparing the IPs just prior to surgery. The surgeon will be unmasked when applying the IPs and should usually be the clinician to manage any safety issues that may emerge. The Sub-Investigators will remain masked and will not have access to randomisation information; they will conduct the study assessments. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization by computer </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>As two donor sites will be demarcated on each participant, the participant will have RepaiRx applied to one site and control to the other site. Therefore each participant acts as their own control.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Standard descriptive statistics including means, standard deviations, ranges, frequencies and percentages will be used to summarise participant demographic and presentation data including age, gender, ethnicity, vital signs, physical examination, biochemistry, haematology, urine dipstick, aetiology, area and location of treatment site location and area of donor site, presence of infection in donor site and concomitant medication. 
All serious and non-serious adverse events will be listed and tabulated separately for the randomised treatments when appropriate, according to preferred terms, relatedness and severity classifications. 
Standard descriptive statistics will be used to summarise the healing rate measures by randomised treatment. This will include means, medians, standard deviation and ranges for continuous measures and frequencies and percentages for categorical measures.

Randomised treatments will be compared using paired t-tests at the different assessment times and summaries of mean differences and 95% confidence intervals presented. If data are not adequately normal then comparisons will be made using non-parametric Wilcoxon signed rank tests. Categorical outcomes will be compared using McNemars chi-square tests. A two-tailed p-value &lt;0.05 will be used to indicate statistical significance. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/07/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>23/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>1</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>20/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/07/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Other reasons/comments</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother>This study was terminated by the Sponsor, taking into account both the pain experienced by the first participant in undergoing wound healing assessment using the TEWL machine (despite pain management), and the low probability of recruiting around 20 participants in the next twelve months even were this assessment removed from the protocol.</withdrawnreasonother>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>VARNZ Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>c/- Deer Industry New Zealand
P.O Box 10-702
Wellington 6143
New Zealand
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>VARNZ Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>c/- Deer Industry New Zealand
P.O Box 10-702
Wellington 6143
New Zealand
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a prospective, randomised, comparative, controlled pilot study of RepaiRx and Control. It will evaluate the safety, tolerability and effects on wounds, with each participant acting as their own control.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Freyburg Building, 20 Aitken Street, PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTX/12/05/039</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Amber Moazzam</name>
      <address>Consultant Plastic Surgeon
National Burn Centre
Middlemore Hospital
100 Hospital Road, 
Otahuhu, 
Auckland 2025

</address>
      <phone>+64 9 276 0044, Ext 7825</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Amber.Moazzam@middlemore.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Catharine Sayer</name>
      <address>c/o Deer Industry New Zealand
PO Box 10702
Wellington 6143
</address>
      <phone>+64 4 471 6116</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 472 5549</fax>
      <email>catharine.sayer@deernz.org</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Catharine Sayer</name>
      <address>c/o Deer Industry New Zealand
PO Box 10702
Wellington 6143
</address>
      <phone>+64 4 471 6116</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 472 5549</fax>
      <email>catharine.sayer@deernz.org</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Lockhart</name>
      <address>Pharmaceuticol Ltd
51 Woodside Road, 
Mt Eden, 
Auckland 1024, </address>
      <phone>+64 21 665 947</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 623 6639</fax>
      <email>michellelockhart@xtra.co.nz </email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>