<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369490">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001243505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effectiveness of Nutrition Education for Overweight/Obese Mother with Stunted Children (NEO-MOM) in reducing double burden of malnutrition</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effectiveness of Nutrition Education for Overweight/Obese Mother with Stunted Children (NEO-MOM) in reducing double burden of malnutrition</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1175-5834</utrn>
    <trialacronym>NEO-MOM Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Maternal Overweight</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Maternal Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Child Stunting</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Double Burden of Malnutrition</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>NEO-MOM project is a randomized controlled trial research with 3 months behavior intervention towards households with stunted children and overweight/obese mother (SCOWT). The intervention in NEO-MOM project will consist of combination of 6 sessions Nutrition Education and 6 sessions of motivational interviewing through home visit. The sessions will be conducted in biweekly basis or every two weeks or twice a months. The 6 nutrition intervention sessions will be administered alternatively with home visit (motivational interviewing session) throughout the intervention period. In total, the intervention will span 3 months. The approximate duration of each nutrition education session is 100 minutes consist of 50 minutes class session followed by 50 minutes hands-on experience. The motivational interviewing session approximately lasted for 1 hour. The nutrition education class will be administered by 3 co-researchers in Indonesia. They are faculty members of Department of Nutrition, Universitas Airlangga with expertise in nutrition and behavioral change intervention. All of them hold master degree in public health or community nutrition. The hands-on experience session will be delivered by 2 trained research assistants that holds bachelor degree in public health nutrition. The motivational interviewing session (through home visit) will be delivered by trained community health worker that live in participants living area. The sessions are administered to mothers only. The general content of the 6 sessions nutrition educations are: session 1) 50 minutes nutrition education class on the introduction on the double burden of malnutrition, especially consequences and management of overweight/obesity and child stunting. The session followed by 20 minutes dance session and 30 minutes hands-on experience on making goal setting to improve physical activity (as in daily steps), fruit and vegetable intake for mother and serving animal protein for their children; 2) 50 minutes nutrition education class on healthy grocery shopping followed by 20 minutes dance session and 30 minutes mocked grocery shopping. 3) 50 minutes nutrition education class on Indonesian balance diet and Indonesian version of MyPlate followed by 20 minutes dance session and 30 minutes menu making for under five year old children with emphasize of including animal protein (chicken liver, catfish or egg). 4) 30 minutes nutrition education class on healthy cooking method followed by 20 minutes dance session and 60 minutes cooking demonstration; 5) 50 minutes nutrition education class on Child feeding practice with emphasize of responsive feeding followed by 20 minutes dance session and 30 minutes role play and jingle/song making related to combating child stunting. 6) 50 minutes FGD on how to overcome barriers towards child feeding practice followed by 20 minutes dance session and 30 minutes creation of pledge and strategies to tackle stunted child and overweight/obese mother (SCOWT) from mothers own perspective. The motivational interviewing delivered through home visit (6 times throughout the study administered in alternate week from nutrition education class and hands-on activity session) will focus on providing verbal motivation for mothers to achieve their biweekly goal setting (consist of: improving daily steps, fruit and vegetables intake, and serving child with animal protein), and help them with strategies to overcome barriers. To monitor adherence to the intervention we will make a log of nutrition education sessions including attendance list filled by our research assistants, form of biweekly goal settings filled by mothers at the end of class and hands-on activity sessions. Through collaboration with local grocery store, we will monitor maternal grocery purchase from the recorded grocery voucher that we gave to the mothers each time they attend our class and hands-on session. In addition, to monitor adherence towards physical activity improvement we will monitor maternal daily steps using pedometer during home visit and record it into the log for each participants.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will be an active control where they receive regular care for malnourished children by Indonesian government through sub-district health center ("puskesmas"). In addition both control and intervention group will receive 6 sets of educational materials in the form of booklets that describe strategies to improve the health of stunted children as well as overweight mothers align with the construct of social cognitive theory (SCT)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of child stunting as measured by height for age z-score (HAZ) using the 2005 WHO reference</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of maternal overweight and obesity as measured by Body Mass Index (BMI) of the mother</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3, 6, and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of Stunted Child and Overweight/Obese Mother (SCOWT) as measure by child's HAZ and maternal BMI</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal self-efficacy for eating fruit and vegetables as measured using 28 items questionnaire with Likert scale answer. It was designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal self-efficacy for feeding their child with animal protein as measured using 25 items questionnaire with Likert scale answer. It was designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3, 6, and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal physical activity as estimated from daily steps count measured using YanMax Digiwalker Pedometer SW200 (Tokyo, Japan).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement. At each time point the pedometer is worn for 3 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal outcome expectation as assessed using 30 items questionnaire with Likert scale answer. It was designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal dietary intake as assessed using repeated 24 hours dietary food recall</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal Dietary Diversity as assessed using 16 food groups of Household Dietary Diversity SCore (HDDS) categorization from FAO</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal Nutrition Literacy as assessed 28 items questionnaire. It was designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The inclusion criteria are: fluent in conventional Bahasa Indonesia, permanent resident and planning to stay in Surabaya City for at least 6 months, having stunted under five years old child, and being overweight/obese. In addition, the child has to be registered in the community health post (posyandu) and receiving complementary feeding program form Indonesian government. The minimum age of the child is 2 years or 24 months at the time of enrollment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The exclusion criteria are: either the mother or the child have physical disability, mother participate in a weight loss program or deliberately fasting due to spiritual deed and if child is diagnosed with serious medical problems.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization using a randomization table created by computer software (excel 2013)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To analyze the difference in the outcome from control and intervention group, the test of ANOVA was used. This statistical analysis was adjusted for possible confounding such as maternal characteristics, SES and household characteristics. All data analysis performed in IBM SPSS Statistics 22. The power calculation of our main outcome variables is based on the previous RCT in Bangladesh with similar 3 months length and twice a month intensive nutrition education intervention along with complementary feeding on childs height gain (Roy et al. 2005). Even though our study did not directly provide complementary feeding, it is one of our inclusion criteria that participant in our study must receive complementary feeding program from the government of Indonesia. The effect size of provision of complementary food and intensive nutrition education on height gain (cm) in Bangladesh was 0.80 (95%CI=0.007-1.53). We select this fairly large effect size of 0.8 expressed as mean difference in childs height, which translates to an ability to detect a difference between two groups of 0.80 cm childs height at 3 months follow-up. Our study has a 90% power to detect changes that may be modest at the individual level, but would have an important impact if occurring at the population level. Minimum total sample size of 66 is needed to detect these differences in our primary hypothesis, with two tailed alpha of 0.05. Assuming dropout rate of 3%, the total sample size of 68 will be required (34 in intervention group and 34 in control group/usual care).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>26/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>16/11/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>68</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <state>East Java</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Trias Mahmudiono</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Nutrition, 
Faculty of Public Health, Universitas Airlangga
Jl. Mulyorejo Kampus C Surabaya - INDONESIA 60115

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Indonesia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Trias Mahmudiono</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Nutrition, 
Faculty of Public Health, Universitas Airlangga
Jl. Mulyorejo Kampus C Surabaya - INDONESIA 60115
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Indonesia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Richard Rosenkranz</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Human Nutrition 
201 Justin Hall
Kansas State University
Manhattan, KS 66506</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Fakultas Kesehatan Masyarakat, Universitas Airlangga</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Jl. Mulyorejo Kampus C Surabaya - INDONESIA 60115
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Indonesia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dini Ririn Andrias</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Nutrition, Faculty of Public Health, Universitas Airlangga 
Jl. Mulyorejo Kampus C Surabaya - INDONESIA 60115</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Indonesia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Triska Susila Nindya</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Nutrition, Faculty of Public Health, Universitas Airlangga 
Jl. Mulyorejo Kampus C Surabaya - INDONESIA 60115</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Indonesia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Hario Megatsari</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Health Education and Behavior, Faculty of Public Health, Universitas Airlangga 
Jl. Mulyorejo Kampus C Surabaya - INDONESIA 60115</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Indonesia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Double burden of malnutrition is a phenomenon where in one household we have problem of under and over nutrition. The magnitude of double burden of malnutrition is highest in the third quintile group of socioeconomic status (SES). Evidence suggests that modifiable behavioral factors like food distribution and dietary diversity is associated with reducing double burden of malnutrition, given the household is food secure. This study aims to decrease the prevalence of double burden of malnutrition through targeting these modifiable behaviors. NEO-MOM project is a randomized controlled trial with 3 months length behavior intervention towards households with overweight/obese mother and stunted children. NEO-MOM project consists of 6 sessions of nutrition education and behavioral strategies to assist maternal adoption of healthy eating and child feeding practices. In addition, community health workers will be trained to perform 6 sessions motivational interviewing in a biweekly home visit for 3 months. During the sessions of nutrition education, we will provide hands-on activities for mothers to improve their self-efficacy towards dietary diversity and child feeding. The targets are to increase maternal consumption of fruit and vegetables as well as to increase child's consumption of animal protein. The effectiveness of the intervention will be measured by the reduction of maternal overweight/obesity and childhood stunting</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Rick Scheidt, Chair; Committee on Research Involving Human Subjects</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University Research Compliance Office (URCO)
203 Fairchild Hall, Lower Mezzanine
Kansas State University
Manhattan, KS 66506-1103
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>7894</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>United States of America</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Trias Mahmudiono</name>
      <address>Department of Nutrition, 
Faculty of Public Health, Universitas Airlangga
Jl. Mulyorejo Kampus C Surabaya - INDONESIA 60115
</address>
      <phone>+62 31 5964808</phone>
      <fax>+62 31 5964809</fax>
      <email>triasmahmudiono@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Trias Mahmudiono</name>
      <address>Department of Nutrition, 
Faculty of Public Health, Universitas Airlangga
Jl. Mulyorejo Kampus C Surabaya - INDONESIA 60115</address>
      <phone>+62 31 5964808</phone>
      <fax>+62 31 5964809</fax>
      <email>triasmahmudiono@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Trias Mahmudiono</name>
      <address>Department of Nutrition, 
Faculty of Public Health, Universitas Airlangga
Jl. Mulyorejo Kampus C Surabaya - INDONESIA 60115</address>
      <phone>+62 31 5964808</phone>
      <fax>+62 31 5964809</fax>
      <email>triasmahmudiono@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Trias Mahmudiono</name>
      <address>Department of Nutrition, 
Faculty of Public Health, Universitas Airlangga
Jl. Mulyorejo Kampus C Surabaya - INDONESIA 60115
</address>
      <phone>+ 62 31 5964808 </phone>
      <fax>+ 62 31 5964809</fax>
      <email>triasmahmudiono@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>