<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83014">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/07/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/08/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000436370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Hepatitis B Acceptability and Vaccination Incentive Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to evaluate the effectiveness of a small financial incentive after the second and third dose of a Hepatitis B vaccine on vaccine completion in people who inject drugs.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>HAVIT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>HAVIT</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hepatitis B</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Provision of a small financial incentives i.e. $30 will be given after the participant receives the second dose and $30 after the participant receives the third dose  of Hepatitis B vaccine. Incentives will be given  to participants randomised to the incentive arm only.</interventions>
    <comparator>no financial incentive as per standard care</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine relative to a standard care control condition the efficacy of incentive payments to increase Hepatitis B Vaccine (HBV) completion using an accelerated schedule (0, 7 and 21 days). Accelerated schedule i.e. receipt of all 3 Hepatitis B vaccinations in a shorter timeframe in comparison to the conventional schedule ( 0,1 and 6 months).</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the cost effectiveness of incentive payments relative to 'standard care' as a method of improving vaccine induced immunity as measured at 12 weeks and rates of successful series completion.The cost effectiveness analysis (CEA) will compare the marginal and incremental costs and outcomes of standard care with the incentive payment arm.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Identify the correlates of immunity(defined as hepatitis B surface antibody levels &gt; =10mIU/ml at 12 weeks post intervention in this group.This will be assessed by blood analysis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess the acceptability of vaccines including HBV vaccines; barriers to immunisation uptake and willingness to participate in vaccine trials among people who inject drugs(PWID). All behavioural data will be collected using Audio Computer-Assisted Self Interview (ACASI) technology at baseline and at week 12 which has been associated with higher reports of sensitive and stigmatized behaviours among PWID, adolescents and HIV positive people (Des Jarlais et al. 1999; Metzger et al. 2000).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess hepatitis B related knowledge in this group using the study-specific instrument (Day et al. 2003).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Aged 16 years and above; 2) Injected drugs at least once in the preceding 6 months; 3) No previous hepatitis B infection, and a maximum of one previous dose of hepatitis B vaccination, or unknown infection and vaccination status, based on self-report and, where available medical records; 4) ability to provide informed consent, to be randomised and attend vaccinations over a period of 3 weeks and attend follow up at 12 weeks post randomisation.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Evidence of natural or vaccine induced immunity; 2) Previous exposure or two+ vaccinations (as identified by self report), where HBV surface antibody =10 mIU/ml; 3) Serious mental or physical illness or disability likely to impact on capacity to complete the study procedures; 4) Insufficient English language skills that will impair ability to give informed consent or provide reliable responses to study interviews/questionnaires; 5) Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) infection; 6) Refusal to be vaccinated against hepatitis B.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealed ( sealed envelopes)</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation: Statistical Analysis Software (SAS) implementation of randomisation will be used with RANUNI (the SAS command which creates random numbers from uniform distribution. It generates random numbers between 01 and 1) function.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>1340</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Kirby Institute (formerly the National Centre in HIV Epidemiology and Clinical Research)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>CFI Building
Corner Boundary and West Sts
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO 1421 Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of New south Wales</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>UNSW Sydney NSW 2052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This trial seeks to investigate if  providing a small financial incentive ($30) will increase the uptake and completion of the hepatitis B vaccine among injecting drug users.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Publications:

Topp L, Day C, Dore G, Maher L. (2009). Poor criterion validity of self-reported hepatitis B infection and vaccination status among injecting drug users: A review. Drug and Alcohol Review 28(6): 669-675(7).

Conference presentations:

1. Deacon RM, Topp L, Wand H, Day CA, Rodgers C, Haber PS, van Beek I, Maher L on behalf of the Hepatitis Acceptability and Vaccine Incentives Trial (HAVIT) Group. Correlates of hepatitis B vaccination status among injecting drug users: a comparison of eligible and ineligible participants in the HAVIT trial. 7th Australasian Viral Hepatitis Conference, Melbourne: September 2010 (oral presentation).  

2. Deacon R, Day C, Topp L, Rodgers C, Wand H, Shanahan M, van Beek I, Haber P, Maher L on behalf of the Hepatitis Acceptability and Vaccine Incentives Trial (HAVIT) Group. Using financial incentives to increase hepatitis B immunisation completion in people who inject drugs: A randomised controlled trial. Australasian Professional Society on Alcohol and other Drugs Conference, Darwin: November 2009, Drug and Alcohol Review 28(s1): abstract 247:A13.

3. Deacon R, Day C, Topp L, Rodgers C, Wand H, Shanahan M, van Beek I, Haber P, Maher L on behalf of the Hepatitis Acceptability and Vaccine Incentives Trial (HAVIT) Group. Using financial incentives to increase hepatitis B immunisation completion in people who inject drugs: A randomised controlled trial. Australasian Professional Society on Alcohol and other Drugs Conference, Darwin: November 2009 (oral presentation).

4. Barnes K, van Beek I, Day C, Topp L, Shanahan M, Wand H, Maher L (on behalf of the Hepatitis Acceptability and Vaccine Incentives Trial (HAVIT) Group). Using financial incentives to increase hepatitis B immunisation completion in injecting drug users. Australasian Professional Society on Alcohol and other Drugs: Drug and Alcohol Conference, Sydney: November 2008 (poster presentation).

5. Barnes K, van Beek I, Day C, Topp L, Shanahan M, Wand H, Maher L (on behalf of the Hepatitis Acceptability and Vaccine Incentives Trial (HAVIT) Group). Using financial incentives to increase hepatitis B immunisation completion in injecting drug users: A randomised controlled trial. Australian Society of HIV Medicine Annual Meeting, Perth: October 2008 (oral presentation). 

6. Maher L, Barnes K, van Beek I, Day C, Topp L, Shanahan M, Wand H (on behalf of the Hepatitis Acceptability and Vaccine Incentives Trial (HAVIT) Group) Increasing hepatitis B immunisation completion in people who inject drug. 6th Australasian Viral Hepatitis Conference, Brisbane: October 2008 (oral presentation). 

7. Maher L, Barnes K, Topp L, Day C (on behalf of the Hepatitis Acceptability and Vaccine Incentives Trial (HAVIT) Group). Use of incentives to increase vaccination uptake and completion in injecting drug users. 11th National Immunisation Conference, Gold Coast: September 2008 (oral presentation).</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Prince Alfred Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Level 8, Building 14
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Camperdown
NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/06/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/RPAH/272</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/05/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Lisa Maher</name>
      <address>The Kirby Institute
CFI Building
Corner Boundary and West Sts
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>02 9385 0936</phone>
      <fax>02 9385 0920</fax>
      <email>lmaher@kirby.unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rachel Deacon</name>
      <address>The Kirby Institute
CFI Building
Corner Boundary and West Sts
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>02 9385 0935</phone>
      <fax>02 9385 0920</fax>
      <email>rdeacon@kirby.unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Lisa Maher</name>
      <address>The Kirby Institute
CFI Building
Corner Boundary and West Sts
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>02 9385 0936</phone>
      <fax>02 9385 0920</fax>
      <email>lmaher@kirby.unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>