<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335441">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/05/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000369022</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Nutritional status in Parkinsons disease pre- and post-deep brain stimulation surgery</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Nutritional status in Parkinsons disease pre- and post-deep brain stimulation surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1114-8766</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Exposure: Deep brain stimulation surgery of the sub-thalamic nucleus: This involves the stereotactic implantation of stimulating electrodes in the sub-thalamic nucleus of the brain. Implanted stimulating electrodes are routed subcutaneously and connected to a permanently implanted stimulating device usually fixed within the pectoral or rectus abdominus fascia.
The entire process takes 5 to 7 hours; the surgery generally takes 3 to 4 hours.</interventions>
    <comparator>Best medical therapy: Dopamine replacement therapy (DRT) which provides substantial therapeutic relief.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nutritional status using 4 compartment body composition analysis, the Patient-Generated Subjective Global Assessment (PG-SGA), weight, Body Mass Index (BMI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-surgery, 3 months post-surgery, 6 months post-surgery for the Parkinson's disease deep-brain stimulation group; baseline, 3 months post-baseline, 6 months post-baseline for control groups with continuing therapy as determine by their treating neurologist/physician</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life using the Parkinson's disease questionnaire (PDQ-39)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-surgery, 3 months post-surgery, 6 months post-surgery for the Parkinson's disease deep-brain stimulation group; baseline, 3 months post-baseline, 6 months post-baseline for control groups with continuing therapy as determine by their treating neurologist/physician</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Deep brain stimulation (DBS) Parkinson's disease (PD) group (DBS-PD): diagnosis of idiopathic Parkinson's disease, scheduled for deep brain stimulation of the sub-thalamic nucleus.

Parkinson's disease control group: diagnosis of idiopathic Parkinson's disease, not scheduled for deep brain stimulation; age, gender, disease duration matched to DBS-PD participants

Elderly control group: no diagnosis of idiopathic Parkinson's disese; age and gender matched to DBS-PD participants</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous surgery for Parkinson's disease; unable to provide informed consent; presence of a co-morbidity (unstable cardiovascular disease, heart failure, liver failure, chronic kidney disease requiring dialysis, cancer, human immunodeficiency virus/acquired immune deficiency syndrome (HIV/AIDS), chronic obstructive pulmonary disease) or acute illness which could influence the presence of nutrition impact symptoms and/or nutritional status</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Victoria Park Road
Kelvin Grove, QLD 4059</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>While it is known that patients with Parkinsons disease (PD) lose more weight and have a higher risk of decreased bone mineral density and increased inflammation when compared with age-matched controls, and deep brain stimuation of the subthalamic nucleus (STN-DBS surgery) in PD is followed by weight gain, there has been limited research that has investigated specific factors that impact upon nutritional status in PD. There has also been limited research in regards to the measurement of nutritional status in Parkinsons disease.
The overall aim of this project is to determine the influence of motor and non-motor symptoms and inflammation on nutritional status in people with Parkinsons disease and how deep-brain stimulation modifies the severity of symptoms and inflammation and therefore their impact on nutritional status.
The specific aims of the proposed project are to: 
*Identify potential factors influencing nutritional status changes in Parkinsons disease.
*Evaluate the effectiveness of available subjective and objective tools in the assessment of nutritional status in Parkinsons disease.
*Provide evidence to inform effective nutritional interventions aiming to address the decline in nutritional status associated with Parkinsons disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Uniting Care Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1013</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jamie Sheard</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove, QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+61731386183</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jamie.sheard@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jamie Sheard</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove, QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+61731386183</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jamie.sheard@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jamie Sheard</name>
      <address>Queensland University of Technology
Institute of Health and Biomedical Innovation
60 Musk Ave
Kelvin Grove, QLD 4059</address>
      <phone>+61731386183</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jamie.sheard@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>