<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1490">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/07/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/08/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000338561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of the Medex Test for the Detection of Gastrointestinal Disorders</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the Medex Test for the Detection of Gastrointestinal Disorders</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gastrointestinal Disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The MEDEXTEST device is intended to differentiate between normal and abnormal function of the stomach and duodenum. The MEDEXTEST is a non-invasive radiation free device. The examination lasts approximately 20 minutes and is performed in the following manner:
1. External measurement of 24 skin zones located on the limbs.
2. Stimulation of four special skin zones  lasting one minutes each.
3. External measurement of the same 24 zones.

 The study design is blind, one-armed, comparative, prospective and without a control group. The examination is only conducted once.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective is to determine the sensitivity of the device through its ability to accurately and effectively diagnose:
1. Disorders of the stomach and duodenum due to Gastritis, Gastroduodenitis, Peptic Ulcer Disease, Gastric Cancer and other causes.
2. Type of disease

Assuming true sensitivity and specificity of 0.90, the criteria for the study success will be observing sensitivity and specificity of above 0.80 at a confidence interval of 97.5.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured and evaluated at the completion of the MEDEXTEST and other investigations (EGD with or without biopsy and Urea Breath Test) on all 200 study participants.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective is to determine the specificity of the device through its ability to accurately and effectively diagnose:
1. Disorders of the stomach and duodenum due to Gastritis, Gastroduodenitis, Peptic Ulcer Disease, Gastric Cancer and other causes.
2. Type of disease

Assuming true sensitivity and specificity of 0.90, the criteria for the study success will be observing sensitivity and specificity of above 0.80 at a confidence interval of 97.5.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective is to determine the total accuracy of the device through its ability to accurately and effectively diagnose:
1. Disorders of the stomach and duodenum due to Gastritis, Gastroduodenitis, Peptic Ulcer Disease, Gastric Cancer and other causes.
2. Type of disease

Assuming true sensitivity and specificity of 0.90, the criteria for the study success will be observing sensitivity and specificity of above 0.80 at a confidence interval of 97.5.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary objective is to evaluate the technical intra-device variability between Medex Test devices.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The observed sensitivity and specificity of the MEDEXTEST in-between study subgroups (age, gender and type of disease) is expected to be of no significant difference.
</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The observed sensitivity and specificity of the MEDEXTEST intra-device variability is expected to be of no significant difference.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome will be measured and evaluated at the completion of the MEDEXTEST and other investigations (EGD with or without biopsy and Urea Breath Test) on all 200 study participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint />
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>200 male and female outpatients with clinical symptoms of active digestive disease will be enrolled into the study.  The recruitment process of study participants will assure that the baseline characteristics (age, BMI and gender) will be similar.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those patients who are amputees, preganant or suffering form local skin damage in the areas of Medex Test examination.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures>All physicians and technicians will be blind to each others examination and MEDEXTEST findings.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/07/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Medex Screen (AustralAsia) Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medex Screen (AustralAsia) Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NONE</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary objective is to compare findings achieved by traditional diagnostic procedures with those of the MEDEXTEST in order to define specificity, sensitivity and accuracy of the MEDEXTEST device. Traditional diagnostic procedures include an evaluation by a physician (history and physical examination), Esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD) with/without biopsy and Urea Breath Test.

	The study population will include 200 male and female patients with clinical symptoms of gastroduodenal disorders of similar baseline characteristics (age, BMI and gender). Investigators and Gastroenterologists at Nepean Hospital will refer patients. Eligibility will be determined by satisfying the following inclusion and exclusion criteria.

	Eligible participants will undergo a baseline evaluation, which includes: written consent, demographic information, medical history, current medications and a physical examination. Participants will undergo the 20-minute MEDEXTEST conducted by a trained Research Assistant. They will be advised of their results at an appointment with their physician following their endodoscopy procedure. The participants will be referred to tests according to clinical and examination findings such as an Esophagogastroduodenoscopy (EGD) (with or without biopsy) and Urea Breath Test.
	
The MEDEXTEST is a non-invasive examination lasting approximately 20 minutes in duration and performed in the following manner: 
- External measurement of the skins electrical resistance of 24 zones located on the participants feet and hands.
- T.E.N.S stimulation.
- A repeated measurement of the 24 zones.
- Mathematical processing of the collected information by the help of a previously composed correlative algorithm.
- The results will be saved in the operators computer memory and, additionally, a printout will be filed in the patients source documentation file.

At the completion of data collection, a trained physician will make an independent reading from the MEDEXTEST results, with another physician diagnosing the participant based on the traditional procedures. To minimize the risk of bias, all physicians will be blind to their colleagues diagnosis. A third investigator will compare the diagnosis from the traditional diagnostic procedures against the MEDEXTEST, record test results in participants CRF and conduct a follow-up consultation with participant. After the required data is obtained from all study participants of the study site, the results of the MEDEXTEST will be compared with the actual participants condition as indicated by the traditional tests, in order to determine the sensitivity, specificity and total accuracy of the device. The estimated duration of the study is 1 year including data analysis and reporting.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney West Area Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee - Nepean Campus</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec> 06/003</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Martin Weltman</name>
      <address>Nepean Hospital
PO Box 63
Penrith NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 47343332</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 47343145</fax>
      <email>weltmam@wahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Johel Neiron</name>
      <address>Medex Screen (AustralAsia) Pty Ltd
Unit 5
20 Twickenham Rd
Burswood WA 6100</address>
      <phone>+61 8 94721184</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 94703836</fax>
      <email>johel@medexaus.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>