<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362233">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/03/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/03/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000295842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effects of Alcohol and Energy Drink on Cognitive Performance and Mood</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An investigation of Red Bull and Vodka on Mood and Cognition in a healthy cohort of men and women aged 18-50 years of age.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alcohol-related cognitive impairment</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Energy drink cognitive improvement</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Interaction of stimulant and depressant</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The design of the current study is a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled and crossover trial administering 0.6g/kg alcohol (Absolut Vodka, 40% alcohol) and 250ml Energy Drink plus water to form 500 ml.  Participants will be randomly allocated to an alcohol, Energy Drink, alcohol and Energy Drink combination, and placebo sequence with a washout period of seven days between each condition.  

The alcohol treatment of 0.6g/kg was selected based on previous research to attain a BAC reading of 0.05 and the 250ml Red Bull was selected based on the 250 ml cans available for purchase and contains:

Energy	480 kj
Protein	0g
Fat total
-Saturated	0g
0g
Carbohydrates
-Sugars	27g
27g
Sodium	100mg
Taurine	1000mg
Caffeine	80mg
Glucuronolactone	60mg
Inositol	50mg
Niacinamide	20mg
Pantothenic Acid	5mg
Vitamin B6	5mg
Vitamin B12	5mcg
	
Participants will be randomly assigned to a treatment sequence and will consume one treatment on each of the four testing sessions. Treatment randomisation and mixing will be completed by a third party to ensure double blinding. Participants will be given 10 minutes to consume the drink.</interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo treatment will be 250 ml energy drink minus the active ingredients (excluding glucose and sucrose). The placebo will be identical in appearance and as close as possible to identical in flavour and smell. In each alcohol free condition, alcohol will be wiped around the rim of the glass to ensure that participants remain blind to the treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Four-Choice Reaction Time

A 2 x 2 stimulus array of circles corresponded to a response array of four squares.  The circles will light up one at a time and the participant has to tap the corresponding square.  The task will be scored for reaction time and number of errors.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 45 minutes, 90 minutes and 180 minutes post administration.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number Pairs

A series of five-digit arrays will be presented on the screen.  For each array the participant is to decide whether the second and fourth digits are the same.  Yes/No responses will be recorded and the task will be scored for reaction time and number of errors.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 45 minutes, 90 minutes and 180 minutes post administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serial Sevens

Participants will be presented with a three-digit number between 800 and 999 from which they will subtract seven, then subtract seven again and so on for the duration of two minutes.  The number of responses and errors will be recorded.  The task is a measure of concentration and working memory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 45 minutes, 90 minutes and 180 minutes post administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visuospatial Working Memory

A series of two arrays of four pictures will be presented on the screen.  Each array will be displayed for five seconds with a delay of two seconds between each array.  Two of the four pictures in the first array will be the same.  The second array will contain four pictures, two of which will be the same as the first and one will be in the same position while the second will be in a difference position.  A third array will appear on the screen containing eight pictures and the direction "Tap on the picture that was shown in both displays IN DIFFERENT POSITIONS".  The task will be scored for accuracy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 45 minutes, 90 minutes and 180 minutes post administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Memory Scanning (Sternberg, 1975)

Participants will be asked to remember a set of three, four and then five digits.  After each set of digits, they will be presented with a series of digits one at a time and have to indicate whether or not each was in the original set.  Reaction times and number of errors will be recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 45 minutes, 90 minutes and 180 minutes post administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rectangular Maze

A light-coloured maze against a dark background will be presented on the screen.  A stylus will be placed against a star in one corner and a ring will signal the participant to begin tracing around the maze to a target flag placed in the opposite corner to the star as quickly as possible while trying to remain within the boundaries of the maze.  The task will be scored for completion time and errors.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 45 minutes, 90 minutes and 180 minutes post administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Digit-Symbol Matching

A key will be presented on the screen displaying the digits one through to nine with a unique symbol below each.  Below this will be a series of digit-symbol pairs appearing sequentially and the participant is to indicate whether it matches the key by selecting "yes" or "no".  Fifty stimuli will be presented and reactions times and errors will be recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 45 minutes, 90 minutes and 180 minutes post administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bond Lader VAS (Bond &amp; Lader, 1974)

The scale comprises a total of 16 100-mm lines anchored at either end by antonyms.  Participants mark their current subjective state between the antonyms on the line. Each line is scored as millimeters to the mark from the negative antonym.  From the resultant scores, three measures derived by factor analysis can be isolated.  These have been described by Bond and Lader as representing the following: "alertness", "calmness" and "contentedness".   Scores for each factor represent the unweighted average number of millimeters (maximum 100 mm) from the negative antonym for the individual scales contributing to the factor.  The antonyms drunk-sober will be added to the end of the scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 45 minutes, 90 minutes and 180 minutes post administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Profile of Mood States (McNair, Lorr &amp; Droppleman, 1971)

Participants indicate on a 5-point scale from 0 (not at all) to 4 (extremely) the degree to which they have identified with each of 65 mood-related adjectives within the past week. Items are summed into six factors; Tension-Anxiety, Confusion-Bewilderment, Vigor-Activity, Anger-Hostility, Depression-Dejection and Fatigue-Inertia. A Total Mood Disturbance (TMD) score is computed as the sum of the first 5 factors minus Vigor-Activity. High scores indicate greater mood disturbance on all scales except Vigor-Activity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 45 minutes, 90 minutes and 180 minutes post administration.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Males and females aged 18-50 years of age
-Currently a regular caffeine consumer
-Fluent in English
-Participant must have signed the consent form
-Willing and able to participate in all scheduled visits</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Smoker
-Diagnosis of any psychiatric disorder
-Diagnosis of any intellectual/mental impairment
-Current or past alcohol abuse
-Individuals with chronic health problems
-Pregnant or lactating
-Taking any prescription medication (other than the  contraceptive pill)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited through advertising and word of mouth. After successfully completing the phone screen and practice session, participants will be randomly allocated to a treatment schedule by a disinterested third person. This will be completed by a randomised computer number sequence generator. Randomization codes will be kept in a sealed opaque envelope in a secure safe and will only be opened in case of emergency.

Over the course of the investigation, participants will complete testing under each of the four conditions plus placebo with treatment order counterbalanced across participants. A disinterested third party will be responsible for the blinding procedure.</concealment>
    <sequence>A simple randomisation technique will be implemented by using a randomization table created by Microsoft excel.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Swinburne University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 218
Hawthorn VIC 3122</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Red Bull GmBH</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5330 Fuschl am</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Austria</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Considering the increasing popularity of mixing energy drinks with alcohol and the very little research to-date, it is imperative that further research is carried out.  The aim of the present study is to extend the available research exploring the effects of the combination of energy drinks with alcohol.  Specifically, the study aims to investigate the effects of the combination of alcohol and Energy Drink on cognition and mood compared to Energy Drink alone, alcohol alone and placebo.

The design of the current study is a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled and crossover trial administering 0.6g/kg alcohol and 250ml Energy Drink plus water to form 500 ml.  Participants will be randomly allocated to an alcohol, Energy Drink, alcohol and Energy Drink combination, and placebo sequence with a washout period of seven days between each condition.  Participants will undergo a practice session where they complete the cognitive task twice and the mood questionnaires once to ensure there are no practice effects in the testing sessions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Swinburne University Human Research Ethics Committee (SUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research ethics officer
Swinburne research (H68)
Swinburne University of Technology
PO Boz 218
Hawthorn Vic, 3122</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/11/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>SUHREC Project 2011/139</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof Andrew Scholey</name>
      <address>Brain and Psychological Sciences Research Instititue,
Swinburne University of Technology,
427-457 Burwood Road,
Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9214 8932</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ascholey@swin.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sarah Benson</name>
      <address>400 Burwood Road
Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9214 4506</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarahbenson@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sarah Benson</name>
      <address>400 Burwood Road
Hawthorn, VIC, 3122</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9214 4506</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sarahbenson@swin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>