<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335870">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/08/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/12/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001059055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The To2rpido Study: Targeted Oxygenation in the Resuscitation of Premature Infants and their Developmental Outcome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The To2rpido Study: Targeted Oxygenation in the Resuscitation of Premature Infants and their Developmental Outcome</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Torpido study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil current</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Oxidative stress in premature infants</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mortality in premature infants</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Bronchopulmonary dysplasia in premature infants</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Extreme prematurity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Resuscitation in premature infants</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other reproductive health and childbirth disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Starting delivery room resuscitation of premature infants below 31 weeks completed gestation with room air and titrating to specific postnatal oxygen saturations. This is a once off intervention. Management after the infant leaves the delivery room will be as per institutional guidelines</interventions>
    <comparator>The use of pure oxygen is the standard of care for newborn resuscitation. Room air for preterm infants during resuscitation will be used in the other arm. Infants will be allocated to start resuscitation with either room air or pure oxygen. FiO2 in each arm will be titrated to set levels ot oxygen saturations via a preductal monitor. This intervention will last about 20-30 minutes (average duration of resuscitation in the delivery room). The intervention occurs only once, at birth. Infants in the room air arm may cross over to pure oxygen if 1. The oxygen saturations remain below 65% at 5 minutes of age 2. The infant requires cardiac compression or inotropic agents.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years of age</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major disability as assessed by the Bayley Scare of Infant Development III</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 years of age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bronchopulmonary dysplasia, as assessed by the need for supplemental oxygen and/or ventilatory support at 36 weeks corrected gestation</outcome>
      <timepoint>36 weeks corrected gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Birth below 31 weeks completed gestation and/or birthweight below 1250g if gestation is unknown.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Hours</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>31</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Major congenital abnormalities resulting in certain death and/or developmental delay and/or oxygen metabolism and distribution</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Mother at risk of preterm delivery before 31 weeks completed gestation is approached and provided information about the study. Approach is not to be attempted if delivery is imminent or &lt;6 hours after admission of the mother to the hospital. Randomisation occurs at the time of delivery from sealed opaque envelopes containing a centrally generated randomised code.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomisation allocated to specific centres and stratified by gestation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Cross over to pure oxygen permitted if room air infant fails to meet the following criteria:
1. Heart rate &lt;100beats per minute despite adequate ventilation and/or
2. Oxygen saturations is&lt;65% at or after 5 minutes [FiO2 - fractional inspired oxygen: 0.5  0.7 at 5 minutes]
3. If external cardiac message or resuscitation medications required at any time</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/12/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/12/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1892</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2031</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Selangor</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Royal Hospital for Women</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Barker St
Randwick NSW 2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Leslie Stevens Fund for Newborn Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Sydney Childrens Hospital
High St
Randwick NSW 2031</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ministry of Health Malaysia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Ministry of Health Malaysia,
Blok E1, E6 &amp; E10 Kompleks E,
Pusat Pentadbiran Kerajaan Persekutuan,
62590 Putrajaya, Malaysia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Malaysia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Malaya</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Pusat Perubatan Universiti Malaya, 
Lembah Pantai, 
59100, Kuala Lumpur, 
Malaysia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Malaysia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The problem with oxygen: Oxygen (O2) is essential for life but too much (hyperoxia) is toxic and may cause cell inflammation and death. The extremely premature infant is particularly susceptible to O2 toxicity because they do not develop or acquire appropriate defense mechanisms until the 3rd trimester (after 28 weeks gestation). Prolonged or excessive exposure to O2 may, in fact, cause problems like bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD) or retinopathy of prematurity (ROP). Children with BPD are in and out of hospitals with chest infections and asthma. They also have lower intelligence and grow more poorly because of repeated episodes of hypoxia (low body O2) from lung damage and steroids. The latter improves lung function but may also impair brain growth. Children with ROP may be severely short-sighted and even blind. Unfortunately, many premature infants, if they survive, still develop BPD and ROP despite considerable advances in prenatal care (e.g. maternal steroids that accelerate lung maturation), postnatal care (e.g. artificial surfactant that aids lung expansion) and an awareness of the profound consequences of O2 toxicity in this population.  
The use of oxygen during resuscitation: More than 1 million infants around the world do not breathe after birth and require resuscitation. For more than a century, pure or 100% O2 has been given to such infants through breathing masks or tubes. A change in color from blue or white to pink is generally taken to be a positive response to resuscitation. However, recent studies of full-term human newborn infants now advocate caution because there is increasing evidence giving an infant 100% O2 may cause excessive formation of toxic reactive oxygen species (ROS) that injure vital cellular components like membranes and DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid). This may delay the infants recovery and even double the risk of death.
What about the premature infant? Studies have shown that full-term infants may be resuscitated with room air (RA, 21% O2) with good result. However, premature infants often have some lung immaturity and may need a bit of O2 after birth to prevent hypoxia. How much O2 that is, is not certain. Whether giving a preterm infant lower amounts of O2 during resuscitation may improve outcome is also not known. 
The aim of the To2rpido study is to see if using RA to start the resuscitation of very premature infants (&lt;31 weeks gestation) reduces oxidative injury and complications such as BPD, ROP, cerebral palsy (CP) and death. 
Location: This is an international study in Australia (n=3), Malaysia (n=6), Singapore (n=1) and India (n=1). These sites are important to show that the resuscitation techniques used in the To2rpido study may be applied to neonatal intensive care units in both developed and developing nations. 
How the study will be conducted: We will compare RA to 100% O2 to start the resuscitation of premature infants below 31 weeks gestation in the delivery suite. O2 will be changed depending on the infants oxygen saturations (percentage of oxygenated hemoglobin, SaO2) and the infants blood will be tested for O2-related stress products. Complications such as death, CP, BPD and ROP will be compared and survivors will be tested at 18-24 months of age for neurological and physical development.
Significance: There is still no cure for prematurity, which affects more than 8% of infants worldwide. The number of premature infants has increased by 15% over the last two decades in the USA alone and their care costs more than $30 billion a year. In addition, most of the premature babies are born in non-Western countries and the techniques used in the To2rpido may therefore also have far-reaching consequences for the almost 13 million premature infants born around the world each year.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil current</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Presentations entitled: The To2rpido Study: Targeted Oxygenation in the Resuscitation of Premature Infants and their Developmental Outcome at:
1. Perinatal Society Meeting, Malaysia, March 2009
2. Congress of the Perinatal Society of Australia and New Zealand, April 2009.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South East Sydney Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Prince of Wales Hospital
High St
Randwick NSW 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/06/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/06/0065</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/02/2006</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Julee Oei</name>
      <address>The Royal Hospital for Women
Barker St
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>61 2 9382 6152</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9382 6191</fax>
      <email>ju.oei@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Julee Oei</name>
      <address>The Royal Hospital for Women
Barker St
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>61 2 9382 6152</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9382 6191</fax>
      <email>Ju.oei@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Julee Oei</name>
      <address>The Royal Hospital for Women
Barker St
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>61 2 9382 6152</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9382 6191</fax>
      <email>ju.oei@sesiahs.health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Julee Oei</name>
      <address>Newborn Care Centre
Royal Hospital for Women
Barker St
Randwick NSW 2031</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 6152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.oei@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>