<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365717">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000159651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Whey protein isolate as a source of vitamin B12 and to lower homocysteine and methylmalonic acid in older person
 </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial evaluating whey protein as a source of vitamin B12 and its effects on serum B12, holotranscobalamin (HTC) and methylmalonic acid levels in the older person
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1152-7783 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Aging older healthy people</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sub-clinical serum levels of vitamin B12 in older people</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a cross-over design. Whey protein isolate provided by Myopure will be used for the intervention arm to see if it increases vitamin B12 levels in older people with sub-clinical serum levels of vitamin B12. The trial duration is 8 weeks. Mode of administration for this trial is oral. After that there is sixteen week wash period and then the second arm of the trial will be performed using soy protein isolate for another  8 weeks. Both these products will be taken along with the diet (50 gm daily; 25 gm at a time; to be taken twice daily - once with the breakfast and once with dinner). During the wash out period, when participants are on normal diet, their vitamin B12 levels will be monitored. If it is more than 300 pmol/L, then their B12 will be brought to the study limits by restricting/modifying their diet.    

Participants will be given the chart so that they can mark on the chart to show the compliance adherence. They will return this chart at the end of every intervention so that w e can monitor the degree of adherence. Participants will be required to attend the clinic at mid point of the sixteen week wash period. They will provid the blood sample and if B12 levels are increased, then the dietician will suggest the food items to be avoided during the next 3-4 week period. Once the B12 level returns to the levels required in the intervention, they will participate in the trial.   </interventions>
    <comparator>As mentioned above, the study involves two parts: one with whey protein isolate and other with soy protein isolate. Soy protein isolate is being used as a control treatment option.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum B12

HPLC based assay will be used for measuring the serum 
B12 levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 8, 16, 24 and 32 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum holotranscobalamin levels 

ELISA based assay will be used to measure serum holotranscobalamin levels .</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 8, 16, 24 and 32 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum Methylmalonic acid

Capillary-gas chromatography based assay will be used to measure this metabolite </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 8, 16, 24 and 32 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum homocysteine levels 

Mass spectroscopy based assay will be used for this measurement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 8, 16, 24 and 32 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in serum folate levels

HPLC based assay will be used. </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 8, 16, 24 and 32 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in plasma brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF)

Plasma levels of BDNF will be measured using enzyme immunoassay </outcome>
      <timepoint>0. 8, 16, 24 and 32 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Chromosomal damage biomarkers

Tissue culture technique will be used to grow the lymphocytes. After 44 hours of the culture set up, cytokinesis is blocked by adding cytochalasin. Cytokinesis block micronucleus assay is the main assay that will be performed to assess the chromosomal damage biomarkers that include micronucleus formation, nuclear buds, nucleoplasmic bridges, apoptosis and necrosis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 8, 16, 24 and 32 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in telomere length as assessed by the Real-Time based qPCR assay </outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 8, 16, 24 and 32 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mitochondrial DNA damage biomarkers assessed by real-time based qPCR assay</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 8, 16, 24 and 32 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive function tests

It includes word list immediate recall, word list delayed recall, Digit Symbol Coding, Verbal Fluency, 2-choice reaction time, Odd-man-out reaction time, Operation Span,
Number Memory Scanning, Colour Stroop. The battery includes some speed tasks, which are
more likely to be sensitive to subtle changes. It also encompasses a number of different cognitive
domains that could change due to intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 8, 16, 24 and 32 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy subjects 

Not undergoing treatment for any life-threatening diseases

Not taking vitamin B12/choline/antioxidants at doses that exceed 25% of the Recommended Dietary Allowance (RDA)

Should have serum concentration of B12 between 100 to 300pmol/L, plasma MethylMalonicAcid &gt;0.26umol/L and serum creatinine concentration of 120umol/L or less 

Able to consume required quantities of either Whey protein isolate or Soy protein isolate
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable to attend an information session and/or read the information sheet

Current smokers

Those who drink more than two standard drinks of alcohol per day

Body mass index (BMI) 30 or greater

Diagnosed with diabetes

Lactose intolerance 

History of pernicious anaemia or atrophic gastritis 

Regular use of antacids
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Bio-availability</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Our previous study in older men (aged 50-70y) showed that they had a mean serum vitamin B12 of 283 pmol/l with a standard deviation of 108 pmol/l. With 50 subjects per group the intervention will have 90% power to detect an increase of 50pmol/L at P&lt;0.05 which is an effect size of 18%. For comparison, another intervention study published by of Eussen and co-workers showed that supplementation with 2.5ug/d of vitamin B12 orally for 16 weeks produced a 20% increase in serum B12 in elderly subjects aged 70y or greater (mean 80y). If, in a worst case scenario, 20%
of participants drop out of the study, it will still be possible to detect an effect size of 18% at 80% power.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dairy Research Institute, United States of America </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>10255 West Higgins Road Suite 900
Rosemont, IL 60018-5616</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dairy Research Institute, United States of America </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>10255 West Higgins Road Suite 900
Rosemont, IL 60018-5616
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation
Division of Animal, Food and Health Sciences</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>gate 13, Kintore Avenue
PO BOX 10041
Adelaide 5000
South Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Vitamin B12 is essential for cells in the body to function and regenerate themselves properly. 

Deficiency in this vitamin causes damage to the genetic material (DNA), anaemia, nervous system malfunction, loss of mental capacity and dementia.  

Older persons have a reduced ability to absorb and utilise vitamin B12 efficiently and are therefore at greater risk of vitamin B12 deficiency.

Cows milk is an important source of vitamin B12. The whey fraction of milk contains highest amount of vitamin B12.  

This study will test whether consumption of whey protein isolated from cows milk: increases vitamin B12 levels in blood, reduces DNA damage and improves memory and other mental functions. 

If this hypothesis is proven, whey protein isolate could be recommended as a part of a dietary pattern designed to increase vitamin B12 levels in older persons.  

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Fenech</name>
      <address>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organistion 
Division of Animal, Food and Health Sciences
gate 13, Kintore Avenue
PO BOX 10041
Adelaide 5000 
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83038880</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.fenech@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Anne McGuffin</name>
      <address>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organistion 
Division of Animal, Food and Health Sciences
gate 13, Kintore Avenue
PO BOX 10041
Adelaide 5000
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8988</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anne.mcguffin@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Varinderpal Dhillon</name>
      <address>Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organistion 
Division of Animal, Food and Health Sciences
gate 13, Kintore Avenue
PO BOX 10041
Adelaide 5000
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83038932</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>varinderpal.dhillon@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>