<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="342973">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/05/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000544976</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does low level laser therapy reduce pain levels in cracked or grazed nipples in breastfeeding Western Australian women?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does low level laser therapy reduce pain levels in cracked or grazed nipples in breastfeeding Western Australian women?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cracked nipples</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast feeding</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Low level laser therapy will be used as a treatment for reducing pain in cracked nipples of breastfeeding women.

The laser is a Class 3B single GaAIAs laser. The laser diode has output 100mW, wavelength of 810nm and pulse width of 100microseconds. Illumination is provided by three blue LEDs of 470nm. Elliptical beam area is 9.2mm2 at the aperture.

Treatment doesage is 3Jcm-2, 100% per point. One point is the surface area covered by the laser diode aperture. The number of points treated will be visually determined by the treating physiotherapist, daily, for as many days as is required for each individual.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control will be a placebo laser diode identical in appearence to the active laser. It will be administered by the blinded treating physiotherapist in the same manner as the active laser treatment will be administered. The number of points of treatment will be visually determined by the treating physiotherapist, daily, for as many days as is required for each individual.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nipple pain will be measured using the change in pain on the Numerical Rating Scale (NRS). At each occasion of treatment, the physiotherapist will use standardised questioning to request NRS scores. Subjects will be asked to score the pain experienced during the most recent breastfeed and on self-palpation of the nipple immediately before and after intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nipple pain measured before and after treatment at each treatment session.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Breastfeeding continuation will be investigated with an interview.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 8 weeks following first treatment session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective improvement of the nipple trauma reported by the subject.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and each treatment session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Breastfeeding women with single and multiple births
Women with broken nipple integrity (cracked or grazed nipples) as assessed by the treating physiotherapist
Women who give informed consent to participate in the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Women who are planning to suppress breastfeeding within 2 weeks
Women with babies in the Special Care Nursery
Women who have infants diagnosed with cleft palate
Women with infectious blood diseased (including HIV, AIDS and Hepatitis C)
Women with nipple piercing on the affected side
Women with breast implants, breast augmentation or who have had breast reduction surgery
Women who are expressing only (other than those resting for treatment) and not attempting to breastfeed
Women who have insufficient English skills to understand and comprehend the study and are unable to give informed consent.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be recruited from breastfeeding women attending King Edward Memorial Hosptial (Western Australia's public womens hospital). Inpatients or outpatiens who are referred (including self referral) to physiotherapy for laser treatment of cracked or grazed nipples will be invited to particpate in the study.

Once referred for laser therapy, the treating physiotherapist will assess subject eligibility. If criteria are fulfilled subjects will recieve detailed information regarding the study including the aims, duration and methods. Written consent will be sought.

Subjects consenting to particpate in the study will be randomised to either the control or intervention group using block randomisation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Four black envelopes will be grouped, two envelopes containing the letter A and two the letter B. Subjects will select an envelope and receive the corresponding treatment protocol. Once the four envelopes have been allocated the process will be repeated.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Main campus location
    Kent Street, Bentley, Perth
    Western Australia. 6102.

Postal address
    GPO Box U1987, Perth
    Western Australia. 6845.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>King Edward Memorial Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>374 Bagot Road
Subiaco, Perth
Western Australia
Australia 6008</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>HR117/2011</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/06/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Laura Snowball</name>
      <address>c/o Judith Thompson
School of Physiotherapy
Curtin University of Technology
GPO Box U1987
Perth, WA 6845
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+614 0796 1984</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>laura.snowball@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Laura Snowball</name>
      <address>c/o Judith Thompson
School of Physiotherapy
Curtin University of Technology
GPO Box U1987
Perth, WA 6845
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+614 0796 1984</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>laura.snowball@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Laura Snowball</name>
      <address>c/o Judith Thompson
School of Physiotherapy
Curtin University of Technology
GPO Box U1987
Perth, WA 6845
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+614 0796 1984</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>laura.snowball@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>