<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364377">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000672752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Novel Technique for the Assessment of Vocal Cords in the Early Postoperative Period after Thyroid Surgery: Bonfils Intubation Fiberscope</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study on the comparison of the Macintosh laryngoscope and Bonfils Intubation Fiberscope for the evaluation of the vocal cords in the early postoperative period

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>goiter</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Thyroid disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1.Bonfils intubation fiberoscope (karl Storz Co., Tutlingen, Germany)  was introduced into clinical practice during the 1980s. It is a rigid, reusable, straight fiberoptic device (40cm in length and 5 mm in diameter), which has a 40 degree curved tip. It includes flexible eyepiece mounted on the handle. Recent studies found that this device was convenient for tracheal intubation in patients with normal airways or in those with predicted airway difficulties. The Macintosh series laryngoscopes are the predominant model of the curved blade types. During laryngoscopy, the tip or beak of the blade is compressed into the angle formed by the base of the tongue and the epiglottis (vallecula), indirectly raising the epiglottis. Macintosh laryngoscope is a device that we use routinely in all intubation procedures. 
2. This procedure was performed after 3 minutes of thyroid 
surgery
3. The duration of the procedure for both devices was 1 minute. 
4.The devices were administered to the patients only for one time. </interventions>
    <comparator>1. The Macintosh series laryngoscopes are the predominant model of the curved blade types. During laryngoscopy, the tip or beak of the blade is compressed into the angle formed by the base of the tongue and the epiglottis (vallecula), indirectly raising the epiglottis. Macintosh laryngoscope is a device that we use routinely in all intubation procedures. 
2.The devices were used in participants after 3 minutes of thyroid surgery. 
3. The duration of the procedure was 1 minute for both of the devices. 
4.The devices were administered to the patients only for one time.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1]:The comparison of the evaluating of the vocal cords in the early postoperative period with The Bonfils intubation fiberscope (BIF) and the Macintosh laryngoscope was done with Cormach-Lehane score. The aim of this study is to compare the vocal cord imaging success of macintosh laryngoscope and BIF. </outcome>
      <timepoint>[1]: Assessed 3 minutes after the thyroid surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2]:Hemodynamics (blood pressure and heart rate were recorded by noninvasive techniques)</outcome>
      <timepoint>[2]: Assessed 3 minutes after the thyroid surgery. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>[3]: Comfort of the patient using with patient reactivity score</outcome>
      <timepoint>[3]: Assessed 3 minutes after the thyroid surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>[1]:Adverse events of the laryngoscopy procedure (the percentage of the adverse events were recorded. heart rate level below 50 per minute was recorded as bradycardia. The percentage of retching, damage to teeth and lips were also recorded).</outcome>
      <timepoint>[1]: Assessed 3 minutes after the thyroid surgery. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>[2]: Adverse events of the thyroid surgery (Cormach-Lehane score was used for evaluation of adverse events of tyhroid surgery)</outcome>
      <timepoint>(2): Assessed 3 minutes after the thyroid surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>50 euthyroid patients aged 18-73 years (ASA I-II) undergoing elective thyroid surgery were included in the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>73</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with cardiopulmonary diseases, such as hypertension, coronary artery disease, bronchitis, or asthma, and those with obstructive-sleep apnea syndrome or previous vocal cord dysfunction and difficult intubation were excluded</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Preliminary estimation was made for sample size calculation. In extubation period percentage of Cormack-Lehane scoring grade I was %10 for Macintosh laryngoscope, while it was %50 for BIF. For an alpha of 0.05 and a power of at least %80, this magnitude of effect could be demonstrated in a study with 15 patients for each group.   </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Hatay</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mustafa Kemal University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Anesthesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Mustafa Kemal University. Serinyol, Antakya, Hatay. 31034.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mustafa Kemal University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Anesthesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Mustafa Kemal University. Serinyol, Antakya, Hatay. 31034.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: The aim of this study was to compare the imaging success of the Macintosh laryngoscope and the Bonfils intubation fiberscope (BIF) when used to assess the vocal cords in the early postoperative period after thyroid surgery. The patients comfort and their hemodynamic responses with the respective techniques were also investigated. 
Methods: Fifty euthyroid patients aged 1873 years (ASA I-II) undergoing elective thyroid surgery were included in the study. In all cases, a Macintosh blade with an appropriate size was used for intubation during the induction of anesthesia. After extubation, the vocal cords were imaged with the Macintosh laryngoscope and the BIF. The Mallampati classification, the thyromental distance, the sternomental distance, the maximum opening of the mouth, and the circumference and mobility of the neck were recorded in the preoperative period. In the postoperative period, the patients CormackLehane scores, their reactivity scores, and their hemodynamic parameters with both the Macintosh laryngoscope and the BIF were recorded. 
Results: The BIF was significantly more successful in imaging the vocal cords after tracheal extubation than the Macintosh laryngoscope (p=0.000). The patients reactivity scores were significantly lower with the BIF when compared to the Macintosh laryngoscope (p=0.000). The mean arterial pressure (MAP) was significantly elevated during Macintosh laryngoscopy compared to Bonfils intubation fiberscopy (p=0.000). 
Conclusions: In conclusion, the BIF provided better glottal visualization, less patient discomfort, and fewer hemodynamic responses during the assessment of the vocal cords in the early postoperative period after thyroid surgery when compared to the Macintosh laryngoscope. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethical Committee Gaziantep University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Gaziantep Universitesi Tip Fakultesi Dekanligi Arka Bina Kat:2 Sehitkamil, Gaziantep.27310.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/05/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14.05.2012/211</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/05/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kasim Tuzcu</name>
      <address>Department of Anesthesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Mustafa Kemal University. Serinyol, Antakya, Hatay. 31034.</address>
      <phone>+903262291000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ktuzcu@mku.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kasim Tuzcu</name>
      <address>Department of Anesthesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Mustafa Kemal University. Serinyol, Antakya, Hatay. 31034.</address>
      <phone>+903262291000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ktuzcu@mku.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kasim Tuzcu</name>
      <address>Department of Anesthesiology, Faculty of Medicine, Mustafa Kemal University. Serinyol, Antakya, Hatay. 31034.</address>
      <phone>+903262291000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ktuzcu@mku.edu.tr</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>