<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362019">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/02/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000177853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Optimal diet patterns for improving muscle strength in older adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A 12 week randomised controlled trial investigating the optimal dietary pattern for improving muscle strength in older adults undertaking resistance training</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Loss of muscle mass and strength in aging</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will undertake three 60 minute resistance training sessions per week on non-consecutive days for 3 months. Participants will perform the exercises on their own with the supervision of gym staff. The program will progress from 1-3 sets of 8-12 repetitions for 6 upper and lower body exercises starting at 100% 8RM measured at baseline. They will be randomised to one of three dietary patterns for three months: high carbohydrate, high dairy protein or high soy protein. Participants will meet fortnightly with a dietician to discuss the diet plan. The high dairy protein group is the intervention under investigation and participants will be prescribed to consume a healthy low fat diet, with one serve of dairy, designed to provide ~1.0 g/kg/day of dietary protein. In addition they will consume snack foods, with an additional ~27 g/day of dairy-based protein from 3 serves of dairy foods to provide a total protein intake of ~1.3-1.4 g/kg/day. The 3 serves will be consumed after resistance exercise training. On non-training days the serves will be consumed as part of their breakfast.</interventions>
    <comparator>They will be randomised to one of three dietary patterns for three months: high carbohydrate, high dairy protein or high soy protein. Participants will meet fortnightly with a dietician to discuss the diet plan. The high carbohydrate and high soy protein diets are the control groups to allow for the determination of the efficacy of the high protein diet and in particular dairy protein. Participants allocated the high protein soy diet will be prescribed to consume a healthy low fat diet, with one serve of dairy, designed to provide ~1.0 g/kg/day of dietary protein, with an additional ~27g/day of non-dairy based protein from three serves of soy protein based foods to provide a total protein intake of ~1.3-1.4 g/kg/day. Three serves of soy protein (~27g protein) will be consumed after resistance exercise training. On non-training days the soy protein will be consumed as part of their breakfast. Participants allocated the high carbohydrate diet will be prescribed to consume a healthy low fat diet, with one serve of dairy, designed to provide ~1.0 g/kg/day of dietary protein, and a high carbohydrate food supplement, which will provide ~3g/kg/day of carbohydrates. These foods will be consumed after resistance exercise training. On non-training days participants will consume the foods at a time that is convenient to them.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in 1 repetition maximum of chest press, lateral pull down, leg press, knee extension and leg curl assessed on gym equipment</outcome>
      <timepoint>There are 2 timepoints, baseline (week 0) and at the end of the intervention at Week 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in isometric knee extensor muscle strength assessed by an isokinetic dynamometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>There are 2 timepoints, baseline (week 0) and at the end of the intervention at Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in body composition assessed by lean tissue and body fat mass by dual energy x-ray absorptiometry, weight and waist circumference.</outcome>
      <timepoint>There are 2 timepoints, baseline (week 0) and at the end of the intervention at Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in grip strength of the dominant hand using an adjustable, hydraulic handgrip dynamometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>There are 2 timepoints, baseline (week 0) and at the end of the intervention at Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in physical function assessed using the six minute walk, De Morton Mobility Index and Human activity profile</outcome>
      <timepoint>There are 2 timepoints, baseline (week 0) and at the end of the intervention at Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in quality of life assessed using the short-form 36 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>There are 2 timepoints, baseline (week 0) and at the end of the intervention at Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in cardiometabolic risk factors assessed using analysis of fasting blood lipids, glucose and insulin</outcome>
      <timepoint>There are 2 timepoints, baseline (week 0) and at the end of the intervention at Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in urea and creatinine from a 24 hour urine sample</outcome>
      <timepoint>There are 2 timepoints, baseline (week 0) and at the end of the intervention at Week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 50-79 yrs
BMI 20-35 kg/m2
Stable medication for at least 3 months</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>79</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diagnosed with diabetes (type 1 or type 2 diabetes), proteinuria, a malignancy, or a history of metabolic disease such as liver, kidney, cardiovascular, respiratory or gastrointestinal disease, cardiac abnormalities or are pregnant or lactating
Uncontrolled hypertension 
Currently have or history of a musculoskeletal injury, joint or peripheral vascular disease sufficient to impede their participation in the exercise program (such as hip arthritis, foot, ankle problems or pain)
Current smoker or history of smoking during last 6 months Heavy alcohol consumption (&gt; 5 STD drinks/day) or unable to limit intake for study duration (upper limit of 2-7 STD drinks/wk)
Participated in regular formal aerobic or resistance exercise program (greater than two 30-min sessions of moderate/vigorous aerobic exercise per week or greater than 1 moderate intensity resistance exercise session per week) during the 6 months prior to study
Widely fluctuating exercise patterns
Currently on a weight reducing diet 
Intolerant/allergic to lactose or bovine milk protein
Untreated depression
Currently using or recent (3 months) use of testosterone therapy</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be recruited by newspaper advertisement and flyers. Volunteers will be screened via questionnaire and a medical screening visit to access their eligibility for the trial. Eligibility will be determined by the study coordinator and medical physician. Treatment will be randomly allocated by the trial manager after eligibility is determined and will only be told to the dietician administering the dietary patterns. Allocation will be concealed from the study staff conducting the outcome assessments at a different site. The participants will know which group they have been allocated to because they will have to follow the required dietary pattern.</concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation to treatments will be via the process of minimisation on the basis of gender, BMI and age.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/05/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>12/04/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>135</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dairy Health and Nutrition Consortium</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>671 Sneydes Road
Werribee, Victoria 3030</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current project will investigate the best dietary pattern when combined with a regular weight training program for improving muscle strength, lean mass and physical function (i.e. tasks of daily living) in older adults. Participants will have to consume diet specific foods containing varying amounts of protein and carbohydrate within 1 hour after their exercise session as this has been shown as an important window for nutrition to stimulate an increase in muscle growth.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>General Purpose Building, Mawson Lakes Campus Mawson Lakes Boulevard Mawson Lakes, SA 5095</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>26921</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/11/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jon Buckley</name>
      <address>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1853</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jon.buckley@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rebecca Thomson</name>
      <address>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.thomson@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Rebecca Thomson</name>
      <address>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre
University of South Australia
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rebecca.thomson@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jon Buckley</name>
      <address>Nutritional Physiology Research Centre University of South Australia GPO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1853</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jon.buckley@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>