<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363298">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000192785</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating web-based pelvic floor muscle education for pregnant women</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised Controlled Trial: Evaluating web-based pelvic floor muscle (PFM) education for pregnant women to enhance knowledge and adherence </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Incontinence during pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Knowledge of pelvic floor muscle function and facilitation during pregnancy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention is a web-based PFM education programme designed by a physiotherapist specialised in women's health.  The programme information is based on current recommendations from research and designed to raise pregnant women's knowledge and awareness of PFM and encourage participation in PFM exercise programme.  There will be 2 Arms.  Arm 1 will receive the 5 minute web-based education via a link on the Internet and usual care.  Arm 2 will only receive usual care.  Usual care is the standard antenatal health care recommended by the Department of Health for pregnant women living in Australia.  Usual care does not prohibit women from participating in any education or exercise programmes unless specified by a health care provider as being contra-indicated during an individual's pregnancy.
Arm 1 will receive the intervention at 20 weeks (+/- 1) gestation and be requested to watch the 5 minute web-based education via a link on the Internet, twice.  Both Arms will answer a post-intervention questionnaire at 35 weeks (+/- 1) gestation.</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator group of pregnant women will continue to receive usual care only.  Usual care does not prohibit women from participating in any education or exercise programmes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of awareness and knowledge of PFM as measured by  pre and post intervention questionnaires</outcome>
      <timepoint>21 weeks (+/-1) gestation then 35 weeks (+/-1) gestation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Confidence and motivation of participant as measured by pre and post intervention questionnaires</outcome>
      <timepoint>21 weeks (+/-1) gestation then 35 weeks (+/-1) gestation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of adherence to PFM exercises as measured by pre and post intervention questionnaires and an exercise diary</outcome>
      <timepoint>21 weeks (+/-1) gestation then 35 weeks (+/-1) gestation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urinary incontinence as measured by pre and post intervention questionnaires and a bladder diary</outcome>
      <timepoint>21 weeks (+/-1) gestation then 35 weeks (+/-1) gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knowledge of whether treatment for incontinence is available as measured by pre and post intervention questionnaires</outcome>
      <timepoint>21 weeks (+/-1) gestation then 35 weeks (+/-1) gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether treatment for incontinence was accessed as measured by a post-intervention questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>21 weeks (+/-1) gestation then 35 weeks (+/-1) gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>21 weeks (+/-1) gestation
Women who have low levels of knowledge of PFM function and facilitation as measured on a Likert Type Scale
Not planning to have a caesarean section
Sufficient levels of English to respond to the pre-intervention survey</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>44</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diagnosed with a neurological condition eg Multiple Sclerosis, Cerebrovascular Accident, Acquired Brian Injury
Bed rest prescribed by a doctor</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All participants will answer a pre-intervention questionnaire.  Women with low levels of knowledge of PFM function and facilitation and who consent in this questionnaire to being contacted and involved in further research will then sign a consent form.  Because the participants are pregnant they will be allocated a number as the consent forms are received.  The allocation of participants will be concealed from the researcher and undertaken by a research assistant using sealed opaque numbered envelopes. </concealment>
    <sequence>On return of the consent form, the participants will be allocated a number from one to 70 using a computerised sequence generation table. The allocation of the participants to either group one or two will be concealed from the researcher and undertaken by a research assistant, who is not involved in the study. The group allocation will be concealed in opaque envelopes labelled outside from one to 70. The researcher will telephone the assistant to ask for the participant’s allocation number in order of recruitment into the trial. Using the envelopes the participants will be allocated to either the intervention (Arm 1) or control (Arm 2) groups.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is a mixed methods study where the quantitative data from the two questionnaires and the diaries will be merged with the qualitative data from the open-ended items in the questionnaires and the semi-structured interviews.
The quantitative data will be analysed using SPSS - General Linear Model, Multivariate Analysis of Variance, t-tests and Chi Square.
The qualitative data will be thematically analysed.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/02/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>26/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/02/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>70</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>1/06/2014</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Rockingham General Hospital - Cooloongup</hospital>
    <hospital>Armadale Kelmscott Memorial Hospital - Armadale</hospital>
    <hospital>Geraldton Hospital - Geraldton</hospital>
    <hospital>Swan Districts Hospital - Middle Swan</hospital>
    <hospital>Bentley Health Service - Bentley</hospital>
    <hospital>Albany Hospital - Albany</hospital>
    <hospital>Bunbury Hospital - Bunbury</hospital>
    <hospital>Busselton Hospital - Busselton</hospital>
    <hospital>Esperance Hospital - Esperance</hospital>
    <hospital>Kalgoorlie Hospital - Kalgoorlie</hospital>
    <hospital>Northam Hospital - Northam</hospital>
    <postcode>6168 - Rockingham</postcode>
    <postcode>6112 - Armadale</postcode>
    <postcode>6530 - Geraldton</postcode>
    <postcode>6056 - Midland</postcode>
    <postcode>6102 - Bentley</postcode>
    <postcode>6330 - Albany</postcode>
    <postcode>6230 - Bunbury</postcode>
    <postcode>6280 - Busselton</postcode>
    <postcode>6450 - Esperance</postcode>
    <postcode>6430 - Kalgoorlie</postcode>
    <postcode>6401 - Northam</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Notre Dame Australia (Fremantle Campus)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Physiotherapy
19 Mouat Street, (Box 1225)
FREMANTLE  6959
Western Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Notre Dame Australia (Fremantle Campus)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Physiotherapy
19 Mouat Street, (Box 1225)
FREMANTLE  6959
Western Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Anne-Marie Hill</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Physiotherapy
19 Mouat Street, (Box 1225)
FREMANTLE  6959
Western Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Adjunct Professor Richard Berlach</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Education
19 Mouat Street, (Box 1225)
FREMANTLE  6959
Western Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In 2008 in Western Australia (WA) there were 30,234 babies born.  Pregnancy is a period when the pelvic floor muscles (PFM) are stretched and weakened which may lead to PFM dysfunction causing urinary incontinence.  During pregnancy PFM exercises are the recommended treatment to strengthen the PFM and reduce the risk of developing urinary incontinence.  Accordingly, pregnant women are encouraged to attend antenatal education which typically includes information on the function and facilitation of the PFM.  This study will examine the effect of providing web-based education on pelvic PFM function and PFM exercises for pregnant women in WA.  The pregnant women will be evaluated on the knowledge, awareness, intention, self-efficacy and adherence to the PFM exercises.  If pregnant women can successfully use web-based PFM education during pregnancy then people with PFM dysfunction and incontinence can be guided to an appropriate evidence-based website.  This may improve quality of life for women.
Hypotheses:
H0: There will be no difference in awareness and knowledge gained on the function of PFM in pregnant women who undertake a web-based PFM intervention programme compared to pregnant women who only receive usual care in WA
H1: There will be an increase in awareness and knowledge gained on the function of PFM in pregnant women who undertake a web-based PFM intervention programme compared to pregnant women who only receive usual care in WA
H0: There will be no difference in confidence and motivation to engage in PFM exercises in pregnant women who undertake a web-based PFM intervention programme compared to pregnant women who only receive usual care
H1: There will be an increase in confidence and motivation to engage in PFM exercises in pregnant women who undertake a web-based PFM intervention programme compared to pregnant women who only receive usual care
H0: There will be no difference in adherence with PFM exercises by pregnant women who undertake a web-based, PFM exercises intervention programme and pregnant women who only receive usual care in rural WA
H1: There will be an increase in adherence with PFM exercises by pregnant women who undertake a web-based, PFM exercises intervention programme and pregnant women who only receive usual care in rural WA

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>None presently</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Notre Dame Australia HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>School of Physiotherapy
19 Mouat Street, (Box 1225)
FREMANTLE  6959
Western Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>012114F</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Australian Country Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Executive Officer
WACHS Research Ethics Committee
WA Country Health Service 
1st Floor Bunbury Tower
61 Victoria Street 
BUNBURY WA 6230 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012:44</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/11/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Metropolitan Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Office 
South Metropolitan Health Service 
PO Box 480 
FREMANTLE WA 6959

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>13/05</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/01/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>North Metropolitan Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee Office
2nd Floor, A Block 
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital, 
Hospital Avenue NEDLANDS WA 6009
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2013-043</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anne-Marie Hill</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and exercise Science Curtin University GPO Box U1987 Perth Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61892664104</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anne-marie.hill@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anne-Marie Hill</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and exercise Science Curtin University GPO Box U1987 Perth Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61892664104</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anne-marie.hill@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Anne-Marie Hill</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy and exercise Science Curtin University GPO Box U1987 Perth Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61892664104</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anne-marie.hill@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Judith Wilson</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
19 Mouat Street, (Box 1225)
FREMANTLE  6959
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9443 0229</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>judy.wilson1@my.nd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>