<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371694">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/12/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001700426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Impact of osteopathy on the Peak Expiratory Flow (PEF) of asthmatic patients.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Impact of the Dog-Technic for D1-D4 and Longitudinal Stroke Technique for Diaphragm on Peak Expiratory Flow (PEF) in asthmatic patients.
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We used the dog technique, which is a type of thrust. This is a high-velocity, low-amplitude thrust to restore specific joint motion .This technique was used in the D1 through D4 vertebrae. ( Group 1 )

The other technique was the longitudinal stroke, which treats the myofascial tissue. Here the force is constant until  the dysfunctional tissues are guided along a path of least resistance and free movement is achieved. (Group 2 )

These techniques were utilized to see if the vertebral pain and dyspnoea diminished, and if the peak expiratory flow (PEF) increased.

This study was performed by an osteopath and physiotherapist.
The entire treatment lasted approximately 10 minutes, but data was collected immediately after each manipulation within that time frame..
Every participant was treated only one time and in only one group ( in Group 1 or Group 2)
No adherence monitoring was necessary.

When participants enter, they breath into the spirometer, and the data is recorded. Then they immediately perform a physical activity, consisting of performing 30 complete leg pressings with the torso erected in 45 seconds, and then returning to the standing position. Immediately after this physical activity, the participant breathes into the spirometer again. Next, participants rested for a mean time of 30 seconds. After rest, the physiotherapist performs the treatment (physical manipulation according to group) and immediately the participant breathes into the spirometer and data is measured. Following this, the participant performs the physical activity for a second time, and immediately following, they breath into the spirometer, and the study ends for that individual.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group is the Group 2 which aplicated Longitudinal Stroke.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peak Expiratory Flow (PEF) is measured with the spirometer Datospir Peak-10. This measures the intensity of the airflow that passes through the airways when the participant gives a fast and intense breath. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The Peak Expiratory Flow (PEF) was measured four times. 

First, at rest, before treatment was started.

Second, immediately after the first physical activity prior to treatment (manipulation by physiotherapist according to the group).

Third, after the participant has rested for about 30 seconds, and the physiotherapist performs the treatment (manipulation according to group)..

And finally, following treatment after participant has performed the physical activity a second time.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The pain was evaluated using an algometer. The location where pain was measured was the spinous processes of the D1-D4 vertebrae.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pain was evaluated after the manipulation of the vertebrae, immediately following treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dyspnea was calculated using the Borg scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The Dyspnea was calculated  before treatment and immediately after physical activity. Moreover then immediately after the treatment and immediately after physical activity</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Must have asthma;
Must have had more than one asthma attack;
Must sign an informed consent form</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Less than 18 years old;
Suffers from some form of bone disorder;
Is depressed;
Suffers from chronic obstructive respiratory disease (COPD);
Suffers from a pulmonary edema;
Older than 65;
Has received phsyical therapy treatment in the last 3 weeks;


</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using procedures like coin-tossing</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>15/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>20/05/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>18</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>18</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Suspended</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>20/05/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <state>Madrid</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Camilo Jose Cela</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>C/Castillo de Alarcon, 49
Urb. Villafranca del Castillo 28692, 
Villanueva de la Canada, Madrid, Espana</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Spain</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Unfunded</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unfunded</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Results:12 Group 1 (Dog Technic and Longitudinal Stroke) patients responded positively to treatment, there was an increase of 5.1% and 6.1% of the post-intervención PEF and post-intervención, and effort. The results of the scale of Borg by which we measure the level of Dyspnea were positive, a % 54,95, patients noted an improvement in breathing. In addition was confirmed through the means of both groups group 1 in which two techniques were applied was 34,05% more effective than group 2 in which applied only a. After handling pain fell by 38% of the cases.
Conclusions:The impact of the technique of Dog-Technic for D1-D4 and the Longitudinal Stroke technique for diaphragm in the volumes of peak expiratory flow (PEF) in asthmatic patients were positive, there was a change of the PEF Post intervention and post-intervención, and effort and showed the most effective group in which only a technique was applied. Furthermore this type of treatment decreased facilitated vertebrae pain and was efficient in the improvement of Dyspnea and the general well-being of the patient.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>With reference to the ethics application status, there is no committee that formally gave permission. Rather, my university approved the study, and all participants signed an informed consent.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Universidad Camilo Jose Cela</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Urb. Villafranca del Castillo, Calle Castillo de Alarcon, 49, 28692 Villanueva de la Canada, Madrid</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec> See public notes </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>20/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371694-Repercusiones de la técnica dog and stroke ( 17-05-2016) FINAL TIPO 2.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Angelo Michele Vagali</name>
      <address>Universidad Camilo Jose Cela
Calle Altamirano 3 4E
Madrid, Madrid, 28008
Spain</address>
      <phone>+34 603337919</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>angelovagali93@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Angelo Michele Vagali</name>
      <address>Universidad Camilo Jose Cela
Calle Altamirano 3 4E
Madrid, Madrid, 28008
Spain</address>
      <phone>+34 603337919</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>angelovagali93@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Angelo Michele Vagali</name>
      <address>Universidad Camilo Jose Cela.
Calle Altamirano 3 4E
Madrid, Madrid, 28008
Spain</address>
      <phone>+34 603337919</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>angelovagali93@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Spain</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>