<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369372">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001256561</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does hydrotherapy influence behaviours in children with autism spectrum disorder (ASD)?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does hydrotherapy influence behaviours in children with autism spectrum disorder (ASD)?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Hydrotherapy, which includes therapeutic exercises held in a warm pool for a relaxing effect, provided by physiotherapists. Each session will last approximately 45 minutes. The number of children in the water at a time will be no more than 4 children. Sessions will run 1-2 times weekly. This treatment intervention will be provided in addition to the children's current educational and therapy programs. Group 1 will complete 4 weeks of hydrotherapy while group 2 continues with their current programs. After 4 weeks, group 1 and 2 will switch, allowing group 2 to complete hydrotherapy and group 1 to return to their current programs without the addition of hydrotherapy.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will continue their usual individual routines which may include physical activity and adjunct therapy. Pharmacological therapy may also be included, depending on the child's needs.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child Behaviour Checklist 6-18 (CBCL 6-18) is a 113 item questionnaire that will be completed by the parents at week 0, 4 and 8. The questionnaire should take approximately 15-20 minutes to complete. It is used to detect behavioural and emotional problems in children and adolescence. The CBCL 6-18 covers children 6  to 18 years of age. This questionnaire covers many different areas: anxiety/depression, somatic complaints, social issues, thought and attention difficulties, rule-breaking and aggressive behaviour, ADHD, oppositional defiant problems and conduct difficulties. </outcome>
      <timepoint>All parents/guardians will be required to complete the Child Behaviour Checklist (CBCL) at week 0, 4 and 8.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>none</outcome>
      <timepoint>none</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The inclusion criteria for participants includes:
a) a patient at Gateway Physiotherapy (Private Practice, Brisbane) or at a local GP clinic
b) aged 6-12 years of age
c) a diagnosis of Autism Spectrum Disorder</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The exclusion criteria for participants includes:
a) patients with contraindications to hydrotherapy
b) if the patient has a fear of water
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A concealed randomized allocation procedure will assign each participant to either Group 1 or Group 2. Parent of participant will select a sealed envelope allocating them to a group. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>NO formal sample size calculation was performed</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bond University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>2 Promethean Way
Robina, 4226 QLD</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bond University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2 Promethean Way
Robina, 4226, QLD</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Gateway Physiotherapy</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>17/590 Mt Gravatt Capalaba Rd
Wishart, QLD  4122
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>After providing consent, if no contraindications to hydrotherapy are identified in the pre-study screening assessment, the child will be included in the study. A concealed randomized allocation procedure will assign each participant to either Group 1 or Group 2 (parent will select a sealed envelope allocating the child to a group). The duration of this study is 9 weeks. Group 1 will be asked to participate in a 45-min hydrotherapy class, 1x weekly for 4 weeks. Group 2; will receive no hydrotherapy intervention. At the end of 4 weeks, Group 1 will cease hydrotherapy, and Group 2 will commence hydrotherapy sessions. Hydrotherapy sessions will involve gentle therapeutic exercise in a warm, temperature controlled pool under the supervision of members of the research team. All parents/guardians will be required to complete the Child Behaviour Checklist (CBCL) at weeks 0, 4 and 8. The CBCL is a short and meaningful questionnaire that assesses a range of concepts associated with children's behaviours. The CBCL, which has been validated for use with children with ASD, will determine any behavioural changes of participants during the study. To limit the bias from the researchers conducting the intervention, parents/guardians will be asked to place their completed questionnaires into an envelope which will be sealed by the participant and returned to a third investigator who will not be in contact with the participants or their parents. The Enjoyment Scale is a visual scale in which the participants can express their willingness participant in the hydrotherapy activities throughout the study. The Enjoyment Scale will be used at the end of each hydrotherapy session to monitor level of enjoyment and willingness to continue with hydrotherapy sessions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> Bond University’s Human Research Ethics Committee (BUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>14 University Drive
Robina, 4226, QLD</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Whitney Mills</name>
      <address>Organization: Bond University
14 University Drive
Robina, 4226, QLD</address>
      <phone>+61468892278</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>whitney.mills@student.bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Rob Orr</name>
      <address>Organization: Bond University Institute of Health and Sport
2 Promethean Way
Robina, 4226, QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5595 1111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rorr@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nikki Milne</name>
      <address>Organization: Bond University Institute of Health and Sport
2 Promethean Way
Robina, 4226, QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5595 4155</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nmilne@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Michael Warburton</name>
      <address>17/590 Mt Gravatt Capalaba Rd
Wishart, QLD  4122</address>
      <phone>07 34206653</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>physio4u@bigpond.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>