<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373843">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/10/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/11/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001532392p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dialysis and Supportive Care in Elderly patients with advanced Renal disease </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>To determine whether medical management including maintenance dialysis versus medical treatment alone reduces mortality and morbidity in highly co-morbid patients aged over 75 years with stage 5 chronic kidney disease,  </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>DISCERN</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>End Stage Kidney disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1: Medical Treatment and Maintenance Dialysis 
Allocation to this study intervention will see the patient receive the usual, appropriate medical treatment for their advanced chronic kidney disease as determined by their treating Renal Physician and integrated team, as per current practices at the Investigational site. Medical treatment includes managing complications such as anaemia, acid/base disturbances, itch, blood pressure and the related comorbid conditions associated with advanced chronic kidney disease. This group will also undergo preparation and entry to a maintenance dialysis program. This treatment component includes preparation of dialysis access, and entry to such a program as clinically indicated by the treating physician and the treating team. This means that some patients in this group may not ever reach the point of entering a dialysis program. The intervention period is up to 3 years, or until a mortality outcome is reached. However, patients will be offered the same clinical care after the study has ended.

Arm 2: Medical Treatment (no Maintenance Dialysis)
Allocation to this study intervention will see the patient receive the usual, appropriate medical treatment for their advanced chronic kidney disease as determined by their treating Renal Physician and integrated team as per current practices of the Investigational site. Medical treatment includes managing complications such as anaemia, acid/base disturbances, itch, blood pressure and the related comorbid conditions associated with advanced chronic kidney disease.  This group will receive treatment for any uraemic symptoms using the usual non-dialysis treatments available at that investigating site but will not undergo preparation for entering a dialysis program nor enter such a program unless the treating physician or participant deviates from the study protocol. The intervention period will last up to 3 years, or until a mortality outcome is reached. However, patients will be offered the same clinical care after the study has ended.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparisons will be made between two treatment arms</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All-cause mortality</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 3 years of randomisation
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Extent of deviation from allocated study treatment arm</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over 3 year follow period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life, as measured by EQ-5D-3L Health Questionnaire and Satisfaction with Life scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health resource utilisation through total hospital bed days, total cost weights of hospital care and total medical procedures (insertion of dialysis access, interventional radiology procedures, surgical procedures)</outcome>
      <timepoint>within 3 years of study follow up period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptom burden of participants, as measured by iPOS-Renal scale questionnaire completed by participants</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional Status as assessed by Renal Physician </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Aged greater than or equal to 75 years
2.	With advanced chronic kidney disease, defined as having an eGFR of less than or equal to 12 ml/min/1.73m2  
3.	Is expected by their treating physician to meet clinical criteria for entry to a maintenance dialysis program within the next 24 months.
4.	Has satisfied the treating units policies relating to education regarding end stage kidney disease treatment options
5.	The treating physician caring for the participant has equipoise about the balance of risk and benefit for the participant should they enter either treatment arm of the study.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>75</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Treating physician considers it unlikely that the participant will adhere to allocated study treatment
2.	Participant unable to understand the implications of both of the study treatment arms for their future care
3.     The treating physician expects that the participant will not survive 3 months beyond study randomisation
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by web-based data management system</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will occur using a computer-generated algorithm employing randomly permuted blocks.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome will be analysed using a comparison of two independent proportions using a Chai-squared statistic. Secondary outcomes will be analysed according to the nature of the underlying data, utilising parametric and non-parametric tests and their appropriate analyses.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/01/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/01/2022</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The George Institute for Global Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5, 1 King Street, Newtown NSW 2042</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The George Institute for Global Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, 1 King Street, Newtown NSW 2042</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The burden of end stage kidney disease is growing globally. Much of this growth since the turn of the century has been in elderly patients, a group in whom the outcomes from both dialysis and non-dialysis treatments are poor.  Optimal therapy for these older patients with end stage kidney disease is not clear and practice varies widely.
Recent literature shows high mortality rates in older patients receiving dialysis, with an average mortality of 27% in the first year. Data on the outcomes from non-dialysis treatment, usually referred to as supportive care, is much less clear. This is because:
	There are no registries of patients receiving supporting care
	It is difficult to define a clear start-in point for supportive care, as opposed to dialysis initiation
	Dialysis patient groups compared to supportive care patients have large differences in co-morbidities
	There is crossover between the two patient pathways
The only effective way to better understand the effects of the dialysis and the supportive care treatment approaches is to randomly apply the treatments in a clinical trial. This approach allows the issues of lead-time bias, residual confounding and cross-over to be eliminated or managed, thereby producing findings of the highest clinical and scientific value.
It is the view of the investigators of the DISCERN Trial that, where clinicians and patients have equipoise around the relative benefits and risks of dialysis and supportive care, to randomly allocate patients to either of these treatment approaches is an appropriate and ethical approach. In a setting for scarce healthcare resources, understanding this balance arising from a resource-intensive treatment such as dialysis is the appropriate path to guide resource allocation.
Objectives: The primary null hypothesis of the DISCERN study is that, in highly co-morbid patients aged over 75 years with stage 5 chronic kidney disease, medical management including maintenance dialysis compared to medical treatment alone is associated with no differences in the outcome of mortality. Secondary null hypotheses will examine the effect of the same comparison upon the outcomes of quality of life, burden of hospitalisation and cost-effectiveness.
Study Design: The DISCERN study is a randomised, controlled trial with blinding of outcome assessment. Participants will be randomised on a 1:1 basis to the two study arms: Medical treatment with maintenance dialysis, OR medical treatment (with no maintenance dialysis). 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Human Research Ethics Committee (CRGH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Concord Hospital
Research and Governance Office
Building 20, Ground Floor
Hospital Rd, Concord NSW 2037</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/10/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Martin Gallagher</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 5, 1 King Street,
Newtown NSW 2042</address>
      <phone>+612 8052 4552</phone>
      <fax>+612 8088 6088</fax>
      <email>mgallagher@georginstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sarah Coggan</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 5, 1 King Street,
Newtown NSW 2042</address>
      <phone>+612 8052 4566</phone>
      <fax>+612 8088 6088</fax>
      <email>scoggan@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Martin Gallagher</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 5, 1 King Street,
Newtown NSW 2042</address>
      <phone>+612 8052 4566</phone>
      <fax>+612 8088 6088</fax>
      <email>mgallagher@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sarah Coggan</name>
      <address>The George Institute for Global Health
Level 5, 1 King Street,
Newtown NSW 2042</address>
      <phone>+612 8052 4566</phone>
      <fax>+612 8088 6088</fax>
      <email>scoggan@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>