<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335278">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/04/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/04/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000282088</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Enhancing the effects of the Positive Thinking Program: a longitudinal evaluation in 8-9 year old children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Longitudinal study of an enhanced Aussie Optimism: Positive Thinking Program in preventing internalising disorders in 8-9 year old children in Independent Goverment schools in Perth Metropolitan area.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Aussie Optimism Program: Positive Thinking Skills (AOP:PTS)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>18931
Healthway</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mental Health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Thirty primary schools will be selected from all the Independent Goverments and private schools in Perth Metropolitan area. They will be assigned at random to either the intervention or control condition. School principals will be invited to participate with the understanding that follow-up assessments will take place at post-test, 6 months and 18, months. A visit and presentation to each of the school principals and teachers involved in the implementation will then follow whereby the rationale and methodology are explained. This presentation will highlight the manner in which the program can be integrated into the regular school curriculum and will encourage individual teachers to become supporters and advocates for the program.  The teachers will be trained in running groups and the principles of the "Positive Thinking" over a 1 day (8 hours) training course run by clinical psychologists who are members of the research team. The training workshop involves information, activity demonstrations, activity practice, feedback and implementation planning. Teachers in the intervention condition will be provided with programs manual and resources.  The full involvement of Year 4 &amp;5 teachers in the selected schools will be critical to the program's success so time will be taken to emphasize the benefits and outcomes for teachers. They will complete an implementation checklist after each session to assess program integrity. 5 x 1 hour coaching sessions will be offered with the intervention schools and teachers. Parents will be addressed as part of the usual parent teacher meetings that are held at the beginning of the year. This project will be fully explained and any questions that are raised will be answered. The active consent of children and parents will be sought after the study has been fully explained to them via school meetings and formal information and consent form.
In April 2010, the assessment battery will be administered to the children in the 15 intervention schools to provide baseline pre-test measures of depressive symptoms, attribution style, anxiety, demographic and emotional competence. At the same time, two trained psychologists will assess any child scoring over 17 on the Children's Depression Inventory (CDI) and 42 on the  Spence Children's Anxiety Scale (SCAS) using The Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, 4th Edition(DSM-IV): Child version (ADIS-C). Follow-up times with the children will be organised in a confidential manner to avoid stigmatisation. For cases where depressive or anxiety disorders are identified, parents will be contacted, and the results of the assessment will be discussed with them. Identified children will be referred for psychological assistance if parents request this. The same procedure will be repeated at the 6 and 18 month follow-up intervals. And additional reply paid envelopes will be provided so that parents can seal their responses. After each follow-up session, a newsletter will be sent to parents and teachers thanking for their involvement, updating the progress, and collecting any changes of address information from parents. 
The weekly intervention sessions will be run in the usual class room groups and the interview session will focus on confidentiality. The mixed sex groups will be conducted by teachers at the school at designated times that are convenient over 10 weekly one-hour sessions. Process measures for children will be administered at the conclusion of each session. The social validity of the program will be measured by the use of social acceptability questionnaires for all key stakeholders, children, parents, and teachers. The instruments that will be used are: 1) Children's Attributional Style Questionnaire (CASQ; Seligman et al.,1984), 2) CDI (Kovacs, 1992), 3) SCAS (Spence,1998), 4) The Assessment of Children's Emotional Skills (ACES; Schultz, Trentacosta, Izard, Leaf, &amp; Mostow, 2004), 5) ADIS-C  (Silverman &amp; Albano, 1996), 6) The Extended Strengths &amp; Difficulties Questionnaires (SDQ-P; Goodman, 1999), 7) Implementation Checklist assessing the degree that teachers have covered the specified information in AOP:PTS program and 8) Demographic information on socioeconomic status, ethnic origin, family structure, family health and history of mental health problems. Administration of the program will be closely monitored by the chief-investigators for adherence to assigned intervention program via log books, reports, interviews and observations made by research assistants and friendly follow-up sessions to help teachers get through the program and by addressing any problems that they might have. Dosage effects will be measured via attendance of students at session.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will run their regular Health and Physical Education Curriculum as usual during the intervention period. Parents will be addressed as part of the usual parent teacher meetings that are held at the beginning of the year. This project will be fully explained and any questions that are raised will be answered. The active consent of children and parents will be sought after the study has been fully explained to them via school meetings and formal information and consent form.
In April 2010, the assessment battery will be administered to the children in the 15 control schools to provide baseline pre-test measures of depressive symptoms, attribution style, anxiety, demographic and emotional competence. At the same time, two trained psychologists will assess any child scoring over 17 on the CDI and 42 on the SCAS using the ADIS-C. Follow-up times with the children will be organised in a confidential manner to avoid stigmatisation. For cases where depressive or anxiety disorders are identified, parents will be confidentially contacted, and the results of the assessment will be discussed with them. Identified children will be referred for psychological assistance if parents request this. The same procedure will be repeated at the 6 and 18 month follow-up intervals. And additional reply paid envelope will be provided so that parents can seal their responses. After each follow-up session, a newsletter will be sent to parents and teachers thanking for their involvement, updating the progress, and collecting any changes of address information from parents. Process measures for children will be administered at the conclusion of each session. The instruments that will be used are: 1) CASQ (Seligman et al.,1984), 2) CDI (Kovacs, 1992), 3) SCAS (Spence,1998), 4) ACES; (Schultz, Trentacosta, Izard, Leaf, &amp; Mostow, 2004), 5) ADIS-C (Silverman &amp; Albano, 1996), 6) SDQ-P (Goodman, 1999) and 7)  Demographic information on socioeconomic status, ethnic origin, family structure, family health and history of mental health problems.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 1: The intervention group will report lower levels of depressive symptoms than the control group and this outcome will be assessed by the CDI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: At post-test (at completion of 10 week intervention), 6 and 18-month follow-ups.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome 2: The intervention group will report lower levels of anxiety symptoms than the control group and this outcome will be assessed by the SCAS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: At post-test (at completion of 10 week intervention), 6 and 18-month follow-ups</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 1: Parents in the intervention group will report lower levels of internalising and externalising symptomatology in their children than the parents in the control group and this outcome will be assessed by the SDQ-P.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 1: At post-test (at completion of 10 week intervention), 6 and 18-month follow-ups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 2: The intervention group will report a more positive attribution style than the control group and this outcome will be assessed by the CASQ.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 2: At post-test (at completion of 10 week intervention), 6 and 18-month follow-ups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 3: The intervention group will report higher levels of emotional attribution accuracy than the control group and this outcome will be assessed by the ACES.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 3: At post-test (at completion of 10 week intervention), 6 and 18-month follow-ups</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 4: The proportion of control group children diagnose as clinical will be significantly greater than the intervention group and this outcome will be assessed by the ADIS-C.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 4: Pre (Baseline test) and post test (at completion of 10 week intervention), 6 and 18 months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 5: The proportion of intervention group children diagnose as  healthy and remain healthy will significantly greater than the control group and this outcome will be assessed by the CDI and SCAS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 5: Pre (Baseline test) and post test (at completion of 10 week intervention), 6 and 18 months follow-ups.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 6: Children who recieve a high dose of the program will report lower levels of internalising symptoms compared to children who receive a low-dose of the program and these outcomes will be assessed by the CDI and SCAS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 6:Post-test (at completion of 10-week intervention), 6 and 18 months follow-ups.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome 7: Students, parents, and teachers will rate the program as socially acceptable and this outcome will be assessed by the Implementation Checklist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint 7: Pre (Baseline test) and post test (at completion of 10 week intervention), 6 and 18 months follow-ups.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The target population consists of Year 4 and 5 students from Independent Goverment and private schools in the Perth Metropolitan area. These schools are targeted because research has shown that private schools have the potential to engender a school culture through aspects such as bullying and pressure to achieve higher level standards that may challenge students' mental health (Watt, 2003). Power considerations dictated that we recruit relatively large schools that have access to about 150 Year 4 and 5 students. We will select these schools from the lower end of the Socioeconomic status (SES) scale. Although SES ratings for Independent Goverment and private schools tend to be relatively high compared to State Schools, students from lower SES private schools should still provide more scope for improvement on the outcome measures than students from higher SES private schools. The sampling strategies involves recruiting private schools with large numbers of Year 4 &amp; 5s, and relatively low SES.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>9</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Year 4 and 5 from public schools in Perth metropolitan area and surrounding surburbs.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Fifteen schools were randomly selected from the population of non-government schools in  Western Australia (WA) which was dictated by considerations of statistical power, that the selected schools had at least 56 Grade 4 students and at least 38 Grade 5 students. Each of the 15 schools was then matched to another school from the population according to socio-economic status and the number of students in Grades 4 and 5. For each matched pair, one school was then randomly allocated to the intervention group and the other school was allocated to the control group.
Allocation concealment procedure was applied by computer central randomisation method.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/04/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/09/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>27/09/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1177</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>868</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>6155</postcode>
    <postcode>6059</postcode>
    <postcode>6923</postcode>
    <postcode>6955</postcode>
    <postcode>6065</postcode>
    <postcode>6024</postcode>
    <postcode>6401</postcode>
    <postcode>6028</postcode>
    <postcode>6062</postcode>
    <postcode>6026</postcode>
    <postcode>6060</postcode>
    <postcode>6530</postcode>
    <postcode>6052</postcode>
    <postcode>6156</postcode>
    <postcode>6231</postcode>
    <postcode>6233</postcode>
    <postcode>6110</postcode>
    <postcode>6054</postcode>
    <postcode>6100</postcode>
    <postcode>6076</postcode>
    <postcode>6531</postcode>
    <postcode>6025</postcode>
    <postcode>6210</postcode>
    <postcode>6941</postcode>
    <postcode>6936</postcode>
    <postcode>6164</postcode>
    <postcode>6969</postcode>
    <postcode>6018</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr. Rosie Rooney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology,
Curtin University of Technology,
GPO Box U1987 Perth, WA 6845.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Healthway</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Healthway, PO Box 1284, West Perth WA 6872</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr. Shari Hassan</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology,
Curtin University of Technology,
GPO Box U1987 Perth, WA 6845.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Prof. Clare Roberts</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology,
Curtin University of Technology,
GPO Box U1987 Perth, WA 6845.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr. Robert Kane</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology,
Curtin University of Technology,
GPO Box U1987 Perth, WA 6845.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current project is a new efficacy trial to evaluate the enhanced version of the Aussie Optimism- Positive Thinking Skills Program (AOP-PTS). This research project builds on recent information about emotional competence and cognitive skills in the middle childhood period to promote and enhance mental health benefits for 8-9 year olds. The projected outcomes are: Children who received the enhanced version of AOP-PTS program in Year 4 and 5 will report lower levels of internalising symptomatology (anxiety and depressive symptoms) and negative attributional style at the post test, 6 and 18 months follow-up compared to the children in control condition.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://psych.curtin.edu.au/research/aussieoptimism/</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Kennedy, T. Rooney, R., Kane, R., &amp; Hassan, S. (2015). The Enhanced Aussie Optimism Positive Thinking Skills Program: Assessing the relationship between internalising symptoms and family functioning in children aged 9-11 years of age. Frontiers in Psychology. 6:504.doi:10.3389/fpsyg.2015.00504 

Myles-Pallister, J, Hassan, S., Rooney, R, Kane, R, (2014). The efficacy of the Enhanced Aussie Optimism Positive Thinking Skills Program in improving social and emotional learning in middle childhood. Frontiers in Psychology 5 (909):1-11. Doi: 10.3389/fpsyg.2014.00909.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee, c/- Office of Research and Development, Curtin University of Technology, GPO Box U1987, Perth,  WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>165/2009</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/12/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Robert Kane</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology,
Curtin University of Technology,
GPO Box U1987,
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 7992 (Perth, WA)</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 2464 (Perth, WA)</fax>
      <email>c.roberts@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dr. Rosie Rooney</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology,
Curtin University of Technology,
GPO Box U1987,
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3050 (Perth, WA)</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 2464 (Perth, WA)</fax>
      <email>r.rooney@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr. Shari Hassan</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology,
Curtin University of Technology,
GPO Box U1987,
Perth, Western Australia 6845</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 7992 (Perth, WA)</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9266 2464 (Perth, WA)</fax>
      <email>s.hassan@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Associate Prof. Rosie Rooney</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Speech Pathology, Curtin University, GPO Box U1987, Perth, Western Australia 6845
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 3050 (Perth, WA) </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.rooney@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>