<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347807">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/12/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/12/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001256965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessment of a single intravenous (IV) iron therapy versus oral iron in the management of preoperative anaemia patients undergoing elective surgery at the Launceston General Hospital</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Assessment of a single intravenous (IV) iron therapy versus oral iron in the management of preoperative anaemia patients undergoing elective surgery at the Launceston General Hospital (LGH).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The study is to assess the prevalence of preoperative anaemia at the Tasmanian population and to offer the most appropriate treatment preoperatively.</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anaemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaemia</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The patients with anaemia will be randomised between oral iron sulphate of 325 mg daily until the time of operation and a single iron carboxymaltose infusion 15mg/Kg body weight once only.  The control group will receive treatment as per standard care at the LGH. 

Outcome measures: by Hb and iron studies.</interventions>
    <comparator>Age and sex matched preoperative patients who are not received intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the efficacy of oral iron versus IV iron in preoperative anaemia setting

Tools: Via Haemoglobin (Hb) and iron studies measurement</outcome>
      <timepoint>this timepoint will be measured until the end of the study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the prevalence of preoperative anaemia in all elective surgery patients in Tasmanian population. Tools: Via assessment of overall number of patients who will be presented for elective surgery at our institution ( tertiary referral centre for the north of Tasmania, Australia) versus the actual number of anaemic patients according the study criteria during the study period. As screening tool we are using a non-invasive Masimo Pronto-7 device in measuring Hb versus standard laboratory during preoperative screening</outcome>
      <timepoint>this timepoint will be measured until the end of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess patient outcome, recovery and quality of life (QoL)Via a dedicated Health related QoL questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>this timepoint will be measured until the end of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess near patient testing with Hb assessment versus standard Hb measurement.
Tools: Correlation between both Hb readings at the same time.</outcome>
      <timepoint>this timepoint will be measured until the end of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurements of operative outcome and the complications of the procedure for all groups.
Tools: via a dedicated form recording all characteristics of the operative intervention in correlation with the outcome.</outcome>
      <timepoint>this timepoint will be measured until the end of the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The inclusion criteria for anaemic patients in the study will be a haemoglobin level above 85g/L, but &lt; normal level in males and in females as measured by an accredited LGH pathology laboratory in addition to low iron stores.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Presence of a specific cause for anaemia apart from haematinic deficiency 
2. Haematological disorders or other malignancies associated with anaemia</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>These patients will be offered to take part in the study at the Launceston General Hospital (LGH) preadmission clinic over a the trial period. The patients will be randomised after an informed consent form obtained when they are eligible for the study by a dedicated research nurse using a random number schedule. Patients will be randomised to 1) intravenous iron or 2) oral iron therapy.</concealment>
    <sequence>A randomised block of closed intervention-envelopes prepared by a third party (the  Pharmacy Department) will be used by the research coordinator and correlated to a unique patient trial number in order to minimise any possible bias.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The study is a prospective, open-label, randomised controlled trial.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/01/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>6/11/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>154</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Clifford Craig Medical Trust Fund</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5
Launceston General Hospital
Charles street
Launceston, Tasmania 7250
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Launceston General Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Charles street
Launceston, Tasmania 7250 
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is a prospective randomised trial screening elective surgical patients from both sexes with full blood count and iron studies during the study period. These patients will be offered to take part in the study at the Launceston General Hospital (LGH). In our interim analysis for a similar orthopaedic trial, approximately 15-20% of patients presented with low haemoglobin in this cohort of patients. 

This study is to be conducted by staff working within the Launceston General Hospital, (LGH) recruiting patients from the Northern half of the state of Tasmania and will be a collaborative project involving the Departments of Clinical Haematology, Anaesthesia, Surgery and Pathology as well as University of Tasmania as part of their collaborative work. It has agreement with the Admissions department of the hospital in regards to notification of prospective patients and their hospital booking dates.  

All patients who offered to participate in the trial will be counselled on any side effects of the iron therapy. If participants decide to withdraw from the study at any time, it will have no effect on their care or procedure.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tasmanian Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Tasmania
Private Bag 01
Hobart, Tas 7001
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/10/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H11973</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>A/Professor Alhossain A. Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital
Charles Street, Launceston, TAS 7250</address>
      <phone>+61373487111</phone>
      <fax>+61373487695</fax>
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Alhossain A. Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital
Charles Street, Launceston, TAS 7250</address>
      <phone>+61373487111</phone>
      <fax>+61373487695</fax>
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Alhossain A. Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital
Charles Street, Launceston, TAS 7250</address>
      <phone>+61373487111</phone>
      <fax>+61373487695</fax>
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Alhossain Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital 
Charles Street
TAS 7250 Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61367776777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>