<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335859">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/01/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/01/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000084987</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Examining the effects of serotonin on perceptual awareness and attention.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In healthy adults, how do buspirone and citalopram compared with placebo effect switch rate in perceptual rivalry?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Binocular rivalry switch rate</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Auditory rivalry switch rate</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Probabilistic reversal learning</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Oral tablets of Buspirone (15mg), Citalopram (20mg) or placebo will be administered to healthy adults. Each participant will participate in 4 separate sessions of testing separated by at least 2 weeks: session1/Placebo + Buspirone (2.5 hours later), session2/ Citalopram + Buspirone (2.5 hours later), session3/ Placebo + Placebo (2.5 hours later), session4/ Citalopram + Placebo (2.5 hours later). The study will investigate the neurochemical basis of binocular rivalry, a phenomenon that is a feature of normal vision. No abnormal condition or disease is being investigated as part of this study. The medications in this study are already approved by the Australian Therapeutic Goods Administration.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo identical in taste and appearance but containing none of the active ingredients. A total of 4 placebo tablets will be administered to each person over the 4 testing sessions. Session1/ Placebo + Busprione, session3/ Placebo + Placebo, and session4/ Citalopram + Placebo (2nd tablet taken 2.5 hours later).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Binocular rivalry switch rate - when visual input is ambiguous, one's conscious visual percept alternates between the two possible interpretations of the visual stimuli (as occurs with a number of popular visual illusions). Participants will be presented the required visual images on a computer screen and will be asked to push buttons on a keyboard every time their visual perception switches between the possible interpretations. Switch rate will be calculated as the number of reported changes in perceptual experience every minute.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.5 or 3.5 hours after administration of Citalopram or Buspirone, respectively, or placebo.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Auditory Rivalry switch rate - when the source of auditory input is ambiguous, one's conscious auditory percept may alternate between the two possible interpretations. Participants will be presented the required auditory tones through headphones and will be asked to push buttons on a keyboard every time their auditory perception switches between the possible interpretations. Switch rate will be calculated as the number of reported changes in perceptual experience every minute.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.5 or 3.5 hours after administration of Citalopram or Buspirone, respectively, or placebo.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Probabilistic reversal learning -- Participants will be asked to view a standard computer screen and will be presented with two coloured patches. Participants will be told that one of the coloured patches is 'correct' on each presentation. If they choose correctly, they will get one point, with the goal of the task to get as many points as possible. Participants will be informed that one colour is more likely to be correct than the other colour on average, but that the 'lucky' colour might reverse from time to time during the session. At each presentation, participants will indicate their choice via key press, and will receive basic feedback about the correctness of their choice. Performance measures will be related to the number of correct choices made during testing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1.5 or 3.5 hours after administration of Citalopram or Buspirone, respectively, or placebo.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy adults</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous personal or first-degree family history of psychiatric or neurological disorders or suicidality, impairements in vision or audition, hepatic or cardiac function (including diagnosed hypertension), pregnancy or breastfeeding, previous intolerance or hypersensitivity to buspirone, citalopram or related medications, current or recent (last 2 weeks) use of psychotropic medication, psychoactive substances or any other medications known to interact with buspirone or citalopram. Participants will also be excluded if their blood pressure is found to be above 140/100 and remains above this level for fifteen minutes.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be carried out by computer. All participants will be involved in all treatment conditions, and equal numbers of participants will be allocated to each sequence. Allocation to a particular sequence of conditions will be randomised, and the particular drug being administered will be in a container labeled by a third party.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>All participants receive all conditions of treatment over four separate sessions.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Psychological Sciences
The University of Melbourne
Victoria, 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Melbourne
Victoria, 3010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Olivia Carter</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Psychological Sciences
The University of Melbourne
Victoria, 3010</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Assoc/Prof Suresh Sundram</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Mental Health Research Institute of Victoria
Locked Bag 11
Parkville, Victoria 3052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Binocular rivalry occurs when different stimuli are presented to the left and right eye simultaneously. Under these conditions the observer will consciously perceive only one of the two images at a time, with the respective dominance of the two images alternating every few seconds. A similar phenomenon is also observed in hearing. Previous studies have shown that the rate of alternation is affected by certain medications that affect the serotonin system. We will administer two such medications to healthy individuals to further investigate how the serotonin system is involved in perceptual rivalry. The main implications of this study relate to pure research and understanding the neural mechanisms underlying perception. There is currently no clinical aim for this study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Royal Melbourne Hospital
Parkville, Victoria 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/07/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2009.648</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Melbourne Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alan Gilbert Building
The University of Melbourne
Victoria 3010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/08/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0932268</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Olivia Carter</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Sciences
The University of Melbourne
Victoria 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 6372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ocarter@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Olivia Carter</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Sciences
The University of Melbourne
Victoria 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 6372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ocarter@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Olivia Carter</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Sciences
The University of Melbourne
Victoria 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 6372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ocarter@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>