<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370666">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000955415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of exenatide once weekly on gastric emptying in healthy subjects..</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of exenatide once weekly on gastric emptying in healthy subjects under steady-state concentrations: a randomised controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>EXQW</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1. Exenatide QW 2mg or Exenatide Placebo to be injected, subcutaneously, once a week for 8 weeks. The injection is administered by one of the investigators to remove any issues relating to compliance.

2. A gastric emptying study using the gold standard technique (scintigraphy) will be performed at baseline and at 8 weeks. 20MBq of 99mTc-sulphur colloid and 7 MBq 67Ga-EDTA are used to perform this study. This equates to an effective radiation dose of 2.25mSv per study, and a total dose of 4.5mSv, which is within The RAH Radiation Safety Guidelines (upper limit 5mSv) and has been approved previously by the Research Ethics Committee of the Royal Adelaide Hospital. </interventions>
    <comparator>A total of 40 healthy subjects that have passed the screening test will be randomised to receive either exenatide QW or placebo, to allow for a 25% drop out rate resulting in a total of 30 completed subjects i.e. 15 in each group. Placebo will be identical to exenatide QW in appearance (without the active ingredient). Placebo will be supplied as a single dose kit containing a vial of powder, a pre-filled syringe of diluent, a vial connector and two needles (one spare). The powder is suspended using the diluent supplied. The diluent is a clear, colourless to pale yellow to pale brown solution. Placebo consists of sucrose encapsulated within biodegradable polyglactin microspheres. During dose preparation, a custom diluent is added to these microspheres, which are dispersed into the diluent to create a suspension. Following administration of the suspension, the polymer biodegrades over time. The diluent contains carmellose sodium, sodium chloride, polysorbate 20, monobasic sodium phosphate monohydrate, dibasic sodium phosphate (as heptahydrate), sodium hydroxide (pre-filled pen only), and water for injections.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the effect of 8 weeks treatment with exenatide QW (once weekly) versus placebo on gastric emptying, measured by scintigraphy. </outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the effect of 8 weeks treatment with exenatide QW (once weekly) versus placebo on postprandial glycaemia in response to a standardised meal. Blood glucose concentrations will be measured immediately using a glucose oxidase analyser (Yellow Springs Institute, USA). Plasma and serum will be separated from the remainder of each sample and stored at  80 degree Celsius for subsequent measurements of plasma insulin, C-peptide, and glucagon concentrations by assay.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples are taken on each of the gastric emptying study days (i.e. on Day 1 and at 8 weeks). Blood samples are drawn at t = 5, 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90, 105, 120, 180 and 240 min, where t=0 represents the time of meal completion. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the effect of 8 weeks treatment with exenatide QW (once weekly) versus placebo on the rate of absorption of the glucose analogue, 3-O-methylglucose (3-OMG). Plasma will be separated from the blood sample and stored at  80 degree Celsius for subsequent measurements 3-OMG concentrations by assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples are taken on each of the gastric emptying study days (i.e. on Day 1 and at 8 weeks). Blood samples are drawn at t = 5, 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90, 105, 120, 180 and 240 min, where t=0 represents the time of meal completion. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the effect of 8 weeks treatment with exenatide QW (once weekly) versus placebo on gastrointestinal symptoms. A total of 9 gastrointestinal symptoms will be assessed using a validated questionnaire with a score of 0=symptom not present, 1=mild symptom, 2=moderate symptom, 3=severe symptom with a total maximum score of 27.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Healthy male subjects aged 55  70 years 
2. Healthy post-menopausal female subjects between 55  70 years (Postmenopausal will be defined as greater than or equal to 55 y of age or at least 12 months since last menses). Post-menopausal will be defined as amenorrhoea for at least 12 months or more, following cessation of all exogenous hormonal treatments and FSH levels in the post-menopausal range.
3. Body mass index (BMI) 25  35 kg/m2
4. Haemoglobin and ferritin in the normal range for gender and age. 
5. Subject has provided written informed consent.  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>55</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Evidence of renal disease (i.e. a creatinine clearance cut-off of less than 50 ml/min. Calculated creatinine clearance will be determined as follows using the Cockcroft-Gault equation: Cr clearance = [140 - age (years) x weight (kg)] / [0.814 x serum creatinine (micromol/L)] (For female subjects, multiply Cr clearance x 0.85)).
2. Iron stores, or liver function tests outside the following ranges:
- Alanine aminotransferase (ALT): less than 55 U/L
- Alkaline phosphatase (ALP): 30 - 110 U/L
- Aspartate transaminase (AST): less than 45 U/L
- Total bilirubin: 2 - 24 micromol/L
- Haemoglobin: 115  165 g/L (Females); 130  180 g/L (Males)
- Ferritin: 15  200 micrograms/L (Females); 30  300 micrograms/L (Males)
3. Hepatic or cardiovascular disease, pancreatitis (subjects with past history of acute or chronic pancreatitis, or amylase or lipase levels greater than 2 fold upper limit of normal at screening, gastric surgery, or known gastroparesis on history or screening biochemistry tests.
4. Subjects with any history of cancer, except for basal cell carcinoma or in situ carcinoma of the cervix treated with apparent success with curative therapy equal to 12 months prior to screening or other malignancies treated with apparent success with curative therapy equal to 5 years prior to screening will be excluded.  
5. History of any clinically significant disease or disorder which may either put the volunteer at risk because of participation in the study, or influence the results or the volunteers ability to participate in the study.
6. Serum calcitonin level at screening suggestive of thyroid c-cell hyperplasia (greater than 50 nanogram/l). Personal or family history of medullary thyroid cancer or Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia syndrome type 2 (MEN 2).
7. History of hyperthyroidism or uncontrolled hypothyroidism.
8. Evidence of diabetes based on history or HbA1c equal to 6.5% at screening.
9. Use of drugs potentially affecting gastrointestinal motility (these include but are not limited to the following medications: opiates, anticholinergics, levodopa, beta blockers, clonidine, nitrates, tricyclic antidepressants, selective serotonin re-uptake inhibitors, phosphodiesterase type 5 inhibitors, sumatriptan, metoclopramide, domperidone, cisapride, tegaserod, or erythromycin)
10. Current history of smoking or consumption of  greater than 2 units alcohol daily on a regular basis
11. Known or suspected history of alcohol or drug abuse, as judged by the Investigator. 
12. History of severe allergy/hypersensitivity or ongoing allergy/hypersensitivity, or history of hypersensitivity to exenatide or drugs with a similar chemical structure or its components.
13. Known hypersensitivity to heparin or IV infusion equipment, plastics, adhesive or silicone, or know history of hypotension or infusion site reactions with IV administration of other medicines
14. Systolic BP  less than 90mmHg or  greater than 140mmHg; Diastolic BP less than 50mmHg or greater than 90mmHg; Heart rate  less than 45 or  greater 85 beats per minute at the screening test.
15. Plasma donation within 1 month of screening or blood donation / loss greater than 500ml during the 3 months prior to screening.
16. Participation in any research studies involving exposure to ionising radiation within the previous 12 months
17. Vegetarian diet</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation will be carried out by the Pharmacy at the Royal Adelaide Hospital (RAH). Allocation will involve contacting the holder of the allocation schedule (RAH Pharmacy) who is at a separate site to provide the medication (so that this is blinded to both the participant and study investigator).</concealment>
    <sequence> Sequence generation will be carried out by the Pharmacy at the Royal Adelaide Hospital using simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The study will follow a randomised double-blind placebo-controlled parallel design</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The two analysis sets include the intervention group and the control/placebo group. Analysis will be undertaken on a per-protocol basis. Analysis of covariance will be used to compare changes in gastric emptying in each group at 8 weeks, adjusting for baseline values. Secondary endpoints will be analysed in similar fashion. Relationships between the reduction in postprandial glycaemia and change in gastric emptying and between the reduction in postprandial glycaemia and baseline rate of gastric emptying, and the mean values will be compared using Students t tests. We will collaborate with our biostatistician prior to reporting the results. The data will be prepared for publication in a peer-reviewed journal. All records will be kept a minimum of 15 years in the Discipline of Medicine and the study will maintain the anonymity of the participants. No medical records will be required for this project. Only the investigators will have access to the research data and results. The Discipline of Medicine, University of Adelaide, will own all data from this study. Determination of sample size was calculated in consultation with a professional biostatistician. Based on a previous study evaluating gastric emptying and postprandial glycaemia using a similar mixed meal, we would assume an intragastric retention of ~52% at 100 min with SD of 29%. We, therefore, estimate that recruiting 40 participants in total (20 in each group) would detect a 50% increase in retention with alpha 0.05 and power 80%, while allowing for a dropout rate of 25% i.e. 30 patients (15 in each group) will complete the study.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/01/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>North Terrace, Adelaide, SA, 5000
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AstraZeneca Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5 Alma Road
North Ryde NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Adelaide</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>North Terrace, Adelaide, SA, 5005
Australia
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is designed to evaluate the effects of 8 weeks treatment with the glucagon-like peptide-1 agonist, exenatide (once weekly (QW)), on the rate of stomach emptying, glucose absorption and blood glucose and plasma insulin concentrations in healthy subjects. This is a randomised parallel designed study. Subjects recruited into the study who pass screening criteria will be randomised to receive exenatide QW or matching placebo. they will have a gastric emptying study performed using the gold standard technique (scintigraphy) at baseline and at 8 weeks. Immediately following the first gastric emptying study they will commence treatment with exenatide QW or Placebo, administered subcutaneously at weekly intervals. Glucose absorption, blood glucose and plasma insulin will be assessed during each of the gastric emptying measurements.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of the Royal Adelaide Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/RAH/183 R20160508</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Karen Jones</name>
      <address>University of Adelaide
Discipline of Medicine
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building,
Royal Adelaide Hospital
Frome Rd
ADELAIDE SA 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5394</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8223 3870</fax>
      <email>karen.jones@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Seva Hatzinikolas</name>
      <address>University of Adelaide
Discipline of Medicine
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building,
Royal Adelaide Hospital
Frome Rd
ADELAIDE SA 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2915</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8223 3870</fax>
      <email>seva.hatzinikolas@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Karen Jones</name>
      <address>University of Adelaide
Discipline of Medicine
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building,
Royal Adelaide Hospital
Frome Rd
ADELAIDE SA 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5394</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8223 3870</fax>
      <email>karen.jones@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Karen Jones</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine, University of Adelaide
Level 6, Eleanor Harrald Building,
Royal Adelaide Hospital
ADELAIDE SA 5005</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 5394</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8223 3870</fax>
      <email>karen.jones@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>