<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373245">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000987369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Prospective Randomized Trial Comparing the Bard Inlay Optima Stent with the Cook Universa Soft Ureteral Stents Using The Validated Ureteric Stent Symptom Questionnaire</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Prospective Randomized Trial Comparing the Bard Inlay Optima Stent with the Cook Universa Soft Ureteral Stents Using The Validated Ureteric Stent Symptom Questionnaire in patients undergoing unilateral retrograde ureteral stent placement  </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1198-7288</utrn>
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Upper urinary tract calculi </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is comparing the Bard Inlay Optima and Cook Universa Soft Ureteral Stents when used for stent insertion for upper urinary tract calculi or large stones before lithotripsy or after ureteroscopy at the Townsville Hospital. 
Materials: The materials being used will be first and foremost the two aforementioned stents  the Bard Inlay Optima and Cook Universa Soft Ureteral Stents. Both will be inserted as part of the clinical trial by urological registrars or consultant surgeons at the Townsville Hospital. Their post operative stent symptoms will be measured through two methods. First, the Ureteral Stent Symptoms Questionnaire (USSQ)  a validated questionnaire produced by the Bristol Urological Institute to measure post-operative stent related symptoms. The second material being used will be the International Prostate Symptom Score (IPSS), a written screening tool which is classically used only for the tracking and diagnosis of symptoms relating to Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia, but has previously been used in other literature to measure stent related symptoms. 
Procedures: Following patient consenting for the procedure, patients will have the stent they are randomized to (either Bard Inlay Optima or Cook Universa Soft), inserted by the urologist registrar or consultant as stated above. Intra-operatively, multi-length double J stents of either the Bard Inlay Optima (4.7 French) and Cook Universa Soft (5 french) variety will be inserted. Post operatively, patients will be provided with appropriate medications for stent pain if desired. Patient narcotic or anti-cholinergic use will be recorded. 
Patients will be then receive a phone call from the Principal Investigator (PI) at 1 and 3 weeks after insertion and surveyed as per the USSQ and IPSS. We would note that throughout this the PI conducting the survey will be blinded to which stent was inserted in the patient. All data will be recorded in a relevant data collection tool in which data pertaining to the date of procedure, average 24-hour narcotic usage during admission, length of procedure, patient characteristics, USSQ score, IPSS +/- early stent removal will be recorded. 
Who: The intervention will be delivered by a recognized urology registrar or consultant urologist at the Townsville Hospital. The survey will be conducted by the Principal Investigator, a doctor with experience in urology. 
Mode of Delivery: The surveys above will be delivered via telephone surveys delivered individually to each patient with the stent inserted. 
Number of times: The intervention (the stenting) will only be delivered once however patients will be followed up at two points  1 week and 3 weeks post operatively. 
Location: The intervention will occur at the Townsville Hospital, a tertiary hospital in Queensland, Australia. 
Intervention Adherence or Fidelity: Patients will be followed up if they have early stent removal and this will be documented accordingly in the data collection tool. A data monitoring board will be set up for the study to ensure randomization and protocol is being carried out as appropriate. </interventions>
    <comparator>No control group is possible however the comparator will be the Cook Universa Soft. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>USSQ Urinary Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 week post stent insertion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>USSQ Pain Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week post stent insertion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>USSQ General Health Score </outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week post stent insertion</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of participants which had early removal of stents. This will be defined as removal of stents prior to when it was medically indicated to have them removed. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Anytime within 3 weeks post stent insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>International Prostate Symptoms Score</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 week and 3 weeks post stent insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post operative narcotic and anticholinergic use. This will defined as determining the overall and mean 24 hour narcotic and anticholinergic intake during admission prior to discharge.  This will be done via reviewing patient medication charts in hospital. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Average 24 hour narcotic usage during admission prior to discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>USSQ Sexual Matters Score (note is meant to be primary outcome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 week post stent insertion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Setting and Target Participants: All consenting patients receiving stent insertion for upper urinary tract calculi or large stones before lithotripsy or after ureteroscopy at the Townsville Hospital

Inclusion criteria
	Patients undergoing unilateral retrograde ureteral stent placement 
	Age  over 18 years</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	Untreated urinary tract infections
	Undergoing additional transurethral procedures or bilateral calculi
	All patients with obstructive uropathy secondary to malignancy
	Anatomical deformities of the urinary tract such as Duplex or Complete Duplex Ureters 
	Pelvic radiation therapy
	Current bladder cancer
	Long term indwelling ureteric stents
	Indwelling catheter (IDC) or Suprapubic Catheter (SPC) dependent
	Performing clean intermittent self-catheterisation
	Ureteric stent present in last 31 days
	Post-operative sepsis
	Patients who do not speak English  USSQ version used has been only validated in English
	Patients with cognitive impairments or intellectual disabilities preventing them from comprehending or answering the USSQ
	Pregnant women
	Patients with history of:
-	Chronic pain 
-	Bladder or prostate surgeries including:
o	Radical Prostatectomy
o	Partial cystectomy
o	Diveritculectomy
o	Ureter reimplant
o	Other significant Bladder Surgeries
-	Neurogenic bladder
-	Chronic alpha-blocker medication, opioid analgesia or anticholinergics
-	Spinal cord injury
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will first be divided up into 32 groups of 4 (16 groups of 4 per stent; 64 patients per stent). Following this, 1 set of 32 unique numbers will be generated using the “Research Randomizer” (Version 4.0) software. Numbers to be assigned will range from 1 to 32 with each number in the set to remain unique. An assigned individual independent from the study to be steward of randomization will generate this list of numbers upon initiation of the study. From that list of numbers all odd numbers will be converted into “As” and all even numbers converted into “Bs”.

The randomization steward will then have this list of 16As and 16Bs assigned in the order they were generated to each group into a designated table document. For example, if the order generated was A,A,B,A, etc. the resultant table would read “Group 1 – A, Group 2 – A, Group 3 – B, etc., Group 4 - A”. The randomization steward will then decide at the beginning of the study A or B represents Bard or Cook stent groups. All this will be documented at the beginning of the “Stent Study Book” in the space provided.

These pre-assigned stent groups will be documented at the start of the book in order to ensure that theatre staff will collect the correct stent for the procedure if patients consent for the study. It will be made clear from the outset of the study to all theatre staff who collect the stents for the procedure that all investigators associated with the data collection and questionnaire process above will not be privy to this knowledge. 

Re-matching patient serial numbers and the relevant data collected during the data collection process to which type of stent they had inserted will only be revealed to any investigators associated with data collection upon completion of the data collection process described above. In doing so, both patient and investigators will be blinded. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Patients will first be divided up into 32 groups of 4 (16 groups of 4 per stent; 64 patients per stent). Following this, 1 set of 32 unique numbers will be generated using the “Research Randomizer” (Version 4.0) software. Numbers to be assigned will range from 1 to 32 with each number in the set to remain unique. An assigned individual independent from the study to be steward of randomization will generate this list of numbers upon initiation of the study. From that list of numbers all odd numbers will be converted into “As” and all even numbers converted into “Bs”.

The randomization steward will then have this list of 16As and 16Bs assigned in the order they were generated to each group into a designated table document. For example, if the order generated was A,A,B,A, etc. the resultant table would read “Group 1 – A, Group 2 – A, Group 3 – B, etc., Group 4 - A”. The randomization steward will then decide at the beginning of the study A or B represents Bard or Cook stent groups. All this will be documented at the beginning of the “Stent Study Book” in the space provided.

These pre-assigned stent groups will be documented at the start of the book in order to ensure that theatre staff will collect the correct stent for the procedure if patients consent for the study.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Data Monitoring
Data will be monitored by an independent committee organized by an assigned associate investigator (Doctor Rajan Narula, Consultant Urologist, Director of Urology at the Townsville Hospital). Regular meetings will be conducted to ensure that the study is following its protocol. The study will be ceased if at any point new information or studies are published suggesting that either stent being analysed has a superior stent related symptoms profile compared to the other. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Tests of normality will be done to ascertain parametric and non-parametric methods for statistical analysis. Where appropriate, data will be presented as mean, median and interquartile range.

Correlation and regression tests will be done to determine association between continuous variables. Chi square test will be used to determine association between categorical variables.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>128</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>0</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>19/01/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Townsville Hospital - Douglas</hospital>
    <postcode>4814 - Douglas</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Doctor Alexander Ngoo</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>100 Angus Smith Dr, Douglas QLD 4814
The Townsville Hospital </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Townsville Hospital Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ground Floor,100 Angus Smith Drive, Douglas QLD 4814</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Avant Doctors In Training Research Scholarship Program 2017</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>NSW State Office
Level 6, Darling Park 3, 201 Sussex Street Sydney NSW 2000
PO Box 746 Queen Victoria Building NSW 1230</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Phillipe Wolanski</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>100 Angus Smith Dr, Douglas QLD 4814
The Townsville Hospital</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Ureteral stents can often cause significant post-stent morbidity and discomfort. There are many different brands of stents currently available but there is no evidence that there is any difference between them in terms of stent related symptoms. This study aims to compare the Cook Universa Soft and Bard Inlay Optima Stents post-op stent related symptoms (SRS) in relation to the validated Ureteral Stent Symptom Questionnaire. This comparison will be through a randomized double-blinded trial of the two different brands of stents. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>N/A</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>N/A</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Townsville Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 670
Townsville Qld 4810</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/08/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373245-Stent Study Protocol V1 - ANZCRT - sans USSQ.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373245-PICF Consent Form.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alexander Ngoo</name>
      <address>PO Box 670
100 Angus Smith Drive, Douglas Queensland 4814
The Townsville Hospital</address>
      <phone>+61744331801</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>AlexanderGa-Onn.Ngoo@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alexander Ngoo</name>
      <address>PO Box 670
100 Angus Smith Drive, Douglas Queensland 4814
The Townsville Hospital</address>
      <phone>+61744331801</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>AlexanderGa-Onn.Ngoo@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alexander Ngoo</name>
      <address>PO Box 670
100 Angus Smith Drive, Douglas Queensland 4814
The Townsville Hospital</address>
      <phone>+61744331801</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>AlexanderGa-Onn.Ngoo@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alexander Ngoo</name>
      <address>PO Box 670
100 Angus Smith Drive, Douglas Queensland 4814
The Townsville Hospital</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>