<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372100">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000114347p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A prospective cohort study evaluating the incidence of and outcomes associated with dose reductions of diabetic medications in a population of older inpatients discharged to a nursing home</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective cohort study evaluating the incidence of and outcomes associated with dose reductions of diabetic medications in a population of older inpatients discharged to a nursing home</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1191-3355 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a prospective observational study design of a minimum number of 60 hospitalised, older patients discharged to Residential Care Facility (RCFs).  As part of usual care, treating clinicians routinely assess the appropriateness of continuing each of the antidiabetic medications (oral and/or injectable) and at what dose. Glycohaemoglobin (HbA1c), as a marker of glycaemic control, is a blood test routinely done when a patient with diabetes is admitted to hospital. Older patients (&gt;75 years) with type 2 Diabetes (DM) treated with antidiabetic medication (oral +/- injectable agents) being discharged to a nursing home will be identified by clinical pharmacists on the Acute Medical Unit (AMU) or longer stay medical wards. The clinical pharmacists will ask the patient and/or carers if the research team can approach them to discuss the project. Patients and/or their carers will then be approached by the researchers (not involved in the patients care) and asked if they are interested in participating.

 Patients enrolled in the study will act as their own control. Rates of emergency presentations and admissions in the 6 months prior to admission will be compared to those in 6 months after discharge (followed prospectively for 6 months) in both patients who had a diabetes medication deprescribed  (Group A)  and those who did not (Group B). Routine HbA1c at admission (as a marker of glycaemic control in the preceding 3 months) will be compared to a repeat HbA1c 3 months after enrollment (a routine blood test to be performed by the GP).. 
Quality of life outcomes at 30 and 90 days will be via phone contact with participants / next of kin/or RCF. 
Deprescribing is defined as a drug dose reduction or cessation. Insulin adjustments are common in hospital and a dose reduction in insulin will not be considered deprescribing, however, cessation of a particular insulin dose or type of insulin will be considered deprescribing.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients enrolled in the study will act as their own control. Rates of emergency presentations and admissions in the 6 months prior to admission will be compared to those in 6 months after discharge (followed prospectively for 6 months) in both patients who had a diabetes medication deprescribed  (Group A)  and those who did not (Group B). .</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of deprescribing of antidiabetic medication in patients discharged to RCF - information from hospital  and GP records and medication charts review</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of re-prescribing of antidiabetic medication that was ceased in hospital
Collected via medication chart review and GP records </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, 90 days and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HbA1c at 3 months to ascertain glycaemic control.
Information recorded from hospital and GP records</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of the Emergency department presentation or readmission (to a South Australian Public Teaching Hospital) or unplanned GP assessments. 
Assessed by hospital records and phone calls to Residential Care Facility at the prescribed time-points </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, 90 days, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mortality
Information gathered  from hospital records, follow-up contacts.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, 90 days, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of re-admissions related specifically to diabetes treatment, i.e. hypoglycemia, hyperglycemia or hyperglycaemic hyperosmolar syndrome as primary reason for admission.
Information from hospital records</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, 90 days, 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Quality of life - administration of Short Form 8 questionnaire (SF-8)</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days, 90 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) Type 2 Diabetes aged &gt;75
(2) Medical inpatient within the Southern Adelaide Local Health Network- with a length of stay greater than 48 hours (to signify a significant hospital admission where a medication review will have occurred by the treating team)
(3) Discharge destination RCF
(4) HbA1C &lt;8% (64mmol/mol) during current admission
(5) Currently managed with antidiabetic medication (oral and/or injectable)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>75</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) Current Hospital admission directly related to diabetes blood glucose management, i.e. cause of admission due to hypoglycaemia or hyperglycaemic hyperosmolar syndrome
(2) Patients determine to be terminally ill 
(3) Patients not discharged to a Residential Care Facility
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The analysis will be primarily descriptive. The primary variable of interest is the incidence of deprescribing of antidiabetic medications, and the potential scope for further deprescribing.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>6</followup>
    <followuptype>Months</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/09/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Noarlunga Health Service - Noarlunga Centre</hospital>
    <hospital>Repatriation Hospital - Daw Park</hospital>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>5168 - Noarlunga Centre</postcode>
    <postcode>5041 - Daw Park</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Flinders Medical Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Adelaide Hopsital - Elders Research Cooperative</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>North Terrace
Adelaide
South Australia 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Modern medical care can provide many medications for problems, whether simply short-term medications like antibiotics or longer-term medications like those used to treat high blood pressure.  But we do not know enough about when medication can and should be ceased, especially in older patients with diabetes.  We know that often medications are ceased while a patient is in hospital; sometimes medications are not ceased.  We want to collect data about those patients who had medications for diabetes stopped and those who did not, and compare the two groups later to look for any differences.
Many older people complain about being on too many medications.  People on lots of medications might wonder what would happen if one or more of their regular medications was ceased.  Our purpose is to understand better any benefits for older people to be on fewer regular medications, and understand any unforeseen risks of stopping regular medications in older people.  Hospital doctors often cease a regular medication.  We will not influence when and how that happens for you, only observe whether or not it does happen for you and call you after discharge to find out how you are feeling. Nothing about your hospital care will be different.  Sometimes a patient is hospitalised as a result of a side effect of a medication which is then stopped; sometimes a patient is admitted to hospital for a different reason but a medicine needs to be stopped in hospital; sometimes a medicine is stopped because it is no longer beneficial. And sometimes no medications need to be stopped.  These measures are all part of routine hospital care.  We simply want to check on you after your hospital stay to see how you are feeling.  We will also ask your nursing home for information about falls and General Practitioner (GP) call-outs to see you and any changes to your medication since discharge. 
With your permission we will also contact your GP and ask them to perform a routine diabetes blood test 3 months after you are discharged. This is called a HbA1c and it is a blood test that looks at your diabetes control in the last 3 months. Your GP would probably be doing this blood test anyway and we will ask him or her for the result.
We will document your age and information such as your list of medications at the time of admission as well as discharge, the reason for your hospitalisation, what over medical conditions you have, whether or not you required another presentation or admission to hospital in the 6 months prior to and after this admission; your glucose (sugar) control before and after the first hospitalisation; the reason for admission if you do require readmission; which medications you are taking at 30 days and 3 months after discharge, to determine if any medications have been restarted that were ceased while you were in hospital the first time and the reason why a medication was restarted; and lastly, how you rate your quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tilenka Thynne</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Pharmacology
Flinders Medical Centre and Flinders University
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park
South Australia 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 5202</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 5114</fax>
      <email>Tilenka.thynne@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tilenka Thynne</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Pharmacology
Flinders Medical Centre and Flinders University
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park
South Australia 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 5202</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 5114</fax>
      <email>Tilenka.thynne@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tilenka Thynne</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Pharmacology
Flinders Medical Centre and Flinders University
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park
South Australia 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 5202</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 5114</fax>
      <email>tilenka.thynne@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tilenka Thynne</name>
      <address>Department of Clinical Pharmacology
Flinders Medical Centre and Flinders University
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park
South Australia 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 5202</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8204 5114</fax>
      <email>tilenka.thynne@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>