<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371029">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000886482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised trial aiming to prevent development of depression and improve quality of life in individuals with dementia (Alzheimers disease)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised trial aiming to prevent development of depression and improve quality of life in individuals with dementia (Alzheimers disease) through a novel Cognitive Bias Modification intervention.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Alzheimer's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Cognitive bias modification (CBM) is a novel, simple, and safe computer-based intervention that requires behavioural responses from participants (i.e., pressing one of two buttons). CBM specifically targets attentional and interpretative biases associated with anxiety, dysphoria, and depression. CBM operates through implicit learning systems.

In this trial two forms of CBM will comprise the intervention, CBM-A (attentional modification) and CBM-I (interpretive modification).During CBM-A participants will be repeatedly exposed to pairs of emotional faces. Each face pair includes one face displaying a negative emotion, and one face portraying a non-negative emotion. The presentation of each face pair lasts 500 ms. After each face pair has been presented, a probe is presented in the same spatial position where one of the faces was located. Participants are asked to indicate the shape of each probe by pressing a square or a circle on a response box. The time taken for participants to discriminate the identity of the probe is recorded. In the active CBM-A condition, designed to reduce attention to negative information, and expected to result in subsequent reduction in symptoms of depression, probes always appear in the position of non-negative faces.

During CBM-I, participants will be repeatedly exposed to single ambiguous words (e.g. 'cane') for 1000 ms on the computer screen, followed by a pair of words. In each word pair, one word will be semantically related to either a negative or benign meaning (e.g. 'hit' or 'furniture') of the cue word, and one semantically unrelated word (e.g. 'cloud'). Participants will be asked to indicate whether the semantically related word appeared on the left or right side of the computer screen by pressing the left or right button on a response box. The time taken for participants to discriminate the location of the semantically related word is recorded. In the active CBM-I condition, designed to reduce negative interpretation of ambiguous information, and expected to result in subsequent reduction in symptoms of depression, the semantically related word will always present a benign meaning.

In this trial, each CBM session will last approximately 30 minutes: 15 minutes each for CBM-A and CBM-I, Over the course of the trial 35 CBM sessions will take place during office hours as follows: Week 1 - daily (5 sessions), Week 2 - 3 sessions, Weeks 3 to 4 - Twice a week (4 sessions), Week 5 to 25 months - Monthly (23 sessions).
The CBM sessions will be delivered on a local PC station at the study centre, under supervision of a trained research officer. The first session will also comprise initial baseline assessment of primary and secondary outcomes. Adherence to the trial will be monitored via registration of participant attendance at each session. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control condition will follow the same procedure as described for the active intervention group, except for the following minor changes. During the CBM-A control condition probes will appear with equal frequency in the location of non-negative and negative faces. During the CBM-I control condition, the semantically related words will portray a benign or negative meaning with equal frequency. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A primary outcome is the incidence of clinically significant depressive symptoms in patients with Alzheimer's disease (AD) across the duration of the trial. 

The Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI) will be used to establish the presence of clinically significant depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This primary outcome will be assessed at multiple time points across the duration of the trial. These time points are; baseline, 4 weeks, 6 months, 12 months, and 24 months. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A primary outcome is the severity of clinically significant depressive symptoms in patients with Alzheimer's disease (AD) across the duration of the trial.

The Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia (CSDD) will be used to measure severity of depressive symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This primary outcome will be assessed at multiple time points across the duration of the trial. These time points are; baseline, 4 weeks, 6 months, 12 months, and 24 months. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary outcome is the change in quality of life of patients with Alzheimer's disease across the duration of the trial.

The Quality of Life - Alzheimer's Dementia Scale (QoL-AD) will be used to measure quality of life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This secondary outcome will be assessed at multiple time points across the duration of the trial. These time points are; baseline, 4 weeks, 6 months, 12 months, and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary outcome is the change in dementia-related behavioural symptoms in patients with Alzheimer's disease across the duration of the trial. 

The Neuropsychiatric Inventory will be used to measure dementia-related behavioural symptoms.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>This secondary outcome will be assessed at multiple time points across the duration of the trial. These time points are; baseline, 4 weeks, 6 months, 12 months, and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary outcome is factors underlying the development of clinically significant depression in patients with Alzheimer's disease. 

Investigators will collect demographic, lifestyle and clinical information via questionnaires and interview protocols designed specifically for this study.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>This secondary outcome will be assessed at multiple time points across the duration of the trial. These time points are; baseline, 6 months, 12 months, and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary outcome will be change in burden of care as reported by carers of patients with Alzheimer disease.

Burden of care will be measured by the Zarit Burden Interview (ZBI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>This secondary outcome will be assessed at multiple time points across the duration of the trial. These time points are; baseline, 6 months, 12 months, and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary outcome is the change in the cognitive ability of patients with Alzheimer's disease across the duration of the trial.

The Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) will be used to assess cognitive ability.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This secondary outcome will be assessed at multiple time points across the duration of the trial. These time points are; baseline, 6 months, 12 months, and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary outcome is the assessment of neuroimaging predictors of clinically significant depression in patients with Alzheimer's disease. A random sample of up to 40 participants (20 in active CBM condition, 20 in control CBM condition) will undergo magnetic resonance scan (MRI).

Participants will undergo volumetric T1 and T2 weighted fluid-attenuated inversion recovery (FLAIR) imaging to assess for grey matter volume and cerebrovascular disease/white matter hyper-intensities. Images will be processes using SPM12 and MATLAB 7.14.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This secondary outcome will be assessed at multiple time points across the duration of the trial. These time points are; baseline, and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary outcome measure will be change, from baseline assessment, in level of attentional bias and interpretive bias across the duration of the trial. A baseline assessment of attentional bias and interpretive bias will be conducted prior to CBM intervention at the initial session, with assessments repeated throughout the duration of the trial. Attentional bias and interpretive bias will be assessed using computer tasks designed specifically for this study that will reflect methodologies typically employed for the assessment of such biases.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This secondary outcome will be assessed at multiple time points across the duration of the trial. These time points are; baseline, 4 weeks, and 24 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The inclusion criteria will be;
* Diagnosis of major neurocognitive disorder due to probable Alzheimer's disease according to DSM-5 criteria
* Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) score of greater than or equal to 15
* Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI)  depression domain score of 1 (i.e. no depression)
* Availability of a close and reliable informant
* Fluent in written and spoken English</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>We will exclude individuals who;
* Have a medical condition that is likely to compromise their ability to complete the required activities of the study (e.g. severe sensory impairment)
* Consume alcohol in excess of 28 standard drinks per week
* Have no health practitioner who can provide ongoing clinical care
* Have a contra-indication to MRI (MRI sub-group only)
* Decline or are unable to provide informed consent. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible participants will be automatically assigned to one of the two CBM conditions (active/control) by a computer. Allocation will be concealed from both the participant and the research team.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly assigned to CBM conditions (active/control) according to a list of random numbers generated by a computer. Group allocation codes will then be linked to random ID numbers that will be assigned to each participant when they log on for their first CBM session. Neither the participant or research staff will be aware of the randomisation code</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data from the longitudinal Maasbed study (Aalten, et al., 2005) showed that the 2-year cumulative incidence of depression from Alzheimer's disease is 33.4%. We estimate the CBM will result in an absolute risk reduction of around 15% (expected NNT=7). We therefore require 133 participants per group to declare as significant an absolute risk reduction of this magnitude given a power of 80%, and a two sided alpha of 0.05. Allowing for a 10-15% loss of participants to follow-up, we would therefore aim to recruit 300 participants in total (150 per group). The primary hypotheses (difference in the incidence of clinically significant depression between groups) will be tested using intention-to-treat analysis of panel data. This approach to the analysis of the data allows for the inclusion of all available information and for the investigation of interactions between terms (such as group and time).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>2</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>Osborne Park Hospital - Stirling</hospital>
    <hospital>Bentley Health Service - Bentley</hospital>
    <hospital>Armadale Kelmscott Memorial Hospital - Armadale</hospital>
    <hospital>Fremantle Hospital and Health Service - Fremantle</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>WA Centre for Health and Ageing</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6
48 Murray St
Perth, WA, 6000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Neuropsychiatric symptoms like depression are common in people with Alzheimer's disease (AD), as are a frequent cause of distress and reduced quality of life. Pharmacological treatments are only modestly effective in treating these symptoms but are largely ineffective for depression people with AD, and are frequently associated with unacceptable side effects. It is therefore essential that we are able to identify safe and easily accessible therapies for these debilitating symptoms.

Cognitive bias modification (CBM) is a simple, novel and safe intervention that targets attentional and interpretative biases associated with anxiety and depression. CBM has been shown to be effective in reducing depressive symptoms in younger adults but studies in people with cognitive impairment and their carers are lacking. Our preliminary research has indicated that CBM is well tolerated by people with AD and could be easily accessed at home, making it a potentially invaluable intervention for depression in this population.
The aims of this study are to determine the effect of CBM in preventing clinically significant depressive symptoms from occurring in patients with AD. This study will also investigate the impact of CBM on quality of life and cognitive decline, as well as investigating factors that may predict the development of depression in AD.
People with AD will be randomly assigned to an active or control CBM intervention group in a double-blind parallel design. The intervention will be conducted over 24 months. Incidence of clinically significant depressive symptoms will be compared between groups across the duration of the trial, and will be the primary outcome of interest. Changes in quality of life, carer burden, and cognitive ability will also be compared between groups across the duration of the trial, and will serve as secondary outcomes of interest. The capacity of demographic, lifestyle, and neurophysiological factors to predict depressive symptom change in AD will also be assessed across participants, and will serve as secondary outcomes of interest.
Dementia is a common condition and is frequently associated with a diverse range of neuropsychiatric symptoms, including depression and anxiety. Our current understanding of the cause and management of these symptoms is far from optimal. The proposed study trials a simple and safe treatment that could be easily implemented into everyday clinical practice. This study will provide high quality evidence for the efficacy of CBM in improving the quality of lives of people with AD.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Metropolitan Area Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-071</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Ford</name>
      <address>WA Centre for Health &amp; Ageing
L6 / 48 Murray Street
Perth, WA, 6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9224 2855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.ford@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Julian Basanovic</name>
      <address>WA Centre for Health &amp; Ageing
L6 / 48 Murray Street
Perth, WA, 6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9224 3095</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julian.basanovic@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Ford</name>
      <address>WA Centre for Health &amp; Ageing
L6 / 48 Murray Street
Perth, WA, 6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9224 2855</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.ford@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Julian Basanovic</name>
      <address>WA Centre for Health &amp; Ageing
L6 / 48 Murray Street
Perth, WA, 6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9224 3095</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julian.basanovic@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>