<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370668">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001303437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Multicentre Tasmanian Study of a Multidisciplinary Intervention to Reduce Readmission and Death of Patients admitted with Heart Failure</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Multicentre Tasmanian Study of a Multidisciplinary Intervention to Reduce Readmission and Death of Patients admitted with Heart Failure</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ETHELRED</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart Failure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This approach will involve the following deviations from standard practice:
1. Pre-discharge
     - 1a. Discussion and assessment of palliative care needs. This will be performed by the physician or nurse on the care team, prompted by study co-ordinator;
     - 1b. Echocardiography (including pulmonary imaging) and/or BNP to ensure that the patient is as close as possible to euvolaemic before discharge. This will be performed by the physician or sonographer, prompted by study co-ordinator;
      - 1c. Assessment of risk based on clinical, cognitive and psychosocial factors. Clinical data will include patient history, medications, physical measurements, blood tests, and findings on echocardiography. Nonclinical data included age, sex, language background, marital status, living alone or with others, education, socioeconomic status, remoteness index (differentiating residence in a metropolitan, rural, or remote area of Australia), medical insurance, and any home health care services provided. Questionnaires used for data collection included the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA), Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9), and Generalized Anxiety Disorder (GAD-7). This was obtained by the study co-ordinator and communicated to the heart failure nurse. 
2.  Transition care - A heart failure nurse who will follow the patient as both an inpatient and outpatient and act as a transition coach to visit the patient in the hospital prior to discharge and ensure appropriate medication reconciliation, follow-up plans, and education. 
3. Follow-up The heart failure nurse will provide at least two calls (telephone and home visit) within the first 30 days to provide post-discharge support. Surveillance over the next year will involve calls and/or home visits, monthly over the 1st 3 months, with frequency determined by the risk and status of the patient thereafter. Telemonitoring of weight and vital signs if needed. Assistance will be provided to maximize the likelihood of up-titration of medications.
4. The heart failure nurse will be the first contact for changes in patient status and liaise with the cardiologists or Emergency Department (ED) if review rather than admission is needed; 
5. Action plan - Provision of clear instructions to patients and caretakers regarding personalized actions to take when weight or symptoms change.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care
- Standard clinical evaluation pre-discharge;
- Usual arrangements for transitional care, including discharge prescriptions, discharge summary and home nursing as required; 
- GP review for surveillance 
- Standard education, including pamphlets from National Heart Foundation</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All-cause readmission (HF and non-HF) or death at 30 days, assessed by data linkage to patient records</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All cause readmission (HF and non-HF) and death at 90 days, assessed by data linkage to patient records</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All cause readmission (HF and non-HF) and death at 12 months, assessed by data linkage to patient records</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General health status (EQ5D)</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General health status (EQ5D)

</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duke activity status index (DASI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duke activity status index (DASI)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart failure disease-specific quality of life (Kansas City HF questionnaire)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart failure disease-specific quality of life (Kansas City HF questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Days alive and out of hospital, assessed by data linkage to patient records</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Days alive and out of hospital, assessed by data linkage to patient records</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Admission to hospital with heart failure</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Unable to provide written informed consent to participate in this study
- Participating in another clinical research trial where randomized treatment would be unacceptable
- Moderate or worse primary mitral or aortic valve disease
- Any HF admission within the last 6 months 
- Concomitant unstable angina, acute myocardial infarction
- Device malfunction, endocarditis
- Patients with LVAD
- Potentially reversible LV dysfunction  post-partum, alcoholic cardiomyopathy, hyperthyroidism
- Concomitant terminal non-cardiac illnesses that could influence 12 month prognosis (e.g. advanced malignancy),
- Inability to acquire interpretable images (identified from baseline echo)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone/fax/computer. Allocation concealment to decision-makers regarding readmission.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation by random numbers generated by computer. Randomisation by computer access to central administration site before discharge to intervention vs usual care. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>n=412 based on assumption of a 90 day readmission rate of 40% and 33%; 206 subjects/group will have 80% power to show a difference in outcome at p=0.05
Analysis will be based upon intention to treat. The readmission and death rates in each arm will be compared using a chi square test. Survival analysis will be used to compare admissions and other events over 12 months. The effect size of the guided-DMP arm will be investigated using a logistic, linear and Cox models for readmissions, QOL and survival, respectively.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>17/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>412</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>410</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <hospital>Launceston General Hospital - Launceston</hospital>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
    <postcode>7250 - Launceston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Tasmania</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Churchill Avenue, Hobart TAS 7005</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1 16 Marcus Clarke Street Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The ageing population and the success of treating previously fatal acute cardiac disease has led to an ongoing epidemic of heart failure. Given the status of this diagnosis as a component of overall health costs, controlling HF readmission represents a significant component of controlling hospital expenditure in the coming years. Furthermore, the lessons learned from a successful partnership approach to integration of hospital and community services will inform similar approaches to other chronic diseases including chronic lung disease and diabetes. In the current context, success of this program will have wide reaching implications for service delivery nationally and internationally.
This randomized trial will provide the information with which to make evidence-based decisions about improved transfer of HF to community care and improved systems of community maintenance. This Partnership seeks to provide the necessary steps in system re-design to overcome identified problems. Specifically, the research-specific outcomes from this project will be to define where best to invest community resources for the management of heart failure, how to improve hospital and primary care integration in the management of this condition, how to identify early deteriorations and keep patients at home, reduce hospitalisations and save money. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1: Huynh QL, Saito M, Blizzard CL, Eskandari M, Johnson B, Adabi G, Hawson J,
Negishi K, Marwick TH; MARATHON Investigators. Roles of nonclinical and clinical 
data in prediction of 30-day rehospitalization or death among heart failure
patients. J Card Fail. 2015 May;21(5):374-81. doi:
10.1016/j.cardfail.2015.02.002. Epub 2015 Feb 24. PubMed PMID: 25724302.

2. Huynh QL, Negishi K, Blizzard L, Sanderson K, Venn AJ, Marwick TH, Predictive Score for 30-Day Readmission or Death in Heart Failure  JAMA Cardiol. Published online April 20, 2016. doi:10.1001/jamacardio.2016.0220 </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tasmanian Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services
Churchill Avenue, Hobart TAS 7005</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0013550</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Thomas H Marwick</name>
      <address>Baker-IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute,
75 Commercial Road,
Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1550</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8532 1160</fax>
      <email>tom.marwick@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Thomas H Marwick</name>
      <address>Baker-IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute,
75 Commercial Road,
Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1550</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8532 1160</fax>
      <email>tom.marwick@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Thomas H Marwick</name>
      <address>Baker-IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute,
75 Commercial Road,
Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1550</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8532 1160</fax>
      <email>tom.marwick@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Thomas H Marwick</name>
      <address>Baker-IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute,
75 Commercial Road,
Melbourne Vic 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8532 1550</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8532 1160</fax>
      <email>tom.marwick@bakeridi.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>