<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373076">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000904370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prevalence of pregnancy related pelvic girdle pain and associated factors in Western Sydney: a cross-sectional study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prevalence of pregnancy related pelvic girdle pain and associated factors in Western Sydney: a cross-sectional study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1197-4846</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pregnancy related pelvic girdle pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Point prevalence of pregnancy related pelvic girdle pain. We will be assessing the presentation to determine if they can be classified as having PPGP based on self - reported location of pain, reported aggravating factors, and a physical examination. Physical examination will consist of four tests being the Active Straight Leg Raise test, the Poster Pelvic Pain Provocation test, modified Trendelenberg and palpation of long dorsal ligament. Participants will be assesses at one timepoint only, at enrolment of study. The duration of assessment, including completion of all questionnaires is expected to be 45 minutes.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group. However the outcomes from the full standard assessment procedure of the four tests will be statistically compared to the outcome from only one of the four tests (the Modified Trendelenberg test) to investigate whether performing only one test would give the same outcomes as performing all four tests. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of Pregnancy related pelvic girdle pain. Classification of PPGP will be made via self- report, location of pain, reported aggravating activities and a physical examination including the Poster Pelvic Pain Provocation test, Active Straight Leg Raise test, Modified trendelenberg test and palpation of long dorsal sacro-iliac ligament.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cross sectional study. Participants will only be assessed at one time point, upon enrolment into the study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Accuracy of a simplified assessment procedure (which consists of the Modified Trendeleneberg test only) in comparison to the standard assessment procedure (which consists of the full set of tests including self-reported location of pain, reported aggravating factors, and a physical examination comprising of the Active Straight Leg Raise test, the Posterior Pelvic Pain Provocation test, the Modified Trendelenberg test and palpation of long dorsal ligament).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at one time point only, upon enrolment into the study</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Being pregnant, over 18 years of age, between 14 and 38 weeks gestation attending Westmead Hospital, Sydney, New South Wales, for ante-natal care, and sufficient command of the English language in order to be able to complete questionnaire data or have access to a health care interpreter to be included in the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any medical or obstetric complication(s) which affects pregnancy, such as any serious pathology of non-musculoskeletal origin, and gestation beyond 38 weeks. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size required is 770 to achieve statistical power. 95% CI for estimated prevalence will be no wider than +/- 5% with 770 participants. Using G*Power sample size calculator, assuming independent samples t-test (2-tailed) with 90% power and alpha=0.05 significance level, this study is powered to detect a 0.34 standard deviation difference in means between the two groups (those with PPGP and those without PPGP).
1.	Prevalence of PPGP will be determined by calculating the absolute frequency of women classified with PPGP relative to all women recruited to participate in this study. 
2.	Prevalence rates will be modelled according to gestational age with logistic regression analysis.
3.	Associated factors, such as age, parity, gestational age, education status, marital status, physical activity level, ethnicity and pain, will be identified with appropriate parametric comparisons between the two groups (women with PPGP and women without PPGP). Categorical variables will be compared across the two groups using Chi Square test or Fishers test to detect if there is a statistically significant difference between groups of women with and without PPGP. For continuous variables the student t-test will be used to detect if there is a statistically significant difference between groups of women with and without PPGP. Multiple logistic regression analyses will be used to identify the independent predictors of PPGP.
4.	The relationship between a simplified assessment procedure and standard assessment procedure will be examined using Kappa reliability or McNemar test.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/08/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>770</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/08/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Westmead Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 533, WENTWORTHVILLE NSW 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Westmead Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 533, WENTOWRTHVILLE NSW 2145</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Western Sydney University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Locked Bag 1797, PENRITH NSW 2751</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Western Sydney University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Locked Bag 1797, PENRITH NSW 2751</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of this study is to determine the prevalence of PPGP in women attending Westmead Hospital for ante-natal care. The secondary aim is to identify factors associated with PPGP. The third aim is to determine the accuracy of a simplified assessment procedure for classification of PPGP compared to standard assessment procedure.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Westmead Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 533, WENTWORTHVILLE NSW 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/17/WMEAD/64</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Dragana Ceprnja</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department, Westmead Hospital, PO Box 533, WENTWORTHVILLE NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 6500</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Dragana.Ceprnja@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Dragana Ceprnja</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department, Westmead Hospital, PO Box 533, WENTWORTHVILLE NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 6500</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Dragana.Ceprnja@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Dragana Ceprnja</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department, Westmead Hospital, PO Box 533, WENTWORTHVILLE NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 9845 6500</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Dragana.Ceprnja@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Dragana Ceprnja</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department, Westmead Hospital, PO Box 533, WENTWORTHVILLE NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9845 6500</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Dragana.Ceprnja@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>