<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371469">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001378415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dietary management of uncomplicated diverticulitis: what is the effect of inpatient dietary restriction and discharge diet prescription on length of stay, recurrence and patient outcomes in patients admitted to an acute-care hospital in South-East Queensland, Australia? </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Conservative management of uncomplicated diverticulitis: what is the effect of inpatient dietary restriction and discharge diet prescription on length of stay, recurrence and patient outcomes in patients admitted to an acute-care hospital in South-East Queensland, Australia? </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1187-4296</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Uncomplicated Diverticulitis </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Acute, uncomplicated diverticulitis is a gastrointestinal disorder for which dietary management guidelines exist, but are based on inconsistent, poor quality evidence. Patients admitted to the surgical ward between October 2016 and July 2017 with acute, uncomplicated diverticulitis, at an acute care hospital in South-east Queensland will be observed from admission to 6-months post discharge. 

Usual practice will be observed, where dietary prescription will be given at the clinical discretion of the treating gastroenterologist and dietary advice will be provided accordingly by dietitians external to the project. Therefore, regular treatment of patients will be observed and no intervention will be applied by researchers. 

Observations will be made and statistical analysis will be carried out to determine whether differences in patient outcomes exist depending on:
1). The diet prescription they receive during admission (restricted (nil by mouth, clear fluid or free fluid hospital foodservice diet codes for the first 48hours post admission) or liberalised (soft, low fibre or full hospital foodservice diet codes for the first 48hours post admission)); and
2). The diet prescription they are given on discharge (high fibre diet (gradual increase of dietary fibre to &gt;30g fibre per day over the first week post discharge) or low fibre diet (&lt;15g fibre per day for two weeks post discharge, then gradual increase in third week post discharge to &gt;30g fibre per day)). </interventions>
    <comparator>Control groups will be that receiving usual care: 
1). Restricted inpatient diet
2). Low fibre diet on discharge</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>readmission to hospital using data linkage to hospital records</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days and 6 months post initial discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital readmission length of stay using data linkage to hospital records</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post initial discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gastrointestinal symptoms as determined by interview with participant</outcome>
      <timepoint>One assessment within 24-48 hours post admission and at 30 days post initial discharge</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Satisfaction using the Acute Care Hospital Foodservice Patient Satisfaction Questionnaire (ACHFPSQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At patient discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult inpatients (18 years old and above) at Robina Hospital, Queensland, admitted to the surgical ward with a diagnosis of uncomplicated diverticulitis (Hinchey 0-Ib) diagnosed via CT scan and managed with conservative treatment (no surgery performed or drainage placed). A translator will be sought for non-English speaking patients. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded from the study if they are pregnant; unable to give informed consent; are discharged in &lt;48hrs; do not have CT-proven diagnosis; or are diagnosed to have complicated diverticulitis (Hinchey II and above). </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>There is estimated to be 70-100 participants as predicted from current trends at at the hospital site showing 5-10 admissions of eligible cases per week.

Statistical analysis will be completed using SPSS software. All data will be assessed for normality (Shapiro-Wilk test) or homogeneity of variance for continuous variables (Levene's Test). Mean +/- SD/SE for normal variables and median (inter-quartile range) for skewed variables will be used to report patient characteristics. 

Liberalised Diet Group versus Restrictive Diet Group; Low Dietary Fibre Diet Group versus Standard Diet Group; and pairing of inpatient and discharge diet prescriptions will be tested for 1). association with hospital readmission and bristol stool chart type via binomial logistic regression adjusting for potentially confounding variables. 2). association with 30 day and 6 month hospital readmission length of stay and GSRS score via multiple linear regression adjusting for potentially confounding variables.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>True</patientregistry>
    <followup>6</followup>
    <followuptype>Months</followuptype>
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/01/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/07/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Robina Hospital - Robina</hospital>
    <postcode>4226 - Robina</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bond University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>14 University Drive, Robina, QLD, 4226</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bond University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>14 University Drive, Robina, QLD, 4226</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Robina Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>2 Bayberry Lane, Robina, QLD, 4226</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is known that modern Australian society is trending towards an ageing population combined with a poor intake of foods rich in dietary fibre such as wholegrains, fruits and vegetables. Therefore, as diverticulitis is highly prevalent in older adults, it is predicted to become even more prevalent in the future. In addition, it is also suggested that the disease is now occurring more commonly in younger ages. Furthermore, the evidence that is in existence to support current dietary managements is inconsistent, of poor quality and lacking in Australia. Therefore, observational research is warranted to explore the impact of current clinical practice in Australia upon patient and healthcare related outcomes.

In adults admitted to an acute-care hospital with acute, uncomplicated diverticulitis in South-East Queensland, Australia, it is hypothesised that:
1). Participants who are prescribed and adhere to liberalised diets during hospital admission have less healthcare use and no difference in gastrointestinal symptom scores compared to those prescribed restricted (fluid only) diets. 2). Participants who are advised to return to a standard diet with gradual increase in dietary fibre following discharge have no difference in healthcare use or gastrointestinal symptom score and greater adherence to dietary recommendations than those prescribed a low fibre diet with gradual increase in dietary fibre.

A Low or Negligible Risk (LNR) research application for ethical approval has been submitted as this study intends to be of low risk to research participants as the likelihood and severity of any risks to the patient is low. Possible risks include using vulnerable, sick patients as the study population as well as fatigue, inconvenience or discomfort of talking about personal issues. To minimise risks, high risk patients will be excluded from the study, patient involvement will be as minimal as possible by accessing medical records and eligible participants will be asked to provide informed consent. Data will also be gathered and kept in a de-identifiable format where possible with identifiable data stored in password protected electronic files or a locked filing cabinet. Researchers will be the only ones to have access to this information. 

The intended outcomes of this study include a greater understanding of acute uncomplicated diverticulitis. Future research that can stem from findings of this study, may then help to formulate best practice guidelines for the dietary management of acute, uncomplicated diverticulitis as such is currently non-existent. This would help to achieve cohesion across treating doctors and dietitians. It is believed that theses outcomes and associated potential benefits that this study can provide will far outweigh the possible minimal risks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Gold Coast Hospital and Health Service (GCHHS) Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Ethics Communications
Level 2, Block E,
GoldCoast University Hospital
1 Hospital Boulevard, Southport, Qld 4215</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/16/QGC/282</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Romina Nucera</name>
      <address>Robina Hospital
2 Bayberry Lane
Robina, Qld, 4226</address>
      <phone>+61 (07) 5668 6000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Romina.Nucera@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Yvonne Chen</name>
      <address>Robina Hospital
2 Bayberry Lane
Robina, Qld, 4226</address>
      <phone>+61 (07) 5668 6000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Yvonne.Chen@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Camilla Dahl</name>
      <address>Bond Institute of Health &amp; Sport
2 Promethean Way
Robina, Qld, 4226 </address>
      <phone>+61417629672</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>camilla.dahl@student.bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Megan Crichton</name>
      <address>Bond Institute of Health &amp; Sport
2 Promethean Way
Robina, Qld, 4226 </address>
      <phone>+61 429005311</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>megan.crichton@student.bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>