<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371214">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001052426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised, Double-blinded, Placebo-controlled Study of the probiotic PCC(Registered Trademark) (L. fermentum VRI-003) capsule for the effect on gastrointestinal health and gut microflora in healthy adults (with no medically diagnosed gastrointestinal disease)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A proof-of-concept study to investigate the effect of ingestion of the probiotic PCC(Registered Trademark) (L. fermentum VRI-003) or placebo capsules on gut health when given to healthy adults (with no medically diagnosed gastrointestinal disease)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>“The BBIG Study” (Bioxyne’s Bacteria in Gut Study)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gastrointestinal health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Treatment Arm 1: One capsule of PCC (containing Lactobacillus fermentum VRI-003) once daily for six months. Each active capsule contains a minimum of two billion live organisms.
Treatment Arm 2: One capsule of placebo capsule (containing microcrystalline cellulose, MCC) once daily for six months. 

Adherence will be monitored through participant self report on daily diary and through accountability of empty containers/number capsule returned.</interventions>
    <comparator>One placebo capsule (containing microcrystalline cellulose, MCC) to be taken once daily for six months </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Outcome 1: change in the balance of the genera of the gut microbiome

Instrument 1: this will be quantified using 16S RNA analysis of faecal samples 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoints.  assessed at three time points: before commencement of study treatment, 3 months after commencement of study treatment and 6 months after commencement of study treatment 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.	Bowel habit and any bowel issues from daily diary 


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Daily from Screening (up to one week prior to intervention commencement) to final visit  (6 months post commencement of intervention).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2.	Use of other medications (based on participant self-report in study diary and at visits)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Daily from Screening (up to one week prior to intervention commencement) to final visit (6 months post commencement of intervention).
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3.	Quality of Life (SF-36)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: At screening and at 3 months and 6 months after randomisation 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4.	Body Weight (using digital scales)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: At screening and at 3 months and 6 months after randomisation 

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5.	Incidence of all adverse events (ie other than GIT) (based on participant self-report in study diary and at study visits) (Note: Strains of L. fermentum and other probiotic are generally regarded as safe (GRAS) and well tolerated, with some bloating and flatulence occurring as the most frequently reported side effects of probiotics in general)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Daily from Screening (up to one week prior to intervention commencement) to final visit (6 months post commencement of intervention).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>6.	6-point Likert Scale* assessment of gastric symptoms (ie for any abdominal pain or discomfort, bloating, flatulence / passage of gas and rumbling stomach):
*Never=0
*1 day per month=1
*2-3 days per month=2
*1 day per week=3
*&gt;1 day per week=4
*Every day=5
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: At screening and at 3 months and 6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Subject is in general good health with NO history of medically diagnosed gastrointestinal disease.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any medically diagnosed gastrointestinal disorder/disease (including inflammatory bowel disease, medically diagnosed IBS)
Clinically significant renal, hepatic, endocrine, cardiac, pulmonary, pancreatic, neurologic, haematologic or biliary disorder
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>20/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>61</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>11/07/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bioxyne Limited</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Bioxyne Limited
Suite 305, Level 3, 35 Lime Street, 
Sydney NSW 2000

</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bioxyne Limited</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 305, Level 3, 35 Lime Street, 
Sydney NSW 2000
Australia
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NA</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The complex ecosystem of the adult intestinal microflora is estimated to harbour at least 500 different anaerobic bacterial species. Several reports have indicated that five genera account for most of the viable forms of anaerobic bacteria: Bacteroides, Eubacterium, Bifidobacterium, Peptostreptococcus, and Fusobacterium. Some of these species are considered potentially harmful because of their capacity to produce toxins, invade mucosal cells and activate carcinogens and inflammatory responses. There are, however, known strains with health-promoting properties, principally Bifidobacteria and Lactobacilli. 
This study will examine the capacity of a human-isolated probiotic strain of bacteria to influence the composition of the gut microbiome in healthy adult human volunteers and to examine what health benefits may be associated with daily consumption of the strain in the form of freeze-dried powder in capsules. The strain that will be tested in this study is Lactobacillus fermentum VRI-003, referred to as PCC(Registered Trademark). PCC(Registered Trademark) has been sold as a dietary supplement in capsule and powder form for over ten years worldwide with no reported adverse effect.  
The study is a proof of concept, single centre, randomised, double-blind placebo controlled, parallel group study. A total of 60 healthy adult subjects (no diagnosed GI disease) will be randomised in a 1:1 ratio to receive either PCC(Registered Trademark) or placebo over a 6 month treatment period. Each active capsule contains a minimum of two billion live organisms. 
There will be 4 study visits in total. Subjects will provide three faecal samples: at Visit 2 (baseline, Day 1), Visit 3 (day 90) and Visit 4 (day 180). The samples will be analysed by 16S RNA analysis to monitor the composition of the gut microbiome. Subjects will be asked to complete a daily diary regarding their bowel habits. Subjects will also be asked to complete a general health questionnaire (SF-36) on three occasions. Weight will also be recorded.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://australianclinicaltrials.com/study/probiotic-clinical-trial/</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road Eastwood South Australia 5063 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Joanne Grimsdale</name>
      <address>Oztrials Clinical Research
Suite1, 56-56A Thompson Street
Drummoyne NSW 2047
Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9719 3852 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trials@oztrials.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter French </name>
      <address>Bioxyne Limited
Suite 305, Level 3, 35 Lime Street, 
Sydney NSW 2000
Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8296 0000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.french@bioxyne.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter French </name>
      <address>Bioxyne Limited
Suite 305, Level 3, 35 Lime Street, 
Sydney NSW 2000
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8296 0000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.french@bioxyne.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Luke Edington</name>
      <address>Datapharm Australia Pty Ltd
PO Box 220 Five Dock NSW 2046


</address>
      <phone>+612 9719 2800</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>luke.edington@datapharmaustralia.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>