<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336924">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/05/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/05/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000550909</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Adrenergic blockade in adult burns patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of adrenergic blockade on hypermetabolism in patients post burn injury</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Burn injury greater than 30% body surface area</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Burns</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The medication propranolol hydrochloride for 30 days  with 1mg/kg/day in four divided doses titrated upwards to decrease resting heart rate by 20%</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be given no extra medication. Standard care only including appropriate fluid resuscitation, early debridement and split skin grafting, optimal nutrition, infection surveillance, compression garments, exercise and  splinting will be provided. There will be no placebo.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition (% fat and lean soft tissue mass) will be estimated with dual energy X-ray absorptometry (DXA, Lunar Prodigy Advance, Madison, WI, USA). Results will be expressed as a % of predicted matched in reference populations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks and three months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiac function- Echocardiography - cardiac output, ejection fraction and wall thickness will be measured</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and four weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical work capacity - tested by the modified shuttle walk test. This is an externally-paced, incremental, symptom-limited maximal test .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four weeks and three months from enrolment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting energy expenditure via metalyzer MetaMax 3B analyser (Cortex:biophysik, GMbH, Germany) actual % REE will be compared with predicted % REE for BMI and age after an  overnight fast, resting conditions and controlled ambient  temperature 270C, based on the Respiratory quotient based equation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Enrolment (baseline), and every week until discharge from hospital then once at the final three month point</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulin sensitivity, glucose and fat metabolism - Eleven mls of blood will be taken after an overnight fast and at least 24 hours since any exercise. Plasma glucose and lipids measured by Beckman DXC 
Serum cortisol, plasma insulin will be measured using Beckman DXI. Insulin resistance will be measured by the reciprocal index of homoeostasis model assessment (HOMA-IR)21.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks and three months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma adrenaline &amp; noradrenaline - Ten mls of venous blood collected into precooled lithium heparin tubes with antioxidant (0.1mL sodium metabisulphite)- will be analysed by HPLC with electrochemical detection.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, four weeks and three months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wound healing - The time to donor site wound healing and to 10% residual burn wound (of original burn size) remaining unhealed, compared between groups. Wound healing will be judged by experienced burn health care practitioners</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and every week until three months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analysis of gait (walking) using 3-dimensional Vicon motion analysis system, EMG and force plates to quantify gait analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Three months post enrolment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Acute burns patients 
18years of age and over 
30% total burns surface area, 
Ready for discharge from intensive care,  at a stage when they do not require inotropic support, are non septic, antibiotic free and capable of spontaneous breathing on a high flow humidifier</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Concomitant multi-trauma, 
Pregnancy, 
Lactation, 
A premorbid history of asthma or bronchospasm, 
Peripheral arterial disease, 
Diabetes, 
Systolic blood pressure&lt;100mmHg or mean arterial pressure of &lt; 65mmHg, 
Heart rate&lt;60bpm, 
Heart block on ECG, 
Previous use of beta blockers before the burn injury, or previous prescription for greater than 24 hours within the preceding 24 hours, 
Allergic disorders 
Any cardiovascular conditions (hypertension, coronary artery disease, left ventricular systolic impairment, pulmonary hypertension, right ventricular impairment, sick sinus syndrome, heart block), 
Renal or hepatic impairment, 
Hyperthyroidism, 
Previous depressive illness 
Compassionate care only</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible patients will be identified and consent will be sought by the chief and principal investigators, with next of kin or substitute decision maker. The randomization sequence will be generated and re-identifiable serial numbers will be assigned by a research personnel not involved in the study. They will be concealed from consent designee research staff for group allocation to prevent selection bias and protected by an electronic password.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants recruited will be randomized into control and intervention arms using computer generated randomization; http://www.randomization.com/ with stratification of females</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>26</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Burns, Trauma &amp; Critical Care Research Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Dept of Intensive Care Medicine,
Level 3, NHB,
Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital
Butterfield St, 
Herston QLD 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Block 20 
Royal Brisbane and Women?s Hospital,                     
Butterfield St, 
Herston QLD 4006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dept of Intensive Care Medicine,
Level 3, NHB,
Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital
Butterfield St, 
Herston QLD 4029</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Post burn injury, survivors undergo a hypermetabolic response resulting in loss of muscle mass and increase in fat tissue, increased cardiac work, and delays in wound healing. Consequently these patients have weakness, increased length of hospital stay decreased functional ability and delayed return to work rates. 
One way to counteract this problem is by pharmacological blockade ie using medication to block the hypermetabolic response. One drug that has been trialled extensively in paediatrics are beta - blockers which decrease the work of the heart. The studies in children have shown these drugs can improve donor site and graft healing, attenuate muscle mass loss, prevent loss of lean muscle mass, improve immune function and decrease in the high temperature, high heart rate, increased cardiac work, and fatty infiltration of the liver. There have been two small trials in adults who did not blind investigators, investigate long term factors and included patients with burns less than 30% total body surface area. 
We plan to complete a  single blinded, randomized trial on beta -adrenergic blockade in large severe adult burns patients investigating a number of important long term outcomes including lean muscle mass, cardiac function, wound healing, exercise capacity and metabolic profile. 
The specific aim is to investigate whether Propranolol)1mg/kg/day) a nonselective beta(1,) beta(2)-receptor antagonist, can prevent the loss of lean muscle mass and improve cardiac function, wound healing, exercise capacity and metabolic profile following severe thermal injury</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Floor 7, Block 7
Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospitral, 
Butterfield St, Herston 4029 QLD</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/04/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11QRBW/128</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/03/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jennifer Paratz</name>
      <address>Dept Intensive Care Medicine,
Level 3, NHB,
Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital, 
Butterfield St,
Herston, Queensland 4029</address>
      <phone>61 7 36361980</phone>
      <fax>61 7 36363542</fax>
      <email>j.paratz@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Jason Roberts</name>
      <address>Dept Intensive Care Medicine,
Level 3, NHB,
Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital, 
Butterfield St,
Herston, Queensland 4029</address>
      <phone>61 7 36364108</phone>
      <fax>61 7 36363542</fax>
      <email>j.roberts2@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Professor Michael Muller</name>
      <address>The Professor Stuart Pegg Burns Centre
Level 4, DJMB,
Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital, 
Butterfield St,
Herston, Queensland 4029</address>
      <phone>61 7 36361621</phone>
      <fax>61 7 36363542</fax>
      <email>Michael_Muller@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>