<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347607">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/10/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/10/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001102965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study of the effectiveness of intranasal ketamine in the treatment of moderate to severe pain in the emergency department</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study of the efficacy of intranasal ketamine in sub-dissociative doses for the treatment of moderate to severe pain in adult patients in the emergency department.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1125-3296</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>acute pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A single dose of intranasal ketamine (0.7mg/kg) will be administered to adult patients presenting to the emergency department with a verbal pain score of 6 or greater out of 10. A second dose of 0.5 mg/kg will be administered 15 minutes later if the patient requests further analgesia or there has not been an appreciable drop in pain score (greater than or equal to 3 out of 10)

An interim analysis will be undertaken after 30 patients to assess response to analgesia and/or presence of sedation. The dose of ketamine will be adjusted up or down depending on response in these first 30 patients.
If patients achieve significant fall in pain score ar 30 minutes and do not require rescue analgesia with parenteral opioids and do not show signs of sedation with the initial dosing regimen, this will be continued for the remaining numbers in the proposed cohort.

If patients do not attain a drop in pain score of 3/10 or greater at 30 minutes with the initial dosing regimen, the initial dose of ketamine will be increased to 1 mg/kg for the remaining 120 patients.

If the patients attain adequate analgesia (pain score fall greater than or equal to 3/10) but show signs of significant sedation, the initial dose of ketamine will be reduced to 0.5mg/kg for the remaning 120 patients.</interventions>
    <comparator>Nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change in Visual Analog Scale pain score from pre-administration (T0) to 30 minutes post-administration (T30)</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 minutes post-administration of ketamine</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>a) Mean change in Visual Analog Scale pain score from pre-administration (T0) to 15 minutes (T15) and 60 minutes (T60) post-administration (T30).</outcome>
      <timepoint>15 and 60 minutes after ketamine administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>b) Percentage responding to each description of change in pain severity (a lot better, a little better, the same, a little worse, a lot worse)</outcome>
      <timepoint>T 15, T30, T60 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>c) Percentage requiring an additional dose of ketamine</outcome>
      <timepoint>T15 minutes</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>d) Percentage responding to each description of satisfaction with amount of analgesia experienced (satisfied, not satisfied, uncertain)</outcome>
      <timepoint>T15, T30, T60.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>e)  Percentage in which study termination was required and the reason for this: 

	i) requiring additional analgesia such as extra ketamine or a different analgesic.

	ii) other (eg adverse effects or interference of study requirements with necessary therapeutic interventions)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at T15, T30, T60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>f) Adverse event profile, specifically including:

	i) Observed level of sedation using the Ramsay Sedation Scale (anxious/restless/both, cooperative/orientated/tranquil, respond to commands, brisk response to stimulus, sluggish response to stimulus, no response to stimulus) will be recorded at.

	ii) Self-reported opinion on level of sedation
        iii) Local adverse effects: presence of nasal irritation, bleeding or any local effects reported by the patient.

	iv) Systemic adverse effects: changes in vital signs      (tachycardia, hyper/hypotension), hallucinations (visual or other).

	v) Suspected allergic reaction (incl type)

	vi) Any other</outcome>
      <timepoint>T15, T30, T60</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age greater than or equal to 18 years of age

Self-report pain severity as being greater than or equal to 6 on the standard 11-point verbal rating scale (0 = none, 10 = worst pain imaginable) 

Medical recommendation for parenteral analgesia (attending doctors discretion)

Pain from any cause other than the 3 specific exclusions (see below)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known current pregnancy or patient suspects that might be pregnant at time of presentation or female of child-bearing age and not using any form of contraception.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>In general, patients who are eligible for this study are triaged as Australasian Triage Scale (ATS) Category 2 because it is felt that they need analgesia within 10 minutes.

The ED triage nurse will notify the nominated ED ‘Cat 2 doctor’ in the usual way. (Note: At the study ED, both the Cat 2 doctor and the ED Consultant In Charge (CIC) receive a pager notification of the arrival of a Category 2 patient (with whatever diagnosis), and so are usually aware of such patients prior to their reaching an ED cubicle.
 
The Cat 2 doctor will perform a rapid assessment of the patient in the usual way, which during the study period will include consideration of the study inclusion and exclusion criteria. Obtaining a verbal numerical rating of pain severity is standard in this setting. 

If the patient is eligible and the Cat 2 doctor or CIC believe that the time involved in patient recruitment will not have an adverse effect on either that patient’s management or the concurrent work of the ED, then either of these doctors or another delegate may broach study participation with the patient.  

If patient consent is obtained, the attending doctor will calculate the appropriate dosage of Ketamine and chart this for administration via the intranasal route.  The drug will be prepared by the attending nurse(s) who will refer to the Study Ketamine Dosing Table.</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable - cohort treatment study</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/02/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>1/02/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Southern Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Clayton Rd,
Clayton, Vic, 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Departments of Emergency Medicine, Southern Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Monash Medical Centre
Clayton Rd
Clayton, Vic, 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Emergency Medicine, Frankston Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hastings Road, 
FRANKSTON, Vic, 3199</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Peninsula Health</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Frankston Hospital
Hastings Road, 
Frankston, Vic, 3199</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims ot assess the effectiveness of ketamine as an pain reliever when administered into the nasal passages in doses that do not produce sedation or anaesthesia in a group of adult emergency department patients coming to hospital with moderate to severe pain.
We hypothesise that ketamine will reduce pain effectively without significant sedation at the proposed dose.
A positive result may allow ketamine to be considered as an alternative pain reliever for acute pain in the emergency department that could be adminsitered through the nose and reduce the need for insertion of intravenous catheters in some patients suffering from moderate to severe pain.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health Humans Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Medical Centre
Clayton Rd
Clayton, Vic, 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/01/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/SHA/54 
Southern Health HREC Ref: 11331A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/10/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Andis Graudins</name>
      <address>Dept of Emergency Medicine
135 Dandenong Hospital, 
David Street,
Dandenong, Victoria, 3175</address>
      <phone>+61395943193</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andis.graudins@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Andis Graudins</name>
      <address>Dept of Emergency Medicine
135 Dandenong Hospital, 
David Street,
Dandenong, Victoria, 3175</address>
      <phone>+61395943193</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andis.graudins@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andis Graudins</name>
      <address>Dept of Emergency Medicine
135 Dandenong Hospital, 
David Street,
Dandenong, Victoria, 3175</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9554 9340</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andis.graudins@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>