<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373410">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001177347p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of brain glutamatergic mechanisms in patients with treatment resistant anxiety</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of brain glutamatergic mechanisms in patients with treatment resistant anxiety - comparative effects of ketamine vs fentanyl</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>None</utrn>
    <trialacronym>N/A</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Single doses of ketamine 1mg/kg as intramuscular injections</interventions>
    <comparator>Single doses of fentanyl 50mcg as intramuscular injections</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exploratory outcome: Magnetic Resonance Imaging scans - data collected include resting state fMRI and magnetic resonance spectroscopy. 

Spectroscopy picks up a glutamate/glycine signal in brain; this is well established; there are multiple (between 10-20) endpoints in terms of brain structure, blood flow, network patterns etc that could be determined from an MRI scan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>predose, 2 hours and 72 hours post dosing.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Electroencephalogram measuring on brain rhythmicity and coherence (connectivity) (composite outcome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>predose, 2 hours and 72 hours post dosing.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma ketamine and norketamine concentrations (composite  outcome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0.5, 1, 2 and 3 hours post dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood rating scales (Hamilton Anxiety Scale and Fear Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 1, 2, 24 and 72 hours after dosing</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability assessments, including adverse events, vital signs via clincal assessments, dissociation ratings using the CADSS rating scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Predose, 1,2, 24 and 72 hours post dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>	Male or female aged 18-65y 
	Diagnosed with DSM-5 Generalized Anxiety Disorder and/or Social Anxiety Disorder, with inadequate response to prior treatment i.e. unsuccessful with 1 or more prescribed antidepressants and prior failed psychotherapy
	Hamilton Anxiety Scale (HAM-A) score of &gt;20, and/or a Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale (LSAS) score of &gt;60 at screening.
	Prior response to ketamine as demonstrated by a &gt;50% decrease in HAMA and/or Fear Questionnaire (FQ) scores 24 hours after dosing. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	evidence of severe acute or chronic medical disorders,
	presence of implanted cardiac pacemakers, hearing aids, insulin pumps or neurostimulators; intracranial metal clips; or metallic bodies in the eye
	past or current diagnoses of schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, or current psychotic symptoms
	female patients who are pregnant or lactating
	drug abuse or dependence in the last 6 months
	current significant suicidal ideation
	current Major Depressive Disorder (MADRS &gt;20 at screening).  
	participants must be free of recreational drug and alcohol use at the time of testing</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involved contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who was "off-site" or at central administration site.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerized  randomization in blocks of 4, stratified by gender</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics / pharmacodynamics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>-fMRI data: FSLs Multivariate Exploratory Linear Optimized Decomposition into Independent Components (MELODIC) will be used to decompose data from all participants into different spatial and temporal components using independent components analysis (ICA). Parameters for MELODIC will be as follows: no brain extraction, brain/non-brain threshold=10, TR=3, mixture modelling=0.5. A general linear model will then be created for use during dual regression.  A factor effects general linear model will be set up to compare the mean of each group with the average mean across all groups. A post-hoc t-test will be used to determine the direction of the difference between groups for any statistically significant results arising from the ANOVAs. 

Using FSLs dual regression function, spatial maps from the group-average analysis will be used to generate individualised versions of the spatial maps and associated time series. An ANOVA comparing group differences over 5000 non-parametric permutations with threshold-free cluster enhancement will be undertaken using FSL's randomise permutation testing tool, following dual regression. The threshold for statistical significance will be set at p=0.05 [family-wise error corrected] and adjusted for multiple comparisons using the null distribution of the maximal voxel-wise test statistic.

-EEG data: The raw EEG will be downsampled to 128Hz, a bandpass of 1-30Hz applied, eye blink artefact components will be subtracted and remaining artefacts of all types deleted. The cleaned EEG will then be processed with a 1s overlapping Hanning window (0.5s steps), fast Fourier power transform, and log10 transform. Relaxation data will be processed for frontal and parietal alpha asymmetry and Higuchis fractal dimension.

-PK data: Descriptive statistics, noncompartmental analysis

-Safety/tolerability: Descriptive statistics.

-PK-PD: General linear models will be used to undertake regression analyses using the  covariates of age, gender, diagnosis, mood rating scores and ketamine and norketamine exposure (AUC measurements) to compare the differences in functional connectivity between the 2 treatment arms.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/10/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/11/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 913, Dunedin 9054</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 913, Dunedin 9054</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Low-dose ketamine has fast-acting positive effects on mood in patients with treatment resistant anxiety, similar to its effects in depression. This is a mechanistic study to assess changes in brain function in patients with treatment resistant anxiety treated with ketamine or a psychoactive control, using a range of assessment methods (brain imaging, EEG analysis, blood pharmacokinetic samples). Data from this study may help clarify the neurobiological basis of treatment-resistant anxiety.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>None</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Health and Disability Ethics Committees
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6140</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Bruce Russell</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7272</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 479 7034</fax>
      <email>bruce.russell@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Glue</name>
      <address>School of Medicine
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 21 243 3372</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 474 7934</fax>
      <email>paul.glue@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Bruce Russell</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7272</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 479 7034</fax>
      <email>bruce.russell@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Glue</name>
      <address>School of Medicine
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+64 21 243 3372</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 474 7934</fax>
      <email>paul.glue@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>