<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362871">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000852853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Preventing Colorectal Cancer Metastases following Surgical Removal of a Primary Tumor</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Preventing Colorectal Cancer Metastases in adults following Surgical Removal of a Primary Tumor by using a cocktail of a B-blocker and a COX2 inhibitor</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Colorectal cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In the current study we aim at testing the safety and efficacy of our drug cocktail in patients undergoing excision of colorectal cancer.  Both short-term outcomes (immune and endocrine indices), as well as 3-year recurrence rates will be assessed within patients. Specifically, we propose a double blind clinical trial with two major arms: (I) placebo treatment, and (II) treatment with a cocktail of a B-blocker (propranolol  to block catecholamines, oral tablet 40 mg , 3 times daily) and a COX2 inhibitor (etodolac  to block prostaglandin receptors, 200 mg oral tablets every 6 hours ). A total of 206 patients will be recruited. The drug treatment will be given for a total of 20-day period, commencing five days before surgery, with no time overlap with adjuvant therapy, and independently of any other routine therapy. The drug treatment is planned for only 15 post-operative days to reduce potential side effects, and because most immunological and endocrine perturbations induced by surgery dissipate during this period. Immune and endocrine baseline levels will be established in a group of thirty healthy matched control subjects.
Short-term endocrine and immune measures will include: serum levels of various cytokines; serum cortisol, C-reactive protien, Vascular endothelial growth factor,  leukocyte subpopulations and their functional markers; and Natural killar cells activity. All indices will be assessed repeatedly within subjects, using freshly drawn blood samples that will be collected twice before surgery (days -5 and on the morning of surgery), and on post-operative days 1 and 3. Resected malignant tumors and normal colonic tissue will be tested for catecolamines (CA) and prostaglandines (PG) receptor expression. Clinical outcomes will include perioperative complication rate and narcotic use, and 2-year recurrence rate.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group receive placebo which are tablets with the same shape and form of the original drug given in the study group</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tumor recurrence by abdominal CT scan and colonoscope</outcome>
      <timepoint>recurrence survey starts 6 months after surgery and then every 6 months for 2 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Distant metastasis by abdominal and Chest CT scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>metastasis survey starts 6 months after surgery and then every 6 months for at least 2 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult patient with colorectal cancer, stage II or III</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Stage IV cancer, liver or renal (kidney) failure , glaucoma, history of immediate allergic reaction (known as anaphylaxis) to a beta blocker of any kind and pheocromocytoma</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Double blind clinical trial with two major arms: (I) placebo treatment, and (II) treatment with a cocktail of a beta-blocker (propranolol – to block Catecolamines) and a COX2 inhibitor (etodolac – to block prostaglandines). A total of 206 patients will be recruited.Choice of patients will be done by a person unaware of the study, randomization will be done before surgery by computer randomization. Allocation of a patient to a the treatment or placebo will be concealed by . sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>computer based randomization</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Khaled Madbouly</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>kolyet el teb street, Azarita, faculty of medicine, university of alexandria, Alexandria 21321, Egypt</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Khaled Madbouly</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>kolyet el teb street, Azarita, faculty of medicine, university of alexandria, Alexandria 21321, Egypt</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>: In the current study we aim at testing the safety and efficacy of our drug cocktail in patients undergoing excision of colorectal cancer.  Both short-term outcomes (immune and endocrine indices), as well as 2-year recurrence rates will be assessed within patients. Specifically, we propose a phase II double blind clinical trial with two major arms: (I) placebo treatment, and (II) treatment with a cocktail of a B-blocker (propranolol  to block CAs) and a COX2 inhibitor (etodolac  to block PGs). A total of 206 patients will be recruited along a two year. The drug treatment will be given for a total of 20-day period, commencing five days before surgery, with no time overlap with adjuvant therapy, and independently of any other routine therapy. The drug treatment is planned for only 15 post-operative days to reduce potential side effects, and because most immunological and endocrine perturbations induced by surgery dissipate during this period. Immune and endocrine baseline levels will be established in a group of thirty healthy matched control subjects.
Short-term endocrine and immune measures will include: serum levels of various cytokines; serum cortisol, CRP, VEGF levels; leukocyte subpopulations and their functional markers; and NK number and activity. All indices will be assessed repeatedly within subjects, using freshly drawn blood samples that will be collected twice before surgery (days -5 and on the morning of surgery), and on post-operative days 1 and 3. Resected malignant tumors and normal colonic tissue will be tested for CA and PG receptor expression. Clinical outcomes will include perioperative complication rate and narcotic use, and 2-year recurrence rate. 

We hypothesize that our 20-day pharmacological treatment will: (i) significantly improve the status of the endocrine factors before surgery (e.g., VEGF, CRP, MMP2, MMP9 &amp; cortisol) and enhance CMI competence, (ii) significantly attenuate the profound postoperative suppression of CMI and improve the postoperative endocrine status, and (iii) increase the 3-year recurrence-free survival rate. We further hypothesize that the peri-operative status of some endocrine/immunological indices will predict the 3-year recurrence rate, and that the within-subject alterations in these indices, caused by surgery and/or our drug intervention, will further predict recurrence-free survival rate. Provided that this study will indicate promising outcomes, our long-term plan is to employ this intervention in a larger sample of cancer patients and assess overall long-term survival rates. Such a larger study, powered to exhibit 5-10% improved survival rates, would be justified provided significant improvements in CMI/endocrine indices and/or a trend toward improved 3-year recurrence-free survival rates.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics committee , faculty of medicine, university of Alexandria</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>kolyet el teb street, Azarita, faculty of medicine, university of alexandria, alexandria, 21321, Egypt</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>khaled madbouly</name>
      <address>kolyet el teb street, Azarita, faculty of medicine, university of alexandria, alexandria, 21321, Egypt</address>
      <phone>+20 34802375</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khaled.madbouly@alexmed.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>khaled madbouly</name>
      <address>kolyet el teb street, Azarita, faculty of medicine, university of alexandria, alexandria, 21321, Egypt</address>
      <phone>+20  34802375</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khaled.madbouly@alexmed.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>