<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366545">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000983505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of phase II cardiac rehabilitation on lower limb function in patients after coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of phase II cardiac rehabilitation on lower limb function in patients after coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery with collection of saphenous vein.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>216787 - National Science Centre </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Heart disease </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients will be qualified to Phase II cardiac rehabilitation in accordance with the standards of cardiac rehabilitation which is up to 4 weeks after CABG surgery on the basis of an exercise test using the modified Bruce protocol. Participants will be randomised to two groups. One group will take part in the early hospital rehabilitation (3 weeks - this is the overall duration of the program), while the second group will take part in ambulatory rehabilitation (8 weeks).

For the group of patients undergoing 3-week early hospital rehabilitation, rehabilitation sessions will be carried out five times a week. 

Cardiac rehabilitation is composed of:
a) aerobic exercise on a stationary cycle ergometer 3-5day/week, 30 minutes
b) resistance training - 3 days/week, 3 session, 6 different exercises, 15 repetitions at 70% HR, 25 minutes for session
c) general development exercises (exercise to increase physical performance) - 5 days/week, 20 different exercises, the intensity selected in accordance with the result of exercise testing (exercises for the upper limbs, lower limbs, breathing exercises), 30 minutes.

Physical activity will be carried out in the form of training on cycle ergometer each time to achieve the patient's submaximal heart rate (submaximal heart rate is 85% of maximum heart rate. Maximum heart is calculated using the formula: 220 - age). 

Exercises take place in a group carried by a physiotherapist.</interventions>
    <comparator>The second group will take part in ambulatory rehabilitation (8 weeks).

 While in the group of patients undergoing 8-weeks ambulatory rehabilitation, rehabilitation sessions will be carried out 3 times a week. 

Cardiac rehabilitation is composed of:
a) aerobic exercise on a stationary cycle ergometer 3 /week, 30 minutes
b) resistance training - 3 days/week, 3 sesion, 6 different exercises, 12-15 repetitions at 70% HR, 25 minutes for session
c) general development exercises (exercise to increase physical performance) - 3 days/week, 20 different exercises, the intensity selected in accordance with the result of exercise testing (exercises for the upper limbs, lower limbs, breathing exercises), 30 minutes.

Physical activity will be carried out in the form of training on cycle ergometer each time to achieve the patient's submaximal heart rate (submaximal heart rate is 85% of maximum heart rate. Maximum heart is calculated using the formula: 220 - age). 

Exercises take place in a group carried by a physiotherapist.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Temperature distribution in lower half of both lower limbs assessed using VarioCam thermal imaging camera;</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. measurement - one day before surgery (for I group),
2. measurement - after surgery (21 days) and simultaneously before the start of the Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation (one day before the start of the Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation - for I and II group)
3. measurement  after completing Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation  for Group I after 3 weeks (after 21 days), for Group II after 8 weeks of cardiac rehabilitation (on the last day rehabilitation).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Venous blood flow in lower limbs assessed by photoplethysmogram;</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. measurement - one day before surgery (for I group),
2. measurement - after surgery (21 days) and simultaneously before the start of the Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation (one day before the start of the Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation - for I and II group)
3. measurement  after completing Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation  for Group I after 3 weeks (after 21 days), for Group II after 8 weeks of cardiac rehabilitation (on the last day rehabilitation).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Composite measure of strength of dorsal and plantar flexors assessed by EMG of gastrocnemius and anterior tibial muscles;</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. measurement - one day before surgery (for I group),
2. measurement - after surgery (21 days) and simultaneously before the start of the Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation (one day before the start of the Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation - for I and II group)
3. measurement  after completing Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation  for Group I after 3 weeks (after 21 days), for Group II after 8 weeks of cardiac rehabilitation (on the last day rehabilitation).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- physical activity assessment using IPAQ (International Physical Activity Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>All tests will be carried out:
1. measurement - one day before surgery (for Group I),
2. measurement  after completing Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation  for Group I after 3 weeks (after 21 days).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Quality of life, assessed using SF-36 and WHOQOL-BREF
</outcome>
      <timepoint>All tests will be carried out:
1. measurement - one day before surgery (for Group I),
2. measurement  after completing Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation  for Group I after 3 weeks (after 21 days).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- Exercise tolerance, assessed by 6MWT.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. measurement - one day before surgery (for I group),
2. measurement - after surgery (21 days) and simultaneously before the start of the Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation (one day before the start of the Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation - for I and II group)
3. measurement  after completing Phase II of cardiac rehabilitation  for Group I after 3 weeks (after 21 days), for Group II after 8 weeks of cardiac rehabilitation (on the last day rehabilitation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. eligible participants must have coronary heart disease and must have been scheduled to undergo CABG surgery
2. Participants written consent,
3. Age between 50-70 years,
4. Stable condition, without periods of exacerbations occurring during the 4 weeks from the surgery, before the start of the rehabilitation program,
5. Patients will be qualified to Phase II cardiac rehabilitation in accordance with the standards of cardiac rehabilitation which is up to 4 weeks after CABG surgery on the basis of an exercise test using the modified Bruce protocol
6. Not participating in rehabilitation programs within a year of the start of the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Unstable angina,
2. Kidney failure,
3. Liver failure,
4. Inflammation,
5. Skin conditions in the assessment point,
6. Acute bronchitis, pneumonia, tuberculosis,
7. Asthma,
8. Uncontrolled high blood pressure (hypertension triggers and accelerates the formation of atherosclerotic in the coronary 
    arteries as well as coronary bypasses,
9. Mental handicap preventing cooperation,
10. Orthopaedic and neurological conditions, which reduce the efficiency of the motor function and the ability of the patient
    to cooperate during the scheduled training,
11. Mental disorder preventing cooperation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The minimum number of patients for analysis participants needed to achieve study objectives was determined for 60 (30 patients for I group and 30 patients for II group). 
The I Group - 30 patients with coronary heart disease in whom measurements will be performed before and after saphenous vein autograft CABG surgery and after 3 weeks of cardiac rehabilitation (Phase II early hospital). 
The II Group - In those 30 patients tests will be carried out before and after 8 weeks of Phase II ambulatory cardiac rehabilitation. Test results will be compiled in an Excel spreadsheet, and then subjected to statistical analysis using STATISTICA PL. The basic descriptive characteristics measurable characteristics will be calculated the arithmetic mean, standard deviation, minimum and maximum value and the median of the upper and lower quartiles.
After checking the normality of the Shapiro-Wilk test, it will be decided on the type of statistical tests used:
* In the absence of evidence to reject the hypothesis of normal distribution is performed univariate analysis of variance with repeated measures and post-hoc test (NIR)
* rejecting the hypothesis of normal distribution effect of cardiac rehabilitation conducted (training) will be assessed Friedman ANOVA for significant relationships between the terms of the following will be used in post hoc test Friedman
* to demonstrate the connection will be used Pearson correlations simple or rank Spaermana (for the characteristics of the distribution is different from the normal).

The statistical tests used to the test values and the coefficients for the level of p &lt;0.05 will be accepted as statistically significant. 
The calculation of sample size were not performed. It was assumed that 30 participants is required.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>21/03/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Wroclaw</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Aleksandra Skomudek</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Opole University of Technology 76 Proszkowska Street, 45-758 Opole
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Poland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Science Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Science Centre
ul. Krolewska 57
30-081 Krakow, Poland</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Poland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the proposed research is to evaluate the effectiveness of phase II cardiac rehabilitation in patients after insertion of coronary bypass with reference to the lower limb venous system adaptation process after surgical intervention; the degree of impairment of blood flow in the designated area of the body, the hemodynamic response and force and muscle function of dorsal and plantar flexors of indicated limb. The research involves two different rehabilitation programs, ie. 3-week and 8-week rehabilitation treatment. That will be compared in this study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Senate Committee Ethics of University School of Physical in Wroclaw</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>51-612 Wroclaw, 
al. I. J. Paderewskiego 35</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Aleksandra Skomudek</name>
      <address>The Opole University of Technology 76 Proszkowska Street, 45-758 Opole
</address>
      <phone>+48 663 266 278</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>olskom2@op.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Aleksandra Skomudek</name>
      <address>The Opole University of Technology 76 Proszkowska Street, 45-758 Opole
</address>
      <phone>+48 663 266 278</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>olskom2@op.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Aleksandra Skomudek</name>
      <address>The Opole University of Technology 76 Proszkowska Street, 45-758 Opole</address>
      <phone>+48 663 266 278</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>olskom2@op.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Aleksandra Skomudek</name>
      <address>The Opole University of Technology 76 Proszkowska Street, 45-758 Opole</address>
      <phone>+48 663 266 278</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>olskom2@op.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>