<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367160">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001088639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A preoperative warming regime versus no preoperative warming for maintenance of normothermia in women receiving intrathecal morphine for caesarean section. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Women receiving intrathecal morphine for caesarean section receiving preoperative warming versus no preoperative warming for maintenance of normothermia. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1162-2246 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Inadvertent perioperative hypothermia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A 20 minute period of full body preoperative warming using a Cocoon (Trademark) forced air warming device, whilst the patient is waiting in the preoperative waiting area and immediately before transfer to the operating theatre for induction of spinal anaesthesia. 
Forced air warming will be administered via a full body warming blanket applied whilst participants are sitting in a recliner.  The temperature setting applied will be 43 degrees celsius. </interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care: no forced air prewarming, warmed cotton blankets applied during the preoperative waiting period in the preoperative waiting area (which have been kept in a warming cabinet set at 60 degrees celsius and remain in place throughout surgery). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome: mean maternal core temperature decline ( in degrees celsius) as measured at the following sites: aural canal via infrared thermometer, bladder (via urinary catheter thermistor) 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (aural)
Prior to induction of spinal anaesthesia (aural)
Post induction of spinal anaesthesia (aural)
Every 15 minutes throughout the surgical procedure (bladder and aural) 
At the end of the surgical procedure (bladder and aural canal)
On post-anaesthetic care unit (PACU) arrival, (aural)
Every 15 minutes until PACU ready for discharge time (aural)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal hypothermia (core temperature to below 36 degrees celsius) measured by infrared aural canal thermometer and urinary catheter thermistor</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to induction of spinal anaesthesia
Post induction of spinal anaesthesia
Every 15 minutes during procedure
At the end of the procedure
On arrival to post-anaesthetic care unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal thermal comfort via a 100mm visual analogue scale (VAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Prior to induction of spinal anaesthesia
At end of surgical procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal shivering measured on a three-point scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
Prior to induction of spinal anaesthesia. 
Operating theatre:end of procedure
PACU: arrival
PACU: 15 mins
PACU: 30 mins
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Apgar scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 minute after delivery
5 minutes after delivery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neonatal axillary temperature (degrees celsius) via electronic thermometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>At birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women receiving intrathecal morphine whilst undergoing spinal anaesthesia for elective caesarean section at the Mater Mothers hospital.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Emergency caesarean section
Epidural top-up, general anaesthesia or epidural opiates during combined spinal-epidural
Women not receiving intrathecal morphine during spinal anaesthesia for caesarean section
Known allergy to morphine
Admission temperature of &gt; 37 degrees celsius
Known impaired thermoregulation or thyroid disorders
Tympanic membrane/aural canal not visible on otoscopy
Vascular disease or poor cutaneous perfusion 
Planned postoperative ICU admissions
American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) score &gt; II
History of preeclampsia or eclampsia.
Delay between completion of warming intervention and the transfer to theatre that is greater than 20 minutes. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants for recruitment will be identified via the elective surgery booking process and will be approached at the Preoperative Assessment Clinic held at approximately 36 weeks gestation.  Written information (Letter of Invitation, Participant Information Brochure) and oral information will be provided by the principal investigator or research assistant. Potential participants will be given the opportunity to ask questions. Informed consent will be obtained prior to randomisation into study groups. Further eligibility for inclusion into the study will be determined on the day of surgery (in relation to inclusion/exclusion criteria related to health status, such as baseline temperature &lt;37 degrees celsius or preeclampsia).
Allocation to treatment or control groups will be concealed from the allocator.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised to either the control or intervention group by the opening of a sealed envelope after they have consented to take part, on the day of admission. The allocation sequence will be generated via simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A sample size of 15 participants in each group is required. The calculation was based on a repeated measures design with the initial temperatures being the same and the temperature decline being 0.4 degrees celsius greater in the unwarmed group than the warmed group 45 minutes after commencement of surgery. A standard deviation of 0.4 degrees celsius was used in the calculation, based on the data reported by Chung et al (2012). A type I error rate of 0.05 and a power of 90% were specified. The sample size was inflated from a total of 30 to a total of 50 to allow for attrition. 

SPSS software (version 15) will be utilised for data analysis. Descriptive statistics will be used to report the sample characteristics, and summarise hypothermia prevalence. Means standard deviations, median and interquartile ranges, will be reported, along with 95% confidence intervals where appropriate. A p value of &lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant. Repeated measures Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) will be used for examining core temperature decline within and between groups.  Additionally, a random coefficients model will be constructed by fitting curves to individual data and these will be used to examine within-group and between-group variability in more detail. All analyses will be performed on the Intention to Treat population. A Bland-Altman analysis will be used for examining agreement between aural canal and bladder temperature.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/01/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>10/02/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>50</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Mater Mother's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Judy Munday</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Mater Nursing Research Centre, Mater Health Services, Rm 284 Level 2, Aubigny Place, Raymond Terrace, South Brisbane, QLD 4101</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mater Nursing Research Centre, Mater Health Services</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Mater Nursing Research Centre, Mater Health Services, Rm 284 Level 2, Aubigny Place, Raymond Terrace, South Brisbane QLD 4101</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Queensland University of Technology </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Nursing, Victoria Park Road, Kelvin Grove, QLD 4059</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr David Sturgess</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Dept of Intensive Care Medicine, Mater Health Services, Raymond Terrace, South Brisbane, QLD 4101</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Women undergoing caesarean section experience high rates of heat loss and hypothermia related to surgery and
anaesthesia. As well as causing discomfort, hypothermia experienced during and after anaesthesia and surgery is
also associated with many adverse effects, for example increased blood loss. It is also thought that spinal
morphine, commonly given during caesarean section for pain relief, may also exacerbate heat loss. This project
aims to test warming patients preoperatively via a warming blanket (which utilises heated air) to reduce the amount
of heat loss during surgery.
A randomised controlled study design will be used: the control group will receive normal care while the intervention
group will receive preoperative warming.
Potential participants will be identified via the surgical booking process. Recruitment and informed consent will
occur at the preoperative assessment appointment. Participants will be randomly assigned, on the day of surgery, to either the control group receiving usual care, or the intervention group receiving preoperative warming.
Temperature will be recorded throughout the preoperative period, during surgery and during the postoperative
period in the recovery unit. Data will be analysed to investigate differences in the amount of temperature lost
(temperature decline) in each group and comparisons made. Thermal comfort experienced by mothers will also be
determined, as well as the incidence of shivering. Comparisons will also be made between newborn temperature and Apgar scores (used to assess the health of the newborn). </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mater Research, Rm 294, Level 2, Aubigny Place, South Brisbane, QLD 4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/MHS/157</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/07/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Judy Munday</name>
      <address>Mater Nursing Research Centre, Rm 284 Level 2, Aubigny Place, Raymond Terrace, South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3163 5368</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3163 2549</fax>
      <email>judy.munday@mater.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Judy Munday </name>
      <address>Mater Nursing Research Centre, Rm 284 Level 2, Aubigny Place, Raymond Terrace, South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3163 5368</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3163 2549</fax>
      <email>judy.munday@hdr.qut.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Judy Munday</name>
      <address>Mater Nursing Research Centre, Rm 284 Level 2, Aubigny Place, Raymond Terrace, South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3163 1908</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 3163 2549</fax>
      <email>judy.munday@hdr.qut.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Judy Munday</name>
      <address>Mater Nursing Research Centre, Rm 284 Level 2, Aubigny Place, Raymond Terrace, South Brisbane QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3163 5368</phone>
      <fax>07 3163 2549</fax>
      <email>judy.munday@hdr.qut.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>