<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362023">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000148875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Promoting Self-Regulation and Cooperation in Pre-Kindergarten children with Conduct
Problems: A Randomized Controlled Trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a "common elements" co-parent training program (called 'Hitkashrut') on conduct in preschoolers at risk for conduct problems.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1127-5296</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>conduct problems</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention (called `Hitkashrut`):
In October 2006 a research pilot was initiated with kindergarten teachers in order to create Israeli norms for a screening instrument and to test screening and referral procedures in collaboration with national supervisors of Ministry of Education`s Preschool education division. Master-level educational psychologists working at three local services in the Jerusalem region co-facilitated a manual-based sequence of semi-structured two-hour meetings with groups of 5-7 couples. Sessions were conducted once weekly over a period of 14 weeks and were organized according to a 4-part structure: joining and following-up on last sessions homework; psycho-educational instruction with facilitators modeling problematic and optimal behaviors using prepared role plays; group discussion including spontaneous parental role plays; summary of take-home points and home-work assignments. Handouts summarized each session and highlighted the take-home points. Behavior management skills were learned and practiced by establishing differential reinforcement programs with each parental dyad during a half-hour couple meeting with one facilitator (after session 5 only), followed by one phone call and in-session checkups.</interventions>
    <comparator>Minimal Support Control Group. The parents were referred for two consultation sessions (2 hours). Sessions occurred at baseline and 3 months later, and were administered by Master-level educational psychologists to each couple. The facilitators made use of Hitkashruts key components and handouts, and where necessary referred parents to regular community care.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome: Children`s Conduct Problems as assessed by Eyberg Child Behavior Inventory (ECBI).</outcome>
      <timepoint>T1: pre-intervention (Baseline); T2: within one month post- intervention; T3: 1-year follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Callous-unemotional traits as assessed by the preschool modification of the Antisocial Process Screening Device and a preschool version of the Inventory of CU traits.</outcome>
      <timepoint>T1: pre-intervention (Baseline); T2: within one month post- intervention; T3 (only intervention group) 1-year follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Effortful Control as assessed by the Child Behavioral Questionnaire (CBQ) adapted for preschoolers</outcome>
      <timepoint>T1: pre-intervention (Baseline); T2: within one month post- intervention; T3 (only intervention group) 1-year follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>parental distress as assessed by the Parental Stress Index-Short Form (PSI-SF), and the Parental Helplessness Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>T1: pre-intervention (Baseline); T2: within one month post- intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Negative/inconsistent parenting as assessed by the Alabama Parenting Questionnaire- Preschool, Revised.</outcome>
      <timepoint>T1: pre-intervention (Baseline); T2: within one month post- intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Couple relationship quality as assessed by the Marital Quality Scale (MQS-I).</outcome>
      <timepoint>T1: pre-intervention (Baseline); T2: within one month post- intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria were (a) enrolment in pre-kindergartens (in Israel usually 3-5 years old); (b) significant disruptive behaviors; (c) no physical disability, intellectual impairment, or pervasive developmental delay reported by teachers; (d) no other psychological treatment; (e) agreement of both caregivers to attend.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>32</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>64</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria were (a) physical disability, intellectual impairment, or pervasive developmental delay reported by teachers; (b) other psychological treatment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>sequentially numbered, opaque, sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>random number sequences were generated using a randomisation table from a statistic book (The 2:1 allocation using random numbers).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/12/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>210</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof. Yoel Elizur</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Mount Scopus, Jerusalem 91905</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Israel</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Education</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Deborah haneviha 2, Jerusalem 91911</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Israel</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Lior Y. Somech</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Mount Scopus, Jerusalem 91905</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Israel</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The objective of the study was to test the real-world effectiveness and mechanisms of Hitkashrut: a theory-based, common elements, PT program for early intervention with preschoolers (3-5) at risk for conduct problems. Hitkashrut, "attachment" in Hebrew, is also an acronym for relationship- supporting and hope-inspiring parenting. Hitkashruts intervention model was based on the theory and research of disruptive developmental pathways that showed elevated levels of child malleability and caretakers' influence during the preschool years and consequently, unique opportunities for changing the CP trajectory by restructuring formative parental/marital patterns.  Hitkashruts overall strategy for changing child CP and associated dispositions is to inhibit negative and oftentimes coercive parent-child cycles and to promote regulated cooperative relationships characterized by mutual responsiveness and positive affectivity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Chief Scientist of the Ministry of Education</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Deborah Haneviah 2, Jerusalem 91911</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/11/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Israel</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof. Yoel Elizur</name>
      <address>Hebrew University of Jerusalem
Mount Scopus, Jerusalem, Israel 91905</address>
      <phone>972-2-588-1331</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mselizur@mscc.huji.ac.il</email>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lior Y. Somech</name>
      <address>Hebrew University of Jerusalem
Mount Scopus, Jerusalem, Israel 91905</address>
      <phone>972-2-588-1331</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>somech.lior@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Israel</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>