<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370748">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000891426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of endotracheal cuff pressure monitoring and regulation by conventional method using a  manometer compared to using a smart cuff manager in intubated Intensive Care Unit patients and nursing outcomes of such practices</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Endotracheal Cuff Pressure Monitoring And Regulation - a comparison between the conventional manometer and Tracoe Smart Cuff Manager in intubated, Intensive Care Unit patients and the nursing outcomes </scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1183-1742</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Nursing staff managing ventilated patients in ICU</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is an educational intervention on nurses knowledge and practice of endotracheal cuff pressure management

The study will be divided into three phases as follows: 

1. Phase one involve data collection on nurses knowledge and practice at the pre-intervention level (baseline knowledge) and educational intervention. 
Nursing continuous education (CNE) sessions will be held where they will be updated regarding latest practices in ETT cuff pressure management. 8 sessions will be held, once a week for an hour for a group of 15-20 nurses. The CNEs will be delivered by a nursing masters student as well as by a representative from Tracoe. Attendance will be taken during each session.
The intervention comprises theoretical educational sessions and this will be followed by the introduction of a TRACOE smart cuff manager to maintain continuous cuff pressure. This will include demonstration of skills on cuff pressure monitoring and management using both methods, traditional method and using TRACOE smart cuff manager.  
  
2.      Phase two will involve implementation of the TRACOE smart cuff manager compared to the conventional method. Both groups of patients will have their ETT cuff pressure measure 6 hourly. 
The TRACOE Smart Cuff Manager is a mechanical device, made up of a small elastic balloon inside a plastic shell which can be used to regulate endotracheal tube (ETT) cuff inflation. The Smart Cuff Manager will be attached to the ETT pilot balloon to monitor and regulate the cuff pressure within the acceptable range. Patients will be randomized to the conventional group (ETT cuff pressure monitored using a handheld manometer) or to the TRACOE Smart Cuff Manager group. Both groups will have the ETT cuff pressure monitored every 6 hours until extubation or until day 15 of intubation, whichever is longer. 
This phase will take approximately 6 months.  

3. In phase three, the nurses perceptions of the endotracheal cuff management in actual practice will collected using focus group interviews. 

- Patients who are randomized to the TRACOE Smart Cuff Manager group will have their cuffs connected to the Smart Cuff Manager and the balloon will be inflated with air until it is 2/3 to 3/4 (usually 60ml) the volume of the outer shell. Cuff pressure will be measured every 4-6 hours using a handheld manometer.   

- The control group will be managed the conventional way, with ETT cuff pressures measured every 4 to 6 hours using a handheld manometer</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be managed the conventional way - no cuff pressure regulation device will be used and the ETT cuff pressure will be measured every 6 hours using a handheld manometer. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nursing knowledge regarding cuff pressure management techniques based on pre and post teaching questionnaire which was specifically designed for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed prior to teaching sessions and after the conclusion of the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the efficacy of the Tracoe Smart Cuff Manager as compared to the conventional way of ETT cuff pressure management - ETT cuff pressure will be monitored every 4-6 hourly for each patient. It will be assessed by the number of readings on the manometer which is outside the recommended range (20-30cmH20)
  </outcome>
      <timepoint>ETT cuff pressure will be measured every 4-6hours for all patients throughout the period of intubation or until day 15 of intubation, whichever is longer</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare between the 2 groups of patients - developement of post extubation stridor, sore throat and requirement for reintubation (a composite secondary outcome). This will be assessed by observation of the patient post extubation. Patients will also be asked if they are experiencing sore throat.
  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Patients will be assessed for these signs and symptoms post extubation which indicates tracheal mucosal injury</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All staff nurses working in the ICU and fulfill the inclusion criteria for nurses: 
(i)	had more than six months working experience in critical care units and 
(ii)	willingness to participate.  

Patients who will be included are:
All adult ICU patients above 18 years old who are intubated with an orotracheal tube or tracheostomy tube.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nurses with less than 6 months of experience in ICU
Unwillingness to participate

Patient's exclusion criteria:
Patients with upper airway pathology
Patients with underlying chronic lung disease or restrictive lung disease
Patients who may have aspirated during intubation (e.g difficult intubation, food particles in oral cavity during intubation)
Patient who are ventilated in the general ward or who have been ventilated in the general ward for more than 24 hours prior to ICU admission.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>None</concealment>
    <sequence>None</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods> A survey method will be used to assess nurses current practice of endotracheal cuff pressure measurement. 
· A quasi-experimental approach will be utilized to examine the effect of educational  intervention on nurses knowledge and practice of cuff pressure management. 
· A qualitative approach will be adopted to explore the nurses perception on managing the patients endotracheal tube cuff pressure using the traditional method and TRACOE smart cuff manager. 
  
No sample size calculations have been performed as the aim is to educate all nurses in the ICU regarding cuff pressure management</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>22/04/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>95</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Kuala Lumpur</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University Malaya Medical Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Malaya Medical Centre, Lembah Pantai, 59100 Kuala Lumpur</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Tracoe Medical</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>TRACOE medical GmbH, Reichelsheimer StraBe 1 / 3, 55268 Nieder-Olm</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Germany</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname> Dr. Vimala A/P Ramoo </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress> Department of Nursing Science, Faculty of Medicine, University of Malaya, 50603 Kuala Lumpur</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Malaysia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is hypothesised that this study could help to improve the practice of endotracheal cuff pressure management in the intensive care unit. The outcome achieved could lead to the establishment of a standardised practice on cuff pressure management that would enhance quality of patient care.
Continuous cuff pressure regulation would be a more cost and time effective way in ensuring the cuff pressure is not under- or over-inflated, hence reducing the risk of VAP and tracheal mucosal injury. 
It is also hoped that nurses would be able to take a more active role in patient management with appropriate knowledge and skill, and this would enhance patients ventilation management and increase patient safety.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Ethics Committee, University Malaya Medical Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lembah Pantai, 59100 Kuala Lumpur</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>20162-2155</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370748-Questionnaire  knowledge and practice on endotracheal cuff(1).pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name> Vimala A/P Ramoo </name>
      <address>Department of Nursing Science, Faculty of Medicine, University of Malaya, 50603 Kuala Lumpur, MALAYSIA</address>
      <phone>+60379492028</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vimala@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name> Vimala A/P Ramoo </name>
      <address>Department of Nursing Science, Faculty of Medicine, University of Malaya, 50603 Kuala Lumpur, MALAYSIA</address>
      <phone>+60379492028</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vimala@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name> Vimala A/P Ramoo </name>
      <address>Department of Nursing Science, Faculty of Medicine, University of Malaya, 50603 Kuala Lumpur, MALAYSIA</address>
      <phone>+60379492028</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vimala@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Basyir</name>
      <address>University Malaya Medical Centre,
Lembah Pantai, 59100 Kuala Lumpur</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>basyir1985@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>