<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335840">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/03/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000318987</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Development of a better screening test for bowel cancer.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of blood-based screening tests for colorectal neoplasia; from biomarker candidates to accurate and acceptable tests.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>colorectal cancer.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Colorectal cancer (CRC) is the second leading cause of death from cancer despite the fact that the disease is curable when detected in its early stages. Furthermore, CRC is preventable by a number of methods which include adenoma detection and removal

Studies of faecal occult blood testing have demonstrated that annual screening with such tests leads to a reduction in mortality

Studies clearly show that screening can also lower cancer incidence through the early detection and removal of precancerous polyps including adenomas.

Based on this evidence, to effectively decrease incidence at the population level, we need to identify and remove adenomas. The current methods for identifying people likely to have adenomas are largely ad hoc and limited.

Conversely, a sensitive and specific marker with strong positive predictive value for colorectal adenomas would provide an effective selection process for individuals to undergo colonoscopy, and polypectomy when an adenoma is found. 

The literature now describes a number of molecular characteristics of adenomas that may be useful in this setting but none of these has been explored for its value in blood or faeces. In addition, preliminary molecular studies here at Flinders University using materials from the tissue bank have identified approximately 67 genes that show promise differentiating adenomas from normal tissue
We now have a need to establish a clinical bank of relevant target clinical materials (specifically faeces and blood), that would allow us to determine the presence of these markers in faeces and blood and to relate them to the neoplastic status of patients.

Phase 1 research and research by others has identified several colorectal neoplasia-associated biomarkers in blood that may be useful, individually or together, for the development of new screening tests for early detection of colorectal neoplasia. 

Phase 2 of the research will evaluate the accuracy in larger population samples of several candidate biomarkers for detection of screen-relevant colorectal neoplasia, relative to a proven immunochemical faecal occult blood test (iFOBT, FIT) and the diagnostic test colonoscopy. The panel includes at least one candidate biomarker, KIAA1199, highly expressed in colorectal neoplasia relative to normal colonic epithelium, and which is also detectable in blood of CRC patients. 

To evaluate the accuracy of a panel of blood-based candidate biomarkers for detection of screen-relevant colorectal neoplasia, relative findings at colonoscopy, a commercial blood based test for CRC and to a proven faecal occult blood test (FOBT). 
We will invite participants who are scheduled for a colonoscopy to complete an FOBT (Faecal Occult Blood Test), on one occasion only, prior to their colonoscopy. 
The participant will be asked to collect a sample of approximately 0.5 g of stool using provided scoop and transfer the scoop with faeces into a double sealed, self-contained transport vessel that stabilizes and disperses the faecal sample for storage and transport. 
We will take one blood sample only just prior to the participants colonoscopy procedure. 
We will view the results (histopathology) of colonoscopy or/and any ensuing colorectal surgery

Phase 2b
Some patients resected for CRC will be subsequently diagnosed with further (recurrent) cancer, not necessarily located within the bowel. Some current simple methods to monitor patients for recurrence of CRC, such as CEA, are not optimal. A blood test using the biomarker panel may more sensitive for detection of recurrent cancers and blood samples will be assayed for our markers during monitoring as approved for serial sampling after diagnosis.
To explore this possibility, we first need to determine whether the CRC biomarkers we have identified are detectable in tumour tissues from both an initial and any subsequent cancer from the same patient. We propose an initial small retrospective observational sub-study within BiBCoN to determine the pattern of expression of the markers across time and tumour locations. One or both of the tumour samples would be derived from the Joint RGH and FMC Tissue Bank where patients have consented for tissue to be accessed for research. Where possible the level of expression of other clinical biomarkers for recurrent cancer may be determined on the same tissue samples. 
If both samples from the same patient prove to be positive for the biomarker test panel in a small initial sample, further prospective studies using tissues and blood from patients with recurrent cancer will be proposed to explore the feasibility of the blood test to detect cancer recurrence.Each patient will be followed for 2 years
</interventions>
    <comparator>Cases are those patients with a neoplastic diagnosis and where a positive FOBT test would be regarded as a true-positive, namely: cancer (also subcategorised into late Dukes C/D or early Dukes A/B stages), advanced adenoma (size &gt;9mm, villous change, HGD, serrated morphology, number &gt;2), or non-advanced adenoma. 
Controls are those without neoplasia where a positive test would represent a false-positive. They will include a range of benign disease such as inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) since biomarkers might be non-specifically elevated in such conditions. Co-variates that might influence test results to be ascertained include: benign colorectal disease such as IBD, age band by decade, family history of colorectal neoplasia and gender.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the accuracy of a panel of blood-based candidate biomarkers for detection of screen-relevant colorectal neoplasia, relative findings at colonoscopy, a commercial blood based test for CRC and to a proven faecal occult blood test (FOBT).</outcome>
      <timepoint>two years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The goal/objective is: To develop a more accurate screening test for CRC.
 
The aim is to determine whether a blood based gene test is as accurate as an FOBT in determining whether a person is at high risk of having curable CRC or advanced adenoma, relative to colonoscopy as the gold standard
 
There are specific aims relating to each of the potential new marker ie is SEPT9 as accurate as FIT.
 
The primary outcomes are the specific measurement used. These will be the levels of gene expression in each genetic marker in the panel of markers and the haemoglobin level in the FOBT. 
 
Relative accuracy is determined by comparison of each of the blood based genetic markers and the FOBT result versus colonoscopy</outcome>
      <timepoint>two years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Phase 2b) To determine whether there is  potential for recurrent cancers to be detected earlier with the new biomarker panel than the currently available blood tests (such as CEA). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Two years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Putative screening test markers need to be validated in larger population samples against a diagnostic test as well as the best available alternative screening test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>two years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The biomarkers are also present in tumour tissues. We therefore wish to obtain data on expression status of the biomarker panel in tumour and/or adenoma samples in CRC cases where cancer has recurred, to determine, in cases where the markers are expressed in the primary (initial) cancer, whether they are also expressed in subsequently developing lesions.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients scheduled for colonoscopy for standard clinical indications.
Patients must be capable of providing satisfactory informed consent
In addition for Phase 2b
Cases with a diagnosis of CRC who have been treated and are being monitored for recurrence. 
Cases where tumour tissues and/or blood samples with associated consent for use in research are available
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability to provide informed consent
Patients who undergo an incomplete colonoscopy which raises doubt as to the status of the colon (post-hoc exclusion).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/04/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/09/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>4000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Repatriation Hospital - Daw Park</hospital>
    <postcode>5042</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Flinders Medical Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1 Flinders Drive
Bedford Park
5042
South Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601 
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Clinical Genomics Pty Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>11 Julius Ave
Riverside Life Science Bldg
North Ryde NSW 2113</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Repatriation General Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>202-216 Daws Road
Daw Park
5041
South Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to develop a more accurate screening test for colorectal cancer (CRC) by evaluating the accuracy of a panel of blood-based candidate biomarkers, and to determine whether there is there potential for recurrent cancers to be detected earlier with the new biomarker panel than the currently available blood tests. Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 to 85 years old, and are scheduled for colonoscopy for standard clinical indications. 
Participants with a diagnosis of colorectal cancer (CRC) who have been treated and are being monitored for recurrence will also be eligible for the second phase of the study. 

Study details All participants in this study will be asked to undergo several tests for bowel cancer and bowel polyps in blood and saliva at the time of their booked hospital procedure]. 
The tests include established tests such as colonoscopy and faecal occult blood tests which we will compare to new tests that we are developing that detect specific markers in blood. If we can reliably detect these markers then we will be able to develop a better screening test for bowel cancer.
 In patients who have been previously treated for bowel cancer and who are being monitored for signs of recurrence, we will also explore the use of the new biomarker blood test. It is hoped that this test may be more sensitive and detect recurrence much earlier than is now possible. The overall duration of observation in each participant is two years post surgery or other treatment for CRC
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Health Service/Flinders University Human Reserach Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics 
Southern Adelaide Health Service
SA Health
Flinders Medical Centre
Bedford Park 
SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/01/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>134/045</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Erin Symonds</name>
      <address>Principal Medical Scientist
Bowel Health Service Repatriation General Hospital 
Daw Park SA 5041 /
Flinders Centre for Innovation in Cancer , Bedford Park , 5042</address>
      <phone>+618 8275 1070</phone>
      <fax>+618 82751838</fax>
      <email>erin.symonds@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Susie Byrne</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology, 
Flinders Centre for Innovation in Cancer,
 Flinders Medical Centre, Bedford Park 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 7402</phone>
      <fax>+618 8204 6330</fax>
      <email>susie.byrne@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Susan Byrne</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology, 
Flinders Centre for Innovation in Cancer,
Flinders Medical Centre, Bedford Park 5042</address>
      <phone>+618 8204 7402</phone>
      <fax>+618 8204 6330</fax>
      <email>susie.byrne@sa.gov.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Graeme P Young,</name>
      <address>Flinders Centre for Innovation in Cancer, Flinders University.
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 417 860 540</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>graeme.young@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>