<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370652">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001512415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Hospital based physiotherapy for patients with non-small cell lung cancer during in-hospital undergoing in-hospital cytostatics treatment</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of hospital based physiotherapy for patients undergoing in-hospital chemotherapy for non-small cell lung cancer on physical fitness, dyspnea and quality of life</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>lung cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Lung - Non small cell</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this project, it is proposed to examine the relationship between comprehensive hospital based physiotherapy in patients with non-small-cell lung carcinoma during cytostatic treatment and its impact on physical fitness, patient endurance, health related quality of life, dyspnea and fatigue. It is believed that the results obtained during our research will emphasise the importance of physiotherapy in the treatment for oncology patients.
In the research will participate 50 patients (in the researched group 25 participants and in the control group 25 participants) with stage III or IV non-small-cell lung carcinoma (NSCLC), diagnosed within the last 6 weeks, or with earlier stage of the disease, excluded from surgery or radiation), confirmed by cytology or histology test results. The research study will take place at the Independent Public Clinical Hospital No. 3 of Medical University of Silesia in Katowice.
The rehabilitation group: Based on the initial 6MWT and spirometry results, subjects will participate in two, two week periods of rehabilitative exercise therapy, supervised by certified Physiotherapist. Before first 2-weeks rehabilitation program and between these two periods, patients proceed to scheduled chemotherapy in hospital condition.The control group: There will be a 6 week period between initial and final assessments; during the middle two weeks patients proceed to a scheduled chemotherapy period.
Patients will participate in exercise sessions 5 times per week. Sessions consisted of:
Morning exercises 
1. (8:30-9:00 am)  specific respiratory exercises for 30 minutes - relaxation exercises for breathing muscles, strengthening exercises the diaphragm with resistance, exercises to increase costal or chest breathing, prolonged exhalation exercise, chest percussion
2. (10:00-10:30 am) 30 minutes of fitness and respiratory exercises -  coordination and balance exercises, stretching exercises using elastic bands, balls rehabilitation, sensory pillows. Performed in a standing position, kneeling, sitting, lying on side, abdomen and back.
3. (11:00-11:30 am) training on a cycle ergometer or treadmill for 20-30 minutes, intensity 30% - 80% peak work rate.
Afternoon exercises
4. (1:00-1:30 pm) Resistance exercise intensity 40% - 70% 1RM, 
5. (3:00-4:00 pm) Nordic walking for 45 minutes (depending on weather and health condition of the patient), 
6. (4:00 pm) relaxation training - Autogenic training is a desensitation-relaxation technique developed by the German psychiatrist Johannes Heinrich Schultz. The technique involves the daily practice of sessions that last around 15 minutes. During each session, the practitioner repeats a set of visualisations that induce a state of relaxation. Each session can be practiced in a position chosen amongst a set of recommended postures (for example, lying down, sitting meditation, sitting like a rag doll). The technique can be used to alleviate many stress-induced psychosomatic disorders.
Heart rate and O 2 saturation will be monitore continuously throughout sessions exercise and blood pressure was assessed intermittently.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The patients of the control group will be assesses before and after 6 weeks of chemotherapy alone. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>physical fitness (endurance, fatigue) assessed using Functional Fitness Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. baseline - Initial assessment of the patient, Chemotherapy session (1 week home care)
2. 3 weeks - Assessment of the patient after rehabilitation physical fitness assessment.
3. 6 weeks - Final assessment of patient after 6 weeks including physical fitness assessment
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung function (composite of FEV1, FVC, FEV1%FVC) assessed using spirometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. baseline - Initial assessment of the patient,
2. 3 weeks - Assessment of the patient after rehabilitation lung function assessment.
3. 6 weeks - Final assessment of patient after 6 weeks lung function assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> dyspnea assessed using MRC, BDI, Borg Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. baseline - Initial assessment of the patient,
2. 3 weeks - Assessment of the patient after rehabilitation  dyspnea  assessment.
3. 6 weeks - Final assessment of patient after 6 weeks   dyspnoea assessment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quality of life assessed using St George's Respiratory Questionnaire, SF-36, Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - Lung (FACT-L)</outcome>
      <timepoint>1. baseline - Initial assessment of the patient,
2. 6 weeks - Final assessment of patient after 6 weeks  quality of life</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>ability to perform the 6 minute walk test, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status 0-1 and ability to complete self-questionnaires and willingness to participate/ cooperate in the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>uncontrolled hypertension or unstable coronary artery disease, anaemia (HB&lt; 10g/dl), severe osteoarthritis and bone metastases or CNS metastases.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The number of participants of research was determined depending on the average number of patients with diagnosis NSCLC in stage III B or IV (disqualified from surgery intervention) admitted to hospital in the previous year from the start of the study.
The data will be express as arithmetic mean (X) and standard deviation (SD). To investigate the difference in indication values between the measurements, the Wilcoxon Signed Ranks Test, which does not require Gaussian distribution.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state>Katowice</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Medical University of Silesia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>18 Medykow Street
40-752 Katowice
POLAND</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Poland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Medical University of Silesia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>18 Medykow Street
40-752 Katowice
POLAND
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Poland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress>none</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>1.	The patients diagnosed in last 6 weeks with non small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) in stage III or IV ( or in early advanced stage, disqualified from operation or radiotherapy), confirmed on the basis of result from cytological examination or histopathological.  Cancer staging TNM from medical records ( x-ray and CT of thorax, ultrasonography of abdominal cavity).
2.	Information for the patients about aims and principle in research and written consent of participation from the patients.
The aim of the study was to assess the effect of rehabilitation program conducted on fitness and exercise capacity, lung ventilatory function, quality of life and dyspnea. Additionally, possibility for rehabilitation in patients with advanced lung cancer was assessed.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> Ethics Committee of Silesian Medical University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress> Poniatowskiego 15 40-055 Katowice</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>KNW/0022/KB1/184a/I/11/12</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/12/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370652-ETHICS COMMITTEE OF MEDICAL UNIVERSITY OF SILESIA.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370652-ETHICS COMMITTEE OF MEDICAL UNIVERSITY OF SILESIA EN.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Anna Rutkowska</name>
      <address>Opole  University of Technology
76 Proszkowska Street 45-758 Opole</address>
      <phone>+48507541143</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.rutkowska@po.opole.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Sebastian Rutkowski</name>
      <address>Opole  University of Technology
76 Proszkowska Street 45-758 Opole</address>
      <phone>+48507027792</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.rutkowski@po.opole.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dariusz Jastrzebski</name>
      <address>Medical University of Silesia in Katowice
41-803 Zabrze, ul. Koziolka 1</address>
      <phone>+483732235</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>darekjdr@poczta.onet.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>