<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369632">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/12/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001379505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of new guidelines for admission for undifferentiated chest pain based on high sensitivity troponin.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of decision-making guidelines for admission of undifferentiated chest pain based on high-sensitivity troponin</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chest Pain</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Myocardial Infarction </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Heart attack</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention Arm: Results for patients randomised into the hs-TnT report will determine their care pathway. Baseline and a 2nd hs-Tn T formatted report at 1 hour will determine the disposition:
Rule-out: baseline troponin less than 5ng/L OR baseline troponin  less than 12ng/L with a change in troponin over 1 hour of  less than 3ng/L: discharge to primary care with instructions regarding repeat episodes of chest pain and primary prevention advice.
Rule-in: baseline troponin greater than  52ng/L OR a change over 1 hour of greater than  5ng/L: Admit to cardiology unit for ruling in as MI.
Observe: baseline troponin between 12-52 ng/L OR a change in troponin over 1 hour of 3-5ng/L will be admitted to an inpatient chest pain assessment unit.

Functional testing to be determined by clinician in the clinic but application of the NICE guidelines recommendations . These guidelines make recommendations regarding functional or invasive coronary testing based characterisation of chest pain and cardiovascular risk factors.

Monitoring will be conducted by data management when the study is analysed. Medical staff do not have to abide by the suggested pathways, but will be discussed as part of the analysis.

Any change in troponin at the 1 hour mark, dependent on those results will fall in that corresponding category. For example a baseline troponin may indicate they are in the rule out category, but the repeat 1 hour troponin for example if reflects a change of greater than 5ng/L would be allocated to the rule in stream.
Troponin is currently only reported in whole integers by the laboratories.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control  Arm:  Current  standard  of  care and  conventional troponin  T (c-TnT) report. Patients  randomised  to  receive current standard  of care  will  have  their admission  and  discharge  determined  by  the  treating  ED  clinician  in discussion  with  the  relevant  inpatient  unit. Decisions will  be based  on the c-TnT  result. Subsequent  care  including  the  scheduling  of  testing, other investigations and management will be physician determined</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety of hs-TNT based management, assessed by incidence of death and new MI which are determined by hospital record review.'
</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days and 12 months post presentation to ED</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate  the  health  system  cost  effectiveness  of  a  hs-TnT  based management strategy at 12 months. This outcome will be provided in the format of reports generated by Medicare, on receipt of signed medicare consent forms which are sought from the participant at the time of recruitment and enrollment into the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint> 12 months post presentation to ED</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Effectiveness of hs-TNT based management, assessed by incidence of death and new MI which are determined by hospital record review.'</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days and 12 months post presentation to ED</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major secondary clinical outcomes will include: 
All-cause mortality at 12 months which will be determined by hospital record review.





</outcome>
      <timepoint> 12 months post presentation to ED</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>New ACS at 12 months, defined as:
-New MI defined as chest discomfort associated with a rise and fall in troponin, or  a  new cardiac  defect  on  imaging,  consistent  with  the current  3rd Universal Definition.
-Unstable  angina  defined  as  chest  pain/discomfort  with  an  accelerated  pattern or  occurring  at  rest,  associated  with:  dynamic  ECG  changes  consistent  with ischaemia;or functional testing consistent    with ischaemia; and/or demonstrated coronary stenosis &gt;70% by visual estimation.</outcome>
      <timepoint> 12 months post presentation to ED</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiovascular mortality as determined by hospital record review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days and 12 months post presentation to ED</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>New MI at 12 months defined as chest discomfort associated with a rise and fall in troponin, or  a  new cardiac  defect  on  imaging,  consistent  with  the current  3rd Universal Definition.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months post presentation to ED</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Unplanned hospital  admission  as  documented  in  a  hospital discharge summary for: 
-non-elective coronary revascularisation (PCI or CABG)
-cerebrovascular accidents with cerebral imaging
-atrial or ventricular arrhythmias
-congestive cardiac failure without MI
-peripheral revascularisation
Significant bleeding using the international clinical trial definitions at 30 days and 12 months from GUSTO, TIMI and ACUITY</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days and 12 months post presentation to ED</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary clinical outcomes for health economic evaluation will include:
-Measures of in-hospital care: stress testing, echocardiography, coronary angiography, cardiac medications at discharge consistent with guidelines

</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days and 12 months post presentation to ED</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>-Health-related quality of life (EQ-5D) questionnaires to be completed by direct contact via telephone, or posted directly to participant with a return pain envelope.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 30 days plus or minus 5 days; 6 and 12 months plus or minus 1 week. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>-Resource utilisation over 12 months: Medicare data among consenting patients using Medicare Benefits  Schedule  (MBS),  medication  use  from  Pharmaceutical  Benefits Schedule (PBS)and SA Health in-patient admissions from the AN-Diagnosis Related Group (DRG) version 6.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>over the 12 month period from presentation to ED</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients  will  be  eligible  for  enrolment  into  the  study  if  they  meet all  the  following  criteria upon presentation to the ED: 
a) Clinical   features   of   chest pain   or   suspected   ACS   as   the   principal   cause   for investigation
b) ECG is interpreted as not definitive for coronary ischaemia
c) Patient is 18 years of age or older
d) Patient is willing to give his/her written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients meeting any of the below criteria will be ineligible for enrolment into the study:
a) Patients requiring admission for non-chest pain related reasons
b) Patients admitted as a result of a transfer from another hospital
c) Patients representing with chest pain within 30 days of last presentation
d) Patients requiring permanent dialysis
e) Patients unable  to  complete  the  clinical  history  questionnaire  due  to  language  or comorbidity</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This  study  will  employ  a  randomised  non-inferiority  trial  design,  nested  within  an  ongoing city-wide registry of ED patients with chest pain. The registry, using current electronic health records including cardiac investigation and pathology tests, will document current care and  outcomes  of  patients  admitted  or  discharged  directly  from  ED following  presentations with chest pain. Employing a prospective randomisation and open labelled blinded endpoint adjudication  (PROBE)  design,  the  trial  will  evaluate  the  effectiveness,  safety  and  cost-effectiveness  of  a  high-sensitivity  troponin  T  assay  guided  management  strategy  facilitating early outpatient management among patients without objective evidence of ischaemia during the initial assessment. All other subsequent investigation and management will be left to the discretion of the clinician. Clinical events will be determined at 30 days and at 12 months.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All sample size calculations assume a Type I and II error rates of 5% and 20% respectively.  Estimates of sample size have been derived from actual clinical event rates observed within the SA health system among 33,374 patients from 2003 to 2012.  The proportion of patients experiencing mortality and recurrent ACS within 30-days with current best standard of care is 0.5%.    We  expect  that  patients  randomised  to  the hs-Tn  T  protocol  arm  will  experience  the same proportion of events.    Subjective impressions for ED clinicians report an acceptable rate for missed MI of no greater than 1% (i.e. the non-inferiority margin is 0.5%). Assuming no  difference  between  the  standard  and  the  hs-TnT  guided  pathway,  then  4924  patients provides  80%  power  to  demonstrate  that  the  proportion  of  30-day  events  occurring  by management by hs-TnT is not more than 0.5% worse than the proportion of events by current practice.  Therefore, the study will seek to enroll 5,100 patients to allow for a lost to follow-up rate  of  3%.  Given  this  sample,  we  have  over  95% power  to  demonstrate  that  for  12-month follow-up the hazard ratio for time to mortality and recurrent ACS between the two groups is no worse than 2</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>27/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>5100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Noarlunga Health Service - Noarlunga Centre</hospital>
    <hospital>Lyell McEwin Hospital - Elizabeth Vale</hospital>
    <hospital>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital - Woodville</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>5112 - Elizabeth</postcode>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <postcode>5011 - Woodville</postcode>
    <postcode>5168 - Noarlunga Centre</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>SA Emergency Department Working Group </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Flinders Medical Centre
1 Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>SA Emergency Department Working Group </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Flinders Medical Centre
1 Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The  health  sciences  are  replete  with  innovations  promising  improvements  in  health  care delivery  and  outcome.    Yet  their  clinical  application  based  on  intuition  is  often  imprecise, conservative and beset with biases leaving these potential gains unrealised.  To translate healthcare  innovations  into  real  patient  and  system  benefits,  clinical  decisions  and  practice must  evolve in  parallel,  supported  by  objective  validated evidence.    One  such innovation  is troponin testing for undifferentiated chest pain in the Emergency Department (ED), the most common  cardiac  test  undertaken  in  Australia.    Each  new  generation  troponin  assays  offer greater  diagnostic  differentiation,  but  as  yet  no discernible improvement  in  management efficiency  or  effectiveness  has  occurred. Translating  improved  test  performance  into  better patient  care  will  require  a  more  structured  approach.    In  all  South  Australian  (SA)  public hospitals, 5th generation troponin assays have been implemented, but reporting of results has remained   at   previous generation   levels   (conventional   reporting),   providing   a   unique opportunity to robustly evaluate the impact of test reporting on patient outcomes. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flat 6
The Flats
1 Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/SAH/27</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Derek Chew</name>
      <address>Flinders Medical Centre 
1 Flinders Drive 
Bedford Park
SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8404 2001</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8404 2150</fax>
      <email>derek.chew@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Josette Wood</name>
      <address>SAHMRI
North Tce
Adelaide
SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8128 4530</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>josette.wood@sahmri.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Derek Chew</name>
      <address>Flinders Medical Centre 
1 Flinders Drive 
Bedford Park
SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8404 2001</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>derek.chew@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>