<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82547">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/02/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/02/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000113358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Pelvic Organ Prolapse Physiotherapy (POPPY)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a physiotherapy-supervised pelvic floor muscle training (PFMT) program on pelvic organ prolapse severity and pelvic floor muscle strength.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1191-0569 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>POPPY</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>pelvic organ prolapse</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Pelvic Floor Muscle Training: 5 appointments with a physiotherapist over 16 weeks, supplemented by a daily program of 3 exercise sessions. Adjunctive therapies such as electrical stimulation and biofeedback may be used as required. In addition, lifestyle advice (weight loss, chronic cough, heavy lifting and general exercise) will be provided. 
ADDITIONAL INFORMATION: The physiotherapy appointments involve subjective and objective assessment and an individualised treatment program. The physiotherapist will ask the patient questions about her pelvic floor symptoms (bladder, bowel, sexual and prolapse), and perform an internal vaginal examination to assess pelvic floor muscle function. Based on the findings of the muscle assessment, the home exercise program will be formulated and the patient will practise a set of these exercises, with feedback from the physiotherapist. The exercises will be practised at home, either spread throughout the day, or done all together, depending on patient lifestyle and exercise ability.</interventions>
    <comparator>Lifestyle advice (weight loss, chronic cough, heavy lifting and general exercise) will be provided.
ADDITIONAL INFORMATION: The lifestyle advice will be delivered via a brochure. This will be the same brochure delivered to the control group. Further customization of any relevant lifestyle risk factors will be provided (verbally, supplemented by written reminders if required) to patients in the treatment group, during the appointments with the physiotherapist.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prolapse severity measured by pelvic organ prolapse quantification system (POP-Q).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months post-randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pelvic floor muscle strength and endurance measured using manometric squeeze pressure.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months post-randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Digital testing of pelvic floor muscle squeeze and lift measured in lying and standing positions, recorded using the International Continence Society strength scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months post-randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of urogential hiatus using transperineal ultrasound.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months post-randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measurement of quality and endurance of a pelvic floor muscle contraction using transabdominal ultrasound.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months post-randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pelvic organ prolapse symptom score mesaured using a 7 item questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months post-randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pelvic organ prolapse quality of life measured on a questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months and 12 months post-randomisation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Women over 18 years of age presenting with symptoms of prolapse to gynaecology clinics. Prolapse severity can be of stage 1, 2 or 3 in one or more compartments.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Stage 4 prolapse, previous treatment for prolapse (surgery, pessary within 12 months, or formal instruction in PFMT within 5 years), inability to comply with PFMT, pregnancy, severe vaginal atrophy(unless pre-treated with local oestrogen).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Suitable patients identified by gynaecologists will be referred to the study. Information will be provided to patients and baseline questionnaire and consent form posted to potential participants. On return of forms women will be assessed by a physiotherapist with regard to pelvic floor muscle function measures, then randomised to intervention or control groups by the Project Coordinator via the remote automated computer randomisation application at the Centre for Health Care Randomsied Trials (CHaRT) at the University of Aberdeen UK. Everyconsenting participant will be registered and given a unique trial number.</concealment>
    <sequence>Automated computer based randomisation sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>25/02/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>168</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>13/04/2012</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3168</postcode>
    <postcode>3053</postcode>
    <postcode>5011</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Grattan Street, Parkville, Victoria (VIC) 3010
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421, Canberra, ACT 2601
ADDITIONAL INFORMATION: Level 5, 20 Allara Street, Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The Royal Women's Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Grattan Street, Carlton Victoria (VIC) 3053
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Nursing,Midwifery and Allied Health Professions Research Unit</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Room K211, Buchanan House, Glasgow Caledonian University, Cowcaddens Road, Glasgow G4 0BA.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United Kingdom</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is a randomised controlled trial investigating the effectiveness of physiotherapy supervised pelvic floor muscle training (PFMT) for pelvic organ prolapse. The hypothesis is that PFMT for prolapse will effective in reducing prolapse severity and symptoms.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Publications
1. Frawley HC, Sherburn M, Hagen S, Galea MP (2008) Pelvic organ prolapse physiotherapy. Australian and New Zealand Continence Journal 14 (2):50-51
2. Hagen, S., D. Stark, C. Glazener, S.Dickson, S. Barry, A. Elders, H. Frawley, M. Galea, J. Logan, A. McDonald, G. McPherson, K. Moore, J. Norrie, A. Walker, D. Wilson, (2014). "Individualised pelvic floor muscle training in women with pelvic organ prolapse (POPPY): a multicentre randomised controlled trial." Lancet 383(9919): 796-806. (related study in UK, partially funded by NHMRC grant).

Conference Presentations selected by peer-review
1. Frawley, H., Whitburn, L., Herbison, P., &amp; Galea, M. (2012). Does e-recruitment affect retention and outcomes in a clinical trial? (abstract #600). International Urogynecology Journal, 23(8). 
2. Frawley, H. C., Hagen, S., Sherburn, M., Neumann, P., Hay-Smith, J., Herbison, P., et al. (2012). Changes in prolapse following pelvic floor muscle training: a randomised controlled trial (abstract 163). Neurourol Urodyn, 31(6), 938-939. 
3. Frawley, H. C., Hagen, S., Sherburn, M., Neumann, P., Herbison, P., Hay-Smith, J., et al. (2011). What is the relationship between pelvic floor muscle strength, prolapse stage and prolapse symptom severity? Neurourology and Urodynamics, 30(6), 862-863. 
4. Frawley, H. C., Whitburn, L., Daly, J. O., &amp; Galea, M. P. (2011). e-Recruitment: the future for clinical trials in a digital world? Neurourology and Urodynamics, 30(6), 811-812. 
5. Mahfooza, A., Frawley, H., Galea, M., Hay-Smith, J., &amp; Delany, C. (2011). Research participants' adherence and understanding: qualitative insights from a randomised controlled trial of conservative therapy for women with pelvic organ prolapse. Neurourology and Urodynamics, 30(6), 812-814.
6. Virtue, D., Sherburn M, Bryant, A., Frawley, Helena C., Galea, M.P. (2011). "A reliability study of two-dimensional transperineal ultrasound measurement of pelvic organ prolapse." Australian &amp; New Zealand Continence Journal 17(4): 107.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, Central Northern Adelaide Health Service</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/o The Queen Elizabeth Hospital Adelaide, PO Box 400 Woodville, South Australia (SA) 5011
ADDITIONAL INFORMATION: 28 Woodville Rd., Woodville, SA 5011.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/12/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/11/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, Southern Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>246 Clayton Road, Clayton Victoria (VIC)3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/01/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>07217C</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/12/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, The Royal Women's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Grattan Street, Carlton Victoria (VIC) 3053
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/03/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/01/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Helena Frawley</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy
School of Primary and Allied Health Care, Faculty of Medicine, Nursing and Health Sciences 
Monash University 
Clayton VIC 3800</address>
      <phone>+61 418 584 813</phone>
      <fax>Nil</fax>
      <email>helena.frawley@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Helena Frawley</name>
      <address>Department of Physiotherapy
School of Primary and Allied Health Care, Faculty of Medicine, Nursing and Health Sciences 
Monash University 
Clayton VIC 3800


</address>
      <phone>+61 418 584 813</phone>
      <fax>Nil</fax>
      <email>helena.frawley@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mary Galea</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine (Royal Melbourne Hospital)
The University of Melbourne
Parkville VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2017</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 8387 2222</fax>
      <email>m.galea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mary Galea</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine (Royal Melbourne Hospital)
The University of Melbourne
Parkville, VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2017</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.galea@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>