<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364743">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000906752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Accuracy and acceptability towards cervical screening by self-collected vs clinician-collected sampling for Human papillomavirus (HPV) DNA testing in female sex workers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study to evaluate accuracy and acceptability towards cervical screening by self-collected vs clinician-collected sampling for HPV DNA testing in female sex workers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cervical cancer </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Cervical (cervix)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study participants were randomized into two groups:
Arm 1: HPV DNA self-collected sampling followed by HPV DNA clinician-collected sampling with Pap smear 

Arm 2: HPV DNA clinician-collected sampling with Pap smear followed by HPV DNA self-collected sampling

1. The women preformed both HPV DNA self-collected sampling and HPV DNA clinician-collected sampling with Pap smear on the same day when they presented for womens health checking. 

2. Explanation and instruction of the HPV DNA self-sampling was given by a trained nurse to each participating women.  Each women will be given a long-handled, sterile Dacron swab in a wrapper which is the same type used by the clinician, a plastic vial and a specimen bag.  The subject was directed to a private, well-lit room.  Verbal and written instructions for cell collection and diagram of the female genital anatomy were provided.  The subject inserted the swab into her vagina at least 2 inches deep and then turn the swab two full rotations.  Then the subject pulled out the swab and place it in the plastic vial which to be placed in the specimen bag.  The subject then passed the specimen bag containing the vial to the nurse who would transfer the swab to the 20ml vial containing 5 ml of phosphate-buffered saline.

3. Each participant was examined by clinician who will first collect a Pap smear sample from the ectocervix using a cytobrush and then collect an clinician-ectocervical sample using a Dacron swab for HPV DNA sampling.  The clinician directed the swab at the cervix and turn the swab two full rotations to maximize cell collection.  The swab was placed into a 20 ml vial containing 5 ml of phosphate-buffered saline.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard cervical screening of Pap smear, HPV DNA clinician-sampling before having HPV DNA self-sampling </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants attitudes and acceptability towards self-collected HPV DNA testing.

The subject was asked her attitudes toward self-sampling including the confidence of skill, preference in the future and acceptability by means of face-to-face interview using a structured questionnaire. Therefore, the participants had an individual face to face interview conducted by the research nurse in the clinic.  The questions were mainly divided into two sections.  The first section covers socio-demographic measure, health status and lifestyle and behavioral variables of the participants and then the second section covered the attitudes and the acceptability to the self-collected sampling for HPV DNA testing.</outcome>
      <timepoint>same day as the screening was done, after obtaining all samples</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluation of the accuracy of self-collected vaginal samples for HPV DNA testing in comparison to clinician-obtained cervical samples and Pap smear finding.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After obtaining all samples </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible participants must be a female sex worker, were aged 18 years or over</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants were excluded from the study if they were currently pregnant, had presenting symptoms of cervical caner, and known abnormal Pap test results, genital cancer, cervical surgery, or immune treatment of the cervix within a half year. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A reasonable and acceptable sample size of 100 with 5% margin of error at 90% power would be targeted for the study.  However, the final sample size was reduced to around 70 samples for this pilot trial because of reduction of granted budget.

Chi-square/Fisher's exact test and t-test were used to examine the differences of participants' attitudes towards two sampling methods. The agreement between HPV detection by two methods was determined by kappa statistic. McNemar's test was used to test the significance of unequal distribution of discordance results in detection of HPV DNA between 2 tests. Statistical significance was considered when p-vales were &lt; 0.05.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/11/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/11/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>4/05/2010</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>4/05/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Eliza LY Wong, Associate Professor, The Jockey Club School of Public Health and Primary Care, Faculty of Medicine, The Chinese University of Hong Kong </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rm 503, School of Public Health Building, Prince of Wales Hospital, 30-32 Ngan Shing Street, Shatin, New Territories</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Direct Grant of Research, The Chinese University of Hong Kong.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Shatin, N.T. </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Hong Kong</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study aimed to provide information of acceptability of HPV DNA self-sampling in female sex workers, and comparing the self-collected vaginal samples with clinician-collected cervical samples and Pap smear in Hong Kong. Participants were randomized into 2 groups, have either self-sampling or clinician sampling first. The results of this study will assist guidelines implementation for future cervical screening, and increase cervical screening uptake rate. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Joint The Chinese University of Hong Kong - New Territories East Cluster Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flat 3C, Block B, Staff Quarters, Prince of Wales Hospital, 30-32 Ngan Shing Street, Shatin, New Territories</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/08/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CRE-2009.373-T</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Eliza LY Wong </name>
      <address>Rm 503, School of Public Health Building, Prince of Wales Hospital, 30-32 Ngan Shing Street, Shatin, New Territories</address>
      <phone>+ 852 2252 8772</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lywong@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Eliza LY Wong </name>
      <address>Rm 503, School of Public Health Building, Prince of Wales Hospital, 30-32 Ngan Shing Street, Shatin, New Territories</address>
      <phone>+ 852 2252 8772</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lywong@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Eliza LY Wong </name>
      <address>Rm 503, School of Public Health Building, Prince of Wales Hospital, 30-32 Ngan Shing Street, Shatin, New Territories. </address>
      <phone>+ 852 2252 8772</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lywong@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>