<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370122">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000377437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised Controlled Trial of the efficacy and safety of an Inhaled Corticosteroid and Long Acting Beta Agonist reliever therapy regimen in asthma 
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A 52-week, open label, parallel group, multicentre, phase III, randomised controlled trial to compare the efficacy and safety of Budesonide/formoterol turbuhaler taken as required for relief of symptoms and Budesonide turbuhaler as maintenance and terbutaline turbuhaler as required for relief of symptoms of asthma in adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1174-2273</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PRACTICAL: PeRsonalised Asthma Combination Therapy: with Inhaled Corticosteroid And fast-onset Long-acting beta agonist</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Inhaled corticosteroid/Long acting beta Agonist (ICS/LABA) reliever therapy; budesonide/formoterol turbuhaler 200micrograms/6micrograms taken one inhalation for relief of symptoms as required for 52 weeks. These participants will receive no maintenance therapy.

In the electronic monitor sub-study, 110 patients will have an electronic monitor incorporated into each turbuhaler device to record the date and time of actuations to allow a detailed assessment of patterns of use of randomised treatments. 55 participants will be recruited from the ICS/LABA reliever group and 55 participants from the maintenance ICS and SABA reliever therapy group. This substudy will run for 52 weeks.

Inhaler use will be monitored electronically. An electronic monitor device will be attached to each inhaler, which is able to measure the date and time of each actuation performed.</interventions>
    <comparator>Maintenance Inhaled Corticosteroid (ICS) and Short Acting Beta Agonist (SABA) reliever therapy; budesonide Turbuhaler 200 micrograms, 1 inhalation twice daily and terbutaline metered dose inhaler 250 micrograms 2 inhalations for relief of symptoms as required, for 52 weeks.

In the electronic monitoring sub-study, inhaler use will be monitored electronically. An electronic monitor device will be attached to each inhaler, which is able to measure the date and time of each actuation performed. The electronic monitoring sub-study will run for 52 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome variable is severe asthma exacerbation rate expressed as number of exacerbations per patient per year.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint is determined by occurrence of either the use of systemic corticosteroids for at least 3 days because of asthma, or Hospitalisation or emergency department (ED) visit because of asthma, requiring systemic corticosteroids

These criteria will be determined from participant self report.
Asthma exacerbations will be assessed throughout the 52 week intervention period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first severe exacerbation of asthma, which is defined as either the use of systemic corticosteroids for at least 3 days because of asthma, or Hospitalisation or emergency department (ED) visit because of asthma, requiring systemic corticosteroids. This outcome will be assessed by participant self report at interview. Participant NHI number will be used to centrally validate exacerbation outcome data relating to hospital attendance and/or admission.    </outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome measure is measured from date intervention commenced, to the date first severe exacerbation begins.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Asthma Control Questionnaire score (ACQ-5 score), as measured by the ACQ-5 validated questionnaire completed by the participant</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 4, 16, 28, 40 and 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>On-treatment Forced Expiratory Volume in 1 second (FEV1) percentage predicted, as measured by spirometry assessment. Percentage predicted values will be obtained for each participant from height, age and ethnicity recorded as part of demographics and processed according to Quanjer et al 2012</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 4, 16, 28, 40 and 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fractional Exhaled Nitric Oxide, as measured by a NIOX VERO device</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 16 and 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Inhaled Corticosteroid dose per day (budesonide micrograms/day), as recorded by the electronic monitor devices on nested substudy inhalers</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collected over duration of study using electronic monitors, and will be assessed  week 0 to 52.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients with at least one day of no inhaled corticosteroid use, as recorded by the electronic monitors on inhalers in nested sub study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of study; week 0 to 52.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Longest duration of no inhaled corticosteroid use, as recorded by the electronic monitors on inhalers in nested substudy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of study; week 0 to 52.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total systemic corticosteroid exposure. 
In the nested sub-study, systemic corticosteroid exposure/year in which the total inhaled Corticosteroid dose/year (as recorded by the electronic monitors on each inhaler)is converted to oral prednisone-equivalent dose and added to the participant self-reported oral corticosteroid use.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of study; week 0 to 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To examine patient attitudes to the treatment regimens through the validated belief about medicines questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0 and 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether baseline socioeconomic characteristics such as housing status predict preferential response to randomised treatment through completion of Housing status questionnaire.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with at least one episode of high use, defined as greater than 16 actuations of Terbutaline in a 24 hour period, or greater than 8 actuations of budesonide/formoterol in a 24 hour period, as recorded by the electronic monitors on inhalers in the nested sub-study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of study; week 0 to 52.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of days of high beta agonist use, defined as greater than 16 actuations of Terbutaline in a 24 hour period, or greater than 8 actuations of budesonide/formoterol in a 24 hour period, as recorded by the electronic monitors on inhalers in the nested sub-study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of stud; week 0 to 52.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of days of high use without medical review within 48 hours, in participants with at least one high use episode, as recorded by the electronic monitors on inhalers in the nested substudy. Medical review will be assessed by participant self-report.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of study; week 0 to 52.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximum number of beta agonist actuations in a 24 hour period as recorded by the electronic monitors on inhaler in the nested substudy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of study; week 0 to 52.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>For the rate of exacerbations (measured by self report) a differential effect of treatment will be explored with each of the following baseline moderating variables: Short Acting Beta Agonist (SABA) use (measured as the average number of occasions per week of self-reported SABA use in the four weeks before enrolment), whether there has been a severe exacerbation in the year prior to enrolment (measured by participant self-report), age (measured by self-report), sex (measured by self-report), smoking status (measured by self report), baseline Asthma Control Questionnaire-5 (ACQ-5) score (measured by ACQ-5 score), Fractional Exhaled Volume in 1 second (FEV1) percent predicted (measured by predicted values based on self reported height, age and ethnicity), Fractional Exhaled Nitric Oxide (FeNO, measured by NIOX VERO device), blood eosinophil count (measured by laboratory test), serum periostin level (measured by laboratory test) and T helper cell 2 (Th2) status (a Th2 score based on tertiles for each baseline measure of blood eosinophil count, FeNO and serum periostin.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of study; week 0 to 52.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of exacerbations defined by the use of systemic corticosteroids for at least 3 days because of asthma, and the proportion defined by the requirement for Hospitalisation or emergency department (ED) visit because of asthma, requiring systemic corticosteroids.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 4, 16, 28, 40 and 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of patients with at least one severe exacerbation.
This outcome will be assessed by participant self report at interview. Participant NHI number will be used to centrally validate exacerbation outcome data relating to hospital attendance and/or admission.    </outcome>
      <timepoint>Weeks 0, 4, 16, 28, 40 and 52</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants withdrawn and reason. The Proportion of participants withdrawn due to treatment failure will also be presented. Treatment failure is defined as withdrawal due to uncontrolled asthma under the randomised regimen resulting in safety concerns, as judged by the investigator or if randomised treatment is modified by the participants GP or other healthcare provider


Data is measured from self-report by participant
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Date of withdrawal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness will be calculated for each treatment regimen (medications, emergency medical attention, ED visits, hospital admissions and non medical costs including days off work).

The following represent current indicative figures, which will be updated to current actual figures at the time of analysis; medications (terbutaline $22/turbuhaler, budesonide $19/turbuhaler, budesonide/formoterol $60/turbuhaler), emergency medical ($86/visit) and ED visits ($339/visit), and hospital admissions (medical ward $1,194/day, high dependency unit $2,763/day, ICU $5,570/day)] and non-medical costs (days off work $167/day). The cost-effectiveness data collected will allow extrapolation to future pricing models with lower cost generic medications. 

This outcome data will be assessed by participant self report at interview. Participant NHI number will be used to centrally validate data relating to hospital attendance and/or admission.    
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of study; week 0 to 52.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with at least one episode of marked beta agonist overuse, defined as greater than 24 actuations of Terbutaline in a 24 hour period, or greater than 12 actuations of budesonide/formoterol in a 24 hour period, as recorded by the electronic monitors on inhalers in the nested sub-study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of study; week 0 to 52.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of days of high beta agonist use, defined as greater than 16 actuations of Terbutaline in a 24 hour period, or greater than 8 actuations of budesonide/formoterol in a 24 hour period, as recorded by the electronic monitors on inhalers in the nested sub-study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of study; week 0 to 52.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of marked beta agonist use episodes without medical review in the following 48 hour period, 7 day period and 14 day period in participants who had a least one marked beta agonist use episode. Where marked beta agonist use is defined as greater than 24 actuations of Terbutaline in a 24 hour period, or greater than 12 actuations of budesonide/formoterol in a 24 hour period, as recorded by the electronic monitors on inhalers in the nested sub-study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of study; week 0 to 52.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults aged 18 to 75 years.

Self-report of a doctors diagnosis of asthma.

Not used Inhaled corticosteroids in the 12 weeks prior to entry into the study and suffering from asthma symptoms or
Need for SABA on two or more occasions in the last 4 weeks, or 
Waking due to asthma once or more in the last 4 weeks, or 
Exacerbation requiring oral corticosteroids in the last 52 weeks

Or has used inhaled corticosteroids in the 12 weeks prior to entry in the study, and is prescribed ICS at low or moderate doses (&lt;500micrograms/day fluticasone propionate or small particle formulation beclomethasone diproprionate (QVAR); 800 micrograms/day budesonide; 1,000 micrograms/day beclomethasone diproprionate (Beclazone)), and:
i. has partly or well controlled asthma as defined by GINA guidelines
OR
ii. has uncontrolled asthma as defined by GINA guidelines and either poor adherence to ICS and/ or unsatisfactory inhaler technique.

Willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the trial.

In the investigator's opinion, able and willing to comply with all trial requirements.

Willing to allow their GP (and specialist if appropriate) to be notified of participation in the trial.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Self-reported use of LABA, leukotriene receptor antagonist, theophylline, anticholinergic agent or cromone as maintenance therapy in the 12 weeks before potential study entry. 
Nasal corticosteroid therapy is permitted.

Self-reported past admission to the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) with life-threatening asthma (representing patients at highest risk of adverse asthma outcomes).

Self-reported treatment with oral prednisone or other systemic corticosteroids in the six weeks before potential study entry (representing recent unstable asthma).

A home supply of prednisone for use in worsening asthma, as part of a current asthma plan.

Self-reported diagnosis of COPD, bronchiectasis or interstitial lung disease.

Self-reported greater than 20 pack year smoking history, or onset of respiratory symptoms after the age of 40 years in current or ex-smokers with more than or equal to a 10 pack year history.

Self-reported current pregnancy or breast feeding at the time of enrolment or planned pregnancy within the study period.

Unwilling or unable to switch from current asthma treatment regimen.

Other illness(es) likely to compromise participant safety or impact on the feasibility of results, at the discretion of the investigator (examples include unstable coronary disease and malignancy).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The central electronic Case Report Form (eCRF) system will perform randomisation. It will conceal the allocations and will release a participant’s randomisation outcome only at the time of randomisation. The randomisation schedule will not be accessed by study staff.
</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer-generated randomisation number sequence will be created by the study statistician, independent of the investigators undertaking recruitment and subsequent visits.
Participants will be block randomised.
Randomisation will be stratified according to whether participants used ICS therapy prior to enrolment or not.
A computer-generated randomisation number sequence will be created by the study statistician, independent of the investigators undertaking recruitment and subsequent visits.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Primary outcome variable analysis
This will be an intention to treat superiority analysis. The primary analysis of the primary outcome variable is comparison of the rate of severe exacerbations per patient per year until completion of the study or withdrawal from the study. This will be by Poisson regression with an offset for the time of observation. Over-dispersion will be evaluated prior to analysis and a corrected analysis applied if necessary.

Secondary outcome variable analyses
The following methods will be used:
Survival analysis illustrated by Kaplan-Meier plots and use of Cox proportional hazards regression to estimate the hazard ratio in relation to the randomised treatment:
Time to first severe exacerbation
Simple t-tests by time of measurement and mixed linear models for repeated measures by time for ACQ-5 score, FEV1 , FEV1 percentage predicted, FeNO, likely on the logarithm transformed scale based on our previous experience with the skewed distribution of this variable and that normality assumptions were better met on the logarithm transformed scale.

The Work Productivity Activity impairment Asthma questionnaire consists of four sub-scores and t-tests will be used to compare each sub-score by randomised treatment if normality assumptions are met and the Mann-Whitney test if they are not.
Beliefs about Medicines Questionnaire consists of five sub-scores and we plan to use t-tests comparing each sub-score by randomised treatment if normality assumptions are met and the Mann-Whitney test if they are not. Estimation of costs will be analysed by simple t-test.

The primary outcome variable is the rate of severe asthma exacerbations per patient per year. Assuming a drop-out rate of 10%, 890 patients will be recruited to enable a sample size of 400 completed patients in each treatment arm, resulting in 90% power, alpha 5%, to detect a 38% reduction in the rate of severe exacerbations from 0.30 to 0.185. 

The conservative baseline rate of severe exacerbations per patient per year of 0.30 is derived from previous randomised controlled trials which have reported a rate of 0.21 in steroid-naïve subjects treated with budesonide 200micrograms/day, (using the same criteria for severe exacerbations, peak flow criteria excluded) and rates in subjects previously treated with ICS at baseline of 0.92 and 0.96 (budesonide 200 and 400micrograms/day), 0.35 (budesonide 800micrograms/day), and 0.35 (budesonide 400micrograms/day). Past research shows a relative risk (RR) of severe exacerbations of budesonide/ formoterol reliever therapy compared with SABA reliever therapy of between 0.52 and 0.55, and a non-significant 38% reduction in severe exacerbations with ICS and SABA reliever therapy (separate inhalers) vs physician-adjusted maintenance ICS. This 38% reduction in severe exacerbations would be expected to be less than that observed in the proposed study, due to their study of highly compliant patients, the use of separate inhalers rather than a combination inhaler, and ICS/SABA rather than ICS/LABA reliever therapy. These estimates are directly relevant to this proposed study, and for the purpose of this power calculation, we plan to detect a conservative relative rate of severe exacerbations per patient per year of 0.62 with the ICS/LABA reliever regimen.

The primary outcome variable for the sub-study is the mean ICS dose per day. Assuming a drop-out rate of 10%, 110 patients will be recruited into the substudy to ensure a sample size of 50 completed patients in each treatment arm, resulting in 90% power, alpha 5% to detect a 18% decrease in ICS use (µg/day) with ICS/LABA reliever therapy, compared with 264 µg/day in the standard ICS and SABA regimen. This calculation is based on data from our previous study of ICS compliance in stable asthma in which participants took a mean (SD) 66% of their prescribed ICS dose.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/04/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/05/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>890</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Tauranga</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Rotorua</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 7 CSB Building
Wellington Hospital
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3 - ProCARE Building, Grafton Mews, at 110 Stanley Street, Auckland 1010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Global Initiative for Asthma (GINA) has established internationally accepted diagnostic and management strategies which aim to achieve optimum asthma control for individual patients however, numerous surveys in NZ and internationally show low adherence to guidelines, suboptimal management, and preventable morbidity.
A number of factors contribute to this largely preventable morbidity in intermittent and mild persistent asthma. The most important are failure to prescribe inhaled corticosteroids (ICS) and poor adherence with them.. Since 2014, the GINA guidelines have recommended that most patients with asthma should be prescribed ICS as first line regular maintenance therapy.This recommendation is based on the evidence that the regular use of ICS reduces symptoms, improves lung function, reduces severe exacerbations, prevents hospital admissions, and reduces the risk of mortality.
The benefits of ICS in clinical practice are limited by poor adherence which is not surprising as patients are required to take twice daily treatment regardless of whether they have symptoms. This is an important issue as poor ICS adherence contributes to asthma treatment failure, resulting in increased morbidity, risk of mortality, and consumption of healthcare resources. A symptom-based ICS/LABA combination inhaler regimen is appealing because it couples ICS and LABA use to automatically ensure adherence to ICS. This has the potential to improve the frequency of daily ICS use in patients with symptomatic asthma, and to lead to a rapid increase in use during worsening asthma. 
We are therefore investigating the safety and efficacy of 2 treatment regimens in mild asthma:
1. A combination inhaled corticosteroid (ICS) and Long Acting Beta Agonist (LABA) as required
2. Regular ICS maintenance, and SABA as required</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern B Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Ethics Department
Freyberg Building
Reception  Ground Floor
20 Aitken Street
Wellington 6011
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/NTB/178</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370122-HDEC Letter 15NTB178 Approved FULL Application.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370122-Protocol PRACTICAL V2 CLEAN 18 Mar 2016 - FINAL.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370122-Protocol PRACTICAL V2.1 08 MAY 2016.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370122-Protocol PRACTICAL V3.0 04 OCT 2016.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370122-Protocol PRACTICAL V3.1 04 APR 2017.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard Beasley</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Level 7 CSB Building
Wellington Hospital
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021 </address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0147 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.beasley@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Mark Holliday</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Level 7 CSB Building
Wellington Hospital
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021 </address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0147 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mark.holliday@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>James Fingleton</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Level 7 CSB Building
Wellington Hospital
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021 </address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0147</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>james.fingleton@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jo Hardy</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Level 7 CSB Building
Wellington Hospital
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021 </address>
      <phone>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jo.hardy@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>