<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367080">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001014640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Kunzea oil for the management of mild to moderate psoriasis (a common, chronic, relapsing, immune-mediated skin disease:  a pilot randomised controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Safety and efficacy of kunzea oil-containing formulations for the management of psoriasis, a pilot, randomised, controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>NIL</utrn>
    <trialacronym>NIL</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Psoriasis of the body and scalp</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Group A [test] received topical test treatment with kunzea oil (20% in an ointment base or scalp lotion, twice daily), and group B [control] applied control medication (twice daily) for 8 weeks.

The control formulation contained the test formulation without the kunzea oil component. Both trialled medications contained 3% salicylic acid (keratolytic agent), which is recommended as a scale lifter, along with liquor carbonis detergens (5% LCD; used instead of crude coal tar which has an unpleasant odour and stains), for the management of psoriasis.

kunzea oil (strength20% in an emollient ointment base or scalp lotion; steam distilled and commercially produced in Tasmania from the bush plant Kunzea ambigua). The type of intervention administered to the study cohort was based on the nature of psoriasis (e.g. scalp psoriasis versus generalised body psoriasis, and if a recruited patient had both forms of psoriasis, both types of trial medications were administered).

Patients were instructed to apply the medication twice daily, once in the morning and once at night, to all psoriatic lesional areas without occlusion for 8 weeks or until cleared. Subjects were advised not to use the medications just before having a bath, a shower or going swimming. Subjects were to apply the study medications (sparingly) by massaging gently on to the affected areas. The maximum application rate was 100 g of ointment and/or 100 ml of scalp lotion per week.

Compliance: Compliance to the treatment protocol was encouraged the use of patient diary. Furthermore, the research assistant reminded the subjects the importance of adhering to the treatment protocol at each of their follow-up visits to the clinical investigators office.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Control medications contained 3% salicylic acid (keratolytic agent), which is recommended as a scale lifter, along with liquor carbonis detergens (5%, LCD; used instead of crude coal tar which has an unpleasant odour and stains), for the management of psoriasis. Patients were given instructions to apply the medication/s twice daily for 8 weeks or until cleared.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The severity of the disease was measured using the Psoriasis Area and Severity Index (PASI), reported previously. Treatment efficacy was evaluated by assessing the PASI score before and after 8 weeks of treatment. The mean change in score (delta PASI) was the primary outcome measure of the trial.

Reference: Fredriksson T, Pettersson U. Severe psoriasisoral therapy with a new retinoid. Dermatology 1978;157:238-244.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: At baseline and 8 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome (pruritus) was evaluated at each visit using a visual analogue scale (VAS) score on a 04 point scale, with 0 as the absence and 4 as the maximum degree of pruritus. The sum of the score based on the four body regions (head, upper limbs, trunk, and lower limbs) constituted a total between 0 and 16.


Reference
Kanzler M, Gorsulowsky D. Efficacy of topical 5% liquor carbonis detergens vs. its emollient base in the treatment of psoriasis. British Journal of Dermatology 1993;129:310-314.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint:At baseline and 8 weeks after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Entry criteria required a clinical diagnosis of psoriasis involving greater than or equal to 10% of the body surface.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The main exclusion criteria were current diagnosis of unstable psoriasis, atopic dermatitis and other skin conditions (e.g. seborrhoeic dermatitis, contact dermatitis, cutaneous mycosis, presence of pigmentation, extensive scarring, pigmented lesion) confounding psoriasis assessment, pregnancy, breast-feeding, and use of medications that are known to exacerbate the course of psoriasis (lithium, beta adrenergic blocking agents, antimalarial drugs). 
Subjects with flexural and pustular psoriasis were not considered because of their rarity and potential treatment difficulties with the trial medications.  All patients had a 6-week washout period for systemic therapy (including phototherapy) and 2 weeks for topical psoriatic treatment before receiving the study drugs. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients were allocated into the test or control group, using a computer-generated randomisation schedule. 
Trial formulations were prepared in the compounding pharmaceutical laboratory in the School of Pharmacy, University of Tasmania, under the supervision of a registered pharmacist. Pharmaceutical grade (USP) excipient vanillin (Sigma-Aldrich, Australia; 1% w/w or w/v) was added into both formulations to mask the characteristic odour of kunzea oil, to ensure effective blinding of subjects to both control and test formulations (ointment and/or scalp lotion).  All trial medications had a 28-day expiry period. Medications were packed in identical containers with the code kept secure by a staff member who was not part of the research team. When patients entered into the trial (after eligibility assessment and wash-out period), the clinical investigator’s office contacted the university staff to send the medications (via express registered post) directly to the patients. The same method was followed for the additional supply of medications to study subjects. This enabled the clinical investigator (performing assessments) and other study personnel to be blinded throughout the study period. </concealment>
    <sequence>Once informed written consent had been obtained, the
inclusion/exclusion criteria and baseline assessments have been satisfied /completed, the participants were randomly allocated into one of two groups (test or control) using a computer-generated randomisation schedule.

Randomisation was provided by the study Sponsor, using an
independent statistician.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Randomised, controlled</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size: The study used a randomised, active-controlled, double-blind design. Power calculations were based on relevant, related published articles. Sample size was estimated using a power index of 7.9 (P=0.05, beta=0.20). A difference of 1 standard deviation between test and control Delta PASI, would have resulted in a statistically significant finding (P &lt; 0.05). Therefore, fifteen patients were needed in each group. 

Statistical analysis: All statistical analyses were performed blinded to group allocation using StatView 5.0 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA). All efficacy end points at weeks 0, 2, 4 and 8 were compared between the two treatment regimens. Continuous variables were presented as mean+/-SD (standard deviation) and discrete variables presented as numbers and percentages. We used one-way analysis of variance for repeated measures (ANOVA), followed by Fishers protected least significant difference (PLSD) post hoc test to assess differences between therapeutic regimens.  Wilcoxon rank test was used to test the significance of difference in any place where the normality of distribution was in question. A paired student t-test established the differences between the pre-treatment and post-treatment values in both the test and control groups. All data analysis were based on an intention to treat (ITT) approach, including all patients randomised, whether treated or not, and including all patients who withdrew prematurely. All statistical tests were two sided and performed at an alpha level of 0.05. All the data were reported as median (and range) or mean (+/- SD) for non-parametric and parametric distributions, respectively.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/11/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/08/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/03/2008</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>20/03/2008</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Tasmania</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Churchill Avenue Rd
Sandy Bay 
Hobart
Tasmania 7005</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mr Bob Armstrong/University of Canberra</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2 Guy Street
Kings Meadows
Tasmania
7249</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Susan Basson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Dr. Sue Bassons Clinic
98 Talbot Road, Kings Meadows, Launceston, Tasmania, Australia
Postcode: 7249</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Psoriasis is a common, non-infectious inflammatory disease characterised by distinctive erythematous scaling plaques of varying sizes usually on the scalp, elbows, knees and other surfaces of the skin. There is no satisfactory or effective cure for psoriasis. Both oral and topical treatment modalities are only partially effective and can induce irritation and/or serious side-effects. Current treatment options are only effective in reducing psoriasis symptoms temporarily. About 70% of subjects are said to prefer topical therapy to manage psoriasis. Myrtaceous essential oils have been found to provide anti-inflammatory effects on human skin. A safe, relatively inexpensive, alternative topical treatment is required to minimise treatment failures and relapses associated with psoriasis. The present study compared the efficacy and safety of topical kunzea oil (twice daily) with 5% Liquor Carbonis Detergens (LCD) and 3% salicylic acid containing formulations (twice daily) for the management mild to moderate psoriasis (study duration 8 weeks). The study recruited patients from single site (GP surgery, Talbot Rd, Launceston).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>NIL</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Thomas J, Narkowicz, CK, Peterson, GM, Jacobson, GA &amp; Basson S, An evaluation of the clinical efficacy of kunzea oil formulations in the therapeutic management of psoriasis in adults,  Proceedings of the APSA Annual Conference, Hobart, (2009)</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>NIL</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (Tasmania) Network </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Private Bag 01, Hobart, Tasmania 7001, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/09/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0008454 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/05/2006</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jackson Thomas</name>
      <address>University of Canberra Faculty of Health, University of Canberra, Kirrinari Street, ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)2 62068928</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)2 6201 5727</fax>
      <email>Jackson.Thomas@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jackson Thomas</name>
      <address>University of Canberra Faculty of Health, University of Canberra, Kirrinari Street, ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)2 62068928</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)2 6201 5727</fax>
      <email>Jackson.Thomas@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jackson Thomas</name>
      <address>University of Canberra Faculty of Health, University of Canberra, Kirrinari Street, ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)2 62068928</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)2 6201 5727</fax>
      <email>Jackson.Thomas@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jackson Thomas</name>
      <address>University of Canberra Faculty of Health, University of Canberra, Kirrinari Street, ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)2 62068928</phone>
      <fax>+61 (0)2 6201 5727</fax>
      <email>Jackson.Thomas@canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>