<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81970">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/04/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/05/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000238471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Accelerated Partial Breast Irradiation for Early Breast Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG) 06.02 - A Multicentre Feasibility Study of Accelerated Partial Breast Irradiation (APBI) Using Three-Dimensional Conformal Radiation Therapy for Early Breast Cancer to test the feasibility of APBI.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TROG 06.02</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Clinicaltrials.gov: NCT00418210</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Accelerated partial breast irradiation (APBI) to region of tumour bed
3-dimensional conformal radiation therapy (3D CRT) 38.5 Gy in 3.85 Gy fractions over 5 consecutive working days</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility rate of APBI using 3D conformal radiation therapy - Proportion of eligible patients treated without a major protocol deviation. 
Major Deviations: 
a. Overall treatment time is more than 10 days
b. Maximum dose (in a volume of = 2 cm3) to PTV_EVAL is more than 110% of the
prescribed dose
c. 90% of the prescribed dose covers less than 90% of the PTV_EVAL on DVH
d. 85% of the prescribed dose covers less than 99% of the PTV_EVAL
e. Maximum dose to critical normal structures is more than 105% of the specified values.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured over the whole duration of the study. The outcome is determined at the end of the study which is until all patients have been treated with APBI (from the data coollected over the whole duration of the study).   </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Radiation toxicity - The National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria version 3.0 will be used for serious adverse event and toxicity reporting. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be measured at Last day of RT &amp; 6 weeks post RT, 3 and 6 months post RT, then on a yearly basis until 10 years post RT. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cosmetic outcome - Cosmetic outcome will be assessed using the following instruments: European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer Cosmetic Rating System and Quantitative assessment of breast cosmesis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be measured at 1 year, 2 years, 3 years and 5 years post Radiotherapy (RT).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be measured at Last day of RT &amp; 6 weeks post RT, 3 and 6 months post RT, then on a yearly basis until death. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to ipsilateral breast recurrence - The time from start of APBI to the time of invasive or intraductal recurrence in any soft tissue of the ipsilateral breast. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be measured at Last day of RT &amp; 6 weeks post RT, 3 and 6 months post RT, then on a yearly basis until 10 years post RT. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease free survival - The time from start of APBI to recurrence of any form. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be measured at Last day of RT &amp; 6 weeks post RT, 3 and 6 months post RT, then on a yearly basis until 10 years post RT. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival - The time from start of APBI to the time of death from any cause. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Will be measured at Last day of RT &amp; 6 weeks post RT, 3 and 6 months post RT, then on a yearly basis until 10 years post RT.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients must fulfil all of the following criteria for admission to study:- Women aged &gt;= 50 years.- Histologically confirmed diagnosis of invasive breast carcinoma of non-lobular histology.- Bilateral mammograms performed within 6 months prior to registration.- Treated with breast conserving surgery (primary excision or re-excision) with negative radial resection margins of &gt;= 2 mm* for both the invasive and if present, associated intraductal tumour.*Patients with superficial or deep resection margin of &lt; 2 mm are eligible if surgery has removed all of the intervening breast tissue from the subcutaneous tissue to the pectoralis fascia.- Unifocal tumour measuring &lt;= 20 mm in maximum microscopic dimension.- Negative nodal status determined by sentinel node biopsy, axillary dissection, or for women &gt;70 years of age, clinical examination.- No evidence of distant metastasis.- Assessed by surgeon and radiation oncologist to be suitable for breast conserving therapy.- Ability to tolerate protocol therapy.- Protocol therapy must commence no later than 12 weeks from the last surgical procedure or 8 weeks from the last dose of chemotherapy.- Availability for long-term follow-up.- Women of child-bearing potential must use adequate contraception during RT.- Written informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who fulfil any of the following criteria are not eligible for admission to study:- Multifocal or multicentric tumours.- Clinical or pathologic evidence of any of the following tumour features: extension to chest wall (excluding pectoralis muscle); oedema (including peau dorange) or ulceration of skin; satellite skin nodules confined to the same breast; and inflammatory carcinoma.- Presence of extensive intraductal component (ductal carcinoma in situ occupying &gt; 25% of the primary invasive tumour and present adjacent to the primary tumour).- Node-positive breast cancer determined by sentinel node biopsy, axillary dissection, or in women &gt; 70 years of age, clinical examination.- Inability to localise surgical cavity on CT scans with no evidence of a surgical cavity, seroma or surgical clips delineating the tumour bed.- Treatment target volume estimated to occupy &gt; 25% of the ipsilateral whole breast volume - Synchronous or metachronous bilateral invasive or intraductal breast cancer.- Locally recurrent breast cancer.- Ipsilateral breast implant.- Serious non-malignant disease that precludes definitive surgical or radiation treatment (e.g. scleroderma, systemic lupus erythematosus, cardiovascular/pulmonary/renal disease).- Previous or concomitant malignancies except non-melanoma skin cancer, carcinoma in situ of the cervix, and invasive carcinoma of the colon, thyroid, cervix or endometrium treated five years prior to study entry.- Women who are pregnant or lactating.- Psychiatric or addictive disorders that preclude obtaining informed consent or adherence to protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>29/08/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>16/05/2008</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>48</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>48</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Edith St Waratah NSW 2298  </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council Project Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, 20 Allara St Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a TROG multicentre feasibility study of APBI using 3D CRT in selected women with node-negative breast cancer treated by breast conserving surgery with negative margins. 
This is a one-arm feasibility study in which the primary endpoint is the feasibility rate for APBI using 3D CRT. This is defined as the proportion of eligible patients treated without a major protocol deviation. Secondary endpoints include radiation toxicity, cosmetic outcome, quality of life, time to ipsilateral breast recurrence, disease-free survival and overall survival. 
Primary objectives: To evaluate the technical feasibility and reproducibility of APBI limited to the region of the tumour bed using 3D CRT following breast conserving surgery. 
Secondary objectives:
- To assess the acute and long term toxicity of APBI using 3D CRT. 
- To examine the cosmetic outcome of women with breast cancer treated by breast conserving surgery and APBI using 3D CRT. 
- To determine the time to ipsilateral breast recurrence, disease free survival and overall survival of women with node-negative breast cancer completely resected by breast conserving surgery followed by APBI using 3D CRT. 
- To assess the quality of life of women with node-negative breast cancer treated by breast conserving surgery and APBI using 3D CRT</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Melbourne VIC</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/01/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal North Shore</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Leonards, NSW</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Calvary Mater Newcastle</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Waratah, NSW</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Wooloongabba, QLD</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Auckland Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Auckland, NZ</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Waikato Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hamilton, NZ</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Perth</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Perth, WA</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Boon Chua</name>
      <address>Division of Radiation Oncology
Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
St Andrews Place
East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9656 1111</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9656 1424</fax>
      <email>Boon.Chua@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rebecca Montgomery</name>
      <address>Level 5 MHA Building 
Calvary Mater Newcastle
Edith Street
Waratah NSW 2310

</address>
      <phone>+61 2 40143910</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 40143902</fax>
      <email>rebecca.montgomery@trog.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>TROG Administrator</name>
      <address>TROG Cancer Research
Central Operations Office
PO Box 88
Waratah NSW 2298</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4014 3910  </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4014 3902</fax>
      <email>administrator@trog.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Boon Chua</name>
      <address>Division of Radiation Oncology Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre St Andrews Place East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9656 1111  </phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9656 1424  </fax>
      <email>Boon.Chua@petermac.org  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>