<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373084">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001030369p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of antenatal pelvic floor muscle exercises on female sexual function: A randomised controlled trial </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For primiparous women, do the antenatal pelvic floor muscle exercises improve female sexual function during pregnancy and the first three months following birth when compared with standard antenatal care alone? A randomised controlled trial
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1197-6617 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>PFMT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Female Sexual Function</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other reproductive health and childbirth disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this study, the intervention will consist of training on how to perform pelvic floor muscle exercise. The researcher (PhD Candidate) will be teaching women on how to perform pelvic floor muscle exercise.{The research is a registered midwife, has been providing care and education to women across midiwfery practice from antenatal care, birth unit and postnatal care. She holds a master of science degree in midiwfery and is currently a PhD candidate of midiwfery. She also has done research before on pelvic floor muscle exercise and urinary incontinece and their association with pelvic floor muscle strength. Moreover, arrangment with physiotherapy department has been done to stay consistent with current practice and also to reivieve supplementary materials such as pamphelet 06 on the benefit of pelvic floor exercise published by Australian Continence association, as stated in next section).
 The initial session will be individual face to face training and is estimated to take 30 minutes.  The pelvic floor muscle exercise program in this study has been extracted from two references including: effective functional motor activation patterns called (The knack) (Miller, Ashton-Miller, &amp; DeLancey, 1998) and the study carried out by Elbegway et al (Elbegway et al., 2010).
Women will be instructed as follows:
1.	Squeeze the anal sphincter as tightly as possible and then to squeeze the vaginal sphincter as tightly as possible. 
2.	 Increase the intensity of their effort. 
3.	 Hold the contraction as tightly as they can for 10 seconds. 
4.	 Relax their effort, allowing their muscle to relax and rest for a few moments.
5.	Repeat the sequence 10 times to complete one set. 
6.	Perform 6 sets three times a day.
7.	Do these daily.
Women in the intervention group will also be provided a compliance diary to record their exercises program. Red stick up spots (as triggers, (red stick up dots): shower, teeth, meals, queues etc) will be used to remind women to do the exercises as this has been demonstrated to be effective (Miller et al., 1998).
Women will be instructed to perform pelvic floor muscle exercises in different positions and also to  grip up before cough, sneeze, lift, bend. They will be encouraged to continue these exercise in the postpartum as above and also incorporating good bladder habits. However, there will not be any fortnightly  follow up in the postpartum period. Intervention will cease when women in intervention group give birth. Women in both control and intervention groups will be contacted once at three months after birth to collect data. 
The duration of intervention is from 20 weeks of pregnancy until birth. The study setting is antenatal clinic of Westmead Public Hospital,  Low risk primiparous pregnant women will be recruited at antenatal clinics at less than 20 weeks gestation and will be randomised to control and training group. Training group will receive routine antenatal care as well as an individual face to face instruction on how to perform pelvic floor muscle exercise as stated above and will receive fortnightly follow up via text messages.  Women will be provided diary to record their compliance. Women in intervention group will be provided additional pamphlets to read. The pamphlet is the vision 06 titled "Pelvic floor muscle training for women" published by continence foundation of Australia and is available at Westmead hospital. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive routine standard antenatal care and education during pregnancy. The routine antenatal care is provided by midwives and information about pelvic floor muscle exercise is given to woman along with the other educations and care in pregnancy in only one antenatal visit which takes normally less than 20 minutes. There are also extra antenatal classes run by midwives at hospital and they carry a fee for participants. These antenatal  classes are not focused on pelvic floor muscle exercise as an ongoing practice with adequate follow up during pregnancy. in this study, women in control group will not receive the intervention and follow up as stated above from researcher. However, they are not discouraged to perform pelvic floor muscle exercise on their own during pregnancy and the postpartum period. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Female sexual function during pregnancy and three months following birth will be measured using female sexual function index self -report questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Information about Female sexual function will be collected at the time of booking at less than 20 weeks gestation, at 36 weeks of pregnancy and at three months following birth from both intervention and control groups</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Childbirth outcomes (including; duration of three stages of labour, fetal positions and presentation at birth, mode of birth (normal vaginal birth, caesarean section and instrumental birth), episiotomy and perineal trauma rate (1st, 2nd, 3rd and 4th degree).
 as well as fetal outcomes such as APGAR score, head circumference, length, weight). (a composite secondary outcome).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>information about Childbirth outcomes will be collected after birth from both control and intervention groups via Obstetrix database system at Westmead Public Hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Urinary incontinence symptoms (a composite outcome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data regarding Urinary  incontinence symptoms will be collected  at the time of booking, at 36 weeks pregnancy and three months following birth from both control and intervention groups using UDI-6 questionnaire</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Specific quality of life</outcome>
      <timepoint>Specific quality of life will be measured at the time of booking,  at 36 weeks pregnancy and at three months following birth from both control and intervention groups using a IIQ-7 questionnaire</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Faecal incontinence symptoms</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data about faecal incontinence symptoms will be collected at the time of booking, at 36 weeks of pregnancy and at three months following birth from both control and training groups via a faecal incontinence questionnaire

The faecal incontinence questionaire being used in this study is the short form of Waxner et al questionnaire which has been validated in Australia. (Sansoni, J.A., Marosszeky, M., Sansoni, E, &amp; Hawthrone, G. (2006). Designing a faecal incontinence instrument using survey data, National Health Outcomes Conference. Australian Health Outcomes Collaboration, Wollongong, Australia, 1-8.)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>	Primiparous women over 18 years old and less than 20 weeks gestation 
	Having a current sexual partner 
	Singleton pregnancy 
	Anticipating a vaginal birth
	 With no history of urinary incontinence or pelvic surgery or pelvic organ prolapse
	Able to read and understand and communicate in English
	No previous history of depression, mental illness, alcohol and drug use, domestic violence
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>	Over 20 weeks gestation 
	Planning to give birth via caesarean section at the time of booking 
	Multiparous women 
	Women with multiple pregnancy, 
	Women with complicated pregnancies (type 1 and type 2 diabetic, vaginal bleeding) and those with known pelvic floor muscle dysfunction) 
	Women who are not able to read and understand English to answer the questionnaires 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A computer-generated randomiser will be used to generate the randomisation sequence and randomisation will be remote to WPH</concealment>
    <sequence>Sequence generation will occur from the online randomisation service</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>There is no blinding in this research. However, in order to reduce the risk of bias, the data collection will be performed electronically. So the researcher will be blind to the answers of participants during data collection. But researcher will not be blind to the allocation and statistical analysis of the outcomes after data collection completed. Also, questionnaires are self report questionnaires to further reduce the risk of bias.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analysis of the primary and secondary outcome will be based on intention-to-treat basis which will include withdrawal and losses to follow up. Odds ratios, percentage differences, confidence intervals, Chi-square and students t tests will be used to examine group differences in the primary and secondary outcomes. Data from REDCAP will be exported and SPSS will be used to analyse data.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/03/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Western Sydney University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Western Sydney University
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Western Sydney university</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Western Sydney University
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of this study is to explore the impact of antenatal pelvic floor muscle exercises (PFME) on sexual dysfunction and quality of life in women during pregnancy and in the first three months following birth. A secondary aim is to determine the effect of antenatal PFMT on labour and birth outcomes, urinary and faecal incontinence and specific quality of life three months following birth. 
This is a randomised controlled trial and the primary hypothesis of this study is that: women who perform antenatal PFMT have better sexual function during pregnancy and three months following birth compared with women who receive antenatal standard care alone. The secondary hypothesis is that; women who perform antenatal PFMT have improved childbirth outcomes, less urinary and faecal incontinence symptoms and also better specific quality of life compared with women who receive antenatal standard care alone.
Findings from this study will help to establish an evidence base for the use and effectiveness of antenatal pelvic floor muscle exercise to improve primiparous womens quality of life, sexual function, childbirth outcome and urinary and faecal incontinence symptoms.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>In progress </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Sydney Health District </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>In progress</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Western Sydney University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Western Sydney University
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Westemad Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Cnr Hawkesbury Road and Darcy Road
 Westmead NSW 2145 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/08/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373084-Study protocol version 1.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373084-participant information sheet VERSION 1.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373084-participant consent form VERSION 1.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sahar Sobhgol</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery
Western Sydney University
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751
Australia
</address>
      <phone>+61 452503035</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9685 9959 </fax>
      <email>18628744@student.westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Hannah Dahlen</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery 
Western Sydney University
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751
Australia

</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9685 9118 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9685 9959</fax>
      <email>h.dahlen@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Hannah Dahlen</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery 
Building EB/LG Room 34, Parramatta South Campus
Western Sydney University
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9685 9118 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9685 9959 </fax>
      <email>h.dahlen@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Sahar Sobhgol</name>
      <address> School of Nursing and Midwifery ,
Western Sydney University
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751
Australia

</address>
      <phone>+61 452503035</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9685 9959 </fax>
      <email>18628744@student.westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>