<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362807">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000803897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of core and peripheral temperature measurement in adult critically ill patients with acute brain injury and sepsis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of intravesical core temperature measurement via a temperature sensing bladder catheter with peripheral temperatures measured at tympanic, nasopharyngeal and axillary sites in critically ill adult patients with acute brain injury and sepsis.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CELSIUS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Traumatic brain injury</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac arrest</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sepsis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Two groups of temperature measurements (at least three hours apart) will be made on two consecutive study days.  

The use of physical cooling (ice packs or cooling blankets), renal replacement therapy and nasal devices including nasogastric tubes, nasal intubation, high flow nasal prongs or nasal prongs will be recorded with each group of temperature measurements.  Total daily urine output and serum creatinine will be recorded for each of the two study days on which temperature measurements are made.
  
The equipment used for measuring temperature will be the Braun Thermoscan Type 6021 for tympanic measurements, the Protec BX/144 digital thermometer for axillary measurements, the General Electric Vital-Temp general-purpose probe for nasopharyngeal measurements, and the Nellcor Mon-a-therm Foley Temp 400 series for intravesical measurements. 

Temperature will be measured at each site as follows: 

a.	Tympanic- an ear-tug will be performed by pulling the pinna upward and backward whilst inserting the probe with a slight rotating motion aiming towards the anterior inferior third of the tympanic membrane. To prevent interference from the air temperature, the probe should penetrate at least one third of the external auditory meatus and form a seal. If the patient wears a hearing aid, this will be removed for 20 minutes prior to measurement. Similarly if the patient has been lying in a lateral position, they will be laid supine at least 20 minutes prior to measurement to avoid ear-warming. Paired measurements will be taken in both the right and left ears and averaged.

b.	Axillary- the thermometer will be placed on dry skin deep into the apex of the axilla with the patients arms adducted so that the tip of the thermometer is covered by the arm to prevent interference from air temperature. Paired measurements will be taken in both the right and left axillae and averaged. 

c.	Nasopharyngeal- the probe will be positioned in the nasopharynx posterior to the soft palate by inserting approximately 10cm into the left or right nostril. The probe should be in situ for at least 20 minutes prior to measurement to allow for temperature to equilibrate. Patients with clinical or radiological evidence of base of skull or facial fractures will not have a nasopharyngeal probe inserted due to the risk of incorrect positioning. 

d.	Intravesical- the temperature sensing urinary catheter will be inserted as for a standard urinary catheter.  The catheter should be in situ for at least 20 minutes prior to measurement to allow for temperature to equilibrate. 

After the cessation of physical cooling, at least 20minutes should be allowed to pass before temperature measurement to allow for temperature to equilibrate.</interventions>
    <comparator>Intravesical core temperature measured via a temperature sensing urinary catheter.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We will analyse our temperature data using the Bland-Altman method for agreement studies, which enables comparison of two measurements made using different instruments to calculate a 'mean difference' (accuracy). The standard deviation indicates the precision of the instrument, and the mean difference plus or minus 1.96 of the standard deviation gives the upper and lower limits of agreement which gives an interval within which we can be reasonably confident that the true value of the measurement lies within.

The primary analysis will use data from all of the patients; a second analysis will be done that includes the measurements that were taken during the use of physical cooling and within four hours of the cessation of physical cooling or active warming.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Four sets of temperature measurements over two days, each set taken at least 3 hours apart. Each set consists of tympanic measurements in both ears, axillary measurements in both axillae, nasopharyngeal and intravesical measurements.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Either:

1.	Mechanically ventilated patients admitted into the intensive care units with a traumatic brain injury, cardiac arrest or stroke within the first week of intensive care treatment following injury

Or:

2.	Patients admitted with sepsis (body temperature greater or equal to 38.0 degrees Celsius and receiving antimicrobial therapy for a known or suspected infection) within the first week of intensive care treatment for sepsis</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Patients under 16 years of age.

2.	Patients for which informed consent is not provided from the patient or patients surrogate decision maker,(unless the ethics committee agree to waiving consent).

3.	Patients for whom insertion (or replacement) of a urinary catheter is contraindicated (for example known history of urethral stricture of severe pelvic trauma with suspected urethral tear).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/04/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St George Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Intensive Care Unit
St George Hospital
Gray Street, Kogarah NSW 2217</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dr Manoj Saxena</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Intensive Care Unit
St George Hospital
Gray Street, Kogarah NSW 2217</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of New  South Wales</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The University of New South Wales
Sydney NSW 2052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Paul Young</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The Wellington Regional Hospital
Riddiford Street, Newtown, Wellington 6021</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The CELSIUS Study is a prospective observational study of temperature measurement in critically ill patients with acute brain injury and sepsis in Australia and New Zealand. 
In these patients we are evaluating commonly used methods of temperature measurement (tympanic, axillary, nasopharyngeal) with assessment against a pragmatic gold standard of urinary bladder temperature (intravesical) measurement.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, James Laws House
St George Public Hospital
Gray Street, Kogarah NSW 2217</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/STG/6</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Manoj Saxena</name>
      <address>Intensive Care Unit
St George Hospital
Gray Street, Kogarah NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9113 3373</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>msaxena@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Manoj Saxena</name>
      <address>Intensive Care Unit
St George Hospital
Gray Street, Kogarah NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9113 3373</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>msaxena@georgeinstitute.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Miss Amy Chur-Yee Liu</name>
      <address>Intensive Care Unit
St George Hospital
Gray Street, Kogarah NSW 2217</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>a.c.liu@student.unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>