<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368895">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000018415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Study examining the effects of altering a diet's macronutrient composition on plasma ketone levels in women with gestational diabetes mellitus</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised controlled trial (RCT) examining the effects of a modestly lower carbohydrate diet on plasma ketone levels in women with gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>MAMI GDM 
(Macronutrient Adjustments in Mothers to Improve Gestational Diabetes Mellitus)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gestational Diabetes Mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Antenatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fetal medicine and complications of pregnancy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1 Intervention - Main focus will be limiting daily carbohydrate intake to 135 g. Carbohydrates should be spread evenly through out the day, with 2 carbohydrate exchanges per main meal (3 times a day) and 1 exchange per mid meal (also 3 times a day). One exchange equals to consuming 15 g of carbohydrate and this proves to be a useful method of monitoring carbohydrate intake, particularly in individuals diagnosed with diabetes. A research dietitian will have ongoing contact with participants via phone (to arrange meetings) and during 4 face-to-face sessions (including a baseline and 3 other follow up visits in Week 2, Week 4 and Week 6, all lasting no more than an hour). 

To prevent study bias, participants will be unaware of their group allocation. They will, however, receive a pictorial booklet containing acceptable  carbohydrate portions of various foods. The study dietitian will also verbally guide participants on the acceptable amount and distribution of carbohydrates . A 3-day food record will be collected at baseline and in the last (6th or 7th) week of the study, where as a 24 hour recall  will be conducted at 2 follow up visits to confirm diet compliance. Non-compliant participants will be re-educated. Food packages including breads, cereals, pasta and rice will be handed to women to help model portion size (i.e. what represents 1 exchange) and enhance participation rate.

The study is designed to last 6-7weeks (though 6 ideally), but this will depend on participant's availability and ability to attend all the face-to-face sessions. </interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 2 Control - People in the control group will have standard GDM care including a standard diet containing ~180-200g of carbohydrates/day, with a distribution pattern of 2-3 exchanges per main meal (3 times a day) and 1 exchange per mid meal (roughly 3 times a day). Similarly to  the intervention group, control will not be informed of their group's allocation. They will have the same number of visits with the research dietitian, who will promote general healthy eating messages. Food packages will also be distributed (but to a lesser degree) to the control  in order to 'mask' that they are in the control group. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety - which will be assessed by blood ketone measurements and medical symptom flags. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>- 3 finger pricks/day on selected days (4th and 7th day of week 1 and week 6) prior to breakfast, lunch and dinner. 
- Random ketone measurements at follow up visits 1 and 2.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary compliance - which will be assess by 24 Hour Recalls and 3-day food record.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>3-day food record (baseline and week 6), 24 hour recall (follow up visit 2 and 3). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Large/Small gestational age babies
</outcome>
      <timepoint>After birth, to be assessed using medical records</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caesarian delivery</outcome>
      <timepoint>After birth, to be obtained from medical records</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Baby's body composition</outcome>
      <timepoint>After birth, to be obtained from PEAPOD measurements</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Women diagnosed with gestational diabetes mellitus (GDM) at 24-30 weeks gestation
2.	Singleton pregnancy 
3.	Age between 18-45 years
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Women with special dietary requirements (e.g. vegan/vegetarian, gluten free)
2.	Existence of co-morbidities other than obesity, hypertension or dyslipidemia
3.	Pre-existing diabetes
4.	Undesirable lifestyle habits such as smoking and alcohol consumption
5.	Pregnancy achieved by assisted reproduction (IVF) 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>SCREENING:  Women will be screened for eligibility at the end of Diabetes Sessions at the Antenatal Clinic. Eligible subjects handed information and consent papers to sign, and asked to provide contact details so that a letter of their next appointment with a 3-day food record could be mailed out. The food record will aim to capture intake of (non-consecutive) 2 weekdays and 1 day of the weekend. 
ENROLLMENT: Women return for their first official visit for the study, bringing completed 3-day food records. Dietitian is to assist women in completing their Enrollment form which aims to capture demographic data ranging from age to past and present medical conditions.
RANDOMISATION: Women will be randomised with an envelope block randomization technique. This ensures that study groups will be equal in size and uniformly distributed by key characteristics – age (&gt; 30 and &lt;30 years old) and weeks gestation (&gt;28 and &lt;28 weeks).  With the exception of the research dietitian, all other research members and participants will be blinded to group allocations
</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation 
We will sort experimental units into 4 groups of similar characteristics. They include: 
1.	Age &gt; 30 yeas
2.	Age &lt; 30 (30 inclusive) years 
3.	&gt;28 Weeks gestation 
4.	&lt;28 (28 inclusive) Weeks gestation 
Treatment will then be assigned at random within the blocks using sealed envelopes
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>NA</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The study is designed to provide 80% statistical power to detect approximately 0.04 mmol difference in blood ketone levels with 25 subjects in each of the two groups. We will aim to recruit 65 subjects, with allowance of 25% (15 subjects) to dropout. Calculations were based on a study by Gin and colleagues, published in 2006. A paired 2 sample t-test will be used to assess between group changes from baseline to final outcomes.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>65</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Campbelltown Hospital - Campbelltown</hospital>
    <postcode>2560 - Campbelltown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Charles Perkins Centre, John Hopkins Drive (off Missenden Road), Camperdown NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Charles Perkins Centre, John Hopkins Drive (off Missenden Road), Camperdown NSW 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To our knowledge no study investigated serum ketone levels in Gestational Diabetes Mellitus (GDM) pregnancy with a modestly lower carbohydrate diet. Our primary aim is to document a range of blood ketone in women on a routine GDM diet (180-200 g carbohydrates/day) and a modestly lower carbohydrate diet (135g carbohydrates/day). The 135 g of carbohydrate/day is an absolute amount of carbohydrate which is in line with Institute of Medicine (IOM) recommendation for carbohydrate intake during pregnancy. We also aim to examine the effect of modestly lower carbohydrate diet on the risk of ketonemia in GDM pregnancy. We hypothesise that when compared to a routine GDM diet, a modestly lower carbohydrate diet will not increase ketone levels in GDM pregnancy, nor will it increase the risk of adverse pregnancy outcomes including risk of large/small gestational age babies and caesarean delivery. If our hypotheses are proven to be correct, perhaps prescribing a modestly lower carbohydrate diet to no less than 135g/day will be the new standard for treatment of GDM.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital Ethics Committe</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Missenden Road, Camperdown NSW 2006, Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/12/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X15-0298</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jennie Brand-Miller</name>
      <address>Level 6 West, The Hub
D17 Charles Perkins Centre
John Hopkins Drive (off Missenden Road), 
The University of Sydney
Camperdown, NSW 2006 
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93513759</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennie.brandmiller@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Jovana Mijatovic</name>
      <address>Level 6 West, The Hub
D17 Charles Perkins Centre
John Hopkins Drive (off Missenden Road), 
The University of Sydney
Camperdown, NSW 2006 

</address>
      <phone>+61 2 86271341</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jmij1646@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jennie Brand-Miller</name>
      <address>Level 6 West, The Hub
D17 Charles Perkins Centre
John Hopkins Drive (off Missenden Road), 
The University of Sydney
Camperdown, NSW 2006

</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93513759</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennie.brandmiller@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Jovana Mijatovic</name>
      <address>Level 6 West, The Hub
D17 Charles Perkins Centre
John Hopkins Drive (off Missenden Road), 
The University of Sydney
Camperdown, NSW 2006 
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 86271341</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jmij1646@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>