<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371878">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001612404</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of the QuickSmart Numeracy program on the mathematics outcomes of year 4 and 8 students.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>QuickSmart Numeracy: A randomized control trial investigating the efficacy of the 30 week QuickSmart numeracy program on Progressive Achievement Test (Mathematics) results among year 4 and 8 students demonstrating low numeracy abilities.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Numeracy ability</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Mathematics efficacy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants (school students in year 4 and 8) are asked to undertake additional mathematics tuition (3 x 30 minute sessions / week within school hours) across 3 school terms (30 weeks). QuickSmart tuition is focused on improving the speed and accuracy of basic arithmetic computation. Sessions are undertaken by teacher's aids who have undertaken the QuickSmart instructor training (3 day workshop). Sessions are undertaken with two students at a time, with the CAAS system (see below) recording session attendance and progress.

QuickSmart tuition involves:
1- Flash cards and number recall games using numerical operations: number naming, addition number facts, subtraction number facts, multiplication number facts, division number facts, and triple addition tasks (for example, 7 + 4 + 3).
2- Cognitive Aptitude Assessment System (CAAS)
The CAAS system provides measures of how rapidly students complete tasks by speaking into a microphone once a number fact is displayed on the computer screen. An instructor scores each response for accuracy. 
3- Students graphing of CAAS results.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group undertake standard mathematics tuition offered during their schools regular programming.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progressive Achievement Test - Mathematics (PAT-M)</outcome>
      <timepoint>May 2018 - 18 months post commencement of the 30 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This composite measure includes: i) student self-efficacy, and ii) engagement in mathematics (Programme for International Student Assessment scales).</outcome>
      <timepoint>May 2018 - 18 months post commencement of the 30 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1- Participants are in Year 4 or 8 in 2017
2- Bottom 30% nationally in the most recent National Assessment Programme - Literacy and Numeracy (NAPLAN) - Numeracy outcome.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1- NAPLAN - numeracy above bottom 30% nationally
2- Previous participation in QuickSmart Numeracy
3- Not in year 4 or 8 in 2017</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomization by independent third party via a coin toss after baseline assessment</concealment>
    <sequence>Coin toss allocation of matched pairs</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analyses will be completed using PASW Statistics 21 (SPSS Inc. Chicago, IL) software. Alpha levels are set at p &lt; 0.05. Independent samples t-tests will be used to compare differences between groups at baseline. Linear mixed models will be fitted to compare intervention and control groups for continuous variables. Group (intervention or control), time (baseline and follow-up) and group-by-time interaction will be assessed as fixed effects within the model. Potential gender effects will be explored using a group-by-time-by-gender interaction term in the mixed model. Differences of means and 95% confidence intervals (CIs) are determined using the linear mixed models. Analyses include all randomized participants. Hedges g is used to determine effect sizes of the change in mean for each group relative to the baseline value (effect of intervention on the change score).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/12/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>280</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/11/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive, Callaghan, NSW, 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Social Ventures Australia - Evidence for Learning Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 6, 6 OConnell Street, Sydney, NSW, 2000 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of New ENgland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Armidale, NSW, 2351
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Students who experience ongoing failure in upper-primary and lower-secondary school face a myriad of difficulties in pursuing post-school options and societal contribution through employment and aware citizenship. Those who exhibit consistent weaknesses in basic skills, such as the recall of number facts are particularly vulnerable. The QuickSmart Numeracy program is focused on improving the speed and accuracy of basic arithmetic computation. This intervention has demonstrated efficacy within quasi-experimental research trials. The purpose of this study is to test the intervention efficacy using a randomized-controlled experimental design.

The aim of this study is to investigate the impact of a numeracy based program, QuickSmart Numeracy, on the numeracy levels of year 4 and 8 students with low proficiency in mathematics. Participants are asked to undertake additional tuition (3 x 30 minute sessions / week within school hours) across 3 school terms (30 weeks). QuickSmart tuition is focused on improving the speed and accuracy of basic arithmetic computation. Evaluation of the primary outcome is via a cluster randomized controlled trial (wait-list control) involving parallel comparison of matched pairs within the same class. The primary outcome is the age scaled score on the Progressive Achievement Test (mathematics version).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle - Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University Drive, Callaghan, NSW, 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/11/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2016-0338</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Miller</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
EN2.05, Chittaway Rd, OURIMBAH, NSW, 2258
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 434 84214</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.miller@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Miller</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
EN2.05, Chittaway Rd, OURIMBAH, NSW, 2258</address>
      <phone>+61 2 434 84214</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.miller@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrew Miller</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle
EN2.05, Chittaway Rd, OURIMBAH, NSW, 2258</address>
      <phone>+61 2 434 84214</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrew.miller@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>