<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372058">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000021370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Combining a web-based intervention (WBI) and Ecological Momentary Intervention (EMI) to curb alcohol consumption in university students: A randomized control trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Combining a web-based intervention (WBI) and Ecological Momentary Intervention (EMI) to curb alcohol consumption in university students: A randomized control trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1191-0811</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alcohol  use</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will receive a computer delivered intervention prior to Orientation Week. The computer delivered intervention will  combine aspects of social norms, provide information on AUDIT score, BAC, risk of alcohol-related consequences, long-term consequences, and protective behavioural strategies. The intervention will be delivered after participants' initial survey and include sections of text with feedback about their drinking. The online intervention will take approximately 5-10 minutes to complete and is to be completed by participants prior to Orientation Week.

Following the online aspect, participants will be assigned to one of 4 conditions outlined below, All conditions will be asked to respond to 2 Orientation Week messages and 7 fortnightly text messages asking them to report their drinking from the past 3 days (e.g., 'How many standard drinks did you consume Thurs, Fri, Sat? Please TB like this 5, 0, 1).:

1. Orientation Week Ecological Momentary Assessment (EMA) and Academic Year EMA: Participants in this condition will only receive messages asking them to report their alcohol use during Orientation Week and fortnightly throughout the academic year.

2. Orientation Week Ecological Momentary Intervention (EMI) and Academic Year EMA: Participants will be sent intervention text messages twice a day (at 1pm and 7pm) on the Tuesday, Thursday, Friday, and Saturday of Orientation Week. The 1pm messages will remind participants of a protective behavioural strategy presented in the online intervention. The 7pm messages will contain a social consequence of alcohol use. These participants will also receive messages during Orientation Week and fortnightly throughout the year asking them to report their drinking from the past 3 days.

3. Orientation Week EMA and Academic Year EMI: Participants in this condition will receive  intervention text messages fortnightly during the first semester. These messages will be sent on a Wednesday reminding participants of the drinking norms (tailored to gender). These participants will also receive messages during Orientation Week and fortnightly throughout the year asking them to report their drinking from the past 3 days.

4. Orientation Week EMI and Academic Year EMI: Participants will receive both the Orientation Week and Academic Year EMIs described above. These participants will also receive messages during Orientation Week and fortnightly throughout the year asking them to report their drinking from the past 3 days.

All participants will also fill out a questionnaire at the start and end of the semester (baseline and 3 months) asking them to report the number of alcohol related consequences they experienced over the past 3 months (B-YAACQ) as well as alcohol use over the last week and the AUDIT.</interventions>
    <comparator>No-intervention control (Ecological momentary assessment (EMA) only condition).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol use</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, during Orientation Week, and fortnightly throughout first semester of the academic year. Baseline assessment will use a modified version of timeline followback asking participants to report their drinking during a typical week. During Orientation Week and the academic year, participants will be sent messages asking them to report their drinking from the past 3 days. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol related consequences as measured by the Brief Young Adult Alcohol Consequences Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after first semester (approximately 3 months after baseline).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Must be a full time first year student residing at a residential college.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Students who do not live at a residential college. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Repeated measures ANOVA and planned comparisons. 

The total sample size [n = 300] should have sufficient power, even when taking potential drop-out into account. The design is well powered for detecting group differences of 6.5 standard drinks during OWeek and 2 standard drinks/week during the academic year.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/10/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago, Department of Psychology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 56, Dunedin, 9054</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of  Otago</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 56, Dunedin, 9054</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Young adults have the highest alcohol consumption of any age group. Within this high risk age group, university students stand out, consuming more alcohol than their non-university attending peers. As a result, university students not only have a higher incidence of alcohol use disorders, but also report a higher incidence of harm resulting from alcohol. A number of factors have been implicated in this increase in alcohol use at university, however, new research suggests that drinking during certain events (e.g., Orientation Week) may have a flow on effect and influence the number of drinks students consume throughout the year. 

The primary aim of the research project is to reduce overall alcohol consumption by university students (i.e., alcohol consumed during the academic year) and to determine whether text message interventions during Orientation Week and the academic year can have an impact on alcohol use over an above an online intervention alone. We hypothesize that an ecological momentary intervention (EMI) aimed at Orientation Week and the academic year will reduce the amount of alcohol use throughout both Orientation Week and throughout the year over and above a condition who only received an online intervention.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 56, Dunedin, 9054</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/11/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/267</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/372058-Ethics approval.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Benjamin C. Riordan</name>
      <address>University of Otago, Department of Psychology
PO Box 56, Dunedin, 9054</address>
      <phone>+64-3-479-9427</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ben.riordan@postgrad.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Benjamin C. Riordan</name>
      <address>University of Otago, Department of Psychology
PO Box 56, Dunedin, 9054</address>
      <phone>+64-3-479-9427</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ben.riordan@postgrad.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Benjamin C. Riordan</name>
      <address>University of Otago, Department of Psychology
PO Box 56, Dunedin, 9054</address>
      <phone>+64-3-479-9427</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ben.riordan@postgrad.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>