<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83504">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/01/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/02/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000134224</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Western Sydney Adolescent Sport and Physical Activity Program (WASPA): A pilot program to manage obesity among adolescents.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of a Community-Based After School Program on Preventing Unhealthy Weight Gain among Overweight and Obese Adolescents.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>WASPA</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Overweight and obese adolescents</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>(1) The WASPA Physical Activity Program - Community based after school physical activity and healthy eating program conducted at a local community setting (leisure centre). The physical activity and healthy eating program focuses on increasing adolescents fitness, sporting skills, and physical activity, and improving their food habits and eating behaviours. The program will run for 20 weeks, with two 1.5 hour sessions each week. Adolescents will also be asked to complete two additional physical activity sessions in their own time each week. The activities are designed to be enjoyable and to develop self-efficacy among participants whilst also accommodating their unique needs.  

Parents will be asked to attend five dietary education sessions with an accredited practising dietitian. The adolescents will also participate separately in five sessions as part of the programme. These are aimed at guiding healthy eating choices through improving knowledge about portion sizes and label reading skills and preparing healthy alternatives such as afternoon snacks and meals.</interventions>
    <comparator>Active control Receive the 'State-of-the-art information-based health education program'. Adolescents and parents will be asked to attend five monthly sessions and to read the monthly newsletters. The session duration is approximately 1-1.5 hours and the newsletters are a maximum on 2 x A4 pages.  sessions and newsletters will focus on physical activity recommendations, small screen recreation guidelines and dietary information sessions aimed at guiding healthy eating choices through improving knowledge about portion sizes and label reading.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anthropometric
1) Height and Weight (Body mass index "BMI")- Portable stadiometer, and portable electronic scales
2_Waist Circumference - non-extensible tape measure
3) Percentage Body Fat - Tanita BC-418 Segmental Body Composition Analyser
4) Resting Heart Rate - Polar heart rate monitor
5)Resting blood pressure - Dinamao automated blood pressure monitor
5) Fasting Lipids (total cholesterol "TC", High-density lipoproteins "HDL-C", Low-density lipoproteins "LDL-C", triglycerides; insulin; glucose) - Blood samples after overnight fast</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1) Physical Activity - MTI Actigraph Accelerometers
2) Cardiorespiratory fitness - 20M shuttle run test
3) Muscular Strength and power - Grip dynamometer, standing long jump
4) Functional strength - prone hold, sit-to-stand</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6-month follow-up (Demographics only taken at baseline)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adolescent Measures (Self-report)
Quality of life, Psychosocial Well-being, Food habits, Body image and eating behaviours - all assessed via questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent Measure 
Quality of life, Demographics (household income, parental education, marital status, parent education level), Adverse events/injuries)- all assessed via questionnaires.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6-month follow-up (Demographics only taken at baseline)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. The adolescent will need to be overweight or obese as defined by Body Mass Index "BMI" according to International Obesity Task Force cut-off points for age and gender. 
2. At least one parent would need to attend all required dietary sessions (5 in total, which run from 4-5:30pm in the given weeks), and only one adolescent from each family can enrol.
3. The adolescent needs to be between 12 and 16 years of age (they can be turning 12 before March 2009).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Adolescents with extreme obesity (Body Mass Index Standard Deviation score greater than 4 "BMI SD score &gt; 4.0") will not be eligible.
2. No known syndromal causes of obesity, long term oral steroids, medications known to be associated with weight gain, chronic illness, or significant dietary restriction.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment will commence approximately 6 weeks before the program commences. Numerous recruitment strategies will be employed to enhance recruitment success and include: personalised letters sent to school Principals inviting them to promote the study within their school and in school newsletters articles and posters places in general Practitioner (gp) surgeries, shopping centers and public libraries. The University of Wollongong media unit will distribute media releases resulting in newspaper articles and radio and television interviews and finally paid advertisements will be placed in local newspapers.

Interested participants will be sent an information package containing an information sheet and a consent form. Once written consent is received from both participants and their parents, participants will be randomized into either the intervention group or the control group.

Allocation was concealed: central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>The bias coin method of allocation, using a computer-based random number-producing algorithm will be used for randomisation. This method ensures an equal chance of allocation to each group. Stratification by gender will be done to ensure an equal representation in groups. Only one study member will have access to the allocation codes and these will be stored on a pass-word protected computer.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Two arm randomised controlled trial (intervention and control groups)</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/03/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Wollongong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Wollongong
Northfields Avenue 
Wollongong NSW 2522</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Wollongong</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Wollongong
Northfields Avenue 
Wollongong NSW 2522</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Fairfield Community Leisure Centre</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Vine Street 
Fairfield NSW 2165</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the study is to test how effective an after-school physical activity and healthy eating program and a health education program are in the treatment of overweight and obesity in adolescents. To test these programs, the following two groups will be involved in the study:

1. A physical activity and healthy eating program; and
2. A state-of-the-art information-based health education program.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Tony Okely</name>
      <address>Faculty of Education. Building 67
University of Wollongong
wollongong NSW 2522</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4221 4641</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4221 3892</fax>
      <email>tokely@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Associate Professor Tony Okely</name>
      <address>Faculty of Education. Building 67
University of Wollongong
wollongong NSW 2522</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4221 4641</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4221 3892</fax>
      <email>tokely@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jacqueline Kelly</name>
      <address>7 Central Road Beverly Hills 2209 NSW</address>
      <phone>+61422575581</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jk486@uow.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>