<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363336">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/12/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/12/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001276842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA1c)  feedback from a Chronic Disease Management Register to treating General Practitioners have an impact on the management of diabetes and increase the proportion of patients with poorly controlled diabetes who achieve good control?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In diabetics with recent glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA1c) &gt; 7 who are on a chronic disease patient register, does a reminder to their GPs about their HbA1c level, compared to usual care, impact upon the management of their diabetes and lead to an improvement in HbA1c levels?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1137-6149 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Letter from register to patient's GP reminding them of the patient's elevated HbA1c level. 

This letter will be sent to all GPs of patients in the intervention group once, at the same point in time. This point in time will be at the beginning of the study when all patients have been enrolled in the study.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care.

The patients in the control group will have no further contact with the study investigators except that the study investigators will follow up these patients' HbA1c results for 6 months after the commencement of the study. They will continue to be managed by their usual care givers, eg, GPs, diabetic educators, endocrinologists. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in GP management of patients (i.e. by altering thinking, ordering a retest, changing advice or changing medication).

This will be assessed by examination of the qualitative information collected at the GP Practice Visits.

The interviews will be semi-structured with the following questions used as a guide for the collection of information:
1.	Did you receive the intervention letter?
2.	What are your views on the letter? Was it valuable to you and/ or your staff (eg Practice Nurse)?
3.	Did it lead to any change in the way you or your Practice Nurse managed your patient's diabetes? For example:
Did it change your thinking regarding the management of your patients diabetes? 
Did it lead to a patient review?
Did it lead to a referral to another health professional?
Did it lead to care plan being developed for the patient? (eg Diabetes Annual Cycle of Care Plan or GP Management Plan) 
Did it lead you to do further investigations? 
Did it lead you to give different advice to the patient (eg regarding diet or exercise)?
Did it lead to a change in the medications or dose of medications?
4.	If the intervention did not lead to any change in the way you managed your patients diabetes can you please explain why?
5.	Do you have any further comments or feedback about the intervention letter? 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in HbA1c levels.

Changes in HbA1c levels will be analysed in two ways:
1)	The proportion of patients in the intervention group whose HbA1c level is less than or equal to 7 at 6 months will be compared to the proportion of patients in the control group whose HbA1c level is less than or equal to 7 at 6 months. We expect the intervention group to have a higher proportion than the control group. The statistical significance of the difference in proportions will be assessed to explore whether any difference may be due to chance.
2)	The mean reduction in HbA1c levels will be compared in the intervention group and the control group at 6 months. We expect that the intervention group will have a greater average reduction in HbA1c levels than the control group. The statistical significance of the differences in the means will be assessed to explore whether any difference may be due to chance.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 6 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults patients on the Chronic Disease Management Register who have a recent Hba1c level &gt;7.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pregnant women.
People unable to provide consent themselves.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All adult patients meeting inclusion criteria (ie. a HbA1c level &gt; 7) will be contacted by mail and invited to participate in the study. Patients will receive comprehensive information regarding the study including an information sheet about the study and a consent form which will also comprise a basic questionnaire about variables that may need to be considered regarding their disease history. Those that don't send in the consent forms will be phoned to ask whether they would like to participate in the study. Consent for these patients will be obtained over the phone with the investigator completing the form. Patients will be randomised in a 1:1 ratio to the control or intervention arm of the study after consent is obtained by a computer generated random allocation algorithm.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation). </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/12/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Health Directorate</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box 825, 
Canberra ACT 2601</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Nil, funded through existing section budget</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Nil</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Australian National University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Canberra ACT 0200
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To assess whether providing General Practitioners with reminders about their patients HbA1c results from a Chronic Disease Management Register leads to better diabetes control.  This will be determined via GP Practice Visits and HbA1c levels.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACT Health Directorate Human Research Ethics Committee Low Risk Sub-Committtee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 11,
WODEN ACT 2606

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ETHLR.12.278</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Clare King</name>
      <address>Chronic Disease Management
ACT Health Directorate
GPO Box 825
Canberra ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+612 62076833</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Paul.Dugdale@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Dugdale</name>
      <address>Chronic Disease Management
ACT Health Directorate
GPO Box 825
Canberra ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+612 62076833</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Paul.Dugdale@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Clare King</name>
      <address>Chronic Disease Management
ACT Health Directorate
GPO Box 825
Canberra ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+612 62051839</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>clare.king@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Dugdale</name>
      <address>Chronic Disease Management
ACT Health Directorate
GPO Box 825
Canberra ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+612 62076833</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Paul.Dugdale@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>