<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363804">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000275763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Data Analysis on the Effects of Taxus Chinensis Scent on Sleeping Quality of People with High Blood Pressure
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Data Analysis on the Effects of Taxus Chinensis Scent on Sleeping Quality of People with High Blood Pressure
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sleeping disorders</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypertension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Herbal remedies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A pillow with Taxus chinensis extract (smells similar to tea) infill (cross-over at the middle of the study, after two weeks break) will be provided for participants to use during their sleep for three weeks.

Each participant will be provided with a mobile device, which has an embedded accelerometer and microphone to record the body movement and the volume of breathing sound during their sleep. Participants will be automatically promoted by a special designed software embedded in the mobile device to record movement and sound volume during the night. The smart phone will be placed close to the body during sleep and will only switch on network during day time to transfer the data. Participants have an option to use it as their primary phone during the study. Participants will also be asked to answer a set of questions on general well-being, sleeping quality, diet and physical activities at pre and post of each intervention, for analysis.</interventions>
    <comparator>A pillow with placebo (tea) infill (cross-over at the middle of the study, after two weeks break) will be provided for participants to use during their sleep for three weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>It is anticipated that this study will discover the details of how Taxus chinensis aromatic therapy improves the participants sleeping quality.

The participants' body movement and breathing sound volume (not to record to the actual sound) will be automatically recorded by the mobile device during their sleep. The Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) is to be used as a self-rated questionnaire which assesses sleep quality and disturbances, at pre, mid (when crossover) and post trial to assess the effects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The outcomes will be measured and analysed at the end of each phase of the trail, ie. when the interventions (treatment and control group) crossover (week 4) and at the end of the trial (week 8). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>It is anticipated that this study will discover the details of how Taxus chinensis aromatic therapy improves the participants general well-being.

Physical and psychological well-being will be investigated by the Short Form 36 Health Survey (SF-36), and a questionnaire to record participants' diet and physical activity levels will be used, and participants' blood pressure will be measured by the researcher, at pre, mid (when crossover) and post trial to assess the effects. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The outcomes will be measured and analysed at the end of each phase of the trail, ie. when the interventions (treatment and control group) crossover (week 4) and at the end of the trial (week 8). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- has lived in Australia for the past 10 years

- has used smart phone and feels comfortable to use it

- aged 45-75 years and with moderate hypertension (blood pressure lower than 159/99 mmHg) 

- has sleeping disorders in the past three month or longer, and 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- acute respiratory infections, olfactory (sense of smell) disorders or nasal blockage

- has other major medical conditions (ie. established CVD, severe diabetes, thyroid dysfunction, asthma, hepatic or renal disorders) or pregnancy / lactation

- has taken other supplements or medicine which may influence blood pressure in the past three months, or has taken blood pressure management tablet in a same dosage and has not changed within the past three month

- allergic to the extract of Taxus chinensis and its scent (this also applies to their family members who could have access to the smell)

- has taken sleeping tablets, supplements or medicine which may influence sleeping 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A researcher who is familiar with this type of clinical trial will be invited as the third party to label the treatment and placebo pillow (which will be packed the same). The pillow is assigned to match the participants’ codes and groups (i.e. A1, A2... or B1, B2...; names will be kept confidential). This researcher will be asked not to reveal relevant information to either researchers or participants.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be grouped based on a random number table. Participants in Group A will receive the treatment of the Taxus chinensis extract scent pillow for the first three weeks while participants in Group B will receive the placebo during the same period. After two weeks of the wash out period (break), for the second three weeks, the interventions will be switched, i.e. Group B will receive the Taxus chinensis extract scent pillow and Group A use placebo. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The data will be analysed through the application of paired t-test using a software program SPSS 18.0 to determine the following:
- The difference between Group A and Group B before treatment commenced.
- The difference between pre- and post-intervention results for all the participants in both groups, i.e. in the first three weeks with Group A as the treatment group and Group B as the control group, and in the second three weeks with Group B as the treatment group and Group A as the control. Pre- and post- treatment effects were also considered for the combination of Group A and B. P &lt; 0.05 was accepted as significant.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/10/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Yuan Miao</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Engineering and Science
Victoria University
PoBox 14428 Melbourne
Vic 8001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Zhangguang 101 Holding Group</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>China Zhangguang 101 Holding Group, No. 4 Yongchang zhonglu BDA, Beijing (100176), China</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Submitted on 29 Jan, 2013, [Dr. Deborah Zion, the Chair of the Victoria University Human Research Ethics Committee informed this ANZCTR is required before final approval is given.] (Office for Research, Victoria University, PO Box 14428, Melbourne, VIC, 8001 or phone (03) 9919 4781.)</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Victoria University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Victoria University
PoBox 14428, Melbourne
Vic 8001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>HRE13-027 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/01/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Yuan Miao</name>
      <address>School of Engineering and Science
Victoria University
PO Box 14428 
Melbourne, Vic 8001</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99194605</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yuan.miao@vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Yuan Miao</name>
      <address>School of Engineering and Science
Victoria University
PO Box 14428 
Melbourne, Vic 8001</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99194605</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yuan.miao@vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Yuan Miao</name>
      <address>School of Engineering and Science
Victoria University
PO Box 14428 
Melbourne, Vic 8001</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99194605</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yuan.miao@vu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>