<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373032">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000808347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>COMBAT-MS (COgnitive reMediation and Behavioural Approaches to Treatment in Multiple Sclerosis)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>COMBAT-MS (COgnitive reMediation and Behavioural Approaches to Treatment in Multiple Sclerosis)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>COMBAT-MS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Randomised, controlled, single-blinded, prospective, longitudinal study to assess psychosocial adjustment, learning and memory in patients with multiple sclerosis treated with a novel therapy combining CBT and Cognitive Remediation. Participants will be randomly assigned to receive either the study intervention for 10 weeks or assigned to receive treatment as usual (usual clinical care by their treating neurologist). Participants across both groups will receive assessments at baseline (prior to study intervention), immediate and long-term follow up. Assessors blinded to participant randomisation will conduct the immediate (3 month) and long-term (12 month) follow up assessments.

The study intervention will combine elements of an evidence-based CBT program targeting adjustment in MS (saMS) with evidence-based cognitive-training techniques involving both strategy training and computer-based cognitive training. The cognitive remediation component will be informed by the Neuropsychological Educational Approach to Remediation (NEAR). 

The delivery of the study intervention will be lead by a Clinical Neuropsychologist with 8+ years of experience in neuropsychological and psychological assessment and the delivery of CBT and cognitive remediation. The intervention will be delivered in a group-based therapy format for two hours a week over one session for 10 weeks. The intervention will be delivered in a university research centre. The therapy will be delivered in small groups of 6-10 people. The content will be shown on slides and presented by the trial psychologists. The format of the sessions will generally follow the following sequence: 1) presentation of psychoeducational content relating to MS, mood, anxiety, stress, and cognition; 2) discussion of how the content relates to the individuals in the group; 3) teaching of strategies to assist with difficulties with mood, anxiety, stress, and cognition; 3) practicing those strategies with a partner from the group. 

Patients enrolled in the study will receive a participant information statement. They will be asked to complete self-report questionnaires assessing factors associated with psychosocial adjustment. During the intervention, they will receive psychoeducational content in the form of print out of slides. They will be able to refer to this content whenever they wish.The trial psychologists will use a battery of neuropsychological measures from the MACFIMS battery to assess patients. Trial neurologists will utilise the Expanded Disability Status Scale to assess disability in trial participants. 

We aim to determine whether this program has an impact on psychological factors (i.e. depression, anxiety, stress, coping, self-efficacy, health related quality of life and productivity) and aspects of cognitive functioning (i.e. memory, attention, speed of information processing, executive functions, visuospatial skills) contributing to adjustment. In a randomized controlled design, this will be achieved by administering standardised psychological and neuropsychological assessments pre and post intervention that have been shown to be sensitive in persons with MS. Sustainability of effects will be monitored by repeating these assessments at a 12-month follow-up visit. We also aim to determine whether the program is associated with secondary benefits to pharmacological treatment adherence and disease course (e.g. number of relapses; severity of physical symptoms).

A register of attendance at each session will be used to monitor adherence. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will be randomly assigned to receive either the study intervention for 10 weeks or assigned to receive treatment as usual (usual clinical care by their treating neurologist). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A primary objective of this research is to explore whether a combined Cognitive Behaviour Therapy (CBT) and Cognitive Remediation program benefits psychosocial adjustment in patients with MS, assessed using the SF-36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 and 12 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A primary objective of this research is to explore whether a combined Cognitive Behaviour Therapy (CBT) and Cognitive Remediation program benefits learning in patients with MS, assessed using the CVLT-II and BVMT-R.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 and 12 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A primary objective of this research is to explore whether a combined Cognitive Behaviour Therapy (CBT) and Cognitive Remediation program benefits memory in patients with MS, assessed using the CVLT-II and BVMT-R.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 and 12 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary objective is to explore whether the program is associated with benefits to general cognition, assessed using the Minimal Assessment of Cognitive Function in Multiple Sclerosis (MACFIMS) battery. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 and 12 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary objective is to explore whether the program is associated with benefits to subjective cognitive impairment, assessed using the MSNQ-P, MSNQ-I and Perceived Deficits Questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 and 12 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary objective is to explore whether the program is associated with benefits to physical impairments, assessed using the MSQLI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 and 12 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary objective is to explore whether the program is associated with benefits to coping strategies, assessed using the Psychological Vulnerability Scale and Ways of Coping Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 and 12 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary objective is to explore whether the program is associated with benefits to social and vocational support, assessed using the Work and Social Adjustment Scale and MOS Modified Social Support Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 and 12 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary objective is to explore whether the program is associated with benefits to  neurological disability, as measured by the Expanded Disability Status Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 and 12 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary objective is to explore whether the program is associated with benefits to mental well-being, as measured by the Beck Depression Inventory-Fast Screen, Mental Health Inventory, and Perceived Stress Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 3 and 12 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patient diagnosed with MS according to McDonald criteria
2. Aged 18 years or over
3. EDSS score between 0  8
4. Be willing and able to comply with study requirements for the duration of the trial
5. Have provided informed consent prior to study participation
6. None of the exclusion criteria
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Have a diagnosis of another neurodegenerative disease
2. Currently receiving other research-based study treatments in any form (e.g. receiving group or individual CBT, ACT, cognitive remediation or cognitive training)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>One group receiving treatment. One group not receiving treatment. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Mixed ANOVAs will be used to test for differences between treatment and control groups on study measures. Sociodemographic characteristics will be described at baseline. Descriptive statistics will include number of participants (N), mean, standard deviation, minimum, maximum and if a non- normal distribution, the median and first/third quartiles will be reported.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>166</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Novartis Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Novartis Pharmaceuticals Australia
54 Waterloo Rd
Macquarie Park NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The COMBAT-MS study will determine the efficacy of a novel, world first management strategy for patients with MS involving combined cognitive remediation and cognitive behavioural therapy. The purpose of combining these techniques will be to create a novel holistic program that; (i) teaches individuals to engage in cognitively stimulating activities that aim to reduce the impact of and/or improve cognitive deficits, optimize day-to-day functioning, and have the capacity to build cognitive reserve and promote neuroplasticity, alongside techniques that; (ii) teach individuals to conceptualise problems as interactions between the person and environment. The COMBAT-MS study intervention will be delivered in a structured program over 3 months, with sustainability of effect tested to 12 months. Participants will be allocated to one of two groups: 1) a group that receives the study intervention, or 2) a group that does not receive the study intervention but receives standard clinical care as usual with their treating neurologist. All participants will be assessed at baseline, 3-month follow up and 12 month follow up. All participants will receive feedback on their results after each assessment. 

In the initial 12-18 months, we aim to determine whether this program has an impact on psychological factors (i.e. depression, anxiety, stress, coping, self-efficacy, health related quality of life and productivity) and aspects of cognitive functioning (i.e. memory, attention, speed of information processing, executive functions, visuospatial skills) contributing to adjustment. In a randomized controlled design, this will be achieved by administering standardised psychological and neuropsychological assessments pre and post intervention that have been shown to be sensitive in persons with MS. We also aim to determine whether the program is associated with secondary benefits to pharmacological treatment adherence and disease course (e.g. number of relapses; severity of physical symptoms).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committees - The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics and Research Integrity
Margaret Telfer Building (K07)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/12/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016/935</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/10/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Barnett</name>
      <address>Sydney Neurology
Brain &amp; Mind Centre, University of Sydney
Lvl 4, 94 Mallett Street,
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0730</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>combat-ms.study@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Caitlin Dawes</name>
      <address>MS Clinical Trials
Brain &amp; Mind Centre, University of Sydney,
Lvl 5, 94 Mallett Street,
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0750</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>combat-ms.study@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Keri Diamond</name>
      <address>Sydney Neurology
Brain &amp; Mind Centre, University of Sydney,
Lvl 4, 94 Mallett Street,
Camperdown NSW 2050
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0750</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>combat-ms.study@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Caitlin Dawes</name>
      <address>MS Clinical Trials
Brain &amp; Mind Centre, University of Sydney,
Lvl 5, 94 Mallett Street,
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 0750</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>combat-ms.study@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>