<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372063">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000080325p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Integrating specialist palliative care into residential care for older people: a stepped wedge trial (INSPIRED trial)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Integrating specialist palliative care into residential care for older people: a stepped wedge trial (INSPIRED trial)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>INSPIRED </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>ageing</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>dementia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dying</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Indirect support
1. Needs rounds. Needs rounds are monthly 60minute triage (and risk stratification) meetings, where up to ten residents with a short prognosis and high symptom burden are presented by facility staff to the specialist palliative care clinician. Residents do not attend needs rounds. Discussions focus on treatment/symptom management planned.  Case-based education is integrated into the needs round, with each residents bio-psycho-social status discussed to promote symptom management, and identify opportunities to extend and reinforce staff knowledge. The markers for a prognosis of six month or less, taken from the Palliative Approach toolkit (Parker &amp; Hughes 2010), are used to identify residents to be discussed in needs rounds:
a. Answering no to the question would you be surprised if the resident died within the next six months
b. Significant functional or medical decline
c. Conflict concerning whether goals of care should be curative or palliative in intent (e.g. after an acute event) 
d. If the resident is transferred or admitted to the facility specifically for comfort or palliative care 
Needs rounds frequently lead to initiating the other elements of the model. 

2. Case-based education for staff.  There are multiple opportunities for educating staff within the model that the specialist palliative care team engage in. Specifically, education may focus on communicating with residents, relatives and GPs, symptom management approaches, identifying deteriorating patients. Education will be provided at the monthly needs rounds to attending staff. This may include some didactic teaching as well as socratic method. All education will be based on the clinical cases presented during the Needs Rounds. Needs rounds last one hour, the education component may be around half of this time. 

3. Case conferences.  These meetings between facility staff, resident, relatives and relevant health care providers (including, but not limited to the GP, geriatrician, dementia services) and are facilitated by either the GP or facility staff. Case conferences are attended and facilitated by specialist palliative care staff at the beginning of the intervention to model how to conduct the meetings. As the facility staff gain confidence, they take over the chair function, and specialist palliative care are involved only when resident/family have complex physical, psychological or social needs. The agenda focuses on resident and/or family concerns, moving to discussion of how quality of life could be improved, goals of care (including discussion about hospitalization), and completion of an advance care plan.  Medications and care plan may be changed as a consequence of these discussions. The facility staff explain their capacity to achieve the goals which have been described. Case conferences will be organised on an 'as required' basis, as identified in the needs rounds.. Typically, they last one hour. Often only one case conference will be required per resident. 

Direct support
4. Clinical work with relevant residents.  Both needs rounds and case-conferences may lead to referrals for direct specialist palliative care clinical work with residents. Clinical referrals may also arise from other residents who have not been discussed in needs rounds or case conferences. Direct clinical work involves: symptom assessment, diagnosis, symptom management.  At times, direct clinical work with residents also included Chairing case-conferences. However, as the model proposes that these are primarily driven and led by the facilities, they are primarily conceptualised as indirect care.  Only the most complex case-conferences are Chaired by the specialist palliative care team, for example where staff report that family conflict over goals of care requires specialist intervention to explain how symptoms and end of life can be supported. 


Duration of intervention will vary. Since this is a stepped wedge design, some facilities will receive the intervention for 13 months, and the last facilities to join the study will receive it for four months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care: Usual care involves access to the specialist palliative care teams two nurses who work in residential aged care. Their role includes elements 3&amp;4 of the model described above. Critically though there is no embedded triage element in the form of the needs rounds and limited case-based education for staff. Essentially, the current model of care (usual care) is reactive, whereas the trial intervention is proactive and anticipatory. 

This is a stepped wedge design, so the length of control period varies for sites throughout the trial. The minimum control period (for sites randomised to receive the intervention first) will be  2 months. The maximum control period will be 10 months for sites receiving the intervention last. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of hospitalisation for residents. This will be measured in days and determined via review of hospital records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Prospectively throughout the control and intervention period. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Preferred place of death will be measured by recording recorded preference and actual place of death. Data will be drawn from the facility's medical records for the resident. Data will be recorded as a binary of yes/no, regarding whether preferred place of death was achieved. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prospectively throughout control and intervention period, following the death of any resident. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A 9-item questionnaire measuring staff death literacy and knowledge will be used (the PEPA questionniare). This paper-based questionniare will be administered to staff at facilities. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prospectively throughout the intervention period, This will be conducted monthly at the needs rounds meetings.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Family views on care will be collected using the Brief Assessment Scale for Caregivers (BASC) of the Medically Ill.  This paper-based questionnaire will be given to families to complete. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prospectively at baseline, end of control and at the end of the intervention period. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Death (using the QODD, Curtis et al. 2002, Curtis et al. 2013). This is a paper-based questionnaire, which staff will be trained to complete </outcome>
      <timepoint>Prospectively throughout control and intervention period, completed following the death of any resident. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria for facilities in the trial:
1. Residential facility operating in the Australian Capital Territory from January 2017-December 2018. 
2. Senior management agreement to access residents records.
3. Staff working at the collaborating facilities who are registered nurses or assistants in nursing (notwithstanding the important role of the whole multi-disciplinary team, these are the staff groups who provide most direct care).
4. Residents whose data is collected must have the facility as their main residence (thereby excluding those on respite stay).

Inclusion criteria for staff completing outcome measures
1. Staff who by virtue of their role, are invited to Needs Rounds meetings. This will include: team leaders, registered nurses, enrolled nurses, site managers, and some carers. 
2. Over 18 and willing/able to give informed consent.

Inclusion criteria for relatives completing outcome measures
1. Relative of a resident in one of the participating facilities.
2. Over 18 and willing/able to give informed consent.


Inclusion criteria for the process evaluation:
Recruitment for the process evaluation will proceed through sampling of residents or relatives whose care was considerably shaped and changed by the palliative care team. Five staff, patients or relatives will be recruited per site. Inclusion criteria are:
*Resident able to provide informed consent, as assessed by the clinician, using the mini-mental state examination, cut-off score of 20 (Pachet et al. 2010) to inform eligibility. 
*Relative or enduring power of attorney of a resident, able to provide informed consent.
*The resident must have had their clinical care discussed at a needs round. 
*Care of the resident was considerably shaped and changed, operationalised as the provision of staff education (for example on death, dying, setting goals of care), or providing advice on symptom management. 

Process evaluation will also include data collection from facility staff. Building on data collected in the pilot work, senior staff within the facility will be identified for individual interviews to identify the impact of the intervention on their staff and working practices. Inclusion criteria are:
*Care managers, educators or general managers who have attended needs rounds.
*Willing and able to give informed consent.
*Aged 18 or over.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Stepped wedge</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Given the intrinsic limitation of the study with a high level of turnover for both staff and residents, that staff and patients in each step at each site are to be considered as independent groups. Hence, the comparison on the primary outcome, namely the length of hospitalisation, between the intervention and control phases will adopt an independent two-group comparison approach  for the overall intervention effect. Based on the underlying distribution of the outcome measure, an appropriate comparison technique will be applied parametrically or non-pararmetrically. A similar approach will also be adopted for the analyses of secondary outcomes. 

Economic analysis of anticipated cost savings will be derived from cost per bed day in local acute hospitals, comparing the control and intervention time periods. 

Qualitative data will be analysed adopting a five-stage process of familiarisation: identifying a thematic framework, indexing the data, synthesising across respondents and data interpretation to form key themes (Braun &amp; Clarke 2006). A more fine-grained approach to analyzing data from patients may be adopted, for example conversation or discourse analysis which has been used to positive effect with adults with cognitive impairment (Pierce et al. 2015). 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>28/02/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>720</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/10/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Catholic University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Antill Street, Watson,
Canberra, 
2600, Australian Capital Territory</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Calvary Public Hosptial, Canberra</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Mary Potter Circuit, Bruce, ACT, 2617</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Catholic University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Antill Street, Watson, Canberra, ACT, 2600</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Calvary Public Hospital, Bruce</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Calvary Public Hospital
Mary Potter Circuit
Canberra, 
Australian Capital Territory, 2617</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to address core goals of the National Palliative Care Strategy, by integrating specialist palliative care into aged care. The intervention is a new model of care: whereby specialist palliative care nurses will help facilities prioritise residents who have palliative care needs. The prioritisation will occur through needs rounds which are staff-only meetings to discuss residents who may die in the next six months. Education to staff will also be provided. 
Following pilot work in 2014-5, this stepped wedge trial will seek to establish whether a new model of care will:
1. reduce length of stay in hospital, leading to significant cost savings
2. improve residents ability to die in their preferred place
3. improve care staff understanding of death and dying, and staff capacity
4. reduce symptom burden at end of life
5. reduces relatives' distress.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Calvary Public Hospital Bruce</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Calvary Public Hospital Bruce
Mary Potter Circuit,
Canberra
ACT, 2617</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACT Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Canberra hospital
Yamba Drive
Canberra
ACT, 2605</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Liz Forbat</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University
Antill Street
Watson
Canberra
ACT, 2600</address>
      <phone>+61 475978476</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Elizabeth.Forbat@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Liz Forbat</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University
Antill Street
Watson
Canberra
ACT, 2600</address>
      <phone>+61 4 7597 8476</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Elizabeth.Forbat@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Liz Forbat</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University
Antill Street
Watson
Canberra
ACT, 2600</address>
      <phone>+61 4 7597 8476</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Elizabeth.Forbat@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Liz Forbat</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University
Antill Street
Watson
Canberra
ACT, 2600</address>
      <phone>+61 4 7597 8476</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Elizabeth.Forbat@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>