<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373649">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/09/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001338358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical outcomes of the pressure cast technique to create low-cost prosthetic sockets for Vietnamese participants with below knee amputations</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Clinical evaluation of a hydrocast technique for transtibial socket fit in Vietnamese participants with below knee amputations</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Transtibial amputation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention Name: Pressure cast (PCAST) Prosthetic Socket
This study was conducted at the Vietnamese Training Centre for Orthopaedic Technologists (VIETCOT) clinic in Hanoi, Vietnam. VIETCOT staff with International Society for Prosthetics and Orthotics (ISPO) category II qualifications cast, fabricated and fitted the PCAST sockets. Briefly, the PCAST technique involved wrapping participants residual limb, wearing a cotton sock, in plaster wrap uniformly; followed by placement of the limb into the PCAST tank (made of polyvinyl chloride) filled with water, separated from the limb by a polyethelene diaphragm. The water pressure was increased until the participants could stand with 50% of their weight supported by the pressurised water. Once the plaster wrap hardened, the tank was depressurised and the plaster removed. No rectifications to the positive socket mould based on the plaster wrap were performed with the exception of the smoothing of obvious rough edges. The hard socket was manufactured using standard International Committee of the Red Cross (ICRC) techniques using ICRC polypropylene technology. The casting and initial fitting of the prosthetic socket took approximately 2 hours. The socket was manufactured once, after which the participants completed a usage period of approximately 5 months. During this time they were under no obligation to use the prosthesis and could replace it with their original prosthesis at any time. There were no strategies to monitor adherence to the study or use of the socket until the participants self-reported use when they returned after the extensive usage period </interventions>
    <comparator>The clinical outcomes of the participants were initially assessed using their current or original limb. This data was used to compare the relative outcomes of the intervention socket (the PCAST socket).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Six-minute-walk-test  (distance a participant is able to walk in a 6 minute window)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before receiving PCAST limb (with current limb), 15 minutes after receiving PCAST limb, and approximately 5 months after receiving PCAST limb. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Timed-up-and-go Test (the time a participant takes to rise from a chair, walk three meters, turn around, walk back to the chair, and sit down).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before receiving PCAST limb (with current limb), 15 minutes after receiving PCAST limb, and approximately 5 months after receiving PCAST limb. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spatio-temporal gait data (the participant walks over an instrumented 4.57 m walkway (Gaitrite).  Spatio-temporal gait data is a composite outcome and data collected included speed, cadence, step length, stride length, support base, swing time, stance time and single and double support times. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Before receiving PCAST limb (with current limb), 15 minutes after receiving PCAST limb, and approximately 5 months after receiving PCAST limb. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with Prosthesis questionnaire (SATPRO). Validated survey (composite outcome) with 19 survey items to evaluate the most significant criteria used by the person when selecting a technical aid. Includes factors relating to comfort, ease of use and aesthetics.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before receiving PCAST limb (with current limb), 15 minutes after receiving PCAST limb, and approximately 5 months after receiving PCAST limb. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Socket Comfort Score (SCS). Validated survey instrument to determine the users perceived socket comfort. Participants rated the comfort of their socket on a 010 scale where 0 represented the most uncomfortable and 10 the most comfortable sockets imaginable</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before receiving PCAST limb (with current limb), 15 minutes after receiving PCAST limb, and approximately 5 months after receiving PCAST limb. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pressure profile at the interface of the socket and participants residual limb. The pressure data was collected using the F-socket residual limb/socket interface pressure measurement system (Tekscan Inc., USA). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Before receiving PCAST limb (with current limb), 15 minutes after receiving PCAST limb, and approximately 5 months after receiving PCAST limb. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligibility for the study dictated that participants were 18 years or older, active wearers and long-term users of their prosthesis.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Significant co-morbidities which affect their ability to provide quality feedback comparing their previous prostheses to that of the PCAST or complete the physical function tests. In addition, they will require minimal physiotherapy or gait training prior to limb use or require walking aids additional to a prosthetic limb (e.g. canes or walkers). </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptive statistics were calculated. Data sets were assessed for normality by measures of skewness and kurtosis. Repeated measures multivariate analyses of variance (RM MANOVA) with contrast testing (two-tailed) were used to compare original and PCAST (pre) data, collected after 15 minutes of a familiarisation, and PCAST (post) data, collected following a usage-period of about 5 months. Three separate RM MANOVAs were conducted on the 1) physical function and SATPRO data, 2) spatial gait data and 3) temporal gait data. Statistical calculations were performed with SPSS (version 17) with the alpha level set at 0.05. Effect sizes were calculated using Cohens d for all comparisons with p &lt; 0.05. The pressure magnitude data exhibited high right skewness and the location data distribution was non-parametric. As such, Mann-Whitey U tests were used to compare the HighSCS and LowSCS group pressure data, with the effect size calculated using the Glass rank-biserial correlation, r.

It was planned that a total of 50 subjects would participant in the study. However, it would be conducted in three phases consisting of 15, 15 and 20 subjects respectively. By conducting the project in phases, there are opportunities for phase two and three to be improved on depending on the results of the preceding phases. In a study of similar aims, Hafner et al.  performed tests to determine the evaluation of function, performance and patient preference as transfemoral amputees transition from one lower-limb prostheses to another. Hafner performed these tests on 17 subjects with significant power, thus 15-20 subjects was deemed appropriate for the current study. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>4/04/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>16/02/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>49</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>17/02/2012</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Viet Nam</country>
      <state>Ha noi</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Grattan St, Parkville VIC 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>CASS Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress> 2/111 Collins St, Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Rotary Club of Richmond</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 138 Richmond Vic 3121</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>RMIT</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Plenty Rd, Bundoora VIC 3083</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Jim Lavranos</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The Royal Melbourne Hospital, 300 Grattan St, Parkville VIC 3050</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The most important part of the artificial limb is the socket, which forms the interface between the amputees residual limb and prostheses. The design and fitting of the socket is a difficult task due to the uniqueness of each amputees residual limb. Every fitting requires much attention from the prosthetist. Although there exists some guidelines to design and fit sockets for different levels of amputation, a successful fitting is still highly dependent on the skill and experience of the prosthetist. The purpose of this study is to examine the comfort of a socket made by an new technique known as pressure casting (PCAST).  The aim of this study is to examine the comfort and function of the PCAST socket. This will be done by measuring the walking pattern and level of mobility with the PCAS Tlimb and the pressure between the residual limb and the PCAST socket during walking. Walking patterns and pressures will be recorded by high-tech state of the art non-invasive measurement systems located at the Vietnamese Training Centre for Orthopaedic Technologists (VIETCOT) in Hanoi. A total of 50 people will participate in this study. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Lee PV, Lythgo N, Laing S, Lavranos J, Thanh NH. Pressure casting technique for transtibial prosthetic socket fit in developing countries. J Rehabil Res Dev. 2014;51(1):101-10. 10.1682/JRRD.2012.10.0191</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Melbourne Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Grattan St, Parkville, VIC, 3010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/09/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1135565</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Labour and Social Affairs - Research Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>43 Tran Duy Hung, Trung Hoà, Cau Giay, Hà Noi, 123002, Vietnam</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/02/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>N/A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Viet Nam</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373649-ULSA ethics approval.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Vee Sin Lee</name>
      <address>The University of Melbourne, Grattan St, Parkville, VIC, 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83444426</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pvlee@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Vee Sin Lee</name>
      <address>The University of Melbourne, Grattan St, Parkville, VIC, 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83444426</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pvlee@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Vee Sin Lee</name>
      <address>The University of Melbourne, Grattan St, Parkville, VIC, 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 83444426</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pvlee@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Sheridan Laing</name>
      <address>The University of Melbourne, Grattan St, Parkville, VIC, 3010</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>laings@pgrad.unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>