<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308092">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/06/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/06/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000506291</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Midazolam Nasal Spray for the treatment of breathlessness in patients with life-limiting disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Intranasal midazolam for the palliation of dyspnoea in patients with optimally treated life limiting disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dyspnoea (Breathlessness)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Conditions of unknown or disputed aetiology (such as chronic fatigue syndrome/myalgic encephalomyelitis)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intra-nasal midazolam. Each participant will receive six identical spray bottles, three will contain midazolam, and three citric acid in Normal saline. The six nasal spray bottles will be numbered 1-6 and will contain either midazolam or placebo (Citric acid in Normal saline) in a random sequence. Participants will be instructed to use a total of 3 inhalations (total dose of 1.5mg active drug) no more frequently than every 4 hours. This dose is administered as 1 spray in alternating nostrils for 3 administrations.
Participants will be asked to use a study nasal spray(SNS) as their first rescue dose for dyspnoea on any day that they require a rescue dose (starting no earlier than 0600hrs), taking number 1 SNS on the first day, number 2 on the second day, number 3 on the third etc, provided no SNS has been used for 4 hours prior, or breakthrough pain medication within 6 hours.  If patients do not experience dyspnoea, they are not required to use a SNS that day.
Only the first dose each day will be formally assessed, but participants can continue to use the SNS throughout the day (no more frequently than every 4 hours) if they find it useful.   All SNS must be used within 14 days.  Washout is at least 6 hours.</interventions>
    <comparator>Citric acid 7.65mg/ml  in Normal saline placebo nasal spray.  Each participant will receive six identical spray bottles, three will contain midazolam, and three citric acid in Normal saline. The six nasal spray bottles will be numbered 1-6 and will contain either midazolam or placebo (Citric acid in Normal saline) in a random sequence. Participants will be instructed to use a total of 3 inhalations (total dose of 2.295mg citric acid) no more frequently than every 4 hours. This dose is administered as 1 spray in alternating nostrils for 3 administrations.
Participants will be asked to use a study nasal spray(SNS) as their first rescue dose for dyspnoea on any day that they require a rescue dose (starting no earlier than 0600hrs), taking number 1 SNS on the first day, number 2 on the second day, number 3 on the third etc, provided no SNS has been used for 4 hours prior, or breakthrough pain medication within 6 hours.  If patients do not experience dyspnoea, they are not required to use a SNS that day.
Only the first dose each day will be formally assessed, but participants can continue to use the SNS throughout the day (no more frequently than every 4 hours) if they find it useful.   All SNS must be used within 14 days.  Washout is at least 6 hours.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome is dyspnoea intensity difference (DID) between active drug and placebo, measured by recording dyspnoea score on an 11-point Numerical Rating Scale (NRS) anchored at 0 = no breathlessness to 10 = worst possible breathlessness.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary end point will be the mean of the dyspnoea intensity difference (DID) at 15 minutes after each dose, compared to baseline (DID15-DID0)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DID at 5, 30 and 60 mins, measured by recording dyspnoea score on an 11-point Numerical Rating Scale (NRS) anchored at 0 = no breathlessness to 10 = worst possible breathlessness.</outcome>
      <timepoint>DID at 5, 30 and 60 mins following the first dose of SNS each day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>sedation (using difference in mean NRS score of placebo compared to midazolam)on 11-point NRS anchored at 0= not at all drowsy to 10= extremely drowsy</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 5, 15, 30 and 60 mins following the first dose of SNS each day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>anxiety scored on an 11-point NRS anchored at 0= not at all anxious to 10= extremely anxious</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 5, 15, 30 and 60 mins following the first dose of SNS each day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General impression of benefit - scored in patient diary on 5-point scale where 0=no benefit to 4=excellent benefit</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily when study spray used</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain scored on an 11-point NRS where Pain right now is scored using a NRS anchored at 0= no pain to 10= worst possible pain</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 5, 15, 30 and 60 mins following the first dose of SNS each day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants must:
be at least 18 years of age
have dyspnoea related to life-limiting disease or its treatment
have a dyspnoea score &gt;3/10 on at least 3 occasions during the previous week
be English speaking or have an interpreter available 
have an adequate performance status Australian Karnofsky Performance Scale (AKPS &gt;30)
be able to operate a nasal spray device 
be able to understand all trial requirements and complete a dyspnoea diary
have had no changes in any medication likely to affect dyspnoea (eg steroids, opioids) within 48 hours of starting the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be excluded in the case of: 
an acute respiratory event likely to resolve eg. chest infection, acute exacerbation of asthma
concurrent treatment with an unstable dose of benzodiazepines (excluding nocturnal sedation)
concurrent treatment with an unstable dose of opioids (change in baseline dose within 48 hours of study entry or during the duration of the study) 
regular use (greater than 3 times/day) of breakthrough opioids for pain or dyspnoea that would interfere with assessment of benefit of the midazolam spray 
a previous adverse reaction to benzodiazepines
concurrent treatment with itraconazole or ketoconazole 
respiratory depression (resting respiratory rate (RR) &lt;10 breaths/minute) 
co-morbid myasthenia gravis, or acute narrow angle glaucoma 
an alcohol and/or drug dependency problem
any intervention or change in therapy likely to effect dyspnoea during the study period or in the 2 weeks prior (this includes radiotherapy to the lung and/or chemotherapy or blood transfusion 72 hours prior with the potential to effect dyspnoea )
any change in oxygen prescription during the study period</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients with dyspnoea related to life-limiting disease or its treatment with an average dyspnoea score of greater than or equal to 3/10 on a dyspnoea screening scale (0 = no breathlessness, 10 = worst possible breathlessness) on at least 3 occasions during the previous week, despite optimal treatment of the underlying cause. This will include both malignant and non-malignant disease. Potentially eligible patients will be screened by research staff. Those that are eligible and provide written consent will be given six SNS numbered 1 to 6 in randomised order and written instructions on how to use the sprays. Research staff will ensure that the patient fully understands the patient information sheet and trial requirements.  Computer generated pseudo-random numbers will be generated and used to allocate patients to one of 20 sequencesof the 6 SNSs.  The randomization codes will be sent to the pharmacy to be dispensed.  In addition, randomization codes will be printed and sealed in opaque envelopes and left in the ward in case of emergency.</concealment>
    <sequence>All possible combinations of 3 midazolam, 3 placebo SNS will be included.  Computer generated pseudo-random numbers will be generated and used to allocate patients to one of 20 sequencesof the 6 SNSs. Randomisation codes will be split equally between the 2 central coordinating centers (Arohanui Hospice and the Mater Hospital).  Individual patient SNS allocation will be the responsibility of the dispensing pharmacist.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4101</postcode>
    <postcode>4215</postcode>
    <postcode>4169</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Manawatu</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Arohanui Hospice Service Trust, Clare Randall as representative</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1 Heretaunga St
Palmerston North 4414</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Arohanui Hospice Service Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 Heretaunga St
Palmerston North 4414</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Society of NZ (Central Districts &amp; Wellington branches)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Palmerston North Hospital Medical Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Palmerston North Hospital</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Mater Adult Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Raymond Tce
South Brisbane, Queensland
Australia 4101</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Dyspnoea, defined as an uncomfortable sensation of breathing (which is often reported by patients as breathlessness), is a common symptom affecting up to 80% of cancer patients and 95% of patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD).  Nearly half of all patients requiring palliative care report breathlessness as a problem during the last year of life.    Moreover, dyspnoea is consistently high-lighted as a poor prognostic factor and harbinger of impending death. Ventilatory drive is the net result of complex automatic and subconscious, peripheral and central, neural and chemical mechanisms.  Dyspnoea is the conscious perception which has taken account of the net result of those mechanisms and integrated it with other cognitive and emotive factors that are also affecting the individual.  Dyspnoea is thus a subjective symptom that is debilitating to patients, impacting greatly on quality of life of both patient and carer.   It is a challenging symptom to manage and is often impossible to reverse despite maximal treatment of the underlying cause.  Anxiety is often reported by patients as a major component of breathlessness with breathlessness leading to anxiety and anxiety exacerbating breathlessness leading to a progressive spiral of cause and effect.   
Hypothesis : Intranasal midazolam is superior to placebo for the palliation of dyspnoea in patients with optimally treated life limiting disease</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Multi-Region Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>2nd Floor, 1-3 The Terrace
P O Box 5013, Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/07/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mater Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Rm 235 Level 2
Aubigny Place
Raymond Tce
South Brisbane
QLD 4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/06/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clare Randall</name>
      <address>Arohanui Hospice
1 Heretaunga St
Palmerston North 4414</address>
      <phone>+64 6 3566606</phone>
      <fax>+ 64 6 3566631</fax>
      <email>clare.r@arohanuihospice.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clare Randall</name>
      <address>Arohanui Hospice
1 Heretaunga St
Palmerston North 4414</address>
      <phone>+64 6 3566606</phone>
      <fax>+64 6 3566631</fax>
      <email>clare.r@arohanuihospice.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Clare Randall</name>
      <address>Arohanui Hospice
1 Heretaunga St
Palmerston North 4414</address>
      <phone>+ 64 6 3566606</phone>
      <fax>+64 6 3566631</fax>
      <email>clare.r@arohanuihospice.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>