<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362921">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000052730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Perineal pain after natural childbirth with episiotomy: the measurement, characterization and effects of cryotherapy.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of cryotherapy in perineal pain after childbirth with episiotomy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1130-1760</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Effects of cryotherapy in perineal pain after childbirth with episiotomy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Childbirth and postnatal care</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We conducted a pilot study for the improvement of the instruments of the study and especially the technique of cryotherapy.
Initially elected to ice packs in the conventional model used in clinical practice, consisting of a sleeve with ice cubes. However, it was noted that this technique does not adapt the perineal region, which has a somewhat irregular anatomy. Furthermore, latex glove propitiated not sufficient cooling for the woman referring significant improvement in pain.
Thus, it was thought at first grind the ice, so that it could mold the genital area of women. Subsequently, we investigated whether any material that could simulate the size of an absorbent and to serve as a pocket for placing the ice. The researchers contacted a manufacturer of plastic products and these have produced a small bag with dimensions of 8 cm wide and 30 cm long, inexpensive.
To protect the skin against possible burns patient's test was performed with the tubular mesh, material used for this protection members receiving compressive bandaging for lymphedema, made of cotton material.
After the refinement of instruments and technique of cryotherapy began the study. The women should be at least 6 hours postpartum and at most 24 hours. Were divided into two study groups: a control and an experimental. In the latter, women received cryotherapy technique.
The cryotherapy technique used consisted of a plastic bag in the form of an absorbent containing crushed ice, applied for 20 minutes. Three evaluations were performed in both groups: initial assessment was questioned where the intensity of pain on a numerical scale and the questionnaire McGill; review two: performed 20 minutes after the initial assessment, whereas the experimental group was performed after cryotherapy; review Three: performed after an hour of the second review.</interventions>
    <comparator>No treatment</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In the pilot study we used the value 2 as clinically relevant improvement demonstrated by Numerica Compartmentalized Scale in 11 points (0 being no pain and 10 the worst pain possible). For the analysis of the final study data was used this same parameter.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before application of cryotherapy, shortly after the withdrawal of cryotherapy and one hour after cryotherapy</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure the temperature of the perineal region through infrared thermometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before cryotherapy, during (at 10 minutes of application), after the withdrawal and an hour after the utilization of the resource.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>An evaluation was performed on all mothers on the functional activities limited by pain, such as walking, sitting, urinating, defecating, eating and layind down. The puerperal should answer yes or no.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The puerperae had limited functions when sitting, laying down, and walking before application of cryotherapy.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A questionnaire was applied to obtain the womens opinion about the therapy with the following issues:
- therapy was comfortable or uncomfortable
- would you use cryotherapy again after another birth
- you were satisfied with the treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>95% of women reported that therapy was comfortable and the same percentage said it would use cryotherapy again. 
87.5% reported being satisfied with the resource and 12.5% reported being much satisfied. This assessment was made one hour after cryotherapy. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Primiparous with low-risk pregnancy, literate; oriented in postpartum normal; undergoing episiotomy with episiorrhaphy; complaining of pain at the episiorrhaphy; absence of diagnostic genitourinary pathology, not referring allergy caused by cold .</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Were excluded mothers who presented beyond the episiotomy, spontaneous laceration grade I in perituretral region.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Block randomization technique being used www.randomization.com. Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>One group received treatment and another group no received, (control group).</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/06/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/06/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/02/2008</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>28/03/2008</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ana Carolina Sartorato Beleza</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Avenida Almirante Cochrane, 158. 
Bairro Aparecida. 
Cep 11040-000. Santos-SP.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Nursing School of Ribeirao Preto, University of Sao Paulo</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Avenida dos Bandeirantes, 3900 
Campus Universitario - Bairro Monte Alegre 
Ribeirao Preto - SP 
CEP: 14040-902</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ana Marcia Spano Nakano</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Avenida dos Bandeirantes, 3900 
Campus Universitario - Bairro Monte Alegre 
Ribeirao Preto - SP - Brasil 
CEP: 14040-902</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>CENTER FOR WOMEN'S HEALTH REFERENCE OF RIBEIRAO PRETO - MATER</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Av. Wanderley Taffo, n. 330 
Bairro Quintino Facci II 
CEP 14070-250  Ribeirao Preto-SP</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Brazil</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study had the purpose to: assess the effect of cryotherapy in providing pain relief of the perinal region of primiparae submitted to natural childbirth with episiotomy using a one-dimensional pain instrument; characterize perineal pain using a multidimensional pain assessment tool, verify what activities performed by the puerperae in the maternity were limited due to the presence of pain; verify the effect of cryotherapy in relieving pain immediately after it application, and one hour later; verify the temperature of the perineal region before, during, and after cryotherapy, and the correlation with the intensity of pain, verify the possible adverse effects caused by cryotherapy; and verify the puerperaes opinion about the treatment. This is a controlled and random clinical trial carried out in a maternity in the interior of Sao Paulo state. Fifty primiparae with perineal pain after vaginal delivery with episiotomy were randomly selected and 26 were assigned to the control group and 24 to the experimental group. A form was used to collect socio-demographic data, as well as information about care during the delivery and regarding the newborn; an 11-point numerical scale and descriptors from the McGill questionnaire were used to assess the pain. In addition, a form was used to assess the functional activities performed by the puerperae that were limited due to the pain. Finally, a questionnaire was applied to obtain the womens opinion about the therapy. The cryotherapy technique used consisted of a plastic bag in the shape of an absorbent pad, containing ground ice, which was applied for 20 minutes. Three assessments were performed in both groups: an initial assessment, in which the women were asked about the intensity of the pain using the numerical scale and by administering the McGill questionnaire. The second assessment was performed 20 minutes after the first, and in the experimental group it was performed after the cryotherapy. It was verified there was pain relief in the experimental group compared to control in the second and third assessment (p=0.000). On the other hand, the women reported feeling pain again in the third assessment. The puerperae from both groups had limited functions when sitting, laying down, and walking. The puerperae characterized the perineal pain as pulsing, pulling, hot, stinging, hurting, annoying, troublesome, tight and tense.  The average perineal temperature before cryotherapy was 34.5 degrees C, dropping to 23.4 degrees  C after the technique. One hour after the treatment, the average lowered to 33.7 degrees  C. There was a positive correlation between the intensity of pain and the changes in perineal temperature. As for the womens satisfaction toward the cryotherapy, 87.5% reported being satisfied with the resource and 12.5% reported being much satisfied. Cryotherapy was effective in relieving perineal pain, however further studies are needed in order to elucidate issues like time of symptom relief, interval time between applications, and the effects over other signs and symptoms of the inflammatory process.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.teses.usp.br/teses/disponiveis/22/22133/tde-06102008-144024/pt-br.php</trialwebsite>
    <publication>- 16th International WCPT Congress (2011). 
THE EFFECT OF CRYOTHERAPY IN PERINEAL PAIN AFTER VAGINAL CHILDBIRTH WITH EPISIOTOMY</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the Nursing School of Ribeirao Preto, University of Sao Paulo</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Avenida dos Bandeirantes, 3900 
Campus Universitario - Bairro Monte Alegre 
Ribeirao Preto - SP  
CEP: 14040-902</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/04/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0761/2007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/02/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ana Carolina Sartorato Beleza</name>
      <address>Avenida Almirante Cochrane 158, ap 42. 
Bairro Aparecida. 
Cep 11040-000 - Santos-SP</address>
      <phone>+55 13 33490054</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>acbeleza@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ana Carolina Sartorato Beleza</name>
      <address>Avenida Almirante Cochrane 158, ap 42. 
Bairro Aparecida. 
Cep 11040-000 - Santos-SP</address>
      <phone>+55 13 33490054</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>acbeleza@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ana Carolina Sartorato Beleza</name>
      <address>Avenida Almirante Cochrane 158, ap 42. 
Bairro Aparecida. 
Cep 11040-000 - Santos-SP</address>
      <phone>+55 13 33490054</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>acbeleza@gmail.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ana Carolina Sartorato Beleza</name>
      <address>Avenida Almirante Cochrane, 158. Ap 42. 
Cep 11040-000. Santos-SP. Brazil</address>
      <phone>+55 13 33490054</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>acbeleza@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>