<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336228">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/11/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000996066</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exercise-induced improvement in insulin levels is maintained in obese youth independently of changes in fat mass</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Structured exercise can improve insulin levels in obese youth and can be maintained without changes in fat mass</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1117-9183</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>non applicable</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Insulin resistance</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants were enrolled in an exercise program that involved one hour of supervised mixed aerobic and resistance training three times a week.
Each training session consisted of individually prescribed cycle ergometer and resistance training, the latter performed at low intensity on weight-stack machines (Pulsestar, UK).  Cycle ergometry was initially maintained at 65% of maximum heart rate (HR), with progression to 85% by week 2/3.  Resistance training (12 repetitions/minute) was initially maintained at 55% of pre-training maximum voluntary contraction, and progressed to 70% by week 2/3.  Subjects completed 2 sets of this circuit at each of the three weekly visits to the gymnasium for 8 weeks.  Inclusive of the 10 min warm-up and cool down periods, each exercise training session lasted approximately 60 minutes.  All group exercise sessions were supervised by the same experienced Exercise Physiologists, with a maximum subject to staff ratio of 6:1.  Exercise training intensity (HR and weights lifted) was maintained within the target zones by intermittent checking undertaken in all subjects throughout each session.</interventions>
    <comparator>We compared three 8 week periods: (1) normal activity before exercise (control period), (2) exercise training and (3) normal activity post exercise.
Subjects participated in the program for 16 weeks. They were randomised to either 8 weeks of normal activity, followed by 8 weeks of exercise, or alternatively, 8 weeks of exercise followed by 8 weeks of return to normal activity. For each subject outcome measures were assessed at 2 consecutive time points 8 weeks apart. This allowed us to obtain data at the following time points: start of the study (timepoint 1, 0 weeks), end of period of normal activity/start of exercise (timepoint 2, 8 weeks), end of exercise (timepoint 3, 16 weeks), end of normal activity post exercise (timepoint 4, 24 weeks). In each subject outcome measurements were restricted to two timepoints to minimise the number of invasive procedures in children.
The resulting periods for analysis were named as follows:
1.	Control period:  normal activity during study weeks 0 to 8 
2.	Exercise period: exercise training during study weeks 8 to 16 
3.	Post exercise period:  normal activity during study weeks 16 to 24.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oral glucose tolerance tests (OGTT) with insulin levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>Start and end of each 8 week period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>cardiovascular and fitness measures</outcome>
      <timepoint>Start and end of each 8 week period, assessed by Multi-Stage Fitness test.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>body composition (DXA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Start and end of each 8 week period, assessed using a DXA scan.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>height and weight.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Start and end of each 8 week period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Obese children and adolescents from the Endocrinology Clinic at Princess Margaret Hospital Perth, WA , Australia</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not matching the weight criteria according to Cole et al. (Cole TJ, Bellizzi MC, Flegal KM, Dietz WH. Establishing a standard definition for child overweight and obesity worldwide: international survey. BMJ Clinical research ed 2000;320(7244):1240-3).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects participated in the program for 16 weeks. They were randomised by taking numbers from a sealed opaque envelope. Groups either started with 8 weeks of normal activity, followed by 8 weeks of exercise, or alternatively, 8 weeks of exercise followed by 8 weeks of return to normal activity. For each subject outcome measures were assessed at 2 consecutive time points 8 weeks apart. This allowed us to obtain data at the following time points: start of the study (timepoint 1, 0 weeks), end of period of normal activity/start of exercise (timepoint 2, 8 weeks), end of exercise (timepoint 3, 16 weeks), end of normal activity post exercise (timepoint 4, 24 weeks). In each subject outcome measurements were restricted to two timepoints to minimise the number of invasive procedures in children.
The resulting periods for analysis were named as follows:
1.	Control period:  normal activity during study weeks 0 to 8 
2.	Exercise period: exercise training during study weeks 8 to 16 
3.	Post exercise period:  normal activity during study weeks 16 to 24.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by taking numbers from a sealed opaque envelope.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Endocrinology and Diabetes
Roberts Road
Subiaco, Perth, WA 6008
Western Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Endocrinology and DiabetesRoberts Road
Subiaco, Perth, WA 6008
Western Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>German Society for Endocrinology</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Geschaeftsstelle der DGE
c/o EndoScience Endokrinologie Service GmbH
Mozartstr. 23
93128 Regenstauf</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Germany</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Being overweight is a major risk factor for diabetes. The main purpose of this study is to determine if exercise can reduce this risk for overweight children and adolescents.  
At entry to the study, participants will be required to complete a 7 day activity record and a 3 day diet history diary. The participant will then be assigned to either an exercise training group, or a control (non-exercise) group. The 8-week exercise program involves attending a gymnasium three days per week for approximately 1 hour each time. The exercise training regime will be fully structured and supervised by experienced exercise physiologists. If a child is initially in the control group, they will be asked to continue with their normal routine for a period of 8 weeks. 
At the beginning and at the end of each 8 week period subjects will have their blood pressure measured, and will have a test called a glucose tolerance test that involves the insertion of a small intravenous cannula for blood sampling. They will be asked to drink a sugary cola flavoured liquid and following this, blood samples for blood glucose levels, insulin and cardiovascular risk factors will be taken from the cannula. The test takes a total of 3 hours.
Other tests will include a special X-ray scan that determines body composition (fat mass and muscle mass) called a DXA scan. A DXA scan requires subjects to lie on their back on a scanning bed for 3-7 minutes and involves a low radiation dose (5% of a standard chest x-ray). This visit will take approximately 1 hour. 
Following the series of tests outlined above participants will be allocated to the alternate training group for a further 8 week period followed by a series of repeat tests which are identical to the tests outlined above. By comparing the repeat and initial tests, the effect of the training program on fitness, insulin levels and body composition will be determined.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children and Adolescent Health Service - Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Margaret Hospital for Children
Roberts Road
Subiaco, Perth, WA 6008
Western Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/05/2001</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>613EP</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Professor Aris Siafarikas</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital
Department of Endocrinology and Diabetes
Roberts Road
Subiaco, Perth, WA 6008
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61893408090</phone>
      <fax>+61893408605</fax>
      <email>Aris.Siafarikas@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Professor Aris Siafarikas</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital
Department of Endocrinology and Diabetes
Roberts Road
Subiaco, Perth, WA 6008
Western Australia</address>
      <phone>+61893408090</phone>
      <fax>+61893408605</fax>
      <email>Aris.Siafarikas@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>