<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369770">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/01/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000270415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Impact of a Berry Extract on Vascular Function</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomized, double blind, placebo controlled, crossover study to evaluate the effect of two doses of berry extract on vascular function in overweight adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Overweight</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A randomized three-­way cross­over design will be used to evaluate the acute and short term chronic effects of supplementation with two doses of a berry extract (250mg and 500mg powdered extract) versus a placebo. The berry extract is a concentrated and dried powder from a North American native berry with a final composition of polyphenols, chlorogenic acids, and fibre (cellulose, pectins, lignins, tannins). Thirty overweight adults will be recruited by public advertisements. Prior to the commencement of the study volunteers will complete a questionnaire designed to assess general health and eligibility, and will have their height and weight measured. They will consume each of the supplements (a single capsule each day) for 14 days with a minimum of one week ­long wash out period between each supplement period. Participants will complete a series of tests at the beginning and end of each 14­-day supplementation period (6 visits in total for the intervention). At each visit, participants will present to the clinic in the fasted state (10 to ­12 hr without food or drink other than water), and will complete a series of anthropometric (e.g. height, weight, waist circumference) and vascular health assessments (e.g. flow-­mediated dilatation (FMD), blood pressure and arterial stiffness), Participants will then consume a single supplement dose before undergoing a second FMD test at 1 hour post consumption (expected peak FMD change). This will determine the acute effects of berry supplementation on vascular health for each of the two doses as well as the chronic effect of 14 days supplementation at each dose compared to placebo. Each testing session is expected to take approximately 120 minutes. Compliance with the supplementation program will be monitored by participants completing a supplement consumption diary and returning their capsule container with any remaining capsules. Any remaining capsules will be counted to determine the number taken.

</interventions>
    <comparator>Coloured maltodextrin (1 capsule per day)</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Flow­-mediated dilation, measured using a two dimensional B-mode ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>The beginning and end of each 14­ day supplementation period (both fasted and 1hr following consumption of supplement).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure, measured using an oscillometric device</outcome>
      <timepoint>The beginning and end of each 14­ day supplementation period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arterial stiffness, measured using a Sphygmocor device</outcome>
      <timepoint>The beginning and end of each 14­ day supplementation period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cerebrovascular reactivity measured using transcranial doppler ultrasonography</outcome>
      <timepoint>The beginning and end of each 14­ day supplementation period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Men aged over 45 years of age and post­menopausal women.
2. BMI between 26.9 and 29.99
3. Blood pressure less than 140/90 mmHg
4. Able and willing to give informed consent and comply with all study protocol procedures.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. More than 150 min/week of moderate activity or more than 75 min/week of intense activity
2. Taking vasoactive medications (e.g. statins, aspirin, blood pressure lowering drugs) or food supplements (e.g. fish oil) 
3. Smoking
4. Weight loss of more than 10% body weight in the previous 6 months 
5. Currently treated with a diet for weight loss
6. Reported participation in another study within 1 month before the study start
7. Chronic­-acute disease, including any kind of metabolic abnormality or major cardiovascular risk factor or both.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Double-­blind randomisation. Supplement containers will be coded and labelled by a third­party and capsules are identical to ensure that all researchers and participants are blinded to active and control treatments.</concealment>
    <sequence>Via random number generator - third party</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Mixed models procedure to determine the effects of treatment and order on outcome variables

The primary outcome measure for this trial is flow-mediated dilatation. Due to the novelty of this particular investigation there is no direct evidence on which to determine the sample size required for sufficient statistical power to detect an effect. As such we have based our calculation on a recent study investigating the effects of red orange consumption on endothelial function due to similar total polyphenol and anthocyanin dosing to that proposed here (Buscemi et al 2012).

A total of 26 participants will be required for this three-way crossover study. The probability is 80 percent that the study will detect a treatment difference at a two-sided 0.05 significance level, if the true difference between treatments is 2.200 units. This is based on the assumption that the within-patient standard deviation of the response variable is 2.7. The proposed figure of 30 participants is to allow for possible participant attrition across the intervention.

Reference
Buscemi, S.; Rosafio, G.; Arcoleo, G.; Mattina, A.; Canino, B.; Montana, M.; Verga, S.; Rini, G., Effects of red orange juice intake on endothelial function and inflammatory markers in adult subjects with increased cardiovascular risk. The American journal of clinical nutrition 2012, 95, 1089-95.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>22/02/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Kade Davison</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Alliance for Research in Exercise, Nutrition and Activity
School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Naturex DBS LLC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 619
39 Pleasant St
Sagamore, MA 02561
USA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Alison Hill</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Alliance for Research in Exercise, Nutrition and Activity
School of Pharmacy &amp; Medical Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Lucy Fairlie-Jones</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Alliance for Research in Exercise, Nutrition and Activity
School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Polyphenols are bioactive compounds found in plants. These compounds have been found to have beneficial effects on vascular function. Arguably the most well-established vascular benefits are attributed to flavanols from cacao beans. Berry fruits are another rich source of polyphenols that have vasoactive properties, and there is a growing body of research exploring these effects in various berries (blueberries, cranberries, strawberries) and other fruit products with similar polyphenol composition. A key polyphenol in berries and other fruits believed to provide much of the benefit is anthocyanin. When given as an isolated extract 320mg anthocyanin has been found to improve blood vessel function both acutely and in response to chronic consumption over 12 weeks. 
Thus the primary focus of this project is to evaluate the effects of berry extracts of differing polyphenol dose on vascular endothelial function.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0000034662</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kade Davison</name>
      <address>Alliance for Research in Exercise, Nutrition and Activity
School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kade.davison@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kade Davison</name>
      <address>Alliance for Research in Exercise, Nutrition and Activity
School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kade.davison@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kade Davison</name>
      <address>Alliance for Research in Exercise, Nutrition and Activity
School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kade.davison@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kade Davison</name>
      <address>Alliance for Research in Exercise, Nutrition and Activity
School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471 Adelaide SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8302 1152</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kade.davison@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>