<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371997">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001726448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>PEARL - Program Enhancing Adjustment to Residential Living</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A cluster RCT of a novel psychological intervention to reduce depression among at-risk older adults transitioning to residential aged care</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1190-6752</utrn>
    <trialacronym>PEARL</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>'Nil Known'</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Quality of LIfe</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Adjustment</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Functional dependency</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>PEARL program is an intervention designed to enhance new residents to permanent aged care adjust to residential living.  It is designed to be suitable for the majority of depressed residents in residential aged care facilities (RACFs), including those with mild-moderate dementia. RACFs will be matched by organisation and facility size (number of permanent beds).  Matched RACFs will be randomly allocated to the intervention 'care as usual' plus PEARL intervention or ' care as usual' (control group) using a random number generator by a biostatistician who is not otherwise involved in the project and blind to the allocated condition.  Residents who are admitted to RACFs over a 24 month recruitment period will be referred to the study by the facility manager (or admission officer) and approached by a researcher for consent(directly or via next of kin as appropriate) and will be screened for eligibility within four weeks of their admission.  Participants in RACFs allocated to the intervention group will receive the PEARL program.  This intervention group is described as 'care as usual' plus PEARL intervention.
Depression is a serious issue in RACFs, affecting one third of older people, but current management approaches are inadequate.  Late life depression is associated with higher mortality and increased care needs.  The transition to a RACF is often highly traumatic and newly admitted residents are at an extreme risk of depression.  The transition period therefore represents an ideal opportunity for early intervention.  Currently, there are no interventions specifically targeting depressed aged care residents early in their admission to  RACFs.  The PEARL program addresses the key factors that facilitate adjustment to life in  RACFs.  They key factors include the resident's view or perception of the move, social support, self-efficacy, autonomy, perceived control and meaningful activity.  These factors are aligned with the framework and key constructs of Self-Determination Theory (SDT) of autonomy, relatedness and competence, and Ryff's theoretical model of late life adjustment where environmental mastery, autonomy and purpose in life have been confirmed as essential components of psychological wellbeing and healthy ageing and predict successful adjustment to  RACFs.
PEARL intervention uses SDT and behavior therapy framework to orient newly admitted residents to their environment and is designed to encourage collaboration with residents and staff to develop care approaches that enhance their purpose in life, autonomy and environmental mastery.
PEARL program is delivered over seven weeks and consists of three weekly 60 minute individual sessions with residents in a one-on-one format in the privacy of residents' own rooms plus two additional booster sessions provided two and four weeks after the final session to review and modify strategies.  Session 1 will focus on orientation to the aged care facility and social support.  Session 2 will focus on enhancing purpose in life through identification of residents' personal goals and values.  Session 3 will assist residents enhance their autonomy and environmental mastery through identification of daily choices important to them and the development of strategies to maintain or adapt their level of autonomy within the RACF environment.  The booster sessions will review the program and reinforce progress and assist residents address any concerns or problems.
PEARL is simple, brief, and adapted to the characteristics of each RACF and is tailored to each resident's needs, interests, aptitudes and background.  Strategies selected to meet resident's needs are behavioral in nature specifically tailored to each individual's level of cognitive function.
PEARL program will be delivered by three trained clinicians using a highly structured treatment manual.  Clinicians will have experience in RACFs settings, with a background in psychology, nursing, occupational therapy or social work.  Treatment fidelity will be monitored using a random review of audio-taped sessions (5% of total sessions, spread across the 5 sessions) with sessions coded for adherence to the intervention manual.  The clinicians will receive fortnightly individual clinical supervision with principle investigator during the first six month of the intervention period, thereafter reducing in frequency to meet their clinical needs.
RACF staff are actively involved in the implementation of PEARL intervention.  A recent meta-analysis found that psychological treatments for depression that involved RACF staff collaboration achieved better outcomes.  Thus, each session with a resident will be followed by a 30 minute consultation with a key staff member involved in their daily care and care plan development.  To ensure successful collaboration with RACF staff, a one hour training session will be provided to RACF staff as group sessions to introduce the program to as many staff as possible and establish rapport with the research team.  This training will incorporate key learning from the program.  In addition, clinicians will provide ongoing support and supervision to RACF staff to  assist them implement the selected strategies or modify individual care plans where necessary.
</interventions>
    <comparator>RACFs will be matched by organisation and facility size (number of permanent beds).  Matched RACFs will be randomly allocated to the intervention 'care as usual' plus PEARL intervention or ' care as usual' (control group) using a random number generator by a biostatistician who is not otherwise involved in the project and blind to the allocated condition.  Residents who are admitted to RACFs over a 24 month recruitment period will be referred to the study by the facility manager (or admission officer) and approached by a researcher for consent(directly or via next of kin as appropriate) and will be screened for eligibility within four weeks of their admission. Participants in RACFs allocated to the 'care as usual' (control) will not receive the PEARL program or any additional intervention.  Participants in both groups will continue to receive the usual care offered to RACF residents including pharmacotherapy, ad hoc support from staff, and standard activities. 'Usual care' in Australian RACFs does not typically include psychotherapy.  Changes in medications will be recorded and accounted for in our analyses.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Presence of current Major depressive disorder and persistent depressive disorder will be determined using the Structured Clinical interview SCID-5</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1: Base line - within 28 days of being admitted to RACFs
Time point 2:  8 weeks after T1
Time point 3:  16 weeks after T1
Time point 4:  29 weeks after T1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of Depressive symptom will be assessed using the Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1: Base line - within 28 days of being admitted to RACFs
Time point 2:  8 weeks after T1
Time point 3:  16 weeks after T1
Time point 4:  29 weeks after T1</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of Anxiety assessed using Geriatric Anxiety Inventory Pachana (2007) 20 item scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1: Base line - within 28 days of being admitted to RACFs
Time point 2:  8 weeks after T1
Time point 3:  16 weeks after T1
Time point 4:  29 weeks after T1</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life - life satisfaction, leisure and participation, satisfaction with living situation, satisfaction with family relations, social relations and general wellbeing assessed using Quality of Life-AD (QoL-AD) Edelman et al (2005) 15 items</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1: Base line - within 28 days of being admitted to RACFs
Time point 2:  8 weeks after T1
Time point 3:  16 weeks after T1
Time point 4:  29 weeks after T1</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Instrumental Activities of Daily Living Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1: Base line - within 28 days of being admitted to RACFs
Time point 2:  8 weeks after T1
Time point 3:  16 weeks after T1
Time point 4:  29 weeks after T1</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Index of Relocation Adjustment </outcome>
      <timepoint>Time point 1: Base line - within 28 days of being admitted to RACFs
Time point 2:  8 weeks after T1
Time point 3:  16 weeks after T1
Time point 4:  29 weeks after T1</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i) Older adults aged above 60 years 
(ii) newly admitted first permanent placement within 28 days of admission to permanent care within residential aged care facility
(iii) a score of above 6 on the Cornell Scale for Depression in Dementia - indicating the presence of depressive symptoms
(iv) a score above 15 on the Mini Mental Examination, based on NICE guidelines - indicative of mild to moderate cognitive impairment
(v) fluency in English</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) acute severe medical illness likely to compromise participation in the program
(ii) severe or moderately severe cognitive impairment (Mini Mental Examination score below 15, based on NICE guidelines)
(iii) non-fluency in English</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>central randomisation by computer by a biostatistician</concealment>
    <sequence>Facilities within each strata were allocated a random ID, using randomised list generator provided by random.org. The facilities were then sorted in ascending sequence by their random ID, within their respective strata. To ensure 1:1.3 allocation ratio, two allocation sequences were then created, one for each stratum. For the below 100 beds stratum (12 facilities), the allocation sequence consisted of 5 “Intervention” and 7 “Control” codes. For the 100 beds and above stratum (20 facilities), the allocation sequence consisted of 9 “Intervention” and 11 “Control” codes. Each allocation sequence was then randomised using randomisation list generated by random.org and matched sequentially with our list of facilities.									
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Participants recruited from RACFs who are allocated to 'care as usual' plus PEARL intervention will receive the intervention.
Participants recruited from RACFs who are allocated to 'care as usual' (control) will not receive the intervention.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Recruitment method:
We will recruit 308 participants from 22 RACFs with a mean of 92 bed places.  A sample size calculator for cluster-randomised trials was used to estimate the required study sample size.  Estimations were based on expectations of k = 22 RACFs, with an average of 14 participants each (n = 308) over a 24-month period, adjusted to allow for:
(i) a within-cluster correlation, reflected in an intra-class correlation of .054 and
(ii) a 6 month attrition rate of 25% based on previous research with newly admitted RACF residents.  The final sample of n = 231 participants at follow-up will provide 80% power to detect a moderate effect (greater than d = .48) with 5% Type I error (two-sided).  The assumptions used in our sample size estimations were based on current data on the Australian RACF population as well as our own Randomised Control Trials.  Approximately one third of permanent RACF places are turned over each year.  Since the RACFs in our study have a mean of 92 places, we estimate that 61 new residents will be admitted to each facility over the two-year study period. We assume that approximately half of the new residents in each RACF (n = 31) will have significant symptoms of depression and that 75% of those (n = 23) will present with normal cognition or mild-moderate dementia and speak fluent English.  We have estimated that at least 14 of the 23 potential participants in each RACF (61%) will agree to participate, a conservative estimate based on previous trials.  
Statistical analysis:
For the analysis of quantitative data, descriptive statistics will be used to summarise baseline characteristics and patterns of change over time in both RACFs and residents.
Primary analyses will be on an intention to treat basis, with supplementary per protocol analyses. To account for the within-facility clustering of participants and repeated assessments, differences in the outcomes of the intervention and control groups will be compared with multilevel modelling.   For each outcome, a separate three-level model will be specified, with repeated measurements as level 1, individuals as level 2, and RACFs as level 3. The models will include group allocation, assessment time, and group by time interaction as predictors and baseline values of the corresponding outcome, medication use at each assessment time, and organisational climate (measured at the level of a RACF) as covariates. Individual and RACF will be modelled as random effects and the remaining variables will be modelled as fixed effects. Supplementary analyses will test treatment allocation by cognitive impairment interaction to examine whether the effect of intervention differs according to the presence of cognitive impairment. Our sample size will allow us to detect a moderate interaction effect (eta squared = 0.06) with 80% power (alpha=0.05, 2-sided). To explore the mediational role of environmental mastery, autonomy, purpose in life and adjustment to RACF, multilevel path analysis (with individuals clustered within RACFs) will be undertaken, using both baseline and follow up data, and controlling for organisational climate. In all analyses, missing outcomes data will be handled with conditional maximum likelihood estimation; missing baseline data will be checked for randomness and imputed accordingly. The impact of possible non-random attrition will be explored with simulation analyses.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/01/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>308</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/07/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3199 - Frankston South</postcode>
    <postcode>3020 - Sunshine</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Rosanna</postcode>
    <postcode>3187 - Brighton East</postcode>
    <postcode>3083 - Bundoora</postcode>
    <postcode>3090 - Plenty</postcode>
    <postcode>3021 - St Albans</postcode>
    <postcode>3181 - Windsor</postcode>
    <postcode>3804 - Narre Warren North</postcode>
    <postcode>3040 - Essendon</postcode>
    <postcode>3166 - Oakleigh</postcode>
    <postcode>3034 - Avondale Heights</postcode>
    <postcode>3170 - Waverley Gardens</postcode>
    <postcode>3046 - Glenroy</postcode>
    <postcode>3124 - Camberwell</postcode>
    <postcode>3101 - Kew</postcode>
    <postcode>3011 - Footscray</postcode>
    <postcode>3030 - Werribee</postcode>
    <postcode>3085 - Macleod</postcode>
    <postcode>3191 - Sandringham</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>3136 - Croydon</postcode>
    <postcode>3810 - Pakenham</postcode>
    <postcode>3135 - Heathmont</postcode>
    <postcode>3162 - Caulfield</postcode>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Tanya Davison</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Institute for Health and Ageing
Australian Catholic University
Level 6
215 Spring Street
Melbourne Vic 3000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra City ACT 2600</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian Catholic University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Melbourne Campus
115 Victoria Parade Fitzroy Victoria 3065 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The transition to Residential Aged Care Facilities is often traumatic and newly admitted residents are at risk of depression.  The transition period represents an ideal opportunity for early intervention.  
AIMS
*To facilitate the adjustment of older adults new to permanent residential aged care.
*To improve new residents quality of life and reduce the severity and incidence of depression.
METHOD
*A cluster randomised controlled trial of a psychological intervention consisting of 5 individual sessions with residents.
*A key element of the intervention is that it is tailored to each residents needs, interests, aptitudes and background.
OUTCOMES 
*Reduced severity of depressive symptoms in newly admitted residents, improved quality of life and adjustment to the residential aged care environment.
*PEARL program is likely to improve staff practices and competence in developing tailored care plans that meet the psychological needs of newly admitted aged care residents.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Catholic University's Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Services Office
Office of the Deputy Vice Chancellor (Research)
Australian Catholic University
Z Block, Level A, Room 13
1100 Nudgee Road
Nudgee QLD 4014</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-142H</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Mercy Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mercy Health Human Research Ethics Committee
Administrative Office
Mercy Hospital for Women
6th Floor
163 Studley Road
Heidelberg Vic 3084</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>R16/53AC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tanya Davison</name>
      <address>Institute for Health and Ageing
Australian Catholic University
Level 6
215 Spring Street
Melbourne Vic 3000</address>
      <phone>+61392308273</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tanya.davison@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tanya Davison</name>
      <address>Institute for Health and Ageing
Australian Catholic University
Level 6
215 Spring Street
Melbourne Vic 3000</address>
      <phone>+61392308273</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tanya.davison@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tanya Davison</name>
      <address>Institute for Health and Ageing
Australian Catholic University
Level 6
215 Spring Street
Melbourne Vic 3000</address>
      <phone>+61392308273</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tanya.davison@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Anastasia Konis</name>
      <address>Institute for Health and Ageing
Australian Catholic University
Level 6
215 Spring Street
Melbourne Vic 3000</address>
      <phone>+61399533725</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anastasia.konis@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>