<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335688">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/07/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/07/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000559011</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Left-ventricular function and autonomic cardiac responses after short-term inpatient cardiac rehabilitation: A prospective clinical trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Left-ventricular function and autonomic cardiac responses after short-term inpatient cardiac rehabilitation following coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) surgery: A prospective clinical trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>no secondary IDs</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patients with left ventricular function normal or reduced undergoing coronary artery bypass graft (CABG)  and cardiac rehabilitation (CR)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients awaiting first-time CABG were invited to participate in the study, and enrolled after giving written informed consent. Participants were divided into left ventricular function (LVF) normal group (LVFN group) or left ventricular function (LVF) reduced group (LVFR group). Pre-operatively, the patients age, gender, weight, height, body mass index, risk factors, pharmacological treatment and other relevant medical history were documented. Additionally, a pulmonary function test was performed to investigate the presence of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and education about the effects of surgery on cardiorespiratory function, post-operative routines and cardiac rehabilitation programme were provided. Post-operatively, surgical and hospital data were recorded and all patients were engaged in cardiac rehabilitation supervised by one of three members of physiotherapy staff, specifically trained. 
All patients participated in a once-daily individual short-term supervised inpatient physiotherapy exercise protocol consisted of early mobilization plus respiratory exercises with approximate duration of daily physiotherapy sessions of 60 minutes per day starting on the first postoperative day until discharge  Briefly, this protocol consisted of progressive exercises, range of movement (ROM) active-assistive movements to climbing flights of stairs. Estimated energy expenditure during this program was initially set at approximately 2 metabolic equivalent (MET)s and progressed to 4 METs. Exercise intensity was gauged by heart rate with an upper threshold set at standing resting heart rate +20bpm, monitored by a Polar S810i telemetry system. 
Moreover, the patients performed voluntary deep-breathing exercises from functional residual capacity to total lung capacity (40 deep breaths in four sets of 10, each breath included a 5 second hold at end inspiration) followed by coughs or huffs (with wound support) supervised once daily. Patients were instructed to perform these breathing and coughing exercises independently every waking hour. 
The outcome measures of heart rate (HR) and R-R intervals (R-Ri) were collected prior (pre-operative and first post-operative day - PO1) and after (day before discharge) to cardiac rehabilitation.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants were divided into left ventricular function normal group (LVFN group) composed of patients with left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) equal to 55.0% or LVF reduced group (LVFR group) composed of patients with left ventricular function between 35.0-54.0% regarded as moderately and mildly abnormal LVF. All patients participated in a similar once-daily short-term supervised inpatient physiotherapy exercise protocol consisted of early mobilization plus respiratory exercises starting on the first postoperative day until discharge.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome measure was non-linear heart rate variability (HRV) indexes (approximate entropy and correlation dimension) after a short-term inpatient supervised physiotherapy protocol.
The heart rate and R-R intervals used to obtain measures of heart rate variability were registered continuously using a Polar S810i telemetry system</outcome>
      <timepoint>day before discharge (pre-discharge)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>As a secondary outcome measure we analyzed  heart rate variability (HRV) indexes in traditional time domain measures (SD2 and RR tri index) after a short-term inpatient supervised physiotherapy protocol. The heart rate and R-R intervals used to obtain measures of heart rate variability were registered continuously using a Polar S810i telemetry system</outcome>
      <timepoint>day before discharge (pre-discharge)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients undergoing first-time elective CABG surgery with LVF normal or reduced were included in this study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>42</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria were emergent or concomitant surgery, recent myocardial infarction (MI) (6 months), implanted pacemaker, unstable angina, chronic disturbances in heart rhythm, significant acute arrhythmias, valvular heart diseases, COPD, severe non-cardiac diseases and the inability to perform cardiac rehabilitation according to our protocol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants were divided into left ventricular function (LVF) normal group (LVFN group) composed of patients with left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) equal to 55.0% or LVF reduced group (LVFR group) composed of patients with LVEF between 35.0-54.0% regarded as moderately and mildly abnormal LVF</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/01/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Renata Goncalves Mendes</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Laboratorio de Fisioterapia Cardiorrespiratoria, Nucleo de Pesquisa em Exercicio Fisico (NUPEF), Rodovia Washington Luis (SP-310), km 235, Sao Carlos - Sao Paulo. CEP 13565-905.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidade Federal de Sao Carlos</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rodovia Washington Luis (SP-310), km 235, Sao Carlos - Sao Paulo. CEP 13565-905.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Audrey Borghi e Silva</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Laboratorio de Fisioterapia Cardiorrespiratoria, Nucleo de Pesquisa em Exercicio Fisico (NUPEF), Rodovia Washington Luis (SP-310), km 235, Sao Carlos - Sao Paulo. CEP 13565-905.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is known that coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) leads to cardiac autonomic (CA) dysfunction and that cardiac rehabilitation (CR) involving physical exercise is associated with CA benefits. However, is not known whether differences in left ventricular function (LVF) interfere in CA responses after CR. The aim of this study was to assess the CA responses in normal and reduced LVF patients undergoing CABG and CR. The hypothesis of this study was that patients with the poorest LVF are likely to derive the greatest benefit in the cardiac autonomic activity from rehabilitation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of Federal University of Sao Carlos</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Rodovia Washington Luis (SP-310), km 235, Sao Carlos - Sao Paulo. CEP 13565-905.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Audrey Borghi-Silva</name>
      <address>Laboratorio de Fisioterapia Cardiorrespiratoria, Nucleo de Pesquisa em Exercicio Fisico (NUPEF), Rodovia Washington Luis (SP-310), km 235, Sao Carlos - Sao Paulo. CEP 13565-905.</address>
      <phone>(+55 16) 3351-8705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>audrey@ufscar.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Renata Goncalves Mendes</name>
      <address>Laboratorio de Fisioterapia Cardiorrespiratoria, Nucleo de Pesquisa em Exercicio Fisico (NUPEF), Rodovia Washington Luis (SP-310), km 235, Sao Carlos - Sao Paulo. CEP 13565-905.</address>
      <phone>(+55 16) 3351-8705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mendesrg@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>