<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363058">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001033831</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An assessment of the safety and pharmacokinetic of ascending doses of sanguinate (Trademark) in healthy volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A single-blind, placebo-controlled, single dose, safety and pharmacokinetic study of 3 ascending doses of SANGUINATE in 3 cohorts of healthy volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1134-8739</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Effect of the drug Sanguinate on healthy volunteers</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A single-blind, placebo-controlled, single dose, safety and pharmacokinetic study of 3 ascending doses of SANGUINATE in 3 cohorts of healthy volunteers. Twenty four (24) eligible healthy volunteers will be sequentially enrolled into one of 3 dosing cohorts, each consisting of no less than three
males and no less than three females. Within each cohort, two subjects will receive placebo (saline) and six subjects will receive active treatment. Active treatment will be consists of 2,4 &amp; 8 ml per kg for 1st, 2nd and 3rd cohort respectively which would be administered as a slow intravenous (i.v.) bolus infusion. duration of investigational product (IP) administration would be 6 to 8 hours of single dose administration.</interventions>
    <comparator>Normal saline solution
In each cohort, out of 8, 6 patients will receive Test product &amp; 2 will receive placebo which is normal saline solution as per the randomization sheet generated by computerized software</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess safety, A complete complete blood count (CBC) with platelets will be performed</outcome>
      <timepoint>at screening and Day 0 (upon admission to the clinical unit), and post-dose on Days 2, 3 and 7.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood biochemistry testing (including amylase and lipase), and urinalysis with microscopic, will be performed</outcome>
      <timepoint>screening and Day 0 (admission), on Day 1 (6 hours post-infusion) and on Days 2, 3, 4, 5, and 7.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Troponin I testing (cardiac assessment) will be performed</outcome>
      <timepoint>screening and Day 0 (admission), on Day 1 (baseline, 1, 3, and 6 hours post-infusion) and on Days 2, 3, 4, 5, and 7</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the plasma pharmacokinetic profile of
SANGUINATE in healthy volunteers
Serial blood samples for pharmacokinetic analysis will be collected at pre-dose and at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24, 36, 48, 72 and 96 hours from the start of infusion. Plasma will be analyzed for concentrations of SANGUINATE using
a validated method</outcome>
      <timepoint>0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6, 8, 12, 24, 36, 48, 72 and 96 hours from the start of infusion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Able to provide written Informed Consent
2. Male or female healthy volunteers
3. Age &gt; 18 years and &lt; 45 years;
4. Body Mass Index &gt; 20 and &lt; 30 kg/m2.
5. In good general health with no clinically significant illness seen on physical examination or ongoing medical history, as determined by the Investigator;
6. Documented 12-lead ECG with no clinically significant abnormalities, as determined by the Investigator
7. No clinically significant abnormalities in screening or Day 0 laboratory tests, as determined by the Investigator
8. Female subjects of reproductive potential must have a negative serum pregnancy (beta-HCG) test at screening and a negative urine pregnancy test at Day 0 prior to dosing. Female subjects must also be non-lactating
9. Adequate venous access and can receive intravenous infusions</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. If female, pregnant or lactating;
2. Any history of significant cardiac, renal, neurologic, metabolic, pulmonary, gastrointestinal, chronic hepatic disease or any other disease which in the judgment of the Investigator would interfere with the study or confound the results;
3. History of allergy or major allergic reaction considered to be clinically significant by the Investigator;
4. Screening or Day 0 clinical laboratory test result(s) determined to be clinically significant by the Investigator
5. Screening or Day 0 laboratory values for Troponin I &gt; 0.31 ng/mL
6. Screening or Day 0 laboratory values for amylase or lipase &gt; 1.1 x upper limit of normal
7. Physical examination or 12-lead ECG result(s) considered to be clinically significant by the Investigator
8. Donated blood within 60 days of screening or otherwise experienced blood loss of &gt;250 mL within the same period;
9. Known to be allergic to any of the test product(s) or any components in the test product(s)
10. Intending to begin new concomitant drug therapy or over-the-counter medication anytime from screening to the time of administration of study drug
11. Received or intending to receive a vaccination in the two weeks prior to dosing, or anytime during study participation;
12. Received treatment with a drug that has not received regulatory approval for an indication during the 60 days preceding study enrollment
13. History of drug and/or alcohol dependence within past 12 months, and/or positive results on drug of abuse or alcohol tests
14. Screening laboratory result indicating HIV-positivity, or previously diagnosed with AIDS, AIDS related complex, or other immunodeficiency
15. Screening laboratory result indicating serologic positivity for hepatitis C antibodies or hepatitis B surface antigens, unless explained by a documented vaccination
16. Has taken any regular, prescribed, or over-the-counter medication with the exception of acetaminophen (maximum 2g/day), multi-vitamins, or hormonal birth control in the 2 weeks prior to dosing (other medication may only be taken with the specific approval of the Investigator in consultation
with the Medical Monitor)
17. Receiving any significant concomitant therapies
18. Malignancy within the last 5 years, with the exception of successfully treated basal cell carcinoma and carcinoma in situ uteri
19. Unable to comply with study attendance, protocol procedures or other study requirements
20. Any condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, might interfere with study objectives.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a single-blind, placebo-controlled, single dose, safety and pharmacokinetic study of 3 ascending doses of SANGUINATE (trademark) in 3 cohorts of healthy volunteers. Twenty four (24) eligible healthy volunteers, ages 18 to 45, will be recruited and sequentially enrolled into one of 3 dosing cohorts, each consisting of no less than three males and no less than three females.
Within each cohort, two subjects will receive placebo (saline) and six subjects will receive active treatment. 
Allocation to a particular arm would be done by central randomisation generated by computer software. Dose escalation to the next cohort will occur after review of the key safety data obtained from the previous cohort indicates that it is safe to proceed. Subjects in a given cohort will receive a single dose by intravenous infusion on the morning of Day 1, and be followed as an inpatient through at least 48-hours post-dose (Day 3), when they will be discharged and asked to return for follow-up visits on Days 4, 5, and 7 (+/-1 day)</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/12/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>2/02/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3004</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prolong Pharmaceuticals</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Prolong Pharmaceuticals
300 Corporate Court 
South Plainfield, NJ 07080, USA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Prolong Pharmaceuticals</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Prolong Pharmaceuticals
300 Corporate Court 
South Plainfield, NJ 07080, USA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Quintiles Australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 10  67 Albert Avenue, Chatswood, New South Wales, Australia 2067.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Through local representative Quintiles, Prolong pharmaceuticals would like to conduct Phase I PK study in normal healthy volunteers for its investigational product - SANGUINATE at Nucleus Network, Alfred Hospital, Melbourne, Australia</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alfred Hospital, Commercial Road, MELBOURNE, VIC 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00315</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/09/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr. Abe Abuchowski</name>
      <address>Prolong Pharmaceuticals
300 Corporate Court 
South Plainfield, NJ 07080, USA</address>
      <phone>+1-908-444-4650</phone>
      <fax>+1 908-444-4661</fax>
      <email>aabuchowski@prolongpharma.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Glenn Kazo</name>
      <address>Prolong Pharmaceuticals, 300B Corporate Court, South Plainfield, NJ 07080, USA</address>
      <phone>+1-908-444-4651</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gkazo@prolongpharma.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Hemant Misra</name>
      <address>Prolong Pharmaceuticals
300 Corporate Court 
South Plainfield, NJ 07080, USA</address>
      <phone>+1 908-444-4653</phone>
      <fax>+1 908-444-4661</fax>
      <email>hmisra@prolongpharma.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jason lickliter</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network Limited, 
5th Floor, Burnet Tower, AMREP Precinct, 89 Commercial Road, Melbourne, VIC 3004, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 407 527 307</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.lickliter@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>