<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370701">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000665437p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Smart-watch to implement quality of life, drug-therapy &amp; physical activity in children with Juvenile Idiopathic Arthritis: a randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Smart-watch to implement quality of life, drug-therapy &amp; physical activity in children with Juvenile Idiopathic Arthritis: a randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Juvenile Idiopathic Arthritis </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autoimmune diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Customised Smart Watch programme: 
The chief investigator will set up discrete prompts / messages during the day through the smart-watch device to inform the child with JIA to record daily pain level fluctuations (using the iVAS App recently developed by Dr Coda and his research team) and to document when the prescribed drugs have been taken by simply tapping the smart-watch to confirm when the measurement has been acquired.
Three discreet prompts per day will be automatically sent to the child with JIA to record pain, at waking, midday and evenings. The inbuilt accelerometer and GPS within the smart-watch allows for the simultaneous gathering of the intensity of physical activity outcome. World Health Organisation (WHO), US Centre for Disease Control, US Surgeon General, American Heart Foundation, US Department of Health &amp; Human Services, and the National Heart Foundation of Australia all recommend individuals take 10,000 steps a day to improve their health and reduce the risk of disease. 10,000 steps a day is a realistic goal that is achievable by people of all shapes, sizes and ages. When daily physical activity targets set by the research are achieved, the child will be informed via a gentle vibration on the wrist, and notified of their achievements with positive reinforcement messages and awards-icons on their smart-watch screen.  The physical activity targets will be set by the chief investigator for each participant for a period of 6 months, which may vary based on symptoms severity and overall health conditions. 
The participants will be kindly asked to wear the smart watch during the whole day; however, it will not be required to wear the device during sleeping time, which enable the watch to be re-recharged. 
All the notifications received by the child will be accessible remotely by the parents as well, in oder to help and support the child towards improving the self-management of the pathology. The child will be informed that the smart watch cannot be worn in certain conditions, such as showering and swimming. The child and the parent will be informed to record water physical activities carried out by the child and to notify the chief investigator with a simple free-messaging system. Under these circumstances the chief-investigator will translate the equivalent of swimming carried out into calories &amp; exercise level, and directly update the individual customised program.  </interventions>
    <comparator>The standard watch will be provided to the JIA children randomly allocated to the control group. 
The watch supplied to the control group will have same appearance as the smart watch (in the trial group); however it will not have any 'smart' functionality. The standard watch screen will only provide the time.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in lower limb pain as recorded by the iVAS app developed by the Dr Coda and his research and also by comparing it with the standard VAS (visual analogue scale). According to Dhanani et al. (2002), 8mm are required to achieve clinical significance difference between data collection sessions, in paediatric rheumatology children.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline 
3rd months 
6th months 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in 'Quality of life' using the disease specific (paediatric rheumatology) - PedsQL questionnaire divided according to the age range (gathered directly by the child and independently also by their parents / carer).  According to Varni et al (2002), 5 points are required to achieve clinical significance difference between data collection sessions</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline 
3rd month 
6th month</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in drug therapy compliancy will be assessed comparing the weekly drug prescribed (frequencies and dosages) by the paediatric rheumatologists  to the actual drug intake from the child with JIA (frequencies and dosages) in both groups  by self-report by participant using study medication diary.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline 
3rd month 
6th month
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in exercise adherence level will be compared using a validated tool called ActivPal device (extensively used in research) that is able to blindly campure physical activity (ie: walking distance, steps,). Both groups will be supplied with an ActivPAL, (attached on	the right thigh) which will be returned to the data  collector  after 7  days, using  the  provided pre paid  envelope  (along  with  the ActivPAL device). Data collected will be downloaded to the ActivPal software and then analysed. This methodological approach   will  be  the essential to compare the effectiveness of the customised watch programme	 versus the control group with regards to basic physical activity activity  levels during the 6 months trial period, </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline 
3rd month 
6th month </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Diagnosed with JIA according to ILAR (International League of Associations for Rheumatology) criteria.
2) No previous use of Apple-Watch 
3) Resident in Australia
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>10</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) Concomitant musculoskeletal disease, central or peripheral nerve disease
2) Heart failure 
3) Severe visual impairments
4) If DMARD and/or Biological therapy are used, not having started these drug therapies within 6 months of enrolling in the trial. 
5) Where assistive drugs therapy administration is required daily by medical staff 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Data collector will use sealed opaque envelopes for allocation concealments into a control or active group</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>58</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>None at the moment </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>NA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NA</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Our novel clinical approach could place innovative non-drug treatment solutions in the hands of children with Juvenile Idiopathic Arthritis (JIA). This multi centre randomised control-trial aims to integrate the Smart Watch to monitor pain levels, customised physical activity progression, and drug-therapy adherence in children with JIA.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Ethics Research Committee, University of Newcastle</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>NA</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/01/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrea Coda</name>
      <address>Lecturer in Podiatry - PhD, Hons (BSc) Pod
The University of Newcastle, School of Health Sciences, Faculty of Health and Medicine - Health Precinct, BE154, PO Box 127. Ourimbah, NSW, 2258, Australia. </address>
      <phone>+61 2 4348 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Andrea.Coda@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrea Coda</name>
      <address>Lecturer in Podiatry - PhD, Hons (BSc) Pod
The University of Newcastle, School of Health Sciences, Faculty of Health and Medicine - Health Precinct, BE154, PO Box 127. Ourimbah, NSW, 2258, Australia. </address>
      <phone>+61 2 4348 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Andrea.Coda@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Andrea Coda</name>
      <address>Lecturer in Podiatry - PhD, Hons (BSc) Pod
The University of Newcastle, School of Health Sciences, Faculty of Health and Medicine - Health Precinct, BE154, PO Box 127. Ourimbah, NSW, 2258, Australia. </address>
      <phone>+61 2 4348 4000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Andrea.Coda@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>