<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368879">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001356459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Determination of human oral carbohydrate taste function and its association with food consumption and Body Mass Index (BMI)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Carbohydrate taste sensitivity testing in healthy volunteers to determine human oral carbohydrate taste function and its association with food consumption and BMI</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>NIL</utrn>
    <trialacronym>NIL</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be required to visit the Centre of Advanced Sensory Science laboratory, Deakin University for at least 17 times (maximum of 7 times per types of carbohydrate). 

Participants may experience:
Visit 1:
Food consumption and anthropometry. Participants will be asked to complete a Cancer Council food frequency questionnaire, a 4-day diet diary, and a 3-factor eating questionnaire at home within 1 month of the sensory tests. Height, weight, waist circumference will be measured at baseline. Weight and waist circumference will be measured again at the end (final session).

Visits 1-2:
Determination of taste thresholds for the five basic tastes. Participants will be presented with a series of eight solutions for each tastants (sweet, sour, bitter, salty and umami), which will be arranged in ascending order of concentration. Participants will be asked to sample each solution, expel it after 10 seconds and then describe the taste of the solution. The process will be repeated twice (for visit 1-2) and will take approximately 1 hour 30 minutes for each visit. 

Visits 3:
Suprathreshold (sufficient strength or quantity to produce a perceptible physiological effect) taste intensity perception for the five basic tastes.
Subjects will be given a brief training session in the use of gLMS (General Labelled Magnitude Scale) (in ascending order). gLMS is a scale consists of a vertical line, used to measure perceived taste intensity. To test for intensity perception of the five basic tastes (bitter, salty, sweet, sour, umami), participants will be presented with numbered trays that contained 4 randomized solution for each taste quality (15mL each). Participants were instructed to held in each of the solutions in the mouth for at least five seconds and expectorate. Participants were then required to rate the taste intensity perception on a computerised gLMS. Participants were also instructed to rinse their mouth for five seconds with filtered deionised water between samples. Solutions will be presented in randomised order. The minimum and maximum concentrations of solutions will range from 0.04g/L-63.1g/L

This will be repeated twice (for visit 3). Visit 3 will take about 50 minutes, depending on their taste sensitivity. 

Visits 4-10; 11-17:
Detection thresholds for maltodextrin and inulin. 
Each participant will be blinded (they will not know which carbohydrate they are tasting). Detection thresholds for carbohydrates (maltodextrin, inulin) will be tested using ascending triangle forced-choice procedure. Participants will be provided with three 25 mL samples: two controls (filtered deionised water solutions) and one containing carbohydrate (maltodextrin or inulin), per set, in ascending order from the lowest to the highest concentration. Participants were instructed to rinse their mouths for five seconds with filtered deionised water before beginning the task and between each sample set. Detection thresholds for each sweetener or polysaccharides was defined as the concentration of carbohydrate required for a participant to correctly identify the sweetened or polysaccharide sample as odd from the two control samples, in three consecutive sample sets at one concentration level (Meilgaard et al., 2007).  
 
Each visit will take about 10-20 minutes, depending on the sensitivity of the individual. 
Each session will be separated by a minimum of 1 hour. The minimum and maximum concentration of solutions will range from 0.04g/l-63.1g/L</interventions>
    <comparator>nil</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Possible associations between carbohydrate taste sensitivity (less sensitive or more sensitive), and its association with dietary consumption. 
Mean taste thresholds for carbohydrates will be determined. Correlations between mean thresholds with dietary consumption (from 7 day diet diary and Cancer Council Food frequency questionnaire) will be used to determine if there are any associations between carbohydrate taste thresholds with food dietary consumption.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed once participants have completed the 17 visits</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Possible associations between carbohydrate taste sensitivity (less sensitive or more sensitive), and its association with body mass index. 
Mean taste thresholds for carbohydrates will be determined. Correlations between mean thresholds with body mass index (anthropometry measurements- heigh, weight, and waist circumference) will be used to determine if there are any associations between carbohydrate taste thresholds with body mass index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assesed once participants have completed the 17 visits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>over the age of 18 years of age and below the age of 85 years. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>smokers, pregnant or lactating, known allergies towards any food used in the study to assess taste thresholds</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Information collected from participants will be used to:
1. A sample size of  30 participants was chosen in line with the central limits theorem to approximate a normal population distribution (Field, 2009).

2. Determine taste thresholds for carbohydrates (inulin and maltodextrin). Correlations between mean thresholds with BMI and food consumption (dietary pattern) will be used to determine if there are associations between carbohydrate taste thresholds with food consumption and BMI. 

3. Information concerning participant's food consumption and food behaviour will be used to evaluate differences between subject's thresholds. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>2/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>30</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>29/02/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>26/02/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3125 - Burwood</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre of Advanced Sensory Science/ School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, Deakin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, VIC 3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Centre of Advanced Sensory Science/ School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, Deakin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>221, Burwood Highway, 3125, Burwood, VIC</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to investigate if humans are able to detect small amounts of carbohydrate orally and investigate links with dietary consumption and weight. Over the past decades, behavioural studies demonstrated that rats are very attracted to starch and that starch is preferred to sucrose at low concentrations, suggesting that rats have different taste receptors for sucrose and starch. Carbohydrates, in the form of sugar and starch, represent a major source of food energy. Except for some fruits, plants contain much more starch than sugar, but it is sugar with its sweet taste that is the most sought after carbohydrate. Compared to sugar, starch is rather bland to the human palate, and has been assumed to be tasteless for other animals as well. However, in the past decades, studies using animal models reported that rats are very attracted to the taste of maltodextrin (starch). The results of these studies suggest that starch and sucrose stimulate different taste qualities, indicating there is an independent taste receptor for polysaccharides. 

Recent studies investigating carbohydrate sensing in the human oral cavity through exercise performance have also found that exercise performance significantly improved after participants rinsed their mouth with solutions containing maltodextrin (see review by e-Silva et al., 2014). The results suggest that there may be an independent mechanism and pathway for oral carbohydrate detection, but as yet, there is not method for assessing carbohydrate detection thresholds in humans. 

A total of 30 people will participate in this project and subjects must be over the age of 18 years. It is also preferred that subjects are non-smokers. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Ethics Advisory Group (HEAG)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Deakin University
221, Burwood Highway, Burwood, 3125, VIC</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HEAG-H 182_2014</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/10/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Russell Keast</name>
      <address>Centre of Advanced Sensory Science, Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, 3125, VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92446944</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>russell.keast@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Julia Low</name>
      <address>Centre of Advanced Sensory Science, Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, 3125, VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92517247</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yqlow@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Russell Keast</name>
      <address>Centre of Advanced Sensory Science, Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, 3125, VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92446944</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>russell.keast@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Julia Low</name>
      <address>Centre of Advanced Sensory Science,
Deakin University,
221 Burwood Highway, Burwood, 3125, VIC</address>
      <phone>+61 3 92517247</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>yqlow@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>