<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308020">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000597291</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study evaluating the effect of platelet transfusion using an electromechanical infusion pump versus conventional gravity flow method</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study evaluating the effect of platelet
transfusion method administered via an electromechanical infusion pump versus conventional gravity flow method on quality and quantity of transfused platelets</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PLATTRANS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Platelet transfusion</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Blood</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haematological diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Our current practice at the Launceston General Hospital (LGH) and many other medical centres in Australia is to administer platelets via a free flowing gravity line. However there are a few reports that employ a pump during platelet-administration as an acceptable practice. Administration of platelets via a pump would ensure the platelets are infused in a timely fashion but in the meantime, we should ensure that the pumping action will not damage the platelets. There are 4 methods for platelets transfusion including 3 pumps currently available on the oncology ward at the LGH and used for red cell transfusion; 1. The Graseby 3000 2. the Imed Gemini PC-1 and PC-2 (double pump) and 3. Baxter Pump. Furthermore the pump offers well controlled infusion rate, accurate volume measurement and an alarm system for monitoring infusion. 

1. gravity flow method - platelets transfused over approximately 30 minutes; 2. Transfusion using the Graseby 3000 takes approximately 15-20 minutes; 3. Transfusion using the Imed Gemini PC-1 and PC-2 (double pump) takes approximately 20 minutes.
4.Transfusion using the baxter pump takes approximately 20 minutes
There is very little data, if any, comparing the effect of the above two recognised methods on platelet-increment after transfusion. 
This pilot study is aiming to determine whether infusion method influences the quality and quantity of platelets transfused. Also to determine the most efficient procedure for the administration of platelets either via electromechanical pump or through gravity method. The study will take place until end of Dec 2009.</interventions>
    <comparator>Although both methods for platelets transfusion utilising both either electromechanical pump or through free flowing gravity are well recognised and considered as standard treatment, there is little data available regarding a comparison of the two methods, which their applications vary according the treatment centre in Australia and the rest of the world.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The aim of this pilot study is to evaluate whether infusion method influences the quality and quantity of platelets transfused.
Platelets count and function will be assessed after transfusion via full blood count and flow cytometry techniques.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Main outcome will be measured by platelet count prior to transfusion and platelet count increment after 60 min of completion of transfusion as well as 24 hours post platelet transfusion recovery as per current 
standard practice.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine the most efficient procedure for the administration of platelets. 
Also whether the rate and method of transfusion influences the quality and quantity of platelets transfused. Platelets count and function will be assessed after transfusion via full blood count and flow cytometry techniques.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until the end of study Dec 2009</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Other factors that might influence platelet recovery include presence of infection/ Dissiminated intravascular coagulopathy (DIC), drugs administration and occurrence of transfusion reactions. These will be studied and recorded as per protocol for correlation with platelet recovery. 
Studying the effect of the rate of transfusion via a pump will also be examined and recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until the end of study Dec 2009</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients requiring a platelet infusion.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients with severe infection/ sepsis with temperature&gt;38.5 C. 
2. Patients with coagulopathy / DIC 
3. Patients with platelet refractoriness e.g. platelet antibody or human leucocyte antigen (HLA) antibody. 
4. Patients under the age of 18 years.
5. Patients with an intellectual or mental impairment.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>We anticipate that almost 120 participants could be enrolled in our trial per year; 30-40 in each arm. Patients will be randomised 1:1:1 into three groups with an equal male to female ratio as possible. Group 1: gravity flow, Group 2: electromechanical pump used at LGH for platelts transfusion and Group 3: other electromechanical pump that used at LGH for platelts transfusion.
Allocation was randomly concealed with random numbered containers at the central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/01/2007</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/01/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>171</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>TAS</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Clifford Craig Medical Trust Foundation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 1963
Launceston
Tasmania, 7250</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Clifford Craig Medical Trust Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 1963
Launceston
Tasmania, 7250</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Launceston General Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Charles Street, Launceston
Tasmania, 7250</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Our current practice at the Launceston General Hospital (LGH) and many centres in Australia is to administer platelets via a free flowing gravity line. However there are a few reports that employ a pump during platelet-administration as an acceptable practice. Administration of platelets via a pump would ensure the platelets are infused in a timely fashion but in the meantime, we should ensure that the pumping action will not damage the platelets. There are 2 pumps currently available on the oncology ward at the LGH and used for red cell transfusion; the Graseby 3000 and the Imed Gemini PC-1 and PC-2 (double pump). Furthermore the pump offers wellcontrolled infusion rate, accurate volume measurement and an alarm system for monitoring infusion. 
There is very little data, if any, comparing the effect of the above two recognised methods on platelet-increment after transfusion. 
This pilot study is aiming to determine whether infusion method influences the quality and quantity of platelets transfused. Also to determine the most efficient procedure for the administration of platelets.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Alhossain A. Khalafallah, Abdul Majeed Al-Barzan,  Annette Camino,  Iain K. Robertson, Gerald Bates Dawn Richardson,  Catherine Austen, David Seaton, Wolfgang Heller and Terry Brain. An Open-Labelled, Randomized Cross-Over Study of the Effect of Electromechanical Pumps versus Conventional Gravity Flow on Platelet Transfusion in Adult Haematology Patients. Transfus Med Hemother 2013;40:2226. DOI: 10.1159/000345681.

http://www.karger.com/Article/Pdf/345681 
http://scholar.google.com.au/citations?view_op=view_citation&amp;hl=en&amp;user=7Ntik6EAAAAJ&amp;cstart=20&amp;citation_for_view=7Ntik6EAAAAJ:Se3iqnhoufwC</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Tasmania Health and Medical Human Research Ethics Committee EC00337</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Executive Officer
University of Tasmania (UTAS) Research and Development Office
GPO Box 252-01
Hobart
Tasmania 7001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/03/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H0009779</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Assoc Prof Alhossain Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital 
Charles St
Launceston
Tasmania 7250</address>
      <phone>+613 6348 7111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Assoc Prof Alhossain Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital 
Charles St
Launceston
Tasmania 7250</address>
      <phone>+613 6348 7111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Assoc Prof Alhossain Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital 
Charles St
Launceston
Tasmania 7250</address>
      <phone>+613 6348 7111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Alhossain A. Khalafallah</name>
      <address>Launceston General Hospital, 
Charles Street, Launceston, TAS 7250 
</address>
      <phone>+61367776777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>khalafallah@dhhs.tas.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>