<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370797">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000723482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Intravenous tranexamic acid ("TXA") and its effect on operating conditions, blood loss, post-operative pain and complications in patients undergoing total shoulder replacement.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of systemic tranexamic acid use on operating conditions, blood loss, post-operative pain and complications in patients undergoing shoulder arthroplasty.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1183-3447</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Blood loss in total shoulder arthroplasty</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Group 1 (TXA group) will receive 2000mg (20ml) of Tranexamic Acid (TXA) intravenously 5 minutes before incision. </interventions>
    <comparator>Group 2 (Control group) will receive 2000mg (20ml) of Saline intravenously 5 minutes before incision.. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in haemaglobin level as measured by the difference between pre-operative and post-operative levels as assessed by serum assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operative haemaglobin will be assessed the day before operation. Post-operative haemaglobin will be assessed in the morning of the first day after operation. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in haemocrit as measured by the difference between pre-operative and post-operative levels as assessed by serum assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operative haemocrit will be assessed the day before operation. Post-operative haemocrit will be assessed in the morning of the first day after operation. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Operative time defined as time from induction of anaesthesia until wound closure as timed by surgical assistant with stopwatch. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Operative time will be calculated at the conclusion of the operation (day 0). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Transfusion requirement as measured by data linkage to patient medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 6 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain assessment using visual analogue score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured daily for 5 days starting from 24 hours after operation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Passive shoulder range of motion by using a goniometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 3, 2 weeks and 8 weeks post operation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Infection rates as measured by data linkage to patient medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 6 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thromboembolic adverse events as measured by data linkage to patient medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 6 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Procedure complexity rating as measured by the operating surgeon selecting either "more complex than usual", "as usual" or "less complex than usual" on a checklist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the conclusion of the operation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Operative field visibility rating as measured by the operating surgeon selecting either "excellent", "good", "fair"or "poor" on a checklist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the conclusion of the operation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Drain output measured in cc.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 hours post operation, 16 hours post operation and 24 hours post operation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative haematoma occurrence as measured by data linkage to patient medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 24 hours post operation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time spent in recovery room as measured by the difference between time of arrival to time of departure. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of departure from recovery room.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time spent in hospital as measured by the difference between date of admission to date of discharge. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Date of discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients who have consented for anatomic or reverse shoulder arthroplasty under one of the principal investigators.
2. Patients who are capable of and have given informed consent for their participation in this study.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients allergic to tranexamic acid
2. Patients with a failed arthroplasty requiring revision
3. Patients with history of deep venous thrombosis or pulmonary embolism
4. Patients with cardiovascular disease, including coronary disease or peripheral arteriopathy
5. Patients with renal or liver failure
6. Patients with a known coagulopathy
7. Patients that refuse a potential transfusion</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>None.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size was calculated based on the primary objective. It was decided to replicate work done by Gillespie et al (2015) who found an average change in haemaglobin level of 2.6g/dL in the placebo group and 1.7g/dL in the TXA group (p &lt; .001) with 111 patients. It was decided that increasing the subjects from 111 to 150 patients might improve the power of the study. 

Correlation analysis, including univariate and multivariate analyses will be used to determine the correlation between systemic administration of TXA and the selected outcome criteria. Subgroup analysis will be carried between the different types of prosthesis (reverse versus anatomic). P value &lt;0.5 will be considered as statistically significant. All data will be entered into Socrates Orthopaedic Outcomes Software (Ortholink Pty Ltd, Sydney, Australia).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/04/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>25/08/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>5/10/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Other reasons/comments</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother>We decided to stop the Study at 60 participants (30 in each group) as statistical analysis showed a highly significant difference in our outcomes which meant we achieved our objective with the research. Specifically, drain output in patients in the treatment group was significantly less than drain output in patients in the control group. Given this results we wish to proceed to preparing an article for publication. </withdrawnreasonother>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>North Shore Private Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Sydney - North Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>2060 - North Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - Royal North Shore Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Benjamin Cass</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney Shoulder Research Institute
Suite 201
Level 2
156 Pacific Highway
St Leonards NSW 2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sydney Shoulder Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 201
Level 2
156 Pacific Highway
St Leonards  NSW  2065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This will be a multicentre multisurgeon prospective doubleblinded randomized and controlled trial looking at the effectiveness of single dose intravenous administration of Tranexamic Acid (TXA) in patients undergoing shoulder arthroplasty.

The aim of this study is to extend Level I category evidence of the known benefits of TXA to shoulder arthroplasty. The primary objective of this study is to test the hypothesis that systemic use of Tranexamic acid improves operating conditions, decreases blood loss, postoperative pain and complications such as haematoma and need for transfusion. The secondary objective is to carry out subgroup analysis between reverse and anatomical shoulder arthroplasty with the hypothesis that reverse causes more blood loss than anatomic.

All consecutive patients presenting to an elective orthopaedic consultation with a failed nonoperative management of shoulder arthritis indicated for shoulder arthroplasty will be considered eligible for this study. After having been screened for inclusion and exclusion criteria, read the information sheet and signed the consent form, patients will be blindly randomized to one of 2 groups: Systemic TXA or Control.

Patients general demographic characteristics such as age, sex, dominance, diagnosis, BMI, American Society of Anaesthesia (ASA) score and other relevant comorbidities will be collected in a deidentified database locked on a password-protected computer. 

During the surgery, patients will be administered either 2mg of intravenous TXA or a placebo equivalent (saline solution). Analysed outcome variables will include: surgeons rating of surgical field visibility and overall appreciation of the complexity of the procedure, operative time, pre- and postoperative haemoglobin and haematocrit levels, drain output at 6,12 and 24 hours, need for transfusion, occurrence of postoperative haematoma, postoperative pain Visual Analog Scale (pVAS), time spent in recovery room and hospital room.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.ssri.net.au/research/txa-study/</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>North Shore Private Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>North Shore Private Hospital
Westbourne Street
St Leonards   NSW   2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Level 6, de Lacy Building
St Vincent's Hospital
390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst   NSW   2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Benjamin Cass</name>
      <address>Sydney Shoulder Research Institute
Suite 201, Level 2
156 Pacific Highway
St Leonards   NSW   2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9460 8888</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9460 6064</fax>
      <email>cassadmin@sydneyshoulder.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Jasmin Gwynne</name>
      <address>Sydney Shoulder Research Institute
Suite 201, Level 2
156 Pacific Highway
St Leonards   NSW   2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9460 8813</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9460 6064</fax>
      <email>jasmin@sydneyshoulder.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Benjamin Cass</name>
      <address>Sydney Shoulder Research Institute
Suite 201, Level 2
156 Pacific Highway
St Leonards   NSW   2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9460 8888</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9460 6064</fax>
      <email>cassadmin@sydneyshoulder.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Jasmin Gwynne</name>
      <address>Sydney Shoulder Research Institute
Suite 201, Level 2
156 Pacific Highway
St Leonards   NSW   2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9460 8813</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9460 6064</fax>
      <email>jasmin@sydneyshoulder.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>