<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365585">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000060640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An open-label, multi-centre Phase I study of the safety and tolerability of intravenously (IV) infused PG545 in patients with advanced solid tumours</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Study of the safety and tolerability of IV infused PG545 in patients with advanced solid tumours</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>PG545102</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Advanced Solid Tumours</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Any cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Once weekly PG545 administered via a 1 hour IV infusion. Subjects will be treated until they exhibit disease progression or are discontinued for reasons of tolerability. Multiple ascending dose study with Cohort 1 receiving 25 mg/week; Cohort 2: 50 mg/week; Cohort 3: 100 mg/week; Cohort 4: 150 mg/week; Cohort 5: 200 mg/week; Cohort 6: 250 mg/week.</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determination of Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) based on dose limiting toxicities (DLT)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Evaluated at the end of the first 1 month cycle</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of safety and tolerability of PG545 when administered by once weekly IV infusion following multiple doses. Determined by frequency and severity of adverse events and collection of laboratory safety data. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Continuously throughout treatment and up until one month following final dose.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Estimate pharmacokinetic parameters of PG545 when administered by once weekly intravenous infusion (by plasma assay) and explore pharmacokinetic / pharmacodynamic relationships (plasma samples assaying target molecules, including but not limited to heparanase, VEGF, VEGFR, FGF2, and IL-12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at 30 minutes, 2, 4, 6, 24, 48, 72, 144, and 168 hours post-infusion during weeks one and four of dosing, at the end of each cycle and at the end of study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To document any anti-tumour activity observed as per RECIST criteria</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every eight weeks throughout treatment and up to four weeks post-treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Age 18 years and older.
- Histological or cytological documentation of non haematological, malignant solid tumour, excluding primary brain or spinal tumours.
- Subjects with advanced solid tumours who have failed all standard therapies, no longer are candidates for standard therapy, have no standard therapy available, or choose not to pursue standard therapy (the later is to be documented).
- Measurable disease (at least 1 target lesion) according to RECIST 1.1.
- Life expectancy of at least 12 weeks.
- ECOG Performance Status of 0 or 1.
- Written, signed and dated informed consent to participate in study.
- Able and willing to meet all protocol-required treatments, investigations and visits.
- Have adequate organ function including: Bone Marrow Reserve: Total white blood cell (WBC) count greater than or equal to 2300 cells/microL, absolute neutrophil count (ANC) greater than or equal to 1500 cells/microL, platelets greater than or equal to 100,000/microL, haemoglobin greater than or equal to 9 g/dL; Hepatic: Bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 x upper limits of normal (ULN), alanine transaminase (ALT) and aspartate transaminase (AST) less than or equal to 2.5 x ULN  if liver metastases are present then less than or equal to 5 x ULN; Renal: serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 times ULN - subjects with a serum creatinine greater than 1.5 x ULN may be enrolled if their creatinine clearance is calculated or measured at greater than 60 mL/minute; Coagulation: Activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT) and prothrombin time (PT) less than or equal to 1.2 x ULN.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Clinically significant non-malignant disease including, but not limited to, major surgery within 6 weeks of randomisation, active clinically significant infection, myocardial infarction within 6 months prior to randomisation, cerebrovascular event or transient ischaemic attack within 12 months prior to randomisation or clinically significant gastrointestinal bleeding within 12 months prior to randomisation. Anti-cancer therapy within 4 weeks of Cycle 1 day 1 (excluding GnRH agonists for prostate cancer). Palliative radiation for bone metastases within 2 weeks of Cycle 1 day 1.
- Active CNS metastases. Subjects with prior CNS metastases treated by surgery and/or stereotactic irradiation are eligible providing they have no evidence of active disease at screening. Subjects with prior CNS metastases treated with only whole brain radiation therapy are ineligible.
- Subjects with uncontrolled diabetes.
- History of allergy and / or hypersensitivity and / or other clinically significant adverse drug reaction to heparin or other anti-coagulant agents.
- History of immune-mediated thrombocytopaenia or other platelet abnormalities or other hereditary or acquired coagulopathies, or laboratory evidence of anti-heparin antibodies, or any previous history of having tested positive for anti-heparin antibodies.
- Concomitant use of aspirin (&gt; 150 mg/day), non steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (except COX-2 selective inhibitors), vitamin K antagonists (other than low-dose prophylactic use), heparin within two weeks prior to randomisation, or other anti-platelet drugs (e.g. abciximab, clopidogrel, dipyridamole, ticlopidine and tirofiban). Low-dose aspirin (= 150 mg/day) and low dose prophylactic vitamin K antagonists (e.g. warfarin = 1 mg/day) are permitted as concomitant medications.
- History of severe allergic, anaphylactic or other significant adverse reaction to radiographic contrast media (iodinated or non-iodinated), which cannot be managed by pre treatment with agents such as steroids or anti histamines, and which, in the opinion of the Investigator, renders the subject unsuitable for routine CT or MRI scanning. Subjects who are contra-indicated for CT or MRI scanning for other reasons (e.g. ferromagnetic implants, profound claustrophobia), should not be enrolled.
- Known seropositivity to the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).
- Women who are pregnant or breast-feeding.
- Women of child-bearing potential and male subjects who are partners of women of childbearing potential who are unable or unwilling to practice a highly effective means of contraception. Effective birth control includes: a) birth control pills, depot progesterone, or an intrauterine device plus one barrier method, or b) two barrier methods. Effective barrier methods are: male and female condoms, diaphragms, and spermicides (creams or gels that contain a chemical to kill sperm).
- Active substance abuse, including alcohol, which, in the opinion of the Investigator, risks impairing the ability of the subject to comply with the protocol.
- Subjects who have received an investigational agent within 28 days prior to Cycle 1 Day 1; or are currently participating in any other clinical study or research project which involves administration of a pharmaceutical product or experimental treatment, or which involves protocol-specified laboratory tests, imaging studies or other investigations.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/12/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/12/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/10/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>2/05/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>23</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/10/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>22/09/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Progen Pharmaceuticals Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>2806 Ipswich Road, Darra, QLD  4076</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Progen Pharmaceuticals Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2806 Ipswich Road, Darra, QLD  4076</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to establish the maximum tolerated dose of PG545 and to evaluate its safety in subjects with advanced solid tumours.

Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are a male or female aged 18 years or above who has been diagnosed with a non haematological malignant solid tumour, excluding primary brain or spinal tumours. To be eligible patients must have failed all standard therapies, no longer be a candidate for standard therapy, have no standard therapy available, or have chosen not to pursue standard therapy.

Study details: All participants in this study will receive the drug PG545 once weekly via a 1 hour intravenous infusion (i.e. directly into the vein). Subjects will be treated until either disease progresses or they can't have further treatment due to tolerability. They will be regularly monitored throughout the treatment period in order to determine the safety and tolerability of treatment. The dose of PG545 will also be increased in new groups of patients in order to determine the maximum tolerated dose. In addition the study will explore whether PG545 exposure results in changes to chemicals produced by the body that are associated with cancer growth and spread. This is the first clinical study of PG545 administered by intravenous infusion.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road Eastwood South Australia 5063 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Millward</name>
      <address>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital, 1st Floor, B Block, Hospital Avenue, Nedlands WA  6009</address>
      <phone>+ 61 (08) 6382 5100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.millward@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Hamza  Cakan</name>
      <address>Linear Clinical Research Ltd, 1st Floor, B Block, Hospital Avenue, Nedlands WA  6009</address>
      <phone>+ 61 (08) 6382 5100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>contactus@linear.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Keith Dredge</name>
      <address>Progen Pharmaceuticals Ltd, 2806 Ipswich Rd, DARRA, QLD, AUSTRALIA, 4076</address>
      <phone>+61 (07) 3273 9179</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>clinicaltrials@progen-pharma.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Darryn Bampton</name>
      <address>Progen Pharmaceuticals Ltd, 2806 Ipswich Rd, DARRA, QLD, AUSTRALIA, 4076</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>darrynb@progen-pharma.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>