<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1116">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/02/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/12/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000508572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does combination therapy increase adherence with inhaled corticosteroids and improve clinical outcomes in asthma?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does therapy with an inhaled combination of fluticasone and salmeterol improve clinical outcomes and compliance with taking asthma medication in patients with asthma?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Randomised, single-blind, parallel group, single centre study. Patients will receive fluticasone propionate (FP) and salmeterol, either as combination inhaler therapy or as separate inhalers.  Participants will be advised to take their metered dose inhalers (2 puffs) twice daily, resulting in a daily dose of 500µg FP and 100µg salmeterol with both regimens. Adherence will be assessed by covert adherence  monitors incorporated into all inhaler devices used. Treatment will be twice daily for 24 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients will receive fluticasone propionate (FP) and salmeterol as separate inhalers</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Adherence, defined as the proportion of medication (fluticasone propionate and salmeterol either in combination or separatetly) taken as directed</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the final six week period of the study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Overuse of medication, defined as the mean number of extra doses taken per day</outcome>
      <timepoint>In the final six week period of the study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1. Adherence: defined as (i) the proportion of medication taken as directed in the first, second and third six week periods of the study and (ii) the proportion of patients who took &gt;50%, &gt;80% or &gt;90% of their mediation as prescribed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 12 weeks and 18 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Overuse: defined as (i) percentage of days in which an extra dose was taken in each six week period, (ii) maximum number of puffs taken in any one day in each six week period and (iii) number of times 'dose dumping' occurred in each six week period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks, 12 weeks and 18 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Doctor diagnosis of asthma, Currently prescribed inhaled corticosteroids (ICS), Steady dose of ICS for at least one month, No exacerbation in the previous month requiring a GP or hospital visit, No exacerbation in the run-in period.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>History of clinically significant disease which may affect the outcome of the study, Currently prescribed combination therapy (inhaled corticosteroid and long acting beta agonist in combined inhaler), No known sensitivity to beta-agonists, salmeterol or any of its ingredients.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The patients only are blinded.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/02/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GlaxoSmithKline UK Ltd.
Stockley Park West,
Uxbridge,
Middlesex,
UB11 1BT</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United Kingdom</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>GlaxoSmithKline</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GlaxoSmithKline UK Ltd.
Stockley Park West,
Uxbridge,
Middlesex,
UB11 1BT</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Asthma is a common condition which can cause significant disruptions to everyday life. There are many different drugs to treat asthma including inhaled corticosteroids (ICS) and long-acting beta-agonists (LABAs). A key problem in treating asthma is that patients sometimes do not take their medication as prescribed. This is commonly seen with ICS as they are not perceived to provide immediate relief.  Combination ICS/LABA inhalers have been developed, which could be expected to improve a patients ability to adhere to their prescription as fewer doses and inhalers are needed, compared with separate inhaler medication. The purpose of this study is to assess whether a combined ICS/LABA inhaler (Seretide) has any effect on adherence to prescribed dose compared with single dose inhalers containing Flixotide (fluticasone propionate) and Serevent (salmeterol). The study will involve a treatment period of 24 weeks and patients will attend the clinic at 6 weekly intervals. Patients will be randomly allocated to receive treatment by either combination or separate inhalers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kyle Perrin</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Level 3, 99 The Terrace
Wellington</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)4 4729199</phone>
      <fax>+64 (0)4 4729224</fax>
      <email>Kyle.Perrin@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kyle Perrin</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Level 3, 99 The Terrace
Wellington</address>
      <phone>+64 (0)4 4729199</phone>
      <fax>+64 (0)4 4729224</fax>
      <email>Kyle.Perrin@ccdhb.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>