<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343361">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000919910</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Are post-operative antibiotics indicated in simple appendicitis? A prospective randomized trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is a single dose of prophylactic antibiotics as effective as a three dose regime in preventing post-operative infection in paediatric patients with simple appendicitis?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1123-7877</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>ClinicalTrials.gov: NCT01420367</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Simple Appendicitis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Post-operative Infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Single pre-operative dose of antibiotics (IV metronidazole 12.5mg/kg up to 500mg and IV cefazolin 25mg/kg up to 1g)
administered at the time of induction.
And Normal Saline (used as a placebo) IV 10mL given at 8 and 16 hours after the antibiotics.</interventions>
    <comparator>Three doses of antibiotics:
One pre-operative dose of IV metronidazole 12.5mg/kg up to 500mg and IV cefazolin 25mg/kg up to 1g
administered at the time of induction
Two post-operative dose at 8 and 16 hours after the first dose (IV metronidazole 12.5mg/kg up to 500mg and IV cefazolin 25mg/kg up to 1g)</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post-operative infection - defined as wound infection (red, swollen, hot around site of incision), fever (temperature &gt;38.5 degrees celsius) or signs of sepsis (tachycardia, hypotension, raise white cell count and CRP).  This is assessed in hospital whilst still an inpatient and at a 6 week follow-up phone call to see if they have been ill since, seen their GP or attended hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks following surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Requirement for further antibiotics - administered by the patients general practitioner or at a hospital due to suspected infection (as per primary outcome 1).  Patients will be telephoned at 6 weeks post-operation to assess whether they have visited their GP or another hospital.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks following surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to discharge</outcome>
      <timepoint>From surgery til discharge home</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Re-admission:   Assessed with 6 week follow-up phone call to see if they have presented at hospital since the operation</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 weeks following surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients who have their appendix removed and are found on operation to have simple appendicitis as defined in the Cochrane review (an appendix that is non-inflamed, acutely inflamed, phlegmonous, suppurative or mildly inflamed).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>4</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Any patient whose guardian does not wish for them to participate in the study.
- Patients who on operation are found to have complicated appendicitis defined as an appendix that is gangrenous or perforated.  
-Patients who pre-operatively appear to be acutely septic or for another reason require extended antibiotic therapy. 
- Patients who, at operation, are found to have other pathology e.g. Meckels Diverticulum, Intussusception; requiring surgical or medical intervention.
-Patients who have additional co-morbidities, including diabetes, immuno-suppression, cardiac, renal or liver failure. 
- If the child continues to show sign of sepsis, in terms of fever, tachycardia, he/she will be discontinued from the study and be given additional doses of antibiotics, as clinically indicated.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Enrollment:  All patients who are being taken to theatre for laparoscopic appendectomy will be consented with regard to the study pre-operatively.  ). An information sheet will be provided to parents.  In theatre the surgeon makes a decision as to whether patient meets the inclusion criteria (appears to have simple appendicitis) and at this point enrolment takes place.  

Treatment Allocation:  Randomisation will occur at the pharmacy department using a computerised random number generator to determine group allocation.  The pharmacy will distribute individually labelled, identical appearing syringes containing whether antibiotics or placebo (normal saline).

Allocation Concealment:  Allocation to single or three dose groups will be triple blinded, that is concealed from the patient, treating team and outcome assessors.</concealment>
    <sequence>Random number generation using excel.  Excel is used to randomly order numbers 1 to 300 with the first 150 numbers listed being allocated to group 1 (single dose + placebo) and the second 150 being allocated to group 2 (three doses).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nicole Mennie, BMedSci Student</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Paediatrics, Department of Surgery
Southern Medical School, Faculty of Medicine, Nursing and Health Sciences, Level 5, Block E, Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Rd, Clayton, VIC 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Paediatrics, Department of Surgery, Monash Medical Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Southern Medical School, Faculty of Medicine, Nursing and Health Sciences, Level 5, Block E, Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Rd, Clayton, VIC 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Wei Cheng</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Department of Paediatrics, Department of Surgery
Southern Medical School, Faculty of Medicine, Nursing and Health Sciences, Level 5, Block E, Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Rd, Clayton, VIC 3168</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Monash University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>BMedSci Course Administrator
Faculty of Medicine, Nursing and Health Sciences
Building 15 Reception, Monash University VIC 3800</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Peter Ferguson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Paediatrics, Department of Surgery
Southern Medical School, Faculty of Medicine, Nursing and Health Sciences, Level 5, Block E, Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Rd, Clayton, VIC 3168</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project will compare patients 16 years and under with simple appendicitis (appendicitis that is not perforated or gangrenous).  Patients will be randomly divided into two groups; 
- Group one will receive a single pre-operative dose of antibiotics (metronidazole 12.5mg/kg up to 500mg and cefazolin 25mg/kg up to 1g) and two doses of normal saline (placebo) eight and sixteen hours after the initial dose, respectively.  
- Group two will receive one pre-operative dose of antibiotics (metronidazole 12.5mg/kg up to 500mg and cefazolin 25mg/kg up to 1g) and two post-operative doses, eight and sixteen hours after the first dose, respectively.  

Group allocation will be concealed from the patient and their guardian, the treating surgical team and outcome assessors (triple blinded).  A process to rapidly reveal group allocation if required will be in place. 

The aim of the study is to determine if a single dose of antibiotics is as effective as three doses in preventing post-operative infection.  This will be assessed by comparing:
- Duration of hospital stay from operation until discharge, based on a standardised discharge criteria.
- Development of wound infection or requirement of antibiotics in the six weeks post-operation 
- Need for re-admission.  

Information will be collected prospectively from each patients hospital notes and from a follow-up phone call six weeks after the operation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Unit, Level 4 Main Block
Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Rd, Clayton, VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/08/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof Wei Cheng</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatrics, Department of Surgery,
Southern Medical School, Faculty of Medicine, Nursing and Health Sciences
Level 5 Block E, Monash Medical Centre, 
246 Clayton Rd, Clayton
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61395945500</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>wei.cheng@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof Wei Cheng</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatrics, Department of Surgery,
Southern Medical School, Faculty of Medicine, Nursing and Health Sciences
Level 5 Block E, Monash Medical Centre, 
246 Clayton Rd, Clayton
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone>+61395945500</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>wei.cheng@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nicole Mennie</name>
      <address>Department of Paediatrics, Department of Surgery,
Southern Medical School, Faculty of Medicine, Nursing and Health Sciences
Level 5 Block E, Monash Medical Centre, 
246 Clayton Rd, Clayton
VIC 3168</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>nmmen4@student.monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>