<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363887">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000452796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving cardiovascular health among smokers with and without mental health problems: The iHeLP (healthy lifestyles) pilot trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In current smokers (with depression, psychosis or neither conditions), will an internet-delivered healthy lifestyles treatment (the iHeLP program) be associated with improvements in tobacco use, physical activity and diet?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1140-7668</utrn>
    <trialacronym>iHeLP pilot</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Tobacco Use</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Psychosis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Psychosis and personality disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In this study, we will pilot test an internet-delivered intervention (iHeLP) designed to reduce tobacco use, and improve cardiovascular and mental health among 3 groups of smokers: people with psychosis, people with depression, or people without a diagnosis of psychosis or depression.  

Participants smoking 10 or more cigarettes a day with or without elevated depressive symptoms or psychosis will have access to five sessions of cognitive-behavioural therapy delivered via an internet-based healthy lifestyles-focused program (iHeLP). The sessions take approximately 30 minutes to complete and participants will be asked to complete the five sessions within a ten week period.  The order of presentation of sessions will be randomised such that following completion of an initial Setting the Scene module participants will have access to the modules in one of four sequences:
1)	Setting the Scene then open access to the iHeLP program;
2)	 Setting the Scene then sequential access to Smoking Cessation (2 modules), Healthy Eating (1 module) and then Physical Activity (1 module) modules;
3)	Setting the Scene then sequential access to Healthy Eating, Physical Activity and then Smoking Cessation modules;
4)	Setting the Scene then sequential access to Physical Activity, Healthy Eating and then Smoking Cessation modules. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>All participants receive the iHeLP intervention, but in four different sequences.  We will compare treatment process and outcomes for participants completing the four different sequences of treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in tobacco use, as measured by the Opiate Treatment Index - Smoking subscale (quantity/frequency measure of tobacco use).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline-6 months post-baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in nicotine dependence (Fagerstrom Test for Nicotine Dependence)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline-6-months post-baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Standardised Residualised Change in cardiovascular risk behaviours This will include scores on the Food Frequency Questionnaire (fruit and vegetable intake), International Physical Activity Questionnaire (physical activity), Opiate Treatment Index - smoking scale (tobacco use), Depression Anxiety Stress Scale (depression), Sitting Behaviour Questionnaire (sedentary behaviours)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6-months post-baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in depressive symptoms (DASS-21 - depression scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 15-weeks post-baseline, 6-months post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in alcohol/other drug use (as measured by the Opiate Treatment Index for alcohol, cannabis, amphetamine, heroin, cocaine, trnaquilisers, barbiturates, hallucinogens, and inhalants)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline-6-months post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in caffeine consumption (as measured by the Opiate Treatment Index created to monitor energy drink consumption)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline-6-months post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceptions of internet-delivered treatments (as measured through the Internet Credibility/Expectancy Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening-Baseline-15 weeks post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in self-rated quality of life (as measured by the WHO-8 EUROHIS Quality of LIfe scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline-6-months post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Website utilisation as measured by tracking data recorded by the iHeLP program</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the 10-week treatment period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self vs. Clinician-Administered ratings of major depressive disorder (online vs. clinician-administered SCID)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 6-months post-baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be respondents to an online Facebook advertisement who reside in Australia. 

Potential eligibility will be met by those with: 
- Consumption of 10 or more cigarettes per day (indicated by self report);
- Group 1 (n=40) will have current elevated depressive symptoms (as indicated by a DASS-21, with a score greater than or equal to 14) and a lifetime diagnosis of a Major Depressive Disorder (as confirmed by a clinician administered SCID);
- Group 2 (n=40) will have a self-reported DSM diagnosis of psychosis or bipolar disorder and currently be enrolled in treatment for psychosis;
- Group 3 (n=40) will not have current elevated depressive symptoms (as indicated by a DASS-21, with a score lower than or equal to 9) with or without a lifetime diagnosis of a Major Depressive Disorder (as confirmed by a clinician administered SCID), and will not have current/previous symptoms or a diagnosis of a psychotic or bipolar disorder; and
- Access to the internet  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>94</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(a) people who are not smoking more than 10 cigarettes per day;
(b) any participant who does have access to the internet; 
(c) people under 18 years of age; 
(d) people who screen positive for psychosis but are not receiving treatment for psychosis; 
(e) people who score greater than 2 on  the SCOFF screening questionnaire for Eating Disorders.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited via Facebook to participate in a screening assessment for the eligibility criteria for the study.  Screening assessments are completed online via Survey Monkey, with participants providing consent for screening data to be retained for later analysis according to CONSORT guidelines.  Those providing consent and completing the screening assessment will then be deemed eligible/ineligible for the main study.  Those participants who are ineligible will be advised of this outcome and provided with options for referral to other services/online programs addressing healthy lifestyle issues.  Eligible participants will also receive an email advising of this outcome, with referral options provided as per the ineligible participants, which will also provide the Participant Information Statement and Consent Form in electronic format and advice regarding a time/day at which an iHeLP assessor will contact them to discuss consent and baseline assessment options.  Consent to participate in the study will be obtained verbally over the telephone and digitally recorded.  All eligible participants who provide consent will complete a baseline assessment (part online and part via telephone) covering the main primary and secondary outcomes for the pilot trial.  At the conclusion of this baseline assessment process, participants will be provided with an email that contains login details for iHeLP, instructions on how to access the modules, and advice of their randomised sequence in which to complete the modules.</concealment>
    <sequence>All participants will receive the iHeLP intervention, but will be randomised to complete the individual modules in either a set sequence or as an open access program.  The randomisation sequence associated with this phase will be generated by an independent researcher not associated with the pilot study.  Each participant will be assigned a unique study number according to a computer-generated randomisation schedule (using IBM Statistics Program Version 21), using permuted blocks of varying sizes (multiples of 4) to reduce potential for guessing.  Separate randomisation lists will be used for each of the Groups 1-3.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The effect of the treatment conditions (Sequential vs. Open; Groups 1 vs. 2 vs 3) on the primary outcome measures will be assessed using a baseline vs. 6-months post-baseline by treatment group interaction in a repeated measures random effects regression model.  Secondary outcomes will be analysed in the same way (family-wise error rate set a 0.01).  All tests will be two-sided.  A post-hoc multi-leve mixed effects model will be used to determine whether treatment groups differ in their trajectory on each outcome measure over the follow-up period.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/05/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Frances Kay-Lambkin</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of NSW
Sydney 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Tobacco, Drug Prevention &amp; Youth Policy section
Commonwealth Department of Health and Ageing</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 9848
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of NSW Goldstar Funding</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>UNSW, Sydney 2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Amanda Baker</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Robyn Richmond</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Public Health and Community Medicine
University of NSW
Sydney 2052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Bonnie Spring</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Preventive Medicine, Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences 
Northwestern University 
633 Clark Street
Evanston IL 60611</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to increase the accessibility of an innovative, evidence-based psychological treatment (Healthy Lifestyles Treatment) for reducing tobacco use, improving cardiovascular and mental health among tobacco smokers with depression, psychosis, or neither of these conditions, by translating it to internet-based delivery (iHeLP) and running a small-scale pilot study of the efficacy of this mode of delivery of treatment.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of NSW Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Secretariat
UNSW Grants Management Office
Rupert Myers Building, Level 3, South Wing
The University of New South Wales 
SYDNEY NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC12547</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Frances Kay-Lambkin</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of NSW
Sydney 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4033 5690</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.kaylambkin@unsw.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Frances Kay-Lambkin</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of NSW
Sydney 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4033 5690</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.kaylambkin@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Frances Kay-Lambkin</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of NSW
Sydney 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4033 5690</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.kaylambkin@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Frances Kay-Lambkin</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of NSW
Sydney 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4033 5690</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.kaylambkin@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>