<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369454">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001091594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of oral sensory exposure on pork sensory specific satiety: a functional magnetic resonance imaging study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of oral sensory exposure on pork sensory specific satiety: a functional magnetic resonance imaging study study in healthy human subjects</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>neural activation in healthy adults</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>subjective appetite in healthy subjects</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study will employ a randomized, two way cross-over design. All participants act as their own control. Participants will be tested on two separate days (one week washout time in between) with one of two interventions:
(1) A placebo chewing gum + standardized breakfast
(2) A pork flavored chewing gum + standardized breakfast

The flavour added to the pork flavored chewing gum related to a mixture of 2 pork ham flavours (5% Acorde JAMON1, 10% Acorde JAMON 2; Lucta SA, Montornes del Valles, Spain) , 5% monosodium glutamate (MSG) (Ajinomoto Inc., Japan), 0.05% inosine monophosphate (IMP, 4666803) and 0.05% guanosine monophosphate (GMP, 2421617) (Givaudan Australian Pty Ltd). This mimic real pork flavor (aroma and taste).

The breakfast consisted of 100g pork (cooked ham), 125g boiled rice, 50g fresh apple and 200ml of pure water. The calculated nutritional content of the meal was 1309KJ, 21.8g of crude protein, 7.5g of total fat and 40.3g of carbohydrate. Pork was the predominant protein source.

On the testing days, participants will arrive at the lab after an overnight fast,  Participants will receive a chewing gum (either placebo or pork-flavored) and will be asked to chew for 7 min (chew rate between 25-30 times per min using a metronome) before they eat the breakfast. Participants will complete two brain scanning sessions: one baseline at arrival (pre-intervention) and the other one at 60 minutes after breakfast (post-intervention) with four categories of food cues (cake, meat, fruit and salad) shown as images alone or as combined image and congruent odors. Subjective ratings of food cues were measured during scanning  as a measure of sensory specific satiety. Subjective specific appetite for sweet, savoury, fatty and salty foods were evaluated outside the scanner to test the transference of pork sensory specific satiety.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a within subjects design, participants are their own controls (receiving placebo chewing gum and pork-flavored chewing gum)

the placebo chewing gum is a 3-gram commercial gum base;
the pork-flavored gum is a 3-gram chewing gum made based on the placebo gum, with addition of the flavor compounds listed above.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>fMRI data will be collected to investigate whether the brain reward regions activations to food cues before and after the chewing gum + breakfast treatments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At arrival (before the treatment) and at 60 minutes after the treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ratings on a 13-points scales for the pleasantness of each category of food cues during scanning as a measurment of subjective sensory specific satiety</outcome>
      <timepoint>At arrival (before treatment) and at 60 min after the treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A composite measurement for sensory specific appetite for four foods with four different flavor (sweet, savory, fatty and salty flavor foods) using visual analogue scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Arrival; after the pre-treatment fMRI scan; 0 min after the treatment; 30 min after the treatment; 60 min after the treatment; and after the post-treatment fMRI scan</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>BMI (18.5-25.9), Right-handed, non-smokers, medication free, non-pregnant, no food allergies; non-vegetarianism; Safety for MRI scanning; Not cognitive dietary restraint (factor 1 score &lt; 13 measured by the three factor eating questionnaire)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>35</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Psychiatric or neurological illness; gustatory, gastrointestinal, olfactory or eating dysfunction; a body mass index (BMI) over 25.9 or below 18.5; drug or medication use; smoking; pregnancy; food allergies; vegetarianism; non breakfast eaters or a change in weight &gt; 5kg in the past 2 months.  Not safety for MRI scanning; cognitive dietary restraint</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>30/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>5/04/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>18</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Queensland, St Lucia,4072, Brisbane, QLD</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Pork CRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>JS Davies Building, University of Adelaide  Roseworthy Campus, Mudla Wirra Road, Kangaroo Flat, S.A. 5371</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Center for Nutrition and Food Sciences</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Hartley Teakle Building (#83), the University of Queensland, St Lucia,4072, Brisbane, QLD</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to study whether the flavor of pork meat, together with a standard meal, could exert higher satiating effect. The satiety will not only be studied using subjective sensation of appetite, but also by looking at the brain response to food-related visual cues and food-related odour cues using Magnetic Resonance Imaging technique. The purpose of this project is to improve the understanding of the correlation between sensory specific satiety and brain activity. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Activation of Human Orbitofrontal Cortex to Visual Only or Visual and Olfactory Food Stimuli Reflects Pork Sensory-Specific Satiety. In: Abstracts of the Australasian Association for ChemoSensory Science (AACSS). 15th Scientific Meeting of the Australasian-Association-for-ChemoSensory-Science (AACSS), Brisbane, QLD Australia, (364-364). 03-05 December 2014. doi:10.1093/chemse/bjv008</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics, Research Management Office, UQ Research and Innovation, Cumbrae-Stewart Building (#72), BRISBANE  QLD  4072</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013000254</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>PENGFEI HAN</name>
      <address>C504 Hartley Teakle Building (83#), Center for Nutrition and Food Sciences, the University of Queensland, St Lucia, 4072, QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 426 882 330</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pengfei.han@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eugeni Roura</name>
      <address>S435 Hartley Teakle Building (83#), Center for Nutrition and Food Sciences, the University of Queensland, St Lucia, 4072, QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)7 3365 2526</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.roura@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>PENGFEI HAN</name>
      <address>C504 Hartley Teakle Building (83#), Center for Nutrition and Food Sciences, the University of Queensland, St Lucia, 4072, QLD</address>
      <phone>+61 426 882 330</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pengfei.han@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>