<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367985">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000315516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Factor concentrates versus Allogeneic blood in CardioThoracic Surgery trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The influence of factor concentrates in comparison to allogeneic blood for haemostatic resuscitation in cardiac surgery on red cell transfusion rate and associated perioperative morbidities.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>FACTS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>HP TRIM Document : D/2015/9001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac Surgery</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Blood transfusion</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention arm will consist of haemostatic resuscitation comprising the use of factor concentrates, specifically a prothrombin complex concentrate (Prothrombinex-VF) and fibrinogen concentrate (RiaSTAP) titrated to point of care viscoelastic testing. Haemostatic therapy will applied when there is clinically documented bleeding (either &gt;60g net weight intraoperatively or &gt;100ml/hr mediastinal drain blood loss) and dosed according to the formulae 1. Fibrinogen concentrate (RiaSTAP) dose = ((12-A10 on FibTEM assay) x body weight)/140 and 2. Prothrombin concentrate in aliquots of 15U/kg if the clotting time (CT) on the ROTEM ExTEM is &gt;90seconds or HepTEM is &gt;240seconds. Both intervention and comparator arms will receive platelet transfusion is there is clinical bleeding and the absolute platelet count is &lt;100 x10^9 or there is a qualitative defect documented on Multiple electrode aggregometry ADPtest, TRAPtest or ASPItest assays.</interventions>
    <comparator>In the comparator arm, haemostatic resuscitation will be made using allogeneic blood products such as fresh frozen plasma and cryoprecipitate in approximate equipotent factor doses, titrated to identical point of care assay endpoints. In the presence of documented bleeding (either &gt;60g net weight intraoperatively or &gt;100ml/hr mediastinal drain blood loss) Haemostatic resuscitation will consist of 1. Cryoprecipitate as a source of fibrinogen which will be dosed in 4U aliquots until the A10 value on the FibTEM assay is &gt;12mm and 2. FFP as a source of thrombin generation in doses of 15ml/kg (approximately 2 units) until the clotting time on the ROTEM ExTEM is &lt;90seconds or HepTEM is &lt;240seconds.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Primary outcome will be red cell transfusion rate (i.e. number of red cell units per hour) and total amount, including rate of avoidance of requirement for transfusion as measured as a comparison of those not requiring transfusion in both the intervention and comparator arms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the course of admission for surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>New onset atrial fibrillation - presence or absence</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the course of admission for surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute kidney injury by RIFLE criteria and need for renal replacement therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the course of admission for surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post operative mediastinal blood loss - ml per hour and totals at 6 hours, 24 hours and total drain output</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the course of admission for surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of return to operating theatre for investigation of bleeding</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the course of admission for surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality - as a percentage of total cases</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the course of admission for surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Embolic stroke - documented either by Head CT or MRI</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the course of admission for surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vascular graft failure - confirmed by coronary catheter study within six months of the operation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the course of admission for surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Deep Venous thrombosis - confirmed by lower limb venous duplex</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the course of admission for surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pulmonary embolism - confirmed by CT pulmonary angiography or Ventilation/Perfusion scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over the course of admission for surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All adult patients, aged 18 and over, presenting for cardiac surgery at St Vincents Hospital capable of giving consent, including solid organ transplantation and patients presenting for surgery on the antiplatelet agents aspirin and/or clopidogrel and/or the anticoagulant warfarin.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Documented haemostatic disease such as Haemophilia or Von Willebrands Disease; Incapable of consent; Surgery to involve placement of a ventricular assist device either left of right sided; Known history of deep venous thrombosis, pulmonary embolism or prothrombotic disorder such as antiphospholipid syndrome; Preoperative use of an antiplatelet agent or anticoagulant other than those allowed in the inclusion criteria, such as a direct thrombin antagonist, eg dabigatran or a different antiplatelet agent such as ticagrelor.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Prospective randomised controlled trial – non-blinded - central randomisation by a computer stored in Intensive Care.</concealment>
    <sequence>Dynamic (Adaptive/Stratified) randomisation will be used to allow for equal allocation of “high risk transfusion” patients as determined by the TRUST score. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The Transfusion Risk Understanding Scoring Tool (TRUST) will be used to assess clinical risk of transfusion. (Alghamdi, Davis, Brister, &amp; Corey, 2006).</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Depending on the distribution of the data, either medians with interquartile ranges will be compared with a rank sum test or if the data is normally distributed using student's t-test. Based on the current St Vincents transfusion mean rate of 4.5U and targeting a reduction to 3.6U (ie 20%) which was achieved in the recent prospective trial of POC targeted therapy (Weber et al., 2012), we will require a minimum of 140 patients assuming a high level of variance in transfusion practise. This assumes a comparable level of variation to the German data (Weber et al., 2012) with a standard deviation of 3.8U. An interim analysis will be planned at 50 patients to assess safety and efficacy and to further refine sample and power size calculations according to the actual transfusion rates which will more than likely reduce during the study. Randomisation will be adjusted during the course of the study to attempt even allocation of high risk patients as determined using the TRUST tool. (Alghamdi et al., 2006)</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3 / Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>140</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's and Mater Health Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Vincent's and Mater Health Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aims of our study are to determine whether the use of algorithms with point of care testing to guide the use of factor concentrates can target bleeding more quickly and precisely and lead to a reduction in red cell transfusion rates compared to the use of allogeneic blood products. We will also examine its impact on other secondary outcomes, such as morbidity and mortality, bleeding and thrombotic complications.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Research Office</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, De Lacy Building
Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/02/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/SVH/418</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Lowe</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
St Vincent's Hospital Sydney
390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61283821111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.lowe@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Lowe</name>
      <address>Department of Intensive Care
390 Victoria Street
St Vincent's Hospital Sydney
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61283821111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.lowe@svha.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bruce Cartwright</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia
St Vincent's Hospital Sydney
390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61283821111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bruce.cartwright@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Bruce Cartwright</name>
      <address>Department of Anaesthesia
St Vincent's Hospital Sydney
390 Victoria Street
Darlinghurst NSW 2010</address>
      <phone>+61283821111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bruce.cartwright@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>