<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373561">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001305314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>PhyzX 2U: An evaluation of a mobile and cloud based outreach service to improve chronic disease outcomes in underserviced rural communities</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>PhyzX 2U: An evaluation of a mobile and cloud based outreach service to improve chronic disease outcomes in underserviced rural communities</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1201-4654 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>chronic disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will take part in a new 12 week mobile health service that uses a combination of face to face consultation, mobile exercise tracking and a health coaching service via telehealth to provide personalised exercise programs to people living with chronic disease in remote rural communities of NSWs Central West. This health service will be conducted by qualified exercise physiologists and physiotherapists as well as existing undergraduate students on clinical placement. Mobile clinics will be conducted in a range of rural towns at which participants will undergo an initial assessment, duration  1 hour. Telehelath (online video calls) will be used to conduct the health coaching for follow up sessions, duration 30 minutes. Telehealth sessions will be conducted by exercise physiology and physiotherapy students under the supervision of their onsite clinical educator. Frequency of telehealth health coaching sessions will be fortnightly. Track Active, an online exercise prescription platform, utilised by PhyzX 2U which enables program participants to access their exercises via a web browser or an app, and to communicate with PhyzX 2U staff to seek remote support and ask questions will be used. Adherence to the program will be collected from Track Active data.  For those participants without internet access, a record of phone calls between recipients and PhyzX 2U staff will be kept and this data will be used to measure their adherence.

 </interventions>
    <comparator>no control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self reported healthcare use- Self-reported hospitalisations and emergency department use in the past three months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 week follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise self-efficacy (ESEQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 week follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Physical Activity Stages of Change Questionnaire (PASOCQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity: Incidental and planned exercise Questionnaire (version WA)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life: EQ-5D health questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 weeks follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility and acceptance of program participants- interview
Feasibility will be measured using both
a.	Clients uptake of, and adherence to, the PhyzX 2U 12-week intervention, collected by the TrackActive data and qualitative data from the interview
b.	Clients quality of life (Eq-5D) and physical activity measures (Incidental and planned exercise Questionnaire(version WA)
	</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 week follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility and acceptance of program from facilitators - interview
Feasibility will be measured by both
a.      Staffing costs in providing the service
b.      Barriers to the provision of the program collected by qualitative data form the interview
</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 week follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant goals - Goal Attainment Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and Follow up 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1)	Enrolled PhyzX 2U program recipients:
a.	With one or more chronic diseases (diabetes, osteoarthritis, obesity, cardiovascular disease, musculoskeletal pain) for 6+ months
b.	Are eligible for a general practitioner (GP) management plan and team care arrangement (TCA).
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1)	Individuals contraindicated to undertake exercise (eg, acutely unwell or deteriorating medical condition such as late stage cancer) 
2)	Individuals unable to communicate remotely with PhyzX 2U, ie, they do not have a telephone contact number or email/internet access
3)	Individuals with a diagnosis of dementia.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>na</concealment>
    <sequence>na</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>As this is a program evaluation of a newly implemented service, our aim is to sample as broadly and completely as possible. PhyzX 2U currently runs one mobile clinic per month servicing 20 clients per clinic, so our aim is to recruit at least 50% of program recipients per clinic for the study duration. This would provide a conservative estimated total sample size of 80 program recipients with outcome measures. Power calculations indicate that 80 participants will be sufficient to detect a 22% change in goal attainment, assuming 80% power, 5% alpha and 15% drop outs
Descriptive statistics will be used to describe the sample of PhyzX 2U program recipients in terms of age, sex, number and types of chronic conditions they present with. Parametric and non-parametric paired t-tests will be used to compare changes in outcomes from baseline to post intervention to ascertain the impact of the remote health coaching intervention on clients goal attainment, quality of life, physical activity levels and self-reported health service use.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/09/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Health Sciences
East St 
Lidcombe
NSW 2141</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Faculty of Health Sciences
East St 
Lidcombe
NSW 2141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>PhyzX clinic</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Orange Arcade,
 150 Summer Street, 
Orange 
NSW 2800</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>PhyzX</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Orange Arcade, 150 Summer Street, Orange NSW 2800</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Physical activity is an effective intervention for managing many chronic diseases. The majority of the general population are not sufficiently active to meet physical activity guidelines and physical inactivity is more prevalent in people living with chronic disease. People with chronic disease require guidance from healthcare professionals to make lifestyle changes to manage their condition and improve health outcomes, however, there is a lack of healthcare professionals and services available people living in regional and remote NSW. PhyzX 2U is a new mobile service that uses a combination of face to face consultation, mobile exercise tracking and a health coaching service via telehealth to provide exercise programs to people living with chronic disease in remote rural communities of NSWs Central West. 
Objectives: To evaluate the delivery of the PhyzX2U service in its pilot phase. The specific aims are to determine the (i) feasibility, uptake and impact of the PhyzX 2U program in improving health and quality of life for people with chronic disease living in rural and remote communities; and (ii) acceptability of the PhyzX 2U program, including facilitators and barriers to implementation, from the perspectives of the providers and recipients. 
Study plan: An observational mixed methods study will be used. Health and goal outcomes from recipients of the PhyzX 2U program will be compared between program initiation and following completion of the 12-week program. Client adherence to the 12-week exercise intervention and PhyzX resources to run the program will also be determined. Semi-structured interviews will be conducted with a subsample of program recipients and program providers  to determine the acceptability of the program, and to identify facilitators and barriers to program implementation. Data will be collected between September 2017 and 30 June 2018.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>na</trialwebsite>
    <publication>na</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2 Margaret Telfer Building (K07)
The University of Sydney, NSW 2006
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/08/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2017/484</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Serene Paul</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Sydney
Rm 228, J Block 
 75 East Street 
Lidcombe 
NSW , 2141</address>
      <phone> +61 2 93519093</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serene.paul@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Serene Paul</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Sydney
Rm 228, J Block 
 75 East Street 
Lidcombe 
NSW , 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93519093</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serene.paul@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Serene Paul</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Sydney
Rm 228, J Block 
 75 East Street 
Lidcombe 
NSW , 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93519093</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serene.paul@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Serene Paul</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences, University of Sydney
Rm 228, J Block 
 75 East Street 
Lidcombe 
NSW , 2141</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93519093</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>serene.paul@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>