<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368904">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/07/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000783527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A comparison of the new laryngeal mask airway (LMA), LMA-Protector with the LMA-Supreme in surgical patients requiring airway management with an LMA. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of the LMA-Protector versus the LMA-Supreme on correct fit and positioning in surgical patients requiring LMA airway management.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1172-0054</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Airway management</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Oropharyngeal leak pressure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Downfolding of epiglottis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The LMA-Protector is a new single-use, silicone, TGA- approved device that has similar features to other LMAs  made of PVC. The silicone composition of the LMA-Protector makes it very flexible and the device allows access to and functional separation of the ventilation and digestive tracts with 2 drainage channels. Its use involves insertion under anaesthesia and inflation of the cuff once correct position in the hypopharynx is achieved. Duration of use is from the start of general anaesthesia to the end of the surgical procedure, and total time is dependent on the surgical procedure. The anaesthetist will administer the intervention and record a log of use time.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment is the single-use LMA device, the LMA-Supreme made of PVC with a drain tube to separate the ventilation and digestive tracts and a strong inner cuff to prevent airway obstruction. Use of both the LMA- Protector and the control LMA-Supreme involves insertion under anaesthesia and inflation of the cuff once correct position in the hypopharynx is achieved. Duration of use for each device is from the start of general anaesthesia to the end of the surgical procedure, with total time dependent on the surgical procedure. The anaesthetist will administer the intervention or the control treatment and record a log of use time.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oropharyngeal leak pressure assessed by detection of audible noise by neck stethoscopy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On device insertion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anatomical position of the device in the hypopharynx is assessed by the anaesthetist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On device insertion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether the correct size of the device is used as assessed by the anaesthetist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On device insertion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Whether the epiglottis is downfolded, as assessed by the anaesthetist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On device insertion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Manoeuvers needed to adjust malplacement as assessed by the anaesthetist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>On device insertion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>American Society of Anesthesiology physical status grade 1-3 and scheduled elective surgery under general anaesthesia.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who are pregnant, at risk of aspiration of gastric contents, requiring surgery in a position other than supine, undergoing head and neck surgery, or need endotracheal intubation.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomised controlled single-blinded trial. Allocation concealment performed by contacting the holder of the allocation schedule on computer at central administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation schedule was created using Stata software for the 2-treatment study, and saved as a Microsoft Excel file. Using 2 block sizes, the block identity number (blockid), number of patients in each block (blocksize) and each recruited patient’s sequence within their block (SeqInBlk) are recorded.  Two treatment arms are labelled “protector” or “supreme”. Patients are allocated in the ratio 1:1 to these two treatments.
</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical power of the oropharyngeal leak test was evaluated on a continuous scale at which each patients oropharyngeal leak was detected, as modelled from a meta-analysis in this subject area published by Maitra et al in 2014. This study provided data to allow assumption that the oropharyngeal leak pressure within each subject group would be normally distributed with standard deviation 5 cm H2O. Based on this data, the participant number of 100 was selected. With 50 interventional participants and 50 controls, this provides comparison with a probability (power) of 80% to detect this difference, with a 2-tailed type I error of 0.05. Analysis of the difference between the means and descriptive analyses of demographic data and risk factors will be performed. Risk difference and risk ratio of the two groups will be calculated. Intention to treat methodology will be followed.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>23/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>100</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>23/06/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Royal Brisbane Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Butterfield Street, Herston QLD 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>St Lucia Qld 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In this study we are comparing two laryngeal mask airways (LMAs), a current model which is commonly used with the latest model of the device for flexibility, traumatic effect and ease of optimal positioning. We are performing a randomised controlled study to find out which device performs better in clinical practice. We are randomly selecting people to the groups and giving each a different device. The results will be compared to see if one is better. There is a 50:50 chance of being in one group or the other.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital Human Reseaerch Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Butterfield Street, Herston. QLD 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/QRBW/248</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andre van Zundert </name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Department of Anaesthesia, Butterfield Street, Herston. QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+617 36465673</phone>
      <fax>+617 36461308</fax>
      <email>vanzundertandre@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Heather Reynolds</name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine, Butterfield Street, Herston. QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+617 36465453</phone>
      <fax>+617 36461308</fax>
      <email>heather.reynolds@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Andre van Zundert </name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine, Butterfield Street, Herston. QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+617 36465673</phone>
      <fax>+617 36461308</fax>
      <email>vanzundertandre@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Heather Reynolds</name>
      <address>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital, Department of Anaesthesia and Perioperative Medicine, Butterfield Street, Herston. QLD 4029</address>
      <phone>+617 36465453</phone>
      <fax>+617 36461308</fax>
      <email>heather.reynolds@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>