<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366841">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000381381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving Care Processes for Patients with Possible Acute Coronary Syndrome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An accelerated diagnostic pathway for ruling out Acute Coronary Syndrome in patients presenting to the Emergency Department with chest pain: does this improve rates of safe (no increase in MACE) discharge within 6 hours.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1159-9891</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ICare-ACS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Coronary Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Acute Myocardial Infarction
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is an audit of a change of practice mandated by the Ministry of Health to implement an accelerated chest pain pathway for suspected Ischaemic Heart Disease into New Zealand hospitals, requiring reliable and consistent retrospective collection of  chest pain data. Each of the eight hospitals will have control period of 6 months prior to the implementation of the accelerated pathway and a minimum of 4 months of cases following the implementation.  Implementation will begin in each of the eight sites in a staggered fashion (1 month apart).  The total data collection time, including a 30 day follow up, will be 18 months.  
Each site will determine its own accelerated pathway based on current evidence and local conditions.  This will comprise biochemistry (a 0h high sensitive troponin I or T, and a 2 or 3 hour second high sensitive troponin, ECG, and a risk evaluation with an appropriate scoring system with a decision point for assigning to low risk and therefore eligible for early discharge).  Sites vary in practice at the moment.  For most sites this will mean measuring an earlier time point second troponin, and implementation of a scoring system not currently implemented. </interventions>
    <comparator>This study is an audit the implementation of an accelerated chest pain pathway for suspected Ischaemic Heart Disease.  Each site is its own control (6 months prior to the implementation of the pathway).  Current practice varies between sites.  In all sites a high sensitive troponin (T or I) is measured on entry to the ED, along with an ECG, a patient history is compiled.  Beyond this, sites vary with the timing of a second troponin and the use of a risk assessment scoring system.  Clinical judgment rather than structured methodology to assess for Low Risk is used.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of service delivery: The proportion of patients successfully discharged home within 6 hours of ED arrival.  A successful discharge is one with no major adverse cardiac event (MACE) during the following 30 days </outcome>
      <timepoint>By 31 March 2015 data will have been collected from the proposed pilot sites. Analysis of patient 30 day follow-up data (for MACE outcomes) will then allow improvements to service delivery before implementation of the new pathway across all district health boards.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The ratio of patients with two troponin measurements within 24 hours compared to one.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Troponin measurements on individual patients within 24 hours of ED presentation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective analysis of lessons learnt of the implementation of the new pathway based on semistructured interviews with staff and informal feedback to study authors</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be completed by the study end.  It is intended to be an assessment of common barriers and solutions to the change of practice which be made available to non-participating hospitals which are also undergoing a change of practice.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults (greater than or equal to 18 years of age), Serial troponin testing for possible cardiac disease as indicated by a cardiac troponin test performed during initial assessment in the ED with a 2nd test performed within 24 hours of attendance.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>A clear non-coronary cause of chest pain, Domiciled overseas.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Successful discharge (without the occurrence of MACE) will be compared between control and intervention arms using a Mantel-Haenszel test for stratified data. Given 5-10% of ED presentations are for Chest Pain, and an annual ED presentation of over 360,000 patients, we expect between 9,000 and 18,000 patients in the control arm and 11,000 to 22,000 in the intervention arm (average duration of intervention is 7.5 months). In the Christchurch randomised control trial of a Modified TIMI score successful discharge occurred in 19.3% compared with 11% in the control pathway (8.3% absolute difference).  If we assume a similar control group rate of successful early discharge (11%), then, conservatively, 9,000 patients in the control arm and 11,000 in the intervention arm will allow detection of an absolute difference of 1.5% at an alpha of 0.05 and with 90% power. We expect even such a small difference will have beneficial health outcomes and economic effects.  </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>6/04/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/12/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>31332</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/01/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Martin Than</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Canterbury District Health Board and Emergency Care Foundation
c/- 21 Taylors Mistake Road
Sumner
Christchurch 8081</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 5541, Wellesley Street, Auckland 1141</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor John Pickering</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>c/- Emergency Care Foundation
P O Box 13-149
Christchurch 8141</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to collect reliable and consistent data relating to a NZ Ministry of Health initiative implementing
an accelerated chest pain pathway for suspected Ischaemic Heart Disease into New Zealand hospitals.
The Ministry of Health has now introduced their requirement for district health boards to introduce accelerated assessment pathways and frameworks as a standard of care for service delivery in New Zealand hospitals. This requirement has been introduced into district health board annual plans and national regional service frameworks. It is planned that all hospitals within New Zealand will be using or near to using such pathways by June 2015. As part of this service implementation a small minimum dataset is planned using health information which is already collected in order to monitor the effectiveness of this service rollout.
The purpose of this project is to focus on producing a very robust dataset in the early adopting sites which will introduce the pathway in a preplanned sequence in order to demonstrate incremental benefits at each site that becomes active. There will also be careful collection of lessons learned regarding the implementation of pathways in each site which will be deliberately passed on to successive sites and hospitals which are not part of the study and which will be introduced in the procedures later.
The purpose of this project therefore is to produce high quality information on the effectiveness and lessons
learned from this service improvement with which it will be possible to inform the Ministry of Health and other New
Zealand hospital sites.
Context: Of the thousands of patients who present to NZ emergency departments every year with suspected cardiac
chest pain, approximately 20% could be discharged early which could reduce patient worry, increase clinician availability to acutely ill patients, reduce ED overcrowding and admissions, and thereby reduce unnecessary healthcare costs.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>c/- Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/NTB/107</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/07/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366841-Protocol for ICARE-ACS v 1.0 140728.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366841-HDEC_Letter_-_14NTB107_-_Out_of_Scope_Application.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Martin Than</name>
      <address>Canterbury District Health Board and Emergency Care Foundation
21 Taylors Mistake Road
Sumner
Christchurch 8081</address>
      <phone>+64 3 326 7599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martinthan@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Martin Than</name>
      <address>c/- Christchurch Hospital
Private Bag 4710
Christchurch 8140
</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3640 640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martin.than@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>John Pickering</name>
      <address>c/- Emergency Care Foundation
P O Box 13-149
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 21 253 7877</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john.pickering@icloud.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Martin Than</name>
      <address>21 Taylors Mistake Road
Sumner
Christchurch 8081</address>
      <phone>+64 3 326 7599</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martinthan@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>