<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82555">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/01/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/01/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000060347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A phase II/III study to evaluate the efficacy and safety of MD 920 (Gibberellic Acid and Salt 1:1)  in patients with hard to heal chronic venous ulceration</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase IIb/III, Randomised, Multi Centre Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of MD 920 (Gibberellic Acid and Salt 1:1) Adsorbed to a Non Adhesive Dressing Used with Standard 4 Layered Compression Therapy Compared with Standard 4 Layered Compression Therapy alone in Participants with Hard to Heal Chronic Venous Ulceration</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>venous leg ulcers</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Gibberellic Acid and Salt 1:1 knowna as MD920 adsorbed onto a non-adhesive wound contact layer dressing in the amount of 0.5mg/cm2.This equates to a total administered dose of 50mg of MD920. This wound contact layer will be applied weekly to the ulcer.
Multi-layer compression bandage will be changed weekly. 
The treatment period will consist of 12 weekly applications of MD920 and compression bandage changes.</interventions>
    <comparator>compression bandage alone changed weekly</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the healing efficacy and safety of MD 920 (gibberellic acid and salt 1:1) applied topically to target venous leg ulcer as evidenced by the percentage reduction in wound size</outcome>
      <timepoint>from baseline compared to week 12 following randomisation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the early healing efficacy of MD 920 (gibberellic acid and salt 1:1) applied topically to venous leg ulcers as evidenced by the proportion of participants who have complete healing</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of treatment period (week12 following randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life measures (SF 36 and Cardiff Wound Impact Schedule).</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, at end of treatment and at 3 month follow up (week12 following randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of treatment related adverse events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of treatment period (week12 following randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure reliability and acceptability (withdrawals).</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of treatment period(week12 following randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of adverse effects and serious adverse events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of treatment period(week12 following randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluate self-reported compliance of compression bandage.</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of treatment period(week12 following randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Economic evaluation</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of treatment period(week12 following randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of recurrence rates</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of treatment period (week 12 following randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male and female study participants who meet all of the following criteria can be entered into the study:
1.	Presence of a venous ulcer that is confirmed by a venous duplex scan (performed by an experienced vascular technologist or ultrasonographer) to be the result of chronic venous insufficiency. 
2.	Aged over 18 years.
3.	Present with clinical evidence of chronic venous insufficiency and chronic venous ulceration as evidenced by one or more of the following:
i. 	lower limb pigmentation, 
ii.	varicose eczema,
iii.	lipodermatosclerosis,
iv.        	varicose veins.
4.	Chronic venous leg ulcer (target ulcer) that 
i.	Has been present for at least 6 weeks but no longer than 52 weeks,
ii.	is of an area equal to or greater than 3 cm2 but less than or equal to 20 cm2 as measured by digital planimetry techniques,
iii.	has no evidence of malignancy,
iv.	has no other aetiological factors, e.g. neuropathic, arterial, or vasculitic.
5.	Clear of cardiac abnormalities evidenced by a normal ECG reading.
6.	Ankle Brachial Pressure index of equal or greater than 0.8 mmHg.
7.	Ankle circumference of greater than 18 cm and less than 25 cm (Profore®  bandaging guidelines).
8.	Mobile, and able to return for required treatments and study evaluations without undue hardship.  
9.	Able to give Informed Consent. A reasonable attempt will be made to provide a translator to those who are unable to speak and read English fluently.  
10.	Able to understand and comply with the requirements of the trial. 
11.	Female study participants of child bearing potential who have a negative pregnancy test.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Study participants who meet any of the following criteria will not be eligible for participation in this study:
1.	Unable or unwilling to wear compression bandage as directed.
2.	Allergy to any of the trial products used. 
3.	Prior adverse reaction to compression products.
4.	Immobility. 
5.	Ankle circumference &lt; 18 cm or &gt; 25 cm (Profore®  bandaging guidelines). 
6.	Participation in any other clinical trial or exposure to an investigational drug within 30 days of study enrolment.
7.	Evidence of severe liver disease, cardiac disease or chronic pulmonary disease. 
8.	History of immunologically mediated disease (for example inflammatory bowel disease, rheumatoid arthritis, systemic lupus erythematosus).
9.	Medical condition likely to require systemic corticosteroids during the study period.  
10.	Any significant condition that may preclude the participant from the study (e.g. severe depression or psychiatric illness).
11.	Presence of malignant disease or documented history of malignant disease excluding dermatological malignancy (study participants with a five year disease free interval may be considered at the discretion of the Investigator).
12.	Clinically documented thrombo-phlebitis or suspected deep vein thrombosis.
13.	Abnormal laboratory results deemed clinically significant by the Investigator.
14.	Unable or unwilling to attend clinic for weekly treatment
15.	Participation in this trial previously and/or who dropped out or were withdrawn</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>To decrease bias and confounders the decision to accept or reject a participant will be made using inclusion and exclusion criteria. Informed consent will be obtained by participant without knowing the next assignment in the sequence. Independent clinicians will apply compression bandage systems according to the computer generated list allocation. The code will be revealed to the researchers once the recruitment, data collection and wound measurement analysis are completed. The allocation list will be stored with CRO.</concealment>
    <sequence>Patients will be randomised to receive either control or intervention group using a central computer generated random number generated by Trident Clinical Research. The randomization code will be sent to the Investigator (or designee) who will prepare treatments according to the randomisation code. Randomisation will be stratified by site and wound size =10cm2 or &gt;10cm2.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>158</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>3004</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>AUS BIO Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Unit 1/27 Normanby Road
NottingHill 3168</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AUS BIO Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 1/27 Normanby Road
NottingHill 3168</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Monash University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dept. Epidemiology and Preventative Medicine
Burnet Building, Alfred Hospital
Commercial road Melbourne 3004</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Research and Ethics Unit</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/11/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/11/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Peter Jenkins</name>
      <address>Unit 1/27 Normanby Road
NottingHill 3168</address>
      <phone>03 9562 6844</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ausbio@bigpond.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carolina Weller</name>
      <address>Dept. Epidemiology and Preventative Medicine
Burnet Building, Alfred Hospital
Commercial road Melbourne 3004</address>
      <phone>03 99030623</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carolina.weller@med.monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>