<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367317">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000507583</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of oligofructose and inulin in management of chronic nonspecific diarrhoea of childhood  intervention study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Safety and efficacy of a combination of oligofructose and inulin used for chronic nonspecific diarrhoea of childhood when compared with dietary recommendations </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1163-3812</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic nonspecific diarrhoea of childhood</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Name of intervention: oral supplement of 4 g of inulin enriched with  oligofructose (1/1, 2g oligofructose and 2g inulin per day), 1 sachet/day,   for 3 months consecutively 

Strategy used to monitor adherence to the intervention: sachets return </interventions>
    <comparator>Dietary recommendation administrated during the enrollment visit lasting for 45 minutes of face-to-face discussion with pediatrician and parents that could ask questions about the diet: Fruit juice intake minimized, juice with low sucrose and fructose loads; normal caloric intake; not to restrict fiber, and to assure adequate but not overhydration (150ml/kg/d)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: duration of acute episodes in chronic nonspecific diarrhoea  
acute episode: defined as increased stool frequency with changes of stool consistency appreciated according to the Bristol Stool Form Scale, where 1 represents hard stools, 7 indicates watery stools, scores lower than 5 indicate normal stool
duration of acute episodes:  is defined as the time from the first loose stool, until at least 12 hours without stool.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: during intervention and 3 months after intervention stopped 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2: severity of acute episode in chronic nonspecific diarrhoea evaluated by association of symptoms: vomiting, abdominal pain, constipation; this was marked with Yes/No answers and counted as episodes per period between visits</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: during intervention and 3 months after intervention stoped </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for antibiotic use for acute infectious intestinal episodes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: during intervention and 3months after intervention stoped </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>use of antibiotics for any reasons, acute infections during the follow up procedure; the first one refers to intestinal infections and the second one refers to use of antibiotics in general</outcome>
      <timepoint>during intervention and 3 months after intervention stoped</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>safety and efficiency of the supplement appreciated by a questionnaire completed by parents in terms of treatment efficiency and acceptance (very good/ good/ moderate were the answers options).</outcome>
      <timepoint>during intervention and 3 months after intervention stoped</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>hospitalization : yes/no answers, duration of hospitalization in days</outcome>
      <timepoint>during the follow up procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) age 1 to 5 years
(2) at least 5 episodes of diarrhoea in the last 6 months
(3) normal weight and length for age
(4) normal development 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>5</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>comorbidities of any kind
abnormal nutritional status
acute infections
food allergies
coeliac disease
inflammatory bowel disease
gastrointestinal malformation
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis was performed using linear regression, and p values of &lt; 0.05 were considered statistically significant. The descriptive results were emphasized using means (+/-SD) or medians and interquantile ranges. Comparative results were obtained with T-test and Mann-Whitney U-tests. Data were summarize for demographic characteristics , efficacy observation and safety observation using standard deviation statistics. We choose to enroll all patients that had the inclusion criteria through clinical assumption, as a pilot study.  Sample size was calculated assuming a proportion of 0.7, with 0.05 precision and a confidence level of 80%.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/11/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/11/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>22/02/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>22/02/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>54</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <state>Bucharest</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>"Grigore Alexandrescu” Children Emergency Hospital </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>30-32 Iancu de Hunedoara Boulevard, zip code 11743, Bucharest</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Romania</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>"Grigore Alexandrescu” Children Emergency Hospital 
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>30-32 Iancu de Hunedoara Boulevard, zip code 11743, Bucharest</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Romania</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We included patients aged 1 to 5 years old, with at least 5 episodes of diarrhea in the last 6 months fulfilling the criteria of chronic nonspecific diarrhea.
The first 31 patients represented the interventional group, named Group A, and the next 23 patients were in the control group (marked as Group B). Group A received a combination of oligofructose and inulin, 4 g/day, divided in 2 daily oral doses for a period of 3 months, and Group B received only dietary recommendations, according to the current guideline.
The follow up evaluation included 6 medical visits, the first visit was at the time of inclusion, the second was after 2 weeks, the 3rd visit was after another 2 weeks, the 4th and 5th visits were performed every 30 days and the 6th visit took place after 3 months. 
The first end point was obtained by comparing clinical efficiency evaluated using gastrointestinal symptoms (vomiting, abdominal pain, constipation) marked with Yes/No answers and counted as episodes per period between visits, number of acute episodes (defined as increased stool frequency with changes of stool consistency) appreciated according to the Bristol Stool Form Scale, where 1 represents hard stools, 7 indicates watery stools, scores lower than 5 indicate normal stool, and the duration of acute episodes is defined as the time from the first loose stool, until at least 12 hours without stool.
The second end point consisted of hospitalization (Yes/No answers and the duration of hospitalization according to medical files), use of antibiotics   (Yes/No answers were registered), safety and efficiency appreciated by a questionnaire completed by parents in terms of treatment efficiency and acceptance (very good/ good/ moderate were the answers options). 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1. 47th Annual Meeting of The European Society for Pediatric Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Nutrition 9 - 12 June 2014 Jerusalem, Israel; Chronic nonspecific diarrhea of childhood : Does oligofructose and inuline combination really work? Cristina Becheanu, Iulia Tincu, Roxana Smadeanu, Ana Maria Bradeanu, Gabriela Lesanu; poster presentation; abstract published in JPGN, Volume 58, Supplement 1, June 2014.
2. 2nd International Symposium of Probiotics and Prebiotics in Pediatrics March 7-9, 2014, Antalya,Turkey; Does combination of oligofructose and inuline reduce the severity of chronic nonspecific diarrhea of childhood? Becheanu Cristina, Lesanu Gabriela, Smadeanu Roxana, Tincu Iulia; oral presentation.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of : "Grigore Alexandrescu” Children Emergency Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>30-32 Iancu de Hunedoara Boulevard, zip code 11743, Bucharest
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/09/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12724</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Romania</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Becheanu Cristina Adriana</name>
      <address>"Grigore Alexandrescu Children Emergency Hospital, 30-32 Iancu de Hunedoara Boulevard, zip code 11743, Bucharest</address>
      <phone>+40213169366</phone>
      <fax>+40213127938</fax>
      <email>cbecheanu@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tincu Iulia Florentina</name>
      <address>"Grigore Alexandrescu Children Emergency Hospital, 30-32 Iancu de Hunedoara Boulevard, zip code 11743, Bucharest</address>
      <phone>+40725535100</phone>
      <fax>+40213127938</fax>
      <email>if_boian@yahoo.com </email>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Becheanu Cristina Adriana</name>
      <address>"Grigore Alexandrescu Children Emergency Hospital, 30-32 Iancu de Hunedoara Boulevard, zip code 11743, Bucharest</address>
      <phone>+40213169366</phone>
      <fax>+40213127938</fax>
      <email>cbecheanu@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tincu Iulia Florentina</name>
      <address>30-32 Iancu de Hunedoara Boulevard, zip code 11743, Bucharest</address>
      <phone>+40725535100</phone>
      <fax>+40213127938</fax>
      <email>if_boian@yahoo.com </email>
      <country>Romania</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>