<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373306">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001085369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can pro-active presentation of information about current health related research increase the general population's interest in this?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of providing information on health related research in a hospital waiting room on interest and attitudes to research amongst patients and visitors</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1199-3106</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Interest in health related research</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A large TV screen is put up in the waiting room at the emergency department (ED) waiting-room. It is linked to a device presenting an extract from a project database of local current health or medical related research. A software presents one project at the time rotating with a 3D-like graphics and the information displayed is automatically updated. The type of information displayed is:
a) Title adapted for lay persons.
b) Brief summary adapted for lay persons.
c) Name of principal investigator and work place for this investigator.
d) Link to a website with more information.
e) A QR code with a link to a website with more information.
Any research related to Health or Medicine (including Dentistry, Nursing, Physiotherapy) is presented as long as any workplace in the local region is involved. The exposure of this intervention may vary for each person pending on their time in the waiting room. We will not approach them with the survey until at least 10 minutes has passed from they have passed reception and sat down. The TV screens will be turned on stepwise as described below. After turned on they will stay turned on until sufficient number of surveys are collected. It is anticipated that all surveys will be collected during 2017. The study is formally completed after that has been done and it will then be up to each hospital to decide if they want to keep the monitor or remove it.</interventions>
    <comparator>The intervention is introduced in a step-wedge randomised design in the two participating hospitals. The first phase collects 500 surveys before any TV screen is turned on. The second phase collects another 500 with one TV-screen at one hospital turned on. The third phase collects 500 surveys with TV screen turned on at both hospitals. The switch between phases is done as soon as the requested number of surveys in each phase is achieved.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants being interested in current local health related research. The question posed is "How interested are you in current local research related to health and medicine?". The response alternatives are "Not at all", "Somewhat" and "Very".</outcome>
      <timepoint>Asked at a single occasion at time of ED visit (either before or after introduction of the TV screens, depending on the timing of their visit)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of patients appreciating being informed about current local health related research. The question posed is "This waiting room has a TV displaying information about current local research related to health and medicine. How interesting do you find the displayed information?". The response alternatives are "Not at all", "Somewhat" and "Very".</outcome>
      <timepoint>Asked at one occasion after introduction of TV screens</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To what extent is the current interest changed by turning on pro-active information about local current research? This is assessed by comparing responses from surveys before and after the TV monitor is turned on (see section Statistical methods / analysis).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Asked at a single occasion at time of ED visit, either before or after introduction of the TV screens, depending on the timing of their visit (see section Statistical methods / analysis). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All individuals (patients or their relatives/friends) attending the waiting room in the emergency department at Mackay and Cairns hospitals meeting the inclusion criteria:
 Walking in (excludes patients transported to ED in ambulance).
 Deemed to be able to sit in the waiting room for their turn (excludes patients with an illness requiring immediate attention).
 Being at least 18 years of age.
 Deemed to have a reasonable understanding of English.
 Deemed to have enough vision to be able to read the survey
 Accept participation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The intervention (TV screens informing about local current health related research) is introduced stepwise where randomisation decides if the intervention is first introduced in Hospital A or hospital B. Measurements are made in both hospitals at three occasions:
a) Before introduction of intervention
b) After introduction of intervention in one site
c) After introduction of intervention in both sites</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Research questions:
1) What proportion of patients in an ED waiting room in North Queensland express an interest in knowing about current health and medical research in their surroundings?
2) Do patients express any appreciation of being informed about current health and medical research in the surroundings by an automated information presentation?
3) What is the potential effect on interest in health related research by actively presenting information to the general public using large TV screens?
  
Corresponding statistical analysis:
1) Proportions with 95% confidence interval will be calculated. We will use logistic regression to further describe the typical patient being interested in medical research.
2) Proportions with 95% confidence interval will be calculated. We will use logistic regression to further describe the typical patient appreciating the automated information presentation.
3) The correlation between patients interested in health and medical research (question D in the survey) and if the patient visited before or after introduction of TV screens will be analysed in a random effect model using hospital as a random effect and intervention (before-after TV screens) as a fixed effect. Gender and age will be included as covariates if they differ between before-after TV screens.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>23/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>500</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/11/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>4870 - Cairns City</postcode>
    <postcode>4740 - Mackay</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>James Cook University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Research office, College of Medicine and Dentistry
James Cook University
Medical 1 (Building 39), Room 126, Townsville campus
James Cook Drive
Townsville, QLD 4811</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>James Cook University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Research office, College of Medicine and Dentistry
James Cook University
Medical 1 (Building 39), Room 126, Townsville campus
James Cook Drive
Townsville, QLD 4811</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Far North Queensland Hospital Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>c/o Tony Franz
Ground Level,
E-Block,
Corner Digger and Grove St,
Cairns, QLD 4870
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Far North Queensland Hospital Foundation</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>c/o Tony Franz
Ground Level,
E-Block,
Corner Digger and Grove St,
Cairns, QLD 4870</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Feeling informed about research seems to correlate with positive attitudes towards researchers and greater trust in researchers. However, many people feel they are not informed enough about ongoing research. 86% of the Australian population seems to be somewhat or very interested in health and medical research suggesting that the population would be rather receptive if we present the information in an acceptable way. Formal peer reviewed publications are lacking in this topic.
  
Recruitment of participants to research projects depends on a reasonable interest for research among the general population. The interest for research among the general population in north Queensland is not yet elucidated. Furthermore, any activity that may increase the general population's interest in health care related research might have a positive influence on recruitment to future research projects.
  
This project aim to estimate:
1) What proportion of patients in an ED waiting room in North Queensland express an interest in knowing about current health and medical research in their surroundings?
2) Do patients express any appreciation of being informed about current health and medical research in the surroundings by an automated information presentation?
3) What is the potential effect on interest in health related research by actively presenting information to the general public using large TV screens?</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee Townsville HHS</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Unit
IMB 52, PO Box 670
Townsville QLD 4810</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/QTHS/174</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373306-Study protocol version 2.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373306-2015-11-18 --- HREC Approval-15QTHS174_4 Approved.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373306-2015-08-14 --- Questionnaire before TV.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/373306-2015-08-14 --- Questionnaire after TV.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ronny Gunnarsson</name>
      <address>Cairns Clinical School
College of Medicine and Dentistry
James Cook University
Cairns Hospital
PO Box 902
Cairns, QLD 4870
</address>
      <phone>+61(0)742267391</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ronny.gunnarsson@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ronny Gunnarsson</name>
      <address>Cairns Clinical School
College of Medicine and Dentistry
James Cook University
Cairns Hospital
PO Box 902
Cairns, QLD 4870</address>
      <phone>+61(0)742267391</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ronny.gunnarsson@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ronny Gunnarsson</name>
      <address>Cairns Clinical School
College of Medicine and Dentistry
James Cook University
Cairns Hospital
PO Box 902
Cairns, QLD 4870</address>
      <phone>+61(0)742267391</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ronny.gunnarsson@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ronny Gunnarsson</name>
      <address>Cairns Clinical School
College of Medicine and Dentistry
James Cook University
Cairns Hospital
PO Box 902
Cairns, QLD 4870</address>
      <phone>+61(0)742267391</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ronny.gunnarsson@jcu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>