<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365215">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/12/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000003673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A single-blind randomised controlled trial of topical Kanuka honey for the treatment of Acne</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In adult patients with Acne will topical medical grade Kanuka honey, in addition to washing with Protex Soap Fresh Antibacterial, reduce acne severity compared with washing with Protex Soap Fresh Antibacterial alone.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1146-7415</utrn>
    <trialacronym>KH07</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acne</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Topical medical grade Kanuka honey with 10% glycerin content applied to the affected facial area twice daily for 30-60 minutes per application, for twelve weeks.  Patients will then wash area with Protex Soap Fresh Antibacterial medicated soap as per manufacturer's instructions, twice daily after honey treatment. A patient diary will record applications during the treatment period.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard care is Protex Soap Fresh Antibacterial medicated soap. Patients in both arms of the study will wash with Protex Soap Fresh Antibacterial medicated soap twice daily as per manufacturer's instructions. The active ingrediant in Protex Antibacterial Soap is Trichlorocarbanilide 0.7%

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of subjects who have a 2 or greater improvement in Investigator Global Assessment (IGA) score for Acne Vulgaris.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and Week 12 visits</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean IGA score</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Week 4 and Week 12 visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean lesion count.  Lesion count will be subdivided into inflamed and non-inflamed lesions.  Lesions will be graded using the Leeds revised Acne grading system.

The lesion count will be performed by the blinded investigator.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Week 4 and Week 12 visits.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in subject-rated global Acne improvement using Visual Analogue Score (VAS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Week 4 and Week 12 visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subject-rated global Acne severity VAS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and Week 4 visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dermatology Life Quality Index (DLQI)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, Week 4 and Week 12 visits</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily self-reported use (applications per day)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weekly self-reported global Acne severity (VAS scale)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weekly for 12 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Withdrawals due to worsening of acne</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the point of withdrawal</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 16-40 years at the time of enrolment
Baseline facial IGA (investigator Global Assessment) of 2 or greater</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Any significant systemic illness 
Current requirement for systemic corticosteroid or has had systemic corticosteroid in the 4 weeks prior to Visit 1 Current requirement for oral antibiotic treatment for acne, or has had oral antibiotic treatment for acne in the 4 weeks prior to Visit 1
Current requirement for topical corticosteroid or topical antibiotics for the treatment of acne
Change in oral contraceptive therapy in the last 3 months 
A systemic retinoid in the 2 months prior to Visit 1 
Known or suspected allergy to honey, or Protex Soap Fresh Antibacterial 
Any other condition which, at the investigators discretion, it is believed may present a safety risk or impact the feasibility of the study or the study results </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible patients will be randomised into the study.  Treatment allocation will be randomised in a 1:1 ratio to receive either washing with Protex Soap Fresh Antibacterial alone, twice daily, or application of topical Kanuka honey prior to washing with Protex Soap Fresh Antibacterial, twice daily.  Randomisation envelopes will contain details of treatment allocation per patient. </concealment>
    <sequence>Biostatistitian to generate randomisation schedule.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Subjects and study site staff will not be blinded to the treatment allocation.  An independent investigator at each site will remain blinded to the treatment allocation throughout the study and perform the IGA assessment.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We anticipate the proportion of participants in the control group who respond will be between 25 and 50%.  A total of 124 participants (62 in each group) has 80% power at 5% significance to detect an absolute difference of 25% responders.  Recruitment of 138 participants allows for a 10% drop-out rate. 

Logistic regression will be used to test for the difference in response rates defined as the proportion of participants who have greater than or equal to two point improvement in the Investigator Global Assessment score for Acne Vulgaris at week 12 compared to baseline.

The continuous secondary outcome variables will be analysed using ANOVA with baseline readings as a continuous co-variate. Daily self-reported use will be analysed by Poisson regression.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/02/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/02/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>11/06/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>138</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>136</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Honeylab Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Honeylab Ltd
305 Karaka Bay Road
Wellington 6022</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Honeylab Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Honeylab Ltd
305 Karaka Bay Road
Wellington 6022</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Private Bag 7902
Wellington 6242</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A recent pilot study using a Kanuka honey product for Acne showed that over 80% of participants self reported improvement, therefore this study treatment has the potential to be an effective treatment for Acne symptoms. In this study 138 adults with Acne will either wash their face with Protex Soap Fresh Antibacterial alone twice daily, or apply topical Kanuka honey to areas of Acne on their face for 30-60 minutes twice a day prior to washing with Protex Soap Fresh Antibacterial for 12 weeks. At baseline and after 4 weeks and 12 weeks the patient's Acne will be assessed to look at changes in severity. Participants will complete a diary for 12 weeks to record their daily treatment applications and weekly severity assessment. Subjects will complete a Dermatology Quality of Life questionnaire at all visits, to note any changes in quality of life. A visual analogue scale will be completed to note any improvement or worsening of a patient's Acne at Visits 2 and 3. This study will investigate the effectiveness of Kanuka honey in treating Acne, potentially improving the health outcomes of those with the condition, and will contribute to the knowledge base around the use of honey for the treatment of skin conditions. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 The Terrace
C/- MEDSAFE, Level 6, Deloitte House
10 Brandon Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/CEN/119</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard Beasley</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Private Bag 7902
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050147</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>richard.beasley@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Anna Hunt</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Private Bag 7902
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050147</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>anna.hunt@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Anna Hunt</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Private Bag 7902
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050147</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>anna.hunt@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Anna Hunt</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Private Bag 7902
Wellington 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 8050147</phone>
      <fax>+64 4 3895707</fax>
      <email>anna.hunt@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>