<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365858">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000293662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical effectiveness of aspirin as an adjunct to compression therapy in healing chronic venous leg ulcers: a randomised double-blind placebo-controlled trial [the ASPiVLU study]
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Clinical effectiveness of Aspirin as an adjunct to compression therapy in healing chronic venous leg ulcers: a randomised double-blind placebo controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1153-7794 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>The ASPiVLU (ASPirin in Venous Leg Ulcer)study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Venous Leg Ulcer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Acetylsalicylic acid (ASA) 300 mg: enteric coated un-scored white tablet [ASPIRIN] taken once daily for 24 weeks.
 
All participants will be treated with compression therapy. The compression system utilised will be selected  based on the treating Investigator's clinical judgement for each patient. Participants will be asked not to remove compression between treatments. Compression adherence will be checked from baseline and weekly until healed or to 12 weeks, whichever comes first, and once healed 4-weekly to 24 weeks. 
Participants will be asked to self-report trial medication adherence, and to present medication containers for a pill-count at 24 weeks.  
As this is a study primarily evaluating the impact of aspirin therapy, the exact mode of compression therapy is secondary and indeed no particular compression system has been proven as universally superior. 
Adherence to medication will be checked throughout the study by participant self-report and by medication container return for pill-count at the end of the study period of 24 weeks.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo: enteric coated un-scored white tablet with identical appearance.

All participants will be treated with compression therapy. The compression system utilised will be selected  based on the treating Investigator's clinical judgement for each patient. Participants will be asked not to remove compression between treatments. Compression adherence will be checked from baseline and weekly until healed or to 12 weeks, whichever comes first, and once healed 4-weekly to 24 weeks. 
As this is a study primarily evaluating the impact of aspirin therapy, the exact mode of compression therapy is secondary and indeed no particular compression system has been proven as universally superior. 
Participants will be asked to self-report trial medication adherence weekly from baseline until healed or to 12 weeks whichever come first, then monthly to 24 weeks from randomisation.  Participants will return medication containers for a pill-count at the end of the study period of 24 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary objective is to determine whether aspirin as an adjunct to compression improves time to healing of venous leg ulcers</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time to healing will be measured by assessing the size of the ulcer that will be measured at baseline and fortnightly until healed using digital planimetry. Proof of healing: will be measured by independent expert review of digital photos of the ulcer at baseline and fortnightly until healed or to 12 weeks, whichever comes first. The ulcer will be photographed using a digital camera to allow independent verification of ulcer size and proof of healing (100% epithelialisation). A paper ruler with mm/cm markings will be used in each photo next to the ulcer to verify size.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The rate of ulcer recurrence over 6 months</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants with healed VLU will be phoned to assess target ulcer recurrence and by research nurse at monthly intervals to check if the healed target VLU has recurred (if recurrence noted the participant will be referred to wound clinic). Monthly phone calls will continue for up to 6 months following randomisation and will commence at the 12-week from baseline visit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible participants will include males and females, aged 18 years and older and have one or more leg ulcers in the presence of venous insufficiency confirmed by clinical assessment and/or duplex ultrasound. 

The ulcer must have been present for at least six weeks. 
Participants must have an Ankle Brachial Pressure Index [ABPI] measure of greater than or equal to 0.7 mmHg to exclude significant arterial insufficiency. 
The eligible target ulcer will have an area of greater than or equal to 1 cm2 to less than or equal to 20 cm2 as measured by digital planimetry techniques (largest ulcer on limb and separated from other ulcers by at least 1 cm).
Participants must have been off aspirin for 6 weeks before coming into the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*	Unable to attend scheduled treatment visits and comply with follow-up contact with study staff. 
*	Current, regular aspirin use.
*	Aspirin intolerance.
*	Any existing condition or treatment that is a contraindication to aspirin or to participate in the trial (decision made according to medical practitioners clinical judgement).   
*	Concurrent use of any other antiplatelet or anticoagulation therapy. 
*	Pregnancy or breastfeeding
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Following the completion of screening and assessment participants to ascertain inclusion/exclusion criteria met and wound size in cm2 will then be randomly assigned to receive either aspirin or placebo. The randomization code will be available on a web-based system which will be protected by passwords for study trial staff, who will be required to enter their unique ASPiVLU identification number/password, along with the following key information: study site number, participant identification number, size of wound and confirmation inclusion and exclusion criteria</concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation will be stratified by study site and wound size as measured by the Margolis index. The Margolis index (0, 1, 2) is a prognostic score for venous ulcer healing derived from dichotomous categorizations of ulcer area and duration of current ulcer [0  = ulcer size less than or equal to 5 cm2 and less than or equal to 6 months; 1 = ulcer size greater than 5 cm2 or greater than 6 months;  2 = ulcer size greater than  5 cm2 and greater  6 months]. 
Computer generated medication numbers will be provided to trial sites through the web portal. The randomisation list will be generated by an independent statistician; this arrangement will ensure that the randomisation code remains inaccessible to all study staff and senior investigators. The randomisation list will be generated using STATA “ralloc” procedure with randomisation stratified for site and wound size. 
Following randomisation process by the research nurse, a study medication number will be provided. The research nurse is required to immediately confirm the study identification number through the web portal system.  </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All primary and secondary outcomes will be in the form of time to healing data and rates of complete healing that will be calculated using univariate Cox proportional hazards regression to directly compare rates between treatment groups. Given the sample size we anticipate randomisation will adequately balance baseline characteristics of participants in the two treatment groups. If necessary a secondary set of analyses will be performed to adjust for baseline characteristics that are found to be imbalanced between groups to the extent of a 0.25 standard deviation difference in means (quantitative measures) or an odds ratio of 1.5 (binary measures). These analyses will be conducted using multivariate Cox proportional hazards regression methods.
The primary and secondary endpoints will be analysed according to intention-to-treat principles, i.e. according to the group to which participants were randomised and without reference to their actual adherence with assigned treatment. 
No statistical adjustments will be made for the multiple secondary endpoints in their analysis but the reporting of all secondary endpoint analyses will make clear whether the primary endpoint was statistically significant and will state the number of secondary endpoints proposed a priori in the study protocol.

Data from our previous compression bandaging study shows that in the placebo group we can expect 50% of ulcers to have healed at 12 weeks.15 Aspirin is expected to increase this proportion by another 20% i.e. we expect 70% (odds ratio, OR 2.3) of the aspirin group to be healed at 12 weeks.20 22 
For 90% power in a two-sided (alpha=0.05) test for difference in proportions we would require 119 people per group. Allowing for 10% loss to follow-up we will recruit n= 132 participants per group. A sample size of 132 per group will ensure greater than 90% power for the analysis of time to healing assuming a commensurate hazard ratio effect as the odds ratio effect at 12 weeks. 
For the secondary endpoint of recurrence, if there is no difference in the proportion remaining recurrence-free of target ulcer at 12 months, then if 53/132 (approx. 40%) in placebo group are healed at 12 weeks and remain recurrence-free at 12 months then we have 80% power to detect a difference of 17%, i.e. a proportion of 57% in placebo group healed at 12 weeks and remain recurrence-free at 12 months. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>268</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,TAS,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Caulfield Hospital - Caulfield</hospital>
    <hospital>Sunshine Hospital - St Albans</hospital>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital - Heidelberg West</hospital>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hobart Hospital - Hobart</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - Royal Park campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6, The Alfred Centre
99 Commercial Road
Melbourne Vic 3181</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We propose a randomised double-blind multicentre placebo-controlled clinical trial to determine the clinical effectiveness of aspirin in addition to compression in healing venous leg ulcers. 
All eligible patients who are treated in participating wound clinics and who fulfil selection criteria will be offered study participation. All participants will be treated with best practice  compression therapy. 
In addition to compression the Aspirin Group: will receive 300 mg of aspirin daily (one tablet each morning) and the Placebo Group: will receive placebo (one tablet in the morning). We will assess wound size/depth, serum samples for inflammatory markers, pain, score, compression adherence, medication adherence, Quality of Life scores, target ulcer recurrence, adverse events and blinding success</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.med.monash.edu.au/sphpm/aspivlu-study/</trialwebsite>
    <publication>TBA</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>TBA</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>99 Commercial Road
Melbourne Vic 3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/06/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00315</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/03/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Carolina Weller</name>
      <address> School of Nursing and Midwifery
Level 3, 35 Rainforest Walk
Monash University, Clayton Campus
Wellington Road, Clayton, VIC 3800
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0623</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9903 0828</fax>
      <email>carolina.weller@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Carolina Weller</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery
Level 3, 35 Rainforest Walk
Monash University, Clayton Campus
Wellington Road, Clayton, VIC 3800</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0623</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9903 0828</fax>
      <email>carolina.weller@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Carolina Weller</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery
Level 3, 35 Rainforest Walk
Monash University, Clayton Campus
Wellington Road, Clayton, VIC 3800</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0623</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carolina.weller@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Carolina Weller</name>
      <address>School of Nursing and Midwifery
Level 3, 35 Rainforest Walk
Monash University, Clayton Campus
Wellington Road, Clayton, VIC 3800</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9903 0623</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>carolina.weller@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>