<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370317">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001131448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of a hospital-wide multimodal intervention on Emergency Department crowding, function and outcomes at Canberra Hospital and Health Services</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective Observational study of the effects of a hospital-wide intervention on process, flow and outcomes in the Emergency Department at Canberra Hospital and Health Services</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Emergency</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Previously planned multimodal hospital wide intervention comprising:
1. Changes to admission, discharge and bed management processes to reduce the load of admitted patients waiting for inpatient beds in the Emergency Department
2. Physical rebuild of the Emergencty Department to increase available space and improve flow
3. Alteration in Emergency Department staffing, roles and administration
These changes began in late 2015 and the study period will be calendar years 2016 and 2017. Observations will be gathered from hospital clinical information systems and patient notes as necessary</interventions>
    <comparator>Retrospective Controls from the previous 3 years - calendar years 2013-2015</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hours per week when number of patients in Emergency department who are waiting for inpatient beds exceeds 10. This is derived from the Emergency Department information system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calendar years 2016 and 2017 (ie Dec 31)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Achievement of the National Emergency Access target (NEAT - a four hour target). This is defined as the proportion of all patients who spend less that four hours in the Emergency Department. It is derived from the Emergency Department information system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calendar Years 2016 and 2017 (ie Dec 31)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality in Hospital (assessed from hospital information system, access to individual notes not required)</outcome>
      <timepoint>10 days and 60 days from leaving ED and at end of hospital admission</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Standard Emergency Department Indicators of process and flow as defined by the Australasian College for Emergency Medicine and the Australian Council on Healthcare Standards: Proportion of patients starting treatment within appropriate time threshold for their triage category derived from ED information system</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calendar Years 2016 and 2017 (ie Dec 31)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Standard Emergency Department Indicators of process and flow as defined by the Australasian College for Emergency Medicine and the Australian Council on Healthcare Standards: Proportion of patients admitted to hospital derived from ED information system</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calendar Years 2016 and 2017 (ie Dec 31)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inpatient Length of stay after leaving Emergency department, derived from hospital inpatient information system (individual inpatient notes not required)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calendar Year 2016 (ie Dec 31)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Readmission Rate at 14 days, derived from hospital inpatient information system (individual inpatient notes not required)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calendar Years 2016 and 2017 (ie Dec 31)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time from arrival to administration of antibiotics in patients with blood culture proven sepsis, derived from review of  relevant patient notes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calendar Years 2016 and 2017 (ie Dec 31)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Standard Emergency Department Indicators of process and flow as defined by the Australasian College for Emergency Medicine and the Australian Council on Healthcare Standards: Proportion of patients who do not wait to be seen derived from ED information system</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calendar Years 2016 and 2017 (ie Dec 31)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All presentations to the Emergency department</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Comparison of Mean, median, and proportion as appropriate with standard statistical tests. In-hospital mortality is approximately 1% of Emergency patients at 10 days. Power calculation suggests that to detect a 20% change in mortality requires a minimum of 44000 cases (alpha 0.o5, power 0.8), or approximately eight months in this Emergency Department. Study design was extended to 12 months for controls and intervention in order to account for seasonal factors</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <postcode>2605 - Garran</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Drew Richardson</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Emergency Medicine
The Canberra Hospital
Garran ACT
2605</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian National University Medical School</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Canberra Hospital
Yamba Dr
Garran ACT 2605</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Emergency Department (ED) Overcrowding is associated with reduced performance in standard process and flow measures, and worse patient outcomes including mortality. Access block, the situation of patients experiencing prolonged delays in the ED whilst waiting for an inpatient bed, is a particular issue for which the solutions lie outside the ED. There have been several detailed reports on effective hospital-wide interventions in Australia, with demonstrated improvements in process and flow and some evidence of mortality benefit.

However, all of the previous reports have been retrospective and thus may suffer from publication bias. The aim of this study is to prospectively document the effects of a multimodal hospital-wide intervention on ED process, flow, and outcomes.

In late 2015 and early 2016, The Canberra Hospital is undertaking such an intervention. This study will examine the effects using retrospective controls, Primary outcomes will be the workload caused by excessive inpatients in ED (hours per week with more than 13 inpatients in ED) and ED flow as measured by the standard National Emergency Access Target (4 hours). Secondary outcomes will be standard hospital measures including length of stay, readmission rates, and mortality.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>This is a prospective observational study of a hospital-wide intervention being undertaken by others</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACT Health Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Second Floor
North
Building
London Circuit
Canberra City
ACT 2601
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ETHLR.16.079</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Drew Richardson</name>
      <address>Emergency Medicine
The Canberra Hospital
Yamba Dr
Garran
ACT 2605</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 2418</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 2594</fax>
      <email>drew.richardson@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Drew Richardson</name>
      <address>Emergency Medicine
The Canberra Hospital
Yamba Dr
Garran
ACT 2605</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 2418</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 2594</fax>
      <email>drew.richardson@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Drew Richardson</name>
      <address>Emergency Medicine
The Canberra Hospital
Yamba Dr
Garran
ACT 2605</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 2418</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 2594</fax>
      <email>drew.richardson@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Drew Richardson</name>
      <address>Emergency Medicine
The Canberra Hospital
Yamba Dr
Garran
ACT 2605</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6244 2418</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6244 2594</fax>
      <email>drew.richardson@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>