<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82039">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/06/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/06/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000326493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial to determine the optimum frequency of Botulinum Toxin injections to the calf in children with cerebral palsy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to determine the optimum frequency of Botulinum Toxin A injections to the calf in children with cerebral palsy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral palsy in children</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention group: Botulinum Toxin A calf muscle injections every 4 months over a 2 year period. 

Dose: 6 U/kg per gastrocnemius in diplegia or per gastrocnemius and soleus in hemiplegia with 6 U/kg available for use elsewhere as clinically indicated.  Total upper dose of 18 U/kg.</interventions>
    <comparator>Active control group: Botulinum Toxin A calf muscle injections every 12 months over a 2 year period. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Passive length of gastrocnemius in degrees of dorsiflexion</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 0, 12 and 26 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of Function measured using the Functional Mobility Scale 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 12, 26 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life measured using the Child Health Questionnaire
</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 12, 26 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary Unresponsiveness to Botulinum Toxin A measured in two ways:
Assessing for the presence of neutralising antibodies to Botulinum Toxin A 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood collected prior to botulinum Toxin injections and assessed every 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessing the amount of dynamic gastrocnemius shortness measured by gait analysis
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre/post final injection at 26 and 27 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3D ultrasound of medial gastrocnemius to determine muscle volumes</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 12 and 26 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Level I, II, or III on the Gross Motor Function Classification System for cerebral palsyGastrocnemius muscle length greater than 5 degrees with the knee extendedGastrocnemius spasticity (no heel contact during the stance phase of gait)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>5</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous Botulinum Toxin A injections to the calf musclePrevious calf surgeryContraindications to the use of Botulinum Toxin A such as known hypersensitivity to any ingredient in the formulation, presence of Myasthenia Gravis or Eaton Lambert syndrome, or the presence of infection at the proposed injection site(s).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation involves contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is "off-site"</concealment>
    <sequence>The dynamic (adaptive) random allocation method of minimisation will be used with subjects categorised according to classification of cerebral palsy, severity of cerebral palsy and Botulinum toxin injections to muscles other than the calf.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Two groups are blinded in this study, the assessor assessing the outcomes and the data analyst analysing the results.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Royal Children's Hospital, Melbourne, Victoria</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Flemington Rd.
Parkville Victoria 3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Centre (NHMRC), Grant Number: 454705</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Monash Medical Centre Southern Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Monash Medical Centre 
246 Clayton Road 
Clayton, Victoria 3168</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Murdoch Children's Research Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Royal Children's Hospital 
Flemington Rd.
Parkville Victoria 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dept of Paediatrics University of Melbourne, Victoria</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Royal Children's Hospital 
Flemington Rd.
Parkville Victoria 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cerebral Palsy (CP) is a disorder affecting around 2 in 1000 live births.  Commonly, children with CP have spasticity in their muscles causing stiffness.  When Botox (Botulinum Toxin A) is injected into a spastic muscle, it helps it to relax for around 3 months, after which the effect begins to wear off.  During this relaxed time, the muscle is able to exercise through a greater range, helping to prevent contractures from forming.  
  
Botox is therefore used to both reduce spasticity in the short term, and to slow or prevent the development of contractures in the long term.  This in turn, assists to delay corrective orthopaedic surgery until the later childhood years when surgical outcomes are more predictable and longer lasting.

Currently, the most important clinical question is how often Botox should be used.  More regular injections may provide additional time that the effects of Botox are working, and muscle contractures could be delayed more effectively.

The aim of this study is to compare over a two-year period, the effects of Botox injections once a year compared to 3 times a year (every four months).  The main measure will be the rate of development of contractures over the two years.  Measurements (such as calf strength, questionnaires and blood tests) will also be made to determine whether either program negatively affects the muscle, whether the children in either group have a different level of function or quality of life and whether either program leads to the Botox having a reduced effect over time.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd,
Parkville Victoria 3052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/11/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>27062A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health Research Directorate</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, Main Block, 
Monash Medical Centre 
246 Clayton Road 
Clayton, Victoria 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/08/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>07083C</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Kerr Graham</name>
      <address>Department of Orthopaedics
The Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455399</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93455447</fax>
      <email>kerr.graham@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tandy Hastings-Ison</name>
      <address>Hugh Williamson Gait Analysis Laboratory
The Royal Children's Hospital
Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455354</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 93455447</fax>
      <email>tandy.hastingsison@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tandy Hastings-Ison</name>
      <address>Hugh Williamson Gait Analysis Laboratory The Royal Children's Hospital Flemington Rd Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 93455354</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tandy.hastingsison@rch.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>