<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365091">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/11/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001268730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Measuring the effectiveness of a phonological awareness teaching program for the kindergarten classroom
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For kindergarten children, is a classroom based phonological awareness programme more effective than a control oral language programme in developing phonological awareness skills.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Oral language delay</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study aims to evaluate the effectiveness of the Cracking the Code (CtC) Program (Fremantle Language Development Centre (FLDC) Outreach Service, 2013) with kindergarten students aged between 3 years and 6 months and 5 years and 6 months. CtC is a teacher implemented program, designed to explicitly target Phonological Awareness (PA) skills and alphabet knowledge over an 18 week period, within a structured intervention regime. A randomised, parallel group design will be used to evaluate the effectiveness of the program and to identify factors which influence a participants responsiveness to the program. Four mainstream schools within the South West Perth metropolitan area will be selected to participate in the study. Schools involved in the study will be matched based on the following characteristics; (1) geographical location, (2) socioeconomic status and (3) educational outcomes. Between 100  120 kindergarten students aged between  3 years and 6 months and 4 years and 6 months on entry to the programme will be included within the final data set with parental/caregiver consent. The schools will be randomly assigned to either the control or treatment condition. The control group will participate in an alternative program matched for duration and intensity, targeting the areas of semantics and grammar. All participants will be assessed on PA, alphabet knowledge, non word reading and spelling, oral language, and short term memory prior to intervention, and on PA, alphabet knowledge, non-word reading and spelling after intervention. 
The language programs involve;
1.	Six intervention blocks each lasting for 3 weeks (18 weeks in total). The intervention phase runs over Term 2 and Term 3.
2.	Then intervention blocks begin at the level of onset and rime and progress towards phonemic awareness activities, following a developmental progression of these skills. An example of the activities in Block 4 are:
Onset-Rime (Rhyme Detection): Piggy Banks
Onset-Rime Segmentation (Initial Sound): First Sound Treasure Hunt
Phoneme Final Sound Identification: Hopscotch
Phoneme CVC Blending: Shopping Trolley

3.	Activity sessions will be conducted twice per week  so six times over the three week period.
4.	Each session will take approximately 40  55 minutes.
5.	Two to three staff members will be required for the running of each session. These staff members may be teachers, education assistants or school support staff.
6.	Support and training will be provided to education staff prior to the commencement of each block.

To ensure treatment fidelity, clear guidelines for dosage and implementation, as well as comprehensive training and modelling support, will be provided. The procedures manuals for the language programmes will be used in training to support adherence to the treatment protocol. Teacher questionnaires, recorded use of activities and direct observations of lessons every three weeks, by the primary researcher will also contribute to treatment fidelity.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Words, Grammar and Fun - will be used as the control intervention programme (Fremantle Language Development Centre (FLDC) Outreach Service, 2013).
The language programs involve;
1.	Six intervention blocks each lasting for 3 weeks (18 weeks in total). The intervention phase runs over Term 2 and Term 3.
2.	The intervention content of Words, Grammar and Fun targets word learning with a focus on vocabulary and syntax (grammar) and morphology. It addresses different goals to the treatment condition which targets phonological awareness but is delivered at the same intensity and in the same format.
3.	Activity sessions will be conducted twice per week  so six times over the three week period.
4.	Each session will take approximately 40  55 minutes.
5.	Two to three staff members will be required for the running of each session. These staff members may be teachers, education assistants or school support staff.
6.	Support and training will be provided to education staff prior to the commencement of each block.
To ensure treatment fidelity, clear guidelines for dosage and implementation, as well as comprehensive training and modelling support, will be provided.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All kindergarten children will be assessed using the (1) Cracking the Code PA Assessment (FLDC Outreach Service, 2013). The CtC PA assessment assesses syllable, onset-rime and phoneme level PA. It was developed for use within the program, and assesses all targeted skills. A blind assessor will be trained by the primary researcher and will be responsible for administering these assessments. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Within the same two-week period during term one (testing time one), and during a two week period in term four 2014 (testing time two).


</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All kindergarten children will be assessed using  (2) an alphabet knowledge assessment (name and sound). A blind assessor will be trained by the primary researcher and will be responsible for administering these assessments. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Within the same two-week period during term one (testing time one), and during a two week period in term four 2014 (testing time two).
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All kindergarten children will be assessed using (3) a simple age-appropriate early non-word reading and spelling assessment, developed for use within the program. A blind assessor will be trained by the primary researcher and will be responsible for administering these assessments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within the same two-week period during term one (testing time one), and during a two week period in term four 2014 (testing time two).
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Four mainstream schools within the South West Perth metropolitan area will be selected to participate in the study. Schools involved in the study will be matched based on the following characteristics; (1) geographical location, (2) socioeconomic status and (3) educational outcomes. Between 100  120 kindergarten students aged between 3 years and 6 months and 4 years and 6 months on entry to the programme will be included within the final data set with parental/caregiver consent. 
Inclusion criteria are therefore: attending the relevant class in a consenting school and parent consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>42</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>54</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>No consent</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box U 1987, Perth
Western Australia, 6845
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box U 1987, Perth
Western Australia, 6845
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Cracking the Code program is designed to target the phonological awareness (PA) skills and alphabet knowledge of kindergarten students (aged 3 years and 6 months to 5 years and 6 months) within the context of classroom based instruction. This study aims to explore the effectiveness of this program in improving; PA, alphabet knowledge and early reading and spelling, when delivered within a Speech Pathologist guided, teacher implemented, intervention structure. Schools will be randomly assigned to either the treatment or control condition. Control groups will participate in an alternative program, targeting alternative language areas.
To evaluate the effectiveness of the Cracking the Code program (CtC) (Fremantle Language Development Centre (FLDC) Outreach Service, 2013) the following hypotheses will be tested;
1.	Participation in CtC will lead to a significant improvement compared to the control group in PA skills across the levels of syllable, onset-rime and phoneme as measured by the Cracking the Code PA Assessment (FLDC Outreach Service, 2013).
2.	Participation in the CtC program will lead to a significant improvement compared to the control group in alphabet knowledge, including the identification of both name and sound of each letter for both upper and lower case representations as measured by an alphabet knowledge assessment.
3.	Participation in the CtC program will lead to a significant improvement compared to the control group in early (a) reading and (b) spelling skills as measured by a non-word reading and spelling assessment.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee, c/- Office of Research and Development, Curtin University, GPO Box U1987, Perth WA 6845 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/12/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suze Leitao</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U 1987, Perth
Western Australia, 6845
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 7620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Leitao@Curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suze Leitao</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U 1987, Perth
Western Australia, 6845
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 7620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Leitao@Curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suze Leitao</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U 1987, Perth
Western Australia, 6845
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 7620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Leitao@Curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Suze Leitao</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U 1987, Perth
Western Australia, 6845
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9266 7620</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Leitao@Curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>