<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371031">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001120460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Combination with Sevoflurane Anesthesia Attenuates Nasopharyngeal Secretions in Propofol-Based Total Intravenous Anesthesia in Ocular Surgery </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Combination with Sevoflurane Anesthesia Attenuates Nasopharyngeal Secretions in Propofol-Based Total Intravenous Anesthesia in Ocular Surgery </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Nasopharyngeal secretions under general anesthesia  </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Ocular surgery</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Propofol-based total intravanous anesthesia (TIVA)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions> In the propofol/sevoflurane group, the anesthesia induction were as the total intravenous anaesthesia (TIVA) group patients, whereas anesthesia was maintained using intravenous propofol infusion and 1% sevoflurane (inhaled concentration) with with 50% oxygen flow of 1 mL/min by the treating anaesthetist. 
Maintenance of the effect-site concentration (Ce) for the  propofol/sevoflurane was adjusted to keep BIS value between 4060 and mean arterial blood pressure at 80100 mm Hg determined by the treating anaesthetist. The EtCO2 pressure was maintained at 35-45 mmHg. Once neuromuscular function returns, rocuronium (0.1 mg/kg, intravenously [i.v.]) was administered as required by the treating anaesthetist. All patients received i.v. methasone 0.1 mg/kg for preventing post-operative nausea and vomiting (PONV) while induction of anaesthesia by the treating anaesthetist..
At the end of the procedure, propofol or sevoflurane was discontinued and the lungs were ventilated with 100% oxygen at a fresh gas flow of 6 L/min by the treating anaesthetist. Reversal of neuromuscular function was achieved by administrating neostigmine (0.03-0.04 mg/kg, i.v.) with glycopyrrolate (0.006-0.008 mg/kg, i.v.) once spontaneous breathing returned to prevent residual paralysis at the clinical discretion of the treating anaesthetist. When the patient regained consciousness by name with spontaneous and smooth respiration, the endotracheal tube was removed and the patient was sent to the postoperative anesthesis care unit for further care. </interventions>
    <comparator>In the propofol-based TIVA group, anesthesia was induced using intravenous (i.v.) fentanyl (2 microg/kg) and 2% lidocaine (1.5 mg/kg, i.v.) by the treating anaesthetist. Continuous intravenous infusion of propofol was delivered subsequently using Schneiders kinetic model of target-controlled infusion (TCI; Fresenius Orchestra Primea; Fresenius Kabi AG, Bad Homburg, Germany) with the effect-site concentration (Ce) of 4.0 microg/mL by the treating anaesthetist. Rocuronium (0.6 mg/ kg, i.v.) was given when patients lost consciousness, followed by tracheal intubation by the treating anaesthetist. GA was maintained with TCI propofol infusion and 1.0 L/min flow with 50% oxygen by the treating anaesthetist..
Maintenance of the Ce for the TIVA  was adjusted to keep BIS value between 4060 and mean arterial blood pressure at 80100 mm Hg by the treating anaesthetist. The EtCO2 pressure was maintained at 35-45 mmHg. Once neuromuscular function returns, rocuronium (0.1 mg/kg, i.v.) was administered as required. All patients received i.v. methasone 0.1 mg/kg for preventing PONV while induction of anaesthesia by the treating anaesthetist.
At the end of the procedure, propofol  was discontinued and the lungs were ventilated with 100% oxygen at a fresh gas flow of 6 L/min by the treating anaesthetist. Reversal of neuromuscular function was achieved by administrating neostigmine (0.03-0.04 mg/kg, i.v.) with glycopyrrolate (0.006-0.008 mg/kg, i.v.) once spontaneous breathing returned to prevent residual paralysis at the clinical discretion of the treating anaesthetist. When the patient regained consciousness by name with spontaneous and smooth respiration, the endotracheal tube was removed and the patient was sent to the postoperative anesthesis care unit for further care. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total volume of nasopharyngeal secretions was determined by collecting them with frequent suction via nasal and oral cavities by using the suction apparatus  from the end of surgery to extubation of the endotracheal tube by the anaesthesiologist,</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the end of surgery to extubation of the endotracheal tube</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of PONV, assessed  by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 day after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with prolonged extubation (&gt;15 minutes from end of surgery to extubation), assessed by review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of extubation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>50 patients scheduled to undergo ocular surgery by one ophthalmologist under GA were enrolled in this study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) age &lt; 20 years or older than 80 years, (2) American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) physical status of more than III, (3) body mass index (BMI) &gt; 30 kg/m2, (4) possible pregnancy, (5) emergent surgeries, (6) uremia, and (7) liver disease.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based on a 10 patients' preliminary data from our institution in the same surgical population, a power analysis was performed by reducing nasopharyngeal secretions as the primary variable. We calculated a sample size so that a reducing 15 ml (50%) of nasopharyngeal secretions would permit a one-tailed type I error rate of a = 0.05 with a power of 80%. This analysis indicated that a sample size of at least 23 patients per group was necessary. To allow for potential dropouts, we enrolled a total of 25 patients in each group. Data are presented as the mean and standard deviation (SD) or number of patients. Demographic and perioperative variables were compared using Students t-tests or MannWhitney test while the data were not normally distributed. Categorical variables were compared using chi-square test. Statistical significance was accepted for two-tailed P values of &lt; 0.05. The statistics was performed by using SigmaStat 3.5 for Windows.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>29/10/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>15/03/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>50</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>15/03/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Tri-Service General Hospital </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>#325, Section 2, Chenggung Road, Neihu 114, Taipei, Taiwan, Republic of China.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>None</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>None</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: About 10% patients under general anesthesia had nasopharyngeal secretions on the face at the end of ocular surgery, and secretions toward the eye in some patients. It may induce postoperative endophthalmitis, although rare, still of great concern to the ophthalmologist. Therefore, anesthetics that produce less nasopharyngeal secretions are desirable. Nasopharyngeal excretion under propofol-based total intravanous anesthesia (TIVA) is greater than sevoflurane anesthesia during surgery. However, postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV) after inhalational anesthesia is higher than TIVA and may increase intraocluar pressure. As our best knlowldge, no previous report discussed the nasopharyngeal secretions and PONV while sevoflurane combines with propofol anesthesia. Therefore, the aim of this study is to investigate the effect of sevoflurane combination with propofol-based TIVA on nasopharyngeal secrtions and PONV in ocular surgery.
Methods: Fifty patients undergoing ocular surgery were randomly assigned for propofol-based TIVA or propofol/sevoflurane anesthesia. In the TIVA group patients (n = 25), anesthesia was induced and maintained with propofol and i.v. fentanyl, whereas, in the propofol/sevoflurane group patients (n = 25), 1% sevoflurane anesthesia was added. All patient were moniotored under bispectral index (BIS). We prospectively compared the nasopharyngeal secretion volume, extubation time and incidence of PONV after the procedure in both groups. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Ethics Committee of the Tri-Service General Hospital </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>#325, Section 2, Chenggung Road, Neihu 114, Taipei, Taiwan, Republic of China. </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>TSGHIRB No: 2-104-05-129</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hou-Chuan Lai</name>
      <address>Tri-Service General Hospital and National Defense Medical Center, #325, Section 2, Chenggung Road, Neihu 114, Taipei, Taiwan, Republic of China.</address>
      <phone>+886-2-87927128</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m99ane@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zhi-Fu Wu</name>
      <address>Tri-Service General Hospital and National Defense Medical Center, #325, Section 2, Chenggung Road, Neihu 114, Taipei, Taiwan, Republic of China.</address>
      <phone>+886-2-87927128</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aneswu@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Zhi-Fu Wu</name>
      <address>Tri-Service General Hospital and National Defense Medical Center, #325, Section 2, Chenggung Road, Neihu 114, Taipei, Taiwan, Republic of China.</address>
      <phone>+886-2-87927128</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aneswu@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>