<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347887">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/12/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000065897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The use of a probiotic to treat bacterial vaginosis and augment IVF pregnancy rates.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised placebo controlled study comparing the use of a one month course of an oral probiotic therapy post tinidazole antibiotic treatment on the medium term (1 month) cure rate of bacterial vaginosis in a cohort of infertile women undergoing a frozen-thawed embryo transfer with documented evidence of bacterial vaginosis at trial entry.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The "ProViva" study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>bacterial vaginosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>infertility</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>In Vitro Fertilisation (IVF)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fertility including in vitro fertilisation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Women identified to have bacterial vaginosis will be administered a single 2 gm oral dose of the antibiotic Tinidazole, followed by a 4 week course of oral probiotic (2 capsules daily- total dose 4.6 Billion organisms Lactobacillus per day).</interventions>
    <comparator>A single 2 gm dose of the antibiotic Tinidazole, followed by 2 placebo capsules daily for 4 weeks. The placebo capsules are identical in size, appearance and taste and contain glucose plus potato starch (141 mg and 18 mg respectively per capsule).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cure of bacterial vaginosis as assessed by established clinical (Amsel) and laboratory (Nugent score) criteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Examination at the time of the embryo transfer, approximately 4 weeks after administration of the Tinidazole antibiotic and commencement of probiotic or placebo capsules.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemical pregnancy rate (proportion of embryo transferes resulting in a positive serum bHCG result)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks after embryo transfer</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Viable clinical pregnancy rate (proportion of transfered embryos that result in a viable fetal heart pulsation on ultrasound scan).</outcome>
      <timepoint>7-8 weeks gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>miscarriage rate</outcome>
      <timepoint>assessed at time of first trimeter ultrasound (7-8 weeks gestation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Concentration of bacterial vaginosis related endotoxins washed off the surface of the embryo transfer catheter after completion of the embryo transfer. Endotoxin will be quantified by the Endosafe-PTS assay system (Charles River, USA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the time of the embryo transfer</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Presence of bacterial vaginosis infection on clinical examination and Nugent score assessment.
 2. Undergoing a frozen embryo (vitrification) transfer cycle of IVF treatment</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Women receiving concurrent vaginal medication (progesterone, antifungal, antibiotic).
2. Allergy to Tindazole or metronidazole
3. Concurrent Candida vaginal infection
4. Women undergoing a frozen embryo transfer using "slow freeze" stored embryos.
5. Antibiotic use in the last 2 weeks
6. Prior enrolment in the ProViva Study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Women who have just had an unsuccessful fresh embryo transfer and who have at least one vitrified frozen embryo in storage will be invited to “self test” themselves for the presence of BV using a vaginal pH glove. This glove has a pH meter on the index finger which when inserted into the vagina by the patient herself enables accurate measurement of vaginal acidity. A pH of 4.5 or less indicates normal vaginal environment and no BV is likely present. A pH of 4.7 and above is abnormal and highly suggestive of the presence of BV. Alternatively, if the woman does not wish to “self-test”, she can present to the clinic for a formal gynaecological examination and assessment. Those women screening positive by the glove pH test will then be invited to attend the clinic where they will undergo a gynaecological examination to confirm the presence of BV. This examination will include a clinical diagnosis of BV using the Amsel criteria and Nugent score testing. Only those women positive for BV on both Amsel and Nugent score tests, and who have no evidence of Candida on microscopy examination, will be enrolled in the next phase of the study. All patients entering the study will be administered a single 2gm oral dose of the antibiotic Tinidazole as soon as the diagnosis of BV is made (i.e. at the screening gynaecological examination). Participants will then be randomly allocated in equal numbers to commence either daily oral probiotic (two capsules orally daily) or an identical appearing placebo. This treatment will commence 2 weeks before the anticipated menstrual period date when the patient will book on for her frozen embryo IVF cycle. Treatment with either oral probiotic or placebo will continue until the embryo transfer day, which in general occurs approximately 2-3 weeks after the commencement of menses (i.e. total 4-5 weeks of probiotic / placebo treatment). At the time of the embryo transfer examination a repeat “proof of cure” BV gynaecological exam will be conducted using the Amsel criteria and Nugent score assessment. The oral study medication (active probiotic or placebo) will be taken on the day of embryo transfer but ceased at that point in time. The experimetal therapy (probiotic / placebo) capsules will be provided by the manufacturer (Hansen, Denmark) and will be identical in appearance and taste. Both study participants and research/ clinical personelle will be blinded to treatment allocation. Treatment packs will be sequentially numbered and prepared by a third party contractor, using a computer generated randomisation sequence. Research personelle will simply allocate study participants the next treatment pack in the numerical sequence.</concealment>
    <sequence>A third party will use an on line random sequence generator program to construct the ransomised treatment schedule.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Terminated</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>North Terrace
Adelaide
South Australia 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Chr. Hansen</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Boge Alle 10-12, Horsholm
Denmark</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Denmark</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Blackmores</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Jubilee Avenue
Warriewood
NSW 2102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Repromed</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>180 Fullarton road
Dulwich
South Australia 5065</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Bacterial Vaginosis (BV) is very common clinical condition with prevalence rates between 10 and 30 % of women in the reproductive age group. While in some cases BV is asymptomatic, in many women BV produces annoying symptoms (vaginal discharge, offensive smell).  BV may also interfer with successful implantation of an embryo during IVF treatment, as these bacteria may be introduced from the vagina into the uterus at the time of the embryo transfer, causing inflammation of the uterine lining (endometrium). BV has been linked with a reduction in implantation rates in IVF and an increase risk of miscarriage. Therefore effective long term treatment/ prevention of BV in an IVF setting is important. The aim of this study is to determine if the oral administration of a probiotic can result in vaginal colonization and a subsequent reduction in reoccurance of BV infection after antibiotic (tinidazole) treatment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mawson lakes Campus
Mawson Lakes boulevard
Mawson Lakes
South Australia 5095</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/01/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>26633</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/12/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kelton Tremellen</name>
      <address>180 Fullarton Road
Dulwich
South Australia 5065</address>
      <phone>+61 883338111</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83338188</fax>
      <email>ktremellen@repromed.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kelton Tremellen</name>
      <address>180 Fullarton Road
Dulwich
South Australia 5065</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83338111</phone>
      <fax>+61 883338188</fax>
      <email>ktremellen@repromed.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kelton Tremellen</name>
      <address>180 Fullarton Road
Dulwich
South Australia 5065</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83338111</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83338188</fax>
      <email>ktremellen@repromed.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>