<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1102">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/02/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/02/2006</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12606000073505</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Methoxyflurane for cancer patients with incident pain receiving radiotherapy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised, open-label, single centre, cross-over study to assess the efficacy and safety of methoxyflurane for the treatment of incident pain in patients undergoing radiotherapy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Incident or movement related pain during transportation to and delivery of radiation therapy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The duration of the intervention/study will last for two days - Day 1 will be either the standard or methoxyflurane arm, and on Day 2 the treatments will cross-over.                                                       Methoxyflurane will be self-administered and monitored, and the possible amount inhaled will not exceed Australian Product information guidelines which is 6ml per day, or 15ml per week. The vapour produced from 6ml of an inhaler last about 50 minutes with continuous use.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                            In addition, should they experience unacceptable pain during therapy a standing order is in place to provide a further breakthrough of the medication after 1 hour.</interventions>
    <comparator>The standard arm reflects current analgesic practice at our institution..                                                                                                                                                                                    This is usually a 'breakthrough' dose of analgesia given a half an hour prior to the radiotherapy session.                                                                                                                                   The particular analgesia and its dose is determined by the background analgesia that they are receiving.                                                                                                                                                             The dose is usually 1/6th to 1/10th of the total 24 hour dose.                                                                      </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if there is a difference in efficacy between methoxyflurane and standard analgesia in controlling pain associated with movement and positioning of cancer patients during a radiotherapy session.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pain will be measured at several points during the procedure with the primary end-points being 5 minutes before transport to and 5 minutes after completion of, radiotherapy.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if there is a difference in efficacy between methoxyflurane and standard analgesia in controlling distress associated with movement and positioning of cancer patients during a radiotherapy session.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Distress Thermometer will measure the patient's perception of distress 30mins and 5 mins before the radiotherapy and again post radiotherapy. Both groups will be measured similarly.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Radiotherapy related incident/movement pain; age: ECOG &lt;=2.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Renal imparirment (&gt;2xnormal); previous toxicity or use of methoxyflurane; family or personal history of hyperthermia or sensitivites to flourinated anaesthetics; patients receiving Patient Controlled Analgesia.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Concealment will occur in that the Biostatistics Department will directly inform the Pharmacy Department as to which group the particular patient has been allocated, thus bypassing the clinicians and investigators.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation charts, based on the adaptive biased coin method will be prepared by the Peter MacCallum Centre for Biostatistics &amp; Clinical Trials for the Pharmacy Department. Patients will be randomised to receive either methoxyflurane or standard analgesia on a 1:1 basis.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Medical Development International Limited</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Introduction/your consent

You are invited to take part in this research project because you have pain related to cancer that requires radiotherapy. This research project is testing a new way of controlling pain especially during movement. The current standard treatment for movement pain includes morphine which is often not effective. This Participant Information Sheet tells you about the research project. It explains what is involved. This will help you decide if you want to take part in the research. 

Please read this Participant Information Sheet carefully. Ask questions about anything that you dont understand or want to know more about. Before deciding whether or not to take part, you might want to talk about it with a relative, friend or your local doctor. 

If you decide you want to take part in the research project, then you will be asked to sign the Consent Form. By signing it you are telling us that you:

·	Understand what you have read in the information sheet
·	Consent to taking part in the research project
·	Consent to the use of your personal and health information as described in the information sheet.

You will be given a copy of this Participant Information Sheet and Consent Form to keep as a record.

Purpose and Background
 
Doctors are looking for better ways to treat pain caused by movement especially when being transported to and from the radiotherapy department as an inpatient. In this research project, the researchers will test whether giving the medication, methoxyflurane given by inhalation (through a device called a Penthrox Inhaler), is better than the current standard treatment. The standard treatment is an extra dose of morphine, or similar medication, given half an hour before being moved to the radiotherapy department. No study has been done comparing the two treatments.

Methoxyflurane has been approved for use in Australia to relieve acute pain. It is used in many situations including ambulances, emergency departments, dentistry, obstetrics and in children. It provides effective pain relief with very few side effects. Therefore this is not an experimental drug.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Simon Wein</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
2 St Andrews Place
East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96561918</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 96561998</fax>
      <email>Simon.Wein@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Odette Spruyt</name>
      <address>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre
2 St Andrews Place
East Melbourne VIC 3002</address>
      <phone>+61 3 96561918</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 96561998</fax>
      <email>Odette.Spruyt@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>