<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363637">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000946718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study of peginterferon-alfa intervention to achieve hepatitis B surface antigen loss in multi-drug resistant chronic hepatitis B participants under long-term viral suppression with tenofovir DF +/- lamivudine salvage therapy (TDF-109 cohort)
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Peg-interferon-alfa to achieve HBsAg loss in multi-drug resistance HBV under long-term viral suppression with tenofovir DF +/- lamivudine salvage therapy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TRUST - 109</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil know</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic hepatitis B</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Hepatitis B virus is a major health issue worldwide and despite the advances in therapy, it is still the tenth leading cause of mortality.  Currently there are two treatments available  peginterferon-alpha (pegIFNa) and nucleos(t)ide analogues (NA).  PegIFNa is a drug which affects the immune system and is a finite treatment of 48 weeks, however majority end up on NA indefinitely, although not concurrently.  NA are oral agents which are highly effective in controlling the virus, patients often flare once this medication is ceased.  The ultimate goal of antiviral therapy is converting chronic hepatitis B (CHB) patients from surface antigen (HBsAg) positive to negative with development of surface antibodies (HBsAb) (HBsAg seroconversion).  
The TDF-109 study (Project No H2006/02552) evaluated the efficacy of tenofovir DF (TDF) +/- lamivudine (LMV) rescue therapy for LMV/ adefovir (ADV)-experienced Asian patients (Protocol No IN-AU-174-0109).  The initial two year data was published by Patterson SJ, George J, Strasser SI, Lee AU, Sievert W, Nicoll AJ, et al. Tenofovir disoproxil fumarate rescue therapy following failure of both lamivudine and adefovir dipivoxil in chronic hepatitis B. Gut. 2011;60:247-54. Most patients have now completed 5 years of treatment and TDF has resulted in significant viral suppression in the majority of patients.  Significant declines of HBsAg titre were observed however no seroconversion.  At this stage, majority of the patients will be on NA life-long.  
We believe that immunomodulation is required to achieve HBsAg loss, and that this explains the very low rates of HBsAg loss, and eventual plateau phase that have been observed during NA therapy. We hypothesize that in patients under long-term viral suppression with potent NA, add-on pegIFNa will reduce serum HBsAg levels and lead to HBsAg loss.
We propose an investigator-initiated proof-of-concept study to evaluate the efficacy of add-on pegIFNa therapy  (180mcg subcutaneously weekly) in patients who have been treated with TDF +/- LMV therapy for at least 5 years as part of the TDF-109 study.
We will aim to recruit all the TF-109 patients into this study. 
Those suitable will be treated with 48 weeks of pegIFNa.  Strategies used to monitor adherence includes taking a history from the patients as well as counting drug tablet return on their reviews.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Those who are not suitable or refusing peg-interferon will be our control group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in HBsAg titre during antiviral therapy (pegIFNa plus NA therapy) measured using the Roche Elecsys assay.  This measures the quantitative hepatitis B surface antigen (qHBsAg) titers expressed in international units/mL (IU/mL).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 48 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean change in HBsAg titre over time, as estimated from the area between the baseline value and the curve of HBsAg titre divided by the duration of treatment
</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 weeks of treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rates of HBsAg loss and HBsAg seroconversion at end-of-treatment and 24 weeks post-treatment
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 48 weeks of treatment and 24 weeks post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In HBeAg-positive patients:
-	the change in HBeAg titre over the course of the study.
The Roche Elecsys assay will be used to measure the quantitative hepatitis e antigen (qHBeAg) titers expressed in international units per millilitre (IU/mL) 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 48 weeks of treatment and 24 weeks post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In patients who stop therapy, the rate of serological (serum HBsAg, HBeAg level) and/or virological (serum HBV DNA level) relapse will be evaluated
-	Protocol requires TDF to be restarted in the event of virological relapse:
-	cirrhotics = detectable HBV DNA
-	non-cirrhotics = HBV DNA &gt; 2,000 IU/mL
The HBsAg and HBeAg will be analysed at the 3 monthly intervals.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within the 48 weeks </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exploratory analysis of clinical / laboratory predictors for serological responses will be performed (baseline and on-treatment factors will be considered).  This will included performing bioplex assays which detects the phenotypic variation of the surface antigen.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>48 weeks of treatment and 24 weeks post treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>In HBeAg positive patients
-	the rate of HBeAg loss and HBeAg-seroconversion.
The HBeAg/Ab serology will be performed 3 monthly during the 48 weeks.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the 48 weeks on peg-interferon therapy.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The initial TF109 has not been registered on ANZCTR.  The initial 2 year data has been published by Patterson SJ, George J, Strasser SI, Lee AU, Sievert W, Nicoll AJ, et al. Tenofovir disoproxil fumarate rescue therapy following failure of both lamivudine and adefovir dipivoxil in chronic hepatitis B. Gut. 2011;60:247-54.  The key inclusion criteria is that they have to have been involved in the initial TF109 study - on long term tenofovir DF.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Severe liver disease which excludes them from peg-interferon therapy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients previously enrolled in the TDF-109 study.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>All patients from the original TF109 cohort maintained on long-term (5 years) TDF +/- LMV therapy will treated with add-on pegIFNa-2a, 180ug, SC, weekly, for 48 weeks total.
This add-on study is not randomised - patients from TF109 will have liver biopsy to determine safety to treat with peg-interferon 180ug, SC, weekly, for 48 weeks total.
Those not suitable or unwilling to be treated will be recruited as the observational/control arm.
</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary efficacy variable, change in log10 HBsAg, will be analysed with ANCOVA using the baseline log10 HBsAg as the covariate.  Similarly for change in log10 HBsAg during follow-up. The mean change in log10 HBsAg with be analysed with ANOVA. HBsAg loss and HBsAg seroconversion will be analysed with logistic regression.
Due to the limited numbers of participants in the TF109 cohort (n=59), the aim would be to recruit all the participants in the add-on study.  However given not all the patients will be eligible or willing to partake in weekly injections - our aim is to have at least half (n=25-30) be treated with add-on peg-inteferon while the other half are the controls on tenofovir DF +/- lamivudine.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>2/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>55</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Royal Melbourne Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord Repatriation Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Peter Angus</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Liver Transplant and Gastroenterology
Austin Health
145 Studley Rd Heidelberg 3084 Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Gilead</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Gilead Sciences - Australia
Level 1, 128 Jolimont Road
East Melbourne 3002
Victoria Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Roche</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>4-10 Inman Road
Dee Why NSW 2099 
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a study to see if add-on peginterferon-­alfa (pegIFNa) can help lose hepatitis B surface antigen in participants who have multi­drug resistant chronic hepatitis B and treated with long­term tenofovir DF +/- lamivudine salvage therapy (TDF­109 cohort)
We hypothesize that in participants under long ­term viral suppression with potent oral therapy nucleoside analogues, add­on pegIFNa will reduce serum HBsAg levels and lead to HBsAg loss.
We propose an investigator ­initiated proof­ of ­concept study to evaluate the efficacy of add­-on pegIFNa therapy in patients who have been treated with tenofovir and/or lamivudine therapy for at least 5 years as part of the TDF­109 study. We will aim to recruit all the TF­109 patients into this study. Those suitable will be treated with 48 weeks of pegIFNa.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>N/A</trialwebsite>
    <publication>The initial 2 year data was published by 1.	Patterson SJ, George J, Strasser SI, Lee AU, Sievert W, Nicoll AJ, et al. Tenofovir disoproxil fumarate rescue therapy following failure of both lamivudine and adefovir dipivoxil in chronic hepatitis B. Gut. 2011;60:247-54.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Gilead and Roche have kindly agreed to sponsor this study by providing medications only.  This is an investigator driven study.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00204)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Austin Hopsital
145 Studley Road, Heidelberg 3084 Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/Austin/16</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/02/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Angus</name>
      <address>Liver Transplant Unit
Austin Health
145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg 3084 Victoria</address>
      <phone> 61 03 94965353</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.angus@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lucy Lim</name>
      <address>Liver Transplant Unit
Austin Health
145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg 3084 Victoria</address>
      <phone>61403300838</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lucy_lim8@yahoo.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Angus</name>
      <address>Liver Transplant Unit
Austin Health
145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg 3084 Victoria</address>
      <phone>61403300838</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter.angus@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Angus</name>
      <address>Austin Health
145 Studley Rd, Heidelberg 3084 Victoria</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>peter.angus@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>