<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335690">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/07/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/07/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000546055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study comparing the efficacy of artesunate alone and artesunate plus azithromycin for the treatment of Plasmodium falciparum malaria in central Vietnam</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study comparing the efficacy and tolerability of artesunate alone and artesunate plus azithromycin for the treatment of Plasmodium falciparum malaria in central Vietnam</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malaria infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Malaria patients will be given either artesunate alone (4 mg/kg on the first day of treatment then 2 mg/kg daily for 6 days) or artesunate (4 mg/kg) plus azithromycin (20 mg/kg) daily for 3 days for the treatment of uncomplicated falciparum malaria.  The mode of administration will be by the oral route.</interventions>
    <comparator>Clinical efficacy and tolerability will be compared between the two treatment groups.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the therapeutic efficacy of artesunate alone and artesunate plus azithromycin for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum in central Vietnam. Also, by evaluating artesunate alone will provide efficacy data as to whether there is reduced susceptibility to the artemisinin at the study site.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Parasitaemia clearance will be determined from blood smears collected 12 hourly after starting treatment until three consecutive smears are negative for parasites.  For the artesunate alone group follow-up blood smears will be taken at days 7, 14, 21, and 28 and for the artesunate plus azithromycin group at days  7, 14, 21, 28, 35 and 42 after starting treatment .  Blood spots on filter paper will also be obtained at enrolment and on days 7 onwards at the same time blood smears are collected for the two treatment groups. A blood smear and filter blood spot will also be obtained for any patient that has a recurrence of malaria infection during the follow-up periods.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the tolerability of artesunate alone and artesunate plus azithromycin for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum in central Vietnam.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Adverse events (eg., nausea, headache, fever, abdominal pain, vomiting and anorexia) will be recorded before commencement of treatment and at 24 h intervals after starting treatment until adverse events have disappeared.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Multiplex Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) analysis will be done to distinguish recrudences from reinfections by targeting the genes, msp1, msp2 and glurp. Molecular genotyping of patient's Plasmodium falciparum parasites will be carried out using Multiplex PCR-Restriction Fragment Length Polymporphism (RFLP) analysis on the collected filter blood spots to characterise the frequency of Plasmodium falciparum chloroquine resistant transporter and multidrug-resistant genes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Multiplex PCR analysis will be done on patients who present with a recurrence of malaria during the 28 days follow-up period for patients on artesunate alone and 42 days for patients on artesunate plus azithromycin. Molecular genotyping of patient's Plasmodium falciparum parasites will be carried out using RFLP analysis on the collected filter blood spots before starting treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i)  Patients with falciparum malaria with parasitaemia between 100 and 200,000 parasites/uL of blood
(ii)  Is willing to give small amounts of blood via finger prick and phlebotomy
(iii)  Written informed consent and agreed to treatment follow-up for a total of 28 days for artesunate alone and 42 days for artesunate plus azithromycin.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i)  Severe/cerebral malaria or history of another serious medical disease
(ii)  Prior treatment with an artemisinin drug within the previous 7 days
(iii)  Pregnancy and lactating
(iv)  Inability to communicate well with the investigator (poor mental development or evidence of psychiatric disorder)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation of drugs will not be concealed. Patients will be sequentially allocated to the two treatment groups: Artesunate alone for 7 days and artesunate plus azithromycin for 3 days, with the first patient to receive artesunate alone , the second patient artesunate plus azithromycin, the third patient artesunate alone , and so on.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/05/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Viet Nam</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australian Army Malaria Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Weary Dunlop Drive, Gallipoli Barracks, Enoggera, Brisbane QLD 4051</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Department of Defence</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>International Policy Division Russell Offices R1-5-C015 Russell Drive Canberra ACT 2600</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Vietnam People's Army</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Military Institute of Hygiene and Epidemiology, 21-Trung Liet Dong Da, Hanoi</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Viet Nam</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Artemisinin-based combination treatments (ACT) are now recommended as first-line treatment for Plasmodium falciparum malaria worldwide. Recent studies have shown reduce susceptibility of artesunate in western Cambodia and thus there is an urgent need to know whether artesunate resistance is present in neighbouring Southeast Asian countries such as Vietnam.  In this study, we propose to assess whether reduce susceptibility exists at a commune in central Vietnam by giving patients a 7 day course of artesunate alone. At the same time, we will evaluate the efficacy of the ACT, artesunate plus azithromycin as this combination is meant to be safe in special risk groups such as young children and during pregnancy. However, before testing the artesunate plus azithromycin in special risk groups we need to know that the ACT is efficacious in the general population between 5 and 65 years.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Defence Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Campbell Park, Campbell, Canberra, ACT 2612</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/04/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ADHREC 586-10</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Mike Edstein</name>
      <address>Australian Army Malaria Institute
Weary Dunlop Drive, Gallipoli Barracks, Enoggera, Brisbane QLD 4051</address>
      <phone>61-7-33324930</phone>
      <fax>61-7-33324800</fax>
      <email>Mike.Edstein@defence.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Mike Edstein</name>
      <address>Australian Army Malaria Institute
Weary Dunlop Drive, Gallipoli Barracks, Enoggera, Brisbane QLD 4051</address>
      <phone>61-7-33324930</phone>
      <fax>61-7-33324800</fax>
      <email>Mike.Edstein@defence.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Mike Edstein</name>
      <address>Australian Army Malaria Institute
Weary Dunlop Drive, Gallipoli Barracks, Enoggera, Brisbane QLD 4051</address>
      <phone>61-7-33324930</phone>
      <fax>61-7-33324800</fax>
      <email>Mike.Edstein@defence.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>