<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369854">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000201471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Outcomes related to symptomatic vasospasm after aneurysmal subarachnoid haemorrhage before-and-after the introduction of neuro-interventional radiology service</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Outcomes related to symptomatic vasospasm after aneurysmal subarachnoid haemorrhage before-and-after the introduction of neuro-interventional radiology service</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>subarachnoid haemorrhage</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a single center retrospective before-and-after cohort study. The primary aim is to to evaluate the difference in unfavorable neurological outcomes, as assessed by modified Rankin Scale (mRS) &gt;=3, among all consecutive Intensive Care Unit (ICU) patients, who were admitted with Subarachnoid Haemorrhage (SAH) and suspected to have symptomatic vasospasm (SV), 30 months before and 30 months after the introduction of the Neuro-Interventional radiology (NIR) service at our university-affiliated tertiary-care referral hospital. The required data will first be collected for the period between 1 Jul 2010 to 30 Dec 2012 (the before phase), and then for the period between 1 Jan 2013 to 30 June 2015 (the after phase). All consecutive patients who would be deemed eligible according to the following criteria would be enrolled.

mRS scores and follow-up are planned to be recorded at or closest to 6 months after the date of ictus.

The NIR service at John Hunter Hospital was introduced in January 2103. Before the service was introduced, patients with SAH were managed by the Neuro-Surgery service either expectantly, having the aneurysm coiled in theatre or transferred to Royal North Shore Hospital for management of complex aneurysms and complications like SV.
Since the introduction of the NIR service, patients have access to angioplasty, coiling and intra-arterial calcium channel blockers when indicated.</interventions>
    <comparator>The primary aim is to evaluate the difference in unfavorable neurological outcomes, as assessed by mRS &gt;=3, among all consecutive Intensive Care Unit (ICU) patients, who were admitted with SAH and suspected to have SV, 30 months before and 30 months after the introduction of the Neuro-Interventional radiology (NIR) service at our university-affiliated tertiary-care referral hospital.
Required data will be collected retrospectively for the 1 Jul 2010 to 30 Dec 2012 period (for the pre-NIR group or 'before' phase) and then for the 1 Jan 2013 to 30 June 2015 period (for the NIR group or 'after' phase).</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the difference in unfavorable neurological outcomes, as assessed by mRS &gt;=3, among all consecutive Intensive Care Unit (ICU) patients, who were admitted with SAH and suspected to have Symptomatic Vasospasm (SV).</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 months before and 30 months after the introduction of the Neuro-Interventional radiology (NIR) service at our university-affiliated tertiary-care referral hospital. 
Time period between 1 Jul 2010 to 30 Dec 2012 (the before phase), and then for the period between 1 Jan 2013 to 30 June 2015 (the after phase). 
mRS data will be recorded at or closest to 6 months after the date of ictus.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess whether the after phase was associated with lower incidence of SV as compared to that during the before phase. Data to be collected from hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collected for eligible patients admitted in the time period between 1 Jul 2010 to 30 Dec 2012 (the before phase), and then for the period between 1 Jan 2013 to 30 June 2015 (the after phase). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess whether the time spent with unsecured aneurysm prior to the onset of SV, have any relationship with MRS scores and mortality. Data to be collected from hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collected for eligible patients admitted in the time period between 1 Jul 2010 to 30 Dec 2012 (the before phase), and then for the period between 1 Jan 2013 to 30 June 2015 (the after phase).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess if there is any difference in the time to develop SV between the two phases.  Data to be collected from hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from onset of SAH to documented SV in the notes. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare World Federation of Neurosurgical Societies (WFNS) grade , Prognosis on Admission of Aneurysmal Subarachnoid Haemorrhage (PAASH) score , Fisher score and Claassen scale as predictors of neurological outcomes assessed by mRS.</outcome>
      <timepoint>WFNS, PAASH, Fisher score and Claassen scale completed at time of admission to tertiary care centre, and neurological outcome assessed by mRS scores available at or closest to 6 months after the date of ictus.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess whether the after phase was associated with lower incidence of cerebral infarcts as compared to that during the before phase. Data to be collected from hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collected for eligible patients admitted in the time period between 1 Jul 2010 to 30 Dec 2012 (the before phase), and then for the period between 1 Jan 2013 to 30 June 2015 (the after phase). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess whether the after phase was associated with lower mortality as compared to that during the before phase. Data to be collected from hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collected for eligible patients admitted in the time period between 1 Jul 2010 to 30 Dec 2012 (the before phase), and then for the period between 1 Jan 2013 to 30 June 2015 (the after phase).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess whether the after phase was associated with shorter length of ICU admission as compared to that during the before phase. Data to be collected from hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collected for eligible patients admitted in the time period between 1 Jul 2010 to 30 Dec 2012 (the before phase), and then for the period between 1 Jan 2013 to 30 June 2015 (the after phase).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess whether the after phase was associated with shorter length of hospital admission as compared to that during the before phase. Data to be collected from hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collected for eligible patients admitted in the time period between 1 Jul 2010 to 30 Dec 2012 (the before phase), and then for the period between 1 Jan 2013 to 30 June 2015 (the after phase).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess whether the time spent in non-critical care areas prior to the onset of SV, have any relationship with MRS scores and mortality. Data to be collected from hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Data collected for eligible patients admitted in the time period between 1 Jul 2010 to 30 Dec 2012 (the before phase), and then for the period between 1 Jan 2013 to 30 June 2015 (the after phase).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adult (18 years or above) ICU patients
Diagnosis of SAH confirmed on a CT scan with suspected SV.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Died or treatment limitations within 3 days of hospitalisation
Died within 3 days of the initial rupture of the aneurysm
Non-aneurysmal causes of SAH (e.g. trauma, arterio-venous malformation)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Standard descriptive analysis of categorical variables (frequencies and percents) with effect sizes modeled using logistic regression. 
The Modified Rankin Score will be used to measure pre- and post- introduction of NIR service. 
Significance level is chosen to be &lt;0.05. 
Statistical analysis will be performed using Stata 13.1 (College Station, Texas).

Previous studies have reported an 18% incidence of SV among SAH patients who had an uncomplicated course of treatment. Endovascular treatment of vasospasm can reverse angiographic vasospasm by 96% and is reported to improve neurologic outcomes in 60% to 80% of these patients. Accordingly, with an estimated baseline SV incidence rate of 20%, we would require a sample size of 75 patients per phase to demonstrate 75% relative risk reduction in the proportion of unfavourable neurological outcomes. This sample size would provide 80% power at a two-sided p value of 0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Retrospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/02/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>John Hunter Hospital Royal Newcastle Centre - New Lambton</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Jorge Pena Mogollon</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>John Hunter Hospital
Lookout Rd, New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Jorge Pena Mogollon</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>John Hunter Hospital
Lookout Rd, New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Hypothesis: We hypothesize that the introduction of NIR service at our hospital is associated with a significant reduction in unfavorable neurological outcomes related to SV among patients with SAH. Our secondary hypothesis is that there is an association between clinical outcomes and the length of ICU stay prior to the surgical or endovascular management of SAH and that prior to suspected SV.

Aims:  Our primary aim is to compare differences in neurological outcomes, among patients who were admitted with SAH and were suspected to have SV, during a period of 30 months before-and-after the introduction of NIR service at a university-affiliated tertiary referral hospital.
Primary objective: To assess and compare modified Rankin scores (mRS), at/or closest to 6 months after hospital discharge, among patients with SAH and suspected SV during a period of 30 months before and 30 months after the introduction of NIR service at our hospital.

Secondary objectives: 
* To assess whether the after phase was associated with lower incidence of SV, lower incidence of cerebral infarcts, shorter length of hospital admission, and lower mortality as compared to that during the before phase. 
* To assess whether the time spent with unsecured aneurysm, or the time spent in non-critical care areas prior to the onset of SV have any relationship with mRS scores and mortality.

Methods: This is a retrospective before-and-after study at a multidisciplinary academic ICU at John Hunter Hospital, Newcastle. The study will be conducted over a period of 12 months during which the required data will be collected retrospectively for the 1 Jul 2010 to 30 Dec 2012 period and then for the 1 Jan 2013 to 30 June 2015 period. All consecutive eligible patients admitted during the two periods will be enrolled in the study. Besides demographics, severity scores and clinical outcomes, the study will also collect data related to process-of-care during the two periods.
 
Significance: The health and financial burden of long-term complications due to SV among patients with SAH are substantial. This observational study will inform the overall clinical outcomes for these patients in our practice. This may help us benchmark our clinical outcomes against those reported in international studies. This baseline data might also be useful to design an interventional trial investigating strategies to improve quality of care delivered to this patient group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not required</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jorge Pena Mogollon</name>
      <address>John Hunter Hospital 
Lookout Rd, New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+61404180627</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrespena9@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jorge Pena Mogollon</name>
      <address>John Hunter Hospital
Lookout Rd, New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+61404180627</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrespena9@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jorge Pena MOgollon</name>
      <address>John Hunter Hospital
Lookout Rd, New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+61404180627</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrespena9@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jorge Pena Mogollon</name>
      <address>PO Box 3253, Wamberal, NSW 2260</address>
      <phone>+61404180627</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>andrespena9@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>