<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="244">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/08/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/09/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000286640</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of a brief self-help intervention for post infectious irritable bowel syndrome (IBS)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial of a brief self-help cognitive behavioural therapy intervention for symptom relief in post infectious irritable bowel syndrome (IBS)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Post infectious irritable bowel syndrome (IBS)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients in this study were randomised to receive either a brief self-help intervention based on cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT) principles or standard medical care across the same seven week period. The self-help intervention developed specifically for this study consists of a structured manual divided into seven weekly sessions.  The first chapter provides a detailed biopsychosocial model of IBS that explains why patients continue to experience symptoms after their initial infection and justifies the approach used in the manual.  The remaining chapters provide behavioural guidelines for managing diarrhoea and constipation, advice on behavioural change for diet and exercise, cognitive strategies to challenge unhelpful thoughts or beliefs about symptoms, identifying and managing perfectionism, as well as stress and sleep management.   Patients received the manual together with an initial face-to-face session with a CBT therapist explaining the programme and the model of IBS and two one-hour phone call follow-ups at 3 and 5 weeks into the programme with the same therapist.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard medical care.
Patients in the standard medical care group received a detailed   assessment by a specialist general practitioner (GP) to determine if they met Rome criteria for IBS, a fact sheet explaining why they have been diagnosed with IBS and a recommendation to consult with their own GP for further treatment options.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Subjects Global Assessment of Relief (Muller-Lissner et al. (2003) which has been developed as a primary assessment of outcome in clinical studies of IBS with the intention of identifying responders to therapy</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at the end of treatment, and 3 and 6 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Irritable Bowel Symptom Severity Scoring System (Francis et al., 1997) which provides an indication of bowel symptom severity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, end of treatment, 3 and 6 months follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Work and Social Adjustment Scale (WSAS) (Mundt et al 2002), is used to measure the impact of IBS on the persons day to day life.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, end of treatment, 3 and 6 months followup.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Hospital Anxiety and Depression scale (HAD) (Zigmond 1983) is used to assess the degree of anxiety and depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, end of treatment, 3 and 6 months followup.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(a) a diagnosis of IBS based on Rome I modified and/or Rome II criteria. (b) a diagnosis of IBS subsequent to an episode of gastroenteritis (c) between the ages of 18-70 (d) primary care attendees in the greater Auckland area. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(a) Patients who have another medical condition that may affect their symptoms or preclude a diagnosis of IBS such as previous bowel surgery or a malignancy, ceoliac disease, inflammatory bowel disease, or obstructive bowel pathology (b) Patients who have any serious psychological disorders for whom treatment would be inappropriate including psychotic disorders or active substance abuse. (c). Non-English speakers and people who are unable to read and write English. (d) Should any participants alter their medication during this time period, or begin a course of anti-depressant medication their data will not be included in the final analysis. (e) Inclusion in another treatment trial.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation was achieved by placing equal numbers of the words â¿¿controlâ¿¿ or â¿¿treatmentâ¿ in 80 separate, opaque envelopes which were ordered according to random numbers and then sealed. These were kept in order by an independent administrator. As each new participant entered the study, the independent administrator opened the envelope on the top of the pile and informed the participant of their group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Through randomization.com a computerised randomisation programme.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2003</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Rona Moss-Morris</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Auckland Staff Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Rosie Williamson</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Leona Didsbury</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Laura Bogalo</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Trudie Chalder</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Rona Moss-Morris</name>
      <address>Psychological Medicine
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland</address>
      <phone>64 9 3737599 (Ext.) 86756</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 3737013</fax>
      <email>r.moss-morris@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Laura Bogalo</name>
      <address>Psychological Medicine
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3737599</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 3737013</fax>
      <email>jbogalo@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>