<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369676">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001286538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An evaluation of environmental enrichment for young girls with Rett syndrome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>What is the effect of an environmentally enriched therapy program on function and health in two to six year old girls with Rett syndrome?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1176-8853</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Rett syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each child will be assessed over a baseline period prior to the intervention period. The length of baseline will be determined randomly and will be either 1, 2 or 3 months. Assessments during baseline will be monthly and there will be 2, 3 and 4 assessments for those with a 1, 2 and 3 month baseline period respectively.
The treatment program will be conducted in a therapy centre in Shenzhen, China and will include multiple supported activities within a rich sensori-motor environment and the specific activities used will target individual goals in the development of motor skills. The activities will be characterised by a high volume of practice and physical activity, and biologically, will aim to increase production of Brain Derived Neurotrophic Factor (BDNF). The programs design is also consistent with Motor Learning Theory, including opportunities for practice, intrinsic and extrinsic feedback, judicious use of rest periods, and performance of tasks in a variety of conditions that provide choice, are developmentally engaging and provide opportunities for cognitive learning. For example, tasks will include a range of motor activities such as transitions, standing and walking and each child will be encouraged to build both skill and endurance. The intervention will be conducted for 2 to 3 hours each morning on five days a week. This will continue over a 6 month period. Sessions will be conducted in small groups. During the therapy sessions, one-on-one supervision will be provided by the physiotherapist. The therapist will record a log of attendance, duration of sessions and the activities practiced. Each therapist-child dyad will work within a small group with one to two other therapist-child dyads to provide additional social stimulation during the treatment sessions.</interventions>
    <comparator>There is no separate control group in this study. However, each child will be assessed over a baseline period and these data will be compared with data collected over the intervention period. Each child will be her own control.
The participants will however form three groups depending on the duration of their baseline period which determined randomly and will be either 1, 2 or 3 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gross motor function as assessed by the Rett Syndrome Gross Motor Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 3, 6 and 9 months during the intervention period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum levels of BDNF</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and 9 months after beginning of intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of sleep using the Sleep Disturbance Scale for Children </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 3, 6 and 9 months during the intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Behaviour measured by the Rett Syndrome Behaviour Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 3, 6 and 9 months during the intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Constipation measured by family report of child bowel habits</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 3, 6 and 9 months during the intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent rating of top three concerns for their childs health and wellbeing on a visual analogue scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline and at 3, 6 and 9 months during the intervention period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The child will have genetically confirmed Rett syndrome and will be aged between two and six years. Over the previous 12 months, the child will have received no therapy or very low doses of therapy that is less frequent than fortnightly.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The child is older than six years and has been participating in an intensive therapy program over the previous 12 months.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Each child will be randomly allocated to either a 1, 2 or 3 month baseline period. Randomisation will be conducted at a separate site and allocation will be concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be conducted using the computer program STATA.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This will be a stepped wedge randomised controlled trial.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based on previous data, we estimate a sample size of 12 girls will give us 90% power to identify within-subject gross motor changes with a change of at least 1.2 points on the complex gross motor skills subscale scale of the Rett Syndrome Gross Motor Scale.
The data describing each of the dependent variables over time will be graphed to illustrate levels and trends, and mean values and the inclinations of the slopes for each outcome variable will be compared. We will use linear mixed models to assess the effect of the intervention, taking into account the confounders of time since regression and the type of BDNF polymorphism.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/12/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/10/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>10/01/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>12</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/02/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Guangdong</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Telethon Kids Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Telethon Kids Institute
PO Box 855
West Perth
Western Australia 6872
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Rettsyndrome.org</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rettsyndrome.org 
P.O. Box 706143
Cincinnati, OH 45270-6143</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Girls with Rett syndrome have difficulties performing motor skills. Animal studies have found that the mice with a MECP2 mutation develop better motor skills if their environment is enriched, possibly due to the extra physical activity which then increases production of Brain Derived Neurotrophic Factor (BDNF). BDNF is an important protein for nerve cell growth and maturity. For Rett syndrome, therapies should be more effective if implemented intensively at an early age due not only to inherent brain plasticity and capacity to learn but also potentially due to stimulation of BDNF production. We know that girls with Rett syndrome can learn new skills with training and practice. However, available research studies have involved small numbers of girls with no comparison group or period and we do not know the precise benefits of intensive early intervention in Rett syndrome. This study involves collaboration between researchers and clinicians in Australia and China. Our study will recruit approximately 12 girls younger than 6 years and assess the girls during a period with no intervention and then during an eight to nine month period with environmental enrichment. We will assess motor function, sleep, behaviour, constipation and serum levels of BDNF. Our study will determine the evidence base for intensive environmental enrichment for young girls newly diagnosed with Rett syndrome giving clearer guidance for both clinicians and families</summary>
    <trialwebsite>None</trialwebsite>
    <publication>None as yet</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, University of Western Australia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Western Australia M459, 
35 Stirling Highway, 
Crawley WA 6009 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/1/7782</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/08/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, Shenzhen Children's Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>7019, Yitian Road 
Fu Tian District 
Guangdong Province 
Shenzhen
China, 518026</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/10/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015[014]</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jenny Downs</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute
PO Box 855
West Perth
Perth
Western Australia
6872</address>
      <phone>+61 9489 7777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jenny.downs@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jenny Downs</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute
PO Box 855
West Perth
Perth
Western Australia
6872</address>
      <phone>+61 9489 7777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jenny.downs@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jenny Downs</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute
PO Box 855
West Perth
Perth
Western Australia
6872</address>
      <phone>+61 9489 7777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jenny.downs@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jenny Downs</name>
      <address>Telethon Kids Institute
PO Box 855
West Perth
Perth
Western Australia
6872</address>
      <phone>+61 9489 7777</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jenny.downs@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>