<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364749">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/08/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000905763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial of Shen Mi Tang in Treating subacute cough</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with post infectious cough of 3-8 weeks, does  Shen Mi Tang compared to placebo, improve cough?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>post infectious cough</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Herbal remedies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>  The study will be a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind clinical trial with medication for 7 days followed by observation for 7 days also.
There were two groups in the study. The subjects of Treatment group will take Shen Mi Tang (400mg), 5 capsules three times a day(6g per day) per oral  for a 7 days course of treatment. 
Components of Shen Mi Tang 
Ephedrae Herba   6g
Armeniacae Semen  4.8g
Magnoliae Cortex  3.6g
Auranti Nobilis Pericarpium   3g 
Glycyrrhizae Radix   2.4g
Bupleuri Radix  2.4g
Perilla Herba 1.8g
These raw herbs were refined   to 4g  extract  and  mixed with 2g starch  to 6g powder by Sheng Chang Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.
  dextromethorphan 15mg/TAB per oral one to three times a day  will be given as rescue drug when cough is intolerable 
  To get cough symptom score , a  phone call at day 3,5 of treatment was given to the patients by study coordinator. a card was also given to patient to record their daily drug taking and Visual Analogue Scale(VAS) of cough.
  The Visual Analogue Scale(VAS) will be adopted for measuring the severity of patient reported cough.The patient will be asked to mark the severity of his/her cough condition on a visual analogous scale of  0 to 100 mm at the time points (Day 1,3,5,8,15).
</interventions>
    <comparator>  The subjects of Control group will take placebo capsules of Shen Mi Tang, 5 capsules three times a day(6g starch per day)  per oral  for a 7 days course of treatment.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of patients with "Significant Improvement" in daytime Cough Symptom Score(CSS) will be the primary efficacy endpoint of  this study.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>"Significant Improvement" is defined as that patient's CSS score on day 8 is reduced by two or more score levels comparing with the baseline CSS on day 1.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percentage of patients with Improvement in daytime or night-time Cough Symptom Score(CSS)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Improvement is defined as that patients CSS score on day 8 is reduced by one score level comparing with the baseline CSS on day 1.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change from baseline in visual analogous scale(VAS) score on cough severity</outcome>
      <timepoint>a visual analogous scale of  0 to 100 mm at the time points (Day 1,3,5,8,15).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.age from  20 to 65 y/o
2.persist cough for 3-8 weeks without present illness as asthma, Gastroesophageal reflux disease,postnasal drip)
3.Cough pattern is dry cough or cough with little sputum. presentations of cough are  throat itching, paroxysmal cough or cough irritated by smoke,dust or temperature.
4.Day time or night-time Cough Symptom Score (CSS) &gt;= 2
5.sign informed consent form
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.chronic respiratory disease as asthma, bronchiectasis
,chronic bronchitis etc.
2.severe disorders which may induce persistent cough (as:cystic fibrosis,congestive heart  failure etc.)
3.Gastroesophageal reflux disease or postnasal drip  detected by patient or diagnosed by doctor in recent 3 months
4.neoplasm or other significant abnormality suspected under chest  X  ray   examination
5.recent smoker   (smoking abstinence  shorter than 6 months ) 
6.pregnant or breast feeding   women
7.taking Angiotension-converting enzyme inhibitors in 1 month
8.body temperature over 37.5 degrees Celsius
9.blood WBC &gt;10000 per microliter or &lt; 4000 per microliter
10.difficult  to fit  in with study process
11.other clinical trial participants in recent 1 month</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Promotional posters about the study, referral criteria and contact number of primary investigator and study coordinator were pasted on bulletin board outside clinic rooms of investigators, including two internal medical physician of traditional Chinese medicine, one chest specialist and one ENT specialist.
Patients with cough as chief complaint will be candidates and be diagnosed on the basis of detailed history and clinical examination and be referred to study coordinator by investigator if they match inclusion criteria. Trained study coordinator is responsible for enrolment of patients, study explanation, data collection. These patients will be enrolled if they fulfill the study’s eligibility criteria. The enrolled patients will be administered with study drug by the investigator and be given patient daily diary by study coordinator. Patients not fulfilling the criteria will accept other treatment administered by investigator.
Allocation concealment procedure was performed by Sheng Chang Pharmaceutical Co. 
</concealment>
    <sequence>Random allocation was made in blocks to keep the sizes of treatment groups similar. It was performed by Sheng Chang Pharmaceutical Co. which was entrusted with production of study drugs. However, the real content of allocation was concealed in envelope and kept by study pharmacist</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size determination
According to reports of Shen Mi Tang s clinical trials and our clinical observation, the response rate (p1) is about 0.6. We also suppose the placebo effect (p2) is 0.1.
Using test for Superiority, a two sided test, 5% significance level test (alpha=0.05) with power 80% power (beta =0.2), p1=0.6, p2=0.1, drop-out rate = 0.05. 
Number obtained is 16 for each group under calculation by formula.
  All analysis will be done on intention to treat basis. 
  Efficacy endpoints will be listed and summarized as appropriate: mean/median,standard deviation, minimum, maximum and total numbers for normally distributed data; median and range for non-normally distributed data; frequencies, total numbers and percentages for categorical data.
       The baseline demographic characteristics in both treatment and control groups will be compared using Chi-square test or Fisher's exact test for categorical variables and t-test or Wilcoxon Rank-Sum test for continuous variables.
      The percentage of patients with "Significant Improvement" and "Improvement" in daytime Cough Symptom Score will be tested using Fisher's exact test or Chi-square test. Logistic regression will be adopted to test the efficacy endpoint, if significant difference is observed in demographic variables.
      Paired t-test will be used to evaluate the change from baseline in VAS score within each treatment group and un-paired t-test will be used to compare the change from baseline in VAS score between the two treatment groups. Wilcoxon signed-rank test and Wilcoxon rank-sum test will be used instead if the normal assumption is violated. The analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) may be used to account for any potential covariate such as baseline and demographic variables when comparing the difference in efficacy endpoints between the treatment group and the control group.
      All efficacy tests will be conducted at an alpha level of 0.05 (2-tailed) and 95% confidence interval will be reported.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>16/12/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <state>Taoyuan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Jong-Jen Kuo (Principal investigator)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Division of Chinese Internal Medicine, Center for Traditional Chinese Medicine, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, No. 123,Dinghu Road, Guei-shan, Taoyuan 33378, Taiwan</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Health and Welfare Department of Chinese Medicine and Pharmacy</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>No.36, Tacheng St., Datong District, Taipei City 10341, Taiwan (R.O.C.)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Clinical Trial Center for Traditional Chinese Medicine in Chang Gung Medical Foundation</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>No.123, Dinghu Rd., Guishan Town Ownship, Taoyuan County 333,Taiwan, R.O.C</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cough is one of the most common causes for medical consultation. Post infectious cough is one of main causes of Subacute cough. The effectiveness of Over the counter(OTC) drugs for cough are controversial.  OTC drugs leading to sedation and other side effects also. 
 The Shen Mi Tang is commercially available herbal concentrates preparation, the indications for asthma, bronchitis. We found its good effects in the treatment of persistent dry cough post colds. So, it deserves evaluation by clinical trial.
    The clinical trial will be undertaken at Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, 32 Subacute cough patients will be enrolled, 16 patients in Control group and 16 patients in Treatment group. The study will be a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blind clinical trial with medication for 7 days followed by observation for 7 days also.The focus of the study is on the evaluation of efficacy of this formula for Subacute cough by Cough Symptom Score(CSS) and Visual Analogous Scale(VAS) and the safety of this formula will also be evaluated.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Chang Gung Medical Foundation Institutional Review Board</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>IRB,  B2, No. 123,Dinghu Road, Guei-shan, Taoyuan 33378, Taiwan</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>101-4441A3</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/11/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jong-Jen Kuo</name>
      <address>Division of Chinese Internal Medicine, Center for Traditional Chinese Medicine, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, No. 123,Dinghu Road, Guei-shan, Taoyuan 33378, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886 3 3196200#2676  or  +886 975360234</phone>
      <fax>+886 3 3294841</fax>
      <email>kjj308@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jong-Jen Kuo</name>
      <address>Division of Chinese Internal Medicine, Center for Traditional Chinese Medicine, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, No. 123,Dinghu Road, Guei-shan, Taoyuan 33378, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886 3 3196200#2676  or  +886 975360234</phone>
      <fax>+886 3 3294841</fax>
      <email>kjj308@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jong-Jen Kuo</name>
      <address>Division of Chinese Internal Medicine, Center for Traditional Chinese Medicine, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, No. 123,Dinghu Road, Guei-shan, Taoyuan 33378, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886 3 3196200#2676  or  +886 975360234</phone>
      <fax>+886 3 3294841</fax>
      <email>kjj308@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jong-Jen Kuo</name>
      <address>Division of Chinese Internal Medicine, Center for Traditional Chinese Medicine, Chang Gung Memorial Hospital, No. 123,Dinghu Road, Guei-shan, Taoyuan 33378, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886 3 3196200#2676  or  +886 975360234</phone>
      <fax>+886 3 3294841</fax>
      <email>kjj308@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>