<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368337">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/04/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000384550</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The benefit of targeted pharmacist education in reducing prescribing errors by junior doctors  a controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The benefit of targeted pharmacist education in reducing prescribing errors by junior doctors  a controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>REPREP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prescribing errors</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention (1): Regular prescribing feedback and targeted education of junior doctors by a clinical pharmacist, through three ten minute sessions per week for four weeks.
- These sessions were face-to-face with a clinical pharmacist, in a convenient ward space (eg meeting rooms), and were conducted as a group (3 interns, 1 registrar and the clinical pharmacist)
- One of the principle investigators collected data from the medication charts of the general medical wards, pertaining to the type and frequency of prescribing errors. This was discussed with the clinical pharmacist and the feedback/teaching sessions focussed on common prescribing errors seen on the wards, as well as dangerous prescribing errors recently identified. 
 

Intervention (2): e-learning intervention whereby junior doctors completed the Australian National Prescribing Services (NPS) National Inpatient Medication Chart Training e-learning course.
- This e-learning course comprises 7 modules covering aspects of safe prescribing. 
- The modules are estimated to take between 80-95 minutes to complete all together. 
- E-learning intervention doctors were asked to complete the course between the end of the baseline data collection period and the start of the intervention data collection (over the weekend) and to show the investigators the certificate of completion. </interventions>
    <comparator>No educational intervention. 

2 General medical units in which the junior doctors received no intervention. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prescribing error rate, calculated by dividing the total number of prescribing errors identified by the total number of medication orders written. We compared pre-intervention error rates to post-intervention error rates. </outcome>
      <timepoint>3 weeks baseline data collected, 4 weeks of intervention data. 

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All junior doctors who were rotated onto general medicine at the time of the study participated, consisting of 12 interns and four registrars. All units were made aware of the study before it began, and doctors were informed that they were expected to participate as part of an ongoing quality assurance process. 
There was no particular age limit for doctors to participate. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>nil. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All junior doctors who were rotated onto general medicine at the time of the study participated, consisting of 12 interns and four registrars. The unit each doctor was assigned to was pre-determined by the hospital as part of the usual junior doctor rotations. 

All units were made aware of the study before it began, and doctors were informed that they were expected to participate as part of an ongoing quality assurance process. Consultants were not involved in the study. Each unit was randomised to an intervention, as described below. 

Allocation was not concealed. </concealment>
    <sequence>The four general medical units were randomised to two intervention groups (one unit each) and control groups (two units) using a random number generator and a pre-defined sequence of allocation. Each medical unit was known by its number (medical unit 1, medical unit 2, medical unit 3 and medical unit 4). We pre-defined a sequence of allocation of unit to intervention group as (in order) Intervention one, intervention two, control unit 1 and control unit 2. Using a random number generator to provide numbers between 1 and 4, we allocated the first intervention to the unit corresponding to the first number produced, the second unit to the second number produced, etc. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis was undertaken by chi-squared comparison of prescribing error rate for each group prior to, and following the intervention. 

Our study objectives related to number of medication errors recorded rather than participant numbers. Based on a two-sided alpha value of 0.05 and 80% power to detect a 20% difference in error rate between the two periods (pre-intervention vs post-intervention: 40% vs 32%), we estimated that 589 medication orders were required per study group (a total of 1767). It was elected to collect data for longer than this number required due to the continuous nature of the pharmacist educational intervention. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/02/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>21/03/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>16</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3050 - Royal Melbourne Hospital</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Melbourne Hosptial</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>300 Grattan Street, Parkville VIC 3050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Melbourne - Provided funding for access to a statistical analysis program for the principle investigator, but provided no further funding for the project. There were no further funding sources. </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Parkville VIC 3010
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Prescribing errors are a known cause of adverse patient outcomes. The objective of this study was to assess the effect of (1) targeted pharmacist feedback and education and (2) an e-learning prescribing module, on prescribing error rates by junior doctors in the inpatient general medical setting. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>nil to date. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>300 Grattan Street, Parkville VIC 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>QA2013185</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jared Gursanscky</name>
      <address>Via Melbourne health: 300 Grattan Street, Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61450504674</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jgursanscky@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jared Gursanscky</name>
      <address>Via Melbourne health: 300 Grattan Street, Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 (03) 9342 7000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jgursanscky@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jared Gursanscky</name>
      <address>Via Melbourne health: 300 Grattan Street, Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 (03) 9342 7000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jgursanscky@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jared Gursanscky</name>
      <address>Via Melbourne health: 300 Grattan Street, Parkville VIC 3050</address>
      <phone>+61 (03) 9342 7000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>