<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373343">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001119381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Circulating Tumour DNA in Stage 1 to 3 Ovarian Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Circulating Tumour DNA as a Marker of Residual Disease and Response to Adjuvant Chemotherapy in Stage I - III Optimally Debulked Epithelial Ovarian, Fallopian Tube and Primary Peritoneal Cancer (EOC)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1199-5975 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>WEHI-ctDNA-10</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ovarian cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Study involves serial blood collections in patients with stage I-III epithelial or carcinosarcoma ovarian cancer who have undergone surgery and are planned to receive adjuvant chemotherapy. Up to four blood samples will be collected from each patient over a 6-8 month period for circulating tumour DNA (ctDNA) and Ca125 analysis. Following completion of chemotherapy the patient will be followed up every three months with blood test for Ca125 for the first two years then followed as per clinician's discretion for survival information.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Association between ctDNA detection in peripheral blood with disease recurrence, as assessed by review of medical records.
Disease recurrence is assessed by medical review of symptoms, standard CA125 blood tests with or without a CT scan</outcome>
      <timepoint>ctDNA samples are collected at 4 time points only; prior to commencing the first cycle of chemotherapy then again prior to the 3rd and 5th cycles of chemotherapy and finally 6-8 weeks following completion of chemotherapy. 
Disease recurrence is then assessed for up to a maximum of 4 years; initially every 3 months for the first 2 years that at intervals at the discretion of the treating clinician.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Association between presence of detectable ctDNA and time to disease recurrence.
Recurrence is assessed by medical review of symptoms, standard CA125 blood test with or without a CT scan.


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Disease recurrence is assessed for up to a maximum of 4 years following completion of chemotherapy; initially every 3 months for the first 2 years that at intervals at the discretion of the treating clinician. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Subjects with optimally debulked stage I-III curatively resected high grade serous, endometrioid and clear cell ovarian, fallopian tube or primary peritoneal cancer or ovarian carcinosarcoma.
2.	A representative formalin fixed paraffin embedded tumour sample is available for molecular testing after surgery 
3.	Fit and planned for adjuvant platinum-based chemotherapy 
4.	Patients that are accessible for follow-up
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	History of another primary cancer within the last 3 years, with the exception of non-melanomatous skin cancer and carcinoma in situ of the cervix
2.	Patients with EOC of mucinous subtype or sarcoma
3.	Medical or psychiatric condition or occupational responsibilities that may preclude compliance with the protocol
4.	Patients who are undergoing neoadjuvant chemotherapy.
5.	Patients that are &lt;18 years old
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/07/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/08/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>3</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/06/2023</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1G Royal Parade, Parkville  VIC  3052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Marcus Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1G Royal Parade, Parkville  VIC  3052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to evaluate whether the presence of circulating tumour DNA (ctDNA) in a patient's blood following surgery or chemotherapy for ovarian cancer, is associated with cancer recurrence.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to enroll in this study if you are aged 18 or over and have optimally debulked stage I-III curatively resected high grade serous, endometrioid and clear cell ovarian, fallopian tube or primary peritoneal cancer or ovarian carcinosarcoma for which you are scheduled to commence adjuvant chemotherapy.

All patients enrolled in this study will have up to four blood samples collected over 6-8 months, followed by further blood samples every 3 months for 2 years following completion of chemotherapy. Your treating clinician may also decide to continue with further follow-up.
It is hoped that the findings from this trial will demonstrate an association between ctDNA detection in the patients blood following surgery, and following chemotherapy, with ovarian cancer recurrence. This would allow real-time testing of the benefit of adjuvant chemotherapy by assessing ctDNA. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Melbourne Hospital
Flemington Rd, Parkville VIC  3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/17/MH/108</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sumitra Ananda</name>
      <address>Victorian Comprehensive Cancer Centre
305 Grattan St, Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3  8559 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sumitra.ananda@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nicole Ng</name>
      <address>WEHI
1G Royal Parade, Parkville  VIC  3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9345 2880</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dynamic-ovarian@mh.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sumitra Ananda</name>
      <address>Victorian Comprehensive Cancer Centre
305 Grattan St, Melbourne VIC 3000</address>
      <phone>+61 3  8559 5000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sumitra.ananda@petermac.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>