<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369598">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/11/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000527460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can video laryngoscopy make a difference in time to successfull tracheal intubation for caesarian section: the comparison between the C-MAC Video Laryngoscope, the King Vision Video Laryngoscopes and Direct Laryngoscopy </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can video laryngoscopy make a difference in time to successful tracheal intubation for  caesarian section: the comparison between the C-MAC Video Laryngoscope, the King Vision Video Laryngoscopes and Direct Laryngoscopy </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Intubation for caesarian section </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>After rapid sequence induction using a combination of propofol 2mg/kg i.v., esmeron 1 mg/kg i.v. and Fentanyl 1 mcg/kg i.v. and anaesthetist used one of three intubation devices.
Direct laryngoscopy using a curved Macintosh blade is still the standard technique for tracheal intubation during C-section but  the video laryngoscopes can provide an indirect view of the larynx and have been used to manage the difficult airway in the operating room.
The King Vision Video laryngoscope (KVL) (King Systems, Indianapolis, Indiana) is a new indirect two-piece design laryngoscope consisting of a reusable monitor attached to disposable blades. All blades are Macintosh #3 size and compared to a normal Macintosh #3 bladed laryngoscope appear wider and shorter. The blade is inserted into the mouth in the middle, over the centre of the tongue with a single circular movement, while its back surface is maintained against the palate and palatopharyngeal curve. Once the view of glottis is optimized, the tube is passed through the vocal cord into the trachea. We used KVL with a guiding channel. The guiding channel is positioned on the right side of the blade and acts as a conduit holding and directing the tracheal tube through the glottic opening when the vocal cords are visualized.
The C-MAC Video laryngoscope has the Macintosh # 3 or 4 blades incorporating a high-power light-emitting diode located in their distal third and extending the viewing angle from the standard 15 degrees to 80 degrees. The VL consists of two parts, a laryngoscope and a monitor, connected via a single cable. A 2-mm digital camera is sited within the shorter laryngoscope handle and a magnified image displayed on a screen. The C-MAC displaces soft tissue in a similar fashion to a classic Macintosh laryngoscope, affording room for tracheal tube insertion and consequently less need for intubating adjuncts.</interventions>
    <comparator>Direct laryngoscopy using a curved Macintosh blade is still the standard technique for tracheal intubation during C-section but it has important limitations, such as the impossibility to always align the oro-pharyngeal-laryngeal axes as well as the difficulty in predicting the airway-related problems by using the routine bedside screening-tests. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>time to successful tracheal intubation (defined as the interval from the blade insertion to the blade removal from the mouth).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>During induction of GA</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>laryngeal view according to Cormac-Lehane grade ( C/L grade 1, 2 or b, 3,4)</outcome>
      <timepoint>During intubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparative ease of tracheal tube insertion, as subjectively assessed using a 100 mm Visual Analogue Scale with 0 mm = extremely easy and 100 mm = extremely difficult</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following intubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the number of attempts at intubation assessed by rewiew of surgical notes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following intubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>rate of successful intubation assessed by review of surgical notes. A failed intubation was defined as an attempt in which the user could not intubate the patient's trachea within two intubating attempts using the same blade, failure to intubate the trachea with the airway device within 60 sec, and patient desaturating at SaO2&lt;92%, will lead to abandonment of the study and the airway will then be managed according to the ASA difficult airway algorithm and guidelines.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following intubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Use of optimisation manoeures such as repositioning of the patients head, use of external laryngeal pressure, increase or decrease lifting force of the laryngoscope handle, further advancement or withdrawal of the laryngoscope blade assessed by review of surgical notes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following intubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for airway adjuncts such as bougie and ILMA assessed by rewiew of surgical notes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following intubation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria> Parturients of ASA physical status 1-3, scheduled for either elective or emergency C-section  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>50</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with the ASA physical status &gt;3 or the predicted difficult airway requiring awake intubation will be excluded.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>allocation involved contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who was "off-site" or at central administration site</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>For the significance level of p &lt; 0.01, power of 95%, clinically important difference of 15s and population standard deviation of 18 sec we are going to require 52 patients per group. In order to allow for drop outs and for ease of randomisation we are planning to recruit 60 patients per group for this parallel three group study design.
SPSS will be used for analyses the data. ANOVA will be used for normally distributed continuous data, Kruskal-Wallis for non-normally distributed continuous and ordinal categorical data and Chi-Squared test for nominal data.
 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>12/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>12/09/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>20/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>180</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>21/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovenia</country>
      <state>Ljubljana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Slovenia</country>
      <state>Ljubljana</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University medical center Ljubljana</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University medical centre Ljubljana, Zaloska 7, 1000 Ljubljana, Slovenia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Slovenia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University Clinical Centre Ljubljana, Slovenia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Zaloska 7, Ljubljana, 1000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Slovenia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University medical center Ljubljana</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University medical centre Ljubljana, Zaloska 7, 1000 Ljubljana, Slovenia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Slovenia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>1.	Introduction
There are few reports of using videolaryngoscopy to manage the airway for C-Section.  We found no study evaluating the use of the KingVision videolaryngoscope for airway management in obstetric anaesthesia. The main goal of this study is to compare the KingVision videolaryngoscope with CMac videolaryngoscope and directoscopy with respect to time to successful intubation. The secondary outcomes are the quality of the laryngoscopic view, comparative ease of blade and tracheal tube insertion, the number of attempts at intubation, the rate of successful intubation, the use of optimization manoeuvres and the need for airway adjuncts. 
2.	Methods
After the Institutional Review Board Ethical Committee approval and the patients informed consent for general anaesthesia and endotracheal intubation, 180 parturients of ASA physical status 1-3, scheduled for either elective or emergency C-section will be included in the study. Patients with the ASA physical status &gt;3 or the predicted difficult airway requiring awake intubation will be excluded. Patients will be assigned to three groups using a computer-generated random number table. After recruitment, a sealed envelope with the group allocation will be opened by the enrolling investigator. All intubations will be performed by experienced anaesthesiologists who have previously done more than 30 intubations with the tested devices. Patients will be preoperatively evaluated to ascertain predictive indices for difficult intubation. GA will be commenced with a classical rapid sequence induction using a combination of fentanyl 1microgram/kg, propofol 2mg/kg and succinylcholine 1.5mg/kg or rocuronium 1 mg/kg. After fasciculation wearing off, the laryngoscopy will be carried out using one of the VLs or the classical metal Macintosh blade #3 or 4. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Republic of Slovenia National Medical Ethics Committe-NMEC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress> Zaloska 7, 1000 Ljubljana</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/02/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>33/02/15</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/01/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Slovenia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Iva Blajic</name>
      <address>Clinical Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Therapy
University Medical Centre Ljubljana
Zaloska 7
1000 Ljubljana</address>
      <phone>+38640524272</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>iva.blajic@kclj.si</email>
      <country>Slovenia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Iljaz Hodzovic</name>
      <address>Section of Anaesthetics, Intensive Care &amp; Pain Medicine
School of Medicine
Cardiff University
Heath Park
Cardiff CF14 4XN</address>
      <phone>+44 2920743109</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hodzovic@cardiff.ac.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Tatjana Stopar Pintaric</name>
      <address>Clinical Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Therapy
University Medical Centre Ljubljana
Zaloska 7
1000 Ljubljana</address>
      <phone>0038640125228</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tatjana.stoparpintaric@kclj.si</email>
      <country>Slovenia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Iva Blajic</name>
      <address>Clinical Department of Anaesthesiology and Intensive Therapy
University Medical Centre Ljubljana
Zaloska 7
1000 Ljubljana</address>
      <phone>0038640524272</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>iva.blajic@kclj.si</email>
      <country>Slovenia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>