<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367533">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/12/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000036516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Developing and testing a motivating communication/teaching style for Les Mills International instructors: A pilot study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of the feasibility and fidelity of a motivation-based communication training intervention with Les Mills International instructors: Effects on clients perceptions of instructor motivational style. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Perceptions of the degree to which Les Mills International instructors are motivationally supportive toward their clients.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will involve 3 workshops delivered by the research team, each lasting 2-3 hours. The workshops will be developed according to self-determination theory (Deci &amp; Ryan 1985). 

In the first workshop (3 hours), the basic principles of motivation (based on self-determination theory) will be introduced and specific examples of how these can be manifested in a fitness setting provided. Instructors will be introduced to different communication styles, using examples of fitness-client interactions. Furthermore, how different styles can have a powerful influence on client motivation and adherence will be explained. Group discussions will focus on how to implement a motivationally supportive instructional style and how to avoid using motivationally unsupportive strategies. The latter part of the workshop will involve brainstorming sessions as to how these ideas can be put into practice in a Les Mills RPM session. At the end of the workshop, instructors will be given specially prepared hand-outs on motivation to reinforce and supplement the content of the workshop. 

After the first workshop, the instructors will be asked to reflect on their own teaching and practise some of the motivational strategies that they were taught in the first workshop. They will also be asked to keep a reflective diary describing what worked, what didnt, obstacles and ways of overcoming them. They will be encouraged to connect face-to-face or via technology (e.g., an invitation-only Facebook page) to brainstorm examples of good and bad practice. Further, on-line material will be available to supplement and augment the material covered in the workshops.

Two weeks following the initial workshop, a booster 3-hour workshop will be offered during which successes and pitfalls in implementing the motivational strategies will be discussed. In addition, reflective diaries will be shared, and further advice will be offered to overcome obstacles. In the second half of the session instructors will be encouraged to use role play to practice using some of the motivational strategies in a mock RPM session.

During the third and fourth month of the project, the instructors will be asked to continue keeping a reflective diary and using our online material. A booster training workshop of 2 hours will be offered 8 weeks after the second workshop, at the end of the fourth month of the project. The booster workshop will reinforce the messages from workshops 1 and 2 and give the instructors the opportunity to share how they have found putting into practice the motivational strategies discussed.  

Additional support will be offered by the researchers to the instructors via telephone or email/Facebook consultations. On the Facebook page we will upload examples of best practice (with commentary from the research team), and there will also be an on-line discussion forum. For that forum, we will encourage the contribution of the 4-5 experienced fitness instructors who will be identified at the beginning of the project. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The active control group will consist of Les Mills RPM instructors who will receive no treatment/training during the intervention period. At the end of the intervention period, in the fifth month of the project, the control group will be given the opportunity to receive training exploring motivational strategies that can be used when instructing fitness classes. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clients perceptions of instructors motivational style including: autonomy support (short version of the Health-Care Client questionnaire by Williams &amp; Deci, 1996, adapted for the fitness context), controlling and non-need supportive behaviours (items written for the study), and Structure and Involvement (items adapted from Markland and Tobin, 2010). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (measured within 3 weeks prior to the first workshop), at the end of the training programme (within 2 weeks following the third workshop), and within 4-6 weeks after the end of the third workshop.  The time interval between the first and third workshop will be about 2 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Instructor reported motivational style: autonomy support (short version of the Health-Care Client Questionnaire, by Williams and Deci, 2006, adapted for the fitness context), controlling and non-need supportive behaviours (items written for this study), and structure and involvement (items adapted from Markland and Tobin, 2010).

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (measured within 3 weeks prior to the first workshop), at the end of the training programme (within 2 weeks following the third workshop), and within 4-6 weeks after the end of the third workshop.  The time interval between the first and third workshop will be about 2 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Instructor reported basic need satisfaction using the basic need satisfaction items from Chen et al.s (under review) Basic Need Satisfaction and Frustration Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (measured within 3 weeks prior to the first workshop), at the end of the training programme (within 2 weeks following the third workshop), and within 4-6 weeks after the end of the third workshop.  The time interval between the first and third workshop will be about 2 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Instructor motivation to teach Les Mills RPM classes measured using Trembley et al.s (2009) Work Extrinsic and Intrinsic Motivation Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (measured within 3 weeks prior to the first workshop), at the end of the training programme (within 2 weeks following the third workshop), and within 4-6 weeks after the end of the third workshop.  The time interval between the first and third workshop will be about 2 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Instructor subjective vitality (Ryan &amp; Fredrick, 1997). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (measured within 3 weeks prior to the first workshop), at the end of the training programme (within 2 weeks following the third workshop), and within 4-6 weeks after the end of the third workshop.  The time interval between the first and third workshop will be about 2 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clients reported motivation to attend the Les Mills RPM class (Behavioural Regulation in Exercise Questionnaire-2; Markland &amp; Tobin, 2004)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (measured within 3 weeks prior to the first workshop), at the end of the training programme (within 2 weeks following the third workshop), and within 4-6 weeks after the end of the third workshop.  The time interval between the first and third workshop will be about 2 months.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Client's reported basic need satisfaction (Vlachopoulos, Ntoumanis, &amp; Smith, 2010).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (measured within 3 weeks prior to the first workshop), at the end of the training programme (within 2 weeks following the third workshop), and within 4-6 weeks after the end of the third workshop.  The time interval between the first and third workshop will be about 2 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Client's reported subjective vitality (Ryan &amp; Fredrick, 1997),</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (measured within 3 weeks prior to the first workshop), at the end of the training programme (within 2 weeks following the third workshop), and within 4-6 weeks after the end of the third workshop.  The time interval between the first and third workshop will be about 2 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Client's intentions to continue participating in Les Mills RPM classes (measured using four items designed for this study). Responses to items were measured on a 5-point Likert Scale from strongly disagree to strongly agree. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (measured within 3 weeks prior to the first workshop), at the end of the training programme (within 2 weeks following the third workshop), and within 4-6 weeks after the end of the third workshop.  The time interval between the first and third workshop will be about 2 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>We have also developed items for an observational sheet that blinded raters can use to capture instructor autonomy support, structure, involvement, and control.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (measured within 3 weeks prior to the first workshop), at the end of the training programme (within 2 weeks following the third workshop), and within 4-6 weeks after the end of the third workshop.  The time interval between the first and third workshop will be about 2 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria for instructors in the intervention group: participant (i) is a registered Les Mills International RPM instructor (ii) teaches at least one RPM session a week on a regular basis (i.e., teaches the same class every week); (iii) operates within 50km of Perth, Australia.

Inclusion criteria for instructors in the control group: participant (i) is a registered Les Mills International RPM instructor (ii) teaches at least one RPM session a week on a regular basis (i.e., teaches the same class every week); (iii) operates within Australia but not within 50km of Perth.

Inclusion criteria for clients: Client (i) attends an RPM class run by one of the Les Mills International instructors in either the intervention or the control group; (ii) is willing and able to complete and return the questionnaire pack to the researchers within the allotted time periods.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria for instructors intervention group: participant (i) is not a registered Les Mills International RPM instructor (ii) does not teach at least one RPM session a week on a regular basis (i.e., does not teach the same class every week); (iii) operates outside 50km of Perth, Australia (iii) is not able to attend all three intervention workshops.

Exclusion criteria for instructors in the control group: participant (i) is not a registered Les Mills International RPM instructor (ii) does not teach at least one RPM session a week on a regular basis (i.e., does not teach the same class every week); (iii) operates within 50km of Perth, Australia.

Exclusion criteria for clients: Client (i) does not attend an RPM class run by one of the Les Mills instructors in either the intervention or the control group; (ii) is not able or willing to complete and return the questionnaire pack to the researchers within the allotted time periods for any reason.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Providing the numbers of participants recruited is as planned, data will be analysed using multi-level growth modelling.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/10/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>16/11/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>40</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nikos Ntoumanis</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology, Curtin University, 
GPO Box U1987 Perth, Western Australia, 6845
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Les Mills International Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>22 Centre Street, Freemans Bay, Auckland 1011 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of the study is to develop and test a motivating communication/teaching style for Les Mills International instructors. More specifically the study will examine the feasibility and fidelity of delivering a motivation-based communication training intervention with Les Mills International instructors and test the effects of the intervention on clients perceptions of the instructors motivational style. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Hancox, J.E., Quested, E., Thøgersen-Ntoumani, C., &amp; Ntoumanis, N. (2015). An intervention to train group exercise class instructors to adopt a motivationally adaptive communication style: A quasi-experimental study protocol. Health Psychology and Behavioural Medicine, 3, 190-203</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research and Development
Curtin University 
GPO Box U 1987
Perth, Western Australia 6845 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>PSYCH SP 2014-59 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nikos Ntoumanis</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia, 6845</address>
      <phone>+61(0)8 92663297</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nikos.ntoumanis@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nikos Ntoumanis</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia, 6845</address>
      <phone>+61(0)8 92663297</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nikos.ntoumanis@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nikos Ntoumanis</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia, 6845</address>
      <phone>+61(0)8 92663297</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nikos.ntoumanis@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nikos Ntoumanis</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth, Western Australia, 6845</address>
      <phone>+61(0)8 92663297</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nikos.ntoumanis@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>