<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335883">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/08/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000734066</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Arterial line versus venous line administration of Low Molecular Weight Heparin, Enoxaparin for prevention of thrombosis in the extracorporeal blood circuit of patients on Haemodialysis or Haemodiafiltration  through arterio-venous access and using high-flux membrane A randomised cross-over trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of venous line administration of Low Molecular Weight Heparin, Enoxaparin compared to manufacturer recommended arterial line administration on four hour post injection anti-Xa level in patients on Haemodialysis or Haemodiafiltration  through arterio-venous access and using high-flux membrane  A randomised cross-over trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1116-7289</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>End Stage Kidney Disease patient on Haemodialysis or Haemodiafiltration.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Experimental - administration of Low Molecular Weight Heparin, Enoxaparin in to the venous line of extracorporeal blood circuit in patients on Haemodialysis or Haemodiafiltration through Arterio-Venous access and using high-flux membrane.

Enoxaparin dose will vary for each patient based on their weight. The starting dose is 0.5mg/kg and the dose will be constant throughout the trial period.
Enoxaparin will be administered as a bolus injection either through the arterial or venous line.
Overall duration of the intervention - 28 days.
In this trial patients will cross over from the arterial administration to venous administration, and vice versa, with a "wash-out" period of 2 weeks in between the switch..</interventions>
    <comparator>Control - administration of Low Molecular Weight Heparin, Enoxaparin in to the arterial line of extracorporeal blood circuit (as per the manufacturers recommendation) in patients on Haemodialysis or Haemodiafiltration through Arterio-Venous access and using high-flux membrane.

Enoxaparin dose will vary for each patient based on their weight. The starting dose is 0.5mg/kg and the dose will be constant throughout the trial period.
Enoxaparin will be administered as a bolus injection either through the arterial or venous line.
Overall duration of the intervention - 28 days.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anti-Xa level four hour post administration of equal dose of enoxaparin.

Plasma Anti-Xa level will be compared between both groups for the same dose of enoxaparin. We are expecting higher Anti-Xa level when enoxaparin is administered via the venous route.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At run in phase (week 1), beginning of week 2, end of week 3 and end of week 5.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anti-Xa level .

Plasma Anti-Xa level will be compared between both groups for the same dose of enoxaparin. This secondary outcome Anti-Xa measurement is done for safety purpose at baseline and immediately after cross-over.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time 0, level before administration of enoxaparin, at week 1, 3 and 5.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Manual compression time.

Manual compression time after removal of the dialysis needle would be measured in minutes/seconds using a stop clock.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every dialysis session from week 1 to 7.

3 per week.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visual inspection of the extracorporeal circuit</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every dialysis session from week 1 to 7.

3 per week.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major, life-threatening and minor bleeding.

Major bleeding - reduction in the hemoglobin level of at least 20 g per liter, transfusion of at least 2 units of blood, or symptomatic bleeding in a critical area or organ. 

Life-threatening bleeding - fatal bleeding, symptomatic intracranial bleeding, bleeding with a decrease in the hemoglobin level of at least 50 g per liter, or bleeding requiring transfusion of at least 4 units of blood or inotropic agents or necessitating surgery. 

Minor - All other bleeding.

These secondary outcome would be assessed by clinical assessment and blood test (haemoglobin measurement)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Throughout the trial period from week 1 to 7.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	18 years of age or above
2.	End stage renal disease on maintenance Haemodialysis/Haemodiafiltration, 3 times a week for 4 hours (3-5 hours).
3.	On Haemodialysis/Haemodiafiltration for greater than or equal to 3 months
4.	No change in Enoxaparin dosage for greater than or equal to 3 months
5.	Stable target weight for greater than or equal to 3 months (2% change permitted). 
6.	Haemodialysis access - arteriovenous access</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Inability to provide consent.
2.	Heparin induced thrombocytopenia.
3.	On other anticoagulants like Warfain.
4.	On Clopidogrel or Dipyridamole.
5.	Hypersensitivity to enoxaparin.
6.	Dialysis through central venous catheter.
7.	Vascular access thrombosis within 3 months of study start.
8.	Pre-existing coagulation abnormalities (e.g. prolonged Activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (APTT))
9.	Baseline thrombocytopenia &lt;140.
10.	Drugs that could affect heparin activity (e.g. tetracyclines, digitalis, and antihistamines)
11.	Pregnancy
12.	Active malignancy
13.	Morbid obesity (Body Mass Index (BMI)&gt;40)
14.	History of circuit clotting or prolonged bleeding from the vascular access site over the last three months
15.	Access flows on Arterio-Venous Fistula (AVF) of &lt;500 mls/min
16.	Single needle dialysis</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A random list of all eligible patients will be generated. The patients on the list will be approached in order by the Principle or Associate investigators, for participation in the study, until the required number of patients are recruited.

Telephone randomisation of consenting patients by the hospital pharmacist who is not an investigator.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/10/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>4215</postcode>
    <postcode>4226</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Gold Coast Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>108 Nerang Street
Southport
QLD 4215</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Gold Coast hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>108 Nerang Street
Southport
QLD 4215</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patient on Haemodialysis need Enoxaparin, a drug which is used to prevent blood clotting when the blood goes through the dialysis machine. The manufacturers recommendation is to give enoxaparin through the arterial route of the dialysis circuit. About 80% of enoxaparin gets eliminated by dialysis when administered through the arterial route of the circuit. Our hypothesis is that by administering enoxaparin via the venous route we will not lose the 80% of the drug and hence use less amount of enoxaparin.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Gold Coast Health Service District Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>108 Nerang Street
Southport
QLD 4215</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/09/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Bhadran Bose</name>
      <address>Department of Nephrology
Gold Coast Hospital
108 Nerang Street
Southport
QLD 4215</address>
      <phone>+61755198211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bhadran_bose@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Bhadran Bose</name>
      <address>Department of Nephrology
Gold Coast Hospital
108 Nerang Street
Southport
QLD 4215</address>
      <phone>+61755198211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bhadran_bose@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Bhadran Bose</name>
      <address>Department of Nephrology
Gold Coast Hospital
108 Nerang Street
Southport
QLD 4215</address>
      <phone>+61755198211</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bhadran_bose@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>