<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363796">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000258752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Rural patients with Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD)  burden of disease and perceived barriers to treatment.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In rural patients with Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD) what is the burden of disease and how does this compare with their urban counterparts.
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Inflammatory Bowel Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study will look at the burden of disease/health outcomes of rural patients with IBD and be compared with metropolitan patients with IBD. The health outcomes will be gathered through a once off questionnaire.

Rural care providers will be surveyed with a separate questionnaire (once off) to obtain information regarding their IBD practice, IBD knowledge and perceived barriers to care of their IBD patients.

Once both groups have been surveyed (after enrollment in study) they will not be contacted again.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group - metropolitan patients with IBD. This cohort will not be contacted as information regarding their health outcomes has previously been collected

Medical Records data for suitable patients from 2002-2012</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease burden/IBD health outcomes of rural IBD patients will be assessed through a once off questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 questionnaire at the beginning of the study period. (ie as soon as the participant has consented to the study).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Data relating to rural doctor's (GP/Surgeon/physician) IBD practice, IBD knowledge and perceived barriers to the care of their IBD patients through a once off questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 questionnaire at the beginning of the study period. (ie as soon as the participant has consented to the study).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients
- Residing in rural location
- diagnosis of IBD

2. Doctors
- practicing in rural location</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>&lt;18 years</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5290 - Mount Gambier</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>SA Department of Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Citi Centre Building 11 Hindmarsh Square Adelaide South Australia 5000

Postal address: PO Box 287 Rundle Mall Adelaide SA 5000
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Janssen</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Address:
1-5 Khartoum Rd, North Ryde NSW 2113 Australia
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>IBD is a complex condition, which is often associated with high morbidity and requires close and continued collaboration between patients, specialist medical care and other holistic, multi-disciplinary facilities. Despite multiple studies documenting differences in health outcomes between rural and urban patients in a number of diseases, little published data exists regarding the level of disease burden in rural patients with IBD and how this compares with what we know about urban populations. Additionally, limited knowledge regarding patient and rural practitioner perspectives on the barriers to optimal medical care exists. This is important as a large burden of disease exists outside of the metropolitan area, where specialist gastroenterology serves are absent and consequently the majority of long-term care is carried out by rural general practitioners and surgeons.

The aim of the study is to initially describe the disease burden and treatment experience of IBD, in patients living in rural areas as compared to metropolitan locations. We then aim to identify any perceived barriers to the care and management of patients with IBD in the rural setting compared with their urban counterparts from the perspective of rural practitioners, IBD nurses, surgeons and gastroenterologists. Finally we will obtain the patient perspective.

The study design is predominantly based upon questionnaires aimed at identifying rural practitioners IBD experience, level of IBD knowledge and perceived barriers. Perceived barriers will also be identified from a group of interested gastroenterologists and then all results will be compared to previously studies. Patients will then be surveyed to obtain their perceptions on barriers to care. Differences in healthcare outcomes will be looked at through review of a South Australian database and a new cohort in Mt Gambier and compared to a previously collected control.
	
This study will provide quantitative data and highlight any real differences in healthcare outcomes compared with metropolitan cohorts. It will then review knowledge of and attitude to IBD amongst several medical cohorts and finally investigate perceived barriers to care from a number of different perspectives. Through the data obtained we aim to identify common perceived barriers to optimal care, which may subsequently guide the development of multi-disciplinary interventions/strategies that could be introduced to enhance rural IBD patient care. 

Given the current limited published data regarding this issue, it highlights an exciting opportunity to obtain such information to determine if and how interventions may be introduced that would aid in over-coming such obstacles and optimise care of this cohort in the long term.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 2
Room 2A221
Flinders Medical Centre
Bedford Park
SA
5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/01/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>365a.12</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alice Bennett</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA
5042</address>
      <phone>+61 4 288 30 979</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alice.bennett@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alice Bennett</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA
5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 4964</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alice.bennett@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alice Bennett</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA
5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8204 4964</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alice.bennett@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alice Bennett</name>
      <address>Department of Gastroenterology
Flinders Medical Centre
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA
5042</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>