<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365839">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000218695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Kangaroo Mother Care and Its Lactogenic Effects</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prolactin Level and Breastmilk Production among Mothers of Low Birth Weight Infants Admitted to Level II Neonatal Intensive Care Unit of the Philippine General Hospital who underwent Kangaroo Mother Care</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1153-2711</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Lactogenic Effects</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Low Birth Weight Infants</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast feeding</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Kangaroo Mother Care (KMC) is an alternative technique developed by Rey in 1978 for care of low birth weight infants. In this method, the infants will be placed on continuous skin to skin contact between the mother and the baby. The mother will keep her newborn infant between the breasts, in close contact with her body and will be covered with the kangaroo tube for 4 hours minimum per day for 7 days. The infants will only wear a diaper and a cap.  Breastfeeding will be the standard feeding method. </interventions>
    <comparator>Conventional method of care is the routine care offered in the neonatal unit to low birth weight infants. This generally includes: an artificial warming system (heated room overhead lamp warmers). Observation period will last for 7 days.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal serum prolactin:
A 4mL blood sample will be obtained from the mothers and sent to laboratory for radioimmuno-assay (expressed in mIU/L). Samples sent will only contain study code to maintain concealment of identity and ensure blinding of laboratory personnel to the allocation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed on  on day 3 and day 7 postpartum days/days of life/intervention days (please note that mother-baby dyad will be enrolled upon delivery)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Expressed Milk Volume:
Mothers will undergo milk extraction via breast pump machine. The adequacy of breast milk emptying will be assessed by the lactation nurses that are not involved in the study and are blinded in the allocation. They will likewise measure the milk volume using volumetric flask (expressed in millilitres)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Outcome will be assessed on day 3 and day 7 postpartum days/days of life/intervention days (please note that mother-baby dyad will be enrolled upon delivery)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Infant's weight gain:
All babies will be weighed using similar electronic weighing scale (expressed in grams)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for 7 days after enrolment/post-partum days/days of life (please note that mother-baby dyad will be enrolled upon delivery)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Mother-baby dyad: Mothers who gave birth to neonates less than or equal to 2000 grams with an APGAR score of more than or equal to 7 on the fifth minute of life.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a. Mothers who gave birth to Extremely Low Birth Weight Infants (ELBW).
b. Mothers who gave birth to neonates with chromosomal and life threatening         congenital anomalies.
c. Mothers who gave birth to severely ill neonates requiring intubation, oxygen or inotropic support.
d. Mothers who are severely ill requiring intubation or any form of oxygen support.
e. Mothers who had Mastectomy.
f. Mothers diagnosed with Prolactinoma.
g. Mothers who are mentally ill.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All prospective candidates (mothers in labor satisfying the criteria) will be informed of the ongoing study and their possible inclusion. This will be done by the resuscitation team in the delivery room. After the delivery of the infant, once the candidate fulfils the enrolment criteria, an informed consent will be taken by the primary investigator in the delivery room. Allocation to study group will be done via sequentially numbered opaque sealed envelopes upon admission in the NICU.</concealment>
    <sequence>After informed consent is obtained from the patient, they will be randomized using a table of random numbers from a statistics book with codes placed in sequentially numbered opaque sealed envelope by a person not involved in the study to ensure concealment. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A sample size of 25 subjects for each of the control and treatment arm was calculated to achieve a power of 80% and an alpha error of 0.05. We will employ students T test and Pearson Chi-square for continuous and dichotomous data respectively. A p value of &lt; 0.5 is considered statistically significant</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>19/05/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <state>Philippines</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of the Philippines</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>4th Flr, Philippine General Hospital
Taft. Avenue, Ermita, Manila, 1000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Philippines</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Bless Tetada Kangaroo Care Mother Foundation, Philippines</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>7431 Brgy. San Dionisio, 1700 Paranaque City, Philippines</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Philippines</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Kangaroo Mother Care (KMC) has been proven by several studies to promote breastfeeding. But much of the studies focus on the success of exclusive breastfeeding, and less on its galactogenic effects.

We aim to provide a physiologic link between KMC and increased maternal serum prolactin levels, subsequently leading to increased maternal milk volume</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of the Philippines Manila Review Ethics Board</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>2nd Floor Paz Mendoza Building, College of Medicine, UP Manila
547 Pedro Gil Street, Ermita, 1000 Manila</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/01/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Philippines</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Francis N. Raguindin</name>
      <address>University of the Philippines Manila
Philippine General Hospital
Department of Pediatrics
Taft Ave., Ermita, Manila, Philippines 1000</address>
      <phone>+63 922 8471964</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>raguindin.md@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Francis N. Raguindin</name>
      <address>University of the Philippines Manila
Philippine General Hospital
Department of Pediatrics
Taft Ave., Ermita, Manila, Philippines 1000</address>
      <phone>+63 922 8471964</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>raguindin.md@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Francis N. Raguindin</name>
      <address>University of the Philippines Manila
Philippine General Hospital
Department of Pediatrics
Taft Ave., Ermita, Manila, Philippines 1000</address>
      <phone>+63 922 8471964</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>raguindin.md@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Francis N. Raguindin</name>
      <address>University of the Philippines Manila
Philippine General Hospital
Department of Pediatrics
Taft Ave., Ermita, Manila, Philippines 1000</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Philippines</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>