<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372721">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000717358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects of combining repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation with treadmill training on gait performance in individuals with chronic stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of combining repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation with treadmill training on gait performance in individuals with chronic stroke</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>stroke </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Fourteen participants with chronic stroke were randomly assigned to experimental (n=8) or control group (n=6). Participants in both groups received treadmill training for 30 minitues, 3 times a week for 3 weeks. The treadmill training started with a 5 minutes warm up session walking at half of participants preferred speed. After warm up, the treadmill speed would be increased gradually until the maximum tolerable and safe speed of the participant has been reached. While training, a suspension system was used to ensure the safety of the participants, and a physiotherapist would be standing aside to ensure that the participants walked with good posture and appropriate weight transfer using verbal cues.

Prior to each treadmill training session, the participants in the experimental group received real repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) with 5Hz, 10s, 18 trains with total 900 pulses at 90% resting motor threshold for 15 minutes to the ipsilesional primary motor cortex of tibialis anterior (TA) muscle, and the control group received sham rTMS.
</interventions>
    <comparator>the control group received sham rTMS plus same treadmill training as experimental group </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>gait velocity obtained from the GAITRite system, </outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-training, post-training, and 4 weeks follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>gait asymmetry index using formulas proposed by O'Sullivan et al, 2007 and Hsu et al., 2003</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-training, post-training, and 4 weeks follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>electromyography (EMG) of TA during walking</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-training, post-training, and 4 weeks follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> lower extremity motor score of Fugl-Meyer Assessment </outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-training, post-training, and 4 weeks follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>brain motor evoked potential (MEP) asymmetry calculated by using amplitude of MEP of both hemispheres obtained from MagStim 200 and the formula built by Brouwer et al., 2006.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-training, post-training, and 4 weeks follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>electromyography (EMG) of rectus femoris (RF) during walking</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre-training, post-training, and 4 weeks follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(1) hemiparesis from a single stroke, (2) after stroke period more than 6 month. (3)able to walk independently for 10 meters with or without an assistive device. (4) Stable medical condition to allow participation in the testing protocol
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(1) subjects have contraindications of TMS, such as: intracranial metal implants, history of epilepsy or severe heart disease; (2) other non-stroke-related neurological diseases, Such as: cerebellum or vestibular system disease; (3) cognitive dysfunction; (4) muscular system diseases of lower limbs and interfere the walking function.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>22/12/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>17/05/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>14</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>5/07/2011</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ray-yau, Wang</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Physical Therapy and Assistive Technology, National Yang-Ming University, 112. No. 155, Sec 2, Li Nong St., Shih-Pai, Taipei, Taiwan</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Science and Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>106, Sec. 2, Heping E. Rd., Taipei 10622, Taiwan, R.O.C</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background and purpose: Decreased gait performance is one of the functional limitations after stroke. Its important to establish effective rehabilitation strategies to restore walking function. Repetitive transcranial magnetic stimulation (rTMS) can modulate the excitability of the motor cortex. Some studies showed that combining rTMS with motor training resulted in better improvements in hand function than motor training alone. However, such effects on lower extremity have not been established. The purpose of this study was to investigate effects of combining rTMS with treadmill training on gait performance in chronic stroke patients. Methods: This is a double-blinded randomized control trial. Fourteen participants with chronic stroke were randomly assigned to experimental (n=8) or control group (n=6). Participants in both groups received treadmill training for 30 minitues, 3 times a week for 3 weeks. Before treadmill training, the participants in the experimental group received real rTMS with 5Hz, 10s, 18 trains with total 900 pulses at 90% resting motor threshold for 15 minutes to the ipsilesional primary motor cortex of tibialis anterior (TA) muscle, and the control group received sham rTMS. The outcome measures were collected at pre-training, post-training, and 4 weeks follow-up, including gait velocity, spatial and temporal gait asymmetry index, and electromyography (EMG) of TA and rectus femoris (RF) during walking, lower extremity motor score of Fugl-Meyer Assessment , amplitude of motor evoked potential (MEP)for both hemispheres and brain MEP asymmetry. Friedman test was used to exam within-group improvement at different time points, Mann-Whitney U test was used to exam the differences between groups, and the significant level was set at a=0.05. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Review Board, Taipei Veterans General Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>No.201, Sec. 2, Shipai Rd., Beitou District, Taipei City, Taiwan 11217, R.O.C.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/11/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ray-yau, Wang</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy and Assistive Technology, National Yang-Ming University, 112. No. 155, Sec 2, Li Nong St., Shih-Pai, Taipei, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886928231905</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rywang@ym.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ray-yau, Wang</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy and Assistive Technology, National Yang-Ming University, 112. No. 155, Sec 2, Li Nong St., Shih-Pai, Taipei, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886928231905</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rywang@ym.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ray-yau, Wang</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy and Assistive Technology, National Yang-Ming University, 112. No. 155, Sec 2, Li Nong St., Shih-Pai, Taipei, Taiwan</address>
      <phone>+886928231905</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rywang@ym.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>