<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347690">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/11/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611001175965</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Spinal Manipulation Reduces Pain in Organized Patterns within Myofascial (Musculoskeletal) Tissues</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Spinal Manipulative Therapy Evokes Reduction of Pain Pressure Threshold in Myofascial Trigger Points that are Segmentally Linked to the Manipulated Segment(s).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>myofascial pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention performed was spinal manipulative therapy (SMT).  SMT was performed on one occasion (duration 1 hour) by a chiropractic physician with over 17 years of experience in the procedure.  Participants were instructed to lay supine during the manipulation procedure(s) with the head resting on a mechanical drop headpiece, which is designed to increase the acceleration of the manual thrust.  Participants assigned to the manipulation group received a bilateral rotary manipulation targeting the C5-C6 segment.  This procedure initially involves preloading the target tissues by inducing mild flexion, lateral flexion and rotation (&lt;40 degrees) of the cervical spine.  A high velocity low amplitude rotary thrust (&lt; 10 degrees) was then manually applied through the C5-C6 spinal segment with the contact hand.  The head and neck was then returned to the neutral position.  A palpable cavitation confirmed successful administration of the procedure.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control participants received a sham manipulation procedure also targeting the C5-C6 segment.  This manoeuvre involves identical preloading of the cervical tissues as in the real manipulation protocol.  In the sham procedure, however, the participants head is supported by the clinicians forearm which rests directly on the headpiece.  The quick release and rapid acceleration of the headpiece during the sham manoeuvre evokes the sensation of a real manipulation in participants.  During this procedure, the clinician thrusts downward into the headpiece with the supporting arm to produce the sensation of a rapid manual thrust to the neck; however, no real thrust is made by the contact hand and no intersegmental manipulation is achieved at the C5-C6 segment.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>pain pressure threshold as measured with a pressure algometer</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 (baseline pre-treatment), 1, 5, 10 and 15 minutes post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>clinically identifiable myofascial trigger point (active or latent) within the right infraspinatus and right gluteus medius muscles.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Conditions that could affect normal somatosensory processing within the cervical spine segments.  Including serious medical conditions (eg cancer), central or peripheral neurologic conditions, recent acute injury to cervical spine (eg whiplash), medication use.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>allocation for treatment was performed by a research assistant who was not involved in the intake assessment.  The presiding clinician involved in the intake assessment procedure was unaware of participant allocation at the time of allocation, however, became aware of group allocation at the time of intervention.</concealment>
    <sequence>random draw technique using labelled slips of paper (test, control) drawn from a bin.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>n/a</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Guelph</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>50 Stone Road East
Guelph, Ontario
N1G2W1</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Canada</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronic widespread pain (CWP), such as fibromyalgia and myofascial pain syndrome, is a significant and growing challenge to our health delivery system.  Cost-effective approaches to management are imperative to the sustainability of our future health care system.  Spinal manipulative therapy (SMT) is a cost-effective and widely employed manual intervention in the treatment of a variety of musculoskeletal pain conditions; however, its physiologic mechanisms and clinical application in the management of CWP are still unclear.  Our aim in this study is to investigate the effect of SMT on musculoskeletal (myofascial) pain.  Specifically, we are investigating whether SMT will evoke decreased pain in systematic patterns within myofascial tissues.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Guelph REB</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Guelph
50 Stone Road East
Guelph, Ontario
N1G2W1</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/04/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08OC024</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Canada</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>John Z Srbely</name>
      <address>Department of Human Health and Nutritional Science
University of Guelph
50 Stone Road East
Guelph, Ontario
N1G2W1</address>
      <phone>+011-1-519-824-4120 ext 52058</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jsrbely@uoguelph.ca</email>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>John Z Srbely</name>
      <address>Department of Human Health and Nutritional Science
University of Guelph
50 Stone Road East
Guelph, Ontario
N1G2W1</address>
      <phone>+011-1-519-824-4120 ext 52058</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jsrbely@uoguelph.ca</email>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>John Z Srbely</name>
      <address>Department of Human Health and Nutritional Science
University of Guelph
50 Stone Road East
Guelph, Ontario
N1G2W1</address>
      <phone>+011-1-519-824-4120 ext 52058</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jsrbely@uoguelph.ca</email>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>