<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371976">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/12/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/01/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000123347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cardiovascular Benefits of Commuter Cycling</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of Commuter Cycling on Cardiovascular Fitness in Healthy Adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>cardiovascular disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>hypertension</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>adiposity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A 10-week intervention will be conducted in which participants will be asked to ride 20+ min/day 3-5 days/week at a self-selected intensity. A minimum ride time of 100 min a week, accumulated over at least 3 days will be necessary to remain in the project. Participants will be allowed one week of less than 100 minutes of cycling (e.g. illness, travel) but must be made up by adding an extra week to the intervention. Bikes, riding accessories and guidelines will be provided. Two 1 h training and support sessions will be held by the Master's student (who is also a bike mechanic) to familiarise participants with bike handling, basic maintenance, road rules and a discussion of routes in and around Dunedin (where the trial will take place). These will occur at baseline and in week 3 of the intervention.
Attendance at these sessions (and all required measures) will be mandatory to participate/remain in the trial and keep the bikes.  Attendance will be registered.
In addition to activity logbooks which will be collected weekly, participants will be given a downloadable HR monitor to be worn during all waking hours for 3 consecutive days at baseline, in week 4 and  in week 8. Heart rate data in weeks 4 and 8 will be used to corroborate cycle commute information from activity logs, including intensity of commute. (Accelerometers are notoriously poor for identifying cycling.)
</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group (CON)
Control subjects will be asked to maintain their present physical activity levels and dietary habits during the same intervention period to provide comparison for any seasonal and individual variation. They will be provided with $150 worth of petrol vouchers or public transport vouchers for completion of all measures.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Maximal oxygen consumption  (VO2max)
This measure is indicative of aerobic fitness and inversely correlated with cardiovascular disease and all cause mortality. 
An incremental exercise test to exhaustion will be performed on a Velotron Elite cycle ergometer (RacerMate Inc., Seattle, Washington, USA) to determine VO2max and maximum power achieved. Respiratory gas exchange will be  measured,  breath-by-breath, with open circuit spirometry (Cosmed Cardio Pulmonary Exercise Testing, CosmedSrl, Rome, Italy) and averaged into 30 s blocks. 
The protocol for the cycle test will start with a five minute warm up at 75 w with a pedalling cadence between 80-95 revolutions·min-1 (rpm). Visual and verbal feedback will be used to assist with maintaining pedalling cadence . The protocol starts at 100 w and increases in 50 w increments every three minutes until a heart rate (HR) of 165 beats·min-1 (bpm) is achieved. Above 165 bpm, stages increases in 25 w increments until exhaustion, defined by plateau in VO2 with increased workload. If no  plateau is observed, exhaustion will be defined as inability to pedal greater than 60 rpm in addition to one of the following criteria: RER equal to or greater than 1.1 or maximal age-predicated HR (+/- 10 bpm). 
If participants are unable to complete the VO2max protocol, a second attempt will be permitted prior to exclusion from the study. In this case, the resistance on the cycle ergometer  will be reduced to a 50 w warm up, with the first stage at 75 w and 25 w increase every three minutes until exhaustion, as defined above.  
 </outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to  (baseline) and upon completion of intervention 
Testing sessions performed by participants prior to the intervention will be repeated upon completion, with replication of the procedures and in chronological order that that all baseline tests were implemented.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HDL cholesterol
Plasma samples analysed with a COBAS Mira Plus analyser (Roche Diagnostic, Basel, Switzerland).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to (baseline) and upon completion of intervention
In the morning, at least 48 hours after their last bout of moderate or high intensity exercise, at least 24 hours from any exercise, at least a 24 hour fast from alcohol and 12 hour fast from food and caffeinated beverages.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting blood pressure- by manual sphygmomanometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to (baseline) and upon completion of intervention
In the morning, after resting supine for 15 min, at least 48 hours after the last bout of moderate or high intensity exercise, at least 24 hours from any exercise, at least a 24 hour fast from alcohol and 12 hour fast from food and caffeinated beverages, and before blood sampling. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate sampling (continuous except showering and sleeping).
Portable heart rate monitors (wrist "watch" with chest strap). to measure the impact of cycle commuting on physical activity levels and to validate and quantify diary data. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over 3 day periods, Prior to intervention  (baseline), and during weeks 4 and 8 of the intervention, </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>HOMA-IR
Fasting plasma insulin and glucose  concentrations will be used to predict insulin sensitivity (HOMA-IR).
Glucose will  be analysed in duplicate with a Cobas c 111 (Roche Instrument Centre, Rotkreuz, Switzerland) and insulin with the electrochemiluminescence method using an Elecsys2010 (Roche/Hitachi, Tokyo, Japan). The homeostatic model assessment for insulin resistance (HOMA-IR) will be calculated using Matthews et al. (1985): 
HOMA(IR) =(Insulin (uU/ml) ×Glucose(mmol/L))/22.5


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to  (baseline)  and upon completion of intervention
In the morning, at least 48 hours after their last bout of moderate or high intensity exercise, at least 24 hours from any exercise, at least a 24 hour fast from alcohol and 12 hour fast from food and caffeinated beverages.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition (DXA scan (in CYC only), sum of skinfolds, body mass, BMI, waist:hip ratio).
[DXA will only be performed in intervention group due to financial constraints.]</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to (baseline) and upon completion of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity (logbooks and International physical activity questionnaire -(IPAQ))
Activity logbooks will be provided for daily logs to record all leisure time physical activities and commuting activities  &gt; 5 min and will be include Ainsworths Compendium of Physical Activities to improve reliability of perceived intensity.
 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>The logbooks are to be kept daily from baseline throughout the intervention, with weekly collection.
IPAQ to be administered at baseline (week 0) and on weeks four and eight.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resting heart rate- with a recordable Polar RS400 (Polar Electro Inc., Kempele, Finland) heart rate monitor  (comprising a wrist band and chest strap)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to (baseline) and upon completion of intervention
In the morning, after resting supine for 15 min, at least 48 hours after the last bout of moderate or high intensity exercise, at least 24 hours from any exercise, at least a 24 hour fast from alcohol and 12 hour fast from food and caffeinated beverages, and before blood sampling</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>C-reactive protein, to be analysed in plasma with COBAS Mira Plus analyser (Roche Diagnostic, Basel, Switzerland). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to (baseline) and upon completion of intervention
In the morning, after resting supine for 15 min, at least 48 hours after the last bout of moderate or high intensity exercise, at least 24 hours from any exercise, at least a 24 hour fast from alcohol and 12 hour fast from food and caffeinated beverages, </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health related quality of life 
Assessed by the Short form 36 questionnaire (SF-36 survey, Ware &amp; Sherbourne, 1992).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to (baseline) and upon completion of intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total cholesterol analysed with COBAS Mira Plus analyser (Roche Diagnostic, Basel, Switzerland)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to (baseline) and upon completion of intervention
In the morning, at least 48 hours after their last bout of moderate or high intensity exercise, at least 24 hours from any exercise, at least a 24 hour fast from alcohol and 12 hour fast from food and caffeinated beverages.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Triglycerides analysed with COBAS Mira Plus analyser (Roche Diagnostic, Basel, Switzerland)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to (baseline) and upon completion of intervention
In the morning, at least 48 hours after their last bout of moderate or high intensity exercise, at least 24 hours from any exercise, at least a 24 hour fast from alcohol and 12 hour fast from food and caffeinated beverages.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>LDL cholesterol determined by Friedewald equation, where cholesterol values are expressed as mmol/L (Friedewald et al., 1972): 
LDL Chol.=Total Chol.   (Triglycerides/ 2.18)  - HDL Chol.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prior to (baseline) and upon completion of intervention
In the morning, at least 48 hours after their last bout of moderate or high intensity exercise, at least 24 hours from any exercise, at least a 24 hour fast from alcohol and 12 hour fast from food and caffeinated beverages.
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pass Physical Activity Readiness Questionnaire (PARQ)
Not currently actively commuting and have neither contraindications to exercise nor cardiovascular disease or diabetes.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria includes smoking, active commuting, unemployed or working from home, a BMI &gt; 30,  or participating in a structured training program or contraindications to exercise as defined in the Physical Activity Readiness Questionnaire.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>allocation not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>From volunteers, 14 males, 14 females will be quasi-randomised into cycling (CYC) or control (CON) groups. To control for varying levels of fitness, each participant will be paired with one other participant with a similar VO2max and randomly split in to CYC and CON. Randomisation process will be performed separately for males and females to ensure equal representation of sex in each group.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Repeated measures ANOVA will be used to detect any time-by-group interactions with measures collected in both groups at three or more time points (e.g. physical activity). One-way ANOVA will be performed on the percentage change between pre- and post-intervention measures for data collected at two time points (e.g. body composition, cardiovascular and metabolic parameters). Measures only taken in CYC intervention group (pre- post- DXA) will be compared paired, with 2-tailed T-test.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>14/03/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>14/04/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>28</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>28</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/07/2011</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago; School of Physical Education</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>46 Union St West, 
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Heart Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>9 Kalmia Street
Ellerslie
Auckland, 1051
Postal Address
PO Box 17-160
Greenlane
Auckland 1546  </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Governmental and other health agencies are encouraging active commuting (e.g. walking or bicycling), which may bring environmental and fiscal benefits, yet knowledge of the effects on overall physical activity levels and health are lacking. 
Although walking is practical for short distances, its role in improving cardiovascular health may be limited to older and sedentary populations. Bicycling, on the other hand, is generally performed at an intensity that improves cardiovascular fitness among young and healthy populations. However, few studies have examined bicycle commuting from the perspective of health gains, which have yielded limited and mixed findings. Additionally, whether initiation of a bicycle commuting routine will increase energy expenditure is currently unknown; as energy compensation from other physical activities may occur. 
The purpose of this study is to provide quantitative evidence of the contribution (or lack thereof) a daily routine of cycle commuting makes to enhancing physical activity, increasing energy expenditure, and altering physical and mental health parameters among New Zealanders. If changes are observed, these data will give an indication of the magnitude of change that may be expected in these criterion measures with a given increase in activity/energy expenditure, i.e. the relationship between load and response.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Conference presentations ( &amp; abstracts):
Novis, B.J., Rehrer, N.J. and Hargreaves, E. The effects of commuter cycling 
	for 10 weeks on fitness, health, and body composition. Sports Medicine 
	New Zealand Annual Conference Abstracts 37(3):101(2011).
2014 Conference  2 Walk and Cycle 2014 Nelson
http://www.2walkandcycle.org.nz/images/2014_Conference/Rehrer_Nancy_-_Cardiovascular_Benfits_of_Commuter_Cycing.pdf
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Human Health Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Manager Academic Committees
Registry PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/10/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10/153</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/07/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nancy J Rehrer</name>
      <address>School of Physical Education, Sport &amp; Exercise Sciences
Otago University
46 Union St West, PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+6434799128</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nancy.rehrer@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nancy J Rehrer</name>
      <address>School of Physical Education, Sport &amp; Exercise Sciences
Otago University
46 Union St West, PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+6434799128</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nancy.rehrer@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nancy J Rehrer</name>
      <address>School of Physical Education, Sport &amp; Exercise Sciences
Otago University
46 Union St West, PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054</address>
      <phone>+6434799128</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nancy.rehrer@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>