<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83018">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/07/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/08/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000387325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Absolute risk trial in general practice</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The feasibility and impact of cardiovascular absolute risk (CVAR) assessment in Australian general practice</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ART</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) 510173</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular risk</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>absolute risk</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>assessment</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>management</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>general practice</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1. Before consultation:	
One 3 hours' general practitioner (GP) training workshop: GPs will receive training in the use of CVAR assessment (an electronic calculator) and recommended treatment guidelines based on CVAR assessment.  The workshop will use simulated patients (which we have used in previous studies) to develop effective communication and motivational interviewing skills in the GPs. 

Two 2 hours' practice visits: After the workshop, two standardized practice visits will be conducted to set up software for CVAR assessment, educate non-GP staff (such as practice nurse, practice mangers) about the process of the study, ensure practice organization for the CVAR assessment visits, and provide patient education materials used in the waiting room and after the CVAR consultation.	

Patients will be sent a self assessment (SA) form to complete in about 10 minutes and a letter requesting them to bring the SA form to attend for a CVAR assessment with their GP. 

2. During consultation:
GPs will take about 15 minutes to review the SA form, assess the patients smoking, blood pressure, weight, waist circumference, blood lipids and glucose level if diabetic, and perform a CVAR assessment and discuss the results with patients. 

GP will use CVAR guideline to provide about management of patients CV risk where appropriate. This may include management of lifestyle risk factors in all patients and pharmacological interventions in patients at high risk. 

GP will use CVAR guideline to arrange referral to smoking quit line or allied health professionals (physiotherapist, nutritionist/dietician or diabetes educator) where appropriate. 

Patients will be provided educational materials
 
3. After consultation	
During the 12 months of the intervention period, continuous support will be provided to GPs and other practice staff via telephone (at least once month) or/and practice visit whenever needed. Duration of each call or visit is as required. 

Patients will be monitored and follow-up arranged for risk management as appropriate.</interventions>
    <comparator>In the control group, GPs will maintain usual care based on the usual cardiovascular risk management strategies.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes of physiological risk (eg: blood pressure and blood lipids). 
Collected by medical record audits</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 12 months after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes of prescribing of medications (lipid lowering and antihypertensive medications).
 Collected by medical record audits</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 12 months after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>lifestyle risk factors (eg self-reported smoking status, physical activity levels and diet (consumption fruit and vegetables) and health status.
collected by questionnaires, which include questions developed and validated by our team, Smoking, Nutrition, Alcohol, Physical activity (SNAP) questions, and questions from Australian National Health Survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 12 months after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change of CVAR calculated by GP.
Collected by medical record audits.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 12 months after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Referrals to dietician, exercise program, smoking cessation program. 
Collected by medical record audits.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 12 months after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of new diagnosis of cardiac disease.
Collected by medical record audits.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes of patient readiness to change and patient Activation Measure.
Collected by questionnaires, which include questions developed and validated by our team and Patient Activation Measure Questions.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 12 months after intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients:
Aged 45-69 (including 45 and 69)
Attend the practice in the last 12 months
Sufficient English to understand the invitation letter and complete the questionnaires.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>45</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>69</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Aboriginal or Torres Strait Islander (not suitable for the calculator). 

2. diagnosed or treated for:
Angina,
Myocardial infarction,
Previous coronary revascularisation = angioplasty, coronary artery stent, coronary angiography +stent, coronary artery bypass graft, coronary artery surgery,
Heart failure,
Stroke,
Transient ischaemic attack,
cognitive impairment (eg dementia).

3. taking any of the following medications:
Nitrates = glyceryl trinitrate, isosorbide mononitrate, isosorbide dinitrate,
Clopidogrel.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomizations will be conducted at the practice level. It will be performed by a person independent of the data collection and intervention teams and chief investigators.

The intervention group of GPs will be trained to use a CVAR implementation model for their patients. The control group of GPs will provide usual care to their patients.</concealment>
    <sequence>A randomization table created by computer software will be used for randomization. After the baseline data collection, randomization will be conducted at practice level with stratification by Division of General Practice (8 in each Division). Randomization will be conducted within each division in 2 blocks.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The analysis will be adjusted for clustering factors at practices.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1640</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>2560</postcode>
    <postcode>2200</postcode>
    <postcode>2018</postcode>
    <postcode>2131</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity,</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity, School of Public Health and Community Medicine, University of New South Wales. NSW, Australia, 2052.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>George Institute for International Health</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>George Institute for International Health, University of Sydney, NSW, Australia, 2006</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Central Sydney Division of General Practice</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Central Sydney Division of General Practice, Level 1, 381 Liverpool Road, Ashfield NSW 2131</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Bankstown Division of General practice</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Bankstown Division of General practice, PO Box 41 MANAHAN NSW 2200 Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>South Eastern Division of General Practice</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>South Eastern Division of General Practice. Level 2, 6-8 Crewe Place,
ROSEBERY NSW 2018</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Macarthur Division of General Practice</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Macarthur Division of General Practice. PO Box 5919, MINTO DC NSW 2566, Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a cluster randomized controlled trial, aiming to investigate both the feasibility of using this model and the impact of CVAR assessment and management on general practice clinical processes and patient care. This trial will be conducted in general practices in Sydney, involving GPs, other practice staff and patients aged 45-69 without existing CVD. 32 practices (40 GPs) and 1600 patients will be recruited. Randomization will be conducted at the practice level. The intervention group of GPs will be trained to use a CVAR implementation model while the control group of GPs will continue usual care. Study variables include clinical processes, patient risk, use of lifestyle intervention and prescribing of antihypertensive and lipid lowering medications. Data will be collected and analyzed using mixed methods. Study variables before and after the intervention will be compared, and the two groups be also compared after adjusting for baseline difference and clustering factors. Results of this study will help improve the primary prevention of CVD and inform guidelines for clinical practice and the implementation of other health initiatives.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://notes.med.unsw.edu.au/CPHCEWeb.nsf/page/Feasibility_impact_cv_absriskassess</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Qing Wan. Cardiovascular absolute risk (CVAR ) study: assessment and management in general practice. Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity Annual Forum.  15 May 2008, Sydney. Available at: http://www.cphce.unsw.edu.au/cphceweb.nsf/page/News%20and%20Events</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee of the University of New South Wales</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>near Gate 14, Barker Street
Grid Reference  M 15  Middle Campus
University of New South Wales
NSW, 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/07/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC 08005</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof. Mark Harris</name>
      <address>Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity, School of Public Health and Community Medicine, University of New South Wales. NSW, Australia, 2052.</address>
      <phone>61 2 9385 2511</phone>
      <fax>61 2 93136185</fax>
      <email>m.f.harris@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Elizabeth Denney-Wilson</name>
      <address>Project Coordinator
Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity, School of Public Health and Community Medicine, University of New South Wales. NSW, Australia, 2052.</address>
      <phone>61 2 9385 1511</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9385 1513</fax>
      <email>e.denney-wilson@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Qing Wan</name>
      <address>Centre for Primary Health Care and Equity, School of Public Health and Community Medicine, University of New South Wales. NSW, Australia, 2052.</address>
      <phone>61 2 9385 1503</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9385 1513</fax>
      <email>q.wan@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>