<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83207">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/11/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000565347</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Impact of a frailty intervention on informal carers. A substudy of the Frailty Intervention Trial - FIT (ACTRN12608000250336)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The impact of a community based multidisciplinary frailty intervention for older people on informal carers' experience of caregiving.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Informal caregiving</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a substudy of the Frailty Intervention Trial - FIT (ACTRN12608000250336).  
The informal carers of the participants in the FIT study will be observed to determine if the FIT impacts on their caregiving experience.
The twelve month FIT study includes a  multidimensional individualised treatment plan designed to treat identified components of frailty.</interventions>
    <comparator>The informal carers of the participants in the  FIT study who are randomised to the control group to recieve usual care will be observed over the course of the trial. 'Usual care' is care available to older residents from their general practitioner and community services.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver Reaction Assessment - assesses negative and positive aspects of the caregiving experience, and changes in reaction over time. The following dimensions of the caregiving experience are examined: health, daily schedule, finances, self worth, and family support.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, six and 12 months after randomisation of care recipient and 6 months post intervention cessation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital Anxiety Depression Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, six and 12 months after randomisation of care recipient and 6 months post intervention cessation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bakas Caregiving Outcomes Scale -measures changes as a result of caregiving and is sensitive enough to detect differences among treatment groups in an intervention study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, six and 12 months after randomisation of care recipient and 6 months post intervention cessation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Semi structured interview: the informal carers be given the opportunity to reflect on and discuss their caregiving experience in a semi-structured interview which will provide a more sensitive and deeper understanding of their caregiving experience.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after care recipient randomised</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Nominated, unpaid, informal carer of the care recipient of the Frailty Intervention Trial - FIT (ACTRN12608000250336)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Paid  carers</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>230</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Christina Aggar</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Nursing &amp; Midwifery 
University of Sydney
(MO2) 88 Mallett Street
Camperdown 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Ian Cameron</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Royal Rehabilitation Studies Unit
PO Box 6 Ryde NSW 1680</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Susan Ronaldson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Faculty of Nursing &amp; Midwifery 
University of Sydney
(MO2) 88 Mallett Street
Camperdown 2050</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This is a substudy of the Frailty Intervention Trial - FIT (ACTRN12608000250336). Please refer to ACTRN12608000250336 for a brief summary of the FIT.

Informal support is an important part of the total care provided to frail older people and essential to the implementation of patient interventions. However, the examination of informal carers experience of a patient intervention is rarely measured. Informal carer experience is an important consideration, particularly in terms of them maintaining their role and quality of care for the frail older person. 

The aim of this cohort sub study is to compare the effects of a multidisciplinary frailty intervention to usual care of a frail older person living in the community on informal carers experience of caregiving.
An informal carer is a person who provides unpaid care to a family member or friend who needs help in their daily activities. This ranges from supervision to assistance with personal care, mobility and communication, through to emotional support and practical and financial assistance. Informal carers are key players or partners in the caregiving process and so a concern for their well-being is of importance, particularly in terms of them maintaining their role and quality of care for the frail older patient. As the population ages, the role of the informal carer will become more significant and providing them with appropriate support will be vital.

Informal carers of the participants in the Frailty Intervention Trial (FIT)(ACTRN12608000250336) will be invited to participate. A background questionnaire delivered at baseline will determine sociodemographic characteristics, caregiving tasks and care duration. The impact of the Frailty Intervention Trial (FIT) (ACTRN12608000250336) on informal carers experience will be measured using three validated carer assessment tools at baseline, 6 months and 12 months. A follow-up measure will also be gathered at 15-18 months. The informal carers will also be given the opportunity to discuss their caregiving experience in a semi-structured interview at 12 months after the baseline questionnaire. 

The primary objective is to evaluate the impact of The Frailty Intervention (FIT) on informal carers positive and negative aspects of caregiving.  The secondary objective is to obtain a more sensitive and deeper understanding of the informal carers experience via a semi-structured interview.  Evaluation of the impact of the Frailty Intervention Trial (FIT)(ACTRN12608000250336) on informal carers experience will increase our understanding of aspects of their caregiving by providing insight into carers perspectives, highlighting complexities and daily realities of care. In addition, it will provide us with information on how informal carers may be integrated more effectively into the implementation of frailty interventions for older people.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>This is a substudy of the FITstudy. The website is http://www.rehab.usyd.edu.au/tie/fit</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Harbour HREC Northern Sydney Central Coast Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Research Office
Level 4, Vindin House
Royal North Shore Hospital
St Leonards NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/05/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>0709-191M</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christina Aggar</name>
      <address>Faculty of Nursing &amp; Midwifery 
University of Sydney
(MO2) 88 Mallett Street
Camperdown 2050</address>
      <phone>0414 754 705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.aggar@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christina Aggar</name>
      <address>Faculty of Nursing &amp; Midwifery 
University of Sydney
(MO2) 88 Mallett Street
Camperdown 2050</address>
      <phone>0414 754 705</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>c.aggar@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Christina Aggar</name>
      <address>Faculty of Nursing &amp; Midwifery 
University of Sydney
(MO2) 88 Mallett Street
Camperdown 2050</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>c.aggar@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>