<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370334">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000399493p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The safety and efficacy of intranasal ketamine delivery for sedation of children in the emergency department. Is a needle-free approach to the care of children in the emergency department,  practical and attainable?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Ketamine Intranasal Delivery in the Emergency Room: A multicentre randomised controlled trial of Intranasal(IN) versus Intravenous(IV)/Intramuscular(IV) ketamine for paediatric sedation in the Emergency Department. Is a totally needle-free approach feasible? </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>KINDER</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>NONE</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Sedation procedures in children</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a comparative study of intranasal (spray inhaled through the nose) to intramuscular/intravenous (injection into the muscle or vein) delivery of ketamine to children for procedural sedation.
Intranasal (N)
IN ketamine 10mg/kg, should be given in a staged and titrated fashion as outlined below. Doses inconsistent with this protocol will be considered protocol violations.
1. 10 minutes before ready to initiate procedure:
2.5mg/kg (0.025mL/kg Ketalar (registered trade name of ketamine) right/left nostril via Mucosal atomising device (MAD)
AND
2.5mg/kg (0.025mL/kg Ketalar other nostril via MAD
Total initial dose = 5mg/kg
2. Assess level of sedation after 2 minutes from initial dose (8 minutes before procedure expected to begin)
3. If initial 5mg/kg dose of sedation is considered insufficient to initiate procedure at this point, further IN doses can be titrated up to total initial load of 10mg/kg to achieve adequate dissociation/sedation to initiate procedure. Do this by alternating further doses of 2.5mg/kg between nostrils:
2.5mg/kg (0.025mL/kg Ketalar  right/left nostril via MAD
AND/OR
2.5mg/kg (0.025mL/kg Ketalar  other nostril via MAD
If 10mg/kg is reached and sedation is still insufficient to allow initiation of procedure 15 minutes after the first intranasal dose was administered, this shall be considered failed IN sedation and an IV cannula should be placed to allow titrated 0.25-0.5mg/kg doses of IV ketamine to achieve adequate sedation. The incidence with which this occurs shall impact the needle-free outcome.
For a prolonged procedure after successful initiation, repeated IN doses of 2.5mg/kg can be given to alternating nostrils 5 to 10 minutely.
The participants level of sedation will be deterined using the FLACC scale (face,legs,acitvity,cry and consolibilty scale), and discussed between the treating doctor and the senior consultant over-viewing the procedure.
It should be emphasised that while it may take longer to titrate the dose via the IN route compared with the IV route, this can be performed by the sedationist while the proceduralist finalises readiness for the procedure. It is anticipated that this longer titration period, if it occurs, shall be offset by the time saved by obviating IV.
The observation Nurse will be recording all data during the procedure, including baseline observations, indication for procedure, pain scores, fasting status, medication dosing, and 5minutely FLACC scores post initial medication administration. </interventions>
    <comparator>Usual Care IV/IM (U)
In keeping with this trial being a practical study of a novel needle-free approach versus the range of current needle-based approaches, For patients randomised to the U arm clinicians will be free to choose either IV or IM routes and will also be free to choose the dose of ketamine administered by either of these routes.
For the U group, no recommendations shall be made about the timing of administering the drug in relation to performance of the procedure. No recommendations will be made regarding when or how to obtain IV access if this route is chosen.
Recommendations regarding dosing shall be made but not mandated:
Intramuscular route chosen
Recommended dose: 4-5 mg/kg IM ketamine; given as single dose into anterolateral thigh as soon as treating clinician/s ready to initiate sedation/procedure.
Child needs to be adequately restrained to ensure correct intramuscular administration.
If this single initial IM dose remains ineffective to initiate the procedure at 15 minutes post administration, or if a prolonged procedure requires top up doses, an IV cannula should be placed and titrated further 0.25-0.5mg/kg doses of IV ketamine should be given to achieve adequate sedation.
Intravenous route chosen
Recommended dose: 1.0-2.0 mg/kg IV ketamine (total initial dose); given by slow IV push of titrated doses (e.g. 0.5mg/kg) over 1-2 minutes as soon as the treating clinician/s are ready to initiate sedation/procedure
If further or top up doses are required to achieve or maintain sedation, then it is recommended that this occur via 0.25-0.5mg/kg doses of IV ketamine</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sedation efficacy/adequacy for procedure
2 Minutes post medication administration, the sedation score will be assessed using the FLACC scale (face, legs, activity. cry, consolability). If sedation is inadequate - a secondary dose can be given with re-assessment required. 
If the patients sedation remains inadequate, this will be highlighted as a failed treatment. The patients care will be escalated at the discretion of the senior Medical office (Eg: utilisation of IM/IV Ketamine - though no data will be collected) </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 minutes post first medication administration and again 2 minutes post second medication administration</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A composite of side effects 'yes' or 'no' out of 9, including; significant non-purposeful movements, involuntary eye movements, visual disturbance, hypersalivation not requiring significant intervention, vomitting during the period of sedation, intermittent throat spasm not requiring intervention, increased heart rate greater than 20beats per minute, increased systolic blood pressure greater than 20mmHg, or persistent balance effects). 
These will be assessed through observation of the individual by clinical staff, observation of the individual by the parent/caregiver, and observation of the continuous screen monitoring of heart rate and blood pressure . 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>this will be assessed during the procedure and recovery stage, and again at the the 48 hour follow-up with the parent/caregiver</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2. Parental/caregiver satisfaction with procedure will be assessed through the use of a 7 point likert scale. This will be assessed during the recovery stage of the procedure and again between 48 and 96 hours after the procedure, by phone call (This allows for research assistants to return to work, ie: long weekends),  

</outcome>
      <timepoint>during the recovery stage and again between 48 and 96 hours after the procedure, by phone call (This allows for research assistants to return to work, ie: long weekends),  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physician satisfaction regarding; the participants level of sedation, adequacy to complete the procedure, the route of administration, timeliness of the procedure, and willingness to use the same route again. These will be assessed using a 7 point likert scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be assessed during the recovery stage of the procedure for each participant</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Requirement for IV cannulation during IN sedation not otherwise required for expected clinical course.
That is, requirement for cannulation to either manage complications of IN sedation or to achieve adequate sedation with IV top up ketamine doses. This will provide evidence of the proportion of paediatric emergency sedations that can be performed entirely needle-free.
Indication of Intravenous catheter or intraosseous insertion is on the medication dosing page of the case report form with yes or no tick boxes. If yes, the data collector is then prompted to indicate the reasoning for insertion (inadequate sedation, management of complications or care unrelated to the sedation).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Duration of the procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time from triage to procedure complete - this will be assessed through a retrospective review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>between 48 and 96 hours after the procedure, by phone call (This allows for research assistants to return to work, ie: long weekends),  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome> Emergency Department Length of Stay. A retrospective review of medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>between 48 and 96 hours after the procedure, (This allows for research assistants to return to work, ie: long weekends),  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of minor adverse effects out of 2, between Intranasal and Intravenous/intramuscular delivery; including unpleasant taste in mouth and burning nose during intranasal administration. This will be observed by the clinical staff of participant discomfort, or if the participant is able to vocalise the effects.</outcome>
      <timepoint>during the procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A composition of serious adverse effects compared between the intranasal and the intravenous/intramuscular deliveries, including; severe agitation or distress requiring resedation/complex management, advanced airway management, basic supportive airway assistance, aspiration, persistent throat spasm that requires intervention, prolonged episodes of not breathing requiring intervention, or severe physiological disturbance requiring intervention. this will be measured out of 8. </outcome>
      <timepoint>during the procedure and recovery stage</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Child of aged between greater than or equal to 12 months and less than or equal to 11 years
2. Weight between greater than or equal to 10kg and less than or equal to 40kg; corresponding to 100-400mg IN ketamine
3. Considered by appropriately qualified senior treating clinician (FACEM or SMO) to have an indication for emergency department sedation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>11</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. IV cannula already in situ at time of consideration for recruitment; or required for non-sedation indications prior to initiation of the sedation
2. Any previous adverse reaction or allergy to ketamine or other components of Ketalar (registered trade name)
3. Past history of significant cardiac disease, especially pulmonary hypertension
4.American Society of Anaesthesiology Classification  &gt; 1
5. Predicted difficult bag-mask ventilation or laryngoscopy
6. Critical illness
7. Severe trauma
8. Procedure better managed in operating theatre
9. Communicating hydrocephalus or other pre-existing condition predisposing to raised intracranial pressure (head injury is not an exclusion criteria unless meeting definition of major trauma)
10. Disease of the nose, significant coryza or nasal discharge, nasal obstruction or other condition preventing effective administration by the IN route</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Once eligibility is confirmed and informed consent obtained; clinicians will open a sequentially numbered (randomised number) opaque envelope to reveal the patients allocated treatment group. Treating clinicians will be required to enter patient details onto the envelope prior to opening and obtaining the allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be via computerised random number generator in a 1:1 allocation ratio, stratified to painful/non-painful procedure to ensure both U and N groups will be balanced in regards to this potential confounding variable. The randomised number will be used to label an envelope containing the allocation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be entered into an Excel spreadsheet, access to which will be available only to study investigators. Data will be stored in a safe and secure location. Data will be analysed using SPSS 22.0. Continuous variables will be tested for normality. Based on the outcome of the test, parametric Students T test or non-parametric Mann-Whitney test will be carried out to determine the differences in data. Categorical data will be analysed using the Chi-squared analysis. A p value &lt; 0.05 will be considered statistically significant.
All data will be analysed on an intention to treat basis. Patients who withdraw or are lost to follow up will be regarded as treatment failures for data analysis purposes and analysed with imputed data.

The sample size calculation is based on the non-inferiority of IN Ketamine compared to standard treatment with regard to the binary outcome of procedural sedation adequacy, as defined above in section Data points to be collected. The non-inferiority design was favoured as it is thought that the delivery of procedural sedation using the IN route has significant advantages over the conventional routes to justify use if it is demonstrated to be non-inferior by the pre-specified margin. Existing literature suggests that the percentage of procedural sedation success in the Usual Care (U) arm will be within the range of 90-98%. Using an estimate of 95% success in the usual care arm in our trial, a 5% margin of non-inferiority, with a one sided alpha of 5% and 90% power we would require 326 participants per group or 652 in total.
Calculations performed on:
https://www.sealedenvelope.com/power/binary-noninferior/
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/08/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>652</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Townsville Hospital - Douglas</hospital>
    <hospital>Redcliffe Hospital - Redcliffe</hospital>
    <hospital>Hervey Bay Hospital - Pialba</hospital>
    <hospital>Bundaberg Hospital - Bundaberg</hospital>
    <postcode>4810 - Townsville</postcode>
    <postcode>4670 - Bundaberg</postcode>
    <postcode>4020 - Redcliffe</postcode>
    <postcode>4655 - Hervey Bay</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Townsville Hospital and Health Service</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>100 Angus-Smith Drive, Douglas, Qld, 4814</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Queensland Emergency Medicine Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2/15 Lang Parade, Milton, QLD, 4064</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>n/a</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>n/a</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Sedation of children in the Emergency Department (ED) for either urgent therapeutic procedures that may be painful or which require a still and cooperative child (such as wound closure, abscess drainage, foreign body removal, lumbar puncture or fracture reduction) or to obtain critical diagnostic information (for example via medical imaging) is an important aspect of emergency medical practice for which a considerable and evolving body of evidence has developed over several decades. Sedation and analgesia for painful procedures is certainly considered a standard of care that should be offered to all children undergoing painful procedures where possible. While there are some published guidelines there is considerable variation in practice both locally and internationally in terms of choice of sedative agent and conduct of the procedure of sedation. Most of the literature relates to parenteral routes of administration of sedative drugs, typically intravenous (IV) or intramuscular (IM) routes, due to the ability to titrate the dose and the reliability of drug effects when administered via these routes. 

Study aims
1. Investigate the feasibility of a novel needle-free approach to paediatric sedation in the emergency department
2. Investigate the scientific merit of IN ketamine sedation of children in the emergency department
3. Investigate the practical merit of IN ketamine sedation of children in the emergency department
4. Improve emergency paediatric sedation practices consistent with humane processes of paediatric emergency care
5. Establish a greater evidence base for the intranasal route of sedative drug administration in the emergency department
Study hypotheses
1. That IN ketamine sedation will not require significant rates of IV cannulation to safely complete the procedure where an IV cannula is not already considered essential for a patients ongoing care
2. That IN ketamine (10mg/kg) will provide non-inferior sedation compared with IV ketamine (1.0-2.0mg/kg) and IM ketamine (4-5mg/kg)
3. That IN ketamine would be associated with higher parental/caregiver satisfaction with the overall procedure and general care in the emergency department
4. That IN ketamine would be associated with greater physician satisfaction with the overall performance of the sedation and the process required to ready the patient for sedation
5. That IN ketamine sedation will lead to earlier readiness for performance of the procedure or diagnostic intervention and hence earlier procedural completion
6. That IN ketamine sedation will not be associated with an overall increase in ED length of stay
7. That IN ketamine sedation will not be associated with an increased rate of emesis, unpleasant psychomimetic effects or other adverse events</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children's Health Queensland Hospital and Health Service Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee
Childrens Health Queensland
Level 7, Centre for Childrens Health Research
62 Graham Street
South Brisbane QLD 4101</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370334-24.02.16 KINDER Protocol version 2.0.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Luke Burman</name>
      <address>The Townsville Hospital and Health Service
Emergency Department
100 Angus-Smith Drive, Douglas, Qld, 4814</address>
      <phone>+617 44331111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Luke.Burman@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Bethany Roche</name>
      <address>The Townsville Hospital and Health Service
Emergency Department
100 Angus-Smith Drive, Douglas, QLD, 4814</address>
      <phone>+61437028839</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Bethany.Roche@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Luke Burman</name>
      <address>The Townsville Hospital and Health Service
Emergency Department
100 Angus-Smith Drive, Douglas, Qld, 4814</address>
      <phone>+61432 472 287</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Luke.Burman@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Bethany Roche</name>
      <address>The Townsville Hospital and Health Service
Emergency Department
100 Angus-Smith Drive, Douglas, 4814</address>
      <phone>+61437 028 839</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Bethany.Roche@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>