<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308350">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/08/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000687291</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A  randomised single-blind comparison of the effectiveness of the high-level disinfectants Tristel Fusion (chlorine dioxide) and Cidex OPA (ortho-phthaldehyde) for use with flexible cystoscopes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised single-blind comparison of the rate of urinary tract infections in participants undergoing flexible cystoscopy when the flexible cystoscope is disinfected with Tristel Fusion (chlorine dioxide) compared with Cidex OPA (ortho- phthaldehyde)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>TSL-001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Effectiveness of high level disinfectants for flexible cystoscopes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Tristel Fusion consists of 100 ml chlorine dioxide in aqueous solution. This is diluted in five litres of water. The flexible cystoscope is then immersed in this solution for five minutes and then rinsed thoroughly.</interventions>
    <comparator>Cidex OPA  is a solution containing ortho-phthaldehyde which is used in conjunction with a Medivator (specialised cleaning machine). The flexible ctstoscope in placed in the Medivator and the cleaning cycle initiated. The cycle consists of a 10 minute soaking and soak rinse phase in Cidex OPA, a rinse 1 phase for 7 minutes in potable water, a rinse 2 phase for 6 minutes in potable water, a 30 second alcohol rinse and then a three minute air purge to dry the instrument.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Primary Endpoint is the rate of acquired urinary tract infections as determined by a mid-stream urine test (MSU) 3-7 days post intervention in the participants undergoing flexible cystoscopy when the cystoscope is disinfected with Tristel Fusion compared with Cidex OPA.</outcome>
      <timepoint>A single measurement at 3-7 days post intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical Endpoints:
Urethra / bladder irritation and quality of life 3-7 days post-cystoscopy compared with baseline using the following questionnaires:
-The Short Form Urogenital Distress Inventory (UDI-6)+2 questions
-The American Urological Association Symptom Index (AUA-7)
-Single Question Quality of Life Score (QoL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>A single measurement at 3-7 days post intervention which is then compared with baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Microbiology Endpoints: 
-Microbiological culture of washings and brushings from the flexible cystoscopes working channel and equipment. Samples of the washings and brushings are inoculated onto each of Blood Agar and MacConkey Agar and incubated aerobically.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post disinfection</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost-effectiveness of the 2 disinfectants will be assessed:
 - The total per-patient cost of high-level disinfection with the Tristel Fusion system and the Cidex OPA system will be calculated using data collected from the participants undergoing cystoscopy.  These costs will include a per-procedure estimate of machine and tray cost, all disposables, irrigation fluids, nursing time and any scope damage caused by the disinfecting agents.
-Timing of the two processes and measurement of patient through-put; time needed for the cleaning process as an indicator of relative efficiency.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Cost effectiveness will be analysed from data from all participants in the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ease-of-use and odour will be assessed using a 5 point Likert scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>These will be rated by the nurses using the disinfection equipment on each study day</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants requiring a flexible cystoscope and who provide written informed consent will be eligible to participate. Other inclusion criteria are a negative MSU at baseline, no symptoms of urinary tract infection (UTI) on the day of investigation, no specific indication for parenteral antibiotic prophylaxis (e.g. artificial heart valve), no current indwelling urinary catheter and no recent surgery on the urogenital tract.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria include the requirement of a biopsy during the procedure.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be allocated to the next available cystoscopy clinic day. When all the available spaces for a clinic day are filled, the randomised high level disinfectant (i.e. either Tristel Fusion or Cidex OPA) for that day will be determined by the study statistician and relevant staff notified. In this way, investigators allocating participants to a cystoscopy clinic study day do not know which disinfectant will be used on that day. While each individual participant is not randomly allocated to disinfectant type with this approach, it has the advantage that each participant is allocated to the next available cystoscopy clinic. It is anticipated that there will be at least 8 clinic study days. The randomisation process will be constructed by the independent statistician to ensure there are equivalent numbers of Tristel Fusion and Cidex OPA study days.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software (i.e., computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>It is not possible to blind the people conducting the disinfection since the two products are different in appearance and procedures required. However the urologists conducting the cystoscopes; the participants reporting the symptoms and the lab staff analysing the mid-stream urine samples will be blinded</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/09/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>180</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Bay of Plenty</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Tristel Solutions Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Lynx Business Park
Fordham Road
Snailwell
Cambridgeshire CB8 7NY</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United Kingdom</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Tristel Solutions Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Lynx Business Park
Fordham Road
Snailwell
Cambridgeshire CB8 7NY</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United Kingdom</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There are several methods and agents which can be used to provide high-level disinfection of semi-critical instruments such as flexible cystoscopes, however non-corrosive methods are required because of the composition of the instrument. 
Cidex OPA (ortho-Phthalaldehyde; 1,2  benzenedicarboxaldehyde) has been widely used for high level disinfection but may elicit an allergic reaction in workers if protective equipment is not used and the vapours produced may be an irritant to the respiratory tract and eyes (Cidex OPA Directions for Use; 2004). 
Tristel Solutions Limited (UK) produces a range of high level disinfectant products which use chlorine dioxide chemistry and the products have also been used as a disinfectant for a wide variety of instruments and surfaces without safety issues (Tristel data on file). Therefore the use of Tristel is expected to pose a very low risk to patients, surgeons and nurses.
If Tristel Fusion is shown to be at least as effective as Cidex OPA in terms of post-intervention complications (infection/inflammation) for patients, less in-use problems for the surgeons and nurses, then it may be a preferable product to use for high-level disinfection of flexible cystoscopes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Y Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>354 Victoria Street
Hamilton 3140</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/07/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTY/09/06/049</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/06/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Peter Gilling</name>
      <address>Promed Urology
Suite 6
Promed House
71 10th Avenue
Tauranga 3001</address>
      <phone>+64 7 5782561</phone>
      <fax>+64 7 5784717</fax>
      <email>Peter@promed.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rana Reuther</name>
      <address>Research Manager
Tauranga Urology Research Ltd
Promed House
71 10th Avenue
Tauranga 3001</address>
      <phone>+64 7 5782561</phone>
      <fax>+64 7 5784717</fax>
      <email>Rana@promed.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Michelle Lockhart</name>
      <address>51 Woodside Road
Mt Eden
Auckland 1024</address>
      <phone>+64 21 665 947</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.lockhart@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>