<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370105">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000229471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Management to Optimise Diabetes and mEtabolic syndrome Risk reduction via Nurse-led intervention (MODERN) Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Management to Optimise Diabetes and mEtabolic syndrome Risk reduction via Nurse-led intervention (MODERN) Study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The MODERN Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) Project Grant 1069043</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metabolic Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease (CVD) risk factors</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Health disparities in regional communities</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A total of 300 individuals with clinically diagnosed metabolic syndrome (MetS) and/or type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) will be randomised to Usual Care (UC, n=150) or the MODERN intervention (n=150). During the 24-month management program: 
1. UC participants will visit the clinic and undergo non-invasive clinical assessments, finger prick blood samples to monitor their MetS risk factors and progression, complete research questionnaires about health behaviours and overall health status on 3 occasions (baseline, 12 and 24 months) that take approximately 60 minutes. 
2. MODERN intervention participants will have between 1 and 4 extra clinic visits lasting approximately 60 minutes each over 24 months (in addition to the baseline, 12 and 24 months clinic visits). The exact number of visits will depend on the amount of assistance required to manage an individuals level of risk based on the adaptation of the intensity of management according to risk and need using the GARDIAN (Green Amber Red Delineation of rIsk And Need) system. The GARDIAN system [*] is a traffic-light system developed to systematically categorise individual risk and need. Based on the initial comprehensive baseline profiling, each participant in the MODERN intervention group will be designated a traffic light colour RED (high), AMBER (intermediate) or GREEN (low), to describe the level of care provided by one of three management levels (+ additional visits): Green: 18 month contact; Amber: 6 and 18 month clinic visits; Red: 3, 6, 15 and 18 month clinic visits. These visits include non-invasive clinical assessments and finger prick blood samples to monitor their MetS risk factors and progression.
The research nurse will provide an individual care plan according to identified risk factors (with input from nurse diabetes educators, the participant and their family/carers, and any other health care team members) and provide education and advice in order to minimise risk based on the 5As model. The 5As model consists of behavioural counselling to help individuals to change multiple health behaviours. The objective is to help participants to develop a personal action plan by systematically applying a series of five interrelated behaviour change principles. An outline of the sequence of support activities is as follows:
Step 1 ASSESS
i. biomedical, behavioural, socio-demographic and familial risk factor results in contrast to recommended levels from published guidelines and reports.
ii. self-efficacy  beliefs (importance, confidence, intentions) in the participants ability to succeed in a particular situation (i.e. in their ability to complete tasks, change behaviours and reach goals).
Step 2 ADVISE:
i. health risks of the many risk factors linked to CVD and diabetes.
ii. benefits of changing one or more behaviours. 
iii. recommend (based on published guidelines and reports) the appropriate amount, intensity and frequency of behaviour needed to help reduce the risk for CVD and diabetes.
Step 3 AGREE:
i. list and collaboratively set specific goals (in behavioural terms) based on the participants interest and confidence to perform the behaviour, which are mutually negotiated and achievable.
ii. develop an agreed personal action plan (what, when, where, how).
Step 4 ASSIST:
i. list any real or anticipated personal barriers to achieving the identified goals and document strategies to overcome these barriers.
ii. identify and aid in connecting with potential community programs or opportunities for lifestyle improvement and social support.
iii. provide educational brochures to be used as a resource and reminder for behaviour change.
Step 5 ARRANGE:
i. specify a plan for follow-up visits, telephone calls, email reminders according to the GARDIAN system (see above).
ii. recommend referral to a medical or allied health professional (e.g. dietician), including utilisation of video conferencing (Tele Health) for treatment or improved pharmacological management.
iii. make use of self-monitoring and completion of a health passport to record behavioural and lifestyle changes for tracking progress and providing feedback.

The clinic manager will be responsible for scheduling all clinic appointments based on a centralised database/calendar. All MODERN intervention participants will also be provided with a MODERN Study Health Passport with all scheduled appointments and all clinical results. This booklet also contains relevant health information and a comprehensive list of latest evidence-based guidelines and recommendations on metabolic syndrome and CVD risk factors. 

*Carrington MJ, Kok S, Jansen K, Stewart S. The Green, Amber, Red Delineation of Risk and Need (GARDIAN) management system: a pragmatic approach to optimizing heart health from primary prevention to chronic disease management. Eur J Cardiovasc Nurs 2013; 12(4):337-345.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Achievement of 3 or more targets (based on the clinical diagnosis of MetS) or clinically meaningful changes in contributory risk factors. 
Blood pressure (BP)
Target: systolic BP less than or equal to 130 mmHg and/or diastolic BP less than or equal to 85 mmHg.
Clinical change: to reduce BP by more than or equal to 7/3 mmHg (in men) and more than or equal to 8/4 mmHg (in women).
Triglyceride
Target: less than or equal to 1.7 mmol/L.
Clinical change: to reduce triglyceride levels by more than or equal to 0.6 mmol/L (in men) and more than or equal to 0.5 mmol/L (in women).
HDL-C
Target: more than 1.03 mmol/L (in men) and more than 1.29 mmol/L (in women)
Clinical change: to increase HDL-C by more than or equal to 0.15 mmol/L (in men) and more than or equal to 0.18 mmol/L (in women).
Waist circumference
Target: less than 94 cm (in men) and less than 80 cm (in women).
Clinical change: to reduce waist circumference by more than or equal to 5 cm (in men) and more than or equal to 6 cm (in women).
Glucose
Target: HbA1c less than or equal to 5.6% or fasting blood glucose less than or equal to 5.5 mmol/L. 	
Clinical change: to reduce blood glucose by more than or equal to 0.7 mmol/L (in men) or more than or equal to 0.8 mmol/L (in women)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At study completion (24 months after randomisation). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biomedical risk  any changes indicative of improvement in risk profile including individual MetS risk factors; absolute CVD risk [1]; adiposity (body mass index: kg/m^2 and body weight); lipids (total cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol: point of care device and blood pathology testing); renal function (estimated glomerular filtration rate [eGFR]); vascular health (ankle brachial index and arterial stiffness [2]); biomarkers of CVD risk (high sensitive C-reactive protein: blood pathology testing [3]) and pharmacological treatments (face to face interview).  

1National Vascular Disease Prevention Alliance. Guidelines for the assessment of absolute cardiovascular disease risk: National Heart Foundation of Australia; 2009.
2Shirai K, Hiruta N, Song M, Kurosu T, Suzuki J, Tomaru T, Miyashita Y, Saiki A, Takahashi M, Suzuki K, Takata M. Cardio-ankle vascular index (CAVI) as a novel indicator of arterial stiffness: theory, evidence and perspectives. J Atheroscler Thromb 2011; 18(11):924-938.
3Ridker PM. Clinical application of C-reactive protein for cardiovascular disease detection and prevention. Circulation 2003; 107(3):363-369.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At study completion (24 months after randomisation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lifestyle behaviours - any changes indicative of improvement in risk profile including smoking cessation (face to face interview); physical activity and sedentary behavior (IPAQ [1] and actigraphy [2]) and diet (Dietary Questionnaire for Epidemiological Studies Version 2 [DQES v2]) [3].
 
1Craig CL, Marshall AL, Sjostrom M, Bauman AE, Booth ML, Ainsworth BE, Pratt M, Ekelund U, Yngve A, Sallis JF, Oja P. International physical activity questionnaire: 12-country reliability and validity. Med Sci Sports Exerc 2003; 35(8):1381-1395.
2Trost SG, McIver KL, Pate RR. Conducting accelerometer-based activity assessments in field-based research. Med Sci Sports Exerc 2005; 37(11 Suppl):S531-543.
3Hodge A, Patterson AJ, Brown WJ, Ireland P, Giles G. The Anti Cancer Council of Victoria FFQ: relative validity of nutrient intakes compared with weighed food records in young to middle-aged women in a study of iron supplementation. Aust N Z J Public Health 2000; 24(6):576-583.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At study completion (24 months after randomisation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental health related quality of life - assessed by a validated self-administered questionnaire: AQol-8D [1]

1Richardson J, Elsworth G, Iezzi A, Khan M, Mihalopoulos C, Schweitzer I, Herrman H. Increasing the sensitivity of the AQoL inventory for the evaluation of interventions affecting mental health: Centre for Health Economics, Monash University, Melbourne.; 2011.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At study completion (24 months after randomisation) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health psychology self-evaluation - assessed by a modified behaviour specific self-efficacy questionnaire designed specifically for this study [1].

1Schwarzer R, Jerusalem M. Generalized Self-Efficacy scale. In: Weinman J, Wright S, Johnston M, eds. Measures in health psychology: A user's portfolio Causal and control beliefs. Windsor, UK: NFER-NELSON; 1995. p. 35-37.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At study completion (24 months after randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A composite endpoint of participant satisfaction with preferences and willingness-to-pay for overall health care delivery and intervention - assessed by a modified participants' preference questionnaire designed specifically for this study [1].

1Poulton BC. Use of the consultation satisfaction questionnaire to examine patients' satisfaction with general practitioners and community nurses: reliability, replicability and discriminant validity. The British journal of general practice : the journal of the Royal College of General Practitioners 1996; 46(402):26-31.


</outcome>
      <timepoint>At study completion (24 months after randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A composite endpoint of health care system utilisation and cost of community/ specialist care and treatments (including prescription data) via access to Medicare claims data (submission to Medicare).

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Study completion (24 months after randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Detailed health economic analyses on the cost of applying the MODERN intervention (including staff salaries, consumable and infrastructure costs, referral to other allied-health professionals and services [non-Medicare] and participant out of pocket cost) - assessed by review of study cost records measured during the MODERN program.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At study completion (24 months after randomisation)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. aged between 40-70 years at the time of recruitment.
2. have a confirmed diagnosis of MetS +/- T2DM.
3. reside in Colac or Shepparton (or surrounding suburbs).
4. be capable of attending clinic visits. 
5. be able to provide informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. any clinically diagnosed form of CVD and/or renal disease.
2. a significant neurological/cognitive impairment or unable to provide written informed consent.
3. any other life-threatening comorbid disease or medical condition that results in the belief (deemed by the CIs) that it is not appropriate for an individual to participate.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible participants will be randomised on a 1:1 basis (150 MODERN intervention:150 UC) following consent and generated via a blinded automated computer program applied by the Data Management Unit. In the unlikely event that two (or more) eligible participants are recruited from the same household, we will ensure that they are randomised to the same study group to reduce intervention contamination.</concealment>
    <sequence>Block (per community) stratified +/- type II diabetes randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We estimate that endpoint data from a minimum of 125 individuals per group will provide 95% study power (assuming a two-sided alpha of 0.05) to detect an absolute 15% difference (20% endpoint achieved in the MODERN intervention group and 5% in the UC group) in the primary endpoint at 24 months. With potential loss to follow-up of 15% (10% in the first year and 5% thereafter) a target of 150 individuals in each group will ensure that sufficient endpoint data will be available to retain estimated study power. Under the same assumptions, this sample size will provide 90% power to detect a 1% absolute difference in absolute cardiovascular risk (from baseline to 24 months) in favour of the MODERN intervention group (conservative mean change 2 +/- 3.8%) compared to the UC group (1 +/- 3.8%).
All analyses will be performed on an intention-to-treat basis. Data from each community will be pooled and summarised with respect to demographic and clinical characteristics. Comparison of baseline and end-point data will involve x^2 analysis (odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals) for discrete variables, Students t-test and Mann-Whitney tests where appropriate. Secondary end-point data analyses will compare change between intervention and usual care subjects using linear regression to correct for between-group differences and obtain the effect size of MODERN relative to other likely determinants of risk factor modification. Multiple logistic regressions will determine independent correlates of achieving the primary endpoint at 24 months.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>26/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>276</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3250 - Colac</postcode>
    <postcode>3630 - Shepparton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research, Australian Catholic University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5, 215 Spring Street, Melbourne, VIC 3000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC Project grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421, Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Baker IDI Heart and Diabetes Institute</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>75 Commercial Road, Melbourne, VIC 3004</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Department of General Practice, Melbourne University </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>200 Berkeley Street, Carlton, VIC 3053</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>People can have many risk factors, but when a combination group together at the same time, including high blood pressure, obesity, blood glucose (sugar) and lipids (cholesterol and triglyceride), it forms what is called the metabolic syndrome and exposes individuals to diabetes and cardiovascular disease. People living in regional areas have higher levels of these risk factors than people living in metropolitan areas. One reason for this is less access to health care. Therefore, a health and lifestyle intervention program led by nurses for participants with metabolic syndrome may be beneficial for preventing these diseases. The aim of this study is to develop a regional health care program that reduces the risk of developing diabetes or cardiovascular disease (such as a heart attack or stroke) by managing risk factors that cause these diseases better.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.cre2rihd.org.au/modern.html</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred Hospital, 55 Commercial Rd, Prahran VIC 3181</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC Number: 145/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/04/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Catholic University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Australian Catholic University Melbourne Campus
Locked Bag 4115 
FITZROY VIC 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC Number: 2014 244V</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Melinda Carrington</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Level 5, 215 Spring Street, Melbourne VIC 3004
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9953 3688</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9663 5726</fax>
      <email>melinda.carrington@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Melinda Carrington</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Level 5, 215 Spring Street, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9953 3688</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9663 5726</fax>
      <email>melinda.carrington@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Melinda Carrington</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Level 5, 215 Spring Street, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9953 3688</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9663 5726</fax>
      <email>melinda.carrington@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Yih-Kai Chan</name>
      <address>Mary MacKillop Institute for Health Research
Level 5, 215 Spring Street, Melbourne VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9230 8054</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9663 5726</fax>
      <email>yihkai.chan@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>