<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367221">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001111662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Sight word and phonics training in children with poor reading</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of phonics and sight-word reading treatment on word reading accuracy, fluency, and comprehension in children who are poor readers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Reading impairment</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dyslexia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Poor reading</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Learning disabilities</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Phonics treatment trained letter recognition, parsing, letter-sound rules, and blending. Sight-word treatment trained children to associate written irregular words (i.e., those that do not follow the letter-sound rules) with the appropriate pronunciations. These skills were trained using software programs. Children trained at home for 30 minutes per day, 5 days per week, for 8 weeks.

There were two treatment groups. Group 1 did no treatment (8 weeks) followed by phonics training (8 weeks) followed by sight word training (8 weeks). Group 2 did the same except the order of training was reversed (i.e., they did sight word training before phonics training). There was one week between interventions. An extended washout period was not required.</interventions>
    <comparator>This study used a double-baseline control. At the start of the study, each child in each group completed the outcomes measures (Time 1). After 8 weeks of *no* treatment, they redid the same tests (Time 2). We subtracted their scores at Time 1 from Time 2 to reveal "non-training" effects (e.g., test-retest effects, regression to the mean effects, maturation effects) on each test. In our analyses, we compared gains over each treatment periods to these non-training effects. Gains were only considered to be valid treatment effects if they were statistically significantly larger than the non-training effects.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Castles and Coltheart 2 Nonword Reading Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Time 1, Time 2 (after 8 weeks of no treatment; baseline control), Time 3 (after 8 weeks of phonics training or sight word training), and at Time 4 (after a further 8 weeks of phonics training or sight word training).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Castles and Coltheart 2 Irregular-word Reading test</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Time 1, Time 2 (after 8 weeks of no treatment; baseline control), Time 3 (after 8 weeks of phonics training or sight word training), and at Time 4 (after a further 8 weeks of phonics training or sight word training).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Test of Everyday Reading Comprehension (TERC)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Time 1, Time 2 (after 8 weeks of no treatment; baseline control), Time 3 (after 8 weeks of phonics training or sight word training), and at Time 4 (after a further 8 weeks of phonics training or sight word training).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Test of Word Reading Efficiency (TOWRE) Sight Word Efficiency and TOWRE Phonetic Decoding Efficiency</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Time 1, Time 2 (after 8 weeks of no treatment; baseline control), Time 3 (after 8 weeks of phonics training or sight word training), and at Time 4 (after a further 8 weeks of phonics training or sight word training).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnostic Spelling Test for Nonwords (DiSTn)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Time 1, Time 2 (after 8 weeks of no treatment; baseline control), Time 3 (after 8 weeks of phonics training or sight word training), and at Time 4 (after a further 8 weeks of phonics training or sight word training).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diagnostic Spelling Test for Irregular Words (DiSTi)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At Time 1, Time 2 (after 8 weeks of no treatment; baseline control), Time 3 (after 8 weeks of phonics training or sight word training), and at Time 4 (after a further 8 weeks of phonics training or sight word training).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children who have (1) English as their first language, (2) no problems with attention, hearing, sight, or behaviour, and (3) poor reading for their age (i.e., their ability to read nonwords or  irregular words - as measured by the Castles and Coltheart 2 Reading Test - was below the average range (a z scores lower than -1) for their age). </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>12</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Poor attention, poor hearing, poor visual acuity, severe developmental delay</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Children with nonword or irregular word reading accuracy below the average range (i.e., below the 16th percentile) were allocated to Group 1 or 2 using minimisation (1:1; age, nonword reading accuracy, irregular word reading accuracy), which is considered by CONSORT to be equivalent to randomisation for trials with less than 100 participants.

Minimisation was executed by the lead research assistant using MinimPy. Group allocation was stored in a centralised database. Children were subsequently tested by another research assistant who was (1) unaware of group allocation, and (2) did not test the same child twice within the study. Children and their parents were unaware of allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Children were allocated to Group 1 or 2 using minimisation (1:1; age, nonword reading accuracy, irregular word reading accuracy), which is considered by CONSORT to be equivalent to randomisation for trials with less than 100 participants.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To determine if there was a reliable difference between 8 weeks of phonics and sight word training, we used a between-group ANCOVA (controlling for each groups corresponding non-training gains) to compare Time 1-Time 3 gains for each group. To determine if different orders of training had different effects on each outcome, we used a between-groups ANCOVA (controlling for non-training gains) to compare Time 1-Time 4 gains for each group. 

Size of groups was determined based on outcomes of previous group studies of case studies suggesting that phonics training would have large effects on reading skills that depended heavily on phonics skills (d =0.8) and sight word training would have large effects on reading skills that depended on recognising whole words from memory (d = 0.8). With a power of 0.8, this equates to at least 26 children per group.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>2/01/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>52</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2000 - Sydney</postcode>
    <postcode>2100 - North Manly</postcode>
    <postcode>2200 - Bankstown</postcode>
    <postcode>2150 - Parramatta</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Macquarie University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Cognitive Science
Macquarie University NSW 2109</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, 20 Allara Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australia Research Council (ARC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 11 Lancaster Place
Canberra Airport ACT 2609 
AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>ARC Centre of Excellence in Cognition and its Disorders</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Macquarie University
NSW 2109</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Literacy Planet</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>3/23 Main St
Varsity Lakes QLD 4227
Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study tested potential treatments for Australian children who have severe problems learning to read. Some of poor readers find it hard to read via the letter-sound rules (phonics), some find it hard to read whole words by sight (sight-word reading), and many have both of these problems.

In this study, one group of poor readers (N = 41) did 8 weeks of specific phonics training (i.e., reading via phonological decoding) and then 8 weeks of specific sight word training (i.e., reading via recognition of irregular words from memory). A second group of poor readers (N = 44) did the reverse order of training. The results showed that both specific sight word training and specific phonics training had large and significant valid treatment effects on trained irregular words, untrained irregular words, and word reading fluency; and that specific phonics training had an additional large and significant valid treatment effect on reading comprehension.

These findings demonstrate the reliability of both phonics and sight word training in treating poor readers. This will aid Australias efforts to counteract the effects of poor reading in children by revealing how different treatments should be tailored to children with different types of reading impairment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Power calculations prior to the study indicated that this study needed to recruit at least 26 participants per group. Our recruitment campaign was more successful than expected, and so we recruited 41 and 44 subjects per group (ie more than 26 per group).</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University Ethics Secretariat</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Secretariat
Macquarie University NSW 2109</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/12/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HE28SEP2007-R05411</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/12/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Genevieve McArthur</name>
      <address>Department of Cognitive Science
Macquarie University NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9162</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>genevieve.mcarthur@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Genevieve McArthur</name>
      <address>Department of Cognitive Science
Macquarie University NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9162</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>genevieve.mcarthur@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Genevieve McArthur</name>
      <address>Department of Cognitive Science
Macquarie University NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9162</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>genevieve.mcarthur@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Genevieve McArthur</name>
      <address>Department of Cognitive Science
Macquarie University NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9162</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>genevieve.mcarthur@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>