<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372380">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000440325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MindCast: A randomised controlled trial of a podcast intervention for relationship separation </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Testing the effectiveness of a web-based, audio podcast to improve adjustment for Australian adults who have recently separated from an intimate partner relationship</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MindCast</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Depression </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Suicidal ideation </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Suicide</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A 2-arm randomised waitlist-controlled trial with a primary endpoint at 3 weeks and a 3-month follow-up, testing the effectiveness of a web-based, audio podcast (using computer, smartphone or tablet) program to improve adjustment following an intimate partner relationship separation. 

The purpose of this intervention is to target individuals who have separated from a romantic relationship in the past six months, and use Brief Interpersonal Psychotherapy (IPT-B) strategies to promote active coping and positive adjustment and decrease suicidal ideation and symptoms of depression. 

The podcast episodes are developed, written and narrated by a Clinical Psychologist.  The podcast content is based on Brief Interpersonal Psychotherapy (IPT-B; Swartz et al., 2014), which is an eight session intervention adapted from the original evidence-based psychotherapy, Interpersonal Psychotherapy (IPT).  The rationale for IPT-B is to provide an opportunity for individuals to be able to access the benefits of traditional IPT and who may not necessarily have the time or resources to be able to commit to a full 16 session intervention.  Following clinical guidelines suggested by Stuart and Robertson (2012), relationship separation can be covered under the role transition interpersonal problem area.  It was determined that by focusing on one specific interpersonal problem area, the content of the podcast can be personalised to reflect on common aspects of a separation while allowing participants to experience the tactics and techniques specific to IPT delivery.  

Content specific to the intervention includes: episode one  introduction to IPT, episode two  role transitions, episode three  interpersonal inventory, episode four  life events timeline, episode five  cons and pros of moving on, episode six  self-concept.  Each podcast episode will run for a maximum of 15 minutes.  Only the Clinical Psychologist will be heard on each episode. 

Once the initial survey is completed, and following randomisation, participants will be invited to access each podcast episode via a link sent through to their email accounts.  The link will redirect participants to an audio file embedded in a website (hosted by the Australian National University) where they can immediately listen to the podcast episode.  Podcast episodes will be made available every three days in a sequential order.  Participants will be emailed a new link every three days.   

The remotely delivered trial will be advertised nationwide using social media and by approaching relevant mental health organisations.  Three-week and three-month assessments will collect self-report measures of suicidal ideation and depression, as well as secondary outcomes (interpersonal needs, benefit-finding, adjustment, self-hate, and  help-seeking ) and potential mediators (demographics) via online surveys.  Fidelity and adherence will be assessed and reported as part of a process evaluation.

The podcasts are informed by interpersonal psychotherapy and social theories informing suicidal ideation and behaviours.  
</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be placed on the waitlist until the intervention period, and the first follow-up (3 months), is complete. Then participants in the control condition will be provided with full access to the program. The delivery of the program to the control condition will be identical to the initial intervention program. The intervention will be open for interested participants for 4-weeks after the completion of the original trial (after the final 3 month follow-up survey). After this period the intervention will no longer be available to the community to allow for analysis of data. 

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Suicidal ideation measure by the Suicidal Ideation Attributes Scale (SIDAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately after the intervention (3 weeks) and at 12-week follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression as measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately after the intervention (3 weeks) and at 12-week follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Suicidal behaviours and attempts as measured by the Psychiatric Symptom Frequency Scale (PSF)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately after the intervention (3 weeks) and at 12-week follow-up.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measuring a sense of Thwarted Belongingness and Perceived Burdensomeness using the 
 Interpersonal Needs Questionnaire (INQ)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately after the intervention (3 weeks) and at 12-week follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measuring benefits using the General Benefit Finding Scale (GBFS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately after the intervention (3 weeks) and at 12-week follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measuring adjustment after the separation using the Psychological Adjustment to Separation Test (PAST)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately after the intervention (3 weeks) and at 12-week follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measuring a sense of self-hate using the Self-Hate Scale (SHS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately after the intervention (3 weeks) and at 12-week follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measuring help-seeking using the Attitude Toward Seeking Professional Psychological Help-Short Form (ATPPSH)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, immediately after the intervention (3 weeks) and at 12-week follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exploring where and how the podcasts were used using a Place of Use Questionnaire specifically designed for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the intervention (3 weeks) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measuring information processing using a Cognitive Load Questionnaire specifically designed for this study</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the intervention (3 weeks) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measuring how stimuli was processed using the Elaboration Likelihood Model Questionnaire </outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the intervention (3 weeks) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exploring participants perception of the intervention with 9 specifically developed questions</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the intervention (3 weeks) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Open ended questions to capture any extra information:
- What did you find most valuable/helpful from the podcast program?
- What did you find least valuable/helpful from the podcast program?
-If you have any other comments on the podcast program, please enter them here:
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after the intervention (3 weeks) </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants are eligible for the study if they:
1.	Are between 18 and 65 years of age
2.	Have separated from a romantic relationship in the last six months
3.	Are an Australian resident 
4.	Are able to competently understand the English language (both spoken and written)
5.	Have or are willing to create an email account, and have access to the internet
6.	Have access to, and basic ability to use a computer
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if they:
1.	Do not provide informed consent or refuse to be randomised
2.	Are in a new relationship
3.	Self-report a current suicide plan
4.	Self-report a suicide attempt in the last month 
5.	Self-report a diagnosis of a substance-related disorder, post-traumatic stress disorder, schizophrenia, bipolar or a personality disorder.

For the purposes of this study, an intimate partner relationship is defined as: an interpersonal relationship between heterosexual or same-sex partners, which involved emotional and physical intimacy. 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (Qualtrics)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>For a moderate post intervention difference between the two groups (with power of .9 and alpha of .05) we would need 60 participants per group (120 in total).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/05/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/01/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Research Excellence in Suicide Prevention (CRESP)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>NHMRC Centre of Research Excellence in Suicide Prevention
Black Dog Institute
Hospital Road
RANDWICK, NSW, 2031
AUSTRALIA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Centre for Research Excellence in Suicide Prevention (CRESP)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>NHMRC Centre of Research Excellence in Suicide Prevention
Black Dog Institute
Hospital Road
RANDWICK, NSW, 2031
AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian National University </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre for Mental Health Research
Building 63
The Australian National University
Canberra ACT 2601
AUSTRALIA</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A 2-arm randomised waitlist-controlled trial with a primary endpoint at 3 weeks and a 3-month follow-up, testing the effectiveness of a web-based, audio podcast (using computer, smartphone or tablet) program to improve adjustment following an intimate partner relationship separation.  The purpose of this intervention is to target individuals who have separated from a romantic relationship in the past six months, and use Brief Interpersonal Psychotherapy (IPT-B) strategies to promote active coping and positive adjustment and decrease suicidal ideation and symptoms of depression. 

The intervention is a web-based, six-session, online podcast program that can be accessed from any location with internet access.  The intervention is free, confidential and easily accessible by people across Australia.  

Assessments will be conducted at baseline, immediately after intervention (3 weeks) and at 12-week follow-up.  Outcome measures will include demographics, mental health status, presence/severity of suicidal ideation, social support, positive adjustment, help seeking and the utility of the program.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ANU Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Australian National University
Acton ACT 2601
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2017/089</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Dominique Kazan </name>
      <address>Centre for Mental Health Research
Building 63
The Australian National University
Canberra ACT 2601
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6125 2741</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dominique.kazan@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Dominique Kazan </name>
      <address>Centre for Mental Health Research
Building 63
The Australian National University
Canberra ACT 2601
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6125 2741</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dominique.kazan@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Dominique Kazan </name>
      <address>Centre for Mental Health Research
Building 63
The Australian National University
Canberra ACT 2601
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6125 2741</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dominique.kazan@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Dominique Kazan </name>
      <address>Centre for Mental Health Research
Building 63
The Australian National University
Canberra ACT 2601
AUSTRALIA</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6125 2741</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>dominique.kazan@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>