<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373196">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001055392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and safety of  artemether+lumefantrine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in Jowhar and Bosaso sites, Somalia.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy and safety of  artemether+lumefantrine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in Jowhar and Bosaso sites, Somalia.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Malaria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of infection and infectious agents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The objective of the study is to assess the efficacy and safety of artemether+lumefantrine (20 mg/120 mg in each table) twice daily doses for three days for the treatment of uncomplicated falciparum malaria. The dose will be calculated based on the recommended weight bands as follows: 1 tablet to those weighing 5 to 14 kg; 2 tablets for 15 to 24 kg; 3 tablets for 25 to 34 kg and 4 tablets for equal or greater than 35 kg. 

All treatments will be taken orally under direct supervision by the health worker and will be followed up for 28 days.
</interventions>
    <comparator>No comparator</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent of treatment failures (early treatment failure + late clinical failure +late parasitological failure). This is composite primary outcome.

Enrolled patients will be assessed for parasitological and clinical responses during the 28 days follow-up and treatment outcomes will be classified according to the latest WHO protocol.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1, 2, 3, 7, 14, 21, 28</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Percent of adverse event following treatment of each drugs will be documented. 
The known adverse events of:

Atemether+lumefantrine are abdominal pain, asthenia, cough, diarrhoea, dizziness, fever, headache, joint and muscle pain, loss of appetite, rush, nausea, vomiting.
Parents or guardians of all enrolled children will be asked routinely about previous symptoms and about symptoms that have emerged since the previous follow-up visit. When clinically indicated, patients will be evaluated and treated appropriately. All adverse events will be recorded on the case report form.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Days 1, 2, 3, 7, 14, 21, 28</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Prevalence of artemisinin resistance molecular markers (K13).
Parasite DNA extracted from the dried blood spots will be analyzed by PCR and sequencing for the presence of K13 (molecular marker for artemisinin resistance).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 0</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	age between 6 months and 60 years with the exception of 12-17years old female minors and unmarried females 18 years and above; 
2.	mono-infection with P. falciparum detected by microscopy;
3.	parasitaemia of 500 - 200000/µl asexual forms;
4.	presence of axillary or tympanic temperature greater or equal to 37.5 degree centigrade or history of fever during the past 24 h;
5.	ability to swallow oral medication;
6.	ability and willingness to comply with the study protocol for the duration of the study and to comply with the study visit schedule; 
7.	informed consent from the patient or from a parent or guardian in the case of children aged less than 18 years;
8.	informed assent from any minor participant aged from 12 to age of majority years; and
9.	consent for pregnancy testing from married female of 18 years and above.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	presence of general danger signs in children aged under 5 years or signs of severe falciparum malaria according to the definitions of WHO;
2.	weight under 5 kg;
3.	mixed or mono-infection with another Plasmodium species detected by microscopy;
4.	presence of severe malnutrition (defined as a child aged 6-60 months who has a mid-upper arm circumference below 115 mm);
5.	presence of febrile conditions due to diseases other than malaria (e.g. measles, acute lower respiratory tract infection, severe diarrhea with dehydration) or other known underlying chronic or severe diseases (e.g. cardiac, renal and hepatic diseases, HIV/AIDS);
6.	regular medication, which may interfere with antimalarial pharmacokinetics;
7.	history of hypersensitivity reactions or contraindications to any of the medicine(s) being tested or used as alternative treatment(s);
8.	a positive pregnancy test or breastfeeding of married women aged 18 years and above; and
9.	unable to or unwilling to take pregnancy test or to use contraception for women of child-bearing age and who are sexually active.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>No concealment</concealment>
    <sequence>Not applicable</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size
As the treatment failure rate to artemether+lumefantrine in the areas is estimated to 5%. At a confidence level of 95% and a precision around the estimate of 5%, a minimum of 73 patients will be included. With a 20% increase to allow loss to follow-up and withdrawals during the 28-day follow-up period, 88 patients per site will be included in the study. 

Analysis of data
The WHO excel software programs will be used for data management and analysis. Data will be analysed by two methods: the Kaplan-Meier method and per-protocol analysis. In addition to the reasons for withdrawal listed in section 3.8, patients will be considered withdrawn from the analysis if the PCR results are unclassifiable or if the results of PCR indicate that the failure is due to reinfection with P. falciparum or P. vivax.

The final analysis will include:

1.	a description of all patients screened and the distribution of reasons for non-inclusion in the study;
2.	a description of all the patients included in the study;
3.	the proportion of adverse events and serious adverse events in all the patients included in the study;
4.	the proportion of patients lost to follow-up or withdrawn, with 95% confidence intervals and a list of reasons for withdrawal;
5.	the cumulative incidence of success and failure rates at day 28, PCR-uncorrected and PCR-corrected; and
6.	the proportion of early treatment failure, late clinical failure, late parasitological failure and adequate clinical and parasitological response at day 28, with 95% confidence intervals, PCR-uncorrected and PCR-corrected.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>176</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/04/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Somalia</country>
      <state>Middle Shabelle and North East Region</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ministry of Health and Human Services, Federal Government </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Mogadihsu Somalia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Somalia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>World Health Organization</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bulo Hubey Airport Street 1
Mogadishu 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Somalia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Title: Efficacy and safety of artemether+lumefantrine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in Johar and Bosaso sites, Somalia.
Purpose: To assess the efficacy of a potential second line treatment policy.
Objective: To assess the efficacy and safety of artemether+lumefantrine for the treatment of uncomplicated P. falciparum malaria infections.
Study Sites: Johar and Bosaso sites.
Study Period: From August 2017 to April 2018
Study Design: One arm prospective study. 
Patient population: Febrile patients aged between 6 months and 60 years, inclusive, with confirmed uncomplicated P. falciparum infection. Female minors aged 12-17 years and unmarried females aged 18 years and above will be excluded as subjecting them to pregnancy testing is unacceptable according to the local customs and cultures.
Sample Size: A total of 88 patients will be enrolled in each site.
Treatment(s) and follow-up: Artemether+lumefantrine twice daily for 3 days will be evaluated. Clinical and parasitological parameters will be monitored over a 28-day follow-up period to evaluate drug efficacy.
Primary endpoints: The proportion of patients with early treatment failure, late clinical failure, late parasitological failure or an adequate clinical and parasitological response as indicators of efficacy.  Recrudescence will be distinguished from re-infection by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) analysis.
Secondary endpoints: 
1. The frequency and nature of adverse events
2. proportion of polymorphism of molecular markers for artemisinin resistance (K13)
</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>WHO ERC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>20 Av. Appia, 
1211 Geneva 27 Switzerland
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/06/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ERC.0002915</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Switzerland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Abdullahi Mohamed Hassan</name>
      <address>Minitry of Health and Human Services
Wadajir, Km5, Zope Street
Mogadishu </address>
      <phone>+252615500514</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amhassanlabfocalp@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Somalia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Abdullahi Mohamed Hassan</name>
      <address>Minitry of Health and Human Services
Wadajir, Km5, Zope Street
Mogadishu </address>
      <phone>+252615500514</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>amhassanlabfocalp@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Somalia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marian Warsame</name>
      <address>20 Av. Appia, 
1211 Geneva 27 Switzerland
</address>
      <phone>+41227915076</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>warsamem@who.int</email>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marian Warsame</name>
      <address>20 Av. Appia, 
1211 Geneva 27 Switzerland</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>