<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364911">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000998741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The use of text messaging to improve attendance in internal medicine outpatient clinic: A randomized controlled trial in a teaching hospital in Saudi Arabia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effectiveness in patients with appointment for outpatient visit to Internal Medicine outpatient clinic of text messaging reminder of the appointment for the intervention group compared to no text messaging reminder in the control group to reduce non-attendance.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non- attendance of outpatient clinic appointment </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All patients whose mobile number were documented in the hospital electronic database and were due to attend an appointment to the IM outpatient clinic during the following week were eligible to be included in the study. Because the SMS reminder messages will be sent in Arabic, non-Arabic speaking patients were excluded from the study. Patients younger than 18 years were also excluded. Each week a list of patients with appointment for the following week was retrieved from the hospital electronic database. A random sample of 20 patients was selected from the list of each day of the week. Using computer generated random number, these 20 patient appointments were then randomly allocated to either receive a reminder text message or to not receive such a reminder (10 appointments per group). This process continued over the study period (3 months) until the required sample size was collected. A standard text message reminder was sent manually to the intervention group using one of the phone service providers in Saudi Arabia 48 hours before the scheduled appointment. It started by a greeting at the beginning of the message followed by a reminder of the date, clinic name, and the hospital name. The text message did not has patients name. Within one week of the appointment, we conducted a telephone survey of a group of participants in the intervention group regarding their perception toward the SMS reminder.   Other data collected from the electronic database included: patient age, sex, nationality, type of visit (new/follow-up) and whether the patient attended the scheduled appointment (show/no-show). The sequence of the randomization was concealed from the IT individual who provided the appointment list. The statistician was also blinded to the patient group.</interventions>
    <comparator>No SMS reminder</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Non-attendance of the outpatient clinic appointment was assessed by checking the hospital administrative database if the patient showed up in intended appointment</outcome>
      <timepoint>Date of outpatient appointment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction with SMS reminder system was assessed by telephone interview among participants who received the SMS reminder .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within one week of the appointment date</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patients who have outpatient appointment within a week
2. Arabic speaking
3. Have a registered phone number</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>&lt;18 years old
Non- Arabic speaking patients</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients whose mobile number were documented in the hospital electronic database and were due to attend an appointment to the IM outpatient clinic during the following week were eligible to be included in the study. Because the SMS reminder messages will be sent in Arabic, non-Arabic speaking patients were excluded from the study. Patients younger than 18 years were also excluded. Each week a list of patients with appointment for the following week was retrieved from the hospital electronic database. A random sample of 20 patients was selected from the list of each day of the week. Using computer generated random number, these 20 patient appointments were then randomly allocated to either receive a reminder text message or to not receive such a reminder (10 appointments per group). This process continued over the study period until the required sample size was collected. A standard text message reminder was sent manually to the intervention group using one of the phone service providers in Saudi Arabia 48 hours before the scheduled appointment. It started by a greeting at the beginning of the message followed by a reminder of the date, clinic name, and the hospital name. The text message did not have patient’s name. The sequence of the randomization was concealed from the IT individual who provided the appointment list. The statistician was also blinded to the patient group.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The statistical analysis was performed using Stata 11 (Stata Corporation, College Station, TX. USA). The primary outcome for the study was non-attendance rate. Patients were considered non-attenders if they were registered in the electronic system as no-show for their scheduled appointment. The non-attendance status was calculated based on intention-to-treat analysis. The non-attendance rate in the SMS reminded group was compared with those in the non-SMS group using chi-squared test. To better control for confounding factors, multivariate logistic regression was conducted with attendance status as the dependent variable (Yes/No) and SMS reminder (Yes/No) as the main exposure factor. Other factors controlled for in the model included patient age, nationality (Saudi/Arab non-Saudi), type of visit (new/follow-up).For the odds ratio (OR) calculation the non SMS reminder group was used as the reference group. The OR and 95% confidence intervals are presented. P-value =0.05 was considered to be statistically significant. The multivariate logistic regression will also allow for hypothesis generation regarding types of patients more likely to not attend their appointment.

Sample size:
For two arm RCT, 151 per group is required to be able to detect 15% reduction due to SMS reminder with a power of 80% and a=5%. For a power of 90%, 198 per group were needed. However, we were able to include a larger number in the study.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/04/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/04/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>4/07/2011</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>4/07/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>502</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <state>Eastern Provience</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Adel Youssef</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>College of Applied Medical Sciences
University of Dammam 
P.O. Box 2435 
Dammam - 31441 
Saudi Arabia 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Saudi Arabia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Saudi Arabia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of sending short messages services (SMS) reminders to patients mobile phone in reducing non-attendance by patients scheduled for an Internal Medicine (IM) outpatient appointment.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HIMT Research Project Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Department of Health Information Management &amp; Technology
College of Applied Medical Sciences
University of Dammam
P.O. Box 2435 
Dammam - 31441 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/02/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HIMT-GP-2</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Saudi Arabia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Adel Youssef</name>
      <address>Department of Health Information Management &amp; Technology
College of Applied Medical Sciences
University of Dammam 
P.O.Box 2435 
Dammam - 31441 
Saudi Arabia 
</address>
      <phone>+966560603410</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aayoussef@ud.edu.sa</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adel Youssef</name>
      <address>Department of Health Information Management &amp; Technology
College of Applied Medical Sciences
University of Dammam 
P.O.Box 2435 
Dammam - 31441 
Saudi Arabia</address>
      <phone>+966560603410</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aayoussef@ud.edu.sa</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adel Youssef</name>
      <address>Department of Health Information Management &amp; Technology
College of Applied Medical Sciences
University of Dammam 
P.O.Box 2435 
Dammam - 31441 
Saudi Arabia</address>
      <phone>+966560603410</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aayoussef@ud.edu.sa</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Adel Youssef</name>
      <address>Department of Health Information Management &amp; Technology
College of Applied Medical Sciences
University of Dammam 
P.O.Box 2435 
Dammam - 31441 
Saudi Arabia</address>
      <phone>+966560603410</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aayoussef@ud.edu.sa</email>
      <country>Saudi Arabia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>