<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366922">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/08/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000922673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Health Promotion for people with or at high risk of Metabolic Syndrome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of a health promotion program on health outcomes and health-promoting behavior of individuals with, or at high risk of metabolic syndrome: a randomized controlled trial </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1160-4432 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Metabolic Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this study is to examine the effect of a health promotion program on health outcomes and health-promoting behavior of community-dwelling adults with, or at high risk of Metabolic syndrome in Hong Kong.

The intervention group will receive a 14-week health promotion program targeting on lifestyle changes. The program consists of 2 weekly 90-minutes group classes at week 1 and week 2. In the earlier section of the class (45 minutes), a nurse will deliver knowledge and information in regard to healthy lifestyle such as healthy eating and exercise. The latter section of the class (45 minutes), knowledge and skills required for a proper exercise regime will be demonstrated by a nurses and a exercise trainer. The nurse will meet participants individually in the intervention group during (week 5) and after (week 14) the health promotion program for a 15mins health counseling. A telephone reminder will also be made by the nurse to remind participants on healthy lifestyle and provide opportunities for asking questions at week 8 and week 10. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The usual care group will receive a 15mins general health education on healthy eating and exercise that is consistent with public health campaigns individually by a nurse at week 5 (DH, HKSAR, 2011).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>body weight will be measured to the nearest 0.1 kilogram using an electronic weight scale by a research assisstant</outcome>
      <timepoint>week 1, week 5, and week 14</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist Circumference will be measured to the nearest 0.1 centimeter using a measuring tape at the level of iliac crest with normal expiration by a research assisstant</outcome>
      <timepoint>week 1, week 5, and week 14</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-promoting behaviors will be assessed using the Health-Promoting Lifestyle Profile II Chinese version in the format of a questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>week 1, week 5, and week 14</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood Pressure will be taken using an calibrated electric blood pressure monitor by a research assisstant</outcome>
      <timepoint>week 1, week 5, and week 14</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting blood glucose will be obtain using the glucose oxidase method serum essay analysis performed in a qualified laboratory. </outcome>
      <timepoint>week 1 and week 14</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lipid profile [(Fasting Triglycerides, Total cholesterol, LDL-C (low-density lipoprotein Cholesterol) and HDL-C (high-density lipoprotein Cholesterol)] will be obtain using serum essay analysis performed in a qualified laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>week 1 and week 14</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of physical activity will be measured by using the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (Chinese version short-form) in the format of a questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>week 1, week 5, and week 14</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults living in the community between the ages of 18 to 65, with two or more risk factors identified for Metabolic syndrome as specified according to the harmonized criteria published by AHA (Alberti et al., 2009).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants unable to read or speak Chinese, with known CVD, uncontrolled chronic diseases conditions, contraindications for exercise such as musculoskeletal diseases and neurovascular diseases, or had recent (&lt;12 months) participation in other health promotion program will be excluded. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment of samples will be done by convenience sampling through community centers. Half of these centers were randomly allocated to the intervention group using a computer-generated randomization. Allocation is not concealed due to the study design that involves recruitment at the cluster-level. Potential participants will be contacted by the researcher and received basic health screening to verify status of MS. After obtaining written consents, eligible participants meeting the inclusion and exclusion criteria will be recruited. </concealment>
    <sequence>computer-generated randomization at cluster level</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Cluster-randomized</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>All statistical analyses will be performed using the commercial statistical package SPSS 19.0 and a significance level of 0.05 will be considered statistically significant. Descriptive statistics such as percentages, means, medians, standard deviations will be used to present the demographics of the participants along with their 95% confidence intervals. Pearson or Spearmans correlation and Chi-square statistics will be used to examine the relationships between continuous and categorical variables respectively. Repeated measures ANOVA will be used to test the difference among matched outcomes across time. Independent t-test and Mann Whitney U tests will be used for investigating the intervention effects according to the measurement scales. All analyses shall be done according to intention-to-treat principle. Where appropriate, multiple regressions will be used to explore correlations across variables according to the modified HBM. 

The estimated sample size will be based on previous literature considering the detected differences between the intervention and control group on the outcomes of this proposed study.  Being conservative, the expected change shall have a medium effect size of 0.5 and the attrition rate shall be approximately 20%. Therefore, a minimum of 80 participants in each group will be needed in order to detect differences between two groups on 80% power at 0.05 significance level </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/06/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/06/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>17/05/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>17/05/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>160</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>183</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Lo Wai Sze</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>8/F, Esther Lee Building, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Sha Tin, NT, Hong Kong</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Hong Kong</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hong Kong Health Check Charity Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>4/F, Town Health Technology Centre, 10-12 Yuen Shun Circuit, Siu Lek Yuen, Shatin</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Hong Kong</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Metabolic syndrome (MetS) has drawn increasing attention among clinicians and health care researchers in the past years around the globe. The syndrome indicated the state a person experiencing a group of metabolic risk factors, which include impaired glucose intolerance; elevated fasting triglycerides (TG); decreased fasting high-density lipoprotein cholesterol; elevated blood pressure; and central obesity (Alberti et al., 2009; Grundy et al., 2005). As indicated by American Heart Association (AHA), risk factors of MetS include central obesity, practice of atherogenic diet, and physical inactivity. Current guideline from AHA suggested that individuals with MetS at their pre-morbid state should be first manifested to lifestyle modifications including diet management and increase in physical activity (Grundy et al., 2005; Stone and Saxon, 2005).  
	The aim of this study is to examine the effect of a health promotion program on health outcomes and health-promoting behavior of community-dwelling adults with MetS in Hong Kong. Recruitment will be carried out in the community centers and eligible participants meeting the inclusion and exclusion criteria will be randomly assigned to either the intervention group or the control group. The estimated sample size will be 80 in each group.
	The intervention group will receive a 14-week health promotion program targeting on lifestyle changes. The program consists of 2 weekly 90-minutes group classes at week 1 and week 2. In the earlier section of the class (45 minutes), a nurse will deliver knowledge and information in regard to healthy lifestyle such as healthy eating and exercise. The latter section of the class (45 minutes), knowledge and skills required for a proper exercise regime will be demonstrated by a nurses and a exercise trainer. The nurse will meet participants in the intervention group during (week 5) and after (week 14) the health promotion program for health counseling. A telephone reminder will also be made to remind participants on healthy lifestyle and provide opportunities for asking questions at week 8 and week 10.  Telephone reminders will also be made to remind participants on healthy lifestyle and provide opportunities for asking questions. The usual care group will receive general health education on healthy eating and exercise that is consistent with public health campaigns (DH, HKSAR, 2011).
	Anthropometric and behavioral assessments will be collected at baseline (T0), after the intervention (T1), and at 14-week (T2) upon the particpnat's enrollment in this study. Anthropometric data on body height, body weight, waist circumference, blood pressure, and body fat composition will be measured at all three data collection time (T0, T1, and T2). Blood tests on fasting blood glucose and fasting lipids will only be measured at the beginning (T0) and at the end of the study (T2) to evaluate effectiveness of the intervention. Behavioral outcomes will be measured at all three data collection time to assess changes in health-promoting behavior using a questionnaire (T0, T1, and T2). 
	This study will provide explicit information on understanding the health beliefs of people with MetS. Moreover, the designed health promotion program will add foundation for future practice on primary preventive care for people at high risk of CVD.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Joint Chinese University of Hong Kong – New Territories East Cluster Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Joint CUHK-NTEC Clinical Research Ethics Committee
8/F, Lui Che Woo Clinical Sciences Building,
Prince of Wales Hospital
Shatin, Hong Kong</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/05/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Hong Kong</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lo Wai Sze</name>
      <address>8/F Esther Lee Building, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Sha Tin, NT</address>
      <phone>+852 39434335</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sallylows@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lo Wai Sze</name>
      <address>8/F Esther Lee Building, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Sha Tin, NT</address>
      <phone>+852 39434335</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sallylows@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lo Wai Sze</name>
      <address>8/F Esther Lee Building, The Chinese University of Hong Kong, Sha Tin, NT</address>
      <phone>+852 39434335</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sallylows@cuhk.edu.hk</email>
      <country>Hong Kong</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>