<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366469">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000635662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of whey proteins for the treatment of atopic dermatitis: A pilot study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effectiveness of Glycomax 'trademark' Lactoferrin and bovine whey-derived Ig-rich fraction for the treatment of atopic dermatitis: A pilot study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Atopic Dermatitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dermatological conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Allergies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Daily oral supplementation for 56 days with a combined 250mg each of bovine whey derived Glycomax 'trademark' lactoferrin and bovine whey-Ig rich fraction or a Placebo, both in tablet form.

Each participant will also be provided with a hypoallergenic sorbolene cream (Dermeze Sensitive Cream) for the relief of dryness as required at their discretion.

Supplements and the Dermeze cream will be collected at the end of the study for assessing adherence.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo supplement (mannitol and calcium carbonate based tablets) in tablet form.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The severity of eczema symptoms measured by SCORAD (SCORing Atopic Dermatitis). SCORAD is a clinical tool used to assess the extent and severity of eczema. It is validated for determining severity of eczema and will be utilised by a consultant dermatologist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Scoring will occur at baseline and then every two weeks for eight weeks (day 56) followed by further assessment four weeks after supplementation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PO-SCORAD: The Patient Orientated SCORAD is a tool to self-evaluate atopic dermatitis. </outcome>
      <timepoint>PO-SCORAD will be undertaken at baseline and then every two weeks during a clinic visit for eight weeks (day 56 of supplementation) and then four weeks following the end of supplementation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skin dermatographism test: This clinical test involves applying physical pressure (scratch) to determine if an allergic-like reaction occurs (dermatographism).  Symptoms of dermatographism, a rare skin condition, are thought to be caused by mast cells in the surface of the skin releasing histamines without the presence of antigens, causing the skin to swell in the affected areas. The weak membrane of the mast cells easily and rapidly breaks down under physical pressure causing an allergic-like reaction, in general a red weal (welt) to appear on the skin. This simple test will be performed by a clinician or nurse.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The skin dermatographism test will be undertaken at baseline, week 8 (end of supplementation) and four weeks following the cessation of supplementation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Full blood count and white cell differential. Cell count will be done on a routine haematology analyser at a pathology laboratory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood will be drawn at baseline, week 2, Week 4, week 6, week 8 and week 12.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood and skin CD4+T cell subsets determined by flow cytometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>A blood sample and a skin biopsy will be collected at baseline, week 8 (end of supplementation) and four weeks following cessation of supplementation. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum inflammatory markers, including C-reactive protein, erythrocyte sedimentation rate, IgE, and Th17 cytokines (IL-1beta, IL-4, lL-6, IL-10, IL-17A, IL-17F, IL-21, IL-22, IL-23, IL-25, IL-31, IL-33, IFN-gamma, sCD40L, TNF-a, IL-17A/F (singleplex only). The markers will be determined by immunoassay or bead array.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples will be collected at baseline, week 4, week8 and week 12.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Presence of atopic dermatitis according to physician diagnosis using SCORAD</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1	is lactose intolerant
2	consumes fish oil, probiotics, prebiotics, whey protein supplements during the trial period
3	requires insulin use (for treatment of diabetes) 
4	has history of liver, kidney or thyroid disease
5	uses anti-inflammatory or immune-modulating medications
6	has heavy alcohol consumption
7	is pregnant or intends to become pregnant
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects will be randomly allocated. Allocation will be concealed as eligibility will be undertaken prior to allocation and the individual conducting the allocation procedure will be independent to those assessing for eligibility. Subjects will also be assigned to groups identified by code that does not reveal the group to which the person was assigned.</concealment>
    <sequence>Sequence generation will be conducted through a simple randomisation computer-based program</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>As a pilot study this will have 30 participants in the treatment arm and 15 participants in the control arm</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The approach will be a repeated measures within group analysis to ascertain the mean effect and 95% confidence intervals of the intervention. Effects in the placebo group will be used to examine underlying changes in the severity of eczema over the study period.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>19/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>5/06/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kessels Road, Nathan, QLD 4111</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Probiotec Pharma Pty Lttd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>83 Cherry Lane North Laverton VIC 3026</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Probiotec Pharma Pty Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>83 Cherry Lane, Laverton North, Victoria 3026</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to investigate the effectiveness of daily supplementation with Glycomax 'trademark' Lactoferrin and
bovine whey-derived Ig-rich fraction on symptoms of atopic dermatitis. The study is a double-blind placebo-controlled parallel trial and consists of two phases, a 56 day supplement period followed by a four week post supplement follow up. The study group will consist of both male and females adults (n=45). Participants will range in age from 18-60 years with a confirmed diagnosis of atopic dermatitis made by a dermatologist.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.griffith.edu.au/health/griffith-health/research</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Griffith University, Nathan, QLD, 4111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MED/09/14/HREC</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Allan Cripps</name>
      <address>Griffith Health Centre, Griffith University, Gold Coast Campus, Parklands, QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5678 0809</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>allan.cripps@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicholas west</name>
      <address>Griffith Health Centre, Griffith University, Gold Coast Campus, Parklands, QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>61419649447</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.west@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicholas west</name>
      <address>Griffith Health Centre, Griffith University, Gold Coast Campus, Parklands, QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>61419649447</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.west@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nicholas west</name>
      <address>Griffith Health Centre, Griffith University, Gold Coast Campus, Parklands, QLD 4222</address>
      <phone>61419649447</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>n.west@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>