<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369341">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001041549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of  an outpatient exercise training programme on haemodynamics and cardiac magnetic resonance parameters of right ventricular function in patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of  an outpatient exercise training programme on haemodynamics and cardiac magnetic resonance parameters of right ventricular function in patients with pulmonary arterial hypertension.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1174-5625</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ExPAH</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil
</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pulmonary arterial hypertension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases of the vasculature and circulation including the lymphatic system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Outpatient rehabilitation exercise training program. 
a) This involves participants attending a physiotherapy department for an exercise training programme.
b) Sessions are twice weekly for 12 weeks (i.e. total of 24 sessions).
c) Each session runs for one hour.
d) Sessions are run by physiotherapist.
e) Exercises involve: aerobic training (treadmill or cycle), respiratory muscle training and light weight training
f) intensity of Borg RPE of 12-13.
g) Format is small group (maximum of 5 participants to one phyisotherapist).
h) Monitoring of adherence will be via record of attendance and exercises performed.

Participants randomised to the training group will also have 3 structured telephone education sessions with the study psychologist (of 20 minutes duration each). These sessions will include education on managing hyperventilation, anxiety during dyspnea, and skills training (progressive muscle relaxation). These will be done at approximately week3, 6 and 9.

In addition, Sydney based participants will have the option of undergoing an exercise right heart catheterisation (RHC). These participants will have exactly the same outcome measures and undergo the same randomisation process. They will have haemodynamics, measured by RHC at rest and during exercise. The only difference is that after the initial standard haemodynamic measurements, the participant is asked to pedal at a certain work rate (for example, 60 rpm). The workload is then increased by 10W every 3 minutes, as tolerated by the participant, to a maximum of 40W, as described by Provencher, S., et al., Changes in exercise haemodynamics during treatment in pulmonary arterial hypertension. Eur Respir J, 2008. 32(2): p. 393-8.
Participants for this sub-study will be voluntary (all participants to the study based in Sydney will be asked if they wish to participate in the sub-study).</interventions>
    <comparator>Home exercise program. Participants in the control group will be given a handout informing them of the benefits of regular exercise, and suggestion of walking (5 days per week for 30 minutes total per day). Suggestions on how to keep motivated (e.g. join Heart Foundation Walking group) as well as diary record provided. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Right ventricular ejection fraction on cardiac MRI.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post start of intervention (exercise).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Haemodynamics, measured by right heart catheterisation at rest, and during exercise in the sub-study participants.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post start of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exercise capacity measured by 6MWT.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post start of intervention and 6 months post start of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life measured by CAMPHOR, DASS 21 and Lawton's Instrumental Activities of Daily Living.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 6 months post start of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscle strength, tested by grip strength.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 6 months post start of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Bio markers of cardiac function, measured by NT-proBNP, IL6.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 and 6 months post start of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pulmonary arterial hypertension, functional class I-III.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Change in PAH specific medication in preceding 3 months.
Enrolment in formal exercise program in preceding 3 months.
Pregnancy.
Unable to follow instructions.
Patients with significant unstable cardiac disease (e.g. unstable angina).
Patients who are unable to have MRI (impaired renal function, permanent pacemaker etc).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants with PAH will be recruited, screened and once consent is obtained, will undergo baseline assessment. After baseline assessment, participants will be randomised to intervention (Exercise group) or control group (home exercise program). Participants will not be blind to their allocation, however, staff involved with outcome measures will be blinded. Allocation concealment will occur, as allocation to the study group will be done at a central administration site by computer randomisation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised after their baseline visit, prior to the intervention. This will be done by adaptive minimisation, stratified by site and whether the participant has connective tissue disease associated Pulmonary arterial hypertension (CTD-aPAH), by a biostatistician external to the research project using a custom written program in SAS (Cary, North Carolina, USA). The participant will be randomised to either control (home exercise program) or the intervention (exercise group). </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome measure will be right ventricular ejection fraction (RVEF) measured by cardiac MRI. Power calculations are based on comparison of randomised arms achieving the primary outcome of an increase in RVEF. We consider a 5% absolute excess increase in RVEF, measured by cMRI, for the intervention group compared to the control group as the desired clinically important effect. Using two-sided normal test, allowing for potential 10% drop out rate, 26 patients in each arm are required to detect a 5% excess increased RVEF associated with intervention versus control group with a power of 80%.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>5/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>52</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Darlinghurst) - Darlinghurst</hospital>
    <hospital>Coffs Harbour Base Hospital - Coffs Harbour</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>St Vincent's Hospital Sydney.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>390 Victoria St, Darlinghurst, Sydney. NSW, 2010.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mid North Coast Local Health District</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Coffs Harbour Health Campus,
345 Pacific Highway, 
Coffs Harbour, NSW, 2450.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Actelion</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>ACTELION Pharmaceuticals Australia
Suite 6
13b Narabang Way
Belrose NSW 2085</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Eugene Kotlyar</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>St Vincent's Hospital 
390 Victoria St
Darlinghurst, NSW, 2010.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Associate Professor Steven Faux</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Sacred Heart Rehabilitation
170 Darlinghurst Rd,
Darlinghurst, NSW, 2010.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Karen Chia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of New South Wales Rural Clinical School,
Locked Bag 812,
Coffs Harbour, NSW 2450.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study looks at the effect of an outpatient exercise program on how the heart functions, using the latest technology (cardiac magnetic resonance imaging) and more established indicators of prognosis measured by right heart catheterisation. It also examines the effect of exercise on patient endurance and quality of life. The results of this study will have important widespread implications for the outpatient treatment of PAH, providing guidance regarding the optimal format of exercise in patients with PAH. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>390 Victoria St,
Darlinghurst, NSW, 2010.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/SVH/340 and HREC/14/SVH/341</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karen Chia</name>
      <address>Mid North Coast Rehabilitation
PO Box 6307,
Coffs Harbour, NSW 2450.</address>
      <phone>+61 414 754 976</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.chia@me.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karen Chia</name>
      <address>Mid North Coast Rehabilitation
PO Box 6307
Coffs Harbour, NSW, 2450.</address>
      <phone>+61 414 754 976</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.chia@me.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karen Chia</name>
      <address>Mid North Coast Rehabilitation
PO Box 6307
Coffs Harbour, NSW, 2450.</address>
      <phone>+61 414 754 976</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.chia@me.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Karen Chia</name>
      <address>PO Box 6307
Coffs Harbour, NSW, 2450.</address>
      <phone>+414 754 976</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>