<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363822">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000311752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Moving from policy to practice: A randomised trial of an implementation intervention to facilitate the adoption of a statewide healthy canteen policy in government primary schools. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Are school canteens that receive an intense intervention (consisting of face-to-face, telephone &amp; print support) more likely than school canteens that receive no intervention to improve their school canteen menus that are consistent with Fresh Tastes @ School- the NSW Healthy Canteen Policy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity Prevention</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Public Health- Health Promotion/ Education
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diet and Nutrition- Obesity
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will include the following evidence based components:
1. Executive support from school principals and the school sector
2. Consensus processes to develop an implementation strategy.
3. Training  of canteen and school staff. 
4. Tools and resources including printed instructional materials, sample policies, planning templates, pricing guides, product lists of policy compliant menu items, and supplier contacts
5. Academic detailing School canteen visits will be conducted to assist Canteen Managers assess and categorise menu items, to demonstrate canteen management, pricing and promotion strategies and to help problem solve barriers to policy implementation.  
6. Recognition and promotion- promotion of schools making positive changes to their school canteen menus.
7. Performance monitoring and feedback Project records will be used to compile quarterly feedback reports regarding adoption progress of intervention schools.  
8. On-going support - Schools will be provided ongoing support contacts at least monthly (via email, telephone or in person) for 12 months to review progress, discuss deficits identified from self -monitoring; &amp; facilitate problem solving.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual support - consisting of standard teacher development opportunities regarding healthy eating and physical activity programs in schools which could include staff training or resources.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of schools with a canteen menu containing foods or beverages prohibited (red and banned items) under the Fresh Tastes @ School policy </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months later</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of schools where healthy canteen items  represent the majority (&gt;50%) of products listed on the menu as recommended by the Fresh Tastes @ school policy. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months later </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The mean total fat, sodium and energy per student, purchased at the school canteen 
A count of all canteen products being sold during canteen service at recess and lunch times will be made. The total fat, sodium and energy of each item will be recorded based on information provided on product labels, or for fresh foods, estimates will be made by Dietitians using food data-bases.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 12 months later</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>A random selection of Government primary schools within the Hunter Region of NSW, with a school canteen, will be invited to participate. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Schools from the Catholic or Independent Schools Association will be ineligible as implementation of the Fresh Tastes @ School canteen policy is not mandated for such schools. Schools with secondary students (central schools), catering exclusively for children requiring specialist care, and schools without a canteen will also be ineligible. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Schools from the Catholic or Independent Schools Association will be ineligible as implementation of the Fresh Tastes @ School canteen policy is not mandated for such schools. Schools with secondary students (central schools), catering exclusively for children requiring specialist care, and schools without a canteen will also be ineligible. </concealment>
    <sequence>Schools will be randomly allocated after baseline data collection in a 1:1 ratio to either an intervention or control group by an independent statistician using a computerised random number function. A block randomisation procedure will be employed to ensure group allocation is equal. The procedure will be stratified based on the socioeconomic area of school locality given evidence of an association between the socioeconomic area of the school and the trial outcome</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A total of 35 intervention and 35 control schools will be recruited. Trial outcomes will be assessed by comparing between group differences at follow-up in the i) the proportion of schools with a canteen menu containing foods or beverages prohibited from regular sale (red and banned items) and; ii) the proportion of schools where healthy canteen items represent the majority (&gt;50%) of products listed on the menu using Chi-square tests under an intention to treat approach. Baseline values will be carried forward for schools not providing follow-up data. Based on previous recruitment experiences of the research team in this setting 80% of participating schools will be retained at follow-up. Assuming a prevalence of 15% at follow-up in the comparison group for both primary trial outcomes, the sample will be sufficient to detect an absolute difference of 30% with 80% power and an alpha of 0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>5/08/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>20/09/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>70</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>70</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2259 - Wyee</postcode>
    <postcode>2264 - Bonnells Bay</postcode>
    <postcode>2265 - Cooranbong</postcode>
    <postcode>2267 - Wangi Wangi</postcode>
    <postcode>2278 - Barnsley</postcode>
    <postcode>2280 - Belmont</postcode>
    <postcode>2281 - Blacksmiths</postcode>
    <postcode>2282 - Warners Bay</postcode>
    <postcode>2283 - Arcadia Vale</postcode>
    <postcode>2284 - Argenton</postcode>
    <postcode>2285 - Cardiff</postcode>
    <postcode>2286 - West Wallsend</postcode>
    <postcode>2287 - Elermore Vale</postcode>
    <postcode>2289 - Adamstown</postcode>
    <postcode>2290 - Charlestown</postcode>
    <postcode>2291 - Merewether</postcode>
    <postcode>2292 - Broadmeadow</postcode>
    <postcode>2293 - Wickham</postcode>
    <postcode>2295 - Stockton</postcode>
    <postcode>2297 - Tighes Hill</postcode>
    <postcode>2298 - Waratah</postcode>
    <postcode>2299 - Jesmond</postcode>
    <postcode>2300 - Newcastle</postcode>
    <postcode>2303 - Hamilton</postcode>
    <postcode>2304 - Mayfield</postcode>
    <postcode>2305 - New Lambton</postcode>
    <postcode>2306 - Windale</postcode>
    <postcode>2307 - Shortland</postcode>
    <postcode>2312 - Minimbah</postcode>
    <postcode>2315 - Nelson Bay</postcode>
    <postcode>2316 - Anna Bay</postcode>
    <postcode>2317 - Salamander Bay</postcode>
    <postcode>2318 - Medowie</postcode>
    <postcode>2319 - Lemon Tree Passage</postcode>
    <postcode>2320 - Maitland</postcode>
    <postcode>2321 - Lochinvar</postcode>
    <postcode>2322 - Beresfield</postcode>
    <postcode>2323 - East Maitland</postcode>
    <postcode>2324 - Raymond Terrace</postcode>
    <postcode>2325 - Cessnock</postcode>
    <postcode>2327 - Kurri Kurri</postcode>
    <postcode>2333 - Muswellbrook</postcode>
    <postcode>2334 - Greta</postcode>
    <postcode>2335 - Branxton</postcode>
    <postcode>2337 - Scone</postcode>
    <postcode>2420 - Dungog</postcode>
    <postcode>2289 - Garden Suburb</postcode>
    <postcode>2282 - Eleebana</postcode>
    <postcode>2290 - Whitebridge</postcode>
    <postcode>2285 - Glendale</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hunter New England Population Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Locked Bag 10
Wallsend NSW 2287</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The adoption of healthy school canteen policies has been recommended as a strategy to prevent excessive weight gain. A number of jurisdictions in Australia and internationally have policies requiring school adoption of healthy canteen strategies. Despite this, internationally, schools have failed to adopt healthy canteen practices consistent with such policies. If the benefits of obesity prevention initiatives are to be realised, policies recommended to prevent overweight must be implemented. However, research measuring the effectiveness of interventions to facilitate widespread implementation of health promoting policies and practices in schools is limited. The aim of the research is to assess the effectiveness of a population wide implementation intervention in increasing canteen practices consistent with the mandatory NSW government healthy canteen policy (Fresh Tastes @ School). The study will employ a randomised trial design. Seventy primary schools will be randomised to receive a 12 month intervention, or a no intervention comparison group.  The effectiveness of the intervention will be determined by comparing post intervention differences between canteen menus audited by Dietitians in: i) the proportion of schools with a canteen menu containing foods or beverages restricted (red items) under the policy and; ii) the proportion of schools where healthy canteen items (green) represent the majority (&gt;50%) of products listed on the menu as recommended by the policy. The proposed research will be the first RCT of its kind, addresses a questions of particular policy relevance and will make an important contribution to reducing the burden of obesity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Wolfenden L, Nathan N, Sutherland R, Williams C, Wiggers J, Gillham K, Bell AC, Freund M, Campbell L, Asmar M. A randomised controlled trial of a school-based intervention to increase the implementation of a healthy canteen policy in Australian primary schools: study protocol for the (PICNIC) trial. Implementation Science. 2014 vol 9; 147

Outcome papers are under review</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag No. 1
New Lambton NSW 2305
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06/07/26/4.04</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>NSW Department of Education and Communities SERAP</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3
1 Oxford St
Darlinghurst NSW 2010
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012277</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Luke Wolfenden</name>
      <address>Locked Bag 10
Wallsend NSW 2287  
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4924 6567  </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4924 6215  </fax>
      <email>luke.wolfenden@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Luke Wolfenden</name>
      <address>Locked Bag 10
Wallsend NSW 2287  
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4924 6567  </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4924 6215 </fax>
      <email>luke.wolfenden@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Luke Wolfenden</name>
      <address>Locked Bag 10
Wallsend NSW 2287  
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4924 6567  </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4924 6215 </fax>
      <email>luke.wolfenden@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Nicole Nathan</name>
      <address>Locked Bag 10
Wallsend NSW 2287  
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4924 6257</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4924 6215 </fax>
      <email>Nicole.Nathan@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>