<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368400">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000503527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Periostin as a predictor of severe exacerbations in asthma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study to determine periostin as a predictor of severe exacerbations in asthma in adult asthmatics</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1167-8494 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>PER09</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Serum periostin levels in adult asthmatics will be measured at a single visit via a specific periostin assay.  The periostin level will be compared to a sample taken at the baseline assessment, when the participant attended the Medical Research Insitute for the New Zealand Respiratory Health Survey (NZRHS) study and the Longitudinal study of periostin levels in asthma (PER02), occurring 1 to 5 years ago.</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A - observational study</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between serum periostin and severe asthma exacerbations in adult asthmatics.  The details of asthma exacerbations will be collected from participants directly via the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire, as well as consulting their General Practitioner (GP) and hospital medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Both serum periostin and the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire will be performed on Day 1 at the enrollment visit.  GP and hospital medical records will be assessed retrospectively starting from the date of their first visit at the Medical Research Institute to the date of their reassessment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between serum periostin and the number of hospitalisations or Emergency Department (ED) attendances because of asthma, requiring systemic corticosteroids.  This information will be gathered via the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire as well as consulting participant's GP and hospital medical records.

This exacerbation outcome is measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the New Zealand Respiratory Health Questionnaire (NZRHS) and periostin 2 (PER02) studies to the time of reassessment, between 1 and 5 years later.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between serum periostin and the number of courses of systemic corticosteroids taken.  This information will be gathered via the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire as well as consulting participant's GP and hospital medical records.

This exacerbation outcome is measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment, between 1 and 5 years later.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between serum periostin and changes in asthma treatment (in accordance with stepwise approach to asthma treatment in Global Initiative for Asthma (GINA) guidelines).  This information will be gathered via the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire as well as consulting participant's GP and hospital medical records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between serum periostin and change in Forced Expired Volume in 1 second (FEV1) (ml/year) between the baseline measurement in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment in PER09.  FEV1 will be measured via spirometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between blood eosinophil count and the number of severe exacerbations of asthma per unit time.  The blood eosinophil count will be measured from blood sample taken during the visit.  This exacerbation outcome is measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment, between 1 and 5 years later.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between blood eosinophil count and the number of hospitalisations or ED attendances because of asthma, requiring systemic corticosteroids.  This exacerbation outcome is measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment, between 1 and 5 years later.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between blood eosinophil count and the number of courses of systemic steroids taken (prescribed or self-administered).  The number of courses of systemic steroids taken by a participant is obtained from their answers to the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire and through consulting their GP and hospital medical records.  This exacerbation outcome is measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment, between 1 and 5 years later.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exploratory outcomes analysing relationships between periostin levels and unspecified immune mediated biomarkers, as measured by laboratory assays</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exploratory outcomes analysing relationships between periostin levels and deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) profiles, as measured by laboratory assays.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between blood eosinophil count and changes in asthma treatment (in accordance with stepwise approach to asthma treatment in GINA guidelines), measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment between 1 and 5 years later.

Changes in asthma treatment will be determined from the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire as well as consulting the participant's GP and hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between blood eosinophil count and the change in FEV1 (ml/yr), measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment between 1 and 5 years later.  

Blood eosinophil count will be measured by laboratory assay.  FEV1 will be measured via spirometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between serum IgE and the number of severe exacerbations of asthma, measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment between 1 and 5 years later.  

Serum IgE will be analysed using standard laboratory assay and be collected via a blood sample.

The number of exacerbations of asthma will be obtained from the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire as well as consulting the participant's GP and hospital records.  

Severe exacerbations of asthma are defined as the use of systemic corticosteroids for at least 3 consecutive days; or hospitalisation or ED attendances because of asthma, requiring systemic corticosteroids.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between serum IgE and the number of hospitalisations or ED attendances because of asthma, requiring systemic corticosteroids.  This exacerbation outcome is measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment, between 1 and 5 years later.

The number of number of hospitalisations or ED attendances because of asthma will be obtained from the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire as well as consulting the participant's GP and hospital records.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between serum IgE levels and the number of courses of systemic steroids taken (prescribed or self-administered).  This exacerbation outcome is measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment, between 1 and 5 years later.

The number of number of courses of systemic corticosteroids will be obtained from the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire as well as consulting the participant's GP and hospital records.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between serum IgE and changes in asthma treatment (in accordance with stepwise approach to asthma treatment in GINA guidelines), measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment between 1 and 5 years later.

Changes in asthma treatment will be determined from the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire as well as consulting the participant's GP and hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between serum IgE and the change in FEV1 (ml/yr), measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment between 1 and 5 years later.  

Serum IgE will be measured by laboratory assay.  FEV1 will be measured via spirometry.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between FeNO and the number of severe exacerbations of asthma, measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment between 1 and 5 years later.  

The number of exacerbations of asthma will be obtained from the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire as well as consulting the participant's GP and hospital records.  

Severe exacerbations of asthma are defined as the use of systemic corticosteroids for at least 3 consecutive days; or hospitalisation or ED attendances because of asthma, requiring systemic corticosteroids.

FeNO levels will be measured using a nitrous oxide monitor (NIOX) according to the American Thoracic Society (ATS) guidelines, published in 2005.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between FeNO and the number of hospitalisations or ED attendances because of asthma, requiring systemic corticosteroids.  This exacerbation outcome is measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment, between 1 and 5 years later.

The number of number of hospitalisations or ED attendances because of asthma will be obtained from the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire as well as consulting the participant's GP and hospital records.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between FeNO and the number of courses of systemic steroids taken (prescribed or self-administered).  This exacerbation outcome is measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment, between 1 and 5 years later.

The number courses of systemic corticosteroids taken will be obtained from the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire as well as consulting the participant's GP and hospital records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between FENO  and changes in asthma treatment (in accordance with stepwise approach to asthma treatment in GINA guidelines), measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment between 1 and 5 years later.

Changes in asthma treatment will be determined from the Asthma Exacerbation Questionnaire as well as consulting the participant's GP and hospital records. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The association between FENO and the change in FEV1 (ml/yr), measured from the time of the baseline assessment in the NZRHS and PER02 studies to the time of reassessment between 1 and 5 years later. 

FeNO levels will be measured using a nitrous oxide monitor (NIOX) and FEV1 will be measured using spirometry, according to the American Thoracic Society (ATS) guidelines, published in 2005.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The associations between serum periostin and serum immunoglobulin type E (IgE) as markers of asthma severity.  IgE will be measured by laboratory assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The associations between serum periostin and fractional exhaled nitrous oxide (FeNO) as markers of asthma severity.  FeNO levels will be measured using a nitrous oxide monitor (NIOX) according the American Thoracic Society guidelines, published in 2005.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The associations between serum periostin and blood eosinophil count as markers of asthma severity.  Blood eosinophil count will be measured by laboratory assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time of reassessment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants from:
-New Zealand Respiratory Health Survey (NZRHS) (ACTR number 12610000666022) phase two and 
-Longitudinal study of serum periostin levels in asthma (PER02)(ACTR number 12614000235606)
Able to perform written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>95</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Known pregnancy
-Surgery within last 3 months, determined at investigator discretion (this includes all major surgery requiring general anaesthetic, dental extractions and root canal procedures.  This does not include minor procedures including, but not limited to, mole or wart removal, dental fillings etc)
-Bone fracture within last 3 months
-Active (current, or within the 3 weeks prior to the visit) upper or lower respiratory tract infection
-Any other safety concern at the investigator's discretion</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>356 participants will be approached to take part in the study, based on the number of participants previously recruited from the NZRHS and PER02 studies.  Assuming a 35% attrition rate, it is envisaged that 230 participants will be enrolled into this study.

Statistical analyses:
Detailed data description using summary statistics, contingency tables, and plots will be used for both the explanatory and response variables including, where appropriate, descriptions of change with time. Our experience with analysis of Periostin, FeNO, and serum IgE, are they are typically highly skew and better analysed on the logarithm transformed scale.

For illustrative purposes data descriptions based on tertiles will also be calculated.

The statistical analysis will be appropriate to the response variable data type.
For the response variables treated as counts (exacerbations, hospital or ED admissions, and courses of steroids) this will be by Poisson regression with an offset for the time observation. It is possible that most of the participants will have no or only one count of a response variable and in this case it may be simpler to analyse the associations using logistic regression, using levels of none versus any.
For the response variable treated as continuous, FEV1, regression will be used, including the baseline FEV1 as a covariate.
For the response variable treated as ordinal, GINA asthma step, proportional odds (ordinal) regression will be used. If in the event there are mainly two asthma step levels achieved it may be simpler to analyse associations using logistic regression with GINA asthma step as a two level response variable.
Periostin will be used as an explanatory variable in both univariate and multivariate analyses.
In the univariate analyses, Periostin or logarithm Periostin, will be used as the sole explanatory variable
The other Th2-related variables: eosinophil count, IgE, and FeNO, will also be used in univariate analyses with each as a sole explanatory variable
Finally multivariate models will be estimated with all of eosinophil count, IgE, and FeNO, to explore if Periostin adds important explanatory power to prediction of poor asthma outcomes.

This is an exploratory analysis with a large number of statistical tests and although 95% confidence intervals, corresponding to a two-sided type I error rate of 5%, will be used, results will be interpreted cautiously because of multiple statistical testing and uncertainty as to what, for some variables, might constitute a clinically meaningful association.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/12/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>28/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/06/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>230</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>212</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/12/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/01/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand
Level 7 CSB, Wellington Hospital
Riddiford Street
Newtown
Wellington 6021</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Genentech, Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Genentech, Inc.
1 DNA Way, South San Francisco,
CA 94080 - 4490
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Levels of POSTN (periostin coding gene, also known as osteoblast specific factor) gene expression and periostin have been measured in a number of tissues and disease states, including asthma.  As yet, an incomplete picture is currently available on the role and effects of periostin level in the blood, however it has shown promise as a biomarker for asthma severity and a marker of inflammation levels, being easy to measure through a simple blood test.  This study will assess the use of periostin as a predictor of severe asthma exacerbations in pre-existing cohorts of adults with a diagnosis of asthma and compare this to currently used markers such as blood eosinophil counts, serum IgE and FeNO.  The cohorts include patients across a range of disease severity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central HDEC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Health and Disability Ethics Committees
Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/03/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>15/CEN/33</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368400-HDEC Letter 15CEN33 Approved FULL Application.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard Beasley</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand, Private Bag 7902, Wellington, 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0147</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>richard.beasley@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruth Semprini</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand, Private Bag 7902, Wellington, 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ruth.semprini@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruth Semprini</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand, Private Bag 7902, Wellington, 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ruth.semprini@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ruth Semprini</name>
      <address>Medical Research Institute of New Zealand, Private Bag 7902, Wellington, 6242</address>
      <phone>+64 4 805 0232</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ruth.semprini@mrinz.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>