<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371507">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001317482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of manual therapy and exercise on age-dependent lung function: a randomised controlled trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of manual therapy and exercise on age-dependent lung function: a randomised controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1187-6962</utrn>
    <trialacronym>The MELT trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Lung function</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the respiratory system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention groups:
Group 1: Exercise
Group 2: Thoracic mobilisation + exercise
Group 3: Thoracic manipulation + exercise

Exercise will involve a standardised 10 minute treadmill walking program at a speed and inclination that is considered 'comfortable' for the participant. 

Thoracic mobilisation will involve soft tissue therapy followed by a joint mobilisation protocol administered to the muscles of the posterior chest wall and the thoracic spine T2-T12), costo-vertebral and costo-transverse joints (2nd-10th) respectively. This protocol will include 5 minutes of soft tissue therapy to the muscles of the posterior chest wall followed by 5 repetitions of joint mobilisation (Maitland Grades III-IV) in each of the following 4 directions: flexion/extension, left and right rotation, left and right transverse, and left and right ribs. The total time for a mobilisation session is 15 minutes.  
     
Thoracic manipulation will involve soft tissue therapy followed by a joint manipulation protocol administered to the muscles of the posterior chest wall and the thoracic spine T2-T12), costo-vertebral and costo-transverse joints (2nd-10th) respectively. This protocol will include 5 minutes of soft tissue therapy to the muscles of the posterior chest wall followed by 2 manipulations (Maitland Grade V) administered to the upper/middle and middle/lower thoracic spine and ribs. Each manipulation will be administered as a 'group' manipulation that involves multiple thoracic inter-vertebral, cost-vertebral and costo-transverse joints The total time for a mobilisation session is 15 minutes.  

A register of attendance at the intervention sessions (exercise, mobilisation and manipulation) will be kept for each participant.
     
Masters of Osteopathy interns will deliver mobilisation and manipulation intervention.
Master of Clinical Exercise Physiology interns will supervise exercise performance.

All three interventions will be administered 6 times over a 3 week period @ 2 times per week.

The trial will be conducted in Southern Cross University's Lismore and Gold Coast Health Clinics.


</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator/Control group.
Group 1: Exercise 
Standardised exercise regime.

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in lung function as measured by spirometry.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
3 weeks (end of intervention)
6 weeks (3 weeks post-intervention)
9 weeks (6 weeks post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in chest expansion as measured by tape measure.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
3 weeks (end of intervention)
6 weeks (3 weeks post-intervention)
9 weeks (6 weeks post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in quality of life as measured by SF-36.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline
3 weeks (end of intervention)
6 weeks (3 weeks post-intervention)
9 weeks (6 weeks post-intervention)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Occurrence of adverse event following mobilisation or manipulation intervention. 
Known adverse events include localised muscle soreness and/or pain, restriction in movement, radiating pain or bone fracture. The presence of these will be assessed through self-reporting by participant in the study and confirmed on X-Ray where appropriate.    </outcome>
      <timepoint>Each of the 6 intervention sessions (weeks 1-3).
Sessions occur twice a week for 3 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i. No history of respiratory disease
ii. Currently non-smoking (preceding 6 months)
iii. Able to walk unaided and unassisted on a treadmill for 10 minutes
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>i. Inability to walk unaided and unassisted on a treadmill
ii. Contra-indication to thoracic manual therapy (mobilisation/manipulation)
        Osteoporosis
        Thoracic joint instability
        Acute pain on thoracic joint range of motion testing
        Below normal chest wall musculature for age and gender 
        High level of anxiety related to receiving thoracic spinal mobilisation or manipulation   
iii. Inability to understand English
iv. People with a cognitive impairment, an intellectual disability or a mental illness 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation.
Minimum clinically important difference in lung volume (FVC) = 200 ml
Standard deviation = 480ml (obtained from previous studies)
Power = 0.8 (80%)
Alpha = 0.05
Minimum sample size for two sample t-test = 92 per group 
Minimum cohort size (i.e. 3 groups) is 3 x 92 = 276
Assuming a drop-out rate = 10%
Minimum cohort size = 306 (3 Groups @ 102)

Statistical analysis plan
Data will be reported as group means, standard deviations and confidence intervals. Analysis will be performed as an ANCOVA for difference between groups with baseline as a covariate. Statistical significance will be set at p&lt;0.05. Missing data will be accounted for by using an intention-to-treat (ITT) analysis with data from subjects lost to follow-up imputed using the last observation carried forward method. The Number Needed to Treat (NNT) will be calculated using Benders method for confidence intervals.  
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>306</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>80</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/08/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2480 - Lismore</postcode>
    <postcode>4225 - Coolangatta</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Southern Cross University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 157
Lismore
NSW 2480</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Osteopathy Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>4/11 Railway St, Chatswood NSW 2067</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Macquarie University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Balaclava Road
North Ryde
NSW 2109</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Ageing is associated with a range of anatomical and physiological changes that include the respiratory system. These changes begin as early as 40 years of age and include stiffening of the spine and chest wall. This stiffening has an impact on breathing mechanics and is a cause of the progressive decline in lung function typically associated with ageing. The aim of this trial is to investigate whether reducing stiffness in the spine and chest wall improves lung function in people over 50 years of age. The trial is designed as a randomised controlled trial with 306 healthy people between the ages of 50 and 65 years randomly allocated to one of three equal groups. 
Group 1 (Control) will receive a standardised exercise program performed on a
treadmill. 
Group 2 will receive a mobilisation protocol designed to increase joint mobility in the
thoracic spine and ribs followed by the same exercise program. 
Group 3 will receive a manipulation protocol designed to increase joint mobility in the thoracic spine and ribs followed by the same exercise program. 
Each participant will receive six intervention sessions over a period of three weeks. Outcome measurements will be taken by assessors who are unaware of
the group a participant has been allocated to. They include non-invasive lung function
measurements, chest expansion and a respiratory function questionnaire. These
measurements will be taken on four occasions: before the first intervention (baseline), at the end of the intervention period (3 weeks), and then at 3 and 6 weeks post-intervention (i.e. in the 6th and 9th weeks of the trial). The last two measuring points are designed to assess whether the effects of intervention are ongoing. Lung function will be measured using spirometry (exhaling into a tube) and chest expansion measured using a tape measure. It is expected that manual therapy plus exercise will improve lung function more than exercise alone. It is also expected that improvements in lung function will be different for the two manual therapy interventions.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SCU Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 157
Lismore 
NSW 2480</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>ECN-16-211</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/07/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Research Hub, Building C5C East
Macquarie University
NSW 2109</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/06/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5201700554</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>4/05/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371507-Protocol Version 2 10 September 2016.docx</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371507-ECN-16-211 NEAF Approval.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371507-Consent Form.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371507-Information Sheet.doc</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Roger Engel</name>
      <address>Department of Chiropractic
Macquarie University
Building C5C, Room 354
Balaclava Road
North Ryde   NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 6387</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 9389</fax>
      <email>roger.engel@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Sandra Grace</name>
      <address>School of Health and Human Sciences
Southern Cross University
PO Box 157
Lismore   NSW 2480 </address>
      <phone>+61 2 6620 3646</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6620 3700</fax>
      <email>sandra.grace@scu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Roger Engel</name>
      <address>Department of Chiropractic
Macquarie University
Building C5C, Room 354
Balaclava Road
North Ryde   NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 6387</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 9389</fax>
      <email>roger.engel@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Roger Engel</name>
      <address>Department of Chiropractic
Macquarie University
Building C5C, Room 354
Balaclava Road
North Ryde   NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 6387</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9850 9389</fax>
      <email>roger.engel@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>