<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368614">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/06/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000838516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A comparison of depth of muscle relaxation to improve performance of percutaneous ablation of liver tumours</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparing depth of muscle relaxation in the performance of percutaneous ablation of liver tumours</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1170-4634</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Liver tumour (primary or secondary)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Liver</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a single-center, prospective, double-blinded, randomized controlled trial involving a sample size of 100 patients (50 per group) undergoing CT-guided radiofrequency ablation of primary and secondary liver tumours in the Department of Biomedical Imaging, University Malaya Medical Centre.

All patients who are eligible to enroll will be given a patient information sheet and have their consent taken prior to procedure. 

There will be 2 groups in this study:
Group (1) deep neuromuscular blockade (DMB) will receive 1.0mg/kg IV Rocuronium bolus during induction followed by infusion to maintain post-tetanic count (PTC) of 1 or 2. Initial pump rate will be set at 0.6mg/kg/hr and adjusted accordingly by increments of 0.1 to maintain PTC of 1 or 2. 

Group (2) moderate neuromuscular blockade (MMB) will receive 0.5mg/kg IV Atracurium bolus during induction followed by infusion to maintain train-of-four count (TOF) of 1 or 2. Initial pump rate will be set at 0.3mg/kg/hr and adjusted accordingly by increments of 0.1 to maintain TOF count of 1 or 2. 

Further boluses of 10mg Rocuronium or Atracurium will be given if requested by the interventional radiologist and documented. All patients will be intubated with cuffed Portex ETT and anaesthesia maintained with a balanced technique to achieve MAC of 1.0-1.3. They will be ventilated with intermittent positive pressure ventilation using pressure control to achieve a tidal volume of not more than 7mls/kg and ETCO2 of 35-40 mmHg. Ventilation will be intermittently suspended at varying lengths of time when required by the radiologist (only allowed if patient is stable with SpO2 of at least 97%). Suspension of ventilation must resume should the oxygen saturation starts to drop below 96% or &gt;4% from baseline. 

Depth of neuromuscular blockade will be monitored with TOF-Watch (Registered Trade Mark) Organon (Ireland) Ltd which will be calibrated prior to use. After completion of procedure, infusions of drugs in both Groups 1 and 2 will be terminated. Group (1) will be reversed with IV Sugammadex 4mg/kg while Group (2) with IV Neostigmine 0.05mg/kg and IV Atropine 0.02mg/kg. Patients will be extubated when TOF ratio becomes 0.9 or more and will be monitored in the recovery area for at least half an hour.
If patients cannot be extubated, reasons will be documented.

Analgesics such as 0.05 - 0.1 mg/kg IV morphine or 40 mg IV Parecoxib will be given after induction with additional boluses of analgesia in the recovery after extubation based on pain scores.
Dexamethasone 4mg will be given as anti emetics when required after induction.

Follow up with records and phone call at 1 year after tumor percutaneous ablation procedure</interventions>
    <comparator>Moderate depth of muscle relaxation during general anaesthesia (TOF 1-2)(Group 2, MMB)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the difference in the mean of liver excursion (in mm) during the procedure between deep neuromuscular blockade (DMB) in  Group 1 and moderate neuromuscular blockade (MMB) in Group 2.
Amplitude of liver excursion will be measured (in milimetres) during baseline CT and post-procedure multiphasic contrast-enhanced CT and recorded. The number and site of lesions will also be recorded in the data collecting form to judge the difficulty of performing the procedure due to anatomical constraints.</outcome>
      <timepoint>CT scans at baseline, during the RFA procedure and immediately following its completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Evaluating the ease of performing the RFA in liver tumours on a 5-point scale by the interventional radiologist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Haemodynamic parameters such as heart rate, ECG recordings, blood pressure measurements using an automated pressure cuff will be recorded during procedure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 10 minutes during the radiofrequency procedure, at the end and recovery period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ventilator variables such as tidal volume, peak airway pressure, respiratory rate, end-tidal CO2 which are automatically recorded on the ventilator device</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 10 minutes during the radiofrequency procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The duration of procedure</outcome>
      <timepoint>From the start until the end of procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complication rates such as bleeding, hypotension, respiratory problems (pneumothorax, haemothorax, pleural effusion), unplanned ICU admission or adverse events in post anaesthetic care unit (nausea, vomiting, severe pain)</outcome>
      <timepoint>During the ablation procedure, at the end and within first 24 hours</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient's satisfaction score of the treatment using a numerical scoring system (1, extremely dissatisfied to 10, extremely satisfied)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post procedure Day 1</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of hospital stay</outcome>
      <timepoint>After procedure until discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1 year mortality 
Assessed through medical records and phone calls</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tumour recurrence rate after 1 year of procedure through medical records and phone calls</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 year post procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-	ASA 1 to 3
-	Age between 18 to 75 years old
-	Confirmed diagnosis of primary or secondary liver tumours and planned for elective percutaneous ablation by primary team and radiologist.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	Refusal to participate in this study by patient or the legal representative 
2.	Any contraindications to the RFA procedure 
3.	Any contraindications to general anaesthesia 
4.	Any contraindications to any of the drugs used such as 
    i)	severe renal impairment for rocuronium and sugammadex 
    ii)	allergy 
5.	Pregnant  or breastfeeding patients
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A research assistant will organize the randomization for 1-100 subjects, label the group numbers 1 or 2 and seal the opaque envelopes bearing the respective subject index numbers before the start of the trial.

Another person will screen and obtain consent from eligible subjects. The sealed envelopes will be opened prior to starting the RFA procedure.
</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using computer software generated randomisation table </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculation was performed using OpenEpi Version 3.03 open source software. Sample size required to achieve at least 80% power (1-beta) at alpha level 5% (a) is 86 (43 per group). Estimation was based on mean and standard deviation differences of 1.3mm between the 2 groups. After considering 15% drop out rate, total sample required is 100 (50 per group). </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/06/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/06/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <state>Petaling Jaya</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University Malaya</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Malaya
Jalan Universiti, 50603 Kuala Lumpur, Wilayah Persekutuan Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Postgraduate research grant from University of Malaya, Malaysia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University Malaya
Department of Anaesthesiology, Faculty of Medicine, University Malaya,  Lembah Pantai, 50603 Kuala Lumpur, MALAYSIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study compares the depth of muscle relaxation that improves the performance of percutaneous ablation in liver tumour. We hypothesise that deep neuromuscular blockade during general anaesthesia would increase the ease of percutaneous ablation performance and reduce mean liver excursion (respiration related liver motion) resulting in a shorter procedure time and fewer complications.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Ethics Committee University Malaya Medical Centre</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Jalan Universiti, 50603 Kuala Lumpur, Wilayah Persekutuan Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/06/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>MECID.NO: 20151-930</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/01/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Malaysia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Pui-San Loh</name>
      <address>University Malaya Medical Centre,
Jalan Universiti, 
50603 Kuala Lumpur,
Malaysia
</address>
      <phone>+60379492052</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lohps@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Naeema S.Masohood</name>
      <address>University Malaya Medical Centre
Jalan Universiti, 
50603 Kuala Lumpur,
Malaysia</address>
      <phone>+60379492052</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>naeema@ummc.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Pui-San Loh</name>
      <address>University Malaya Medical Centre
Jalan Universiti, 
50603 Kuala Lumpur,
Malaysia</address>
      <phone>+60379492052</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lohps@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Pui-San Loh</name>
      <address>University Malaya Medical Centre
Jalan Universiti, 
50603 Kuala Lumpur,
Malaysia</address>
      <phone>+60379492052</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lohps@um.edu.my</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>