<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364359">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000681752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>McCusker KARVIAH: Curcumin in Alzheimer's disease prevention</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>McCusker KARVIAH: Investigating the role of curcumin in preventing Alzheimer's Disease_MK002</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1144-1011</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prevention of Alzheimer's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Alzheimer's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be aged 65-90 and the introduction of the  Curcumin (Biocurcumax TM) will be titrated as follows: 
500mg daily for 2/ wks, progressing to  
500mg twice daily (1,000mg/daily) for 2 weeks, then
500mg three times daily, (1,500mg) onwards 

The Curcumin is formulated into a capsule and is taken with a glass of water after meals.

The intervention will be for a period of 12 months in total.

 </interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo capsule, contains roasted rice powder and is identical in colour, shape and size to the active capsule. The dosage frequency is consistent with the active treatment regime. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biocurcumax will positively alter AD-related blood biomarker profiles compared with placebo
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 &amp;12 months </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biocurcumax TM will be associated with reduced amyloid ligand uptake as determined by Pib PET imaging as compared with placebo</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biocurcumax will slow cognitive decline, as demonstrated by a battery of neuropsychological tests compared to placebo.

Tools used to assess cognitive function will include RAVLT; Wechsler Logical Memory-II; Category fluency; COWAT; BNT; Digit Span; Stroop; Rey; and the computer generated CogState (brief version).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biocurcumax will increase brain glucose utilisation, as measured by FDG-PET, and correlate with improvement in cognitive functioning.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biocurcumax will bind to aggregated ABeta in the retina and be detectable with fluorescence imaging </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biocurcumax levels  of retinal fluorescence imaging will positively correlate with amyloid ligand uptake as determined by PET brain imaging </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biocurcumax will slow cognitive decline over 12 months compared to placebo. 

Tools used to assess cognitive function will include RAVLT; Wechsler Logical Memory-II; Category fluency; COWAT; BNT; Digit Span; Stroop; Rey; and the computer generated CogState (brief version).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lifestyle factors including lower levels of physical activity, as assessed by Community Healthy Activities Model Program for Seniors (CHAMPS) questionnaire;  poorer diet as assessed by Food Frequency Questionnaire (FFQ-Cancer Council, Vic Version) and lower sleep quality as assessed the Pittsburgh Quality Sleep Index (PQSI), individually, negatively impact on the cognitive performance </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biocurcumax will slow cortical atrophy and loss of hippocampal volume as measured by MRI</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 12 months. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Age 65-90 years, with good health and no significant cerebral vascular disease 

Living in independent living units, or similar accommodation 

English speaker

Adequate vision and hearing to enable testing

Memory complaint as determined by MAC-Q, and preferably corroborated by an informant

No objective memory impairment, based on cognitive test scores 

Normal general cognitive function as determined by a Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) score, greater than or equal to 26 during screening

No significant functional impairments

Intact ADL i.e. no or minimal impairment in activities of daily living (ADLs), as determined by a clinical interview 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of dementia based on the revised criteria from NIA/AA
 
Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) score less than or equal to 17

Significant functional impairments/behavioural problems as indicated by the Informant Questionnaire on Cognitive Decline in the Elderly (IQCODE) and the 36-Item Short Form Health Survey (SF-36)
 
Presence of acute functional psychiatric disorder including; lifetime history of schizophrenia or bipolar disorder

Prior medical history of stroke
 
History of  alcohol or drug abuse / dependence within 2 years of screening

Depression, as indicated on the DASS

Use of Warfarin, within 4 weeks of screening

Current or previous bile duct obstruction, gallstones, and gastrointestinal disorder

Contraindication to MRI, including, but not limited to those with a pacemaker, presence of metallic fragments near the eyes or spinal cord, or cochlear implant 

History of closed angle glaucoma, or related conditions, contraindicated for retinal scanning

Uncontrolled hypertension (systolic BP &gt; 170 or diastolic BP &gt; 100) 

Any significant systemic illness or unstable medical condition that could lead to difficulty complying with the protocol including: history of myocardial infarction in the past year or unstable or severe cardiovascular disease including angina or congestive heart disease, chronic renal failure, chronic hepatic disease, severe pulmonary disease

Clinically significant and unstable gastrointestinal disorder such as ulcer disease or a history of active or occult gastrointestinal bleeding within two years.

 </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Stage 1 will involve recruiting 200 participants who will undertake a comprehensive health assessment, including cognition, blood and buccal cell swab and lifestyle questionnaires.
100 participants, assessed as most at risk of AD will then proceed to the intervention (curcumin / placebo). At this point Allocation will be done under concealment, by the NSW study site contacting the allocation schedule holder, who is located in WA 'central laboratory'. This will be done by email/phone correspondence.  
</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation is done using a dynamic random allocation process, using a computer generated table for recording, the two groups will be stratified for gender, age, education and ApOE4 status. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>In the current study, the main outcome variables used to assess differences between the intervention and placebo groups are cerebral amyloid load, cognitive and clinical measures. Using the G*Power software (version 3.1.5) for Power analysis (1 - Beta) indicated a sample size N equals 100 is required to detect any significant differences between two groups at greater than/ equal to 80% power and alpha equal to 0.05. The analysis may include 4 covariates (age, sex, APOE e4 allele status, and education) and a commonly used F test (e.g. ANCOVA). 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/06/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>24/06/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>27/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>134</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>4/11/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>27/10/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2229 - Taren Point</postcode>
    <postcode>2232 - Kirrawee</postcode>
    <postcode>2154 - Castle Hill</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>McCusker Alzheimer's Research Foundation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Suite 22, 85 Monash Avenue, Nedlands, WA. 6009,</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>McCusker Alzheimer's Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Suite 22, 85 Monash Avenue, Nedlands 6009, WA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Foundation for Aged Care, ARV</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>284 Castle Hill Road, Castle Hill, 2154, NSW</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Edith Cowan University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>270 Joondalup Dr  Joondalup WA 6027
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Anglican Retirement Villages, ARV, Sydney</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>P.O. Box 284, Castle Hill 1765, NSW</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study is designed to examine the lifestyle and health risk factors of participants in an older age group, living in retirement setting. 
Those most at risk of Alzheimer's disease (AD) will then be given curcumin /placebo to examine its abiltity to reduce or slow the risk of developing the AD. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Kathryn Goozee, Pratishtha Chatterjee, Ian James, Hamid Sohrabi, Kaikai Shen, Prita Asih, Preeti Dave, Bethany Ball, Candice Man Yan, Kevin Taddei, Scot Ayton, Manohar Garg, Ashley Bush, Ralph N. Martins. Elevated plasma and serum ferritin levels in subjective memory complainers with high neocortical amyloid load.  Molecular Psychiatry, (2017), 11 Jul. doi: 10.1038/mp.2017.146

Goozee K, Chatterjee P, James I, Shen K, Sohrabi H, Asih P, Dave P, Ball B, Man Yan C, Taddei K, Chung R, Garg ML, Martins RN. Alterations in erythrocytye fatty acid composition in preclinical Alzheimers disease. Scientific Reports (2017), 7(1):676. DOi: 1038/s4 1598-017-00751-2.

Goozee, K.G ; Shah, T; Sobrai, H.; Rainey-Smith; Brown B; Verdile, G  and Martins, R.N. (2015). Examining the Potential Clinical Value of Curcumin in the Prevention and Diagnosis of Alzheimers disease. British Journal of Nutrition, 1-17, doi:10.1017/S0007114515004687.

</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellbury Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>229 Greenhill Road
Dulwich
South Australia 5065

</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012-09-1086-A1</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Western Australia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>8716 Hackett Dr  Crawley WA 6009
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/1/6225</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ralph N. Martins </name>
      <address>McCusker Alzheimer's Research Foundation
Suite 22, 85 Monash Avenue, 
Nedlands, 6009
W.A. </address>
      <phone>+61893474201 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.martins@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kathryn G. Goozee</name>
      <address>Anglican Retirement Villages, 
C/- McCusker KARVIAH Research Centre
2 Alexander Avenue, 
Taren Point, 2229, NSW </address>
      <phone>+61297107352</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kathryn.goozee@anglicare.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kevin Taddei</name>
      <address>Sir James McCusker Alzheimers Disease Research Laboratory, Edith Cowan University; and McCusker Alzheimer's Research Foundation

Suite 22, 85 Monash Avenue, Nedlands 6009, WA</address>
      <phone>+61893474201</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>k.taddei@ecu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kathryn Goozee</name>
      <address>Anglican Retirement Villages, 
C/- McCusker KARVIAH Research Centre
2 Alexander Avenue, 
Taren Point, 2229, NSW</address>
      <phone>+61297107352</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Kathryn.goozee@anglicare.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>