<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81594">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/09/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/01/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000103460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of a primary care-based electronic screening and brief intervention for hazardous drinking</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to evaluate the effects of web-based motivational feedback on hazardous drinking for the prevention of alcohol-related harm in healthy participants</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Harmful alcohol consumption in healthy participants</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>B: Screening (The screening involves patients to complete the 10-item Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT) at a computer in the waiting area which is connected to the Internet. They also answered questions about the largest amount they consumed in a single episode in the last 4 weeks, the duration of the episode, their age, gender, and ethnicity. It takes 3 minutes.), information leaflet (An educational leaflet providing information on the effects of alcohol and recommended upper limits for low-risk consumption) plus assessment of alcohol use, perceptions of peer drinking norms, and problems 4 weeks later. The assessment involves a 14-day retrospective account of drinks per day, the Alcohol Problems Scale - 14 items, the Academic Role Expectations and Alcohol Scale - 5 items, estimates of others' drinking (7 items) and their height and weight. Median completion time is 11 minutes.
C: Web-based motivational intervention (single-dose); including comparison of patient's drinking with age/gender norms and recommended upper limits. This intervention takes 11 minutes to answer the questions (see above) plus the time required to read the feedback, which we estimate to be 3-5 minutes. Overall, total time is approximately 15 minutes.
D: Web-based motivational intervention (multi-dose); as in C, provided at the commencement of the trial, at 6 months and at 12 months. This intervention takes 15 minutes at baseline and a further 10 minutes four weeks later for assessment and feedback.</interventions>
    <comparator>A: Screening and information leaflet (control). An educational leaflet providing information on the effects of alcohol and recommended upper limits for low-risk consumption. The screening involves patients to complete the 10-item Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test (AUDIT) at a computer in the waiting area which is connected to the Internet. They also answered questions about the largest amount they consumed in a single episode in the last 4 weeks, the duration of the episode, their age, gender, and ethnicity. It takes 3 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment by computer over the Internet of the Quantity and frequency of drinking</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment by computer over the Internet of Binge Drinking.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment by computer over the Internet of Personal and Academic Problems.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 and 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment by computer over the Internet of the Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test Score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in normative perceptions</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured at 6 months and 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients of the University of Otago Student Health Service, Sufficient English to understand consent form</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>17</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>29</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>If too sick or injured to participate</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Research staff involved in the trial were not informed of participants’ group allocation during intervention or follow-up. The generation of the sequence and loading of it into the server database were conducted by off-site staff who were not involved in the implementation of the trial on site, who never came into contact with study participants. Participants were informed that they were participating in a series of surveys about their drinking. Thier perceptions were checked in a pilot study, and found to be consistent with the aim to conceal group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>The random sequence was generated in Microsoft Excel using the rand function, and this was loaded into the server which administered the intervention.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Subjects were blind. Note: there were no assessors or therapists as such: all done by computer. The intervention, assessment, and analysis may therefore be said to have been conducted blindly.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/03/2003</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>572</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Kypros Kypri</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry />
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Health Research Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Alcohol Advisory Council of New Zealand</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is compelling evidence for the efficacy of screening and brief intervention (SBI) for hazardous drinking, yet it is not widely available in primary healthcare. Electronic (computer/web-based) intervention offers the prospect of ease, simplicity, and economy of access. 
The objective was to examine whether electronic SBI (single- and multi-intervention) reduces hazardous drinking and related problems compared with an information leaflet alone (control condition).
Design and Setting: Randomized controlled trial at a university health service (enrolment 8/2003), with follow-up measures taken at 6 and 12 months.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Student Health Service.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/02/2002</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>02/010.</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kypros Kypri</name>
      <address>School of Medicine and Public Health
University of Newcastle
David Maddison Building
King &amp; Watt Streets
Newcastle NSW 2300</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49236231</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 49236148</fax>
      <email>kypros.kypri@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Kypros Kypri</name>
      <address>School of Medicine and Public Health
University of Newcastle
David Maddison Building
King &amp; Watt Streets
Newcastle NSW 2300</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49236231</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 49236148</fax>
      <email>kypros.kypri@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>