<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371858">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001616460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cerebral palsy check up: Supporting allied health professionals to provide the best service at the best time</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of a tailored multi-faceted knowledge translation intervention on allied health professionals' treatment implementation behaviours for children with cerebral palsy: A before and after study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1189-8947 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>Best Service Best Time (BSBT)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cerebral palsy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Occupational therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Tailored multi-faceted knowledge translation intervention provided to allied health professionals (AHP: physiotherapists, occupational therapists, speech pathologists) who provide services to children with cerebral palsy in four Australian non-government organisations (collectively defined as the Commencing Knowledge Translation group) with the aim on increasing the implementation of routine clinical assessment and provision of evidence-based interventions provided to children aged 3-18 years. 

The intervention is implemented at each organisation for 2 years and includes four strands: 
(1) Identification of Knowledge Brokers (expert research translators) based at each organisation who will aim to re-dress workplace barriers unique to each site.  Each organisation will nominate one or more knowledge brokers for their site.  The knowledge brokers will work with the project team, the organisations management and the AHPs to act as agents in the process of translating and contextualising evidence for users within the organisation.  
Materials and procedures used to support knowledge brokers include 1 day training sessions, about the knowledge broker role, delivered by researchers at the beginning and mid-way through the project; peer support through periodic  (approximately twice yearly) telephone conferences involving knowledge brokers across organisations; provision of an on-line discussion forum monitored by researchers. Knowledge brokers are intended to provide support to AHP within their own organisation throughout the trial period. Experience and ongoing fidelity of the broker role will be evaluated through focus groups conducted at baseline, 6, 12, and 24 months.

(2) Provision of a customised e-evidence library  - CP Decision - to enable AHPs rapid access to synthesised and critiqued cerebral palsy research evidence.  This library employs a traffic light system corresponding to evidence levels and will be updated on an ongoing basis to accommodate new evidence as it emerges.  
Materials are an on-line database of cerebral palsy specific evidence. Procedures include providing all participating organisations with a password that can be used by employees to log in and review the information as frequently as each individual AHP wishes. CP Decision will be available to all organisations throughout the study period. Intervention fidelity will be assessed for each organisation monthly, by evaluating the frequency of 'visits' to the site as well as by determining the most frequently viewed pages.

(3) Negotiated education and professional development days for AHP at partner organisations (implemented by the project investigators, organisation-based knowledge brokers and other experts) about how to implement or administer the current and most effective treatment and measurement options for cerebral palsy. 
This intervention strand will include two elements: a) a study specific element provided to all organisations and b) an organisation-specific element, tailored to meet the needs of individual organisations. 
The study-specific element is provided at baseline, 6, 12 and 24 months by researchers in a face to face professional development workshop format for half a day. Attendance of participating AHP is recorded, and fidelity assessed via feedback on learning sought through an evaluation form. 
Organisation-specific elements are negotiated annually with the researchers and can include purchase of educational events (e.g. experts to deliver training sessions on site at the organisation; or payment of registration fees for individual AHP to attend courses) or resources to support implementation of evidence based practices for children with cerebral palsy (e.g. purchase of evidence-based assessment tool). Procedures involve knowledge brokers collaborating with local AHP and managers to develop an annual professional development plan, presenting (in writing) the plan to researchers for consideration and approval against an agreed budget. Fidelity/processes will be assessed by recording of all education events and professional development purchases made for each organisation throughout the project and monthly reporting to the project steering committee. 

(4) Provision of an electronic cerebral palsy clinical outcomes database (CP Check-UpTM, provided by Cerebral Palsy Alliance).  This electronic tool will be used by AHPs to record routine valid and reliable clinical measurements of participating children and to summarise the therapeutic interventions provided to these children.  Through generation of an electronic report, the tool will provide feedback about changes in outcomes of individual children over time, guiding evidence-based clinical decision making to support direct therapeutic intervention and timely referral to ancillary services.  
Materials provided are a study manual and paper-based forms to enable AHP to learn what is included and how to access the database and enter details for children. In addition, personalised log-in details are provided for all participating AHP so that they can access the electronic database and enter data for included children. The Database is made available to each organisation for the period of the study. Support is provided by researchers and the manager of the database. 
Fidelity is assessed as one key outcome of the study - by extracting data related to number of children for whom an assessment is recorded, frequency of assessment of each included child and proportion of the minimum data set recorded for each assessment. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>A fifth organisation is identified as the 'Comparison organisation' as the four strands of the tailored intervention are mandated in that organisation and embedded in routine practice. This organisation is deemed to be further along the knowledge translation implementation time line than the Commencing KT organisations. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Longitudinal change in AHP evidence-based behaviours measured in two ways:
1) self report using the Evidence Based Practice Competency Questionnaire-Cerebral Palsy (Campbell et al., 2013) scored as two reliable sub-scales (Kerr et al.) and
2) actual AHP assessment behaviours evaluated using data extracted from the CP Check-Up TM database to assess changes in number of children receiving assessment (proportion of those eligible) and amount of evidence-based assessment provided (compliance score range 0-100). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6, 12 and 24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Longitudinal changes in AHP evidence based practice knowledge assessed using a knowledge quiz adapted from Campbell et al. 2013, </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Longitudinal change in supports and barriers to implementation of evidence-based assessment. evaluated using  a multiple methods approach to derive an outcome from composite measures including:
1) Supports and Barriers questionnaire, adapted from Rivard et al. 2010, and
2) Focus groups held with AHP; </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months, and 24 months. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Longitudinal change in adverse outcomes for children with cerebral palsy, including severe scoliosis, hip dislocation, progressive limb contractures over the study period.
Assessed using data extracted from the CP Check Up electronic database in which AHP record measures taken using goniometry, reports from X-Rays.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 29 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Longitudinal changes in AHP attitudes to evidence based practices assessed using 2 sub-scales from the Evidence Based Practice Attitudes Scale (Aarons et al. 2004, 2012): 
1) Perceived Divergence sub-scale and 
2) Openness to Innovation sub-scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Longitudinal changes in supports and barriers to implementation of evidence based assessment processes assessed through data gathered through composite outcomes including focus groups held with (i) Knowledge brokers; (ii) clinical service managers and (iii) individual interviews with Chief Executive Officer or senior managers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 6, 12 and 24 months for focus group data collection and baseline and 24 months for senior managers. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The study has 2 groups: 
The primary outcomes are focused on the Allied Health Professionals:
All physiotherapists, occupational therapists and speech pathologists working, or having the potential to work with children with cerebral palsy in participating service providers, will be eligible to participate.  There are no exclusion criteria.

The secondary outcomes are focused on children with cerebral palsy:
Children aged 3-18 years with a diagnosis of cerebral palsy will also be recruited to the study. There are no exclusion criteria.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>N/A</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This study will employ a before and after design in four Australian non-government organisations that provide allied health services to children with cerebral palsy, with a fifth organisation acting as a comparison site.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Estimated Sample Size and Power of the Study 
Based on organisational commitment to the project, and expected workforce changes during the course of the study, it is anticipated that 80% of the eligible AHP will take part in the study (i.e. 192 participants from an estimated 240 eligible AHP participants across all partner organisations).  Calculations indicate that this sample will be sufficient to detect a difference of 6 points on the Best Service Best Time Evaluation with &gt;90% power.  

Pre-study estimation of the number of participating children, suggests a sample size of 614 may be achieved (80% of the 768 eligible children identified across all partner organisations). A 10% arithmetic difference between baseline and subsequent child-based quality measures (e.g. range of movement) will be able to be detected with &gt;90% power (where baseline percentage is around 50%; power will be greater where the baseline percentage is smaller or larger than 50%).

Statistical analyses 
Cross-sectional data will be examined and reported, however primary analyses will focus on the longitudinal design of this study, assessing change over time in AHP evidence-based practice behaviours, and in clinical outcomes for participating children.  

Quantitative analyses will be carried out with multivariate statistical models such as population-averaged generalized estimating equations and subject-specific generalized linear and latent mixed models.  These models allow for correlated longitudinal data structures and intraclass correlation coefficients (required due to children being clustered within AHP and AHP within organisations). In addition, these models can include outcomes of mixed types including counts, ordered and un-ordered responses, and dichotomous and metric outcomes.  Potential confounders will be examined and study sites will be treated as covariates to account for differing adoption of new practices rates. The significance of the covariates will be ascertained with 95% confidence intervals. 

Qualitative focus group and interview data will be digitally recorded and transcribed, coded and analysed using a grounded theory approach to thematic analysis.  Themes within and between participants, and groups of participants, will be used to understand the feasibility and acceptability of the knowledge broker role and aligned evidence based practices within the different organisations.  

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>7/05/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/12/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>192</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>447</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>15/12/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,SA,TAS,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2086 - Frenchs Forest</postcode>
    <postcode>7250 - Launceston</postcode>
    <postcode>7000 - Hobart</postcode>
    <postcode>5010 - Regency Park</postcode>
    <postcode>3220 - Geelong</postcode>
    <postcode>3127 - Surrey Hills</postcode>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Christine Imms</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Australian Catholic University, 
17 Young Street, Fitzroy, Melbourne 3065, </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra City ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Yooralla </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 223, 
Surrey Hills, Victoria 3127</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Novita Children's Services</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>171 Days Road Regency Park, 
Adelaide, South Australia 5010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St Giles</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 416, 
Launceston, Tasmania 7250</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cerebral Palsy Alliance</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 6427, 
Frenchs Forest NSW 2086, Sydney</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Kids Plus</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>163 Myers St, 
Geelong, Victoria 3220</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Iona Novak</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Cerebral Palsy Alliance, 
PO Box 6427, Frenchs Forest NSW 2086, Sydney, </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nora Shields</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Allied Health, Corner of Plenty Road &amp; Kingsbury Drive La Trobe University, Bundoora, Victoria 3086</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>H. Kerr Graham</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Royal Children's Hospital, 50 Flemington Road Parkville, VICTORIA 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dinah Reddihough</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Royal Children's Hospital, 50 Flemington Road Parkville, VICTORIA 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Steve Bowe</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Deakin Biostatistics Unit, Faculty of Health, Deakin University, 
221 Burwood Hwy, Burwood VIC 3125</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Claire Kerr</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Australian Catholic University, 17 Young Street, Fitzroy, Melbourne 3065
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Petra Karlsson</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Cerebral Palsy Alliance, 
PO Box 6427, Frenchs Forest NSW 2086, Sydney, </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Sarah Foley</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Kids Plus Foundation, 163 Myers St, Geelong, Victoria 3220</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Lyndsay Quarmby</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>St Giles, PO Box 416, Launceston, Tasmania 7250</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Kerry Evans</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Novita Childrens Services, 171 Days Road Regency Park, Adelaide, South Australia 5010</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Marisa McCague</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Yooralla, PO Box 223, Surrey Hills, Victoria 3127, </othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Cerebral palsy is a permanent disorder of posture and movement caused by disturbances in the developing brain.  It is the most common form of childhood physical disability.  People with cerebral palsy may also have problems with speech, vision and hearing, intellectual difficulties and epilepsy.  Health and therapy services are frequently required throughout life, and this care should be effective and evidence-informed; however accessing and adopting new research findings into day-to-day clinical practice is often delayed.

This study employs a before and after design to evaluate if a multi-strategy intervention can improve research implementation among allied health professionals (AHP) who work with children and young people with cerebral palsy, and to establish if childrens health outcomes can be improved by routine clinical assessment.  The intervention comprises (1) knowledge brokering with AHP, (2) access to an on-line research evidence library, (3) provision of negotiated evidence-based training and education, and (4) routine use of evidence-based measures with children and young people aged 3-18 years with cerebral palsy.  The study is being implemented in four organisations, with a fifth organisation acting as a comparison site, across four Australian states.  Effectiveness will be assessed using questionnaires completed by AHPs at baseline, 6, 12 and 24 months, and by monitoring the extent of use of evidence-based measures.  Childrens health outcomes will be evaluated by longitudinal analyses.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Imms, C., Novak, I., Kerr, C., Shields, N., Randall, M., Harvey, A., Graham, H.K. &amp; Reddihough, D., (2015). Improving allied health professionals' research implementation behaviours for children with cerebral palsy: protocol for a before and after study. Implementation Science 10:16 DOI 10.1186/s13012-014-0202-0</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Australian Catholic University Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 968 North Sydney NSW 2059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2012 309V</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/11/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Cerebral Palsy Alliance</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 6427, Frenchs Forest NSW 2086, Sydney, </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013-04-02</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/03/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Department of Education and Early Childhood Development</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box 4367
Melbourne 3001
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013-001962</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine Imms</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University, 
17 Young Street, 
Fitzroy, Melbourne 3065, </address>
      <phone>+61399533404</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.imms@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine Imms</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University, 
17 Young Street, 
Fitzroy, Melbourne 3065, </address>
      <phone>+61399533404</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.imms@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine Imms</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University, 
17 Young Street, 
Fitzroy, Melbourne 3065,</address>
      <phone>+61399533404</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.imms@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Christine Imms</name>
      <address>Australian Catholic University, 
17 Young Street, 
Fitzroy, Melbourne 3065,</address>
      <phone>+61399533404</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>christine.imms@acu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>