<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368535">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/12/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001364561p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Development and evaluation of a low-literacy decision aid about reproductive choices for younger women with breast cancer.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The impact of a low health literacy decision aid about reproductive choices for younger women with early breast cancer on decision-related outcomes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1170-1252</utrn>
    <trialacronym>aLLIAnCE (Low Literacy Decision Aid about Reproductive Choices for Younger Women with Breast Cancer) study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Breast Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Low Health Literacy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Decision-making</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Fertility preservation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Breast</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fertility including in vitro fertilisation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is a low-literacy decision aid (DA) designed to assist patients to reach an informed decision about fertility preservation. The DA has been developed in accordance with the latest International Patient Decision Aid Standards (IPDAS) established by a group of experts. The content will be based on a literature review and consultation with experts, including health literacy experts, oncologists, breast surgeons, breast care nurses, reproductive health specialists, psychologists, behavioural scientists, and consumers. The DA includes information concerning the pros and cons of fertility preservation in women with early breast cancer and has evidence-based representation of chances of success. It addresses the complexity, uncertain benefits and potentially large costs in this setting. A summary of treatment procedures are presented with a set of values clarification exercises to help weigh up the pros and cons of fertility preservation in light of patient values and life situation. The format of the DA will be a website. The DA will be provided to women after the completion of the baseline questionnaire. </interventions>
    <comparator>A placebo controlled group will be used. This group will be directed to information already avialable about the impact of cancer treatment on fertility (http://canceraustralia.gov.au/affected-cancer/cancer-types/breast-cancer/living-breast-cancer/managing-physical-changes-due-breast-cancer/breast-cancer-and-fertility) </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is Decisional Conflict. This outcome is assessed by the Decisional Conflict Scale, a validated measure of decisional conflict.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (at time of recruitment), and one and 12 months after recruitment. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome is Knowledge - of cancer treatment and impact on fertility. This questionnaire was created for a previous DA study to assess current knowledge of cancer treatment and it's impact on fertility, and changes in knowledge over time. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (at time of recruitment), and one and 12 months after recruitment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary outcome is Decisional Regret. This outcome is assessed by the Decisional Regret Scale, a validated measure of decisional regret.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One and 12 months after recruitment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary outcome is Informed Choice. This outcome is assessed by the Multi-dimensional Measure for Informed Choice, a validated measure of decision quality. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (at time of recruitment), and one and 12 months after recruitment. One and 12 months after recruitment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A secondary outcome is Psychological Adjustment. This outcome is assessed by the Depression Anxiety Stress Scales (DASS 21), a validated measure of anxiety, depression and stress. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (at time of recruitment), and one and 12 months after recruitment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible to participate women must:
a)	be aged between 18-40 years (inclusive) at the time of diagnosis
b)	histologically confirmed diagnosis of early-stage breast cancer
c)	pre-menopausal at time of diagnosis, 
d)	have no history of metastatic disease prior to diagnosis, 
e)	have not completed their families at the time of diagnosis, 
f)	able to give informed consent, 
h)	identified as having low health literacy. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Although women whose primary language is other than English (LOTE) will not explicitly be excluded, women will need to have enough English capability to complete the questionnaires and communicate with the researchers. Should the oncologist consider the patients English skills to be insufficient, they will be excluded. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/01/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,QLD,SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Melbourne, Parkville Victoria 3052 Australia
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Breast Cancer Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 9, 50 Pitt Street
Sydney
NSW 2000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Women's Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Flemington Rd, Parkville VIC 3052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this study is to develop and evaluate a new low literacy decision aid relating to fertility preservation for younger women with early stage breast cancer.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are a pre-menopausal woman aged 18 to 40 years of age, who has been diagnosed with early stage breast cancer with no history of metastatic disease, and who has not yet completed their family.

Study details
Participants in this study will be randomly selected (by chance) to receive either usual care or to access the decision aid website. The decision aid includes easy to understand information regarding the side effects of cancer treatments in terms of their effects on women's fertility, and options for preserving fertility to increase chances of having a baby at a later date.

Participants will then be asked to fill out a questionnaire before seeing the decision aid website, and also a questionnaire regarding the choices made and the use of the decision aid after one month and again after one year.

It is hoped that the findings of this trial will provide information on how helpful fertility preservation information is to women with early stage breast cancer, and to improve access to this information by women as part of their medical care going forward.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6, East, 300 Grattan Street, Parkville Victoria 3052 Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Peate</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics &amp; Gynaecology, University of Melbourne, Level 7, Royal Women's Hospital, Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road, Parkville, VIC  3052 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 3792</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mpeate@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Peate</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics &amp; Gynaecology, University of Melbourne, Level 7, Royal Women's Hospital, Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road, Parkville, VIC  3052 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 3792</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mpeate@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Peate</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics &amp; Gynaecology, University of Melbourne, Level 7, Royal Women's Hospital, Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road, Parkville, VIC  3052 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 3792</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mpeate@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michelle Peate</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics &amp; Gynaecology, University of Melbourne, Level 7, Royal Women's Hospital, Cnr Grattan Street &amp; Flemington Road, Parkville, VIC  3052 </address>
      <phone>+61 3 8345 3792</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mpeate@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>