<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365982">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000296639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Electronic Snapshot for Outpatient Management of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, does an electronic personalised COPD Snapshot improve GP uptake of clinical care recommendations?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>ESO-COPD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients in the intervention group will receive a COPD Snapshot for the duration of the study. The COPD Snapshot is a communication tool that is a checklist-format adaptation of the Lung Foundation Stepwise Management of Stable COPD Guidelines. This Snapshot will be developed and piloted in-house in the initial phase of this project, and will contain key management points that have been identified by each patients thoracic physician as requiring ongoing review by the patients GP. It will also contain relevant recent investigation results, current medication list, and allergies. In addition, the Snapshot will be accessible if patients attend the ED. Utilisation of the Snapshot by ED will be monitored as a guide to feasibility for potential future expansion of the Snapshot scope based on initial results.

The Intervention Group (n=100 participants) will receive an electronic personalised COPD Snapshot in the form of a credit card sized USB stick, in addition to usual care from their thoracic physician (consultation, and clinic letter to GP). The electronic Snapshot will be given to participants during their consultation at the respiratory outpatient clinics. They will be asked to provide it to their GP to review when they next attend for ongoing care, within the next 2 months. After reviewing the Snapshot, GPs will return it to their patient and complete a brief, 3-question satisfaction survey. After attending follow up with their GP, participants will return the COPD Snapshot to the investigators by mail in a pre-addressed envelope. In addition, participants will complete a brief follow up survey (free text comments from patient and/or telephone interview) regarding their experience with the Snapshot and the clinical care they received.</interventions>
    <comparator>The Control Group (n=100 participants) will receive usual care from their thoracic physician (consultation, and clinic letter to GP), without the addition of any COPD Snapshot. In addition, participants will complete a brief follow up survey (free text comments from patient and/or telephone interview) regarding their experience and the clinical care they received. For comparison with the intervention group, the GP will be requested to complete a brief, 3-question satisfaction survey regarding the usefulness of the clinic letter they have received.

Participants in both groups will be provided with a paper copy of the Lung Foundation Stepwise Management of Stable COPD Guidelines to give to their GP when they attend for follow up, to provide all GPs with this up-to-date guideline information.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP uptake of clinical care recommendations from the thoracic specialist, as measured by survey (survey specifically designed for this trial).

</outcome>
      <timepoint>At time of first GP follow-up consultation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease impact on quality of life as measured by COPD Assessment Test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 4 month follow-up survey.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to first exacerbation as measured by survey (survey specifically designed for this trial).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 month follow-up survey (included in survey specifically designed for this trial)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction and experience as measured by survey (survey specifically designed for this trial).</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 months after enrolment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>GP satisfaction as measured by survey (survey specifically designed for this trial).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after follow-up consultation with participant.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thoracic physician satisfaction as measured by survey (survey specifically designed for this trial).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At conclusion of study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mortality as measured by hospital and other records.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 month follow-up after enrolment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of recommendations made by thoracic physicians per patient.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after enrolment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of patients who take the COPD Snapshot to their GP follow-up appointment as measured by participant survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of GPs who open and access COPD Snapshot as measured by GP survey (survey specifically designed for this trial).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after GP follow-up appointment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of GPs who confirm electronically that they have reviewed the COPD Snapshot as measured by observation of editing COPD Snapshot tool.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately after GP follow-up appointment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Adult patients of any age with thoracic-physician diagnosed COPD.
- COPD diagnosis will be based on Global Initiative in Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) spirometric criteria of post-bronchodilator FEV1&lt;80% predicted and FEV1/FVC &lt;70%. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Inability to give written informed consent.
- Presence of other respiratory conditions which are more predominant than the COPD (e.g. asthma; bronchiectasis; interstitial lung disease; current lung cancer). Patients with previously treated lung cancer, without known current active lung cancer, will be able to be included.
- No current regular general practitioner.
- High care level in a residential care facility.
- Women who are pregnant.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited from the respiratory outpatient clinics at The Prince Charles Hospital (TPCH), Brisbane, Australia. Both newly referred and current patients with COPD will be invited to join this study while attending their clinic appointment with their thoracic physician at the hospital.
Randomisation will take place at time of enrollment in the study. Participants will be randomised into one of two groups, using a random sequence generator, with 1:1 ratio in permuted blocks, and using balanced stratification based on new or review patient status. Allocations will be concealed in opaque envelopes, which are randomly assigned to participants, and not revealed until after informed consent. Allocation concealment will be implemented, so that investigators and participants are not aware of the treatment allocation prior to randomisation. Once randomised, both investigators and participants will be fully aware of the treatment allocation in an unblinded manner, and there will not be a sham intervention for the usual care, control group.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised into one of two groups, using a random sequence generator, with 1:1 ratio in permuted blocks, and using balanced stratification based on new or review patients status.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>In order to compare between control and intervention groups, we will test differences between the primary and secondary outcomes using t-test for continuous variables, and chi squared test for categorical variables. Multivariate analysis using relevant clinical and demographic covariates will be performed. All analysis will be performed using SPSS Version 20. A p value (two-tailed) &lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant.
The power of the study was estimated using the PS Power Calculation Software. Assuming a baseline uptake of 50% of recommendations by GPs in the usual care group, 100 patients in the intervention group and 100 patients in the control group would give 80% power (alpha 0.05) to find an increase in uptake by 20% to 70% with use of the COPD Snapshot.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>17/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>17/08/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Prince Charles Hospital - Chermside</hospital>
    <postcode>4032 - Chermside</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Prince Charles Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Prince Charles Hospital Rode Rd
Chermside
QLD 4032</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Prince Charles Hospital Foundation
(funding sought)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Prince Charles Hospital Foundation
Level 1 Admin Building, 627 Rode Road 
Chermside
QLD, 4032</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Queensland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Queensland 
St Lucia
QLD 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The University of Queensland 
St Lucia
QLD 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is a complex chronic disease that is characterised by a progressive deterioration of pulmonary function punctuated with exacerbations that frequently require hospitalisation. COPD affects approximately 2.1 million Australians and it is the 4th leading cause of death in this country.

Evidence-based guidelines for clinical management of COPD are widely available, however concordance with treatment guidelines is relatively low in the primary care setting. Numerous barriers to guideline adherence have been identified, and there are evidence-based approaches that could be used to address these barriers. Currently, there is no formal, systematic process for specialists to provide personalised, guideline-based recommendations to GPs beyond the traditional referral letter. 

This prospective randomised controlled trial will test the effect of an electronic checklist, the COPD Snapshot, on the management of outpatients with COPD. We aim to determine whether this checklist will improve GP uptake of specialist treatment recommendations.

Patients attending the outpatient clinic at The Prince Charles Hospital will be invited to participate in the study. After obtaining written informed consent, participants will be randomly allocated to either a control group or an intervention group. The control group will receive usual best practice care from their thoracic physician. The intervention group will receive a COPD Snapshot in addition to usual best practice care form their thoracic physician. The COPD Snapshot is a communication tool that is contained on a credit card-sized USB stick. It is a checklist-format adaptation of the Lung Foundation Stepwise Management of Stable COPD Guidelines. This Snapshot will contain key management points that have been identified by each patients thoracic physician as requiring ongoing review by the patients GP. The electronic Snapshot will be completed during the clinic appointment and given to the participant at the end with instructions to give it to their GP to review when they next attend for ongoing care, within the next 2 months. After reviewing the Snapshot, GPs will return it to their patient and complete a brief, 3-question survey. After attending follow up with their GP, participants will return the COPD Snapshot to the investigators by mail in a pre-addressed envelope. In addition, participants will complete a brief follow up survey regarding their experience with the Snapshot and the clinical care they received.

We will assess whether the COPD Snapshot has an effect on GP implementation of specialist treatment recommendations. In addition, we will assess the feasibility of the Snapshot, clinician uptake, and clinician and patient satisfaction.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Prince Charles Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Lower Ground Floor, Administration Building
The Prince Charles Hospital
Rode Road
Chermside Qld 4032</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/01/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/QPCH/324</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/11/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jeffrey Overington</name>
      <address>Thoracic Department
The Prince Charles Hospital, 627 Rode Rd
Chermside QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 478 049 078</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jeffrey.overington@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jeffrey Overington</name>
      <address>Thoracic Department
The Prince Charles Hospital
627 Rode Rd
Chermside QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 478 049 078</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jeffrey.overington@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ian Yang</name>
      <address>The Prince Charles Hospital
627 Rode Rd
Chermside QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 (0)7 3139 5050</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ian.Yang@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Jeffrey Overington</name>
      <address>Thoracic Department
The Prince Charles Hospital
627 Rode Rd
Chermside QLD 4032</address>
      <phone>+61 478 049 078</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jeffrey.overington@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>