<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335981">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/09/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000800022</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of coronary sinus ablation for treatment of atrial fibrillation.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In long-episode/non-lone paroxysmal and persistent atrial fibrillation patients, is pulmonary vein isolation, roofline and coronary sinus ablation more effective than pulmonary vein isolation and roofline ablation in terms of drug free clinical success at 12 months?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>No secondary ID number</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Drug refractory non-lone/long episode paroxysmal or persistent atrial fibrillation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cardiovascular diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Pulmonary vein isolation, roofline and coronary sinus ablation

Pulmonary vein isolation will be performed by positioning a circular mapping catheter sequentially at each pulmonary vein ostium, with location confirmed via fluoroscopy and virtual 3D navigation. Pulmonary vein isolation will be defined as abolition or dissociation of pulmonary vein potentials on a circumferential mapping catheter positioned at the ostium of the vein. All veins will be individually isolated via this technique. Common ostia venous architecture will be isolated en bloc with circumferential ablation and confirmation of electrical disconnection by positioning of the Lasso catheter within each of the inferior and superior branches. The permanence of electrical disconnection (ie. ablation line continuity) will be verified at least 30 minutes after the last ablation at that vein. 

Roofline ablation will be performed in a continuous motion from the left superior pulmonary vein ostium to the right superior vein ostium as defined by fluoroscopy and 3D navigation. To maintain atrial wall contact, the ablation catheter will be looped within the atrium so that superior torque (ie. pressure on the roof) can be maintained throughout a continuous burn.

Ablation of the coronary sinus musculature and left atrium will be performed both endo- and epicardially through the coronary sinus in an attempt to electrically disconnect (ie. isolate) this structure from the left atrium. For the endocardial approach, the ablation catheter will be dragged along the endocardium of the inferior left atrium after looping the catheter in such a way as to position it parallel to the coronary sinus catheter. The ablation endpoint will be elimination of local endocardial electrograms bordering the mitral annulus. Ablation within the coronary sinus will be performed by starting distally (4 oclock in the left anterior oblique position) and continuously dragged to the ostium, where the coronary sinus empties into the right atrium. Additional point ablation will be performed around the coronary sinus (CS) orifice from the right atrium to ensure its electrical disconnection from the atrial myocardium. The endpoint of epicardial ablation will be the electrical isolation (as represented by the abolition or dissociation of electrograms in the coronary sinus catheter) of the coronary sinus. 

Total procedure duration should be 3-4 hours, inclusive of the time required to isolate the coronary sinus (30 mins).</interventions>
    <comparator>Pulmonary vein isolation, roofline ablation

The control group does not undergo coronary sinus ablation and hence, patients randomized to this arm will have a procedure duration ranging between 2.5-3.5 hours.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arrhythmia free clinical success (without anti-arrhythmic drugs) using a combination of patient symptoms and/or atrial fibrillation (AF) detected on 7 day Holter monitoring at 3 monthly intervals.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 9, 12 months post procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Peri-procedural and long term complications
eg.
Bleeding complications at catheter access site
Pericardial effusions detected via echocardiography
Pulmonary vein stenoses (via cardiac magnetic resonance imaging at 6 months)
Embolic events detected via symptoms and consequent clinical investigations (eg. computed tomography scan)</outcome>
      <timepoint>3, 6, 9, 12 months post procedure</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Slowing of atrial fibrillation on a stable intracardiac catheter placed into the left atrial appendage after pulmonary vein isolation, roofline and coronary sinus ablation.

Termination to sinus rhythm at any stage of ablation via electrocardiography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Slowing of atrial fribrillation will be assessed after each stage of ablation.

Termination to sinus rhythm will be monitored continously throughout the procedure</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Drug refractory patients long-episode/non-lone paroxysmal and persistent atrial fibrillation presenting for a catheter ablation procedure.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Age &lt; 18 years, 
Pregnancy,
Thrombus in left atrium on trans-esophageal echocardiogram,
Patients with lone paroxysmal AF (paroxysms lasting &lt;48 hours) and permanent AF, 
Patients unable to sustain induced AF for &gt; 10 minutes</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Numbered sealed envelopes opened upon consent to the trial and confirmation of exclusion and inclusion criteria.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated block randomised with random block size.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>29/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>5006 to 5116</postcode>
    <postcode>5118</postcode>
    <postcode>5125 to 5174</postcode>
    <postcode>5240 to 5252</postcode>
    <postcode>5000</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>North Terrace
Adelaide
5000
SA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr. Anthony Brooks</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 5, McEwin Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North terrace
Adelaide
5000
S.A.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr. Glenn Young</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 5, McEwin Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North terrace
Adelaide
5000
S.A.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The coronary sinus shares similar morphological and electro-anatomical characteristics to pulmonary veins, which have already been established as arrhythmogenic triggers of AF, but the former structure has received relatively sparse attention. The coronary sinus has been indirectly implicated in atrial arrhythmias; however, no one has systematically assessed the clinical efficacy of ablating this structure in addition to the conventional AF ablation approach.
The study aims to establish irrevocably, in a blinded randomised controlled comparison, whether or not the coronary sinus plays a role in maintaining AF in non-lone/long episode paroxysmal and persistent AF.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital (RAH) Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics Committee, RAH
Level 3, Hanson Institute 
Frome Road
Adelaide, 5000
S.A.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/10/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>080433</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/04/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Anthony Brooks</name>
      <address>Level 5, McEwin Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide 5000
S.A.</address>
      <phone>+61 8  8313 1615</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 2722</fax>
      <email>anthony.brooks@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof. Prashanthan Sanders</name>
      <address>Level 5, McEwin Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide 5000
S.A.</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 2725</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 2722</fax>
      <email>prash.sanders@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Anthony Brooks</name>
      <address>Level 5, McEwin Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide 5000
S.A.</address>
      <phone>+61 8  8313 1615</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 8222 2722</fax>
      <email>anthony.brooks@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>