<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369919">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001181493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An observational study of the efficacy of the Cxbladder a urine test for the detection of urothelial carcinoma in patients presenting with macroscopic or microscopic haematuria.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An observational study of the performance characteristics including Sensitivity and NPV of the Cxbladder urine test for in the detection of urothelial carcinoma in patients presenting with macroscopic or microscopic haematuria


</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1178-4425</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CHT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bladder cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>haematuria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bladder</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This study is an observational study of a molecular diagnostic test, Cxbladder used in the detection of Urothelial Carcinomas (UC) in patients presenting with macroscopic or microscopic haematuria. Cxbladder is a diagnostic urine based test, which quantifies 5 RNA biomarkers present at elevated levels in the urine of patients with UC. A midstream urine sample is collected from the patient as part of standard care. A 5 ml aliquot of this sample is stabilised with Cxbladder proprietary liquid buffer stabilisation solution and sent to a central laboratory for analysis . The remainder of the urine sample may be used for other diagnostic tests as clinically indicated. This is an observational study. The information collected during the study will not be used in any way to influence the clinical evaluation process or decisions made with regard to any patients enrolled in the study.

Samples are analysed and scores determined as below (however no sites are provided with direct patient scores). 
Score &lt;0.12 NPV of 97%, High probability of no urothelial carcinoma
0.12 &lt; Score &lt; 0.23 NPV of 94%,  Low probability of urothelial carcinoma but suggests further clinical investigation needed
Score &gt; 0.23 PPV of 68%, High probability of urothelial carcinoma

The study is observational only and results are only provided to the site after the study is closed and for the purpose of collating data for publication.</interventions>
    <comparator>To determine the performance characteristics (accuracy, sensitivity, specificity, positive and negative predictive values) of the Cxbladder test for the detection of primary UC in patients with a recent history haematuria and who are undergoing investigative cystoscopy. Analysis will be performed on macroscopic and microscopic haematuria cohorts. 

Performance characteristics of Cxbladder will be evaluated with and compared to other clinical sites, and to the results of the published clinical study (J Urology 2012). The current gold standard for comparison of UC detection is cystoscopy plus follow up.

The cystoscopy is the reference test in this study and is conducted the same day as the urine diagnostic test.
During the cystoscopy, samples are collected and pathology conducted to confirm the presence of urothelial carcinoma of the bladder.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The sensitivity and specificity of the Cxbladder test will be compared to cystoscopy results. 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Approximately 100 patients with macroscopic haematuria and 200 patients with microscopic haematuria will participate in the study. The primary timepoint is for analysis is after all participants have completed Cxbladder urine tests and required clinical results and history for each patient is recorded. The estimate for completion of recruitment of 300 patients but is dependent on patient presentation and clinical resources for recruitment. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>None</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patient is undergoing investigative cystoscopies for investigation of recent macroscopic or microscopic haematuria

Patient must be able and willing to comply with study requirements.

Patients must be over 18 years of age.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prior history of urotherial carcinoma.
Prior genitourinary manipulation in the 14 days before urine collection. 
Current or known history of urinary tract inflammatory disorder.
Recent history of glomerulonephritis, nephrosis or other renal inflammatory disorders.
Recent history of pyelonephritis.
Patient is presenting with symptoms indicative of a current urinary tract infection.
Patient is presenting with symptoms indicative of bladder or renal calculi.
Prior history (past 12 months of an episode of macroscopic haematuria with confirmed diagnosis (malignant or otherwise).
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>All enrolled patients that satisfy the protocol requirements will be included in the analysis.
Approximately 100 patients with macroscopic haematuria and 200 patients with microscopic haematuria are required for comparison of the accuracy of Cxbladder and a reference test. Accuracy refers to the difference between specificities plus the difference between sensitivities.

Calculations for performance characteristics and efficacy are given below. Results for macroscopic and microscopic haematuria populations will be calculated separately and as a combined data set.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>10/10/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>4006 - Herston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Pacific Edge Diagnostics Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>60 Ridge Road
Kallista VIC 3791</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Pacific Edge Diagnostics</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>69 Ridge Road
Kallista VIC 3791</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>n/a</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>n/a</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to investigate the diagnostic test accuracy of Cxbladder for diagnosis of bladder cancer in patients presenting with macroscopic or microscopic haematuria. 

Who is it for? 
You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged between 18 years or over and are to undergo an investigative cystoscopy for recent macroscopic or microscopic haematuria (presence of red blood cells in the urine) and do not have a prior history of urothelial carcinoma of the bladder.

Study details 
All participants of this study will provide urine samples just prior to undergoing cystoscopy. These samples will be analysed using Cxbladder diagnostic test and results compared with pathology results from samples collected during cystoscopy. These findings will not be used in treatment decisions but will help establish if Cxbladder test can be used in diagnosis of bladder cancer.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Melbourne Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 6
East
300 Grattan Street
Parkville Victoria</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/MH230</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Paul Anderson</name>
      <address>Urology Department, Royal Melbourne Hospital, Cnr Grattan St and  Royal Parade, Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9342 7294</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9342 8928</fax>
      <email>mr.paul.anderson@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anabela Correia</name>
      <address>Pacific Edge Pty Ltd 
PO Box 2237
Prahran VIC 3181
</address>
      <phone>+61 412 003 606</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anabela.correia@pacificedgedx.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Paul O'Sulivan</name>
      <address>Pacific Edge Ltd
87 St David St
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9016
</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 5800</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 479 5801</fax>
      <email>paul.osullivan@pacificedge.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anabela Correia</name>
      <address>Pacific Edge Pty Ltd
PO Box 2237
Prahran VIC 3181
</address>
      <phone>61 412 003 606</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>anabela.correia@pacificedgedx.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>