<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365588">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000055606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of ultrasound-guided Platelet Rich Plasma injection to promote recovery in athletes with ankle syndesmosis injury. A pilot study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In ankle syndesmosis injury in Rugby Union players, how does a single ultrasound-guided Platelet Rich Plasma injection with conservative therapy compare to conservative therapy alone in terms of ankle pain, function and return to sport? </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Ankle Syndesmosis Sprain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A single platelet-rich plasma (PRP) injection, administered intra-syndesmotically via ultrasound guidance within ten days of the initial ankle syndesmosis injury. This will be performed only once during the trial. Patients receiving the PRP procedure will have blood taken. Four to six blood collection tubes containing citrate will be obtained. Each will be labelled and confirmed with the patient with their correct identifying information.
- They will be centrifuged for 8 minutes at 2500 revolutions per minute. A 22gauge needle will be used to obtain 1-3mL of plasma, which is the platelet rich portion. The syringe of platelet rich plasma obtained will be labelled and confirmed with the patient with their correct identifying information.
- Ultrasound guidance will be used to localise the superficial peroneal nerve in identifying the safest pathway for injection of the anterior inferior tibiofibular ligament of the syndesmosis. 
- Under sterile conditions, a 25 gauge needle will be used to inject 1-2mL local anaesthetic (1% lignocaine) into the skin and superficial tissues. 
- An individualised dose of 2-3mL of the platelet rich plasma will then be injected into the point of the tear as visualised by ultrasound. The injection amount will depend on the size of the defect in the syndesmosis seen on ultrasound, with larger defects accommodating more platelet-rich plasma.
This all occurs in a single session lasting less than thirty minutes.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The results of this study will be compared to a conservatively treated group of 21 Rugby Union players with MRI confirmed ankle syndesmosis injuries, collected from 2011-2012 during a previous investigation (HREC no 13099). Conservative treatment consists of relative rest and graduated return to functional activity as guided by symptoms, monitored by the treating physiotherapist and Dr Katherine Rae, Sports and Exercise Medicine Physician. The results published demonstrated that conservatively treated ankle syndesmosis injuries took four times longer to recover from than lateral ankle sprains (PMID 24002346). Participants in the previous study consented for their data being used for determining the prognosis of recovery following a syndesmosis injury.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Return to function - including return to normal activity, training and match-play. Return to match-play will be recorded as the first competitive match played by the athlete.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Subjects will be followed up for 12 months or until they return to match-play if less than 1 year.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>VAS scores of pain- to assess pain numerically on a scale 0-100.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks post-injury (or 2 weeks after removal of Controlled Ankle Movement boot), and within 1 week of return to match-play. VAS scores will be recorded before and after the testing measures undertaken, in order to assess irritability.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight Bearing Lunge (toe to wall test) to assess loaded dorsiflexion.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks post-injury (or 2 weeks after removal of Controlled Ankle Movement boot), and within 1 week of return to match-play.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vertical Jump- testing how high the athlete can jump using a standardised jumping mat.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks post-injury (or 2 weeks after removal of Controlled Ankle Movement boot), and within 1 week of return to match-play.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Star Excursion Balance- tests the athletes balance whilst they reach with their leg in different directions. Normalised for leg length.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks post-injury (or 2 weeks after removal of Controlled Ankle Movement boot), and within 1 week of return to match-play.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fear Avoidance Beliefs Questionnaire (modified to assess subjects with ankle injury) to assess for behaviours associated with worry and fear because of injury. </outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks post-injury (or 2 weeks after removal of Controlled Ankle Movement boot), and within 1 week of return to match-play.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Illinois Agility Test from both the left and right side of the standardised obstacle set up.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1 week of return to match-play.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Triple Hop- assesses the overall distance from three consecutive jumps on the same leg.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 1 week of return to match-play.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All players (male and female) aged 16 and over from football clubs competing in the Sydney Rugby Union Premiership Competition (all grades and levels) with acute ankle injury and signs of possible syndesmosis injury may participate in the study. They will require MRI confirmed ankle syndesmosis injury to be eligible for enrolment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-	previous ankle surgery
-	inter-current injury that causes more prolonged or severe disability, as judged by medical staff e.g.) knee injury requiring surgery and 6 months rehab
-	non-syndesmosis related injury
-	fracture of the foot or ankle
-	concurrent grade 3 ATFL (anterior talofibular ligament) injury
-	osteochondral defect
-	tibiofibular separation by 4mm on MRI at the level of the talar dome
-	pregnancy (all female participants of childbearing age will require a medical clearance including a urinary pregnancy test at screening)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All consenting enrolled subjects will receive an un-blinded injection of PRP.  </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A t-test analysis will be appropriate to detect statistically significant differences between groups if normally distributed. Otherwise alternative analysis methods will be selected to compare groups.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>27/09/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr David Samra</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Sports Clinic, Crn Western Ave and Physics Rd, The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Institute of Sport
Tim Kelly, Manager
AIS Performance Research
</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 176
BELCONNEN ACT 2616
Australia
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Katherine Rae</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The Sports Clinic, Crn Western Ave and Physics Rd, The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Amy Sman</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Kids Research Institute
The Children's Hospital at Westmead
Kerry Packer Building
Cnr Hawkesbury Rd and Hainsworth St
Westmead NSW 2145</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr James Linklater</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Castlereagh Imaging
60 Pacific Highway,
ST LEONARDS
2065 NSW </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Claire Hiller</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>C43S - S Block Cumberland Campus  
The University of Sydney
Lidcombe
NSW 2141</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Kathryn Refshauge</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>C43A - Jeffrey Miller Admin Building Cumberland Campus  
The University of Sydney
Lidcombe
NSW 2141</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>As a low risk, readily available treatment, PRP injection is becoming an increasingly popular therapeutic adjunct offered by musculoskeletal clinicians. However, there is a clear need to scientifically assess the merits of this treatment option for athletes with ankle syndesmosis injury in order to establish recommendations for evidence-based practice. Since there are no trials that have investigated PRP for ankle syndesmosis injury, this pilot study aims to assess the feasibility of progression to such a higher quality, larger scale trial.

If the treatment is shown to be beneficial, this would be of significant value to competitive and professional athletes who may otherwise require either a prolonged conservative treatment or a surgical treatment requiring at least six weeks of rest from competition.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Margaret Telfer K07
University of Sydney 
NSW 2006
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013/439</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Samra</name>
      <address>The Sports Clinic, Crn Western Ave and Physics Rd, The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+612 477 275 715</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>davidjsamra@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Samra</name>
      <address>The Sports Clinic, Crn Western Ave and Physics Rd, The University of Sydney 
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+612 477 275 715</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>davidjsamra@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Samra</name>
      <address>The Sports Clinic, Crn Western Ave and Physics Rd, The University of Sydney 
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+612 477 275 715</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>davidjsamra@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>David Samra</name>
      <address>The Sports Clinic, Crn Western Ave and Physics Rd, The University of Sydney 
NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+612 477 275 715</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>davidjsamra@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>