<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372909">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/06/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000860369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Shockwave therapy and ultrasound therapy for chronic Achilles tendinopathy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Objective and subjective assessment of the efficacy of radial shock wave therapy and sonotherapy in Achilles tendinopathy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Achilles tendinopathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The main aim of the study is to assess the efficacy of radial shock wave and ultrasound therapies for Achilles tendinopathy. Patients diagnosed with Achilles tendinopathy will be randomly allocated to one of three experimental groups:
Group A: radial shock wave therapy
Group B: ultrasound therapy 
Group C: placebo ultrasound
Group A - radial shock waves will be applied without local aesthesia using ShockMaster 500 (Gymna-Uniphy) with a pneumatic applicator. A gel will be applied on the patients skin in the target area to help conduct the shock waves. The patient will be positioned prone with a roll under ankles and foot dorsiflexion.

Applicator: standard 15 mm applicator, D-Actor vibration applicator.
Pressure: 2.5  4.0 bars.
Number of shocks: 2000-6000.
Frequency: 4  15 Hz.
Number of therapy sessions: 3 (duration of intersession break 4-10 days).
Duration of each session: approximately 7-10 minutes

Group B - sonotherapy will be performed with a device for ultrasound applications  Pulson 400(Gymna). The skin will be coated with  a coupling agent, ie., ultrasound  gel. The patient will be positioned prone with a roll under the ankles. 

Tranducer head size: 4 cm^2.
Ultrasound frequency: 3 MHz.  
Ultrasound power density (spatial average of the density): 0.1  1.5 W/cm^2.
Pulse ratio (duty cycle): 25  100 %.
The duration of a therapy session will depend on the size of the treatment area  each square centimeter will be exposed to ultrasonic energy for 1 to 2.5 minutes. 
Frequency of therapy sessions: everyday, five days a week (except for Saturday and Sunday).
Number of therapy sessions: 10.
Duration of each session: approximately 7-10 minutes


The parameters of the treatment in Group A and in Group B were determined based on our own clinical experience and reasoning, literature review (Val Robertson et al.: Electrotherapy Explained, Principles and Practice, 4th Edition, Elsevier; Król Piotr &amp; Franek Andrzej: Fala uderzeniowa w leczeniu dysfunkcji ukladu narzadów ruchu, Meden 2014) and general principles of application of physical modalities.

Group C quasi sonotherapy will be performed with Pulson 400 (Gymna). The skin will be coated with a coupling agent, ie., ultrasound  gel. The patient will be positioned prone with a roll under ankles. 
All ultrasound device parameters and therapy procedures will be identical as in Group B except that the transducerwill not generate sound waves. The number of therapy sessions will be 10.  

The following measurements will be performed to objectively assess therapy effects: 
I.	Stabilography will be carried out using 2 AMTI AccuSway platforms with integrated sensors to register ground reaction forces and the horizontal torque applied by the subjects feet. 
A two-platform test (Platforms A and B) will consist of 7 trials:
a/ Quiet standing with one foot resting on Platform A and the other on Platform B situated next to Platform A. Two 60-second trials in a quiet standing position will be recorded for each of the two testing conditions: eyes open and eyes closed. 
b/ Two lean-forward trials to the limits of stability (LOS) with movement at the ankles only. The protocol of LOS will consist of three phases: Phase 1  10s of quiet standing (quiet standing with one foot resting on Platform A and the other on Platform B situated next to Platform A); Phase 2  the maximal forward-lean in a self-paced manner; Phase 3  maintenance of the maximal forward-lean.
c/ Two lean-backward trials to the limits of stability (LOS) with movement at the ankles only. The protocol of LOS will consist of three phases: Phase 1  10s of quiet standing (quiet standing with one foot resting on Platform A and the other on Platform B situated next to Platform A); Phase 2  the maximal backward-lean in a self-paced manner; Phase 3  maintenance of the maximal backward-lean.

The step initiation's tests:
d/ Three repetitions: quiet standing on platform A for 15 seconds, then changing to Platform B (1 step) followed by quiet standing for another 15 seconds. The distance between platforms: 10cm.
e/ Three repetitions:quiet standing on Platform A for 15 seconds, then changing to Platform B (1 step) followed by quiet standing for another 15 seconds. A 15-cm obstacle over the edge of the platforms; the distance between platforms: 10 cm. 
f/ Three repetitions  quiet standing on Platform A for 15 seconds, then changing to Platform B (1 step up) followed by quiet standing for another 15 seconds. Platform B is placed on a 17-cm base directly at the edge of Platform A.
g/ Three repetitions  quiet standing on Platform B for 15 seconds, then changing to Platform A (1 step down) followed by quiet standing for another 15 seconds. Platform B is placed on a 17-cm base directly at the edge of Platform A.
The step initiation's tests: The recording of COP displacements will be divided into three phases:
Phase 1  quiet standing before step initiation
Phase 2  transit
Phase 3  quiet standing until measurement completion.
The recording will be divided into phases using an algorithm whose main elements will be foot contact with the platform and the limit of momentary COP displacement; beyond that point exit from stability or stability gain will be observed. Stability is defined as body sway where momentary COP displacement does not exceed average COP displacement plus three standard deviations. For Phase 1, average COP and SD will be calculated based on measurements made within the first 5 sec of the test. For Phase 3  based on the last 5 sec of the test. 

Platform changing will each time start at a sound signal. The procedure of step initiation will be performed twice to make sure that each trial is initiated using alternate limbs. 

II.	Vertical jump (without an arm swing) measurements will be taken on an AMTI AccuSway platform. 
The following trials will be performed:
- countermovement jump (starting position: quiet standing) ,
- squat jump (starting position: knees flexed to 90°). 
In each of the above trials the patients will perform three maximal jumps and three sub-maximal jumps (approximately 50% of the maximum height).
- muscle stiffness test: five maximal countermovement jumps in a row without an arm-swing, with a minimum bend at lower limb joints.

Posturographic measurements, countermovement jump quantification, forward body lean and subjective assessment will be taken prior to therapy and at 1, 6, and 24 weeks of therapy completion. </interventions>
    <comparator>All ultrasound device parameters and therapy procedures in Group C  quasi sonotherapy will be identical as in Group B except that the transducer will not generate sound waves.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This is a composite outcome. 
Measurement parameters of limits of stability (LOS):
-mean value of Center of Pressure (COP) anterior -posterior (AP) position with appropriate index denoting the phase of trial (1, 2 or 3)  
-range (R)  position of COP between the maximal and minimal positions in AP plane in each specific phase 1 (R1), 2 (R2), 3 (R3) 
This outcome will assessed using AMTI platform and Matlab software.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The assessment will be taken prior to therapy and at 1, 6, and 24 weeks of therapy completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This is a composite outcome. Step initiation / making steps under different conditions (with and without an obstacle, stepping up onto a platform situated at a higher level, stepping down onto a platform situated on a lower level).
The following will be determined:
-Center of Pressure (COP) displacement, ie., mean COP, path and velocity of COP signal;
-D1  time from exit from stability state until the foot resting on the other platform
-D2 time from raising the foot from the first platform until gaining stability on the other platform
-double-support period (DSP)  foot contact with both platforms
-Transit time (Phase 2)  time from exit from stability state until gaining post-transit stability; the sum of D1 + DSP + D2
-Step length  distance between double-support site on each platform
This outcome will assessed using AMTI platform and Matlab software.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The assessment will be taken prior to therapy and at 1, 6, and 24 weeks of therapy completion.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This is a composite outcome of measurement parameters of .countermovement jump, squat jump and muscle stiffness tests:
- countermovement jump test:
jump height [cm], flight time [s], index of force differentiation error
- squat jump test: 
jump height [cm], flight time [s], index of force differentiation error 
- muscle stiffness test: 
K -  vertical stiffness [N/m]
KrealF vertical stiffness calculated from platform measurements
KmodelF  vertical stiffness calculated  from flight time and physical model
VtoffR take-off  velocity based on real dynamograph [m/s]
VtoffM  take-off velocity based on flight time and physical model [m/s]
Tflight  flight time [s]
modelFmax  maximum  model value of the vertical ground reaction forces component [N]
realFmax  maximum value of the vertical ground reaction forces component [N] 
dLmodel- centre of mass (COM) lowering (countermovement jump depth) based on model ground reaction forces  [m]
dLreal  centre of mass (COM) lowering (countermovement jump depth)based on real ground reaction forces recording  [m]
This outcome will assessed using AMTI platform and Matlab software.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The assessment will be taken prior to therapy and at 1, 6, and 24 weeks of therapy completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Therapy effect will also be evaluated based on:
- Visual Analogue Scale for Pain (VAS) 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The assessment will be taken prior to therapy and at 1, 6, and 24 weeks of therapy completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This is a composite outcome of COP signal in a quiet standing position.
The measurements of rambling (RM) trajectory : 
-Range, path length, root mean square, standard deviation , velocity, 

The measurements of trembling (TR) trajectory 
-range, path length, root mean square, standard deviation, and velocity.
All calculations will be made for anterior- posterior (AP) and medial-lateral (ML) directions.
This outcome will assessed using AMTI platform and Matlab software.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The assessment will be taken prior to therapy and at 1, 6, and 24 weeks of therapy completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- VISA-A function score (Victorian Institute of Sport Assessment Achilles questionnaire)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The assessment will be taken prior to therapy and at 1, 6, and 24 weeks of therapy completion. 
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>- subjective 4-point assessment of pain and limitations of activity after therapy (Roles and Maudsley score).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The assessment will be taken prior to therapy and at 1, 6, and 24 weeks of therapy completion. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- symptoms of pain of the Achilles tendon over 3 months duration
- tendon abnormalities identified on ultrasound
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-	candidates under 18 years of age
-	pregnancy
-	thrombophlebitis
-	atherosclerosis
-	renal failure
-	local lower limb infection
-	neoplastic disease
-	history of Achilles tendon surgery
-	knee instability
-	ankle instability
-	lower extremity length discrepancy
-	lower extremity cellulitis
-	anticoagulant therapy
-	physical therapy during 6 weeks preceding the study
-	corticosteroid injections during 6 weeks preceding the study 
-	type 1 diabetes mellitus and type 2 diabetes mellitus with insulin therapy
-	rheumatoid arthritis and other rheumatoid disease
-	cardiac pacemaker
-	cardiac arrhythmia
-	cardiovascular insufficiency
-	patellar tendinitis
-	bilateral Achilles tendinopathy
-	history of stroke (ischemic, hemorrhagic)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Determination of sample size

We assum the probability of a type I error a = 0.05, target power of 1-beta = 0.80 and a 25% minimum significant difference between the means of parameters studied. The resultant minimum sample size is 12 patients. The target sample size is 36; 3 additional participants will be recruited to account for dropouts. The study participants will be randomly assigned to 3 groups. Data analysis will be performed with Statistica, version 10. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/03/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/03/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Jerzy Kukuczka Academy of Physical Education</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Mikolowska 72, 40-065 Katowice, Poland </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Poland</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Jerzy Kukuczka Academy of Physical Education</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Mikolowska 72, 40-065 Katowice, Poland 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Poland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Tendinopathies are among the most common musculoskeletal system disorders, mainly in the population of manual workers and athletes. Achilles tendinopathy hampers engagement in intense physical activity and causes patients to seek effective treatment. Physical therapy is a valuable component of a complex intervention program facilitating the achievement of the desired outcomes. The main objective of the study is to determine and compare the efficacy of radial shock wave therapy and sonotherapy for Achilles tendinopathy.
Candidates qualified for the study will be randomly allocated to one of three experimental groups: Group A will receive radial shock wave therapy, Group B ultrasound therapy and Group C placebo ultrasound.
Posturographic measurements, countermovement jump quantification, forward body lean and subjective assessment will be taken prior to therapy and at 1, 6, and 24 weeks of therapy completion.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Research Ethics Committee from The Jerzy Kukuczka Academy of Physical Education in Katowice </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Mikolowska 72, 40-065 Katowice 
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5/2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Poland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Stania Magdalena</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy, The Jerzy Kukuczka Academy of Physical Education, Mikolowska 72, 40-065 Katowice, Poland</address>
      <phone>+48694979640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.stania@awf.katowice.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Stania Magdalena</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy, The Jerzy Kukuczka Academy of Physical Education, Mikolowska 72, 40-065 Katowice, Poland</address>
      <phone>+48694979640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.stania@awf.katowice.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Stania Magdalena</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy, The Jerzy Kukuczka Academy of Physical Education, Mikolowska 72, 40-065 Katowice, Poland</address>
      <phone>+48694979640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.stania@awf.katowice.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Stania Magdalena</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy, The Jerzy Kukuczka Academy of Physical Education, Mikolowska 72, 40-065 Katowice, Poland</address>
      <phone>+48694979640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.stania@awf.katowice.pl</email>
      <country>Poland</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>