<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368058">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000225516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot randomised open-label taste-testing study to evaluate the acceptability of chocolate-based midazolam in children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study comparing taste and adherence to administration of a midazolam chocolate formulation compared to the standard hospital midazolam solution used as a premedication prior to general anaesthesia for surgical procedures in children aged 3 to 16 years of age. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Children needing a sedating premedication prior to general anaesthesia for a surgical procedure</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anaesthetics</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will be recruited at the pre anaesthetic review prior to the procedure once the treating anaesthetist advises that the patient will be prescribed midazolam as a pre medication. 
The participants will be randomised to receive either the chocolate tablet formulation of midazolam (5mg mini tablet with score lines for dose division) or the hospital standard IV solution of midazolam (5mg/ml injection Pfizer) by mouth as prescribed by treating anaesthetist. This injection solution is what is currenlty used clinically in the hospital and it is given by mouth. The dose of the midazolam to be administered will be determined by the treating anaesthetist based on the patients weight and clinical status.
Compliance of taking the drug as well as a scale scored by the child and the parent on how much he/she likes/dislikes the sample will be recorded. 
If the child spits out the dose immediately, the treating anaesthetist will decide in line with current routine management, whether a second dose is required. If the second dose is recommended, the treating anaesthetist along with the parent/child will decide upon the same dosage form or the alternative form. The time to onset of sedation (clinical effect of midazolam) will be also recorded.
The pharmacokinetic parameters of the chocolate-based midazolam tablet and the IV midazolam solution will be evaluated using a validated HPLC assay for midazolam and a flexible blood sampling protocol.</interventions>
    <comparator>Comparator is the currently used hospital standard IV solution of midazolam (Pfizer). This will be administered into the mouth. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean visual analogue scale scores from the participants and their parents to evaluate taste adherence.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded after administration of the midazolam.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of children who spat out the dose</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded at the time of the administration of the midazolam.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of children willing to take the alternative </outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded at the time of the administration of the midazolam.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of children willing to consume the assigned dosage form again</outcome>
      <timepoint>Recorded at the time of the administration of the midazolam.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>This study also aims to evaluate the pharmacokinetic parameters of the chocolate-based midazolam tablets in children. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The first sample will be collected as soon as possible after the child is asleep (approximately 30 minutes or slightly earlier after taking midazolam). The second and third samples will be collected between 45-60 minutes and 90-120 minutes respectively. The final sample will be collected as late as possible, before the procedure is completed.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male or female, 3 to 16 years of age undergoing a wide range of surgical procedures requiring a general anaesthetic.
Treating anaesthetist consider that pre-procedural midazolam is required
Obtained informed parental or guardian consent and child assent where appropriate
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Allergic to chocolate (chocolate base does not contain nuts)
Allergic to midazolam
Unable to understand the information sheet and the consent form
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients will be recruited at the pre-anaesthetic review. Only patients who meet the inclusion criteria for the study will be enrolled and only after informed consent is given voluntarily by the parent/guardian and by the patient if appropriate.
The patients will be randomised by computer generated block randomisation. Following written informed consent, the participant will be assigned the next available Participant Number. The Participant Number will correspond to a numbered randomisation envelope. The
randomisation is concealed in the closed envelope and will only be opened by the administering nurse at the time of  administration of the midazolam. The participant number will be used to identify the patient for the duration of the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated block randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This pilot study will apply the Wilcoxon-Mann-Whitney statistical test to test our hypothesis. We estimate that, with the effect size d=0.5 and alpha=0.05, we will have 80% power to detect a difference with 67 children in each group. Given that some children may drop out of this study, we will recruit 75 children in each group. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/06/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/08/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>18/11/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>150</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>23/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Margaret Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Princess Margaret Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Roberts Road
Subiaco 
WA 6008</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Princess Margaret Hospital Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>68 Hay Street
Subiaco
WA 6008
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>ANZCA - Australia New Zealand College of Anaesthetists</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Australian and New Zealand College of Anaesthetists
ANZCA House,
630 St Kilda Road,
Melbourne, Victoria 3004,
Australia.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Laurence Cheung</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital
Roberts Road
Subiaco
WA 6008</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Britta Regli-Von Ungern-Sternberg</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Princess Margaret Hospital
Roberts Road
Subiaco
WA 6008</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To achieve the benefits of a medicine, the patient must be willing to take it in the correct amount at the appropriate time. Most medicines are not formulated for use in children. For those that are, few are considered sufficiently palatable. Lack of palatability can be attributed to poor taste and, for children below 6 years, the inability to swallow solid medicines, such as tablets.

Midazolam is a highly effective oral sedative and pre-procedural medicine for children and adolescents. The lack of an oral commercial product in Australia has led the local hospitals to administer midazolam injection solution which has a foul taste and is often rejected by the children. Inadequate sedation presents difficulties in children who are very anxious or uncooperative in the preoperative setting (e.g. children with autism). Uncooperative children have then to be held down and restrained for the induction of anaesthesia, which is traumatizing for the child and the family. In adolescents, this can also pose significant safety risks for the attending staff.

We believe that chocolate-based mini tablets can effectively provide palatable formulations for bitter drugs such as midazolam to assist clinicians achieve the desired therapeutic outcomes in paediatric patients.
The aims of this project are:
1.	To evaluate the rate of acceptance of the chocolate-based midazolam tablets in children (age 3-16) required pre-procedural midazolam
2.	To evaluate the pharmacokinetic prarameters of the chocolate-based midazolam tablets in children

We have developed prototype chocolate tablets measuring 0.5 x 1 x 0.5 cm that can mask the taste of the highly bitter drug. The aims of this project are to perform further clinical evaluations on these formulations to fully realise the potential of midazolam for preprocedural sedation and anxiolysis of sick children in WA.

This study will pave the way for the scaled up manufacture of chocolate-based midazolam tablets for use in WA paediatric hospital wards, and the adaptation of the chocolate base for the formulation of other bitter drugs (e.g. antibiotics). Pharmaceutically, the chocolate tablets, which are prepared without water, will provide more stable products for labile drugs than liquid mixtures. They are also more convenient and cheaper to store and transport than bulky liquid formulations.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Margaret Hospital Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Roberts Road
Subiaco
WA 6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EP/2014102</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/10/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Laurence Cheung</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital
Pharmacy Department
Roberts Road
Subiaco
WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 8206</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Laurence.Cheung@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Laurence Cheung</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital
Pharmacy Department
Roberts Road
Subiaco
WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 8206</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Laurence.Cheung@telethonkids.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Britta Regli-von Ungern-Sternberg</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital
Department of Anaesthesia and Pain Managment
Roberts Road
Subiaco
WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 8109</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Britta.Regli-VonUngern@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Lliana Slevin</name>
      <address>Princess Margaret Hospital
Department of Anaesthesia Research
Roberts Road
Subiaco
WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9340 8109</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lliana.slevin@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>