<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81550">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/08/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/01/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000040460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised clinical trial (RCT) of the effect of Neuro-Emotional Technique (NET) on the clinical manifestations of primary overt hypothyroidism</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised clinical trial (RCT) of the effect of Neuro-Emotional Technique (NET) on the clinical manifestations of primary overt hypothyroidism</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hypothyroidism</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic and endocrine disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Neuro-Emotional Technique (NET) Neuro-Emotional Technique is a technique used by chiropractors which is similar to Cognitive behavioural therapy (CBT). Participants in the treatment group will receive 10 NET treatments over a period of 6 weeks. The treatments will last for approximately 5-20 mins in duration.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the placebo (sham) intervention group will receive a non-therapeutic sham intervention. This placebo intervention mimics the NET protocol with the purported therapeutic components removed and replaced with innocous steps. The placebo intervention will be administered at the same frequency as the treatment group.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the influence of Neuro-Emotional Technique (NET) on the clinical manifestations of individuals with primary overt hypothyroidism. Outcome measures include: Depression scores as measured by the Depression, Anxiety, Stress (DASS) questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at the beginning of the trial, and at 6 weeks and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Basal Temperature (BT) measurement</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures will be performed every day for the duration of the trial (6 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Basal Heart Rate (BHR) measurement</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures will be performed every day for the duration of the trial (6 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self report daily health and well being questionniare.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures will be performed every day for the duration of the trial (6 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the influence of Neuro-Emotional Technique (NET) on the clinical manifestations of individuals with primary overt hypothyroidism. Outcome measures include measurement of Anxiety and Stress using the DASS questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at the beginning of the trial, and at 6 weeks and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the influence of Neuro-Emotional Technique (NET) on the clinical manifestations of individuals with primary overt hypothyroidism. Outcome measures include: Serum thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at the beginning of the trial, and at 6 weeks and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the influence of Neuro-Emotional Technique (NET) on the clinical manifestations of individuals with primary overt hypothyroidism. Outcome measures include: Serum thyroxine (T4)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at the beginning of the trial, and at 6 weeks and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the influence of Neuro-Emotional Technique (NET) on the clinical manifestations of individuals with primary overt hypothyroidism. Outcome measures include: Serum Triiodothyronine (T3)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at the beginning of the trial, and at 6 weeks and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the influence of Neuro-Emotional Technique (NET) on the clinical manifestations of individuals with primary overt hypothyroidism. Outcome measures include: Serum Thyroid peroxidase antibodies (anti-TPO)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at the beginning of the trial, and at 6 weeks and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the influence of Neuro-Emotional Technique (NET) on the clinical manifestations of individuals with primary overt hypothyroidism. Outcome measures include: Serum Thyroglobulin antibodies (anti-TG)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at the beginning of the trial, and at 6 weeks and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the influence of Neuro-Emotional Technique (NET) on the clinical manifestations of individuals with primary overt hypothyroidism. Outcome measures include: Short Form -36 (SF-36) questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at the beginning of the trial, and at 6 weeks and 6 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Hypothyroid sufferers.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Iatrogenic hypothyroidism, &lt; 18 years, significant co-morbidities, Deaf/mute, Non-English speaking, Serious illness/mental illness, Pregnant, Individuals recently diagnosed (within the last 6 months) with hypothyroidism, medications that are known to influence thyroid function other than standard meds for hypothyroidism.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Person responsible for applying inclusion/exclusion criteria was not aware of the group to which the participant would be allocated. Participants are not advised which group they have been allocated. Central randomisation performed by phone /computer well after participants have been accepted into the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>Using random.org This is a web site which assists the randomisation of participants by providing a true random sequence generator</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Doube blind. Participants are blind as to the group they have been allocated (treatment or sham). In addition, the assessors (pathologists) are blind to the allocation. The data analyst is also blinded to the status of the participants.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/12/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>102</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Rod Bonello</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Chiropractic, Macquarie University, NSW 2109</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Spinal Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Australian Spinal Research Foundation (ASRF)
PO Box 1047
Springwood QLD 4127
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project is a comparative study investigating the effects of Neuro-Emotional Technique (NET) treatment on Hypothyroidism. Hypothyroidism is defined as any condition that results in a decrease in the amount of circulating thyroid hormones in the body. NET is a therapeutic procedure developed by Chiropractors as an adjunct to standard Chiropractic techniques. The development and structure of this technique ties in with the biopsychosocial model of health care, which represents a holistic approach to patient management. General aims: -To determine the effect of Neuro-Emotional Technique (NET) in the treatment and management of primary hypothyroidism. Specific Aims: - To determine the emotional/ psychological/ social/ hormonal profile of a group of primary overt hypothyroid participants. - To determine if the emotional/psychological/ social/hormonal profile of a group of primary overt hypothyroid participants changes with NET treatment. - To determine if primary overt hypothyroidism can be affected by NET treatment in the short term (2 months) and the medium term (6 months) Interpretation of Results and Discussion Accumulated data will be statistically analysed using T-tests, longitudinal analysis with an alpha value of 0.05</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1) Brown BT, Bonello R, Pollard H. The biopsychosocial model and hypothyroidism Chiropractic &amp; Osteopathy 2005, 13:5 

2) Brown BT, Bonello R, Pollard H. The use of Traditional Chinese Medical Principles in Chiropractic Technique Chiropr J Aust 2008, 38: 18-26

3) Brown, BT, Bonello R, Pollard H. Response to a letter to the editor Re:The use of Traditional Chinese Medical Principles in Chiropractic Technique Chiropr J Aust 2008, 38: 18-26. in Chiropr J Aust 2008, 39:122

4) Brown BT, Bonello R, Pollard H, Graham, P. The influence of a biopsychosocial-based treatment approach on the clinical manifestations of primary overt hypothyroidism: a protocol for a pilot study Trials 2010, 11:106

Conference Proceedings
1) Brown BT. A Biopsychosocial Approach to Hypothyroidism Third International Congress of Complementary Medicine Research 29-31 March 2008, Sydney Australia</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University Human Ethics Committee-Macquarie University Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Benjamin Brown</name>
      <address>Department of Chiropractic, Macquarie University, 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9850 7694</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 9850 6565</fax>
      <email>benjamin.brown@students.mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Benjamin Brown</name>
      <address>Department of Chiropractic, Macquarie University, 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 02 9850 7694</phone>
      <fax>+61 02 9850 6565</fax>
      <email>benjamin.brown@students.mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>