<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366990">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000972628</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pragmatic randomised trial of an intervention to increase childcare service implementation of healthy eating and physical activity promoting policies and practices</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The impact of a review and feedback intervention to increase the healthy eating and physical activity policy and practices in centre based child care versus standard care</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Childhood overweight and obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention will seek to increase service implementation of healthy eating and physical activity policies and practices consistent with best practice Australian healthy eating and physical activity guidelines for the childcare setting, and evidence reviews of policies and practices shown to be associated with child healthy eating and physical activity

Five performance review and feedback cycles will be provided to nominated supervisors across a period of 10 months. Each performance review and feedback cycle will include a written feedback report and one telephone feedback discussion.  The review process will require services nominated supervisor (or other identified lead educator) to complete a brief telephone survey regarding current implementation of the targeted policies and practices. Using this information, feedback will be provided by a support officer (via a face-to-face visit for cycle 1 and by telephone in following cycles. 

 Services will also receive quarterly interactive email newsletters which will communicate key messages relating to the healthy eating and physical activity policies and practices. 

The intervention aims to facilitate the following policies and practice changes   

1. Policies: Service will be supported to develop and implement three policies; nutrition policy, physical activity policy and small screen recreation policy (if they have a TV on site). 
2. Provision of information to families:  Services will be supported to provide information to families from registered health authority about healthy eating, physical activity, limiting screen time. 
3.  Engagement in Daily fundamental movement skill (FMS) development: Services will be supported to implement a daily fundamental movement skill component into their program. 
4. Healthy eating learning experiences: Services will be supported to engage children in a healthy eating learning experience two times per week. 
5. Appropriate drinks: Services will be supported to provide appropriate drinks for children every day (only water and plain milk and reduced fat milk for children over 2 years of age. 
6. Small screen recreation: Services will be supported to use small screen recreation within their service appropriately, by limiting use for 3  5 year olds for educational purposes. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual support - consisting of standard staff development opportunities regarding child health and development which could include staff training or resources.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The change in prevalence of all targeted service policies and practices from baseline to immediately following the intervention as assessed via telephone interview with Nominated Supervisor/ or key service contact. 

Specifically, the policies and practices to be measured include:  
i.Service policy (nutrition, physical activity and small screen recreation 
ii.Service provides information to families (healthy eating, physical activity, small screen time and breast feeding, where relevant).
iii.Service provides structured and specific learning experiences about healthy eating at least two times/week 
iv.Service supplies age appropriate drinks to children 
v.Service provides fundamental movement skills activities for children aged 3-5 years every day to at least 90% of children
vi.Service limits use of small screen recreation by children aged 3-5 years for educational purposes and learning experiences  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 1 month after the completion of the intervention </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Centre based child care services: eligible services within the Hunter, Taree and New England geographical areas of NSW Australia will be invited to participate. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria include:
*Services already involved in an alternative randomised controlled trial currently underway in the Hunter New England Area Health Service;
*Services already implementing healthy eating and physical activity policies to a high standard (as defined by a government region wide surveillance system) (state-wide program)
*Services catering exclusively for children requiring specialist care; Mobile preschools, Department of Education and Communities preschools.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Study information and consent forms will be mailed to services approximately 2 weeks before a telephone call from a research assistant requesting consent to participate in data collection. Randomisation will occur after baseline data collection and will be carried out centrally using a random number function in Mircosoft Excel. </concealment>
    <sequence>Services will be randomised in a 1:1 ratio to either an intervention or control group by an independent statistician using a computerised random number function . </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/08/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>25/09/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>25/09/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>165</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hunter New England Population Health </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Longworth Ave, Wallsend, NSW, 2287 
Australia 
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hunter New England Population Health </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Longworth Ave, Wallsend, NSW, 2287 
Australia 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Newcastle</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University Dr, Callaghan NSW 2308</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Implementing initiatives to promote healthy eating and physical activity in childcare services has been identified as a priority to prevent excessive child weight gain. Despite this, few trials have been conducted to assess the effectiveness of interventions to support population-wide implementation of such initiatives. The aim of this study is to assess the effectiveness and acceptability of a performance review and feedback intervention, targeting childcare service staff, in increasing the implementation of healthy eating and physical activity promoting policies and practices.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 1, New Lambton NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/09/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>06/07/26/4.04</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Meghan Finch</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked bag 10
Wallsend, NSW, 2287
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49246131</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Meghan.finch@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Luke Wolfenden</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked bag 10
Wallsend, NSW, 2287
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4985 5168</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>luke.wolfenden@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Meghan Finch</name>
      <address>Hunter New England Population Health
Locked bag 10
Wallsend, NSW, 2287</address>
      <phone>+61 2 49246131</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Meghan.finch@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>