<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363053">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/09/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001030864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Grasp rehabilitation with motor imagery after spinal cord injury</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In quadriplegic patients with chronic non-evolutive motor impairments does motor rehabilitation including mental training with motor imagery improve residual upper limb motor functions through the induction of cerebral reorganizations potentially reflected during motor imagery?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1134-6932</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Spinal cord injuries</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Mental practice with motor imagery, whereby participants visualise themselves grasping objects. Different motor imagery modalities are used (e.g. visual, kinesthetic, etc.) focusing various tenodesis grasping skills (e.g. different seizes of objects, contralateral and ipsilateral tenodesis grasping actions.. etc.). Administration mode: one-on-one supervision by a physiotherapist. Frequency and duration of mental practice sessions: SCI patients underwent 3×30 minutes sessions per week for 5 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Posttest level is compared with the baseline pretests level (i.e. before rehabiltiative interventions with mental training) in spinal cord injured patients. Age and sex-matched healthy control participants follow similar a repeated pretests and posttest assessments procedure. They do not recieve rehabilitative interventions but a control task (i.e. playing cards with a physiotherapist 3×30 minutes per week for 5 weeks).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Kinematic analysis of tenodesis grasp actions</outcome>
      <timepoint>At weeks 1, 3 and 5 following inclusion and at weeks 1 and 8 following intervention. Experimental intervention is administered during weeks 6 to 10 relative to patient's inclusion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Magnetoencephalographic cerebral activity during imagined and executed tenodesis grasp actions</outcome>
      <timepoint>At weeks 1, 3 and 5 following inclusion and at weeks 1 and 8 following intervention. Experimental intervention is administered during weeks 6 to 10 relative to inclusion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Autonomic nervous system (i.e. heart rate and electrodermal activity) activity during imagined and executed tenodesis grasp actions. We used an autonomic nervous system acquisition device (E-MOTION) and recorded the electrocardiogram. We also recorded skin resistance responses, using two 50 mm2 unpolarizable Ag/AgCl electrodes (Clark Electromedical Instruments, Ref. E243) placed on upper limb regions correponding where sympathetic innervation was spared by the neurological lesion. Isotonic conductive paste was used to improve skin/electrode contact. Skin resistance was recorded with 15 uA current (current density=0.5 uA/mm2).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At weeks 1, 3 and 5 following inclusion and at weeks 1 and 8 following intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motor imagery ability assessment with mental chronometry</outcome>
      <timepoint>At weeks 1, 3 and 5 following inclusion and at weeks 1 and 8 after experimental intervention. Experimental intervention is administered during weeks 6 to 10 relative to inclusion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motor imagery ability assessment with the Kinesthetic and Visual Imagery Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>At week 1 following inclusion, before the first kinematic analysis and magnetoencephalographic recording.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physiotherapy and occupational therapy functional motor assessments</outcome>
      <timepoint>At weeks 1, 3 and 5 following inclusion and at weeks 1 and 8 after experimental intervention. Experimental intervention is administered during weeks 6 to 10 relative to inclusion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(i) Quadriplegia elicited by traumatic SCI at the C6/C7 level
(ii) Complete infra-lesional motor deficit (score &lt; 20/100 on the ASIA impairment scale) (iii) Time post-injury superior or equal to 6 months, with non-evolutive general, motor and sensory deficit</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>(i) Non-stabilized HTN or pathological autonomous nervous system dysfunction (e.g. orthostatic hypotension) (ii) Cerebral damage and/or cognitive deficit (iii) Elbow or shoulder joint amplitude restriction, upper limb para osteo-arthropathy (iv)Presence of metallic objects within the body (e.g. pacemaker, auditory device) incompatible with neuroimaging recordings (v) Participation to another research program</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients were hospitalized after traumatic cervical spinal cord injury. The head medical doctor responsible for patient's hospitalization and medical care delivery checked that participants met the inclusion criteria, and informed of the possibility to participate in a rehabilitation research program. Participants provided written informed consent according to the statements and principles of the Declaration of Helsinki.
Healthy control participants matched according to genre and age to the patients also participated in the trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>SCI patients were systematically allocated to the treatment group. Healthy control participants matched according to genre and age to the patients were assigned to the control group.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Due to ethical reasons, we could not deprive voluntarily SCI patients from the treatment condition so as to constitute a patient control group. Indeed, there is a rich scientific background supporting the therapeutical relevance of motor imagery interventions in the management of motor rehabilitation in neurological populations.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>8</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>France</country>
      <state>Rhone Alpes</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universite Claude Bernard Lyon 1 - CRIS EA 647</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>27-29 Boulevard du 11 Novembre 1918
69622 Villeurbanne Cedex</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>France</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Hospices Civils de Lyon</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5 place d'Arsonval 
69437 Lyon cedex 03</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>France</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Hopital Henri Gabrielle (Neurological Rehabilitation)</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>20 Route de Vourles 
69230, Saint Genis Laval</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>France</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>CERMEP Imagerie du vivant - Departement MEG</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Centre Hospitalier Le Vinatier 
95 Boulevard Pinel
69500 Bron</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>France</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Grasp function is severely impaired after quadriplegia elicited by traumatic spinal cord injury. Patients can learn a modified type of grasp called tenodesis, where pinch grip is generated by active wrist extension (a movement spared by the lesion below the C6-C7 level). We investigate whether mental training with motor imagery can improve tenodesis grasp function in quadriplegic patients. Using magnetoencephalography, we seek to delineate whether mental training can induce cerebral reorganizations enabling functional motor recovery. We also investigate whether the neural networks mediating motor imagery are reorganized due to motor rehabilitation with mental training.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite de Protection des Personnes Sud-Est II</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hopital Hotel-Dieu, place de l'Hopital, porte 16 
69288 Lyon Cedex 02</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/04/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>France</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Di Rienzo Franck</name>
      <address>27-29 Boulevard du 11 Novembre
69622 Villeurbanne Cedex</address>
      <phone>+33 4 72432734</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>franck.di-rienzo@etu.univ-lyon1.fr</email>
      <country>France</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Di Rienzo Franck</name>
      <address>27-29 Boulevard du 11 Novembre
69622 Villeurbanne Cedex</address>
      <phone>+33 4 72432734</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>franck.di-rienzo@etu.univ-lyon1.fr</email>
      <country>France</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Di Rienzo Franck</name>
      <address>27-29 Boulevard du 11 Novembre
69622 Villeurbanne Cedex</address>
      <phone>+33 4 72432734</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>franck.di-rienzo@etu.univ-lyon1.fr</email>
      <country>France</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>