<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367096">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001134617</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised Controlled Clinical Trial comparing C-MAC (Trademark) Videolaryngoscope Intubation with Direct Laryngoscope Intubation in Neonates. The HEADS UP Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In neonates is intubation with videolaryngoscope superior to conventional laryngoscope for first attempt success.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The HEADS UP Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Endotracheal intubation in neonates.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Endotracheal intubation using Storz C-MAC (Trademark) Videolaryngoscope Miller blade size 0 or 1. The C-MAC has a tiny digital video camera and light source built into the tip of the blade and handle, allowing indirect vision of the glottis. The camera enables a magnified image to be displayed on a small monitor. The operator keeps their head up watching the monitor during the intubation procedure. Duration times for intubation vary from between 20-60secs.</interventions>
    <comparator>Endotracheal intubation using standard laryngoscope Miller blade 0 or 1.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>First attempt success rate. Intubation success is defined as endotracheal tube placement confirmed by end-tidal CO2 detection.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Primary outcome is assessed during intubation.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of intubation attempt. Defined as the time from when the laryngoscope blade passes the lips until it is removed and intubation is either successful or abandoned and infant returned to mask ventilation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During intubation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of intubations occurring within 30second American Academy of Pediatric guidelines.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During intubation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stability of infant during the intubation. Measured by the length of time of hypoxia, based on infants saturations and heart rate. Infants will be monitored by use of Massimo pulse oximeter and ECG chest leads.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During intubation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of complications related to intubation. Trauma to lips, gums, pharynx, lacerations or perforation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After intubation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of the videplaryngoscope by the operator. Qualitative information will be recorded based on ease of use and view of glottis. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After intubation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Babies born at 24 completed weeks gestation and above, and require endotracheal intubation in the delivery room or delivery theatre. Infants requiring endotracheal intubation in the neonatal intensive care unit.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Hours</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Infants with major oral or upper airway malformation will be excluded from the analysis.
Any emergency intubation where there is insufficient time to prepare the videolaryngoscope.
Any emergency intubation without sufficient time to prepare randomisation.
Babies &lt;24 weeks gestation at the time of intubation due to limitation of blade size.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The inclusion and exclusion criteria will be checked. The allocation will be concealed in sequentially numbered opaque envelopes. The most senior staff member will take the next sealed envelope to the delivery. Once it is known the baby will be intubated, the person performing the intubation will be decided upon, then the envelope will be opened to reveal allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Allocation will be by permuted block randomisation. It will be a stratified randomisation based on gestation to ensure the randomisation is evenly spread across gestation groups. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To the best of our knowledge there have been no randomised controlled trials assessing videolaryngoscope intubation at delivery or in a NICU on which to base a sample size on. This NICU does not have a record of intubation success rates from which a sample size can be calculated. In a previous published study by ODonnell et al, during neonatal resuscitation using a standard laryngoscope, the overall success rate including all levels of experience, was 62%. If we base the sample size on these success rates and hope to improve first attempt success rates by 20% overall, to detect a difference between a rate of 55% in the direct intubation (control) group to 75% in the videolaryngoscope (intervention) group, 168 patients (84 in each group) will be required to achieve a power of 80% with a type 1 error rate of 5%. To detect an absolute difference of 20% and RRR 36.7%.
The demographic factors and clinical characteristics will be summarised with counts (percentages) for categorical variables, mean (standard deviation, SD) for normally distributed continuous variables or median (interquartile range, IQR or minimum-maximum) if the distribution is skewed.
The primary outcome, first time success (yes or no), will be analysed using logistic regression conducted within a generalised estimating equations (GEE) framework to account for the correlation in the data due to staff members performing more than one intubation. The outputs produced will be the odds ratio (95% confidence interval) and a p-value for the test that the odds ratio is different from 1. Pre-specified subgroups will be examined for the primary outcome: gestational age at time of intubation, weight at time of intubation (&lt;1000g, 1001-1500g, 1501-2500g, &gt;2500g), location at intubation (DS or NICU), premedication, nasal or oral tube insertion and level of experience of the person performing the intubation. This will be done to look at any difference in effect by these factors on success rate. The statistician will be blinded as to which group was the intervention.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>170</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Missenden Road</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Prince Alfred Hosital, Department of Newborn Care</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown
2050
NSW</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Department of Newborn Care</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown
2050
NSW</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>When a neonate requires intubating it needs to occur quickly. Successful intubation can be challenging in small infants. It entails visualization of the glottis followed by insertion of the endotracheal tube through the cords, in a timely manner with minimal compromise to the infant. The current method is to use a laryngoscope to allow direct vision of the vocal cords. Direct vision requires a line of sight along the laryngoscope blade with a light source to view the vocal cords. In the neonate achieving a good view can be a challenge. The videolaryngoscope enables an excellent view of the glottis and its use has been widely studied in adults and paediatric surgical patients. Although many neonatal intensive care units (NICUs) have integrated the use of this tool into standard care, there is limited evidence for its use in neonates. Intubation is a specialised skill and takes time to learn. The more attempts and longer it takes to intubate can potentially impact on an infant due to hypoxia or local trauma. We need to expand our knowledge of the safety of this instrument in acute neonatal care, value in the usefulness of the tool and determine its potential for teaching. If the videolaryngoscope is superior to the standard method, then its use may become even more widely implemented.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 11, KGV Building
Missenden Road 
Camperdown 2050
NSW</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/09/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Bellhouse</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Care
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61295158459</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Sarah.Bellhouse@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Bellhouse</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Care
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61295158459</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Sarah.Bellhouse@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Bellhouse</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Care
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61295158459</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Sarah.Bellhouse@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Bellhouse</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Care
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61295158459</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Sarah.Bellhouse@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>