<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369944">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000795493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Role of isothermic irrigation on preservation of body temperature in endoscopic ureteral stone surgery under spinal anesthesia</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Role of isothermic irrigation on preservation of body temperature in endoscopic ureteral stone surgery under spinal anesthesia</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1181-2982</utrn>
    <trialacronym>IIEUSSBT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Preservation of body temperature in ureteral stone surgery under spinal anesthesia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other renal and urogenital disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>the patients were randomly divided into two groups by sealed envelope technique. the irrigation fluid was given at room temperature to the control group and the irrigation fluid for the study group was at body temperature. the irrigation fluid was heated by an incubator set at 37 celcius degrees and was protected in a non permenant heat protecting bag. The temperature of the irrigation solution was controlled by a digital thermometer by the study stuff. Room temperature, patient's body temperature were recorded before spinal anesthesia. Spinal anesthesia was performed by an anesthesiologist who was unaware of the heat of the irrigation fluid at L4-L5 interspace with 15mg 0.5% hyperbaric bupivacaine. the body temperature and the hemodynamic parameters were recorded each minute for the first 10 minutes and at 5 minute intervals till 30 minute after spinal anesthesia and at the end of the operation. the spinal anesthesia was monitored with loss of sensation to pinprick test at midclavicular line and recorded at the same time points with temperature measurements. </interventions>
    <comparator>Irrigation at room temperature was the control group, which is the standard care. The room temperature is set at 21 degrees celcius and monitored by a thermometer continiously.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body temperature of the patient was monitored with a tympanic digital thermometer. </outcome>
      <timepoint>measurement time points started with the patients' entering to operation room which was basal body temperature and continued each minute for 10 minutes after spinal anesthesia and every 5 minutes till 30 minutes after spinal anesthesia and at the end of the operation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>affect of  irrigation fluid temperature on surgical comfort is assessed by a questionare  completed by the surgeon (1: worse than conventional , 0: there is no difference when compared to cenventional technique, 2: better than conventional technique) at the end of the surgery. conventional technique is the technique regularly used for this surgery  in our clinic before the study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of the surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>affect of irrigation fluid temperature on shivering of the patient. Shivering is assessed by the study staff with a scale (0: no shivering, 1: no shivering but piloerection and/or vasoconstriction present, 2: muscle activity at single muscle group, 3: muscle activity at more than one muscle group, 4: total body shivering) </outcome>
      <timepoint>assessment of shivering started with the induction of anesthesia till the end of surgical procedure every minute for the first 10 minutes and with 5 minutes interval till the end of surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the correlation between irrigation fluid volume and the body temperature measured by a tympanic digital thermometer will be assessed by correlation tests.total amount of irrigation will be documented at the end of surgery by the study staff.</outcome>
      <timepoint>amount of irrigation will be recorded at the end of surgery. tympanic measurement of body temperature by a digital thermometer will start with the entrance of the patient to the operation room and will continue each minute for 10 minutes after spinal anesthesia and for 5 minute intervals till the end of surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>patients consenting to spinal anesthesia for endoscopic ureteral stone treatment surgery</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>patients rejecting spinal anesthesia or any contraindication for spinal anesthesia</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>sealed envelope technique</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>G*power statistical analysis program will be used to determine the sample size for 90% power and 0.05 statistical significance. Kolmogorov-Smirnow and Shapiro-Wilk tests will be used for determining normal data distribution. Repeated measures ANOVA, Friedman test, Chi-square, Friedman test, Spearman's Rho Correlation tests will be used. statistical significance is accepted as 0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>28/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>28/12/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>kirsehir</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mehmet Canturk</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Medical doctor at government hospital
asikpasa mahallesi
sehit ahmet dogangun caddesi
caglar apartmani
30/8
merkez/kirsehir/Turkey p.k.40100</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>mehmet canturk</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>asikpasa mahallesi sehit ahmet dogangun caddesi caglar apartmani 30/8 merkez/kirsehir/Turkey p.k.40100</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Thermoregulation is one of the major problems affecting both morbidity and mortality of the patients undergoing either general anesthesia or regional anesthesia. in general, monitorisation of body temperature is neglected for the operations lasting no more than two hours. in this randomised controlled clinical trial we hypothesised that isothermic irrigation will prevent the patient from hypothermia with respect to irrigation at room temperature resulting in preservation of body temperature and an increased surgeon satisfaction.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Turgut Ozal University Clinical Trials Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>99950669/115</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mehmet Canturk</name>
      <address>Kirsehir Ahi Evran Universitesi Egitim ve Arastirma Hastanesi 3.Kat Ameliyathane Kervansaray Mahallesi 2019. sokak no:1 p.k. 40100 kirsehir</address>
      <phone>+905053574372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drmcanturk@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mehmet Canturk</name>
      <address>Kirsehir Ahi Evran Universitesi Egitim ve Arastirma Hastanesi 3.Kat Ameliyathane Kervansaray Mahallesi 2019. sokak no:1 p.k.40100 kirsehir</address>
      <phone>+905053574372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drmcanturk@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mehmet Canturk</name>
      <address>Kirsehir Ahi Evran Universitesi Egitim ve Arastirma Hastanesi 3.Kat Ameliyathane Kervansaray Mahallesi 2019. sokak no:1 p.k. 40100 kirsehir</address>
      <phone>+905053574372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drmcanturk@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mehmet Canturk</name>
      <address>Kirsehir Ahi Evran Universitesi Egitim ve Arastirma Hastanesi 3.Kat Ameliyathane Kervansaray Mahallesi 2019. sokak no:1 p.k.40100 kirsehir</address>
      <phone>+905053574372</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drmcanturk@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>