<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363227">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001172897</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation on simulator sickness in healthy adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of application of Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (TENS) on posterior neck and the Zusanli acupoint on simulator sickness (SS) symptoms and sleepiness in healthy adults</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1136-5906</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>motion/simulator sickness</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (TENS) used in a within-subject crossover design wherein each subject will complete 4 test sessions (control, SS, TENS, and TENS + SS) in a randomized order. 
[control session: no simulator exposure and no TENS stimulation]
[SS session: simulator Sickness; exposure to flight simulator for 30 minutes to induce simulator sickness] 
[TENS session: transcutaneous electrical stimulation: electrical stimulation at midline posterior nuchal region and right Zusanli acupoint for 30 minutes using a self-contained, battery-operated, dual channel transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulator at a pulse rate of 100 Hz and the level of intensity (1 through 10) at the highest comfortable setting, per the manufacturers instructions] 
[TENS + SS session: treat with TENS for 30 minutes then exposure the subject in flight simulator to induce simulator sickness. Purpose: to observe the effect of the TENS (the intervention)]
To prevent the carryover of intervention, sessions were spaced at least 2 days apart. (The wash out period between sessions is at least 2 days apart).

Each session consisted of 4 phases: phase 1 (10 minutes), consisting of preparation and recording of baseline physiologic parameters; phase 2 (10 minutes), electrical stimulation (for TENS and TENS + SS sessions); phase 3 (20 minutes), SS stimulation (for SS and TENS + SS sessions) and electrical stimulation (only in TENS + SS sessions); and phase 4 (30 minutes), the post-test period.  
TENS treatment will last 30 minutes (complete duration of phases 2 and 3) at two sites: (1) the midline posterior nuchal region and (2) the Zusanli acupoint, located 1 finger breadth lateral to the tibial anterior crest, about 4 finger widths below the knee.</interventions>
    <comparator>Active treatment (no treatment given).

In this crossover design, subject act as their own control. The SS session is considered control treatment to the SS + TENS session. (TENS is considered the intervention)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Simulator sickness symptoms including sleepiness were evaluated with the Simulator Sickness Questionnaire (SSQ) and Visual Analogue Scales for evaluating Sleepiness Symptoms (VAS-SS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>before phase 1 and after phase 3 of the experiment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The d2 test, a standardized paper-and-pencil test, will be utilized to assess cognitive function, more specifically the visual attention</outcome>
      <timepoint>The d2 test will be tested before (during phase 1) and after simulator sickness induction (after phase 3) in each session</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Salivary stress biomarkers' level (salivary alpha amylase activity and salivary cortisol concentrations) were evaluated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before (during phase 1) and after simulator sickness induction (15 min and 30 min after phase 3) in each session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>heart rate and derived heart rate variability (HRV) were recorded and analyzed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before (during phase 1) and after simulator sickness induction in each session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>healthy, non-smoking, young male participants (age 20-40)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>vestibular, visual, cardiovascular, respiratory, and gastrointestinal tract disorders.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Healthy volunteers will be recruited through advertisements. The allocation sequence will be generated prior to the recruitment of participants by the Research Randomizer Program and concealed in sequentially numbered and sealed opaque envelops, which will be opened when participants are ready for allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Blocked randomization will be determined using a computer program (Research Randomizer), which generates a list of random numbers. For every block of  persons, a balanced block (equal numbers of persons are assigned to each session) is used. Randomization will be conducted by a separate researcher.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Institute of Aerospace and Undersea medicine</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>No. 161, Section 6, Min-Chuan East Road, Taipei, 114 Taiwan, R.O.C.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Defense Medical Center</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>No. 161, Section 6, Min-Chuan East Road, Taipei, 114 Taiwan, R.O.C.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Hsin Chu</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>No. 161, Section 6, Min-Chuan East Road, Taipei, 114 Taiwan, R.O.C.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>GanShan Armed Force Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>1, Dayi 2nd road, GangShan 
Kaohsiung 820
Taiwan, R.O.C.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Flight simulators have been used to train pilots to experience and recognize spatial disorientation, a condition in which pilots incorrectly perceive the position, location, and movement of their aircrafts. However, during or after simulator training, simulator sickness (SS) may develop. Spatial disorientation and SS share common symptoms and signs and may involve a similar mechanism of dys-synchronization of neural inputs from the vestibular, visual, and proprioceptive systems. Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (TENS), a maneuver used for pain control, was found to influence autonomic cardiovascular responses and enhance visuospatial abilities, postural control, and cognitive function. The purpose of present study was to investigate the protective effects of TENS on SS.  Subjects meeting inclusion criteria will be recruited. After informed consent, each participants have to finish four sessions (baseline, SS, TENS, TENS + SS). SS was induced by a flight simulator. TENS treatment involved simultaneous electrical stimulation of the posterior neck and the Zusanli acupoint. SS severity and cognitive function were quantified by the Simulator Sickness Questionnaire (SSQ) and d2 test of attention. Sleepiness symptoms were rated using the Visual Analogue Scales for Sleepiness Symptoms (VAS-SS). Autonomic and stress responses were evaluated by heart rate variability (HRV) and salivary stress biomarkers (salivary alpha-amylase activity and salivary cortisol concentration).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Review Board in aviation medicine research of Gangshan Armed Force Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1, Dayi 2nd Road, Gangshan
Kaoshiung, 820, Taiwan, R.O.C.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/06/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>098-007</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/05/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Hsin Chu</name>
      <address>No. 161, Section 6, Min-Chuan East Road, Taipei, 114 Taiwan, R.O.C.</address>
      <phone>+886-287923100 ext 18390</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hrchu@ndmctsgh.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Hsin Chu</name>
      <address>No. 161, Section 6, Min-Chuan East Road, Taipei, 114 Taiwan, R.O.C.</address>
      <phone>+886-287923100 ext 18390</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hrchu@ndmctsgh.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Hsin Chu</name>
      <address>No. 161, Section 6, Min-Chuan East Road, Taipei, 114 Taiwan, R.O.C.</address>
      <phone>+886-287923100 ext 18390</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hrchu@ndmctsgh.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>