<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371263">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/05/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/05/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000767303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Prospective Randomised Controlled Trial Comparing the, Early Clinical
Outcome, and Accuracy of Mechanical Alignment after Computer Navigated
Total Knee Replacement Utilizing the Tibial cut first versus Femoral cut first.
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective Randomised Controlled Trial Comparing the, Early Clinical
Outcome, and Accuracy of Mechanical Alignment after Computer Navigated
Total Knee Replacement Utilizing the Tibial cut first versus Femoral cut first.
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>'Nil Known'</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Total Knee Arthroplasty</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Tibial First:
Patients will undergo primary total knee arthroplasty using the Apex Knee system and the Praxim navigation system from Global Orthopaedic Technology. The first cut is performed on the tibial site and the following femoral cuts are determined according to the mediolateral soft tissue tension.

The Praxim 'Registered Trademark' OmniNav 'Trademark' Navigation system is a complete computer surgical navigation
system for use with the APEX Knee. The iBlock 'Registered Trademark' is an intelligent instrument allowing intraoperative customisation in total knee arthroplasty using real-time virtual planning technology followed by automated placement of the cutting guide.

The Apex Knee reconstruction system has been designed to precisely match the size of the tibial insert to the femoral component. The Apex 'Trademark' Knee System offers both porous coated uncemented and cemented versions of its tibial and femoral components.
The Apex Knee reconstruction system is a commercially available, TGA ( Therapeutic Goods Administration)  listed device.

The BTS G-walk is a wireless sensor that is placed around the waist with
an ergonomic belt to analyse the walking pattern.
BTS G-Walk 'Registered Trademark' enables functional analysis with objective, accurate and quantitative data. BTS G-WALK 'Registered Trademark' analyzes the walking pattern applying a suite of specific protocols, validated through clinical studies.

.X-Rays will be assessed pre-operatively, post-operatively, at 12 months and 2 years to
evaluate femoral and tibial components orientation and inclination.



</interventions>
    <comparator>Femoral first:

Patients will undergo primary total knee arthroplasty using the Apex Knee system and the Praxim navigation system from Global Orthopaedic Technology. All femoral cuts (distal, anterior, posterior, both chamfer) done first using navigation system followed by tibial cut.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Range of motion
Measured in the clinic using standard goniometer .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operative,  3 months, 12 months and 2 years  post operative.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mechanical axis assessed by Radiographic Analysis


</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operative,  Post-op/discharge, 3 months, 12 months and 2 years  post operative.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Joint height measured by radiographic analysis
 </outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operative,  Post-op/discharge, 3 months, 12 months and 2 years  post operative.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking duration, assessed by 10 metre walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operative,  3 months, 12 months and 2 years  post operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait length measured using the G-walk device</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operative,  3 months, 12 months and 2 years  post operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Sit to stand movement measured using the G-walk device</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operative,  3 months, 12 months and 2 years  post operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life assessed by SF36</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operative,  3 months, 12 months and 2 years  post operative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Patient has diagnosis of Osteoarthritis of the knee eligible for total knee replacement               based on history, physical examination and radiological evaluation.
2. The individual has signed a Participant Informed Consent (PIC), specific to this study,
    and approved by the Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)
3. The individual is over 18 years of age. 
4. The individual is physically and mentally willing and able to comply with postoperative
    scheduled clinical and radiographic evaluations and rehabilitation.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. The individual has an active infection within the affected knee joint.
2. The individual has a neuromuscular or neurosensory deficiency that limits the ability
     to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of the device.
3. The individual is unable to return for follow-up visits as outlined in the protocol.
4. The individual has inflammatory arthritis
5. The individual has had a previous Patellectomy
6. The individual has had a previous proximal tibial or distal femoral osteotomy.
7. The individual has Extra-articular deformity
8. The individual has Neuroarthopathy
9. The individual does not speak, read or comprehend the English language.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone/fax/computer</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A literature review of 7 knee studies reporting Range of motion post knee arthroplasty with
Posterior stabilised implants with a total of 425 patients revealed a mean range of motion
of 123 degrees and SD of 12. In the worst case study, the standard deviation was 21.

The null hypothesis: There is no difference in range of motion between the two groups.
The alternative hypothesis there is a difference of 15 degrees or larger in range of motion
between the two groups.

Accept type I error rate of 5%
If we accept Type II error rate of 20% then
Sample Size 11 for each group (total 22 patients)

If SD=21 (worse case scenario from systematic literature review study sample) will need 32
in each group (n=64 total)

If we accept Type II error rate of 10% then
Sample size 14 in each group (28 in total)

If SD=21 (worse case scenario from systematic literature review study sample) will need 42
in each group (n=84 total).

A total of 100 patients will be recruited to allow for potential lost to follow-up and still
maintain sufficient numbers in both study groups.
Data monitoring will be reviewed and entered into a clinical database. Patients missing the measure of the primary end point will be considered missing in the intent to treat analysis; no inputting of missing data will be conducted for any variables. A secondary per protocol analysis of the primary end point involving only those patients satisfying certain important protocol requirements will be made.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/06/2020</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Macquarie University Hospital - Macquarie Park</hospital>
    <hospital>Norwest Private Hospital - Bella Vista</hospital>
    <postcode>2109 - Macquarie Park</postcode>
    <postcode>2153 - Bella Vista</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Global Orthopaedic Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Unit 10, 7 Meridian Place, Bella Vista, NSW 2153
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Global Orthopaedic Technology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Unit 10,7 Meridian Place, Bella Vista, NSW 2153</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Study design: Prospective, multi-centre, randomised, clinical study. The study will
enrol 100 patients over a 12-month recruitment period between surgeons at up to
three centres.

Objectives: To determine the relationship between Surgical Technique (workflow) and
patient reported outcomes after total knee arthroplasty (TKA) utilising computer
navigation, comparing tibia cut first with ligament balancing technique to measured
femoral cuts technique. To investigate if patient range of motion and component
alignment is affected by the order of workflow. To investigate if the order of surgical
cuts during total knee replacement affects other parameters such as patient
satisfaction. The study will also demonstrate safety, and equivalent clinical outcomes
on pain and function to other published data.

Groups: Apex Total Knee Replacement using Computer Navigation utilising Tibial Cut
First. Apex Total Knee Replacement using Computer Navigation utilising Measured
Femoral Cuts First.
Number of subjects to be enrolled: 100 patients will be enrolled into this study.

Medical Devices: The Apex Knee is intended for use as a primary total knee
replacement device consisting of a femoral, tibial, tibial bearing and optional patellar
component. The BTS G-walk is a wireless sensor that is placed around the waist with
an ergonomic belt to analyse the walking pattern.

Regulatory status: The Apex Knee is CE marked, TGA approved and has a rebate code
on the Prostheses List.

Clinical evaluations: Standard, functional parameters will be assessed preoperatively,
and post-operatively at 6 weeks, 3months, 1 year, 2years. Published early
results at 1 year then mid-term and long term results after 2 and more years

Patient outcome assessments: The Oxford Knee Score and RAND SF36 operatively at
6 weeks, 3months, 1 year and 2 years.

Radiographic evaluations: X-Rays will be assessed pre-operatively, post-operatively, at 12 months and 2 years to evaluate femoral and tibial components orientation and inclination.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office, Research Hub, Building c5c East, Macquarie University, NSW 2109</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/04/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5201600390</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Munjed Al Muderis</name>
      <address>Norwest Advanced Orthopaedics,
Norwest Private Hospital - Ground floor Suite 3B,
Norbrik Drive,
Bella Vista, 2153
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8882 9011</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>munjed@me.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Lyndon Crossley</name>
      <address>Director of Clinical Affairs
Global Orthopaedic Technology
PO Box 7745
Baulkham Hills BC NSW 2153</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8887 0100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lyndon@globalortho.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Munjed Al Muderis</name>
      <address>Norwest Advanced Orthopaedics,
Norwest Private Hospital - Ground floor Suite 3B,
Norbrik Drive,
Bella Vista, 2153
NSW</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8882 9011</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>munjed@me.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Lyndon Crossley</name>
      <address>Director of Clinical Affairs
Global Orthopaedic Technology
PO Box 7745
Baulkham Hills BC NSW 2153</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8887 0100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lyndon@globalortho.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>