<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372130">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>25/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000193370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effectiveness and acceptability of the 'BALatrine': a culturally acceptable latrine intervention in resource limited environments.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Indonesian villagers' use of a new household latrine to reduce soil transmitted helminth infection and environmental contamination.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Helminthiasis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Gastroenteritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is a household latrine (BALatrine) plus health education/promotion on hygiene and sanitation. The BALatrine is a simple squat latrine, usually constructed by the villagers themselves, at the side of a house. It comprises a 2 metre pit (with optional bamboo/concrete pipe strengthening); a base cover with raised footsteps (which can be used during dry periods); and a flushable U-bend porcelain bowl that may be removable. All can be made from local materials. All householders in the intervention village will construct one, with material support and advice from the researchers, if required. The intervention period is 12 months, after which the control villages will also receive the intervention. The Health education/health promotion intervention will be delivered via community meetings in each sub-village in the Intervention group of communities. Community meetings will be run by the local research team. A representative from all dusun households will be invited to the meetings which will be held in the Village meeting hall.. The Health education/health promotion intervention will be implemented through 1 two-hour village wide mobilization meeting and 1 two-hour village wide meeting covering hygiene/sanitation educational inputs meeting after all latrines have been constructed. 
After the baseline survey all cohort members (intervention and control villages) will receive a singe dose of Albendazole (400mg) in the form of an oral tablet, as per WHO guidelines. This will be administered during the national de-worming program delivered by local health officials and recorded onto a treatment registry. According to Indonesian guidelines, pregnant women will not be treated Albendazole.   
The first meeting - to be implemented after the baseline questionnaire and prior to latrine construction-will be the project launch and mobilization of households (consciousness-raising and provision of general information about parasite infection and burden of STH). This will comprise description of the BALatrine intervention, its construction, maintenance and use. BALatrine construction workshops will assist village residents (particularly those with special needs) to plan, construct, use and maintain their latrines.
Leaflets supporting the meeting and summarising the health education content discussed will be distributed to each household.

The second meeting will present/discuss hygiene and sanitation educational inputs for each intervention household, plus information about cleaning, maintenance and use of the latrine. This meeting will cover behavioural change (hygiene and sanitation behaviour change) requirements. All aspects of the questionnaire relating to Knowledge, Attitudes and Behaviour associated with WASH will be covered in this meeting, either as revision of content presented in Meeting 1, or as new material.
 
Health Education content will comprise both general hygiene/sanitation topics that provide the context and background of the need for introduction and appropriate use of improved latrines, and topics specifically related to STH:

(a)	Presentation and group discussion:
1.	STH and other Gastro-intestinal diseases (types, definition, symptoms, treatment, complications, causes)
2.	Prevention of STH and GI diseases (drinking water, defecation, sanitation, hand-washing, food safety, insects)
3.	STH (definitions, lifecycle, types: Pinworms, Hookworms, Whipworms, Ascaris, Tapeworms, 
4.	Preventing STH infection (personal hygiene, sanitary environment)
5.	Significance of the latrine (definition, types, characteristics of good latrine construction)
6.	Water quality (characteristics of pure water, water purification  boil, solar, chlorine, storage)
7.	Healthy wells (requirements,special layout, pollutants, structure, maintenance)
8.	Animals in house (benefits, zoonotic diseases  toxoplasmosis, rabies, avian flu, worms, leptospirosis, prevention of animal-borne diseases)
9.	Healthy food (definition, common food-borne diseases, digestion, infections in food)
10.	Principles of food management (preparation, storage, processing, transporting)
11.	Digestion and the normal gut (germs and pathogens).

(b)	Leaflets
1.	Similar information as (a) above
2.	How to construct a BALatrine.

All community meeting attendees will be registered onto a meeting register.
</interventions>
    <comparator>A community based cluster-randomised intervention trial will be undertaken to determine the impact of the BALatrine on STH infection, in Central Java Province. Eight villages with no/or non-functioning latrines will be identified and randomly assigned intervention/control status (4 intervention; 4 control). matched as closely as possible, based on criteria related to transmission (infection levels; transmission ecology) into pairs to reduce confounding and increase statistical efficiency. One village within each pair will be randomly assigned intervention status (installation of the BALatrine) leaving the other as the control (no latrine). A fixed cohort (n=500) of people (aged &gt;5 years, including equal numbers of males and females) in each village will be selected and followed up over 1 year (2 years if funding available) (total N=4000). All participants (including from the control group) will: participate in the baseline survey; provide a stool sample at the start and end of the study; and receive treatment (single oral tablet dose of 400mg/kg) after the baseline survey. All control villages will also receive the intervention once the study has concluded.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The main end-point for the study will be human soil-transmitted Helthinth (STH) cumulative incidence. A stool sample will be collected from all study participants at baseline and follow-up and undergo qPCR analysis and microscopy for the determination of infection status and infection intensity. </outcome>
      <timepoint>9-12 months - follow-up October 2017</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome of this study will be proportion of participants with improved health knowledge and hygiene and sanitation behaviour (i.e. the effect of the health education intervention on health knowledge, hygiene and sanitary behaviour). This will be assessed as a composite secondary outcome using data collected from a questionnaire (the Helminth, Education and Latrine Project (HELP) questionnaire) to be administered at the start of the study and during follow-up (12 months later). </outcome>
      <timepoint>9-12 months - follow-up October 2017</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Residing for the length of the project in 1 of the 8 study villages;
2. member of a fixed cohort (n=500) of people aged over 2 years, who agree to participate in the study;
3. member of a randomly selected household from each study village;
4. physically and mentally competent to answer the interview questions; and
5. consent to be included.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Younger than 2 years
2. Have an 'improved' latrine</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>5/09/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>4000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Indonesia</country>
      <state>Central Java</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Griffith University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>170 Kessels Rd
Nathan
Brisbane
QLD 4111</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>UBS-Optimus Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>UBS AG
Augustinerhof 1
P.O. Box
CH-8098
Zurich</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (Australia)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GHD Building Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke St
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian National University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Acton, ACT 2601</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Yayasan Wahana Bakti Sejatera (YWBS) Foundation</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Jl. Fortunately Soerapatti 445
Semarang
Central Java</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Indonesia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Diponegoro University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Rectorat Building, Prof. Soedarto, SH street,
Tembalang Campus, Kotak Pos,
Semarang, 1269
Central Java</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Indonesia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>QIMR Berghofer Medical Research Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>300 Herston Rd, 
Herston
QLD 4006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>2 George St
Brisbane City 
QLD 4000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>St Lucia 
QLD 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project will be a definitive study to assess the efficacy of the household latrines on STH infections. Our study design requires the intervention sample to have an effective household latrine (the BALatrine) installed plus supporting health education; the control sample will not receive this intervention package. All participants will receive deworming medication (Albendazole). A cluster RCT allows us to undertake systematic and scientific testing of the efficacy and acceptability of the BALatrine and to investigate its health benefits. The efficacy of the latrine in reducing STH infection will be measured by comparing human STH incidence across intervention and control populations. We hypothesise that there will be a significant reduction in human infection rates and a lower infection intensity in the intervention sample.

A community based cluster-randomised intervention trial will be undertaken to determine the impact of the BALatrine on STH infection in sub-villages (dusuns) located in Wonosobo, Central Java Province. Eight sub-villages/Dusunss (4 intervention; 4 control) with low levels of household latrine ownership will be identified. They will be stratified by topography (mountain: 4 Dusuns; Hillsides: 4 Dusuns). Two dusuns within each topography type will be randomly selected as the intervention group (ALB + installation of the BALatrine + health education) leaving the other 2 as the controls (ALB only). Following the baseline survey all study participants will receive Albendazole (ALB) treatment by the local STH control program.  A fixed cohort (n=500) of people aged &gt; 2 years, including equal numbers of males and females, in each dusun will be selected and followed up over 12 months. The main end-point for the study will be human STH incidence. Secondary endpoints include knowledge, attitudes and practices relating to hygiene behaviour. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Griffith University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office for Research
170 Kessels Rd
Bray Centre, Nathan Campus
QLD 4111</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016/442</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Donald Stewart</name>
      <address>Room 4.07 / S07 - South Bank Campus
Griffith University, PO Box 3370
South Brisbane, QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 - 7 373 53218</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>donald.stewart@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Donald Stewart</name>
      <address>Room 4.07 / S07 - South Bank Campus
Griffith University, PO Box 3370
South Brisbane, QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 - 7 373 53218</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>donald.stewart@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Donald Stewart</name>
      <address>Room 4.07 / S07 - South Bank Campus
Griffith University, PO Box 3370
South Brisbane, QLD 4101</address>
      <phone>+61 - 7 373 53218</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>donald.stewart@griffith.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Johanna Kurscheid</name>
      <address>Australian National University
62a Mills Rd
Acton 
ACT 2601</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6197 0076</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>johanna.kurscheid@anu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>