<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335081">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/01/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/02/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000128099</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparison of lactate values obtained from different sites and its clinical significance in patients with severe sepsis: an observational study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparison of lactate values obtained from different sites and its clinical significance in patients with severe sepsis: an observational study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>perfusion in sepsis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients with a central venous access and health volunteers as a control group were prospectively assessed. Blood was drawn simultaneously for measurements of Lart, Lper and Lcen with the first sample collected within 24h after onset of organ dysfunction. A blinded intensivist stated clinical intervention based on each of the lactate values obtained. Results were analyzed using Pearson correlation, Bland-Altman and McNemar tests and considered significant if p=0.05. Overall duration of this study: 6 months</interventions>
    <comparator>arterial lactate, regarding comparisons with venous and central venous lactate

health voluntears in comparison with septic patients, regarding behavior of this sites of collection potencial differences</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison of lactate values.  Pearson?s correlations will be calculated using arterial lactate as a reference for comparison both with central venous lactate and peripheral lactete. The results will be expressed through the correlation coefficient (R) and the descriptive level (p) to test its significance. Additionally, the Bland and Altman test will be used to determine the bias and the limits of agreement between central venous and peripheral lactate compared with the reference value (arterial). The results of Bland Altman test will be expressed in bias ? standard deviation (confidence interval 95%), with this confidence interval representing the limits of agreement.</outcome>
      <timepoint>measured after 6 months of the study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>This is a cross-sectional study involving patients admitted at the intensive care unit of a tertiary university hospital who were diagnosed with severe sepsis and septic shock, according to the definitions of the 1992 American College of Chest Physicians/Society of Critical Care Medicine (ACCP/SCCM) consensus.16 Organ dysfunction should be acutely associated with the sepsis episode Patients could be included if they met the following inclusion criteria: onset of organ dysfunction within less than 24 hours of the first sample collection, indication for or presence of a central venous catheter, signature of an informed consent term by the patient or his/her legal representative and age over 18 years</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The exclusion criteria were the presence of chronic or acute hepatic failure and the need for dialysis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>81</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidade Federal de Sao Paulo</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Universidade Federal de Sao Paulo
R, Napoleao de Barros 715 5a andar
04024900 Sao Paulo - SP</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidade Federal de Sao Paulo</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Universidade Federal de Sao Paulo
R, Napoleao de Barros 715 5a andar
04024900 Sao Paulo - SP</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Blood will be drawn simultaneously for measurements of Lart, Lper and Lcen, every 12 hours, with a maximum of 3 collections per patient. For collection of Lart, 1mL of blood will be obtained through arterial puncture or from an arterial line. A tourniquet will be used in the upper limb for up to 2 minutes and 1mL of peripheral venous blood will be obtained for Lper determination. Lcen will be obtained through the collection of 1mL of blood from a central venous catheter placed in subclavian or internal jugular vein. To analyze the concordance in medical management a boarded-certified intensivist, blinded to the site of blood collection, will define the management in face of each sample, following the unit protocol that was based on Surviving Sepsis Campaign resuscitation bundle.The correlation and agreement between the lactate values were analyzed in subgroups of patients according to the presence of respiratory dysfunction, septic shock and central venous oxygen saturation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>none</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite de Etica em Pesquisa Universidade Federal de Sao Paulo (UNIFESP)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/02/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Flavia R Machado</name>
      <address>Napoleao de Barros 715 5a andar
Sao Paulo SP</address>
      <phone>55 11 - 55764069</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fmachado.dcir@epm.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Flavia R Machado</name>
      <address>Napoleao de Barros 715 5a andar
Sao Paulo SP</address>
      <phone>55 11 - 55764069</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fmachado.dcir@epm.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>