<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362371">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/04/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/04/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000417886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Beijing Adolescent Obesity Peer Education</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study to evaluate the feasibility and acceptability of a school-based peer education obesity program in adolescents in Beijing, China</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention (September 2010 to December 2010):
1. Peer leaders recruitment and training
After the baseline assessment, four to eight peer leaders balanced by gender in each intervention class were selected by the class teacher from volunteer students based on their organization and oral expression ability, influence among students and sense of responsibility. 
Then peer leaders in each intervention school were trained by research staff in three after-school 90-minute workshops over 3 consecutive days at school. The training covered four components: food choice, physical activity and sedentary behavior, carbonated drinks, and goal setting, which directly aimed at behavior change. 
2. Peer education
Peer leaders then delivered four 40-minute peer education lessons to their classmates over four consecutive weeks in their classrooms. 
3.Student action
Students were encouraged to maintain a healthy lifestyle based on the personal goals set in the fourth peer education lesson.</interventions>
    <comparator>No intervention was implemented in the two control schools during the study.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility and acceptability of the peer education project that was evaluated by observing the peer education activities, in-depth interview with school teachers, focus group discussion with peer leaders and peers, semi-structural questionnaires. The evaluation was implemented by trained research staff.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline: September 2010
On completion of intervention at 3 months: December 2010
Follow-up at 7-8 months: April-May 2011</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dietary behavior that was evaluated by validated 3-month Food Frequency Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline: September 2010 
On completion of intervention at 3 months: December 2010
Follow-up at 7-8 months: April-May 2011</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>physical activity that was evaluated by validated 7-day physical activity questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline: September 2010 
On completion of intervention at 3 months: December 2010
Follow-up at 7-8 months: April-May 2011</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychosoical mediators were evaluated by psychosocial mediators questionnaire on dietary behavior and physical activity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline: September 2010 
On completion of intervention at 3 months: December 2010
Follow-up at 7-8 months: April-May 2011</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Students in grade 7 in the four junior high schools that had at least 160 students in grade 7</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>11</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those with disease that influence energy metabolism</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A convenience sample of two small-sized and two large-sized junior high schools in Dongcheng District, Beijing were selected by the Dongcheng District Institute for Student Healthcare from schools with more than 160 students in grade 7. These schools were matched by school population size, and in each matched pair, one school was randomly allocated by research staff by throwing a coin to intervention or the control group.  The allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/09/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>640</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Beijing</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The George Institute for Global Health, China</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Room B1302, Horizon Tower, No 6, Zhichun Road, Haidian District, Beijing 100088, PR China</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Nestle Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Place de la Gare 4,  PO Box 581, 1001 Lausanne</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>With economic development over the last decade, China is undergoing a rapid nutrition transition from under- to over-nutrition, especially in urban areas. The China National Nutrition surveys indicate that the prevalence of obesity of children and adolescents aged 7-17 years in urban areas has increased by 42% from 3.1% in 1992 to 4.4% in 2002 according to Chinese screening criteria. The situation is even worse in Beijing, the capital of China. The latest data in 2004 indicate that prevalence of obesity in adolescents aged 13-15 in urban Beijing has reached 11% according to Chinese screening criteria. As the prevalence of adolescent overweight and obesity continues to rise, the need for feasible and effective prevention is becoming increasingly urgent.
The best available evidence indicates a lack of established and effective preventive interventions for adolescent obesity around the world. It is well recognized that peers are an important influence on health related behaviour and a key source of information for young people. Promotion of healthy eating and physical activity by peers is more likely to be accepted than promotion by authority figures like parents and teachers. Recent studies have shown peer education programs can significantly improve a range of health behaviours, including increasing fruit intake and reducing the risk of eating disorders in primary school students as well as improving clinical and quality of life indicators in adolescents with asthma. However, little is known about whether this premise holds for educating junior high school students about obesity-related behaviors like dietary and physical activity. 
The proposed pilot study aims to evaluate the feasibility of innovative peer-led interventions in students in grade 7 in 2 intervention and 2 control junior high schools in urban Beijing, based on theory and prior research and provide scientific basis for the development of formal intervention studies in future.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Peking University Biomedical Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>38 Xueyuan Road , Haidian District, Beijing 100191</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/10/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>IRB00001052 - 09077</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, The University of Sydney, Australia</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12046</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Zhaohui Cui</name>
      <address>Room B1302, Horizon Tower, No 6, Zhichun Road, Haidian District, Beijing 100088, PR China</address>
      <phone>86-10-82800577</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cuizhaohui2008@yahoo.com.cn</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Zhaohui Cui</name>
      <address>Room B1302, Horizon Tower, No 6, Zhichun Road, Haidian District, Beijing 100088, PR China</address>
      <phone>86-10-82800577</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cuizhaohui2008@yahoo.com.cn</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>