<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366441">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000678695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Development of a group e-Parenting Intervention Targeting Behavioural Problems for Children with Leukaemia  A pilot study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Targeting Behavioural Problems for Children with Leukaemia: Feasibility of the group TripleP e-parenting intervention.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1146-6083 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukaemia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Child behavioural problems</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Child sleep problems</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Child diet</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Child emotional problems</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Children's - Leukaemia &amp; Lymphoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The current study aims to assess the feasibility of the Triple P Positive Parenting Program for parents who have a
child diagnosed with acute lymphoblastic leukaemia. Triple P is an evidence-based program developed specifically to provide parents with practical strategies for dealing with problem behaviour in their children.

Current research shows that parents of children being treated for childhood leukaemia have reported treatment related behavioural problems, including sleep, diet and general behaviour. Currently no evidence-based parenting interventions targeting these issues exist. The aim of the current study is pilot an existing evidence-based parenting intervention: Triple P - Positive Parenting Program (Group format for 0-12 year old children) using a live online meeting platform in order to: 1) assess the relevance of the intervention for paediatric cancer; 2) identify any modifications required to better tailor the program to the needs of parents of children with cancer; and 3) assess the feasibility of the live online delivery modality. 

The intervention will be delivered in an online group format therefore providing accessible and equitable parenting
support for metropolitan, regional and rural families. The results from this pilot intervention will be used to inform the
development of a cancer-specific Triple P Intervention (CancerCare Triple P) for implementation across multiple
paediatric oncology sites nationally.

Participants will be randomly allocated to an intervention (N=12) or control (N=12) arm. Intervention group parents will participate in a 9-week live online (5 x 1 hr face-to face via iPads and 4 x 30minuts via phone) group-based parenting intervention, facilitated by a TripleP trained Psychologist. Both intervention and control groups will complete online surveys measuring parenting strategies, child sleep, child diet, child behaviour and other feasibility questionnaires at three timepoints (2 weeks prior to the first intervention, and again at 2 and 12 weeks post intervention).  </interventions>
    <comparator>The aim of the current study is to assess the efficacy of a live online parenting intervention, and therefore a waitlist control group, in which participants do not receive the intervention will be used.

Participants in this group, which is based on random allocation, will not receive the intervention at the commencement of the study, but will have the opportunity to access the intervention at the completion of all time points (i.e. after completion of Time 3 assessments (12 weeks post baseline)). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child emotional and behavioural problems: % with a score 17 or more on the total difficulties scale of the Strength and Difficulties Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 12-weeks post intervention completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child Diet: % with score 14 or more on the fruit and vegetable sub scale of the Children's Dietary Questionnaire and % with a score of 2 or less on the non-core food sub-scale of the Children's Dietary Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 12-weeks post intervention completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child Sleep: % with score 41 or more on the total sleep problems scale of the Children't Sleep Habits Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 12-weeks post intervention completion.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Examine participant satisfaction and acceptability of the intervention: Mean score on the Abbreviated Acceptability Rating Profile (AARP) and the Client Satisfaction Questionnaire (CSQ).




</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks post-intervention completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Examine whether participation in Triple P results in increases in effective parenting practices. Assess changes in parenting strategies using validated survey measures of parental laxness (measured using the Arnold Parenting Scale) , parental overprotection (measured using the Parenting Protection Scale), interpersonal conflict over child rearing (measured using the Parent Problem Checklist), feeding strategies (measured using the Parental Feeding Style Questionnaire) and sleep strategies (measured using the Children's Sleep Habits Questionnaire together with a scale devised by the research team).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 12-weeks post intervention completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Identify any modifications to the Group Triple P that will be needed in order to develop a cancer-specific Triple P Module (i.e., CancerCare Triple P).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Focus group at week 9 of the intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will include English-speaking parents of a child who meets the following eligibility criteria: 

a)	Is aged 2-8 years at the point of recruitment; 
b)	Has been diagnosed with acute lymphoblastic leukaemia (ALL);
c)	Is on the maintenance phase of treatment;
d)	Has not relapsed and is not receiving palliative care;
e)	Has no other significant and unrelated medical condition (e.g. Autism, Down Syndrome). 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Parents/Caregivers will also be excluded from participating if deemed by the clinical treating team that the family should not be approached and also if their child:

a)	Is considered palliative;
b)	Has a neurological condition or major developmental disorder ;
c)	Does not reside with the parent at least part-time.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Concealed Allocation: Randomisation via sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation schedule created by a biostatistician (idependent from the Research Team) using computer software. Randomisation schedule is concealed in 24 individual envelopes to be opened (1 p/participant) after each participant is recruited.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample characteristics will be described together with caregiver report of each components acceptability, frequency of use and ease of use. Barriers to session attendance and uptake of specific intervention strategies will be presented. Changes (baseline-4 months) in child and family outcomes will be reported. Specific details associated with each study aim are provided below.
a)	Examine participant satisfaction and acceptability of the intervention;
The CSQ and AARP are administered at T2 and T3 for intervention group participants. An examination of mean scores at each time point as well as mean change in scores (using paired-samples t-tests) will be examined. 
b)	Examine whether participation in Triple P shows promise for improvements in effective parenting practices;
Group differences in mean change scores (e.g. Time 1 minus baseline and time 2 minus baseline) in parenting practices (using independent samples t-test) will be examined.
c)	Explore whether participation in Triple P shows promise for improvements in child behaviour (sleep, diet and internalising/externalising behaviour);
Group differences in mean change scores (e.g. Time 1 minus baseline and time 2 minus baseline) for child sleep, diet and internalising/externalising behaviour (using independent samples t-test) will be examined.
d)	Identify any modifications to the Group Triple P that will be needed in order to modify and improve CancerCare Triple P.
Qualitative thematic analysis will be employed using the focus group data collected during session 9 of the intervention (intervention group only) to derive any main themes that were identified by participants regarding modifications/improvements to the program. Information from informal focus group discussions that include the intervention moderator and project investigators will also be used to identify any avenues for intervention improvement.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>23/10/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch Childrens Research Institution</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>50 Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052 Australia.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50 Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052 Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ponting Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1/189 Rouse Street
Port Melbourne Vic 3207</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Queensland</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>The University of Queensland
Brisbane QLD 4072 Australia
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current study aims to assess the feasibility of the Triple P Positive Parenting Program for parents who have a child diagnosed with cancer. 

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you are an English-speaking parent of a child aged 2-8 years who has been diagnosed with acute lymphoblastic leukaemia (ALL), and is on the maintenance phase of treatment.

Study details
Participants in this study will be randomly (by chance) allocated to one of two groups. Participants in one group will undergo the Triple P Positive Parenting Program straight away. Participants in the other group will be offered the same program approximately 5 months later. Triple P is an evidence-based program developed specifically to provide parents with practical strategies for dealing with problem behaviour in their children. This intervention will be delivered in an online group format, hence making it accessible to all families regardless of their personal or geographic circumstances.

Both intervention and control group parents will complete online surveys measuring parenting strategies, child sleep, child diet, child behaviour and other feasibility questionnaires at three timepoints (2 weeks prior to the first intervention, and again at 2 and 12 weeks post intervention completion). 
The results from this pilot intervention will be used to inform the development of a cancer-specific Triple P Intervention (CancerCare Triple P) for implementation across multiple paediatric oncology sites nationally.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Ethics &amp; Governance
The Royal Children's Hospital
Level 2 East, Zone K
50 Flemington Road
Parkville Vic 3052
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>17/04/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>34005A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366441-34005A App Cert 17 4 14.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lauren Williams</name>
      <address>Social and Mental Health Aspects of Serious Illness, 
Clinical Sciences
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
The Royal Childrens Hospital
50 Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052 Australia.
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99366024</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Lauren.Williams@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lauren Williams</name>
      <address>Social and Mental Health Aspects of Serious Illness, 
Clinical Sciences
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
The Royal Childrens Hospital
50 Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052 Australia.
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99366024</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Lauren.Williams@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lauren Williams</name>
      <address>Social and Mental Health Aspects of Serious Illness, 
Clinical Sciences
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
The Royal Childrens Hospital
50 Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052 Australia.
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99366024</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Lauren.Williams@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lauren Williams</name>
      <address>Social and Mental Health Aspects of Serious Illness, 
Clinical Sciences
Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
The Royal Childrens Hospital
50 Flemington Road Parkville Victoria 3052 Australia.
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 99366024</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Lauren.Williams@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>