<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364404">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/06/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000680763</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial evaluating the use of Motivational Interviewing compared to usual care to increase physical activity in people living in the community after a hip fracture</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial evaluating the use of Motivational Interviewing compared to usual care to increase physical activity in people living in the community after a hip fracture </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1144-5538</utrn>
    <trialacronym>MIPAHIP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>hip fracture rehabilitation - increasing activity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>hip fracture rehabilitation - quality of life </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>hip fracture rehabilitation - mental health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The participants who are randomly allocated to receive the Motivational Interviewing intervention will receive usual care they would receive in the community plus the 8 weekly 30-minute sessions of motivational interviewing (Miller &amp; Rollnick, 2002, 2013) over the telephone for 8 weeks. This intervention is a directive style of communication in which the person delivering the intervention works collaboratively with the client to assist the client to increase his/her motivation to change their behaviour (in this case physical activity). This is done through a process of clients forming their own arguments for change which builds the clients importance and confidence of change (Miller &amp; Rollnick, 2002, 2013). Motivational Interviewing has been demonstrated to lead to health behaviour change, in non-hip fracture populations, in several large meta-analytic studies (Hettema et al., 2005; Rubak et al., 2005; Lundahl et al., 2010).
</interventions>
    <comparator>standard care in the community, which may involve people seeing their GP or physiotherapist when required  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity  1-week assessments at baseline and 8 weeks as measured by ActivPal accelerometer and log diary (type of activity, whether inside or outside activity, when monitor was removed)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>7-day assessments at baseline and then 8 weeks - immediately after the intervention </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life: as measured by the Assessment of Quality of Life Instrument(AQoL) 8-D (35 items, measures Independent Living, Happiness, Mental Health, Coping, Relationships, Self Worth, Pain, Senses) 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>assessed at baseline and then at 8 weeks - immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression and Anxiety: as measured by the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS) 21 (21 items  normed for older people)</outcome>
      <timepoint>assessed at baseline and then at 8 weeks - immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-efficacy (associated with activity and falls  e.g. Modified falls efficacy scale  14 questions, Ambulatory Self-Confidence Questionnaire  22 items)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>assessed at baseline and then at 8 weeks - immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity stages of change (simple single-item measure tick one box) </outcome>
      <timepoint>assessed at baseline and then at 8 weeks - immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mobility: de Morton mobility index (DEMMI  15 items)</outcome>
      <timepoint>assessed at baseline and then at 8 weeks - immediately after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	They have had a hip fracture and are now living at home independently within 6 months of discharge 
2.	They are aged over 65 years 
3.	They speak conversational English 
4.	They are currently insufficiently active  as defined by obtaining less than 30 minutes of activity most days of the week
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>89</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	They have a cognitive impairment of any kind  this is because the Motivational Interviewing intervention is a talking intervention that requires people to be able to think clearly and generate their own ideas of how they can change their behaviour 
2.	They score in the severe range of depression or anxiety as measured by the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale (DASS: Lovibond &amp; Lovibond, 1995)
3.	They do not speak conversational English - this is because the Motivational Interviewing intervention is a talking intervention and the person delivering the intervention only speaks English and there are not sufficient funds to employ another person who is able to speak in other languages 
4.	They are less than 65 years of age  this is because the population of interest for the current study is people 65+, because this is the group who is most likely to experience problems with reduced mobility following a hip fracture
5.	They  are highly dependent on medical care, in either high level or low level care   this is because the population of interest is people living independently in the community who are capable of becoming more active
6.	They are already sufficiently active, as defined as obtaining at least 30 minutes of activity most days of the week
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Method of randomisation - Participants will be allocated to the intervention or usual care group based on a random number sequence produced by a random number generator produced by MS excel. Specific details about group allocation for each participant will be sealed in sequentially numbered opaque envelopes prepared by an independent researcher. 

</concealment>
    <sequence>the use of a random number generator  produced by MS excel</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data on outcome measures will be analysed on an intention-to-treat basis. Groups will be compared on primary and secondary outcomes using Analysis of Covariance (ANCOVA) which will compare the group means at week 8 using baseline scores as covariates.  Effect sizes will be calculated, by calculating Hedges g, in order to be able to obtain a measure of the magnitude of the impact of the intervention. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>8/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/03/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>24</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Paul O'Halloran from La Trobe University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Faculty of Health Sciences 
plenty road 
Bundoora 
Victoria 3086</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>La Trobe University 
Faculty of Health Sciences 
Physical Activity and Rehabilitation group </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>plenty road 
Bundoora 
Victoria 3086</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Eastern Health </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress> Eastern Health, Level 4, 5 Arnold St, Box Hill,
Victoria 3128 Australia
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of the study is to examine if a telephone based intervention designed to increase confidence and motivation (i.e. Motivational Interviewing) increases physical activity in people living in the community following a hip fracture. Secondary aims relate to the effect of this intervention on confidence, quality of life, mental health and mobility. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Eastern Health, Level 4, 5 Arnold St, Box Hill,
Victoria 3128 Australia  </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/06/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Paul OHalloran</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences 
La Trobe University 
Bundoora 
Victoria
3086</address>
      <phone>+61 03 9479 5607</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.ohalloran@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Paul OHalloran </name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences 
La Trobe University 
Bundoora 
Victoria
3086</address>
      <phone>+61 (03) 9479 5607</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.ohalloran@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Paul OHalloran </name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences 
La Trobe University 
Bundoora 
Victoria
3086</address>
      <phone>+61 (03) 9479 5607</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.ohalloran@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Paul OHalloran</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Sciences 
La Trobe University 
Bundoora 
Victoria
3086</address>
      <phone>+61 (03) 9479 5607</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.ohalloran@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>