<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370231">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000568415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A multiple dose study to investigate the safety of ACH-0144471 in healthy volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Multiple Ascending Dose Study to Assess Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, and Pharmacodynamics of ACH-0144471 in Healthy Volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1181-8776</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>ACH471-002</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Complement-mediated diseases.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Autoimmune diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects will receive either active (ACH-0144471) or placebo.
A total of 46 subjects in four separate dose cohorts are planned. ACH-0144471 will be administered as multiple doses over a 14-day period. The dosing interval will be determined based on emerging data, and there will be flexibility to explore different dosing frequencies. In order to ensure sufficient placebo subjects for comparison at the first dose level, the first dose cohort will include 16 subjects, randomized 1:1 to active drug and placebo; the remaining dose cohorts will enroll 10 subjects per cohort, randomized 4:1 (8 active drug and 2 placebo).

The dose for the first cohort will be determined based on the data from at least 2 doses in the currently ongoing SAD study (ACTRN12616000082404p) (clinical safety, observed PK/PD relationships). The dosing for the next cohort will proceed at a new dose level/regimen, based on the acceptability of available safety and PD results. This procedure will be repeated for all doses in this study. The maximum dose for this study will be calculated so that the predicted Cmax and AUC0-24 do not exceed the NOAELs observed in nonclinical studies, and may be adjusted upward or downward based on emerging nonclinical and clinical safety, PK, and PD data.

All doses of ACH-0144471 or placebo will be administered orally. Dosing should be at the same time each day. All doses should be administered within 5 minutes of the scheduled time.

All dosing is to occur during subject housing optimizing subject compliance.

</interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo for ACH-0144471 liquid filled capsules (LFCs) dosage forms will be extemporaneously prepared by the clinical site and/or an alternative approved site. The excipients used in the placebo for ACH-0144471 LFCs will be the same as the excipients used in the active ACH-0144471  LFCs. All excipients will be precedented and have regulatory acceptance. The number of capsules required will be adjusted based on the final doses chosen for each group.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of multiple, ascending oral doses of ACH-0144471 in healthy volunteers.

This outcome is assessed using the following tests and assessments:
Assessment of AEs/SAEs, recording concomitant medications, obtaining vitals, ECGs and collection of blood and urine samples. Previous Human Experience with ACH-0144471 is limited, not allowing for examples of known/possible adverse reactions/events </outcome>
      <timepoint>Days -1 through 14, then approximately weekly through Day 42</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of ACH-0144471 in healthy volunteers following administration of multiple ascending oral doses.
This outcome is assessed using the following tests:
Pharmacokinetic Assessments: Serial blood samples will be collected to determine plasma
concentrations of ACH-0144471 and any potential metabolites.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for Days 2-3, 6, 8-9, 13, 15-17 &amp; Day 21.  For Days, 1, 7, and 14: Serial draws approximately every half hour for 4 hours, then approximately every 2-4 hours through Hour 16, dependent on dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To investigate the pharmacodynamic (PD) profile of ACH-0144471 in healthy volunteers following administration of multiple ascending oral doses.
This outcome will be assessed using AP Wieslab and other tests of the complement system</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for Days 2-3, 6, 8-9, 13, 15-17 &amp; Day 21.  For Days, 1, 7, and 14: Serial draws approximately every half hour for 4 hours, then approximately every 2-4 hours through Hour 16, dependent on dose
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate the relationship between ACH-0144471 multiple-dose pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics effects through inhibition of alternative pathway (AP) activity (PK/PD).
This outcome is assessed using the following tests: AP Wieslab and Pharmacokinetic Assessments</outcome>
      <timepoint>Daily for Days 2-3, 6, 8-9, 13, 15-17 &amp; Day 21.  For Days, 1, 7, and 14: Serial draws approximately every half hour for 4 hours, then approximately every 2-4 hours through Hour 16, dependent on dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Healthy male and female subjects of any ethnic origin between the ages of 25 and 55 years, inclusive
2. Body mass index (BMI) of 18 to 30 kg/m2 with a minimum body weight of 50 kg
3. Female subjects must be of non-childbearing potential
4. Male subjects must agree to abstinence or use a condom when engaged in sexual activity</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. History or clinically relevant evidence of significant cardiovascular, pulmonary, hepatic, renal, hematological, gastrointestinal, endocrine, immunologic, dermatologic, neurological, or psychiatric disease in the opinion of the Principal Investigator (PI)
2. Any condition possibly affecting drug absorption (including gastrectomy or cholecystectomy)
3. Subjects with C3 complement protein (C3) or C4 complement protein (C4) &gt;110% of the upper limit or &lt;90% of the lower limit of the reference ranges at Screening
4. Subjects with alternative pathway hemolysis (AH50), or classical pathway hemolysis (CH50) assay results outside the reference ranges at Screening
5. Body temperature greater than or equal to 38 degrees C on Day  1 or Day 1, Hour 0
6. History of febrile illness, or other evidence of infection, within 14 days prior to first study drug administration
7. History of meningococcal infection, or a first-degree relative with a history of meningococcal infection
8. Current tobacco users and smokers (defined as the use of any tobacco or nicotine-containing product within 3 months prior to first study drug administration) or a positive cotinine test at Screening or Day -1
9. History of hypersensitivity reactions to beta-lactams, penicillin, aminopenicillins, flouroquinolones (specifically including ciprofloxacin), cephalosporins, and carbapenems.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Study drug components will be shipped to the study center in open-label fashion. An unblinded pharmacist and the associated pharmacy staff at the study site will be responsible for dispensing according to the randomization schedule provided. The unblinded pharmacy staff will affix a blinded, unitdose label to the drug identifying which study subject should receive which dose. All doses will be administered by blinded site staff.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>14/12/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>46</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>45</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>4/05/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Achillion Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>300 George Street
New Haven, CT 06511</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Achillion Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>300 George Street
New Haven, CT 06511</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Clinical Network Services (CNS) Ltd</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 78312
Grey Lynn
Auckland 1245</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>ACH-0144471 is a new orally (by mouth) administered complement factor D (fD) inhibitor being developed by Achillion Pharmaceuticals, Inc. for the treatment of complement mediated diseases. Many diseases are associated with inefficient control of complement or too much activity of the complement system. This study will help determine the correct dose, whether this medication has any side effects and how effective it is at controlling the complement system.

A total of 46 subjects in four separate dose cohorts are planned. ACH-0144471 will be administered as multiple doses over a 14-day period. The dosing interval will be determined based on emerging data, and there will be flexibility to explore different dosing frequencies. In order to ensure sufficient placebo subjects for comparison at the first dose level, the first dose cohort will include 16 subjects, randomized 1:1 to active drug and placebo; the remaining dose cohorts will enroll 10 subjects per cohort, randomized 4:1 (8 active drug and 2 placebo).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Health and Disability Ethic Comittee (HDEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/CEN/53</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Roderick Ellis-Pegler</name>
      <address>Auckland Clinical Studies Ltd
Ground Floor
MEDACS House
3 Ferncroft Street
Auckland 1010</address>
      <phone>+6493733474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rod@clinicalstudies.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Glenn Schulman</name>
      <address>Achillion Pharmaceuticals, Inc.
300 George Street
New Haven, CT  06511</address>
      <phone>+12037525510</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gschulman@achillion.com</email>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Roderick Ellis-Pegler</name>
      <address>Auckland Clinical Studies Ltd
Ground Floor
MEDACS House
3 Ferncroft Street
Auckland 1010</address>
      <phone>+6493733474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rod@clinicalstudies.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>