<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367189">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/10/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/10/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001109695</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A study to investigate the underlying molecular characteristics of allergic asthma</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A study to investigate the underlying molecular characteristics of allergic asthma by comparing biomarkers in the airways or blood among healthy subjects, mild and severe asthmatics. 
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mild to moderate asthma </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Severe allergic asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Allergies</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Group 1: Subjects with mild to moderate allergic asthma (n=20)who are controlled on inhaled corticosteroids will be asked to withdraw their inhaled corticosteroids (ICS) immediately following a 2 week run-in prior to an 8 week observational period. Subjects will visit the clinic every two weeks where their asthma status will be assessed. 

Group 2: Subjects who have attended the severe asthma clinic at the John Hunter Hospital and are deemed suitable under current PBS guidelines for add on therapy for difficult asthma with omalizumab (Xolair) will be recruited to an observational study during their 6 month Xolair trial. Xolair administration  will follow standard therapeutic guidelines and be administered every 2 or 4 weeksby the Xolair clinic nurse. The dose of omalizumab for each patient is detrmined by IgE levels and body weight. Frequency of dosing is determined by clinical status as assessed by the supervising physician. For the purposes of this study this group of subjects will be seen once per month only. If omalizumab is administered fortnightly, subjects enrolled in this study will be seen every second omalizumab injection.

Group 3: Healthy control volunteers will be recruited (n=20) to provide induced sputum and bloods samples for comparison to groups 1 &amp; 2. The length of study involvement for this group will be dependent on the availablility of the subject to attend a post-baseline clinic visit if the subject catches a cold. These subjects will remain on stand-by and will be considered active participants until either the subject expresses an unwillingness to be involved in the study or the investigators obtain sufficient data to complete the study.</interventions>
    <comparator>Healthy persons 6 - 75 years.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine if individuals with poorly controlled allergic asthma who have persistent eosinophilic airway inflammation, also have impaired antiviral responses to RV. Characterised by impaired TLR7 signaling and increased CCL7 at baseline. These analyses will be determined using ELISA and FACscan.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Loss of asthma control (within the ICS withdrawal period (i.e. 8 weeks) for mild asthmatics; or within 6 months for the severe athma group; or, in healthy controls, the contraction of a cold during the 6 months following baseline assessment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants:
This is a prospective case control study; we will recruit the following subjects:
1.	Stable allergic asthma. Subjects aged 6  75 years with mild-to-moderate asthma (control of asthma symptoms (Asthma control questionnaire (ACQ6) score &lt;1.5), and who have evidence of AHR to hypertonic saline and allergic sensitization to common inhalant allergens. On less than 1000mcg/d beclomethasone equivalent.
2.	Severe uncontrolled allergic asthma, suitable for Omalizumab. Participants with severe refractory asthma, 18 years and older who have persistent poor asthma control (ACQ6 &gt;1.5) despite treatment with greater than 1000mcg/d beclomethasone equivalent per day and a history of an acute exacerbation in the last 12 months requiring systemic corticosteroids for 3 days or more, and who are suitable for commencement of treatment with omalizumab.
3.	Healthy controls. Non-asthmatic subjects aged 6  75 years with normal lung function and no allergic sensitization. 

Key inclusion criteria

Cases with severe allergic asthma
*Asthma diagnosis, and who have evidence of AHR to hypertonic saline or change in FEV1 following bronchodilator &gt;12% and at least 200mls.
*Age: 18 years and older and determined to be suitable for omalizumab treatment 
*Regular maintenance treatment with inhaled corticosteroid and long acting beta agonist (dose of ICS &gt;1000mcg/d fluticasone or 1600mcg/d of budesonide)
*Evidence of atopy, defined by positive skin prick test or RAST.
*Total serum IgE &gt;75 IU/ml
*Persistent poor symptom control (ACQ6 &gt;1.5).
*Oral corticosteroid use of at least 10mg/d of prednisone for at least 6 weeks in the last 12 months.
*Current non-smoker with &lt;10 pack year history of smoking

Cases with controlled mild to moderate allergic asthma
*Asthma diagnosis, and who have evidence of AHR to hypertonic saline or change in FEV1 following bronchodilator &gt;12% and at least 200mls.
*Age 6 -75 years
*Regular maintenance treatment with inhaled corticosteroid (dose of ICS &lt;1000mcg/d fluticasone or 1600mcg/d of budesonide)
*Evidence of atopy, defined by positive skin prick test or RAST.
*Good asthma symptom control (ACQ6 &lt;1.5)
*Current non-smoker with &lt;10 pack year history of smoking

Healthy controls 
*Normal lung function; FEV1 &gt;80% predicted, FER &gt;70% predicted and no evidence of AHR to hypertonic saline or change in FEV1 following bronchodilator &gt;12% and at least 200mls.
*Age 6 -75 years
*No previous history of chronic cardiac or respiratory disease
*Non-atopic, negative skin prick test or RAST
*Current non-smoker with &lt;10 pack year history of smoking


</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Acute exacerbation of asthma within the last 4 weeks that required a change in treatment
*History of a viral respiratory tract infection within the last 4 weeks.
*Current smoker or former smoker with &gt;10 pack year history of smoking.
*Inability to understand or comply with the study requirements
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>A total of 50 participants distributed into 3 study goups will be sought. We will need 10 participants to be treated with Omalizumab to have 80% power to find a 0.4 unit difference in the mean level of TLR7 between the two groups at the 5% level of significance. This calculation assumes that the Standard Deviation (SD) of TLR7 is 0.3. 
We will need 20 subjects with mild to moderate asthma to have 80% power to find a 0.4 unit difference in the mean level of TLR7 between the two groups at the 5% level of significance. This calculation assumes that the Standard Deviation (SD) of TLR7 is 0.3. We are planning a study of a continuous response variable from independent control and experimental subjects with 1 control(s) per experimental subject. In the three month period we would expect 50% of subjects to exacerbate. In a previous study the response within each subject group was normally distributed with standard deviation 0.4. If the true difference in the experimental and control means is 0.4, we will need to study 10 exacerbating subjects and 10 stable subjects to be able to reject the null hypothesis that the population means of the experimental and control groups are equal with probability (power) 0.8. The Type I error probability associated with this test of this null hypothesis is 0.017. We plan to recruit 20 subjects, this will be sufficient to determine our primary endpoint as defined. 20 healthy control subjects will be recruited to provide comparative data for the mild and severe asthma groups. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>John Hunter Hospital Royal Newcastle Centre - New Lambton</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>John Hunter Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Respiratory Medicine
John Hunter Hospital
Lookout Road
New Lambton NSW 2305
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council (NH&amp;MRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra City
ACT 2600</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to determine if markers in the airways or blood can predict when someone with mild/moderate or severe asthma is at risk of developing an acute asthma attack associated with a virus infection. This may allow us to better determine who needs treatment to prevent attacks of asthma and for how long.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>John Hunter Hospital
Lookout Road
New Lambton NSW 2305
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/07/16/3.01</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Wark</name>
      <address>Level 2 HMRI
John Hunter Hospital
Lookout Road 
New Lambton NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4042 0138</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4042 0046</fax>
      <email>peter.wark@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Douglas Dorahy</name>
      <address>Level 2 HMRI
John Hunter Hospital
Lookout Road 
New Lambton NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4042 0133</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4042 0046</fax>
      <email>douglas.dorahy@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Wark</name>
      <address>Level 2 HMRI
John Hunter Hospital
Lookout Road 
New Lambton NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4042 0138</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4042 0046</fax>
      <email>peter.wark@hnehealth.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>