<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373420">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001154392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effects of Environmental Enrichment on Wound Healing in Healthy Participants</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The  Effects of Environmental Enrichment on Wound Healing in Healthy Participants</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Wound Healing</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention: Interaction with Environmental Enrichment Item
Participants will be exposed to a tape stripping procedure which removes the top-layer of skin through the repeated application of tape. The participant will have 20-40 pieces of tape applied and gently removed from their forearm.  This procedure is a non-invasive and minimally painful method to assess wound healing in humans.
After the tape-stripping procedure has been performed, participants will be randomised to 1 of 4 conditions where they will (or will not) receive a different type of enrichment item. They will be asked to interact with this enrichment item during a 30 minute period, in order to examine whether the enrichment item improved wound healing over this period. There will be three different environmental enrichment items and a control group. The enrichment items include; (1) relaxing music which will be presented using a CD player and headphones, (2) materials in the form of soft blankets and pillows and (3) a seal companion robot, Paro. The Paro seal robot proposed for one of the conditions is a therapeutic robot designed to provide a safer alternative to animal-assisted therapy. Paro uses sensors to respond to human contact in a socially supportive and comforting way and has a soft fur coat to provide tactile comfort  All groups, including the control group, will also be provided with magazines to read. Reading magazines has been used previously as a control condition in similar trials.
The researcher (a doctoral candidate) will introduce the item to the participants and explain what is going to happen. Participants will be asked to interact with their assigned condition over a 30 minute period where the researcher is not in the room. They will be video-recorded during this period to ensure that they have interacted with their assigned item and have not interfered with their wound.
The intervention will only be delivered to the participants in a one-off 30 minute period. This procedure will occur in a research clinic at the University of Auckland
</interventions>
    <comparator>The active control group will receive some magazines to read through during the 30 minute time period and will not receive any other form of enrichment item.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in trans-epidermal water loss (TEWL) as measured using the Tewameter TM 300</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-Tape stripping and post-intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in salivary cortisol </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-tape stripping and post-intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mood as measured using a Modified version of the actual affect sub scale of the Affect Valuation Index </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-tape stripping and Post-Intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in salivary alpha-amylase</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-tape stripping and post- intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in current stress levels as measured using 100mm visual analogue scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-tape stripping and post- intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in current anxiety levels as measured using 100mm visual analogue scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-tape stripping and post- intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in current pain levels as measured using 100mm visual analogue scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-tape stripping and post- intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in current relaxation levels as measured using 100mm visual analogue scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, Post-tape stripping and post- intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Over 16 years of age 
Can read and write in English fluently
Can provide written informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Are allergic to tape or adhesives
Have an inflammatory skin disorder
Are taking medication that affects the immune system (e.g. antibiotics or corticosteroids)
Are pregnant
Cannot write or read in English fluently
Are under 16 years of age
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation to condition will be done by another researcher who is not conducting the experiment. Group allocation will be concealed from the participant and researcher until the time of the intervention. At this point, the researcher will open a sealed envelope which contains the randomised group allocation for that participant.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)
</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size required for this study was calculated using the programme G*Power. The analysis was conducted using a 4(conditions) x 3(time points) mixed design analysis of variance (ANOVA). A power level of .80 and alpha level of .05 were chosen as they are the recommended parameters. An effect size of F= 0.28 was calculated using the results of a similar tape-stripping study which  also examined the changes in trans-epidermal water loss (TEWL) due to an intervention, in this case a relaxation intervention (Robinson et al., 2015).  These parameters led to a required total sample size of at least N=100. This sample size was increased by 20% due to the possible error rate of TEWL measurement.
Mixed factorial Analysis of Variance (ANOVAs) will be used to analyse the interaction and main effects of condition (control, music, comfort and Paro) and time-point (baseline, post-tape stripping and post-intervention) on TEWL.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/08/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/12/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Auckland</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
New Zealand</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to investigate whether different forms of environmental enrichment (EE) (i.e. tactile enrichment, auditory enrichment, and social and sensory enrichment) can improve wound healing. The current study will estimate wound healing using the tape stripping model to assess skin barrier recovery over a 30 minute recovery period. During this period, participants will be randomised to one of four groups which will either receive an EE item or not.(comfort-blankets-, music, Paro or control groups).
The hypothesis for this study states that the three EE groups (the comfort, Paro and music groups) will have improved wound healing during the 30 minute recovery period, as assessed by trans-epidermal water loss (TEWL) measures, than the control group who does not receive a form of EE. The EE groups are also expected to have improved mood and stress scores as assessed by the questionnaires after interacting with their form of EE when compared to the control group.
There are no specific hypotheses for any possible differences in skin barrier recovery or mood and stress for the three EE groups as no research has yet to directly compare these forms of EE.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee (UAHPEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of the Vice Chancellor, Research Office
Alfred Nathan House, The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019, Auckland 1142</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/07/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>019556</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/06/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Broadbent</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine, 
 University of Auckland,
 Level 12, Auckland Hospital Support Building, Grafton, 
Private Bag 92019,  Auckland, 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 Ext. 86756</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.broadbent@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Broadbent</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine, 
 University of Auckland,
 Level 12, Auckland Hospital Support Building, Grafton, 
Private Bag 92019, Auckland, 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 Ext. 86756</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.broadbent@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Broadbent</name>
      <address> Department of Psychological Medicine, 
 University of Auckland,
 Level 12, Auckland Hospital Support Building, Grafton, 
Private Bag 92019, Auckland, 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 Ext. 86756</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.broadbent@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Mikaela Law</name>
      <address>Department of Psychological Medicine, 
 University of Auckland,
 Level 12, Auckland Hospital Support Building, Grafton, 
Private Bag 92019, Auckland, 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 373 7599 Ext. 89453</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mlaw382@aucklanduni.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>