<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336012">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000901000</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Implementing a Minimal Intervention Dentistry Clinical Protocol for adolescent public dental patients at high risk of dental caries: a pilot study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In adolescent public dental patients at high risk of dental caries, does a minimal intervention dentistry clinical protocol change caries risk assessment when compared to standard care?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>MID-APP (Minimal Intervention Dentistry Adolescent Pilot Project)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dental caries</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm 1 - Control Arm - Standard course of dental care 

Arm 2 - Test Arm - will have all four principles of Minimal Intervention Dentistry (MID) approach for the management of dental caries implemented by the community clinic oral health practitioners, namely:
1. prevention and early intervention to control the disease. Patients caries risk level will be identified as outlined by Evans et al (2008) and a treatment plan based on the caries risk assessment will be developed and implemented. A dental therapist will undertake motivational interviews with the patients to promote self management of dental caries including oral hygiene instruction, dietary habits, the importance of saliva, the role of fluoride and antibacterial therapies.
2. Remineralisation and ongoing monitoring of non-cavitated active lesions including preventive and re-mineralization procedures, application of fluoride varnish and bioavailable calcium phosphate agents, and application of fissure sealants. In addition, patients will be provided with oral health care products for home care as required.
3. Any carious lesion becoming cavitated or progressing into the outer third of the dentine (based on the bitewing radiographs) will be restored by the dental therapist/s employed by the community dental clinic using adhesive and biomimetic restorative materials according to the protocol for the management of carious lesions devised by Jenson et al (2008).
4. Where appropriate, failed restorations will be repaired rather than being replaced by the dental therapists/s employed by the community dental clinic with the use of minimal cavity designs and adhesive and biomimetic restorative materials.
The overall duration of the intervention is 12 months with review appointments at 3 months, 6 months and 12 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients identified to be at risk to dental careis are examined, provided with dental treatment as required and are reviewed every 12 months as the standard course of dental care.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1: Change in caries risk assessment. A   Caries Risk Assessment tool based on the literature has been developed for this project which include disease indicators, biological predisposing factors and protective factors. Three caries management by risk assessment catagories have been identified: 1. Low risk, moderate risk and high risk.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at baseline, 3, 6 and 12 months after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Secondary outcome: identify barriers within a community dental setting to the implementation of an MID clinical protocol for the magagement of adolescent public dental patients at high risk to dental caries. The assessment will include semi-structured interviews with the clinicians involved in the MID-APP Pilot Project at the completion of the project in 12 months.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: at 12 months after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria for this study include:
1. Adolescent patients (13-18 years) who hold a concession card or are dependents of a concession card holder. 
2. Adolescent patients assessed as being at high risk to developing dental caries.
3. Adolescent patients attending 12-month high-risk recall visit at the Western Region Health Centre Dental clinic.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>13</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria for this study include:
1. Methamphetamine users and drug addicted patients
2. Patients with severe salivary gland hypofunction
3. Patients with medical or physical conditions that may, in the opinion of the investigators, compromise the study outcome e.g. requiring anticoagulant therapy; diagnosed intellectual, physical or mental health disability; conditions requiring chemotherapy or radiotherapy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After assessing the eligibility of the participants, obtaining consent and collecting baseline data, subjects will be randomly allocated to treatment groups.  Treatment allocation will be concealed with treatments being assigned by opening sequentially numbered opaque envelopes.  The treating dentist will be required to sign and date the randomization log as each envelop is opened.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated block randomization schedule using random blocks. The random allocation sequence will be contained within opaque envelopes with numerical sequencing corresponding to the order in which subjects are recruited into the trial.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dental Health Services Victoria</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Corporate Office 
GPO 1273L Melbourne 
Melbourne VIC 3001

720 Swanston Street
Carlton VIC 3053
VIC</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Dental Health Services Victoria</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Corporate Office 
GPO Box 1273L 
Melbourne VIC 3001

720 Swanston Street
Carlton VIC 3053</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Dental School</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>720 Swanston Street
Carlton VIC 3053</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Colgate-Palmolive Ltd.,</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Level 4
345 Geroge Street Sydney
NSW 2000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>GC Asia Dental PTE Ltd</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Changi International Logistics Centre
19 Loyang Way, #06-27
508724</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Singapore</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Dental caries (tooth decay) is the second most costly diet-related disease in Australia. Its economic impact is comparable with that of heart disease and diabetes with an increasing total expenditure for dental services from $4.4 billion per annum (6.1 % of total health expenditure) in 2001 to more than $5.3 billion per annum (10% of total health expenditure across Australia) in 2007. Research has demonstrated that placing dental fillings does nothing to manage the dental caries disease process. Minimal Intervention Dentistry (MID) is a multi-pronged approach which focuses on the management of dental caries as a diet related, transmissible, infectious disease. It comprises measures that range from prevention, early intervention, and treatment. The proposed research will be undertaken with a group of adolescent public dental patients (concession-card holders). The current direct-service delivery model does not place specific emphasis on the management of dental caries through caries risk assessment, prevention or early intervention.  The overall goal of this project is to undertake a pilot study to test the impact on caries-risk status of implementing a MID clinical protocol to a group of adolescent public dental patients (aged 13-18 years) who are at high risk to dental caries.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Dental Health Services Victoria Human Research Ethics Committee.</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Corporate Office
GPO 1273L 
Melbourne VIC 3001

720 Swanston Street
Carlton VIC 3053</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/09/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>219</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Hanny Calache</name>
      <address>Dental Health Services Victoria
GPO Box 1273L 
Melbourne VIC 3001

720 Swanston Street
Carlton VIC 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9341 1291</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9341 1234</fax>
      <email>hanny.calache@dhsv.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Su-yan Barrow</name>
      <address>Dental Health Services Victoria
GPO Box 1273L 
Melbourne VIC 3001

720 Swanston Street
Carlton VIC 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9341 1393</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9341 1234</fax>
      <email>suyan.barrow@dhsv.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Su-yan Barrow</name>
      <address>Dental Health Services Victoria
GPO Box 1273L 
Melbourne VIC 3001

720 Swanston Street
Carlton VIC 3053</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9341 1393</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9341 1234</fax>
      <email>suyan.barrow@dhsv.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>