<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362756">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000781842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Association between oral health and nutritional status in three generations.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Understanding aging: reflection of nutritional status on the oral conditions in three generations.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Oral health</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Nutritional status</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Brazilian population is aging at an increasing pace, especially in recent decades. This increase in life expectancy is due to several factors that together has provided an improvement in living conditions. The result is a significant change in the age of the population pyramid distribution, with a reduction in birth rate and aging population. The feed can affect the development and cooperate in the progression of diseases of the oral cavity, while these diseases can result in tooth loss, which in turn, within this cycle, may influence the choice of food. Cross-sectional study with 54 subjects (grandparent-elderly), of both sexes, each with his child (54 adult) and grandchild (54 child). In this study was measured the association between oral condition and nutritional status. The oral health status was determined using the codes and criteria established by the World Health Organization (1997) and assessed by a dmft index (decayed, missing or filled primary teeth) for children, DMFT index (permanent teeth decayed, missing and filled) for adults and the number of functional units present in the oral cavity was used for grandparents. The classification of nutritional status was performed according to criteria adopted by World Health Organization (WHO, 2008) for adults and the elderly and, for children was used the criteria recommended by WHO, 2006, 2007, based on Body Mass Index (BMI). The approximate duration of assessment in each participant was of the 2 hours and on one occasion only.</interventions>
    <comparator>Uncontrolled</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of oral health status
Oral health status was assessed by a single calibrated operator under natural light. The dmft index (decayed, missing or filled primary teeth) for children, DMFT index (permanent teeth decayed, missing and filled) for adults and the number of functional units present in the oral cavity was used for grandparents, were determined using the codes and criteria established by the World Health Organization (1999). The oral health status was classified into satisfactory and unsatisfactory, according to age, adapted indexes, established for oral health by the WHO (1997) and SB-Brazil Project (2004). For ages between five and under twelve years was considered satisfactory when dmft/DMFT equal zero and unsatisfactory when dmft/DMFTmore than zero. For ages between twenty years and less than or equal to sixty-five years was considered satisfactory when DMFT less or equal to 13 and unsatisfactory when DMFT more than 13. For individuals with more than to sixty-five years was considered satisfactory when have 10-14 functional units dental and unsatisfactory when less or equal to 10 functional units dental. Habits related to oral health care were investigated through an interview with questions that relate to the following variables: frequency of consumption of foods with sugar and visit to the dentist.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Evaluated only once at the end of study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of nutritional status
For the evaluation of body weight was used a portable electronic scale (Marte MS-160 with platform, Sao Paulo, Sao Paulo, Brazil), with a sensibility of 50 g and maximum capacity of 160 kg. To check this, was following this procedures: light clothes and without shoes, the individual remained standing on the center of scale platform, with your weight evenly distributed on both feet, with arms side of the body. Weight was recorded in kilograms (kg) and grams (g) (WHO, 1995). To check the height was used a anthropometer (Alturaexata, Belo Horizonte, Minas Gerais, Brazil), with a precision of 0.1 cm, as recommended by WHO (1995). With the head in the line of sight perpendicular to the body, ie, parallel to the ground, the individual was instructed to inhale deeply, and in apnea was taken the measure of stature. The reference was the measure the highest point of the head with sufficient pressure to compress the hair. There were two measures, by calculating the arithmetic mean of these (WHO, 1995). The classification of nutritional status was performed according to criteria adopted by World Health Organization (WHO, 2008) for adults and the elderly and, for children was used the criteria recommended by WHO, 2006, 2007, based on Body Mass Index (BMI). The triceps skinfold (TSF) was collected with the skinfold compass (Lange Skinfold Caliper, Santa Cruz, California, USA) in the right hemibody, according to the methodology of the World Health Organization (1995). For TSF were used the reference values of Frisancho (1981). The waist circumference (WC) was collected using the procedure described by Callaway et al. (1991). Were used a flexible tape measure with an precision of 1 mm. The values of waist circumference for children and adolescents are presented as percentiles, with the cut off points by age and sex according to Taylor et al. (2000). The classification of central obesity in adults and older met the criteria suggested by WHO (2000). To measurement the circumference of the calf was used the methodology of the World Health Organization (1995). Was used a tape measure graduated, flexible, inelastic, with an accuracy of 0.1 cm. Habits eating were investigated through an interview.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Evaluated only once at the end of study.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Socio-economic status
The sample was classified according to a criterion adapted from the Brazil economic classification, developed by the Associacao Brasileira de Empresas de Pesquisa (2003), that classifies the population in economic classes A, B, C, D and E, as determined by their spending power and level of schooling of the head of the family.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Evaluated only once at the end of study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Aged 60 years and above, the cut-off point for the definition of elderly recognised by the World Health Organization (1989), together with members of their family, following a trigenerational lineage: their son/daughter  adult, and their grandchild- child, aged 5 to 12 years (age groups recognised by the World Health Organization (1999) for evaluations of oral health).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>5</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>84</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Absence of three generations (child and grandchild) who did not reside in Florianopolis, presence of diseases that prevented the exams.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>7/04/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>162</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Santa Catarina</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Emilia Addison Machado Moreira</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina (UFSC), Centro de Ciencia da Saude, Departamento de Nutricao - Campus Reitor Joao David Ferreira Lima, Trindade, s/n, Florianopolis, Santa Catarina, ZIP: 88.049-970.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cientifico e Tecnologico (CNPq)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>SEPN 507, Bloco B - Ed. Sede do CNPq - ZIP: 70740-901 - Brasilia, Distrito Federal.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Michelle Soares Rauen</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina (UFSC), Centro de Ciencia da Saude, Departamento de Nutricao - Campus Reitor Joao David Ferreira Lima, Trindade, s/n, Florianopolis, Santa Catarina, ZIP: 88.049-970.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: The literature reports an interface between nutritional status and oral health status, as there is a close relationship between oral health, chewing function and dietary intake. Objective: The objective of this study was to examine the relationship between nutritional status and oral condition in three generations. Subjects and methods: The cross-sectional study was carried out with 54 subjects (grandparent-elderly), of both sexes, each with his child (54 adult) and grandchild (54 child). The assessment of nutritional status was the according to World Health Organization (1995). The classification of nutritional status was performed according to criteria adopted by World Health Organization (WHO, 2008) for adults and the elderly and, for children was used the criteria recommended by WHO, 2006, 2007, based on Body Mass Index (BMI). Assessment of oral health status was assessed by a single calibrated operator under natural light were determined using the codes and criteria established by the World Health Organization (1997). The dmft index (decayed, missing or filled primary teeth) was used for children, DMFT index (permanent teeth decayed, missing and filled) was used for adults and the number of functional units present in the oral cavity was used for grandparents. The oral health status was classified into satisfactory and unsatisfactory, according to age, adapted indexes, established for oral health by the WHO (1997) and SB-Brazil Project (2004). Outcome: In relation with intrafamilial agreement, both in oral health status as eating habits, there was statistical significance between the adult and children generations. Furthermore, we found a high percentage of agreement between these two generations in the eating and oral habits.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>ROSSI, A; MOREIRA, EAM; RAUEN, MS. Determinative of the eating behavior: an approach in the family a review. Journal of Nutrition (ISSN 1415-5273) 2008; 21(6):739-748.

ROSSI, A. Body composition intragenerational family. 2007. Dissertation (MSc Nutrition), Post-graduate Programme in Nutrition, Federal University of Santa Catarina, Florianopolis.

RAUEN, M.S. Oral condition and its relationship with the nutritional status in three generations. 2006. 127 f. Thesis (Doctorate in Dentistry Public Health)  Post-graduate Programme in Dentistry, Federal University of Santa Catarina, Florianopolis.

RAUEN, MS; BATISTA, LRV; MOREIRA, EAM, CALVO, MCM. Oral condition in three generations. In: 23 Reuniao Anual da Sociedade Brasileira de Pesquisa Odontologica SBPqO, 2006, Atibaia. Brazilian Oral Research, v.20, Suppl. set, p. 255. Sao Paulo: 2006. 

ROSSI, A; RAUEN, MS; MOREIRA, EAM. Body composition intragenerational family. In: 14 Congreso Latinoamericano de Nutricion, 2006, Florianopolis. Anais do 14 Congreso Latinoamericano de Nutricion. Florianopolis, novembro, 2006, v.1, p. NS 0067 - NS 0067. 

RAUEN, MS; ROSSI, A; MOREIRA, EAM. Oral condition and nutritional status intragenerational family. In: 14 Congreso Latinoamericano de Nutricion, 2006, Florianopolis. Anais do 14 Congreso Latinoamericano de Nutricion. Florianopolis, novembro, 2006, v. 1, p. NS 0300-NS 0300.

ROSSI, A; RAUEN, MS; MOREIRA, EAM. Correlation between body mass index (BMI) and anthopometric index and metabolic adiposity. In: 14 Congreso Latinoamericano de Nutricion, 2006, Florianopolis.  Anais do 14 Congreso Latinoamericano de Nutricion. Florianopolis, novembro, 2006, v.1. p.NS 0048 - NS 0048.

ROSSI, A; RAUEN, MS; MOREIRA, EAM. Eating behavior: intragenerational relation. In: 14 Congreso Latinoamericano de Nutricion, 2006, Florianopolis. Anais do 14 Congreso Latinoamericano de Nutricion. Florianopolis, novembro, 2006. v.1. p. NS 0081-NS 0081.

RAUEN, MS; ROSSI, A; MOREIRA, EAM. Behavior: parents and childs. In: 14 Congreso Latinoamericano de Nutricion, 2006, Florianopolis. Anais do 14 Congreso Latinoamericano de Nutricion. Florianopolis, novembro, 2006, v.1. p.NS 0383 - NS 0383.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committe for Researchs with Humans of Federal University of Santa Catarina (UFSC).</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Pro-Reitoria de Pesquisa e Extensao. Campus Universitario - Trindade - Florianopolis/SC. ZIP: 88040-900 Caixa Postal 476.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/03/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>320/2004</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/09/2004</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emilia Addison Machado Moreira</name>
      <address>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina (UFSC), Centro de Ciencia da Saude, Departamento de Nutricao, Campus Reitor Joao David Ferreira Lima, Trindade, s/n, Florianopolis, Santa Catarina, ZIP: 88040-970.</address>
      <phone>+55 (48) 3721-9784 (for Santa Catarina, Brazil)</phone>
      <fax>+55 (48) 3721-9542 (for Santa Catarina, Brazil)</fax>
      <email>addison@ccs.ufsc.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emilia Addison Machado Moreira</name>
      <address>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina (UFSC), Centro de Ciencia da Saude, Departamento de Nutricao, Campus Reitor Joao David Ferreira Lima, Trindade, s/n, Florianopolis, Santa Catarina, ZIP: 88040-970.</address>
      <phone>+55 (48) 3721-9784 (for Santa Catarina, Brazil)</phone>
      <fax>+55 (48) 3721-9542 (for Santa Catarina, Brazil)</fax>
      <email>addison@ccs.ufsc.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emilia Addison Machado Moreira</name>
      <address>Universidade Federal de Santa Catarina (UFSC), Centro de Ciencia da Saude, Departamento de Nutricao, Campus Reitor Joao David Ferreira Lima, Trindade, s/n, Florianopolis, Santa Catarina, ZIP: 88040-970.</address>
      <phone>+55 (48) 3721-9784 (for Santa Catarina, Brazil)</phone>
      <fax>+55 (48) 3721-9542 (for Santa Catarina, Brazil)</fax>
      <email>addison@ccs.ufsc.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>