<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82061">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/05/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/06/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000291482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can singing training can improve voice projection for people with a spinal cord injury?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effects of singing and vocal training on respiratory function and voice projection of people with a spinal cord injury</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Quadriplegia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the respiratory system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>12 weeks of singing training vs an active control intervention. The treatment condition involves instruction in breath control and vocal techniques for singing and the opportunity to sing familiar, popular songs in small groups (n=4). Treatment sessions will be held twice a week for the first 4 weeks for approximately 1 hour and participants will be expected to practise at least once per week at home with a practise CD. The following 8 weeks will involve only 1 group session and 2 home practise sessions.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control condition involves 12 weeks of music therapy activities that do not include singing: music appreciation and relaxation. The sessions will be run in small groups (n=4) similar to the treatment arm. Sessions will be held twice a week for the first 4 weeks for approximately 1 hour and once a week for the following 8 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory capacity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures of effectiveness will be made at baseline, 6weeks (midway), 12 weeks and 6 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory muscle strength (specifically maximal sniff and inspiratory (MIP) muscle pressures)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures of effectiveness will be made at baseline, 6 weeks (midway), 12 weeks and 6 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quantitative measures of voice (pitch, amplitude)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measures of effectiveness will be made at baseline, 6 weeks (midway), 12 weeks and 6 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measures of thoraco-abdominal motion, indices of respiratory flow and volume and qualitative assessments of voice.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at baseline, 6 weeks (midway), 12 weeks and 6 months post intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Quadriplegia C4-C7, at least 1 year post injury. Currently resident in Victoria and able to travel to the Royal Talbot Rehabilitation Centre for 12 weeks for training. English speaking and stable general health without pulmonary disease at the time of assessment.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Previous history of speech disorder, respiratory disease, psychiatric disorder, or neurological impairment prior to SCI. Currently receiving singing or voice tuition.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated sequence</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>All data will be analysed by a researcher blinded to the treatment allocation (blinded assesor)</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/04/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/04/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>24</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>12/07/2010</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 5555 Studley Rd, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Victorian Neurotrauma Incentive</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 14, 222 Exhibition Street, Melbourne Victoria 3000, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Melbourne</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Parkville, Victoria, 3052, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Institute for Breathing and Sleep,</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 5555 Studley Rd, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084, Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Melbourne</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Parkville, Victoria, 3052 Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Respiratory dysfunction is a major cause of morbidity and mortality in spinal cord injury (SCI). Therapeutic singing exercises have been demonstrated to develop muscle control, expand lung capacity and increase vocal intensity with other clinical populations. This study will be the first to systematically document the physiological effect of singing instruction on respiratory function and voice projection in a quadriplegia population. All subjects will participate in physiological and acoustic assessments whilst vocalising, singing, and speaking. Forty subjects with chronic cervical SCI will be randomised into control and experimental groups. Subjects in the treatment group will participate in twice weekly singing instruction in small groups (n=5), with an additional weekly homepractise session, for a period of 20 weeks. All subjects will repeat the initial assessments after 10 and 20 weeks. Control subjects will participate in the vocal training after 20 weeks. The relevance of this project is indicated by research that shows that respiratory disorders and subsequent diminished vocal projection are common and disabling in the quadriplegia population. Singing training has been shown to improve respiratory capacity and voice projection in other clinical populations. In a health care setting where evidence-based practise is highly valued, the examination of the effect of this innovative therapy on ventilatory function is strongly indicated.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Tamplin, J., Baker, F., Grocke, D., &amp; Berlowitz, D. J. (2014). A thematic analysis of the experience of group music therapy for people with chronic quadriplegia. Topics in Spinal Cord Injury Rehabilitation, 20(3), 256-268. IF: 1.226.

Tamplin, J., Baker, F., Buttifant, M., &amp; Berlowitz, D. J. (2014). The effect of singing training on voice quality and intensity for people with quadriplegia. Journal of Voice. 28(1), 128.e19128.e26. Doi.10.1016/j.jvoice.2013.08.017.  IF: 1.55.

Tamplin, J., Baker, F., Grocke, D., Brazzale, D., Pretto, J. J., Ruehland, W. R., et al. (2013). The effect of singing on respiratory function, voice, and mood following quadriplegia: A randomized controlled trial. Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, 94(3), 426-434. 
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Austin Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/12/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H2007/02931</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/05/2007</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jeanette Tamplin</name>
      <address>Music Therapy
University of Melbourne
234 St Kilda Road
Southbank
VIC 3006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 3003</phone>
      <fax>no fax</fax>
      <email>jeanette.tamplin@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jeanette Tamplin</name>
      <address>Music Therapy
University of Melbourne
234 St Kilda Road
Southbank
VIC 3006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 3003</phone>
      <fax>no fax</fax>
      <email>jeanette.tamplin@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jeanette Tamplin</name>
      <address>Music Therapy
University of Melbourne
234 St Kilda Road
Southbank
VIC 3006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 3003</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jeanette.tamplin@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jeanette Tamplin</name>
      <address>Music Therapy
University of Melbourne
234 St Kilda Road
Southbank
VIC 3006</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 3003</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jeanette.tamplin@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>