<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370519">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/05/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000608460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The feasibility of the Huarahi Hauora wellness intervention for obese Maori adults.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluating the feasibility of the Huarahi Hauora wellness intervention for weight loss for obese Maori adults.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>UTN: U111111792602</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Indigenous Health and Wellness</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Duration of intervention 9 months - Trial arm 1; 6 months Trial arm 2 (initial 3 month wait list) - acting as wait list control. Indigenous knowledge and customs - no physical materials will be supplied in this intervention. Indigenous customs will involve whakawhanaungatanga (relationship building), manaakitanga (the process of showing respect, generosity and care for others), kaitiakitanga (guardianship) and karakia (incantation, prayer). The intervention currently described has been designed so that it integrates indigenous knowledge and customs. 

Participants will become part of a closed Facebook Group. They will be encouraged to make postings on Facebook that will be administered by the on-site researcher.  The style and content of the postings will be left up to the participants and they will be encouraged to share in any way they see fit  both successes and challenges. Participants will be posting on health related successes and challenges. Weekly contacts by the on-site researcher will be Recordings of all postings will be kept while inappropriate postings will be removed by the administrator in consultation with the off-site researchers. Off-site researchers are the other 4 researchers already named in this proposal (ST, GK, CS and LH) excluding Ricky Bell. Ricky Bell is the University Based on-site researcher. Participants will be encouraged to make postings on Facebook that will be administered by the off-site and on-site researchers. This research will adhere to the ethical guidelines and use of social media (Basevi, Reid, &amp; Godbold, 2014). Basevi, R., Reid, D., &amp; Godbold, R. (2014). Ethical guidelines and the use of social media and text messaging in health care: a review of literature. (Report). New Zealand Journal of Physiotherapy, 42(2), 68.  

Participants will also receive at least one contact per week by the on-site researcher either via phone call, social media, text or email. The purpose of these weekly contacts is intended to encourage participation in physical activity and to encourage posting to the Facebook group. The mode of weekly contact (call, text or email) will be guided by tikanga (custom) and what the participants preference is on enrolment, although this may freely change at the direction of the participant over the course of the trial. Fortnightly gatherings for group physical activity events (PAE) will be made available to participants during the intervention. Initially these will be made available by the on-site researcher (a registered physiotherapist with over 20 years experience). Fortnightly PAE gatherings are entirely optional will be in a variety of settings from traditional meeting venues (marae), and the many sites of significance around Te Tai Tokerau (TTT). A variety of venues and locations will be employed given the geographical sparseness of TTT, hence not all participants will be able to attend on each occasion. Importantly, the PAE for physical activity is not the focus of this trial or intervention. The emphasis of this feasibility trial is not to provide passive options for participation in PAE (i.e. more frequent PAE, such as 5 sessions per week at 30minutes each), instead it is to encourage participants to engage in PAE that fit with their lifestyle, time constraints, and within their physical capability. In doing so it positions this research in a real world environment and hopefully will offer more meaningful results.  The format and content of the PAEs will be simple, variable and developed by the on-site researcher. PAE will be graded according to the capacity of each participant. Emphasis will be on participation not intensity level or degree of difficulty of PAE.  Fortnightly PAE gatherings will be held at any place chosen by the group, local park, etc. - total duration that these will be made available is a maximum of 9 months.  Participants will only be able to attend at the chosen time that suits the majority of the group. PAE events may include walking on the spot, walking, squat variations, lunge variations, and group or whanau PAE events. Fidelity will be monitored by the on-site researcher in collaboration with the off-site researchers. Importantly, other aspects of this trial incorporate indigenous knowledge systems to be retained by the indigenous people of Te Tai Tokerau and are not for the public domain (Bell, R., Tumilty, S., Kira, G., Smith, C., &amp; Hale, L. (2016). Using a community based participatory research model within an indigenous framework to establish an exploratory platform of investigation into obesity. Obesity Medicine, 2, 19-24).



</interventions>
    <comparator>3 month wait list control group</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of recruitment of participants, both GP and whanau/hapu referred - will be noted within the indigenous domain.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>9 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Level of engagement/participation levels - with a participation log (will upload the document)</outcome>
      <timepoint>9 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Information elicited from participant and exit questionnaire that have been specifically designed for this study. (attached) The outcome being elicited from participants is satisfaction with the program. </outcome>
      <timepoint>9 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Te Ao Maori Outcome

Tihei-wa mauri ora - wellness indicator (wairuatanga). See Piripi, T and Body, V (2010). Tihei-wa Mauri Ora. New Zealand Journal of Counselling. 30(1):34-46.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>9 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>BMI - is calculated using he formula: weight (kg) / [height (m)]2</outcome>
      <timepoint>9 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist to hip circumference ratio assessed using a tape measure. </outcome>
      <timepoint>9 months post commencement of intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference - a tape measure placed around the waist. </outcome>
      <timepoint>9 months post commencement of intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Consenting participants between 18-65 years will be Maori, reside or whakapapa into Te Tai Tokerau and have a BMI greater than or equal to 30 kg/m2. They will have been assessed by their GP to be considered medically safe to participate in this trial. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Non-Maori, known pregnancy and any co-morbidity or serious condition(s) which are considered by the researchers to be too at risk of sustaining a serious adverse event such as a cardiac event or death at any time over the course if the trial. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment  will be done via central randomisation by phone/fax/computer by the off-site researchers.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software will be employed.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/04/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/08/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/02/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Centre for Health, Activity, and Rehabilitation Research (CHARR), School of Physiotherapy, University of Otago</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Physiotherapy
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Department of Internal Affairs, Lottery Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Department of Internal Affairs
46 Waring Taylor Street
WELLINGTON 6011
PO Box 805
WELLINGTON 6140</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this feasibility trial is to investigate if indigenous knowledge systems and customs will enable Maori to progress towards a place of wellness. The primary purpose of the study is to determine if a tikanga (protocol) based intervention whose purpose is to enable Maori to progress towards a place of wellness is feasible. We also aim to see if this approach will offer suggestion of improved health outcomes.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>
    </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees Ministry of Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Health and Disability Ethics Committees
Ministry of Health
Freyberg Building
20 Aitken Street
PO Box 5013
Wellington
6011
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/NTB/28</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>11/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370519-HDEC Letter 16NTB28 Approved EXP Application.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370519-Particpation - Compliance Log Huarahi Hauora.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370519-Huarahi Hauora exit questionnaire.doc</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Steve Tumilty</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 3 479 7193</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>steve.tumilty@otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ricky Bell</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64212545422</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bodyhealthnz@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ricky Bell</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64212545422</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bodyhealthnz@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Ricky Bell</name>
      <address>School of Physiotherapy
University of Otago
PO Box 56
Dunedin 9054
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64212545422</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bodyhealthnz@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>