<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363570">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/03/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000339651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Increasing physical activity levels in the general population: Evaluating the benefit of a brief online coaching session in a web-based intervention that provides personalised physical activity advice. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Comparing the physical activity outcomes of a web-based physical activity intervention, 'My Activity Coach' with and without a brief online coaching session, in Australian adults. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>The health consequences of physical inactivity (e.g. chronic disease)   </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>An 8 week web-based physical activity intervention with 4 modules of computer-tailored physical activity advice. Each module is delivered bi-weekly and has a duration of approximately 30 minutes. The modules deliver personalised physical activity advice based on the participants demographics, physical activity and psychosocial correlates of physical activity as assessed via a survey at the beginning of each module. The content of the modules is based on the theory of planned behaviour. Participants will also receive 4 brief online video coaching sessions with an activity coach. These coaching sessions will take place fortnightly, on alternate weeks to the modules and will be approximately 15minutes in duration. They will be delivered through an online video calling program of the participants choice (e.g. Skype, Google Hangout, Yahoo Messenger, FaceTime). Participants who fail to complete a module in the first 7 days of the fortnight will be given a follow-up phone call.</interventions>
    <comparator>There will be one comparator treatment group, and one wait-list control group which will make 3 groups in total. The comparator group (tailoring only group) will receive the same 8 week web-based physical activity intervention with 4 modules of computer-tailored physical activity advice as the main intervention group (coaching + tailoring group), but will not receive the brief online video coaching sessions. The wait-list control group will complete the research questionnaires (baseline, 9 weeks, 6 months and 12 months post intervention) before they are given access to complete the web-based physical activity intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical Activity Behavior, measured by the Active Australia Questionnaire (AAQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 9 weeks (post intervention), 6 months (follow up), 12 months (follow up)   </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life, measured by the SF-12v2 Health Survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 9 weeks (post intervention), 6 months (follow up), 12 months (follow up)    </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Constructs of Theory of Planned Behaviour including attitude, subjective norm, perceived behavioural control and intentions. These constructs will be measured using the items developed by (Rhodes, Hunt Matheson, &amp; Mark, 2010). Additional items will be used to measure participants planning. These items were developed by (Trinh, Plotnikoff, Rhodes, North, &amp; Courneya, 2012).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 9 weeks (post intervention), 6 months (follow up), 12 months (follow up)   </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intervention satisfaction will be assessed for participants in the coaching + tailoring and tailoring-only group. Participants satisfaction with components of the intervention including the questions, the tailored advice, website usability, the coaching sessions (for coaching + tailoring participants only) and the overall program will be assessed by 5, 19, 18, 9 and 17 items respectively. The majority of items are on a 5-point Likert scale where participants are asked to rate their agreement to statements about the components of the advice. The response options range from strongly agree to strongly disagree. Four open ended items will also be included in the sections on the tailored advice, website usability, the coaching session and the overall program to provide participants with the opportunity to describe 1) what they did like, 2) what they did not like, 3) any recommendations they have and 4) if they have any further comments about the components.</outcome>
      <timepoint>9 weeks (post intervention).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intervention engagement and retention. Intervention engagement will be measured through participants adherence to the intervention modules, and web-site user statistics. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Intervention engagement and retention will be measured throughout the intervention period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Residents of Mackay and Rockhampton Regions, Queensland, Australia.  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Non-English speaking, Pregnant, under 18 years of age, currently meeting the physical activity guidelines, and at risk of injury or ill health from increasing physical activity (as assessed by the Physical Activity Readiness Questionnaire).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Online advertisements (Facebook, Google and community forums) and print advertisements (newspaper, leaflets and posters) will direct interested individuals to a recruitment page of the intervention website where they can find out more information about the study, and download the information sheet. If they wish to register they are invited to complete an online screening questionnaire which includes an online consent form. Participants who give their consent and are eligible to participate will be identified electronically by the computer software used to administer the surveys. A researcher will then randomly assign eligible participants to one of the three treatment groups. Participant's group assignment will not be disclosed until after they have completed the online baseline questionnaire. As the questionnaires are delivered online, the researchers are not involved in their administration. </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly allocated to one of the three groups based on the order of a computer-generated sequence (randomisation.com).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Intervention effects
Data will be analysed using intention to treat principles. Physical activity will be modelled using the using liner mixed models with random intercepts, the fixed effects of group (control, tailoring only, coaching + tailoring) and time (baseline, post-intervention, 6-months, 12-months), and a group by time interaction and will adjust for potential confounders including gender, age group and BMI if they are associated with physical activity and time.
Secondary analyses
The secondary analyses will be conducted using linear effects modelling to determine the effect of group and time on theory of planned behaviour constructs and quality of life. Linear mixed modelling will also be used to compare retention, satisfaction, adherence and web-site user statistics between groups. Multiple regression analyses will be conducted to assess TPB concepts including intention, attitude, subjective norm, perceived behavioural control and planning as mediators for physical activity changes. Descriptive statistics will be used to assess participant adherence and satisfaction of the brief online coaching session. 
Sample Size
The sample size needed to detect any between group differences in the physical activity across the two time points was calculated from the sample size analysis determined by Cohen (1992). The alpha level was set to =0.05, so there is only a 5% chance of rejecting the null hypothesis. The power level was set to .80 which leaves a 20% chance of incorrectly rejecting the null hypothesis. The effect size was estimated to be small (.14) based on findings from a recent meta-analysis that the average effect size for web-based physical activity interventions is .14 (Davies et al., 2012b). An estimated attrition of 50% was also factored into the calculations based on the attrition of previous physical activity interventions of similar length. (Vandelanotte et al., 2007b). The analysis revealed that a sample size of 288, or 96 in each study arm, is required for the current study to detect any between group differences in physical activity across the two time points. (Davies et al., 2012b; Ferney et al., 2009) We will round up, and aim to recruit 100 participants in each study arm.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>7/11/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Central Queensland University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Building No. 5
CQUniversity
CQMC
Rockhampton QLD 4702</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Stephanie Alley</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Building No. 18
CQUniversity
CQMC
Rockhampton QLD 4702</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Over half of Australians fail to reach the physical activity guidelines necessary to reduce the risk of cardiovascular disease, diabetes and cancer. Due to rising levels of chronic disease placing a significant burden on Australias health care and economy, there is a need for effective population-based physical activity interventions. The internet provides a practical platform to deliver physical activity interventions as it can reach large numbers of people at low cost. Whilst the short term effectiveness of web-based interventions has been established, participant engagement and retention into the intervention have been identified as problems affecting population-level reach and long term effectiveness. This project will measure the effectiveness of brief online coaching provided via Skype versus personally tailored advice alone will be examined in terms of improving website usage, retention and physical activity outcomes. Overall study findings will inform the next generation of web-based physical activity interventions effective in improving physical activity levels in a large range of Australians, and reducing the prevalence of disease in Australia. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.myactivitycoach.org.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Building No. 5
CQUniversity
CQMC
Rockhampton QLD 4702
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H13/04-044</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/03/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Stephanie Alley</name>
      <address>Building No. 18
CQUniversity
CQMC
Rockhampton QLD 4702</address>
      <phone>61749232263</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.alley@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Stephanie Alley</name>
      <address>Building No. 18
CQUniversity
CQMC
Rockhampton QLD 4702</address>
      <phone>61749232263</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.alley@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Stephanie Alley</name>
      <address>Building No. 18
CQUniversity
CQMC
Rockhampton QLD 4702</address>
      <phone>61749232263</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.alley@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Stephanie Alley</name>
      <address>Building No. 18
CQUniversity
CQMC
Rockhampton QLD 4702</address>
      <phone>61749232263</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>s.alley@cqu.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>