<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368700">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000408482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Oral vitamin A for prevention of bronchopulmonary dysplasia in extremely preterm infants: a randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Oral (enteral) vitamin A for prevention of bronchopulmonary dysplasia in extremely preterm infants: a randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>EVARO study (Enteral vitamin A to improve Respiratory Outcomes) </trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bronchopulmonary dysplasia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Enteral water-miscible vitamin A 5000 IU (0.5 mL) once daily started within 24 hours of the introduction of oral feeds and continued until 34 week post-menstrual age. The trial medication will be prescribed on the routinely used medication charts in the neonatal nursery and the medication will be administered by a nurse caring for the baby. The nurse will document the administration of the medication in the medication chart. The charts will be reviewed every week to ensure compliance.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive identical volume (0.5 mL) of placebo solution (normal saline mixed with Quinoline Yellow 2.5 mg/100mL) enterally.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of bronchopulmonary dysplasia assessment using SpO2-PiO2 curve </outcome>
      <timepoint>36 weeks post-menstrual age (PMA) or before discharge/transfer (if it occurs before 36 weeks PMA)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Correlation between plasma and salivary retinol levels (First 30 infants) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28-30 of the study based on availability of the staff to process blood samples</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Death</outcome>
      <timepoint>Home discharge or transfer to other hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Moderate to severe BPD (defined as need for supplemental oxygen at 36 weeks' postmenstrual age (Ehrenkranz et al, 2005)) - The outcome will be assessed prospectively using Shift test / Modified Walsh Oxygen Reduction Air Trial as per ANZNN protocol (http://anznn.net/Portals/0/DataDictionaries/ANZNN_Shift_Test_protocol_template.pdf accessed on 29/03/2016) </outcome>
      <timepoint>36 weeks post-menstrual age</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Use of postnatal steroids for BPD before discharge to home (assessed by reviewing medical records and prospective data collection) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Home discharge or transfer to other hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of supplemental oxygen for the infants who did not require supplemental oxygen at the discharge/transfer (assessed by reviewing medical records and prospective data collection) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Home discharge or transfer to other hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Number of infants discharged with home oxygen (assessed by reviewing medical records and prospective data collection) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge to home</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Days of positive pressure support [mechanical ventilation + continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) + humidified high flow (HHF)] (assessed by reviewing medical records and prospective data collection) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Home discharge or transfer to other hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lung volume and alveolar moment ratio as measured with multiple breath washout method (Robinson 2013, Pillow 2004)</outcome>
      <timepoint>36 weeks PMA/pre-discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Diaphragmatic function assessment will be done using a method described by Rafferty et al. 
(Rafferty GF, Greenough A, Dimitriou G, Kavadia V, Laubscher B, Polkey MI, et al. Assessment of neonatal diaphragm functionusing magnetic stimulation of the phrenic nerve. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2000;162:2337-2340)</outcome>
      <timepoint>36 weeks PMA/pre-discharge </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Weight gain in  gram per day during the period of supplementation of the study medication (assessed by reviewing medical records and prospective data collection)   </outcome>
      <timepoint>34 weeks PMA</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Retinopathy of prematurity (ROP) requiring treatment in the form of laser ablation or bevacizumab injection (assessed by reviewing medical records and prospective data collection) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Diagnosis of suspected and culture positive sepsis (Blood or cerebrospinal fluid) (assessed by reviewing medical records and prospective data collection) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Home discharge / transfer to other hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Grade 3 or 4 intraventricular haemorrhage (IVH) / periventricular leucomalacia (PVL) (Volpe 2008) (assessed by reviewing medical records and prospective data collection) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7 and 28 of age brain ultrasound scans and MRI brain at 36-38 weeks PMA</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>	Diagnosis of necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC) using Bells criteria 2a or more. (Bell 1978)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Home discharge / transfer to other hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Vitamin A adverse effects: Tense or bulging fontanelle, hepatomegaly, skin changes (by weekly physical examination) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Death / discharge home / transfer to other hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Correlation between plasma and salivary relative dose response (RDR) (First 30 infants)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 28-30 of the study based on availability of the staff to process blood samples</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Gestational age at birth less than 28 weeks and postnatal age less than 72 hours and 	Informed parental consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>72</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Hours</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Congenital gastrointestinal and respiratory tracts abnormalities</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sequentially labelled opaque sealed envelopes containing information regarding group allocation will be used to conceal allocation. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization will be done by a hospital pharmacist using a computer generated random table. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size:  The normal SpO2: PiO2 curve in preterm infants without BPD is shifted to the right of the adult oxygen-haemoglobin dissociation curve by 6 kPa.  In the preterm infants with BPD the mean shift (standard deviation) was 16.5 (4.7) kPa. (Quine 2006) For this pilot trial, we propose a 20 % improvement in the rightward shift in the treatment group compared with the control. Allowing for up to 20 % loss of the cohort at follow-up, the required sample size is 188 (94 in each group) (power 80 %, significance 5 %). 

Statistical analysis: The data will be statistically analysed using SPSS statistical package (version 23.0, IBM Corporation and others, USA).  The primary outcome of right shift in the SpO2-PiO2 curve is a continuous outcome and will be reported as mean +/- standard deviation for two groups. The two groups will be compared for the outcome using Students t test. 
For other outcomes the groups will be compared using Mann-Whitney U test for continuous data if not normally distributed and Students t test if normally distributed and 'chi-squared' test for categorical data. Correlation between serum and salivary vitamin A levels, and blood and saliva RDR values will be tested using Pearson r correlation analysis. Bland-Altman analysis will be used to analyse agreement between two assays. A p value of &lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>19/12/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/03/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>188</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>King Edward Memorial Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Abhijeet Rakshasbhuvankar</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Neonatal Paediatrics
King Edward memorial Hospital
374 Bagot Road, Subiaco, WA 6008
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Channel 7 Telethon Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>50 Hasler Road, Osborne Park, WA 8017</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Vitamin A is required for the development and growth of lungs in premature babies who are born with low vitamin A body stores. Supplementing premature babies with additional doses of vitamin A by intramuscular injections decreases bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD - a chronic lung disease related to premature birth). As intramuscular injections are painful, the supplementation has not been widely practiced. Oral vitamin A, especially fat soluble form, is poorly absorbed by premature babies and therefore may be less effective. This study aims to investigate if supplementation of water soluble form, which is better absorbed, to extremely premature babies decreases risk of BPD. 	As a part of the study we are also looking at if we can use saliva to assess vitamin A status instead of blood in the babies. .  
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee (King Edward Memorial Hospital)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>374 Bagot Road, Subiaco, WA 6008</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/03/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016028EW</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Abhijeet Rakshasbhuvankar</name>
      <address>Department of Neonatal Paediatrics, King Edward Memorial Hospital
374 Bagot Road, Subiaco, WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61893401260</phone>
      <fax>+61893401266</fax>
      <email>abhijeet.rakshasbhuvankar@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Abhijeet Rakshasbhuvankar</name>
      <address>Department of Neonatal Paediatrics, King Edward Memorial Hospital
374 Bagot Road, Subiaco, WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61893401260</phone>
      <fax>+61893401266</fax>
      <email>abhijeet.rakshasbhuvankar@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Abhijeet Rakshasbhuvankar</name>
      <address>Department of Neonatal Paediatrics, King Edward Memorial Hospital
374 Bagot Road, Subiaco, WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61893401260</phone>
      <fax>+61893401266</fax>
      <email>abhijeet.rakshasbhuvankar@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Abhijeet Rakshasbhuvankar</name>
      <address>Department of Neonatal Paediatrics, King Edward Memorial Hospital
374 Bagot Road, Subiaco, WA 6008</address>
      <phone>+61893401260</phone>
      <fax>+61893401266</fax>
      <email>abhijeet.rakshasbhuvankar@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>