<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83081">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/08/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/10/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000522314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cognitive behavioural therapy for children with anxiety disorders</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Cognitive Behavioral Treatment versus a Non-Specific Control 
for Children and Adolescents with Anxiety Disorders: Changes in anxiety symptoms and diagnosis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>anxiety disorders in children</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Cognitive Behavioural Therapy [COOL KIDS treatment program (Rapee, Wignall, Hudson and Schniering, 2000)] 10 x 2 hour sessions delivered in group format, once weekly for 10 weeks. Treatment included parents and child. The treatment components included: Psychoeducation, cognitive restructuring, parent management, gradual exposure.</interventions>
    <comparator>non-specific control:  The Group Support and Attention (GSA) Condition was adapted from previous control conditions by removing apparent CBT components (e.g., cognitive behavioral rationale, psychoeducation about anxiety; description of techniques). Treatment involved 10 x 2 hour sessions delivered in group format once weekly for 10 weeks. Treatment included parents and child. The aims of GSA were to: (i) provide a supportive environment; (ii) provide activities to help express and understand emotions; and (iii) to build relationships between and within families. Therapists were instructed not to provide cognitive behavioral interpretations or strategies, or engage in problem solving with the families. Session content included: treatment rationale, description of anxiety (session 1); understanding emotions (sessions 2-3); understanding the childs experience of anxiety (sessions 4-10).  Participants completed weekly writing tasks for homework involving 3x 5-10 minute periods of writing about emotion. GSA families also gave a short presentation to the group about their family. Typically, parents presented the material to the group and the child provided assistance.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>presence/absence of anxiety disorder assessed by the Anxiety Disorder Interview Schedule for Children (ADIS-IV-C/P: Silverman &amp; Albano, 1996)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre treatment, post  treatment and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>maternal and child reported anxiety symptoms:
The Spence Children's Anxiety Scale (Spence, 1998)
Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (Goodman, 1997)</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre treatment, post treatment and 3 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>principal anxiety disorder</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>mental retardation, psychoses and concurrent psychological treatment</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Following a brief telephone screen, parents signed consent forms at the assessment and children provided verbal assent.  Children who met criteria for inclusion and agreed to participate were allocated to a group based on the child’s age.Allocation was concealed: clinicians determined the child's eligibility for the study and then the clinic administration team contacted the research officer who held the allocation schedule ( in a different building on campus)</concealment>
    <sequence>The first author used a schedule from a random number generator (computer software obtained online) to assign each group to treatment condition and to therapists.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Macquarie University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Balaclava Rd
Macquarie University
NSW 2109</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Macquarie University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Balaclava Rd
Macquarie University
NSW 2109</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Objective: The current trial examined whether a specific cognitive behavioral treatment package was more efficacious in treating childhood anxiety disorders than a non-specific support package. Method: One-hundred and twelve children (ages 7-16 years) with a principal anxiety disorder were randomly allocated to either a group cognitive behavioral treatment (CBT) program or a control condition (Group Support and Attention; GSA). Results: Overall, results showed that CBT was significantly more efficacious compared to the GSA condition: 68.6% of children in the CBT condition did not meet diagnostic criteria for their principal anxiety diagnosis at 6 month follow-up compared to 45.5% of children in the GSA condition. The results of the child- and parent-completed measures indicated that whereas mothers of CBT children reported significantly greater treatment gains than mothers of GSA children, children reported similar improvements across conditions. Conclusions: Specific delivery of cognitive behavioral skills is more efficacious in the treatment of childhood anxiety than a treatment that includes only non-specific therapy factors.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University Human Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Macquarie University
NSW 2109</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/05/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HE23APR-R02932A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/04/2004</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jennifer L Hudson</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Balaclava Rd
Macquarie University
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+612 98508668</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jhudson@psy.mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jennifer L Hudson</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Balaclava Rd,
Macquarie University
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>612 98508668</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jhudson@psy.mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jennifer L Hudson</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology
Balaclava Rd
Macquarie University
NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+612 98508668</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jhudson@psy.mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>