<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364000">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/04/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000422729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised clinical trial of slow versus fast intravitreal injection of ranibizumab (lucentis (Registered Trademark)) and its impact on intraocular pressure 

</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised clinical trial of slow versus fast intravitreal injection of ranibizumab (lucentis (Registered Trademark)) and its impact on intraocular pressure  in patients with age-related macular degeneration (AMD)

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Speed IOP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Intraocular pressure elevation following intravitreal injections</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants in this study will be patients who are receiving lucentis injections for the treatment of the Age-related Macular Degeneration. The trial will involve only measuring the intraocular pressure (IOP) before and after the injections to investigate the different impact of slow versus fast injections on IOP. The study will run for 4 months and involve 2 study visits. Participants will receive the intravitreal injection that they are already receiving for AMD. The IOP will be measured before the injection, 2 minutes after the injection and 15 minutes after the injection. Study participants will be randomly assigned to two groups (group A and group B). Participants assigned to group A will receive their intravitreal injection as a quick push in the first visit and slowly (over 3-4 seconds) in the second visit. Participants assigned to group B will receive the opposite allocation. The two injections will be given 4-12 weeks apart according to the scheduled treatment for the participants AMD." </interventions>
    <comparator>This is a crossover study and each participant will be his/her own control. </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The mean change in IOP 2 minutes after injection in comparison with pre-injection IOP measurement. Intraocular pressure of the study eye will be measured using Goldmann applanation  tonometers and Icare tonometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 minutes after the injection</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The mean change in IOP 15 minutes after injection in comparison with the pre-injection level.
Intraocular pressure of the study eye will be measured using Goldmann applanation  tonometers and Icare tonometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>15 minutes after injection. 

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Any adverse effects associated with the intravitreal injections.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Monitored throughout the 4 month study period. At each visit patients will be asked if they have any adverse events.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Age=or&gt;50 years.
2. Clinical need for a therapeutic ranibizumab intravitreal injection for AMD.
3. A written informed consent is required before enrolling patients in the study.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with advanced glaucoma will be excluded from the study. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Based on the investigators clinical experience, 50% of eyes which will receive the fast injections will have IOP elevation of &gt; 40 mmHg regardless of their baseline IOP or an increase of &gt;20 mmHg than the baseline IOP. We are expecting these events to happen in 25% of the eyes which will receive the slow injections. 
Based on these event rates, a sample size of 32 eyes per group will be required for an 80% power of detecting a significant difference at the two-sided 5% level. 

The primary outcome- IOP 2 minutes after injection compared to the pre-injection IOP will be analysed using the paired t-test.                                                                       

The secondary outcome - IOP 15 minutes after injection will also be analysed using the paired t-test.

Data will be analysed on the basis of intention to treat.

Patient will be considered lost to follow up if he/she did not attend the second visit to receive the second injection.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>64</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to investigate the different impact of slow versus fast injection of the anti-VEGF agent, ranibizumab, which is the treatment participants are receiving for the treatment of age-related macular degeneration (AMD). The study will run for 4 months and involve 2 study visits. Participants will receive the intravitreal injection that they are already receiving for AMD. The IOP will be measured before the injection, 2 minutes after the injection and 15 minutes after the injection. 

Study participants will be randomly assigned to two groups (group A and group B). Participants assigned to group A will receive their intravitreal injection as a quick push in the first visit and slowly (over 3-4 seconds) in the second visit. Participants assigned to group B will receive the opposite allocation. The two injections will be given 4-12 weeks apart according to the scheduled treatment for the participants AMD. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Samantha Fraser-Bell</name>
      <address>Save Sight Institute, The University of Sydney
South Block, Campus of Sydney Eye Hospital, 8 Macquarie St Sydney NSW, Australia, 2000
</address>
      <phone>+61-2-9382 7309</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>sfraserbell@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wedad Salem</name>
      <address>Save Sight Institute, The University of Sydney
South Block, Campus of Sydney Eye Hospital, 8 Macquarie St Sydney NSW, Australia, 2000
</address>
      <phone>+61-2-9382 7386</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>wedad.salem@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Wedad Salem</name>
      <address>Save Sight Institute, The University of Sydney
South Block, Campus of Sydney Eye Hospital, 8 Macquarie St Sydney NSW, Australia, 2000</address>
      <phone>+61-2-9382 7386</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>wedad.salem@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>