<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371914">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000338369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Using eye movements to measure vision in children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Objective Assessment of Visual Performance Using Optokinetic Nystagmus in Young Children</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1190-2839 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>OKN (optokinetic nystagmus) study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Amblyopia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anisometropia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Significant refractive error </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Visual impairment </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Strabismus </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is a clinical device designed by Dr. Jason Turuwhenua, and consists of multiple components: a stimulus display unit, infrared (IR) camera for optokinetic nystagmus (OKN) video recording, IR illumination, and a computer. Data collection will be done with a prototype device by Objective Acuity Ltd, a UniServices (University of Auckland) start-up company co-founded by Lead investigator, Dr. Jason Turuwhenua, and A/Prof. Ben Thompson. The overall aim of this study is to accurately test visual acuity in young children to allow for the early detection and treatment of vision problems. The OKN device assesses visual acuity by inducing and measuring an involuntary, reflexive eye movement known as OKN. This eye movement only occurs when a moving target is visible. The intervention will be done one eye at a time, and the eye not being tested is covered by an eye patch. 

The intervention will be delivered by optometrist(s), orthoptist(s), ophthalmologist(s), and vision researcher(s) with minimum 2 years' clinical/clinical research experience. The mode of delivery is face to face, one participant at a time, in an optometry/ophthalmology clinic or a clinic in vision research institution..

Children will undergo the intervention once, but in the event of technical difficulties or child unable to cooperate, we will invite children and their parents to reschedule for a second attempt. The duration of intervention is approximately 10 minutes (5 minutes per eye). </interventions>
    <comparator>The sensitivity and specificity of the OKN device will be compared against the clinical gold-standard crowded HOTV visual acuity test using the EVA (electronic visual acuity) system. Children will be shown letters on the EVA monitor one eye at a time, and asked to identify the letter verbally or by letter-matching. The eye not being tested is covered by an eye patch. All children enrolled in this trial will have their visual acuity measured using both the gold-standard and OKN device. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the sensitivity and specificity of the OKN device for detecting uncorrected monocular visual acuity impairment caused by strabismic amblyopia, anisometropic amblyopia or refractive error in developmentally normal children from 3-6-years of age. The HOTV test delivered using the Electronic Visual Acuity (EVA) system will be used as the gold-standard comparison.  

Uncorrected monocular visual acuity impairment will be defined using the ATS-HOTV test in the absence of refractive correction according to age-specific visual acuity cutoffs for vision screening provided by the American Association for Pediatric Ophthalmology and Strabismus (AAPOS, 2014): 36-47 months, &gt;0.4 LogMAR; 49-59 months, &gt;0.3 LogMAR; 60-83 months, &gt;0.2 LogMAR.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The proposed timepoint for data analysis is January 2018. The primary outcome will be presented between January-March 2018.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Testability of the OKN device (proportion of completed measurements vs. attempts) compared to the ATS-HOTV test. A complete measurement is defined as a visual acuity measurement at the age-appropriate cut-off LogMAR level for each eye separately. </outcome>
      <timepoint>The proposed timepoint for calculation and presentation of secondary outcome is January-March 2018. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the specificity and sensitivity of OKN in the detection of impaired visual acuity for pre-specified subgroups, if sufficient number of children can be recruited for each category:
* Study sites (Auckland vs Melbourne vs Texas) 
* Age groups (36-47, 48-59, 60-83 months of age)
* Sex (Male, Female)
* Hyperopes vs. Myopes
* High astigmatism vs. low/no astigmatism
* Strabismic vs. non-strabismic
</outcome>
      <timepoint>The proposed timepoint for calculation and presentation of secondary outcome is January-March 2018. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>* Aged 3-6 years old (36-83 months at the time of registration)
* Have parent(s)/guardian(s) willing to provide informed consent
* Had paediatric eye examination, including cycloplegic refraction within the past 6 months OR is a child for whom the parent consents to having a paediatric eye examination including cycloplegic refraction at the time of registration.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>36</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Months</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>83</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Infantile nystagmus syndrome
* Eye muscle surgery within the past 6 months
* Current eye disease
* Developmental delay (known or suspected)
* Systemic disease or syndrome</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis will be performed using SAS version 9.4 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA) and R version 3.3 (R Foundation for Statistical Computing). All statistical tests will be two-sided at 5% significance level. The STROBE statement will be used as the guidelines for reporting observational studies. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>29/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>13/10/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3010 - University Of Melbourne</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland </state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>Texas </state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Auckland Bioengineering Institute
70 Symonds Street
Auckland 1010
AND 
School of Optometry &amp; Vision Science
85 Park Road 
Auckland 1023</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>15 Stout Street, Wellington 6011</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr. Shuan Dai (Eye Doctors)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Eye Doctors Ltd
Level 2, 90 Greenlane Rd East
Auckland, 1050</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Prof. Eileen Birch (Retina Foundation of the Southwest)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Retina Foundation of the Southwest
9600 N Central Expy #200, Dallas, TX 75231</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ms Christine Nearchou (University of Melbourne Eye Care Clinic)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Melbourne Eye Care Clinic
2/800 Swanston St
University of Melbourne
VIC 3010
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>If eye problems occur in early childhood, they can affect the development of the brain areas that are responsible for sight and cause lifelong visual impairment. In addition, vision problems can affect the development of fine control over arm and hand movements and, in older children, impact on education. Many of the eye problems that affect young children can be treated effectively, however detecting these problems is challenging. Young children find it difficult to complete standard tests of vision because these tests require high levels of attention. Many tests also involve recognising shapes and letters and are therefore not suitable for young children.

To address this problem we are developing a new computer-based vision test suitable for use with children as young as 2-years old. The test is simple and easy to use; carefully designed moving patterns are shown to the child that causes a reflexive, involuntary movement of the eyes if the child is able to see the pattern (which thereby yields a measure of visual performance). At the same time we record the movement of the eyes with a video camera attached to a computer and the software we are developing will identify whether the child is able to see the pattern or not. Finally, the visibility of the pattern will be varied to measure how well the child can see.

In this project, we will develop and perform clinical validation tests in ophthalmology and optometry clinics in New Zealand and the USA. The overall aim of this research is to validate a device that we envisage could be used to rapidly and accurately test visual acuity in young children to allow for the early detection and treatment of vision problems. 

We propose here to conduct data collection of OKN eye movement using our prototype system developed from our own research to date. This study will involve three clinical sites: (1) the University of Auckland Optometry research clinic, (2) a private ophthalmology clinic (Eye Doctors, Ascot Hospital) led by co-investigator and ophthalmologist Dr Shuan Dai and his research assistant (orthoptist, Nia Stonex), and (3) the Retina Foundation of the Southwest (a non-profit eye research institute in Texas, USA) led by co-investigator Prof. Eileen Birch and her research team.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee (UAHPEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The University of Auckland Research Office
Level 10, Building 620
49 Symonds Street
Auckland 1010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>018420</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371914-Outcome Approved with comment.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371914-OKN protocol.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371914-child_PIS CF_018420_ANZCTR.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jason Turuwhenua</name>
      <address>Auckland Bioengineering Institute 
The University of Auckland 
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 5807</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.turuwhenua@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lily Yu-Li Chang</name>
      <address>Auckland Bioengineering Institute 
The University of Auckland 
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 1689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lily.chang@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jason Turuwhenua</name>
      <address>Auckland Bioengineering Institute 
The University of Auckland 
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 5807</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>j.turuwhenua@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lily Yu-Li Chang</name>
      <address>Auckland Bioengineering Institute 
The University of Auckland 
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 1689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lily.chang@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>