<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347670">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/11/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000766819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improved treatment of Asthma by using natural sources of antioxidants</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Novel drug composition for the treatment of Human Asthma</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1125-6317</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>'Nil"</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Asthma is a clinical syndrome that highly possible involves both airways inflammation with an oxidant/antioxidant imbalance, providing that reactive oxygen species (ROS) can lead to lung injury as a result of direct oxidative damage to epithelial cells and cells shedding, therefore the effectiveness of supplying regularly natural antioxidants has thoroughly been studied in management and or treatment of  asthma. In this study,  a kind of 500mg pill was prepared and named as BRONAS, and described as below:

- BRONAS was prepared from 200mg of dried extract powder of Hippocampus kuda, 200 mg of dried extract powder of Rhizoma Homalomenae 130 mg of honey, and then used hands to roll pills of around 500 mg each. 

BRONAS is a combination bioactive antioxidant compounds that exhibits antioxidant activity in linoleic acid system, effective reducing power, DPPH radical scavenging, hydroxyl radical scavenging, superoxide radical scavenging, alkyl radical scavenging and inhibitory intracellular ROS (originated from the extract of Hippocampus kuda) together with presence of phenolics such as protocatechuic acid, vanillic acid, syringic acid, caffeic acid, p-coumaric acid, ferulic acid and apigenin (originated from the extract of Rhizoma Homalomena). Phenolic acids are the main phenols consumed by humans. These mentioned six phenolics are all prominent and naturally occurring, and all of them individually possess potent antioxidant activity(Rebecca J. Robbins, 2003; Natella, Nardini,  Felice and Scaccini, 1999). The honey was intentionally used with the dried extract powder of Rhizoma Homalomenae and the extract powder of Hippocampus kuda since it has been scientifically considered as an antimicrobial agent and chelating in traditional medicine. In addition, there is a great variety of minor components, including phenolic acids and flavonoids, the enzymes glucose oxidase and catalase, ascorbic acid, carotenoids, organic acids, amino acids, proteins, and a-tocopherol (Kesic, Mazolovic, Crnkic, Catovic, Hadzidedic and Dragosevic, 2009). 

Fifty two patients  with asthma  aged 12  65 years (24 Male :28 Female, forced expiratory volume in 1 s &lt;60% predicted, Peek Expiratory Flow Rate (PEFR) &lt;5%,  Maximal Mid-expiratory Flow Rate (MMEFR)&lt; 55%, and FEV1 to FVC &lt;70%) taking BRONAS with a single dose of 1200 mg/kg daily for 49 days (BRONAS is a combined composition of natural antioxidants such as DPPH radical scavenging, hydroxyl radical scavenging, superoxide radical scavenging, alkyl radical scavenging and inhibitory intracellular ROS, phenolic acids and flavonoids of which, are commonly found in seahorse of Hippocampus kuda species; in medicinal plant of Rhizoma Homalomena species, and in honey). BRONAS was in the form of pill which was prepared from dried extract powder of Hippocampus kuda and dried extract powder of Hippocampus kuda (with a ratio of 1: 1 w/w) in presence of sufficient honey used as an antimicrobial and chelating agent. Similar to the classical treatment of asthma, sets of pulmonary functions test were monthly conducted for checking the reduction of asthmatic incidence, if any.</interventions>
    <comparator>None</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All the asthmatic patients were fully or almost fully recovered after taking the BRONAS for 83 days.

Pulmonary functions test was performed by Spirometry test, adapting the method of Ahmed S. Sahib et al (Faruk, Al-Jawad, Hayder, Al-Atabee, Ahmed S. Sahib, 2010) for checking possible effects of given medicines on the treated patients. By doing this, a total computerized spirometer (Discom-14 Autospiror, Chest Corporation Tokyo, Japan) that measure Forced Volume Capacity (FVC), Forced Expiratory Volume in First Second (FEV1), Peek Expiratory Flow Rate (PEFR), and Maximal Mid-expiratory Flow Rate (MMEFR) were extensively applied as it would provide predicted values.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The frequency of the measurements was monthly measured from for the treatment duration, and then 06 months after the end of treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The ratio of FEV1 to FVC reached almost 94%.</outcome>
      <timepoint>16/02/2012 was the date at the end of the treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Treatments that might lessen the recurrent attacks of breathlessness and wheezing to make it more susceptible to providing relief for asthmatic patients.

- Participants were informed about the purposes, methods and intended uses of the research. They were informed about what participation will involve and the risks and potential benefits explained. 

- Participants wereallowed to withdraw themselves from participation at any time and for any reason without disadvantage.

- Information and data obtained about participants were confidential</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Out of age range of 12 to 65</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The patients were BRONAS with a single dose of 1200 mg/kg daily for 21 days. 

All the patients were advised to take the given medicine for 21 consecutive days and then stop for pulmonary function test.</concealment>
    <sequence>Restricted randomization was used to generate the sequence in which subjects will be randomized and to control the randomization to achieve balance between groups in size or characteristics.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>52</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Viet Nam</country>
      <state>Saigon</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Nguyen Van Toan</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Biotechnology, International   University
Vietnam National University
 Block 6, Linh Trung Ward, Thu Duc District, Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Viet Nam</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>none</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Buddhist Priest Thich Giac Lam from Dat Nhau ward, Bu Dang District, Binh Phuoc Province, Vietnam</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Dat Nhau ward, Bu Dang District, Binh Phuoc Province, Vietnam</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Viet Nam</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>AIMS: to investigate the effects of natural source of antioxidants on the treatment of  asthma

METHODS: Fifty two patients  with asthma  aged 12  65 years (24 Male :28 Female, forced expiratory volume in 1 s &lt;60% predicted, Peek Expiratory Flow Rate (PEFR) &lt;5%,  Maximal Mid-expiratory Flow Rate (MMEFR)&lt; 55%, and FEV1 to FVC &lt;70%) taking BRONAS with a single dose of 1200 mg/kg daily for 21 days (BRONAS is a combined composition of natural antioxidants such as DPPH radical scavenging, hydroxyl radical scavenging, superoxide radical scavenging, alkyl radical scavenging and inhibitory intracellular ROS, phenolic acids and flavonoids of which, are commonly found in seahorse of Hippocampus kuda species; in medicinal plant of Rhizoma Homalomena species, and in honey). BRONAS was in the form of pill which was prepared from dried extract powder of Hippocampus kuda and dried extract powder of Hippocampus kuda (with a ratio of 1: 1 w/w) in presence of sufficient honey used as an antimicrobial and chelating agent. Similar to the classical treatment of asthma, sets of pulmonary functions test were monthly conducted for checking the reduction of asthmatic incidence, if any.

RESULTS: All the asthmatic patients were fully or almost fully recovered after taking the BRONAS for 63 consecutive days.

CONCLUSIONS:  By and large, the BRONAS can protect cellular components from many types of oxidative stress by both free radical scavenging mechanism and stabilizing the cell membranes and this may explain the improvement that occurred in both dynamic performance of the lung in moving air and the elastic recoil force of the lung, especially when the ratio of FEV1 to FVC reached almost 94%.

Key words: asthma,  natural antioxidants, BRONAS</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>School of Biotechnology, International University, Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam Vietnam National University, Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University, Block 6, Linh Trung Ward, Thu Duc District, Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/09/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Viet Nam</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Steven Neill</name>
      <address>Associate Dean, Faculty of Health and Life Sciences
(International and Head of School of Life Sciences)
Director, Centre for Research in Plant Science
University of the West of England, Bristol
Bristol BS16 1QY</address>
      <phone>+44 (0) 117 32 86554</phone>
      <fax>+44 (0) 117 32 82132</fax>
      <email>steven.neill@uwe.ac.uk</email>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Nguyen Tan Phat</name>
      <address>Huynh Thuc Khang, high school
Van Gia, Van Ninh, Khanh HOa</address>
      <phone>+84 58 3910368</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>phathtk@yahoo.com.vn</email>
      <country>Viet Nam</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Nguyen Van Toan</name>
      <address>School of Biotechnology, International   University
Vietnam National University
 Block 6, Linh Trung Ward, Thu Duc District, Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam</address>
      <phone>+84 972304607</phone>
      <fax>+84-83- 7244271</fax>
      <email>nvtoan@hcmiu.edu.vn</email>
      <country>Viet Nam</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Nguyen Van Toan</name>
      <address>School of Biotechnology, International University, Vietnam national university. 

Block VI, Linh Trung Ward, Thu Duc District, Ho Chi Minh City</address>
      <phone>+84 972304607</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nvtoan@hcmiu.edu.vn</email>
      <country>Viet Nam</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>