<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366067">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>31/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000374662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Optimising Protection for Pregnant Women with Influenza Vaccination </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Optimising Protection for Pregnant Women with Influenza Vaccination </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>OptiMum</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Influenza vaccination in obese and non-obese pregnant women</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Approximately 300 pregnant women will be enrolled in this study at the Womens and Childrens Hospital over two influenza seasons. Whilst recruitment will not be targeting any specific BMI of potential participants, we expect that approximately 150 obese and non-obese participants will be enrolled in 2014 and 2015.   This is a prospective cohort study including obese and non-obese pregnant women to assess difference in seroprotective status after a seasonal influenza vaccination given according to standard practice.  All pregnant women will be administered 1 (0.5ml) dose of the licensed influenza vaccine into the upper deltoid muscle of the arm. 

Group 1: Participants with a BMI &gt;=30kg/m2 
Group 2: Participants with a BMI &lt;30kg/m2

All participants will have a follow-up 28 days after vaccination to assess antibody responses.  
</interventions>
    <comparator>Obese and non obese pregnant women will be compared. All participants will received a standard licensed influenza vaccine (as recommended). Immunogenicity following vaccination will be compared to determine the impact of obesity on immune response. </comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Paired sera will be collected pre- and post-vaccination for the assessment of vaccine immunogenicity, using haemagglutination inhibition (HI) against vaccine-related viruses. Samples will be batched, collected and sent frozen to the WHO Collaborating Centre for Reference and Research on Influenza.

HI titres &gt;=40 are accepted as a correlate of protective efficacy for influenza vaccines. The primary outcome will be the proportion with seroprotective HI titres &gt;=40 and differences betwen obese and non obese groups assessed  using chi square tests and logistic regression. </outcome>
      <timepoint>end of 2014 and end of 2015</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>geometric mean anti-influenza virus antibody concentrations will be assessed and reported on paired sera ( pre and post vaccination) via assays conducted by the WHO Collaborating Centre for Reference and Research on Influenza.  The proportion achieving a four-fold rise in titres post influenza vaccination between obese and non obese groups will be assessed statistically for differences .</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of 2014 and 2015</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Geometric mean anti-influenza virus antibody concentrations will be assessed and reported on paired sera ( pre and post vaccination) via assays conducted by the WHO Collaborating Centre for Reference and Research on Influenza.  Geometric mean titres and the mean geometric increase will be assessed statistically using appropriate descriptive and inferential statistics (ie. to compare obese vs non obese groups)</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of 2014 and 2015</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of women with altered cytokines (elevated or reduced).
Serum cytokines will be measure using a standardised commercial human cytokine assay kit.  Proportions with altered cytokines will be reported for obese and non-obese groups with differences assessed using chi square tests.</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of 2014 and 2015</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The average cytokine levels will be reported for :
a)	Obese vs non obese women 
b)	Women achieving haemagglutination inhibition (HI)  assay  titres &gt;=40 vs women not achieving &gt;=40

Serum cytokines will be measure using a standardised commercial human cytokine assay kit and reported using descriptive statistics</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of 2014 and 2015</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*Pregnant women aged 18 to 40 years (inclusive) at the time of the vaccination. 
*Written informed consent obtained from the participant. 
*Ability to understand the information sheet and provide informed consent
*Participants who in the opinion of the study staff can and will comply with the requirements of the protocol (eg return for follow-up visits, blood collection)
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Any major illness that, in the investigators judgment, will substantially increase the risk associated with the subjects participation in the study, or interfere with the evaluation of the study objectives.
*History of serious medical conditions (eg cardiac, respiratory, renal, hepatic disorders, diabetes mellitus requiring treatment with insulin).
*History of seasonal influenza vaccination within the last six months prior to enrolment. 
*History of any immunosuppressive condition (eg HIV infection) or on immunosuppressing medication.
*Any contraindication to influenza immunisation according to the Australian Immunisation Handbook.
*Anaphylaxis following a previous dose of any influenza vaccine
*Anaphylaxis following any vaccine component. 
*History of egg allergy. 
*History of Gullain Barre syndrome.
*Bleeding diathesis or condition associated with prolonged bleeding that may contraindicate intramuscular injection or blood draw, including participants taking anticoagulant medications or antiplatelet therapy (except for low dose daily aspirin therapy) within 30 days before enrolment.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Womens and Childrens Hospital - North Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5006 - North Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Women's and Children's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>72 King William Road
North Adelaide
South Australia 5006
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Women's and Children's Hospital Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>55 King William Road
North Adelaide
SA 5006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Pregnant women are at greater risk of complications from influenza infection and vaccination provides the best protection against influenza to pregnant women and their infants.  Since 2010, the Australian Government has provided free seasonal influenza vaccine to all pregnant women (in any trimester).

Whilst there are numerous data suggesting that influenza vaccination during pregnancy is beneficial to the mother and infant, there is limited data on factors that could potentially reduce the effectiveness of the influenza vaccine response in pregnant women. It is possible factors such as body mass index (BMI), may influence the immune response to influenza vaccine. Studies have shown that obese adults are at increased risk of severe disease from influenza and the immune response to some inactivated vaccines is reduced.

The main objective of this study is to determine whether there is any relationship between BMI and the effectiveness of influenza vaccination in pregnant women. Approximately 300 pregnant women will be enrolled in this study at Womens and Childrens Hospital over two influenza seasons (2014 and 2015). Approximately 150 obese and 150 non-obese participants will be enrolled. Licensed 2014 or 2015 seasonal influenza vaccines will be provided to all participants, with the vaccine administered during ultrasound imaging for a subset of pregnant women (n=70) to determine exact location of vaccine deposition. Two blood samples will be collected from all participants during the study (at baseline and at approximately 28 days post vaccination) in order to assess antibody responses to the vaccine. We will also measure cytokines (IL6 + TNFa) to determine associations with obesity and immunogenicity.

In addition, for influenza vaccines we dont know whether the immune response is different for people who receive the influenza vaccine subcutaneously vs intramuscularly. We will investigate whether obesity is associated with a lower likelihood of intramuscular vaccination and the implication of this for immune response. As it is likely that many pregnant women do not receive the influenza vaccine (standard fixed 16mm needle) intramuscularly.

This study will inform vaccine policy and guidelines by providing evidence on the impact of BMI on influenza vaccine response for pregnant women.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Women's and Children's Health Network Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>72 King William Road
North Adelaide
South Australia 5006
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/WCHN/3</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Marshall </name>
      <address>Discipline of Paediatrics 
Women's and Children's Hospital
72 King William Road
North Adelaide
South Australia 5006
</address>
      <phone>+618 81618115</phone>
      <fax>+618 81617031</fax>
      <email>helen.marshall@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Marshall </name>
      <address>Discipline of Paediatrics 
Women's and Children's Hospital
72 King William Road
North Adelaide
South Australia 5006
</address>
      <phone>+618 81618115</phone>
      <fax>+618 81617031</fax>
      <email>helen.marshall@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Marshall </name>
      <address>Discipline of Paediatrics 
Women's and Children's Hospital
72 King William Road
North Adelaide
South Australia 5006
</address>
      <phone>+618 81618115</phone>
      <fax>+618 81617031</fax>
      <email>helen.marshall@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Michelle Clarke</name>
      <address>Discipline of Paediatrics 
Women's and Children's Hospital
72 King William Road
North Adelaide
South Australia 5006
</address>
      <phone>+618 81618117</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michelle.clarke@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>