<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365657">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000091606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Targeting pain mechanisms from the 'top-down' and the 'bottom-up' in chronic tension-type headache</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An investigation of non-invasive brain and spinal cord stimulation versus brain stimulation (with sham spinal cord stimulation), and spinal cord stimulation (with sham brain stimulation) in people with chronic tension-type headache to evaluate feasibility, safety and effect on chronic tension type headache intensity, frequency and duration.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic tension-type headache</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will receive 30 minutes of combined active transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) and active transspinal direct current stimulation (tsDCS) for five consecutive daily sessions. 

Transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS): will be delivered using a direct current stimulator via two 35 cm2 surface sponge electrodes. The active electrode (anode) will be placed over the primary motor cortex and the reference electrode (cathode) over the contralateral supraorbital region. Current intensity will be ramped up (0 mA to 1 mA) and down (1 mA to 0 mA) over 10 s at the beginning and end of the stimulation period. 

Transspinal direct current stimulation (tsDCS): will be delivered using a direct current stimulator via two 35 cm2 surface sponge electrodes. The active electrode (anode) will be positioned over the thoracic spinal cord at the tenth thoracic vertebra and the reference electrode (cathode) above the right shoulder. Current intensity will be ramped up (0 mA to 1 mA) and down (1 mA to 0 mA) over 10 s at the beginning and end of the stimulation period. </interventions>
    <comparator>1. Participants will receive 30 minutes of combined active transspinal direct current stimulation (tsDCS) and sham transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) for five consecutive daily sessions. 

Transspinal direct current stimulation (tsDCS): will be delivered using a direct current stimulator via two 35 cm2 surface sponge electrodes. The active electrode (anode) will be positioned over the thoracic spinal cord at the tenth thoracic vertebra and the reference electrode (cathode) above the right shoulder. Current intensity will be ramped up (0 mA to 1 mA) and down (1 mA to 0 mA) over 10 s at the beginning and end of the stimulation period. 

Sham transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS): will be delivered with electrodes placed in an identical position to that used for active tDCS. Stimulation will be turned on for 15 s and then off. This is a standard sham approach in tDCS studies which ensures that participants feel the initial tingling sensation associated with tDCS. The tDCS unit will be placed out of sight for both active and sham interventions.


***

2. Participants will receive 30 minutes of combined sham transspinal direct current stimulation (tsDCS) and active transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS) for five consecutive daily sessions. 

Sham transspinal direct current stimulation (tsDCS): will be delivered with electrodes placed in an identical position to that used for active tsDCS. Stimulation will be turned on for 15 s and then off. This is a standard sham approach in tsDCS studies which ensures that participants feel the initial tingling sensation associated with tsDCS. 

Transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS): will be delivered using a direct current stimulator via two 35 cm2 surface sponge electrodes. The active electrode (anode) will be placed over the primary motor cortex and the reference electrode (cathode) over the contralateral supraorbital region. Current intensity will be ramped up (0 mA to 1 mA) and down (1 mA to 0 mA) over 10 s at the beginning and end of the stimulation period.  
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived response to therapy will be assessed using a 7 point Likert scale ranging from completely recovered to vastly worsened (Global Perceived Effect Scale (GPES)).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and immediately following the 5-treatment intervention. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Headache intensity, frequency, duration and use of analgesics: Headache intensity will be recorded on a 10 cm visual analogue scale (VAS) with 'no pain' at zero and 'worst pain imaginable' at 10, headache duration as hours per day, frequency as the number of days with headache per month, and use of analgesics as the number of doses. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed immediately before treatment and immediately after treatment over a 4-week period using responses to a daily, automated SMS system. 
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and adverse events: data on any side effects or adverse events (such as headache, nausea, dizziness) will be recorded. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and immediately following the 5-treatment intervention. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Central pain modulation (CPM): CPM is tested as a change in the pain perceived in one body region [electrical stimulation, 4 ms pulse duration, applied to the left upper arm] as a result of pain induced in another [heat pain, 30 pulses/minute to 1 degree C above pain threshold via thermode, applied to the right forearm]. Twenty heat pain stimuli will be delivered to the left arm alone followed by 20 combined with electrical pain stimulation to the right arm. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and immediately following the 5-treatment intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pressure (PPT) and cold pain thresholds (CPT): PPT will be measured using a pressure algometer [probe size of 1 cm2, application rate 40 kPa/s]. CPT will be measured using the Thermotest system [preset to 30 degree C, temperature change rate of 1.8 degree C/s]. Participants will push a button when the pressure or cold sensation first becomes painful. The average of three recordings will be analysed at each of six sites: bilateral temporal muscle, bilateral upper trapezius muscle and bilateral thumbnail. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and immediately following the 5-treatment intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nociceptive flexor withdrawal reflex (NFR): Surface stimulating electrodes will be positioned at a retromalleolar location along the right sural nerve. Recording electrodes will be positioned over the belly of the biceps femoris muscle. Stimulation will consist of pulse trains of 20 ms duration at an interval frequency of 300 Hz. The intensity needed to evoke a response in the biceps femoris muscles, indicating activation of the NFR, and the subjective pain threshold will be recorded. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and immediately following the 5-treatment intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants with a diagnosis of chronic tension-type headache (CCTH) according to the international Classification of Headache Disorders, 2nd edition (ICHD-II) criteria will be recruited. Additional inclusion criteria will comprise: i) diagnosis of CTTH for greater than 12 months prior to commencing the trial, ii) experience painful episodes on 15 or more days per month, iii) experience painful episodes that last more than 4 hours when untreated, and iv) experienced symptom onset before age 50 years.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Individuals under 18 years or who present with neurological or psychiatric conditions or use of prophylactic migraine drugs will be excluded. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Off-site concealed randomisation will be prepared by a researcher using a computer generated random number sequence. Consecutively numbered, randomly ordered opaque envelopes containing group allocation will be opened consecutively by the therapist implementing the types of intervention. The person recruiting thus will not know to which group the subject will be allocated.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated random number will be used to generate the sequence. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>This is a proof of concept study designed to generate data that can be used to inform a future large randomised controlled trial should the intervention appear feasible, safe and show effectiveness. We have selected a sample size of 10 individuals per group, or 30 participants in total. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Siobhan Schabrun</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Western Sydney, Campbelltown Campus, Locked Bag 1797, Penrith NSW 2751</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Western Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Campbelltown Campus, Locked Bag 1797, Penrith NSW 2751, Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Julia Treleaven</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of Queensland, School of Health and Rehabilitation Science, Therapies Annex, Building 84a, St Lucia QLD 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Tension-type headache (TTH) is the most common and costly primary headache disorder. Up to 2-5% of individuals with TTH experience severe, persistent and disabling headaches (chronic tension-type headache; CTTH). CTTH is a major health problem and currently, there are few effective therapies available for CTTH, which only target generic symptoms. Recent work has revealed a role for biological mechanisms in affecting pain in CTTH. Therefore, novel therapies that aim to target the biological mechanisms are needed to reduce the social and economic burden on sufferers and the wider community. 

Here we aim to conduct a 'proof of concept' study to investigate the use of an innovative 'top-down' and 'bottom-up' approach to therapy through the combined application of transcranial (tDCS) and transspinal direct stimulation (tsDCS). This study will provide the initial test of the feasibility, safety and potential benefit on pain outcomes. 
We anticipate that the combination of tDCS and tsDCS will have an affect on improving CCTH intensity, frequency and duration by targeting the biological mechanisms that contribute to pain. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Human Research Ethics Committee, University of Western Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Services
Building K, Room K.1.45 K Kingswood Campus
University of Western Sydney Locked Bag 1797, Penrith NSW 2751</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H10184</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Siobhan Schabrun</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney, Campbelltown Campus, Locked Bag 1797, Penrith NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3497</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4620 3792</fax>
      <email>s.schabrun@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Siobhan Schabrun</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney, Campbelltown Campus, Locked Bag 1797, Penrith NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3497</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4620 3792</fax>
      <email>s.schabrun@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Siobhan Schabrun</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney, Campbelltown Campus, Locked Bag 1797, Penrith NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3497</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4620 3792</fax>
      <email>s.schabrun@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Siobhan Schabrun</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney, Campbelltown Campus, Locked Bag 1797, Penrith NSW 2751</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4620 3497</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4620 3792</fax>
      <email>s.schabrun@uws.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>