<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369405">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001098527</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>10-session Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT-T): Pilot study of a newer, shorter psychotherapy for the treatment of eating disorders</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In clients with eating disorders, does CBT-T, compared with a wait-list control period, increase the rate of remission?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Eating Disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Eating disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this research is to investigate a new treatment for eating disorders, a 10-session Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT-T), formulated by Professor Glenn Waller in the United Kingdom, which is a shorter version of the current best psychological treatment targeting all eating disorders. CBT-T is an  interview style psychotherapy which aims to identify and change unhelpful behaviours and thinking related to eating disorders. Participation involves being assessed on six occasions. On the first occasion this will involve an assessment appointment as well as completing a self-report questionnaire. You will then be given information to read from Glenn Wallers book discussing getting ready for change. Four weeks after that you will be assessed again with the questionnaire and an interview and treatment will begin. The treatment will involve attending weekly face-to-face sessions of one hour duration for ten weeks, and experimenting with changing the way that you manage eating and mood. After the fourth session of CBT-T treatment you will be assessed for a third time with the questionnaire, and then again after the last session of treatment with the questionnaire and interview. You will be assessed a fifth time 4 weeks after the CBT-T treatment has finished, and again for a sixth and final time after another 8 weeks.  Each assessment will take approximately 1.5 hours of your time. Therapists will be supervised provisional psychologists. Adherence will be monitored by registering attendance of CBT-T sessions and completion of assessments. GPs and other involved professionals will be corresponded with at the beginning and end of treatment to inform them of your progress or if you have withdrawn from the study. </interventions>
    <comparator>Participants will each act as their own control. After the initial assessment there will be a 4 week period of no treatment prior to commencing CBT-T. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eating disorder remission is the primary outcome. Remission will be defined as a score of less than one standard deviation away from community norms on the Eating Disorder Examination Questionnaire. In addition, remission will be defined as no bingeing, vomiting, or laxative abuse and a BMI of greater than or equal to 18.5 (the cut-off for healthy weight). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Remission will be specified when the above is met during the month prior to assessment. The criteria for remission will be assessed at baseline, immediately prior to treatment, after the fourth treatment session, after the last treatment session, 4 weeks post end of treatment and 12 weeks post end of treatment. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Eating disorder psychopathology as measured by the Eating Disorder Examination Questionaire (EDE-Q) and the 15-Item Eating Disorder Measure (ED15).</outcome>
      <timepoint>The EDE-Q will be  assessed at baseline, immediately prior to treatment, after the fourth treatment session, after the last treatment session, 4 weeks post end of treatment and 12 weeks post end of treatment. The ED15 will be assessed at baseline, at all ten CBT-T sessions, 4 weeks post end of treatment and 12 weeks post end of treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychosocial impairment due to eating disorder psychopathology as measured by the Clinical Impairment Assessment. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately prior to treatment, after the fourth treatment session, after the last treatment session, 4 weeks post end of treatment and 12 weeks post end of treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General psychopathology as measured by the Depression Anxiety and Stress Scales 21 and the Outcome Rating Scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately prior to treatment, after the fourth treatment session, after the last treatment session, 4 weeks post end of treatment and 12 weeks post end of treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of therapeutic alliance as measured by the Working Alliance Inventory - Short Revised (WAI-SR) and the Session Rating Scale (SRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>The WAI-SR will be  assessed at the first treatment session, after the fourth treatment session, after the seventh treatment session, after the last treatment session, 4 weeks post end of treatment and 12 weeks post end of treatment. The SRS will be assessed at all CBT-T treatment sessions. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Motivation as measured using two 10-point Likert scales. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Motivation will be assessed at baseline, immediately prior to treatment, after the fourth treatment session, after the last treatment session, 4 weeks post end of treatment and 12 weeks post end of treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body image as measured by the Body Image Acceptance and Action Questionnaire, the Body Checking Questionnaire, and the Body Image Avoidance Questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately prior to treatment, after the fourth treatment session, after the last treatment session, 4 weeks post end of treatment and 12 weeks post end of treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perfectionism as measured by the Multidimensional Perfectionism Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately prior to treatment, after the fourth treatment session, after the last treatment session, 4 weeks post end of treatment and 12 weeks post end of treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-compassion as measured by the Fears of Compassion Scales and the Forms of Self-Criticising/Attacking and Self-Reassuring Scales. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline, immediately prior to treatment, after the fourth treatment session, after the last treatment session, 4 weeks post end of treatment and 12 weeks post end of treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Personality traits related to psychopathology as measured by the Personality Beliefs Questionnaire. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline only.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>DSM-IV Axis 1 disorders as measured by the MINI International Neuropsychiatric Interview.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at treatment sessions 1 and 10. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Weight</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weight will be assessed at baseline, at all ten CBT-T sessions, 4 weeks post end of treatment and 12 weeks post end of treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>BMI</outcome>
      <timepoint>BMI will be calculated at baseline, at all ten CBT-T sessions, 4 weeks post end of treatment and 12 weeks post end of treatment. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Have a BMI greater than 17.5, be willing for their therapist to communicate with GP and other treating professionals, and meet DSM-5 critieria for Anorexia Nervosa (AN), Bulimia Nervosa (BN), Binge Eating Disorder (BED), or Other Specified Feeding and Eating Disorders (OSFED). </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Severe physical and/or psychiatric conditions that would interfere with treatment (e.g. high suicidality, active psychosis, if already receiving psychotherapy for an eating disorder, or if difficulty speaking or understanding English. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>26/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>14/04/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/03/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>90</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>14/10/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Mia Pellizzer</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Flinders University
School of Psychology 
Sturt Road
Bedford Park SA 5042</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Flinders University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Sturt Road
Bedford Park SA 5042
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Tracey Wade</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Flinders University
School of Psychology
Sturt Road
Bedford Park SA 5042</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this research is to investigate a new treatment for eating disorders, a 10-session Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT-T), formulated by Professor Glenn Waller in the United Kingdom, which is a shorter version of the current best psychological treatment targeting all eating disorders. Because CBT-T is new we hope to learn more about how well it works, how it works and who it works best for. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Adelaide Clinical Human Research Ethics Comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Flinders Medical Centre
The Flats G5 - Rooms 3 and 4
Flinders Drive
Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>204.15</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mia Pellizzer</name>
      <address>Flinders University 
School of Psychology 
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8201 7993</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mia.pellizzer@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mia Pellizzer</name>
      <address>Flinders University 
School of Psychology 
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8201 7993</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>fused@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mia Pellizzer</name>
      <address>Flinders University 
School of Psychology 
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8201 7993</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mia.pellizzer@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>