<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372530">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000418370p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Clinical interventions to reduce the burden of persistent symptoms following concussion in children and adolescents. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of a multimodal intervention, incorporating physical and psychological modules, for the treatment of post-concussive symptoms following child concussion</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1194-0683 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>APP1040270</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Concussion </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Name of the intervention: Take CARe Active (TCA).  This is a single site, randomised trial, stratifying for post-concussion symptom cluster (physical vs psychological) according to CONSORT guidelines, of standardised multimodal treatment versus usual care for children with persistent post-concussive symptoms (PPCS).
Recruitment: We will recruit from the Emergency Department of the Royal Childrens Hospital (RCH), the RCH Acquired Brain Injury (ABI) follow-up clinic, and from Melbourne hospitals (e.g., Sunshine Hospital), community-based health practitioners (sports medicine physicians, physiotherapists, GPs, schools and sporting clubs) and family/self-referrals. The research team will review referrals and conduct online screening. All concussed patients (or caregivers) presenting at RCH ED will be asked to consent to being contacted 2 weeks post-injury for telephone screen to identify eligibility for the intervention study. Eligible participants will attend the TCA clinic at the RCH where trained clinic staff will conduct pre-intervention assessments.  This will include the administration of the Post-Concussion Symptom Inventory (PCSI), a developmentally appropriate and well-validated concussion symptom measure. It assesses current (acute) symptoms as well as the frequency of symptoms pre-injury (e.g., headaches, fatigue). When scored, individual symptoms are combined into clusters (e.g., psychological, physical). PPCS will be defined as endorsement &gt; 2 post-concussion symptoms on the PCSI, over and above those endorsed pre-injury and at 4 weeks post-injury. PPCS cluster membership will be determined based on cluster scores from PCSI ratings.  For example, a child with higher ratings on the physical subscale would be classified as fitting the physical cluster. Participants will be randomly allocated to treatment (TCA) or usual care (UC) at 4 weeks post-concussion, and stratified by the two PPCS clusters based on PCSI ratings to ensure balanced PCS profiles across treatment arms, via computer randomisation plan generator.
 
Take CARe Active (TCA): Participants enrolled in TCA will receive usual care plus a 6-week (10 sessions) multimodal intervention, on an individual basis, provided by trained clinicians. Each session will last approximately 60 minutes. TCA incorporates 3 modules based on the key PPCS clusters, generic, physical, psychological, as described above
1.	Generic module: delivered to all TCA participants, addressing symptoms commonly endorsed by children with PPCS (standardised management of fatigue and headache)
2.	Physical module: participants meeting criteria for the physical cluster will receive individual treatment comprising standardised components to treat vestibular, ocular-motor and cervical impairments, and supporting graded return to aerobic exercise, delivered by researchers under supervision by a neurophysiotherapist experienced in concussion management 
3.	Psychological module: participants meeting criteria for the psychological cluster will receive individual evidence-based treatment (cognitive behaviour therapy: CBT), adapted for concussion and targeting emotional symptoms (anxiety, depression, avoidance) coupled with cognitive training (working memory, processing speed). This intervention will be delivered by supervised research psychologists experienced in concussion management. 

Program fidelity: To ensure a high degree of proficiency, staff providing interventions will require appropriate discipline training, and will be trained to a proficient standard in all aspects of the TCA by experienced clinical psychologists and neurophysiotherapists. To optimise adherence to treatment structure and to minimise therapist drift, researchers will participate in monthly supervision sessions. A randomly selected set of 10% of sessions will be video-recorded for fidelity checking by independent raters.

</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group (usual care) includes provision of a booklet and online resources consistent with the recent CISG child concussion guidelines and App-based symptom monitoring (HeadCheckV2), which will provide children/parents with automated information on a) symptom progress and b) tailored alerts when PPCS either cease (seek medical clearance) or increase (seek medical attention). Participants will be provided with psycho-educational material at pre-intervention assessment, and be informed regarding the HeadCHeckV2 symptom monitoring and alerts symptom. There will be no restriction on accessing other clinical resources for the period of the intervention.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Post concussion symptoms as measured by the Post Concussion Symptom Inventory (PCSI), </outcome>
      <timepoint>Screening (2-4 weeks post-injury), pre intervention (4-weeks post-injury),  post-intervention (3-months post-injury) and follow-up (6-months post-injury), and monitored every second day during intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants rate their participation at school: return to pre-concussion activity, partial return, not returned.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed pre- and post-intervention and at 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pediatric QOL Inventory (PedsQL): physical, emotional, social, school</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed pre- and post-intervention and at 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health economy measures: Child Health Utility 9D (CHU-9D): measures health related QoL for use in cost utility analyses. Linked health service utilisation and cost data from hospitals and Medicare will be sought, providing data on use and cost of general practice, physiotherapy, mental health and pharmaceuticals. Cost of lost parental employment, childcare, travel, accommodation and school absenteeism will be obtained through parent survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed pre- and post-intervention and at 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants rate their participation at sports: return to pre-concussion activity, partial return, not returned.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed pre- and post-intervention and at 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants rate their participation in normal daily activity (e.g., social): return to pre-concussion activity, partial return, not returned.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed pre- and post-intervention and at 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria: Children aged between 6-18 years, history of concussion 2-4 weeks prior referral, with PPCS at 2-4 weeks post-injury. Consistent with the CISG guidelines, concussion diagnosis will be confirmed with evidence of a blow to the head and: i) loss or altered consciousness; ii) post-impact confusion and disorientation; iii) two or more acute concussion symptoms including headache, dizziness, gait unsteadiness and blurred vision; iv) GCS 13-15. Only children with PPCS ongoing at or after 2 weeks post-injury will be eligible for participation.

Criteria for intervention clusters: This will be determined using the Post-Concussion Symptom Inventory (PCSI), a developmentally appropriate and well-validated concussion symptom measure. It assesses current (acute) symptoms as well as the frequency of symptoms pre-injury (e.g., headaches, fatigue). When scored, individual symptoms are combined into clusters (e.g., psychological symptoms, physical symptoms). PPCS will be defined as endorsement &gt; 2 post-concussion symptoms on the PCSI, over and above those endorsed pre-injury and at 4 weeks post-injury. PPCS cluster membership will be determined based on cluster scores from PCSI ratings.  For example, a child with higher ratings on the physical subscale would be classified as fitting the physical cluster.  Similarly, a child with higher ratings on the psychological subscale would be classified as fitting the psychological cluster.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria: i) intubated patients, ii) need for surgical intervention or general anaesthesia, iii) presence of structural/hemorrhagic intracranial injury on CT scan, clinical evidence of CSF leak, iv) non-accidental injury, alcohol or drug intoxication at ED presentation, v) multiple trauma, vi) Glasgow Coma Score (GCS) on hospital presentation &lt;13, viii) insufficient English to complete study requirements.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Researchers conducting pre-, post-injury and follow-up assessments will not be involved in delivering intervention and will be blind to treatment allocation. Participants will be randomly allocated to treatment (Take CARe Active [TCA]) or Usual Care [UC] at 4 weeks post-concussion, and stratified by the two PPCS clusters based on PCSI ratings.  Allocation concealment will be performed by the study statistician (who will have no contact wit participants) via computerized central randomization. </concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A review of the literature indicates that ~40% of all concussed children remain symptomatic at 4 weeks post-injury, with some further reduction in these numbers to 3 months (3 months: 31% delayed recovery). These results indicate a figure of 35% spontaneous recovery from 1 to 3 months, and thus an expected recovery rate of 35% in the UC arm of the trial .  In order to attain a clinically significant impact, we aim for a 65% improvement in recovery rate in the TCA compared to UC group 3 months, we require a sample of 100 per group to have 90% power to detect this difference. Taking into account a drop out rate of 10%, we will recruit 110 participants per group . </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2018</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>220</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Michael Takagi</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Children's Hospital
50 Flemington Rd, Parkville VIC 3052
Australia </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Children's Hospital Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2/48 Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052
Australia 
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Vicki Anderson </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Royal Children's Hospital
50 Flemington Rd, Parkville VIC 3052
Australia </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>By age 10, 1 in 5 children (~51,000 Australian children) will sustain a concussion and present with post-concussive symptoms (PCS) requiring medical treatment. Many children and youth recover rapidly from these symptoms and are symptom free and returned to pre-injury activities within 4 weeks. In contrast, ~40% of children suffer persisting PCS (PPCS), defined as 2 or more PCS lasting more than 4 weeks. This group of children have limited tolerance for routine academic, sport/leisure and social activities and are unable to return safely to these activities. Despite their debilitating impact, intervention trials addressing PPCS in children are lacking. We propose a randomised trial of a novel multimodal intervention to reduce the burden of debilitating  PPCS for the ~40% of children who experience delayed recovery after concussion. Participants with PPCS at 4 weeks post-injury will be recruited and randomised to either active (TCA) or Usual Care (UC) interventions, which will be delivered over 10 sessions between 4  10 weeks post-injury. The primary aim of the TCA is to reduce the number and severity of PPCS. We propose the following hypotheses: 

Hypothesis 1: Compared to the UC, children in the TCA condition will have a clinically significant reduction in number and severity of PPCS by treatment completion 

Hypothesis 2: Compared to the UC, children in the TCA condition will have a significantly higher proportion of children who, at treatment completion, have:
2.1  Demonstrated reduction in PPCS across all clusters: generic, physical, psychological
2.2  Returned to normal activity (school, sports, leisure activities) 
2.3  Improved physical and psychosocial quality of life
2.4  Lower rate of utilisation of health services 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Children's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>50 Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052
Australia </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/11/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Takagi</name>
      <address>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute 
Child Neuropsychology
50 Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052
</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9936 6615</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.takagi@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Takagi </name>
      <address>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute 
Child Neuropsychology
50 Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9936 6615</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.takagi@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Takagi</name>
      <address>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute 
Child Neuropsychology
50 Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9936 6615</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.takagi@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Michael Takagi</name>
      <address>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute 
Child Neuropsychology
50 Flemington Rd
Parkville VIC 3052</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9936 6615</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.takagi@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>