<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365771">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/02/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/02/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000177651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Alcoholic Chlorhexidine or Alcoholic Iodine Skin Antisepsis Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Cluster Randomised Controlled Trial comparing Surgical Skin Preparation with Alcoholic Chlorhexidine versus Alcoholic Iodine for the Prevention of Superficial Wound Complications in Prosthetic Hip and Knee Replacement Surgery</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1153-2057 </utrn>
    <trialacronym>ACAISA</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prosthetic joint replacement surgery</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Superficial wound complications</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The aim of this cluster randomised controlled trial is to compare the incidence of superficial wound complications in all patients undergoing elective prosthetic hip or knee replacement surgery receiving surgical skin preparation with either: 0.5% chlorhexidine gluconate in 70% alcohol or 1% iodine in 70% alcohol. </interventions>
    <comparator>Both surgical skin preparation agents are currently used as part of standard care in patients undergoing surgery.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Superficial surgical wound complications, specificially superficial incisional surgical site infections (as defined by the Centers for Disease Control / National Healthcare Safety Network) and prolonged wound ooze (wound ooze requiring intervention, such as superficial surgical debridement). These will be assessed clinically. </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of superficial surgical wound complications according to the joint replaced (knee or hip). Superficial surgical wound complications include either superficial incisional surgical site infections (as defined by the CDC / NHSN) and prolonged wound ooze (wound ooze requiring intervention, such as superficial surgical debridement). These will be assessed clinically. </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment of the causative microorganisms of  surgical site infections. The diagnosis of surgical site infections is clinical and is according to the CDC/NHSN definition).</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Undesirable adverse consequences from surgical skin preparation (SSP) including toxicity and allergies. This will be assessed clinically.</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Economic analysis including cost-effectiveness of surgical skin preparation. We will apply health economic modelling to estimate the potential cost-effectiveness of 0.5% chlorhexidine in 70% alcohol compared with 1% iodine in 70% alcohol. Decision analysis will be used to compare the downstream consequences of SSP. The incorporation of Markov and life-tabling techniques will allow for the modelling of outcomes beyond one year. The main output of interest in health economic modelling is incremental cost-effectiveness ratios in terms of net costs per unit of health gain. Net costs will comprise the costs of the SSP agents minus costs saved from the reduction in downstream health services utilization. Health gains can be measured in a variety of ways. In our study, other than clinical outcomes, we will be also estimating years of life gained and quality-adjusted life years (QALYs) gained. Both are enabled by the collection of time-to-outcome data and the latter also by collection of quality of life data. All health economic analyses will be undertaken in accordance with recommended approaches, such as 5% discounting of estimated future costs and health gains. To account for any uncertainty in the data inputs for health economic modelling, sensitivity and uncertainty analyses will be undertaken via Monte Carlo simulation. </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants undergoing hip or knee replacement surgery</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with a documented allergy to chlorhexidine, alcohol, or iodophors
Patients with a primary language other than English for which certified translation services for that specific language are not available
Patients undergoing arthroplasty surgery for traumatic fractured neck of femur
Patients undergoing insertion of an tumour endoprosthesis for bone and soft tissue tumours
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study population will be drawn from patients on the waiting list for elective hip and knee replacement surgery at St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne). Once a participant is placed on the waiting list, they will be sent the Patient Information Statement for Opt-Out Consent, which will detail the problem of SWC and the nature of the study. In addition the Patient Information Statement for Opt-Out Consent will explain the process to ‘opt-out’ of the study. Two weeks after the Patient Information Statement for Opt-Out Consent is sent to the participant, the Project Research Officer will review the medical record; any potential participant with a documented allergy to either study agent, will be excluded from the study. 
In the opt-out approach, willingness to participate is presumed unless the participant communicates a choice not to participate in the research. Eligible participants undergoing hip or knee replacement surgery on a given day will be randomly assigned in a ratio of 1:1 to have skin preparation either with 0.5% chlorhexidine gluconate in 70% alcohol or 1% iodine in 70% alcohol. 
the research team involved in the assessment or treatment of patients will have no role in the assignment process. The patients will be blinded to treatment allocation. We recognise that blinding of the operating surgeons to the assigned preventative strategy is not feasible , however the operating surgeons will be blinded to the allocation until the day of surgery. In addition, the Project Research Officer will be blinded and data will be analysed on an intention-to-treat basis. </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will be performed by a computer-generated random assignment sequence prepared in advance by a statistician. Opaque, numbered, tamperproof envelopes containing assignment will be prepared in advance.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Cluster randomised controllled trial based on the day of surgery</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary analysis is an intention to treat analysis including all participants who underwent randomisation. Factors associated with SWC will be examined by chi-squared tests or Fishers exact tests for categorical variables or Student t-tests (parametric) or Mann-Whitney test (non-parametric) for continuous variables. Time-to-outcome data will also be collected and the independent contribution of relevant factors associated with SWC will be assessed using multivariable Cox proportional hazard regression. All reported p-values will be two-tailed and for each analysis p&lt;0.05 will be considered statistically significant. 

The sample size calculations were based on pilot data; the proportion of patients with superficial wound complications was 27% in the 0.5% chlorhexidine/70% alcohol group versus 8% of patients in the 1% iodine/70% alcohol group. On multivariate analysis there was an 80% reduction in the risk of superficial wound complications in the group receiving 1% iodine in 70% alcohol SSP (Odds Ratio 0.20, 95% Confidence Intervals[CI]; 0.06,0.67). The sample size estimation for this study is based on the worst case scenario (based on the upper limit of the 95% CI of the pilot study) and includes the following parameters: (i) alpha value = 0.05, 2-sided; (ii) power = 80%; (iii) expected rates of the primary outcome (defined above) at 30 days post prosthetic hip or knee replacement surgery of 27% for 0.5% chlorhexidine in 70% alcohol and 18% for 1% iodine in 70% alcohol. The sample size required in each of the 2 (equally-sized) groups is 359 patients. To allow for an estimated lost to follow-up rate of 5%, we will recruit 750 patients in total. At St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne), over 700 prosthetic joint replacements are performed each year therefore recruitment will be completed over the first 2 years of the study. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/08/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>22/01/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>750</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>769</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>22/06/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Peter Choong</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Director
Department of Surgery, St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne)
29 Regent Street
Fitzroy VIC 3065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Trisha Peel</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Surgery, St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne)
29 Regent Street
Fitzroy
VIC 3065</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Alcoholic Chlorhexidine or Alcoholic Iodine Skin Antisepsis (ACAISA) Study is a cluster randomised controlled trial comparing alcoholic chlorhexidine to alcoholic iodine skin antisepsis at the time of surgery for prevention of superficial wound complications in patients undergoing elective prosthetic hip and knee replacement surgery.

Skin antisepsis is a simple and effective strategy to remove soil and microorganisms from the patients skin prior to surgical incision. The three main agents commonly used for skin antisepsis are chlorhexidine, iodophors (such as iodine) or alcohol. Despite their use for over a century, no studies have adequately assessed the comparative effects of these agents on wound complication risk, particular in patients undergoing orthopaedic surgery.

Joint replacement surgery is a national healthcare priority and represents high volume, high cost surgery. In 2011, 90 000 Australian patients underwent prosthetic joint surgery and this rate will double by 2020. The conservative estimate of direct medical costs for prosthetic joint surgery in Australia is $2 billion annually. Superficial wound complications are a major cause of morbidity for patients following prosthetic joint replacement surgery and are associated with increased risk of deep prosthetic joint infection. In addition, treatment of superficial wound complications are estimated to add a further $34 million annually to the direct cost of prosthetic joint surgery. Prevention of superficial wound complications will substantially decrease morbidity and mortality, improve patient outcomes and reduce the economic burden to the healthcare system.

The ACAISA study represents an international first. In addition, this study is a unique collaboration between orthopaedic surgeons, infectious diseases clinicians and infection control practitioners in both the public and private healthcare sector.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) HREC-A</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne)
PO Box 2900
Fitzroy VIC 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC-A 016/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/02/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter Choong</name>
      <address>Director
Department of Surgery, St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne)
29 Regent Street
Fitzroy, VIC 3065</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9288 2365</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9416 3610</fax>
      <email>pchoong@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Trisha Peel</name>
      <address>Department of Infectious Diseases, Monash University, 85 Commercial Road, Melbourne, VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2000</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 90762431</fax>
      <email>trisha.peel@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Trisha Peel</name>
      <address>Department of Infectious Diseases, Monash University, 85 Commercial Road, Melbourne, VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9076 2000</phone>
      <fax>+62 3 90762431</fax>
      <email>trisha.peel@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Trisha Peel</name>
      <address>Department of Infectious Diseases, Monash University, 85 Commercial Road, Melbourne, VIC 3004</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90762000</phone>
      <fax>+61390762431</fax>
      <email>trisha.peel@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>