<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371065">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000952448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Wear assessment of highly crossed linked (X3) acetabular liners by Radio stereometric analysis (RSA).  An analysis  of patients with osteoarthritis treatment  hip replacement surgery.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Wear assessment of highly cross-linked (X3)  polyethylene liners with Radio stereometric analysis (RSA).  A double cohort study  of osteoarthritis patients with hip replacements of 32 mm  head size compared to 36 to 40mm head sizes.

</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1185-2074</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients with advanced osteoarthritis will be treated with a hip replacement that is the standard practice of the senior author. The migration of femoral head into the polyethylene liner over time will be measured by Radio stereometric analysis (RSA). 

The Trident acetabular system comprises a metallic hemispherical acetabular shell, used in association with a highly cross-linked polyethylene liner (X3).. The surgery is performed by a specialist hip arthroplasty surgeon, through a posterior approach and according to normal standards at the clinic.  

During surgery six one-mm tantalum markers are inserted in the plastic liner to facilitate migration measurements.   This will add about 5 minutes to the 60 minute surgical procedure. Tantalum is the most biocompatible metal known. In 25 years of use no problems have ever been identified with the use of this technique. 

Outcomes will be measured by radiological examination and general outcome survey. The general outcome surveys will be compled at the standard follow up visits. These surveys will include the Harris hip a disease specific survey form and SF12 a general outcome survey. The forms will take approximately 20mins to fill out and the patients will be deidentified to protect their privacy

The study is an interventional trial of two groups of patients. The first study cohort will include patients implanted with a standard sized 32 mm femoral head articulating with an X3 polyethylene liner. The first group of patients will have a preliminary analysis to ensure safety and efficacy of the X3 polyethylene. Once initial safety requirements have been met a second group of patients will be recruited with the largest femoral head size that permits a minimum 6mm polyethylene thickness, a 36-40 mm Cobalt Chrome (CoCr) femoral head articulating with a highly cross linked (X3) polyethylene liner.</interventions>
    <comparator> The study consists of two cohorts and both are compared to historical clinical and migration values. There are limited RSA wear studies on  conventional and cross-linked polyethylene. Nivbradt et al (Rohl, Nivbrandt, Minuggo, Hewitt, In Vivo Wear and Migration of Highly Cross-linked Polyethylene cups. J Arthroplasty, vol 20 (2), 2005) report RSA derived wear rates for traditional and  second-generation cross-linked polyethylene. Campbell et al (Campbell D, et al., Eur J Orthop Surg Traumatol. 2009; 20(1):23-27) report RSA  derived wear  of an  intermediate cross-linked (5Gy)  polyethylene  and these two studies form an historical  control group .</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>RSA assessed femoral head migration as a measure of polyethylene wear.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Two years, five years, and 10 years post surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxford hip scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>One year and five years post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SF-12 scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>One and five years post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Harris hip scores.</outcome>
      <timepoint>One and five years post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients between 50 and 80 years of age, planned for Total Hip Arthroplasty (THA) due to osteoarthritis </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Residence outside Adelaide metropolitan area, abnormal gross anatomy of hip, age above 80 years, inflammatory arthritis or severe osteoporosis</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>nil</concealment>
    <sequence>nil</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Consecutive cohort interventional trial</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Migration and wear is calculated with UMRSA software (RSA Biomedical). Statistic analyses of the material will be done with the SPSS 10 package. Migration and wear differences between patients analyzed with Mann Whitney U-test and repeated measurement ANOVA and correlations to other parameters with linear regression. Probability values of less than 0.05 will be considered significant. An earlier study of the same cup showed a SD of 0.17 mm. Difference in migration between the patients is anticipated to be at least 0.15 mm. To accommodate these facts a power analyses suggests a sample size of 27 patients when comparing two implant types. Again, this number is based on a head-to-head assessment of two different prostheses and is included to indicate our appreciation of what is actually required to meet statistical validity. We believe that the numbers cited (20) with be more than adequate to evaluate the performance of a single system.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>23/09/2005</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>6/09/2009</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>6/09/2009</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>40</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>6/09/2019</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>David Campbell</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Wakefield Orthopaedic clinic
270 Wakefield Street
Adelaide5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Styrker Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Stryker South Pacific
PO Box 970
Artarmon NSW 1570
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aseptic loosening, wear and dislocation are complications of primary total hip arthroplasty that have a high cost to society and is unpleasant for the patient to endure. 

New technology has enabled manufactures to improve the mechanical strength of the bearing surfaces which function well in vitro. Cross-linked polyethylene a second generation polyethylene was introduced into orthopaedic implant designs to address the problems of osteolysis, which is induced by polyethylene wear particles. These implant designs also enable the constructs to accommodate larger femoral heads which create stability and low wear rates which will decrease the amount of osteolysis (Burroughs, Hallstrom et al. 2005) and (Geller, Malchau et al. 2006). 

X3 'Trademark' represents the third generation of polyethylene, and has been developed in order to address the issues of reduced mechanical properties compared with second generation cross-linked polyethylene, whilst still maintaining the benefits of reduced wear rates.  Hip simulator testing shows that the wear rate of X3 polyethylene is significantly less than conventional cross-linked polyethylene (McKellop, Shen et al. 2000).  This reduction in wear will result in significantly less wear particles around the joint and therefore less biological reaction, less osteolysis and a lower incidence of osteolysis induced component failure.

This Radiostereometry analysis (RSA) study will investigate in vivo wear, migration and performance and the results will be compared to the current standard PE liners study using RSA as the form of analysis (Rohrl, Nivbrant et al. 2005).



Hypothesis to be tested 

Part 1: Annual volumetric wear of the of the highly cross-linked polyethylene (X3 PE) lining used with a 32mm CoCr head is no more than 0.01mm/annum. 

Part 2: Annual volumetric wear of the of the highly cross-linked polyethylene (X3 PE) lining used with a  large (36-40mm) CoCr heads is no more than 0.01mm/annum.

Part 3: Annual volumetric wear of the of the highly cross-linked polyethylene (X3 PE) lining used with a  Large (36-40mm) CoCr head and thin X3 PE is no more than 0.01mm/annum. 
 </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Second-generation Highly Cross-linked X3 ' Trademark' Polyethylene Wear: A Preliminary Radiostereometric Analysis Study
David G. Campbell, John R. Field and Stuart A. Callary
Clinical Orthopaedics and Related Research. 468 910), 2704-2709 , 2010
DOI: 10.1007/s11999-010-1259-y

Low Wear of a Second-generation Highly Cross-linked Polyethylene Liner:
A 5-year Radiostereometric Analysis Study
Stuart A. Callary, John R. Field, David G. Campbell
Clinical Orthopaedics and Related Research. 2013
Nov;471(11):3596-600. doi: 10.1007/s11999-013-3188-z. Epub 2013 Jul 27.

Wear of highly crosslinked polyethylene acetabular components.
Callary SA1, Solomon LB, Holubowycz OT, Campbell DG, Munn Z, Howie DW.
Acta Orthop. 2015 Apr;86(2):159-68. doi: 10.3109/17453674.2014.972890. Epub 2014 Oct 10.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Calvary Wakefield research and ethics committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Calvary wakeful Street Hospital
250 Wakefield Street 
Adelaide 5000
 South Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/03/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>REC ref: 2007 P1</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/06/2004</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David Campbell</name>
      <address>Wakefield Orthopaedic clinic
270  Wakefield Street
Adelaide 5000
 South Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82364196</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Hipknee@TPG.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David Campbell</name>
      <address>Wakefield Orthopaedic clinic
270 Wakefield Street
Adelaide 5000
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82364196</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>woc@woc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David Campbell</name>
      <address>Wakefield Orthopaedic clinic
270 Wakefield Street
Adelaide 5000
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82364196</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Hipknee@TPG.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David Campbell</name>
      <address>Wakefield Orthopaedic clinic
270 Wakefield Street
Adelaide 5000
South Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82364196</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>