<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320856">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/11/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/12/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609001043224</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Management of Refeeding Syndrome in Critical Illness: An Australasian Society of Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition (AuSPEN) Endorsed Multi-centre Phase II Randomised Controlled Trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In Critically Ill patients with Refeeding-related Hypophosphataemia, does energy restricted nutritional support compared with Standard/Usual care affect Intensive Care Unit (ICU) free days. A Phase II multi-centre randomised controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Nutrition - Refeeding-related Hypophosphatemia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Protocol directed and energy restricted nutritional support during management of  refeeding-related hypophosphataemia. Protocol currently under development by management committee and will be based on review of best available evidence.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard/usual care, which encompasses all aspects of standard/usual care delivered for the entire duration of Intensive Care Unit (ICU) stay.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of Days spent outside the Intensive Care Unit (ICU), also known as ICU Free days. Assessed and defined by the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome Clinical Trials Network Investigators (Schoenfeld DA, Bernard GR for the Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS) Network. Statistical Evaluation of ventilator-free days as an efficacy measure in clinical trials of treatments for acute respiratory distress syndrome. Crit Care Med 2002;30:1772-1777).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at day 90 post randomisation into the trial</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Immune Function. Assessed by prospectively observing and recording measures of immune function (CD4, CD8, NK cell counts) in enrolled patients on each day of Intensive Care Unit (ICU) stay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during ICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Infectious complications. Assessed by prospectively observing and recording infectious complications in enrolled patients on each day of Intensive Care Unit (ICU) stay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during ICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Need for antibiotics. Assessed by prospectively observing and recording antibiotics delivered to enrolled patients on each day of Intensive Care Unit (ICU) stay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured during ICU stay</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life assessed using the Short Form (SF)-36 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at day 90 post randomisation into the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical function assessed using the physical function component of the Short Form (SF)-36 questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at day 90 post randomisation into the trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients will be considered eligible for the trial is all of the following inclusion criteria are met at the time of screening: 1)Presence of refeeding hyphosphataemia (a serum phosphate drop of more than 0.16mmol/l from a previous reading to below 0.65mmol/L within 72 hours of the onset of nutritional support, 2)Age at least 18 years, 3) ICU specialist intends to manage the patient with continued normal nutritional support</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients will be considered ineligible for the trial if any of the following exclusion criteria are met at the time of screening: 1)Intensive Care Unit (ICU) discharge anticipated on day of screening or day after screening, 2)Diabetic ketoacidosis, 3)Presence of acute or chronic renal failure, 4)Admitted to the Intensive Care Unit (ICU) for palliative care only and not expected to survive hospital discharge, 5)Moribund and not expected to survive 24 hours, 6)Brain dead or suspected to be brain dead, or 7)Admitted to the study Intensive Care Unit (ICU) directly from another Intensive Care Unit (ICU).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Centralised randomisation by computer using a password protected webserver. 
As in any centralised method, individual patient treatment assignment will not be revealed until the potential participant is determined to be truely eligible for the trial and patient identifiers are submitted over the web. 
Persons recruiting patients into the trial will not be able to predict or influence treatment assignments, hence concealing treatment allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised (SAS)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>348</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box 1421, 
Canberra, ACT 
2601</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council(NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421, 
Canberra, ACT 
2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary />
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname />
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/10/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Gordon Doig</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital (RNSH) Intensive Care Unit (ICU), Pacific Highway St Leonards, NSW 2065.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99268656</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gdoig@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Gordon Doig</name>
      <address>Royal North Shore Hospital (RNSH) Intensive Care Unit (ICU), Pacific Highway St Leonards, NSW 2065.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99268656</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gdoig@med.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>