<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368925">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001000594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Exercise training effects on biochemical, metabolic, physical fitness, body composition and hemodynamic markers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects of aerobic training and resistance training on the levels of FNDC5/irisin, ghrelin, metabolic profile, insulin resistance, metabolic syndrome, inflammatory, hemodynamic, body composition and physical fitness markers in middle-aged overweight and obese men.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Overweight </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The training protocols were based on American College of Sports Medicine positions stands, and was composed of Aerobic Training and Resistance Training performed in the same session or in separated sessions, divided into three stages (S1, S2 and S3), each stage consisting of eight week, 3 per week, of training and was conducted one after the other for a total intervention duration of 24 weeks.
In S1, the subjects performed the Resistance Training through a linear periodization with six exercises (leg press, leg extension, leg curl, bench press, lateral pulldown and arm curl), with 3 sets of 10 repetitions at 10 RM (repetition maximum), and 1-min rest between sets. After this, participants were taken to an athletic track and performed 30 minutes of Aerobic Training  by walking or running with varying intensity (5 minutes at less than ventilatory threshold intensity, 10 minutes at ventilatory threshold intensity, 10 minutes above ventilatory threshold and at less than respiratory compensation point intensity, 5 minutes at less than ventilatory threshold intensity), with these intensities corresponding to 5085% of VO2peak. 
In S2, the Resistance Training was performed with the same exercises and sets from S1, however, with 3 sets of 8 repetitions at 8 RM (repetition maximum) and 1 minute and 30 seconds rest between sets. In the Aerobic Training the same duration was maintained, however, there was an adjustment in the training zone and time duration (5 minutes at less than ventilatory threshold intensity, 10 minutes at ventilatory threshold and at less than respiratory compensationpoint intensity, 10 minutes at respiratory compensation point intensity, 5 minutes at less than ventilatory threshold intensity), with these intensities corresponding to 5085% of VO2peak . 
In S3, the Resistance Training was performed with the same exercises and sets from S1, however, with 3 sets of 6 repetitions at 6 RM (repetition maximum) and 1 minute and 30 seconds rest between sets. In the Aerobic Training, the same duration was maintained and an adjustment in the training zone and time duration (3 minutes at ventilatory threshold intensity, 12 minutes at ventilatory threshold and at less than respiratory compensation point intensity, 10 minutes at respiratory compensation point intensity, 5 minutes at ventilatory threshold intensity), with these intensities corresponding to 5085% of VO2peak.
In all three stages of training, the total duration of the sessions was approximately 30-60 minutes. The frequency of sessions was 24 per stage, given three per week and a total of 72 sessions.
In all sessions, the subjects performed the resistance training or aerobic training or the resistance training following aerobic training protocol as his group. The resistance training was performed in a gym and the aerobic training in the athletic track, both located in the same place.
Aerobic training intensity for ventilatory threshold and respiratory compensation  point was controlled by the velocity achieved during the respective physiologic points in the treadmill test, since it was performed on 1% grades to reproduce athletic track  conditions. The treadmill test was performed at baseline and end of stages 1 and 2 to determine ventilatory threshold and respiratory compensation point for the upcoming stage. The treadmill test was conducted by Physical Education professional and consisted by a maximum-effort protocol, where running at maximal effort on a treadmill whilst wearing a face mask to measure respiratory gases, which were collected continuously using an automated breath-by-breath metabolic cart.  The treadmill duration test varied from subject to subject.
Furthermore, the Resistance Training workloads were adjusted weekly. The subjects were encouraged to perform the greatest number of repetitions when they came to the last set of each exercise, maintaining the same range of motion and execution velocity previously determined. Workloads were increased by 1 kg for lower body and 1/2 kg for upper body for each repetition performed over the established training protocol, according to the greatest number of repetitions achieved by the participants in the previous week.
The subjects were recommended to not change their pre eating and physical activity habits during the program.
The training sessions was performed in group and was carried by Physical Education professional. The training adherence was monitored by log of session attendance.














</interventions>
    <comparator>No treatment</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemical Metabolic markers related to lipid and glucose homeostasis (composite primary outcome), assesssed by blood sample 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biochemical inflammatory markers (composite primary outcome) which are cytokines and adipokines assessed  by blood sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>body composition markers (composite primary outcome) assessed by skinfold and body circumferences</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>physical activity level using the IPAQ and Baecke Questionnaire </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>feeding behavior using food record in 3 days food recall</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>cardiorespiratory fitness  using the treadmill incremental VO2 maximum test</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximal-strength assessed in quadriceps muscle, pectoral muscle and arm biceps muscle using respectivement one repetition maximum test by leg press, bench press and barbell exercises</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anthropometry using Body weight, height and waist circumference measurements</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Abdominal fat using evaluation of skin folds and Ultrasound</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical metabolic markers (composite secondary outcome) composed by Lipid profile, glucose, and glycated hemoglobin serum concentrations using commercially available kits and Friedewald equation</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Metabolic profile and biomarkers using nuclear magnetic ressonance (metabolomic). Composite secondary outcome assessed by serum sample analyzed by nuclear magnetic ressonance, which determine the metabolic present in the sample. This method detects around one hundred metabolics,
but this number depends on the physiological individuality of each subject </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Insulin resistance and sensibility using Homeostasis Model Assessment index, QUICKI index, triglycerides/glucose index and Z score of metabolic syndrome (composite secondary outcome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Type I of membrane protein fibronectin type III domain-containing protein 5 (FNDC5)/irisin levels using commercially available kits  assessed by serum sample</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ghrelin using commercially available kits assessed by serum sample</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inflammatory markers (Interleukin 6, interleukin 10, interleukin 15, C- reactive protein, prostaglandine E 2, tumor necrosis factor alpha, Leptin, Resistin, Adiponectin,  lipopolysaccharide) assessed by commercially available kits for Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay using serum sample</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hormone profile and enzyme (Insulin, Testosterone, Cortisol, Growth hormone, insulin growth factor 1, lactate dehydrogenase) composite secondary outcome assessed by serum assay sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Myocardial circulation, assessed by myocardial echocardiography 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Heart rate variability using commercial frequency meters</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure assessments using a mercury sphygmomanometer and stethoscope</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rest metabolic rate using indirect calorimetry at open circuit gas analysis system</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardio and cerebro vascular index risk (Framingham risk score)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Carotid artery structure, assessed by carotid ultrasound </outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and at 2, 4 and 6 months after randomization</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>. Inactive middle-aged male subjects with body mass index (BMI) between 25 and 34.9 kg/m^2 were recruited through dissemination in the local media.
To be included in the study, subjects completed medical examination and were approved in effort electrocardiogram carried out by cardiologist. Participants had not been engaging in regular exercise programs during the previous 12 months and also were classified as physically inactive according to the IPAQ and Baecke Questionnaire. All participants provided their written informed consent prior entering the study.

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>The exclusion criteria established for both groups were:
-Presence of acute illness, severe hypertension, diabetes mellitus, myocardial infarction and orthopedic limitations
-Use any medication that could interfere in the test results -Not be approved in effort electrocardiogram carried out by cardiologist. 
-The participants must not change the eating habits and physical activity  levels, other than the training sessions, for the study period.

Specifically the training subjects should participate in at least 85% of the training sessions and not miss more than two consecutive training sessions.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment by numbered containers</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using sortition by research randomizer site.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>To assess the number of participants needed, the sample size calculation were performed based on previous study of our group and using G*Power3.1.9.2 software. To do it, we considered a power = 0.8, effect size = 0.40 and an alpha of 0.05, resulting in a target sample size of 80 participants. Data are presented in values of means +/- standard deviation (SD). The Student t-test was used to analyze differences between groups in the baseline and to identify the differences among percentages of changes. The mixed model was used to determine significant condition x time interactions. The Tukey post hoc test was applied to determine the source of significance, where a significant main effect and/or interaction was/were observed. The Pearson test was used to correlations analysis. The significance level for all these analyses was P &lt; 0.05.The software packages used for all analyses were (SAS 9.2, SAS Institute Inc.,Cary, NC, USA).</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/03/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/03/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>13/12/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>13/12/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>77</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo / Campinas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname> Fundacao de Amparo a Pesquisa de Sao Paulo - FAPESP. "Foundation of the Sao Paulo Research"</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rua Pio XI, 1500 - Alto da Lapa, Sao Paulo  SP, CEP: 05468-140 - Brazil</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname> Fundacao de Amparo a Pesquisa de Sao Paulo - FAPESP. "Foundation of the Sao Paulo Research"</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rua Pio XI, 1500 - Alto da Lapa, Sao Paulo  SP, CEP: 05468-140 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cientifico e Tecnologico - CNPQ. "National Counsel of Technological and Scientific Development"</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>SHIS QI 1 Conjunto B - Blocos A, B, C e D
 
 Lago Sul - Brasilia.DF - Cep: 71605-001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cientifico e Tecnologico - CNPQ. "National Counsel of Technological and Scientific Development"</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>SHIS QI 1 Conjunto B - Blocos A, B, C e D
 
 Lago Sul - Brasilia.DF - Cep: 71605-001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Brazil</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Campinas</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Cidade Universitaria Zeferino Vaz - Barao Geraldo, Campinas - SP, 13083-970</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Brazil</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To Evaluate the effects of combined aerobic and resistance training on body composition, physical fitness and inflammatory , biochemical, hemodynamic and metabolic risk markers in middle-aged men. We hypothesize
that the training will improve the variables analyzed.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>The publications are being written or submitted and still not  accepted</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research Ethics Committee at the State University of Campinas - UNICAMP</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Rua Tessalia Vieira de Camargo, 126, caixa postal 6111, CEP: 13083887 Campinas-SP </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/12/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368925-Approval Ethics Committee.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Claudia Regina Cavaglieri</name>
      <address>University of Campinas
Avenida Erico Verissimo, 701. University City "Zeferino Vaz" Barao Geraldo - Campinas  SP, CEP: 13083-851
</address>
      <phone>+55 19 35216625 or  +55 19 35216756 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>cavaglieri@unicamp.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ivan Luiz Padilha Bonfante</name>
      <address>University of Campinas
Avenida Erico Verissimo, 701. University City "Zeferino Vaz" Barao Geraldo - Campinas  SP, CEP: 13083-851
</address>
      <phone>+55 19 35216625 or  +55 19 35216756 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ivanlpb@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ivan Luiz Padilha Bonfante</name>
      <address>University of Campinas
Avenida Erico Verissimo, 701. University City "Zeferino Vaz" Barao Geraldo - Campinas  SP, CEP: 13083-851
</address>
      <phone>+55 19 35216625 or  +55 19 35216756 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ivanlpb@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ivan Luiz Padilha Bonfante</name>
      <address>Avenida Erico Verissimo, 701. University City "Zeferino Vaz" Barao Geraldo - Campinas  SP, CEP: 13083-851
</address>
      <phone>+55 19 35216625 or  +55 19 35216756 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ivanlpb@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>