<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372273">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000192381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The association between looking or smiling at a patient and requests for assistance: A single-centre, blinded, randomised, controlled clinical trial
</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial to determine if either looking or smiling at an Emergency Department patient increases patient requests for assistance</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>The SMIRK Trial</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>patient requests for assistance</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The interventions will be administered as the researcher (medical student) walks past the patient's cubicle on a single occasion. Walking past will take approximately 4-5 seconds. - Arm 1: neither looking nor smiling at the patient. Arm 2: looking at the patient only, for the duration of the time walking past. Arm 3: looking and smiling at the patient for the duration of the time walking past..
The researchers administering the intervention will have classes from a departmental physiotherapist and speech pathologist to standardise the walking past and smile prior to commencement of the study. Both actions will be checked for intervention adherence by these health professionals after the first 50 patients have been enrolled and on subsequent occasions if adherence is thought to be inconsistent.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control intervention (study arm) is Arm 1 - simply walking past the cubicle and neither looking nor smiling at the patient</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient request for assistance. This is defined as either a call out by the patient to the intervention administrator or a wave/gesture as an attempt to attract attention. Requests for attention are very clear.</outcome>
      <timepoint>While administering the intervention. That is, while walking past the patient's cubicle </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The nature of the patient's request for assistance. For example, assistance to go to the toilet</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within a few seconds of administering the intervention and responding to the patient's request.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Confounding variables associated with requests for assistance e.g. age/gender of patient, age/gender/ethnicity of the researcher administering the intervention</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately following the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Emergency department patients, aged 18 years of more,  who are alert and looking out of their cubicle</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Family or friends in attendance with the patient</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible patients will be identified by the department's electronic patient list (for age criterion) and by direct observation (for alertness and looking out of the cubicle). Suitable patients will be assigned the next sequential study intervention determined a priori by computerised random number generation. Allocation will be will be concealed with the use of sealed opaque envelopes. Only the intervention administrator will know the patients allocation. </concealment>
    <sequence>computerised random number generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We anticipate 1% of patients will request assistance in the Control Arm. We expect that a clinically significant difference would be 5% in either of the other Arms. To demonstrate this we need at least 332 patients in each arm (equal number of patients in each group, alpha 0.05, power 0.8, 2 sided). Total number of patients = 3 x 332 = 996. This will be rounded up to 1000. 
The proportion of requests for assistance in each group will be compared using the Chi square test.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/05/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>31/05/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Austin Health - Austin Hospital - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Austin Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Studley Rd., Heidelberg, Victoria 3084</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Austin Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>na</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>na</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is considerable anecdotal evidence that smiling at a patient while walking past their cubicle increases the number of requests for assistance. This is perceived as a nuisance by some staff who believe they are busy enough and that the assistance should be provided by the patient's attending nurse. Given this perception, some staff deliberately do not look at or smile at a patient as they walk past. This trial will determine if smiling truly does increase requests. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not required</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Thé protocol for this project was reviewed by the Austin Health Office for Research. Details were also discussed with the Principal Investigator. It was noted that one of the three interventions (not looking, looking, smiling) will happen every time anybody walks past a patient's cubicle. Also, the interventions last only a few seconds, are associated with no risk to the patient and, as no patient data is collected, there are no confidentiality or privacy issues. Given these conditions, it was determined that review and approval by the institutions ethics committee was not required. </publicnotes>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Taylor</name>
      <address>Emergency Department, Austin Hospital, Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 4711</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>David.Taylor@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Taylor</name>
      <address>Emergency Department, Austin Hospital, Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 4711</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>David.Taylor@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Taylor</name>
      <address>Emergency Department, Austin Hospital, Studley Road, Heidelberg, Victoria, 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 4711</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>David.Taylor@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David Taylor</name>
      <address>Emergency Department, Austin Hospital, Victoria,</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9496 4711</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>David.Taylor@austin.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>