<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367090">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/09/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614001022651</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>First-in-Human, Single Ascending Oral Dose Study of DV-928 in Healthy Volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A First-in-Human, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Single Ascending Oral Dose Study to Assess the Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of DV-928 in Healthy Volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Treatment of Fatty Liver Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>DV-928 powder for reconstitution and oral administration.
Each subject will receive a single dose of either active DV-928 or placebo (calcium carbonate) according to the Cohort they are participating in and the intervention they are randomised to. 
1.	The doses of the intervention are described below per cohort:
* Cohort 1: DV-928 or placebo (30 mg)
* Cohort 2: DV-928 or placebo (100 mg)
* Cohort 3: DV-928 or placebo (300 mg)
* Cohort 4: DV-928 or placebo (600 mg)
* Cohort 5: DV-928 or placebo (1000 mg)
</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo (Calcium carbonate powder for reconstitution)
Each subject will receive a single dose of either active DV-928 or placebo (calcium carbonate) according to the Cohort they are participating in and the intervention they are randomised to. 
</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 1:
To evaluate the safety and tolerability of single, ascending oral doses of DV-928 in healthy volunteers.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint for Primary Outcome 1: Various safety measures including safety laboratory tests, 12-lead ECGs and Adverse Events collected at various timepoints in the 48 hours post study drug administration and during the 7-day follow up visit.  

</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary Outcome 2:
To characterize the pharmacokinetics of DV-928 in plasma following administration of single, ascending oral doses in healthy volunteers
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint for Primary Outcome 2: PK samples at pre-dose (pre-dose, representing baseline concentration levels) and at 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 3.5, 4, 6, 8, 12, 16, 24, 36 and 48 hours post-dose.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine any dose limiting adverse drug effects following single ascending oral dosing of DV-928 in healthy volunteers.

Routine vital sign measurements (blood pressure [BP], pulse and respiratory rate [RR]) will be measured at various timepoints from screening until trial completion. 
Physical examinations will be performed at screening, Day -1, and at trial completion. 
Safety Laboratory tests (Chemistry, Hematology, Gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase (GGT), and Urinalysis) will be drawn at various timepoints from screening until trial completion. 
Twelve-lead ECGs will be obtained from subjects at various timepoints from screening until 48 hours post dose and additional ECGs may be obtained if clinically indicated.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timepoint: Adverse events will be reported following study drug administration throughout the 7 day duration of each cohort, for all cohorts.

</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-	Be in good health as determined by medical history, physical examination, 12 lead ECG and clinical laboratory evaluations at screening;
-	Male subjects must agree to use a medically acceptable method of contraception/birth control throughout the study duration and for 90 days after the study is completed.  
-	Female subjects must be of non-childbearing potential 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>19</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-	Significant blood loss or donated blood in the 30 days prior to study participation
-	Participation in an investigational drug study within 30 days prior to dosing.
-	History of drug or alcohol abuse.  
-	Use of any medications, including OTC and herbal or nutritional supplements during the week prior to drug dosing 
-	Positive tests for HIV, hepatitis B/C, drugs of abuse or alcohol breath-test. 
-	Clinically significant abnormalities 
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Six subjects per cohort will be randomized with a 2:1 randomization whereby 4 subjects receive DV-928 and 2 subjects receive placebo. The dose will be provided to blinded study staff in a blinded fashion.

A Master Randomization schedule will be held off-site by an unblinded Pharmacist. Once the PI confirms eligibility a Subject Randomisation Number will be allocated and provided to the unblinded  Pharmacist. The unblinded Pharmacist will reference the randomization schedule and  prepare and dispense DV-928 or placebo to each patient according to their Subject Randomisation number. No other site staff have access to the Master Randomisation Schdeule and therefore remain blinded at all times.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table/schedule generated by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Six subjects per cohort with a 2:1 randomization ratio will be treated with 4 subjects receiving DV-928 and 2 subjects receiving placebo for a total of 5 cohorts (30 subjects total will be enrolled).  Each cohort of 6 subjects continues only after the safety assessment of the previous cohort.
For Cohort 1 only, sentinel dosing will be used. For all other cohorts, the 6 subjects will be dosed on the same day.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Safety  Safety will be evaluated by assessment of clinical laboratory tests, physical examinations including vital signs, and ECGs, and by the documentation of all spontaneously reported adverse events. 
Pharmacokinetics  Plasma concentration data of DV-928 and its metabolite at each dose level will be used to calculate relevant pharmacokinetic parameters.  
Pharmacokinetic parameters will summarized by dose level using descriptive statistics.
Due to the exploratory nature of this first-in-human study, no power or sample size calculations have been performed.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/10/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/10/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>11/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>4/02/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>36</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>15/02/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>15/02/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3004 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>INC Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>159 Port Rd, Hindmarsh South Australia, 5007 </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>DURECT Corporation </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>10260 Bubb Road
Cupertino, CA  95014, USA
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research project is being conducted to look at how safe and well tolerated a new drug called DV-928 is when different amounts are given to healthy volunteers.  The pharmacokinetics of DV-928 will also be studied; this is done by measuring the amount of DV-928 in the blood at different times throughout the initial 2 days following administration, allowing us to evaluate how DV-928 is handled by the body (for example how quickly it gets into the blood stream).  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Alfred Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>55 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria  3004</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/10/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jason Lickliter</name>
      <address>Nucleus Network
5th Floor, Burnet Tower, AMREP Precinct
89 Commercial Road
Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, 3004
</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9076 8906</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 3 9076 8911</fax>
      <email>j.lickliter@nucleusnetwork.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jemma Lawson</name>
      <address>INC Research, Level 1, 159 Port Road, Hindmarsh, SA 5007, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7202 1510</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7202 1599</fax>
      <email>jemma.lawson@increserach.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jemma Lawson</name>
      <address>INC Research, Level 1, 159 Port Road, Hindmarsh, SA 5007, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7202 1510</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7202 1599</fax>
      <email>jemma.lawson@increserach.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jemma Lawson</name>
      <address>INC Research, Level 1, 159 Port Road, Hindmarsh, SA 5007, Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7202 1510</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7202 1599</fax>
      <email>jemma.lawson@increserach.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>