<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363119">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001085864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A vegetarian style diet versus a Western style diet on biomarkers of health and ageing in healthy volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study investigating the effect and feasibility of a methionine restricted diet on biomarkers of health and ageing in healthy volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Healthy volunteers</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Methionine restricted diet: As methionine content tends to be high in flesh foods, the methionine restricted diet will contain fewer meat options. The composition and energy intake of the methionine restricted diet will reflect that of the standard Western diet (~50% carbohydrate, ~15% protein and ~35% fat; 8400 KJ daily energy intake). To obtain a desirable amount of protein in the methionine restricted diet, foods that are higher in protein but lower in methionine will be chosen. For example, lentils contain roughly 25% more protein and less than half the methionine content per 100 g than beef. This study aims to restrict methionine as much as is practicable, approximately in the range of at least 40% but no more than 80% with a view to achieving 60% on average methionine restriction relative to the standard Western diet. This dietary intervention will run for 4 weeks. CSIRO will be providing a daily main meal during the intervention and guidelines for appropriate breakfast and lunch meals. There will be a 4 week washout between dietary interventions.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard Western diet: The standard Western diet is typically high in red meat, sugary desserts, high-fat foods, high-fat dairy products, sugary drinks and processed meat. In the current study, the standard Western diet will contain ~50% carbohydrate, ~15% protein and ~35% fat as is common with Western pattern diets. Energy intake will be targeted in the recommended range of 8400 KJ. This dietary intervention will run for 4 weeks. CSIRO will be providing a daily main meal during the intervention and guidelines for appropriate breakfast and lunch meals. There will be a 4 week washout between dietary interventions.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma methionine measurement (blood sample assay).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0, 2, 4, 8, 10, 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Oxidative Stress: ratio of reduced to oxidised glutathione and oxidised guanine in DNA (assay kit).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0, 2, 4, 8, 10, 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Metabolic Stress as measured by mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) Activity (assay kit).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0, 2, 4, 8, 10, 12</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum inhibition of in vitro cancer cell culture growth as measured by Microculture Tetrazolium (MTT) assay.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0, 2, 4, 8, 10, 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Genome integrity of lymphocytes as determined by the cytokinesis-block micronucleus (CBMN) assay - frequency of chromosome breakage (micronuclei), chromosome loss (micronuclei), chromosome rearrangement, for example, dicentric chromosomes (nucleoplasmic bridges), gene amplification (nuclear buds), necrosis and apoptosis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Week 0, 2, 4, 8, 10, 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Male or Female
- Aged 50-70
- Healthy with no history of cancer
- Body mass index in the healthy range (BMI): 18.5-27</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- History of smoking
- Currently on medication/dietary supplements which may impact methionine, folate and B vitamin content in the blood
- Current vegetarians/vegans</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/11/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/11/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>1/11/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>20</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>CSIRO</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Gate 13 Kintore Avenue
Adelaide, SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>CSIRO</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Gate 13 Kintore Avenue
Adelaide, SA 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The proposed project will investigate whether a methionine restricted diet is a feasible nutritional regimen for healthy ageing in a healthy population. This project will consist of 2 diets: a methionine restricted diet and a standard western diet. As methionine content tends to be higher in flesh foods, the methionine restricted diet will be predominantly plant based. The proposed project will utilise a randomised cross-over design so that each volunteer consumes both diets. Healthy volunteers (n=20) with no history of cancer will be recruited. The proposed project will measure the effect of a methionine restricted diet on biomarkers of health and ageing. Blood will be collected from the volunteers at specific time points and analysed for biomarkers of ageing; lymphocytes will be isolated to measure genome integrity and serum will be utilised in vitro to determine rate of growth of established cancer cell lines.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Oral Presentation:
Cavuoto P, Taylor P, May B, Weaver J, Lim Y, Zhou X, Fenech M. Methionine restriction as a healthy ageing strategy, is it safe and plausible in humans? Nugo Week 2015, 12th edition, Mechanisms of a Long-Life Health, Barcelona, Spain, September 7-9, 2015</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>CSIRO Food and Nutritional Sciences Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Gate 13 Kintore Avenue
Adelaide, SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/08/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/08/2012</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Paul Cavuoto</name>
      <address>Gate 13 Kintore Avenue
Adelaide, SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61883038877</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.cavuoto@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Julia Weaver</name>
      <address>Gate 13 Kintore Avenue
Adelaide, SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61883038876</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julia.weaver@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Paul Cavuoto</name>
      <address>CSIRO
Gate 13 Kintore Avenue
Adelaide, SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8303 8877</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>paul.cavuoto@csiro.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>