<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364927">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/09/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001014741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Acute Effects of a Single Bout of Exercise on Asthmatic Airway Inflammation: A Pilot Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Acute Effects of a Single Bout of Exercise on Asthmatic Airway Inflammation</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ExI Study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will attend four visits.

Visit 1: Two hours prior to visit 1, participants will be directed to consume a carbohydrate-based breakfast (caffeine free). On arrival at the clinic, participants will perform spirometry and plethysmography, have a venous blood sample collected and exhaled nitric oxide (eNO) measured. Participants will then be treated with 400mcg inhaled salbutamol via spacer and spirometry performed 15-minutes post-bronchodilator. Participants will be randomised to complete one of the following interventions: 1) 30-minutes of moderate-intensity exercise on a treadmill or 2) 30-minutes of rest. Moderate-intensity exercise will be performed at 60-80% of the age predicted maximum heart rate. At 0, 1 and 2 hours post-exercise/rest a venous blood sample will be collected, eNO measured and spirometry performed. eNO will also be measured and spirometry perfomed 0.5 hours and 4 hours post-exercise. Participants will be instructed to maintain a food diary for the entire day and breakfast the following morning.

Visit 2: Visit 2 will be conducted 24 hours after visit 1. Two hours prior to visit 2, participants will be directed to consume the same breakfast they had prior to visit 1. On arrival at the clinic, participants will perform spirometry, have a venous blood sample collected, exhaled nitric oxide (eNO) measured and have an allergy skin prick test. Participants will also complete 7 days of pedometry between visit 2 and visit 3.

Visit 3: Visit 3 will be conducted 4 weeks after visit 2. Two hours prior to this visit, participants will be directed to consume the same breakfast as they had prior to visit 1. On arrival at the clinic, participants will perform spirometry, have a venous blood sample collected and exhaled nitric oxide (eNO) measured. Participants will then be treated with 400mcg inhaled salbutamol via spacer and spirometry performed 15-minutes post-bronchodilator. Participants will be randomised to complete the alternate intervention to visit 1: either 1) 30-minutes of moderate-intensity exercise on a treadmill or 2) 30-minutes of rest. Moderate-intensity exercise will be performed at 60-80% of the age predicted maximum heart rate. At 0, 1 and 2 hours post-exercise/rest a venous blood sample will be collected, eNO measured and spirometry performed. eNO will also be measured and spirometry perfomed 0.5 hours and 4 hours post-exercise. Participants will be directed to have the same foods for the entire day as they had during visit 1. Participants will be instructed to maintain a food diary for the entire day and breakfast the following morning.

Visit 4: Visit 4 will be conducted 24 hours after visit 3. Two hours prior to visit 4, participants will be directed to consume the same breakfast they had prior to visit 1. On arrival at the clinic, participants will perform spirometry, have a venous blood sample collected and eNO measured.
</interventions>
    <comparator>The comparator or control treatment will be no exercise, where the participant will rest in a chair for 30 minutes.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Exhaled nitric oxide (eNO), which will be measured using an Ecomedics nitric oxide analyser.</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 1, 2, 4 and 24 hours (versus baseline)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma eosinophil count</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 1, 2 and 24 hours (versus baseline)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma Interleukin (IL)-5</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 1, 2 and 24 hours (versus baseline)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma IL-4</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 1, 2 and 24 hours (versus baseline)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma IL-10</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 1, 2 and 24 hours (versus baseline)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>C-reactive protein (CRP)</outcome>
      <timepoint>0, 1, 2 and 24 hours (versus baseline)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Doctor diagnosed asthma; stable asthma (no respiratory tract infection, oral corticosteroid use or antibiotic use in the 4 weeks preceding the intervention visits); 18-65 years of age and body mass index (BMI) &lt;=40kg/m2; never or ex-smokers (last cigarette at least 6 months prior); FEV1 &gt;50% predicted. GP clearance for exercise must be provided for females aged &gt;50 years, males aged &gt;40 years, and all participants who respond yes to any question in Part A of the Adult Pre-Exercise Screening Tool.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current smoker; cardiac contraindication to exercise; cancer; pregnancy or breastfeeding; currently undertaking exercise training (&gt;=90 minutes per week); any issue that in the opinion of the investigator would impede the participants safety and/or ability to undertake the exercise intervention; participation in an exercise session within 3 days of the scheduled study visit.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After screening for eligibility, participants will be assigned to the next available study number. Allocation will be concealed by blinded list held by an independent statistician.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated sequence, using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Because this is a pilot study, sample size could not be calculated. Therefore n=20 participants will be recruited. Repeated measures ANOVA will be performed to examine the effects of exercise on systemic and airway inflammation at each time point. Associations between change in exhaled nitric oxide concentration and markers of systemic inflammation will be examined using Spearman rank correlations. P-values =0.05 will be considered statistically significant.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/10/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/10/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>25/07/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>16</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Hunter Medical Research Institute</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hunter Medical Research Institute
Lot 1 Kookaburra Circuit
New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>John Hunter Hospital Charitable Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>John Hunter Hospital
Lookout Road,
New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>John Hunter Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>John Hunter Hospital
Lookout Road,
New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>University of Newcastle</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Newcastle
University Drive,
Callaghan NSW 2308</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project will determine the acute anti-inflammatory effects of a single bout of exercise in asthma. It is well known that exercise has numerous health benefits; however, research regarding the effect of exercise on airway inflammation in asthma is scarce. This project will examine the mechanisms by which exercise reduces airway eosinophilia in asthma. This research is highly significant to asthma management, as those with asthma have been shown to have very low exercise levels, possibly stemming from the belief that exercise will worsen asthma. We will begin with this study of short-term exercise and use the findings to inform the design of a later study which will examine the effects of exercise training on asthma.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Scott HA, Latham JR, Callister R, Pretto JJ, Baines K, Saltos N, Upham JW, Wood LG. Acute exercise is associated with reduced exhaled nitric oxide in physically inactive adults with asthma. Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol. 2015; 114: 470-479. 

Scott HA, Latham JR, Callister R, Pretto JJ, Baines K, Saltos N, Upham JW, Wood LG. A single bout of exercise is associated with a transient reduction to exhaled nitric oxide in physically inactive adults with asthma. Respirology. 2015; 20: 68. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee
Locked Bag 1 HRMC
New Lambton NSW 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hayley Scott</name>
      <address>Centre for Asthma and Respiratory Diseases
Level 2 West Wing, HMRI Building
Lot 1 Kookaburra Circuit
New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4042 0113</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 4042 0046</fax>
      <email>Hayley.Scott@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hayley Scott</name>
      <address>Centre for Asthma and Respiratory Diseases
Level 2 West Wing, HMRI Building
Lot 1 Kookaburra Circuit
New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4042 0113</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 4042 0046</fax>
      <email>Hayley.Scott@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hayley Scott</name>
      <address>Centre for Asthma and Respiratory Diseases
Level 2 West Wing, HMRI Building
Lot 1 Kookaburra Circuit
New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4042 0113</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 4042 0046</fax>
      <email>Hayley.Scott@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Hayley Scott</name>
      <address>Centre for Asthma and Respiratory Diseases
Level 2 West Wing, HMRI Building
Lot 1 Kookaburra Circuit
New Lambton Heights NSW 2305</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4042 0113</phone>
      <fax>+ 61 2 4042 0046</fax>
      <email>Hayley.Scott@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>