<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368417">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/04/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/05/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000421538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of prolonged wear of textured shoe insoles on walking in people with Multiple Sclerosis</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can gait be improved by way of plantar tactile stimulation? An exploratory randomized controlled trial of the effects of prolonged wear of textured shoe insoles in people with Multiple Sclerosis </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Multiple Sclerosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Walking Impairment</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Falls Risk</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Multiple sclerosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Textured shoe insoles (Evalite Pyramid EVA, 3mm thickness, shore value A50, black, OG1549; Algeos Ltd, Liverpool, UK) - constructed from EVA soling material, which has small, pyramidal peaks with centre-to-centre distances of approximately 2.5mm. Participants will be instructed to wear the textured insoles, in their own shoes, as much as possible over the 3-month intervention period. Participants will be followed for 3-months with insole-wear diaries to determine the number of hours insoles are worn. All participants will receive emergency contact details for a local podiatrist, who will provide advice and podiatry care for participants, as required.  
</interventions>
    <comparator>Flat, control insoles (Medium Density EVA, 3mm thickness, shore value A50, black, OG1304; Algeos Ltd., Liverpool, UK) - constructed plain EVA material, which has a flat surface with no indentations. Participants will be instructed to wear the flat control insoles, in their own shoes, as much as possible over the 3-month intervention period. Participants will be followed for 3-months with insole-wear diaries to determine the number of hours insoles are worn. All participants will receive emergency contact details for a local podiatrist, who will provide advice and podiatry care for participants, as required.  </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Temporospatial Gait Parameters: 
Base of Support, Stride Length, Stride Time Variability, Double-Limb Support Time, Gait Velocity during walking over even and uneven surfaces.
Measured using an electronic walkway (GAITRite) and motion capture system (Vicon).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at: 
Baseline Assessment 1 (Upon entry into study)
Baseline Assessment 2 (4 weeks after Baseline Assessment 1, prior to the commencement of insole use) 
Assessment 3 (3-months after the commencement of insole use)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait Kinetics:
Lower limb and trunk muscle activation during walking over even and uneven surfaces. 
Measured using surface electromyography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at: 
Baseline Assessment 1 (Upon entry into study)
Baseline Assessment 2 (4 weeks after Baseline Assessment 1, prior to the commencement of insole use) 
Assessment 3 (3-months after the commencement of insole use)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait Kinematics:
Lower limb joint and trunk movement
Measured using a motion capture system (Vicon)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at: 
Baseline Assessment 1 (Upon entry into study)
Baseline Assessment 2 (4 weeks after Baseline Assessment 1, prior to the commencement of insole use) 
Assessment 3 (3-months after the commencement of insole use)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Foot Sensation and Proprioception:
Light-touch sensation, Vibration sense, Two-point discrimination, Ankle joint position sense.
Measured using monofilaments, tuning fork, 2-point discriminator, and 2-dimensional webcam kinematic software analysis application. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at: 
Baseline Assessment 1 (Upon entry into study)
Baseline Assessment 2 (4 weeks after Baseline Assessment 1, prior to the commencement of insole use) 
Assessment 3 (3-months after the commencement of insole use)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Men and women aged &gt;18 years, with a clinical diagnosis of Multiple Sclerosis; Disease Steps grading 1-4; and ambulant over 100 metres with or without the use of an assistive device (cane/crutch).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Neurological conditions other than Multiple Sclerosis;
Peripheral neuropathy to a degree that would preclude the ability to perceive the textured insole;
Currently being prescribed over-the-counter or custom-made foot orthoses;
Cardiovascular or orthopaedic conditions including recent injury to the back or legs limiting ambulation; 
Unstable psychiatric condition; 
Cognitive impairment.

Participants who report a formal exacerbation of Multiple Sclerosis symptoms persisting &gt;24hrs, four weeks prior to, or at any time during, the intervention period will be excluded from the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be randomized to either the control insole or textured insole group. The randomisation schedule will be generated and maintained by an offsite investigator and revealed via telephone to a second Research Assistant, prior to Baseline 2 Assessment. The Principal Investigator, first Research Assistant, and all other Co-Investigators will remain blinded to the insole group allocation. Participants will be instructed not to divulge their group allocation. Following Baseline Assessment 2, the Principal Investigator and first Research Assistant will leave the gait laboratory to ensure blinding to the insole condition. The second Research Assistant will then fit the participant with their allocated insole, and provide advice regarding; frequency of wear, completion of insole wear diaries, and emergency contact details for local podiatry care. The second Research Assistant will not be involved in any aspects of data collection or analysis.</concealment>
    <sequence>The schedule will be generated using simple randomisation by way of a randomisation table created by computer software (computerised sequence generation).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size was calculated for our primary outcome measure, base of support during even surface walking, based on our pilot data. Our preliminary study reported mean (SD) readings at baseline for base of support of 13.78 (5.11) cm and a significant mean change of -1.66 cm (P=0.02) at 2-week follow up. With a power of 80%, and alpha level set to 0.05, a calculation for two related groups gave a figure of n=76. In our pilot study we recruited 46 people with MS, of whom 100% completed all tests (2 visits). As this exploratory RCT involves a longer intervention period, we will allow for a 15% attrition rate. An 85% retention rate over a 4-month period (baseline assessment at 1 month, intervention 3-months) is accurate and appropriate, based on previous MS intervention studies. Three RCTs with 3-month intervention periods conducted in people with MS, report retention rates of 82%, 88%, and 90%. Other RCTs conducted in people with MS report retention rates of 88% over 1-month, 86% and 95% over 7-weeks, and 80%, 83%, and 96% over 6-months. Therefore, 88 participants per group will be recruited, giving a total of n=176. This will be a suitably large sample size for this exploratory trial to provide estimates of effect sizes and yield between-group confidence intervals to inform a future full-scale RCT.

Data will be analysed using SPSS and MATLAB software. All analyses will be conducted in a blinded manner, on an intention-to-treat basis. To determine if there is any difference between intervention and control groups in gait, foot sensation or proprioception over the intervention period a repeated measures mixed models approach will be undertaken using data at baseline and 3-months. Non-parametric tests will be used where data is not normally distributed or violates the assumption of sphericity. Participant characteristics (e.g. age, gender, height) will be included as covariates. Multiple regression modelling will be used to determine any relationships between foot sensation (light touch-pressure, vibration, and two-point discrimination), proprioception (joint position sense) and gait.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/05/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>7/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>176</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Anna Hatton</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, Therapies Building (84A), The University of Queensland, St Lucia, QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Multiple Sclerosis Research Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 26, Northpoint, 100 Miller Street, North Sydney NSW 2060</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Sandra Brauer</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, Therapies Building (84A), The University of Queensland, St Lucia, QLD 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Graham Kerr</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Institute of Health &amp; Biomedical Innovation, School of Exercise and Nutrition Sciences, Queensland University of Technology, Kelvin Grove, Brisbane, QLD 4059
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Keith Rome</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Auckland University of Technology, 90 Akoranga Drive, AA Building, Northcote 0627, Auckland. </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr John Dixon</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Health and Social Care Institute, School of Health and Social Care, Borough Road, Teesside University, Middlesbrough, TS1 3BA 
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>United Kingdom</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ms Katrina Williams</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, Therapies Building (84A), The University of Queensland, St Lucia, QLD 4072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Many people with Multiple Sclerosis (MS) experience problems with walking, which can make day to day activities difficult and often leads to falls. Improving walking ability is, therefore, of primary importance in maintaining health, independence, and quality of life in people living with MS. Walking problems in MS are often caused by a combination of typical symptoms, such as altered function of muscles, nerves, and senses. The key to improving mobility is, therefore, to use a range of different treatment techniques which address each of these symptoms. Foot sensation plays an important role in keeping the body upright and balanced whilst walking, yet, we know from previous studies that people with MS often have poor sensation on the soles of their feet. It is, therefore, possible that wearing a specially designed shoe insole, which enhances sensory information at the feet, could help people affected by MS to walk better. This would offer health care professionals a new, additional treatment technique to help manage walking problems in MS. This study will explore whether long-term wear of a textured shoe insole can improve walking in people with MS. We will analyse how people with MS walk over an even and uneven surface, when they are wearing the insoles for the first time, and after wearing the insoles for three months. We will explore whether wearing the insoles changes the way the body moves, or the leg and trunk muscles work during walking. We will also monitor any changes in the perception of foot sensation and the awareness of foot position, to help us better understand how our insoles may bring about their effects on walking. The benefit for people affected by MS is that this study could lead to the development of a new treatment technique, specifically an inexpensive, easy-to-administer shoe insole, which could help towards improving mobility and independent living.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics, Research Management Office, UQ Research and Innovation, Cumbrae-Stewart Building (#72), St Lucia, QLD 4072 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/07/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2014000871</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Ethics and Integrity, Queensland University of Technology, Kelvin Grove, QLD 4059</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>6/04/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anna Hatton</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, Therapies Building (84A), The University of Queensland, St Lucia, Brisbane, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61733654590</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.hatton1@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Anna Hatton</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, Therapies Building (84A), The University of Queensland, St Lucia, Brisbane, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61733654590</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.hatton1@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anna Hatton</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, Therapies Building (84A), The University of Queensland, St Lucia, Brisbane, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61733654590</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.hatton1@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Anna Hatton</name>
      <address>School of Health and Rehabilitation Sciences, Therapies Building (84A), The University of Queensland, St Lucia, Brisbane, QLD 4072</address>
      <phone>+61733654590</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.hatton1@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>