<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83141">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/09/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000473369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effects on environmental, child, maternal and family outcomes for children born to at risk mothers (who have one or more risk factors for poorer parental coping) receiving sustained nurse home visiting compared with usual care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effects on environmental, child, maternal and family outcomes for children born to at risk mothers (who have one or more risk factors for poorer parental coping) receiving sustained nurse home visiting compared with usual care</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>MECSH</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>child development</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>child health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Sustained nurse home visiting commencing in the second trimester of pregnancy and continuing to child-age 2 years. Each mother receives 25 visits of 1 hour duration. During visits the nurse provides education and support for the mother and family to enhance their coping and problem solving skills and ability to mobilise resources; foster positive parenting skills; establish supportive relationships in their community; mentor maternal-infant bonding and attachment; and provide primary health care and health education, including but not limited to immunisation, Sudden Infant Death Syndrome risk reduction, infant nutrition and child safety.</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard treatment of one postnatal home visit by a child health nurse from the local community-based primary health care service, additional postnatal or clinic visits with the local primary health care service and access to early childhood services within the local area.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mean scores on Bayley Scales of Infant Development</outcome>
      <timepoint>at child age 18 and 30 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mean score on Wechsler Preschool &amp; Primary Scale of Intelligence - Australian Standardisation (WPPSI-III Australian)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 6 months post child entry to formal schooling</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>number of inpatient and outpatient hospital separations</outcome>
      <timepoint>at child age 24 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mean child behaviour and psychological attribute scores measured using Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>at child age 4 years and 6 months post entry to formal schooling</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>mean National Institute of Child Health and Development (NICHD) parent child interaction scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>at child age 18 and 30 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pregnant women, and English speaking, and
Resident in New South Wales, Australia postcode area 2168, and One or more risk factors for poorer parental coping from maternal self report of expected lack of practical and emotional support, stressors in the past 12 months, personality, mental health, history of abuse in the mothers childhood, and family violence, or Current probably distress measured as Edinburgh Depression Scale score of 10 or more</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Poor English requiring an interpreter or no telephone</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligible participants were identified by the Senior Research Officer (SRO) who was provided daily with the records of all new women booking into hospital for pregnancy care. Details of eligible women were entered by the SRO onto a central database and a random selection of cases to receive intervention was made using computer.
Allocation was concealed from all intervention and research staff until after mothers consented to participate in the study and baseline data had been collected by the research assistant who was blinded to the allocation. After baseline measures were completed, women were given a sealed opaque envelope that contained information advising them of their group assignment.</concealment>
    <sequence>A permuted block design was used to randomly allocate mothers to the intervention or comparison group. Blocks were based on the weekly intake of eligible clients at the antenatal clinic and varied in size. Within each weekly block, a random selection of cases to receive intervention was made using the computer program Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2003</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/02/2003</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/03/2005</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>190</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>208</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of NSW</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of NSW
Sydney NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1st Floor, 8 Brindabella Circuit
Brindabella Business Park
Canberra Airport ACT 2609</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sydney South West Area Health Service</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Liverpool Hospital
Locked Bag 7103
Liverpool BC NSW 1871</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NSW Department of Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Locked Mail Bag 961
North Sydney NSW 2059</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NSW Department of Community Services</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Locked Bag 4028
Ashfield NSW 2131</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Home visiting programs comprising intensive and sustained nurse home visits over the entire first two years of life (SNHV) show promise as interventions to promote child health and family functioning, and ameliorate disadvantage. This study is the first Australian randomised trial to determine the impact of a comprehensive SNHV program commencing antenatally in a population group living in an area of known disadvantage. As such this trial is a best-practice demonstration model for professional home visiting in Australia, with significant implications for the development of early childhood policy and strategy throughout Australia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Kemp L, Harris E, McMahon C, Matthey S, Vimpani G, Anderson T, Schmied V, Aslam H, Zapart S. (2011) Child and family outcomes of a long-term nurse home visitation program: a randomised controlled trial. Archives of Disease in Childhood 96:533-540.
Kemp L, Harris E. (2012) The challenges of establishing and researching a sustained nurse home visiting programme within the universal child and family health service system. Journal of Research in Nursing 17:139-141.
Kemp L, Harris E, McMahon C, Matthey S, Vimpani G, Anderson T, Schmied V, Aslam H. (2013) Benefits of psychosocial intervention and continuity of care by child and family health nurses in the pre and postnatal period: Process evaluation. Journal of Advanced Nursing 69(8), 1850-1861.
Zapart S, Knight J, Kemp L (2016) It was easier because I had help: mothers reflections on the long-term impact of sustained nurse home visiting. Maternal and Child Health Journal 20(1)196-204.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney South West Area Health Service (WZ) Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 7103
Liverpool BC NSW 1871</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/11/2002</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>02/119</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of NSW Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of NSW
Sydney NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/12/2002</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>02382</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>NSW Department of Education and Training</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>GPO Box 33
Sydney NSW 2001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/08/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008027</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lynn Kemp</name>
      <address>TReSI, Ingham Institute
Western Sydney University
I Campbell St
Liverpool NSW 2170</address>
      <phone>+61 2 87389394</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 96120762</fax>
      <email>l.kemp@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lynn Kemp</name>
      <address>TReSI, Ingham Institute
Western Sydney University
I Campbell St
Liverpool NSW 2170</address>
      <phone>+61 2 87389394</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 96120762</fax>
      <email>lynn.kemp@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lynn Kemp</name>
      <address>TReSI, Ingham Institute
Western Sydney University
I Campbell St
Liverpool NSW 2170</address>
      <phone>+61 2 87389394</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 96120762</fax>
      <email>lynn.kemp@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lynn Kemp</name>
      <address>TReSI, Ingham Institute
Western Sydney University
I Campbell St
Liverpool NSW 2170</address>
      <phone>+61 2 87389394</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lynn.kemp@westernsydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>