<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363115">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/10/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001173886</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation in the treatment of Huntingtons Chorea</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For patients with Huntingtons Disease, can repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (rTMS) in comparison with sham rTMS, reduce choreic movements.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1135-5250</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Huntington's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Neurodegenerative diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (rTMS).
	Both active treatments are applied to the presumed site of motor cortex origin of the hand muscles, regardless of the actual chorea. A total of 900 pulses are delivered at 1Hz (15 minutes). Intensity is set at 100% of magnetic threshold. A MagStim Rapid magnetic stimulator (Magstim, Whitland, UK), connected with a figure-of-eight coil with a diameter of 70mm, will be used to deliver stimuli with the coil handle pointing posteriorly and 45degrees below the coronal plane.
	Prior to the commencement of the treatment course, resting motor threshold is measured with single-pulse TMS applied to the motor cortex. The resting motor threshold was measured as the minimal stimulator intensity producing a visible peripheral motor evoked potential response by inspection. 
     Session by session comparison wherein the stimulus is varied daily (common in rTMS with chorea research), over 10 days (2 week). Washout between active and sham TMS is overnight, or over a weekend if a week based change.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo rTMS.
     Placebo rTMS will be conducted using active stimuli applied with the coil rotated at 90degrees to the skull. The technician administering the rTMS thus cannot be blind, but the assessment of movement is conducted by a third party without stimulus knowledge. The participant cannot know which stimulus is intended to be a placebo. It is possible to distinguish the two treatments, but not to identify the sham, so the participant is practically blinded.
     Sham rTMS can be performed using the same stimulator connected to the placebo butterfly coil (MCF-P-B-65), which has no stimulating effect on the cortex but produces auditory and tactile sensations similar to those produced by the real coil. Unfortunately we currently do not have this form of coil.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction in choreic movements. The UHDRS chorea severity scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after each rTMS session.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Global Huntington's severity. General measures for each patient will be made with the Unified Huntington's Disease Rating Scale (UHDRS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and Final (after 2 week periods)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cortical excitability will be measured using a varying number of standard techniques depending on the patient's comfort. 
The motor evoked potentials (MEP) threshold curves using MEP amplitude at the Abductor Pollicus Brevis muscle, short-interval cortical inhibition (SICI), long-interval cortical inhibition (LICI), interacortical facilitation and inhibition (IFI), intercortical facilitation and inhibition (IHI, IHF), and silent period have all been used as measures of excitability, but impose varying demands on the patient.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after each rTMS session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who attended that Huntingtons Study Group (HSG) at the Neurosciences Unit, Graylands Hospital, who have choreic movements, and for whom the movements are especially intrusive or poorly controlled, will be offered the option of the rTMS trial.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children.
Pregnancy.
History of epilepsy.
Metal implants in the head.
Pacemaker</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The Trial is initially an un-randomised study, but ultimately with a randomised controlled component, and is labelled as such.
      A randomised list is generated (SPSS) with the two arms (real rTMS, sham rTMS) and stored separate to the investigation (site manager). Each participant recruited (Consent signed) is assigned an initial arm for the investigation.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer package (SPSS for Windows11.5) randomly selected from 200 cases. Participants assigned in sequence of recruitment.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This study seeks to investigate short term effects (up to 24 hours) on chorea, as have been reported previously, but also will seek to establish a lasting effect of rTMS. In designing these investigations, the value of the scientific information has been balanced against the patient impost, and the likelihood of patient attrition. The project develops in three parts contingent upon a patients capacity and interest, with data in each part informing subsequent components.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>North Metropolitan Area Health Service</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Statewide Department of Neurophysiology
Gascoyne House, Graylands Hospital
John XXIII Avenue
Mount Claremont, Western Australia, 6010.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>North Metropolitan Area Health Service</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Statewide Department of Neurophysiology
Gascoyne House, Graylands Hospital
John XXIII Avenue
Mount Claremont, Western Australia, 6010.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Neuroscience Unit, Graylands Hospital.</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Ord House, Graylands Hospital
John XXIII Avenue
Mount Claremont, Western Australia, 6010.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Australian Neuromuscular Research Institute</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Australian Neuromuscular Research Institute
QEII Medical Centre
Verdun Street 
Nedlands, WA, 6009</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Huntingtons disease (HD) is an autosomal dominant neurodegenerative illness characterized by disorders of movement, cognition, behavior, and functional capacity. In Huntington's disease (HD), the cerebral cortex is involved early in the disease process, and this region has been shown to have abnormal excitability characteristics prior to illness onset, as well as different long term potentiation. 
Repetitive Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (rTMS) is a potential new treatment for depression, and other psychiatric disorders. Using TMS, circuits of the human motor cortex can be activated non-invasively, and because the excitability of neural circuits in the cerebral cortex is not static, repetitive TMS (rTMS) can produce changes in neurotransmission that outlast the period of stimulation. rTMS has been shown to modify excitability in the motor cortex in general, has been used extensively in the treatment of movements in Parkinsons and other dyskinesias, and has positive preliminary findings in the treatment of Huntingtons chorea. 
	The purpose of the study is twofold: to investigate the short term effects (up to 24 hours) of inhibitory rTMS on choreic movements as have been reported previously; and to seek to establish a lasting effect of rTMS in a double blind, randomized, sham-controlled study. Firstly, we intend to replicate previous work, using the standard protocol for decreasing excitability in the motor cortex (1Hz). This is also the best practice protocol in limited previous studies in this area. The hypothesis, based on previous findings, is that a group receiving rTMS treatment will experience a reduction in choreic movement rating scores when compared with their pre-treatment scores.	In addition, the study will extend investigation by applying a complete treatment set of 6 sessions of real treatment, putatively sufficient to induce long term potentiation effects. If such effect is shown, then a sham crossover trial will be continued to compare real and sham effects. The hypothesis is that real rTMS stimulation will be more effective in its long term effect, than the sham form. 
      The Statewide Department of Neurophysiology has experience in using rTMS in the treatment of depression. In addition, Dr Lee with the Huntingtons Study Group (HSG) at the Neurosciences Unit, Graylands Hospital has extensive experience with this patient population. Patients who attended that unit, who have choreic movements, and for whom the movements are especially intrusive or poorly controlled, will be offered the option of the rTMS trial. This is the rationale for an investigation that combines both fields in an assessment of rTMS as a treatment of choreic movements with Huntingtons disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>North Metropolitan Area Mental Health Services Human Research Ethics Committee (EC00273)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Gascoyne House, Graylands Hospital,
John XXIII Avenue
Mount Claremont WA 6010
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/09/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Joseph Lee</name>
      <address>The Statewide Department of Neurophysiology
Graylands Hospital
Brockway Road
Mount Claremont WA 6010</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9347 6801</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9384 5128</fax>
      <email>Joseph.Lee@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Greg Price</name>
      <address>Statewide Department of Neurophysiology
Gascoyne House, Graylands Hospital,
John XXIII Avenue
Mount Claremont WA 6010
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9347 6493</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9384 5128</fax>
      <email>Greg.Price@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Greg Price</name>
      <address>Statewide Department of Neurophysiology
Gascoyne House, Graylands Hospital,
John XXIII Avenue
Mount Claremont WA 6010
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 9347 6493</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 9384 5128</fax>
      <email>Greg.Price@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>