<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372742">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/04/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000569303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluating the role of a diary in new onset stress,anxiety, depression and post traumatic stress disorder in relatives of patients in the intensive care unit</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>
Psychological support for relatives of patients in the intensive care unit using diaries- an exploratory study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Post-traumatic Stress Disorder ( PTSD)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>ANXIETY</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Family members of 100 consecutive patients admitted to the Royal Adelaide Hospital
Intensive Care Unit and remaining in the unit for 48hrs or more will be identified.
On day 3 of admission family members will be approached by the research team and asked to identify a primary next of kin or decision maker. This person will then be approached to participate in the study.The study will be explained to them and they will be asked if they consent to participate. 

The diary is a free flowing manuscript that portrays the patients journey in a critical care environment. It has headings/ templates to be completed, and contains key points for the person writing in it. This is included under the title this is me and gives an opportunity for us to know the patient better. By divulging all possible information about the patient, we believe the relative is likely to be less stressed and this will hopefully impact on the incidence of PTSD. The diary does have a preamble and includes guidelines on how each entry should be written. 

The family members were given the opportunity to contribute to the diary with photographs, testimonials and vignettes. Medical input was limited unless specifically requested by the patients relative. The diary was identified as complete only if it had an entry on every day of their ICU stay either by the family member or by the nurse. Family members were given an opportunity to document in the diary retrospectively, if they were unable to be present on a particular day. 

During their stay in the ICU, the family members were encouraged to express their feelings in writing in the diary. At the time of discharge from the ICU, the diary was hand-delivered.by the Investigator to the designated family member. Family members who chose not to fill in diaries were compared to those who had. At 90 days post discharge of the patient from ICU, all the participants were telephoned to go through the IES-R and DASS21 questionnaires again.
A separate consent form will be provided. There will be a declination form given to the
consenting next of kin at the time of obtaining consent to give them the opportunity to
withdraw consent if their circumstances change. Even before the commencement of the
telephonic interview the interviewer will ask for a verbal consent before proceeding with
the questionnaire. In the event of the next of kin disagreeing to participate in the
interview, the interview will be abandoned.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome of this pragmatic study was to explore the feasibility of recruitment, assessed by review of study records to determine the proportion of eligible participants who complete the diary</outcome>
      <timepoint>11 months since commencement of the trial</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impact on depression assessed using DASS-21 scoring system</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post discharge from the ICU</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Impact on anxiety assessed using DASS-21 scoring system</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post discharge from ICU</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome of the study were to ascertain if there was an association between provision of an ICU diary and PTSD symptoms as defined by an Impact of Event Scales-Revised ( IES-R SCORE of &gt;33) .
This information would then provide us a baseline profile for future hypothesis testing on its impact</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post discharge</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) Inclusion criteria:
A relative who has been designated as the official next of kin for the patient and is aged &gt; 18 years of age
Expected stay of the patient in the RAH ICU &gt;48h
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>2)Exclusion criteria:
No identifiable relative or next of kin for the patient</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis
Statistical analyses were performed using SAS Version 9.3 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA). Continuous variables such as age, APACHE III and Injury Severity Scale  were generally not normally distributed and were therefore described by median and interquartile range. A Fishers exact test or a chi-square test was used to assess the association between survival and categorical variables. Wilcoxon rank sum tests were used to assess the association between survival and continuous variables. These tests were also used to assess the association of the presence/absence of intervention with other variables. p &lt;0.05 was considered significant. Logistic generalised estimating equations (GEE) models were used to get the average population values with adjustment for repeated measures, whilst testing the association between presence of PTSD and time period (controlling for completeness of diaries). 
 A logistic regression was performed to see how PTSD at follow-up (IES_R&gt;33) is associated with useful completion of the diary, controlling for PTSD at baseline. 
Univariate logistic regression was performed with the outcomes of intervention and survival versus various continuous predictors; results are reported as odds ratio (OR) and 95% confidence intervals. Univariate linear regression was used to investigate the association between IESR at 3 months and various predictors, adjusting baseline IESR  Stress at 3 months was also investigated in this manner, </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>25/05/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>60</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>24/08/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data analysis is complete</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr KRISHNASWAMY  SUNDARARAJAN</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Intensive Care Unit, Level 4, 

Robert Gerard Wing, Royal Adelaide Hospital

NORTH TERRACE

Adelaide. South Australia 5000
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide. South Australia 5000
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of this pragmatic study was to explore the role of an intensive care diary in the ICU, particularly with reference to the logistics of recruitment, potential acceptance of diaries amongst our patient population and its impact on anxiety, stress and depression. The secondary aims of the study were to ascertain if there was an association between provision of an ICU diary and PTSD symptoms which could then provide baseline profile for future hypothesis testing on its impact

Ethical approval for this study was obtained from the Royal Adelaide Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee 

HREC reference number: HREC/15/RAH/48

RAH Protocol No: 150216</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital   Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, Womens Health Centre
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, South Australia, 5000
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/05/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC reference number: HREC/15/RAH/48     RAH Protocol No: 150216</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/02/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Krishnaswamy Sundararajan</name>
      <address>Dr Krishnaswamy Sundararajan
Deputy Director, Intensive Care Unit, Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 4, ICU,  Robert Gerard Wing, Royal Adelaide Hospital
North terrace
Adelaide. South Australia 5000
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82220038</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>krishnaswamy.sundararajan@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Krishnaswamy Sundararajan</name>
      <address>Dr Krishnaswamy Sundararajan
Deputy Director, Intensive Care Unit, Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 4, ICU,  Robert Gerard Wing, Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide. South Australia 5000
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82220038</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>krishnaswamy.sundararajan@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Krishnaswamy Sundararajan</name>
      <address>Dr Krishnaswamy Sundararajan
Senior Clinical Lecturer, Discipline of Acute Care Medicine, University of Adelaide
Level 4, ICU,  Robert Gerard Wing, RAH
North Terrace
Adelaide. South Australia 5000
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82220038</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>krishnaswamy.sundararajan@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>