<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366068">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/03/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>7/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000363684</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Promoting healthy eating, active play and sustainability consciousness in early childhood curricula: Addressing the Ben10 (Trademark) problem.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of early childhood curriculum interventions on pre-school children's knowledge about healthy eating, active play and sustainability consciousness.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Childhood obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Pre-school teachers to develop a curriculum intervention that integrates content knowledge about healthy eating, active play and sustainability consciousness. Each teachers curriculum intervention will be workshopped to ensure they have included the following components: 1) implementing the interventions over a period of 3-4 weeks to build a solid portfolio of experiences and strong base for childrens discussions; 2) implementing the interventions in the morning when the children are most cognitively alert; 3) combining both whole group and small group experiences and discussions; 4) using real world props/resources, such as cereal boxes, McDonalds Happy Meal (Trademark) boxes and toys and merchandise; and 5) maintaining assessment records of childrens learning using Learning Stories, observation and documentation. Teachers will be provided with an Intervention Implementation Checklist and asked to record all components/elements associated with their curriculum interventions including: date, time, and duration of the intervention; the number of times the intervention or iterations of the intervention were implemented; Early Years Learning Framework Learning Outcomes aligned with the intervention; complete description of the intervention (including any resources/props used) and examples of any approaches to assessing childrens learning  used in relation to the intervention. A booster session of 1 day duration, will be conducted 6 weeks after teachers implement their curriculum interventions whereby children will be exposed to an abridged version of the intervention. </interventions>
    <comparator>The wait-list control group children will receive usual care, that is, their usual teaching and learning experiences as designed by participating educators. Qualitative and quantitative measures will be administered at the same time points as the intervention group. The teachers and children in this group will be offered the intervention at 7 months post baseline assessment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Childrens knowledge about healthy eating, active play and the sustainability consequences of their food and toy selections.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Semi-structured interview with children at baseline, the end of the intervention and 6 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite secondary outcomes consisting of childrens food preferences, digital media viewing and physical activity habits.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Eating and Physical Activity Questionnaire (EPAQ) completed by parents at baseline, the end of the intervention and 6 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children aged 4-5 year old who attend preschool together with their English speaking parents. The children will be in their final year of preschool.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>4</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>5</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Children not aged 4-5 years.
Children not attending preschool programs.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Stratified allocation based on age of child and preschool attendance.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We calculated the sample size necessary to detect a clinically meaningful difference in vegetable consumption, significant at the 0.05 level, with a power of 0.8; this calculation resulted in a sample of 150 children in each group. Making a prudent allowance for attrition of 20% (based on our previous research with preschool children and their parents), the adjusted number per treatment condition is 180. A total of 360 4 year old children will therefore be recruited. This sample size is also sufficient to detect medium effect sizes in both the primary and secondary measures with a power of .8 at a is equal to 0.05 (Cohen, 1992). Our formative work indicated a potential 11% attrition rate. Making a prudent allowance for attrition of up to 20%, 360 4-5 year old children and their parents will therefore be recruited and the adjusted number of preschools per study arm is likely to be 18 (i.e. a total of 36 kindergartens in 18 pairs).
Baseline quantitative data (collected from parents) will be secured prior to treatment allocation, missing values will be scrutinized to check for non-random distribution and primary analyses will be executed twice: once using observed data, and once using multiple imputations under multivariate normal assumptions, so that all participants will be analysed in their allocated condition. Analyses of variance (with corrections for potential clustering effects of individuals within childcare centres) will test the between group differences in the primary outcome measure (childrens knowledge about healthy eating, active play and the sustainability consequences of their food and toy selections; interview data will be quantified, after each childs interview has been transcribed, for the analyses) and the secondary outcome measures (child eating and activity habits) at each assessment time point and across time points for the children. The teachers qualitative interviews 6 months post intervention will be analysed using elements of phenomenology and thematic content analysis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>1/07/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deakin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>221 Burwood Highway
Burwood
Victoria 3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 2, 11 Lancaster Place
Majura Park ACT 2609
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Australian Catholic University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>115 Victoria Parade 
Fitzroy Victoria 3065</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Southern Cross University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Military Road
East Lismore NSW 2480</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This paper details the research protocol for a study funded by the Australian Research Council. An integrated approach towards helping young children respond to the significant pressures of 360 degree marketing on their food choices, levels of active play, and sustainability consciousness via the early childhood curriculum is lacking. The overall goal of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of curriculum interventions that educators design when using a pedagogical communication strategy on childrens knowledge about healthy eating, active play and the sustainability consequences of their toy food and toy selections. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee (DUHREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>221 Burwood Highway
Burwood
Victoria 3125 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/10/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013-220</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/09/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Skouteris</name>
      <address>Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood
Victoria 3125 </address>
      <phone>+61 03 9251 7699</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>helen.skouteris@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Skouteris</name>
      <address>Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood
Victoria 3125 </address>
      <phone>+61 03 9251 7699</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>helen.skouteris@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Helen Skouteris</name>
      <address>Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood
Victoria 3125 </address>
      <phone>+61 03 9251 7699</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>helen.skouteris@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Mandy O'Connor</name>
      <address>Deakin University
221 Burwood Highway
Burwood
Victoria 3125 </address>
      <phone>+61 0407 162 639</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mandy.oconnor@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>