<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372139">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/01/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000452392</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Core muscles strengthening for balance and gait performance in individuals with chronic stroke</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Core muscles strengthening for balance and gait performance in individuals with chronic stroke</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic stroke</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Balance disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will receive 6-weeks core muscle strengthening. Core muscle strengthening contains bracing exercise that is to activate the deeper core muscles particularly which is important components in core muscles strengthening exercises. Bracing exercise are performed by pushing the abdomen out externally. Participants should hold the breath and "brace" abdominal muscles. About the trial, bracing exercise includes bracing with heel slides, bracing with leg lifts, bracing with bridging, quadruped arm lifts with bracing, and quadruped leg lifts with bracing. Participants need to learn how to contract local muscle accurately in those different bracing exercise. If deeper core muscles have been activated, core muscles strengthening can be conducted continually. Exercises have some steps, as follow: (Gymnic Physio Ball will be used in the exercises)
1. Warm-up: participants step on Swiss ball in sitting position for 1 minutes
2. Bridge exercise: hold position for 5 seconds. Perform 10 repetitions for 1 set
3. Bridge exercise with legs crossed, Hold this position for 5 seconds. Perform 10 repetitions for 1 set
4. Bridge exercise with one leg. Hold this position for 3 seconds. Perform 10 repetitions for 1 sets
5. Curl-ups with straight reaching. Hold this position for 3 seconds. Perform 10 repetitions for 1 set
6. Curl-ups with diagonal reaching. Hold this position for 3 seconds. Perform 10 repetitions for 1 set
7. Patient sit on Swiss ball and combine with pelvis anterior tilt. Hold this position for 5 seconds. Perform 15 repetitions for 1 set.
8. Patient sit on Swiss ball and combine with pelvis posterior tilt. Hold this position for 5 seconds. Perform 15 repetitions for 1 set.
9. Supine on Swiss ball with feet on the floor. Hold this position for 10 seconds. Perform 10 repetitions for 1 sets.
10.Patient prone on Swiss ball and combine with trunk extension. Hold this position for 5 seconds. Perform 10 repetitions for 1 sets
11. Cool-down: patient sit on Swiss ball and step on the ball for 1 minutes
Sessions will be delivered by a certificated physiotherapist. Training frequency will be core muscles strengthening for 20 min and treadmill walking training with comfortable speed for 10 min per session, 2 sessions per week for a total of 6 weeks. It will be individual one-on-one sessions taking place in Balance training center in Yang Ming university All participants will be supervised by certified physiotherapist in the exercises program. If participants don't know how to conduct, physiotherapist will use manual contact to teach them. And, demonstrate the repeated exercise. </interventions>
    <comparator>Control group receive 6-weeks conventional training: . (same format as intervention group except for the exercise component)
1. Lower extremity strengthening 
2. Sit to stand 
3. Weight shifting to affected lower extremity
4. Stretching ankle plantarflexors
5. Walking training for 10 mins
Participants will be instructed by physiotherapist in individual one-on-one and the sessions are taking place in Balance training center in Yang Ming university. Training frequency will be 30 min per session, 2 sessions per week for a total of 6 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Limit of stability by SMART Balance Master, NeuroCom International, Inc., USA</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be assessed within one week before and after the 6-week intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Spatial-temporal parameters of gait by GAITRite system</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be assessed within one week before and after the 6-week intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Trunk muslce strength by hand-held dynamometer, Power Track II, Jtech Medical Company, USA</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be assessed within one week before and after the 6-week intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Stroke &gt;6 months
Trunk impairment scale &lt; 23
Can walk &gt; 15 meters independently with or without assistive device 
 Mini-mental state examination (MMSE) &gt; 24
Brunnstrome stage &gt; IV ( Lower extremity )
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>20</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Have any musculoskeletal problem
Visual, and language problems </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>10/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <state>Taipei</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>National Yang-Ming University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>No.155, Sec.2, Linong Street, Taipei, 112 Taiwan, R.O.C.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Yang-Ming University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>No.155, Sec.2, Linong Street, Taipei, 112 Taiwan, R.O.C.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background and purpose: Core muscles are a key part of our body and play an important role in providing stability for balance and gait. Individuals with stroke often suffer from balance and gait problems even in the chronic stage. Core muscles strengthening exercise has been reported to be beneficial for balance and trunk control. However, few studies investigated core muscles strengthening for the gait symmetry, quantitative dynamic balance performance in chronic stroke patients. Thus, the aim of this study is to investigate the effects of core muscles strengthening in chronic stroke patients for balance performance and gait symmetry.
Methods: This is a single-blinded, randomized controlled trial study. Forty subjects meeting the criteria will be recruited and be randomized to the core muscle strengthening training group or conventional training group. The training for each group will be 30 minutes each time, twice a week for 6 weeks. Primary outcomes include balance performance as indicated by limit of stability, directional control and maximum excursion, measured by Balance Master and gait performance as indicated by gait speed, temporal and spatial symmetry measured by GAITRite system. Secondary outcome include  trunk muscle strength measured by dynamometer. All outcomes will be assessed before (pretest) and after (post-test) the 6-week training program.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>National Yang-Ming University Office of Research and Development</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>National Yang-Ming University, 155, Sec. 2, Li-Nong Street,
Shih-Pai, Taipei, Taiwan.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>YM105062F</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Chen, Chiao-Ju</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy and Assistive Technology, National Yang-Ming University
No.155, Sec.2, Linong Street, Taipei, 112 Taiwan, R.O.C.</address>
      <phone>+886-963022715</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>crb81230635@yahoo.com.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Wang, Ray-Yau</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy and Assistive Technology, National Yang-Ming University
No.155, Sec.2, Linong Street, Taipei, 112 Taiwan, R.O.C.</address>
      <phone>+886-2-28267210</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rywang@ym.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Wang, Ray-Yau</name>
      <address>Department of Physical Therapy and Assistive Technology, National Yang-Ming University
No.155, Sec.2, Linong Street, Taipei, 112 Taiwan, R.O.C.</address>
      <phone>+886-2-28267210</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>rywang@ym.edu.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>