<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83128">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/09/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000465358</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Self-guided Internet based education for social phobia: A randomized controlled study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A comparison of self-guided Internet based education for social phobia with automatic reminders vs. telephone reminders: A randomized controlled trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Social phobia (an anxiety disorder)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two groups:  1) Self-guided Internet based education for social phobia with automatic email and sms reminders, or; 2) self-guided Internet based education for social phobia with automatic email and sms reminders, and weekly telephone reminders from an administrative assistant.  

All participants will meet Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 4th Edition (DSM-IV) criteria for social phobia.

All participants will complete 6 lessons of Internet based education about management of symptoms of social phobia.  One lesson will be completed every 7 to 10 days.  Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to complete.  Participants will also have access to summaries of each lesson, and will read anonymous stories about other people with social phobia, taking a further 20 minutes per summary.  Participants in Group 1 will receive weekly emails and fortnightly sms reminder messages to continue with the program.  Participants in group 2 will receive weekly emails and fortnightly sms reminder messages as well as weekly telephone reminders from a research assistant.  The duration of each phone call is expected to be 2 minutes.  The duration of the program is 8 weeks, but participants will be contacted 6 months post program and asked to complete follow-up questionnaires.  

Study questionnaires will be administered at application, pre-education, post-education, and at 6-months post-education.   These will take about 20 minutes to complete.

The educational materials are based on the Shyness Program, which applies cognitive behavioural techniques.</interventions>
    <comparator>Self-guided Internet based education for social phobia with automatic email and SMS reminders.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social phobia is measured by the Social Phobia Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at application, pre-education, post-education, and at 6-months post-education.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social phobia is measured by the Social Interaction Anxiety Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at application, pre-education, post-education, and at 6-months post-education.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Symptoms and severity of depression is measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at application, pre-education, post-education, and at 6-months post-education.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress is measured by the Kessler-10 (K-10)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at application, pre-education, post-education, and at 6-months post-education.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability is measured by the World Health Organisation Disability Assessment Schedule II</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at application, pre-education, post-education, and at 6-months post-education.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generalised anxiety is measured by the Generalised Anxiety Disorder 7-Item Scale (GAD-7)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at application, pre-education, post-education, and at 6-months post-education.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Meet DSM-IV criteria for social phobia - Internet access + printer access. - Australian citizen- Males and females- Active pulse.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current substance abuse/dependence- Psychotic disorder- Current or planned psychological treatment during study duration- Change in medications during last 1 month or intended change during study duration.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants apply on line, followed by a telephone interview to confirm diagnosis via structured diagnostic interview (MINI 5.0.0). Participants will be randomized using a list generated prior to the study. Allocation concealment will occur by contacting the holder of the allocation schedule who is off-site.</concealment>
    <sequence>A randomisation list will be generated prior to the study using computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>6/10/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/10/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>6/12/2008</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>170</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>170</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales at St Vincent's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>299 Forbes Street
Darlinghurst
NSW2010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>School of Psychiatry, University of New South Wales at St Vincent's Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>299 Forbes Street
Darlinghurst
NSW2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project is part of a research program examining the efficacy of Internet based education and treatment programs for people with social phobia.  This project compares the effectiveness of different types of reminders at encouraging people with social phobia to complete the 6 lessons in the Program.  We expect that people who receive telephone reminders (in addition to weekly emails and fortnightly smss) will complete more lessons and report more benefit from the program than participants who do not receive the weekly phone call (but who do receive the email and sms reminders).</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.climateclinic.tv</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Titov, N, Andrews G, Schwencke G, Drobny, J, &amp; Einstein D.  (2008).  Shyness 1: Distance treatment for social over the Internet.  A randomized controlled trial.  Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry, 42, 585-594.

Titov, N, Andrews G, &amp; Schwencke G.  (2008).  Shyness 2: A replication of Shyness 1.  Are the results reliable, and who benefits?  Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry, 42, 595-605.

Titov, N, Andrews, G, Choi, I, Schwencke, G.  (In press).  Shyness 3:  An RCT of guided versus unguided Internet based CBT for social phobia.  Australian and New Zealand Journal of Psychiatry.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>UNSW
Kensington Campus
NSW2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/09/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08230</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic
Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
Talavera Road, North Ryde, NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Dr Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic
Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
Talavera Road, North Ryde, NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic
Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
Talavera Road, North Ryde, NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Nickolai Titov</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic
Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology
Macquarie University
Talavera Road, North Ryde, NSW 2109</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9850 9901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nick.titov@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>