<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373231">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001095358p</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase I, randomised, double blind, placebo-controlled, single ascending dose study to evaluate the safety and tolerability of allogeneic adipose-derived mesenchymal stem cells injected into patients with osteoarthritis of the knee.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase I, single centre, randomised, double blind, placebo-controlled, single ascending dose (SAD) study to evaluate the safety and tolerability of allogeneic adipose-derived mesenchymal stem cells (MAG200) administered by intra-articular injection to patients with symptomatic osteoarthritis of the knee.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1198-6900</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Magellan Biologicals Pty Ltd, MSC-OAK-001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Investigational Product MAG200 is a preparation of allogeneic human adipose-derived mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) in sterile, clinical grade injectable isotonic solution. 
Participants will receive a single dose of Investigational Product (MAG200 / placebo) which will be administered by intra-articular injection into the study knee. 
Up to 40 eligible subjects will be randomised into the study in four sequential cohorts.  Each cohort will comprise 10 subjects, who will be randomised in a 4 to 1 ratio to active or placebo treatment arms (i.e. 8 active: 2 placebo). Dosing will commence at the lowest dose level of MAG200. An internal Safety Review Team (SRT) will be established to  review safety data of the previous cohort to determine if dose escalation to the next dose level is recommended.  A maximum of 4 dose levels of MAG200 will be studied: 10 million cells, 20 million cells, 50 million cells and 100 million cells.</interventions>
    <comparator>The Placebo solution will contain sterile, clinical grade injectable isotonic solution. 
Placebo will be administered as a single dose via intra-articular injection into the study knee. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety and tolerability of MAG200 is the primary outcome. It will be assessed by monitoring adverse events, conducting physical examination, vital signs, ECG, clinical laboratory data and concomitant medication usage.
This is the first time that MAG200 has been given to humans before so possible adverse events are unknown. However based on prior experience with autologous MSC injections, potential adverse events may include pain, swelling and stiffness of the joint into which the Investigative Product has been injected. Study visits will include a physical exam, collection of subject reported adverse events and concomitant medication usage to monitor for these possible side effects or others not yet known of.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Changes from Baseline to End of Study (Month 3/Day 84).
Physical exam and vital signs will be assessed at Days 0, 7, 14, 28 and month 3.
ECG will be performed at Days 0, 28 and month 3.
Clinical laboratory testing will be assessed at Days 0, 7, 28 and month 3.
Adverse events and concomitant medication use will be captured and assessed from Day 0 to month 3.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Not applicable</outcome>
      <timepoint>Not applicable</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>i) Body mass index BMI must be 'greater than or equal' to 19.0 kg/m2 and 'less than or equal to' 35.0 kg/m2; 
ii) A documented diagnosis of osteoarthritis (Grade 2 or Grade 3) of the study knee</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>i) MRI-confirmed displaced meniscal tear, ligament deficiency or generalised Grade 4 chondral loss in the study knee.
ii) History of or suspected infective or inflammatory joint disorders.
iii) Joint surgery within 3 years prior to study start.
iv) Females who are pregnant or planning a pregnancy during the following 12 months.
v) Any contraindication to intra-articular injection.
vi) Any contraindication to an X-ray or MRI of the study knee.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation to treatment group is concealed ie. the Investigator / delegate who determines if a person is eligible for inclusion into the study, does not have any influence over, or knowledge of the Investigational Product (IP) the participant is administered. 
Eligible subjects will be allocated a Randomisation Number in order of their entry into the study. The Investigator will simply apply the next available Randomisation Number to each subject at the time of entry. The unblinded laboratory technicians will then prepare the IP according to the randomisation schedule. The prepared IP is masked (see details below) and provided to the study site for administration. The unblinded laboratory technicians are independent of the conduct of the study at the study site. </concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated randomisation schedule will be prepared by a statistician prior to the start of the study. The randomisation schedule will be provided to the site by the study statistician. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Due to differences in appearance between the MAG200 suspension and Placebo solution, two unblinded laboratory technicians, independent of the study conduct, will prepare the syringes of study treatment. The syringes will be covered with black plastic to prevent the identification of the injectable material. Syringes will be over-labelled, with each syringe identifiable by the unique Subject Randomisation Number only. </designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>No formal sample size calculation will be performed for this study. The sample sizes chosen for this study are based on clinical and regulatory considerations and precedence for first-in-human studies, and have no formal statistical basis. The number of subjects proposed is considered sufficient for this initial study to explore the safety and tolerability of MAG200 in patients with OA of the knee.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/11/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Magellan Biologicals Pty Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>c/- Minter Ellison
525 Collins Street
Melbourne  3000
Victoria</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Magellan Biologicals Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>c/- Minter Ellison
525 Collins Street
Melbourne  3000
Victoria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This Phase I, dose escalation trial will evaluate the safety and tolerability of Magellan Biologicals allogeneic (obtained from a donor) adipose-derived mesenchymal stem cells (MAG200) when injected into the knees of patients with osteoarthritis of the knee. This is the first time MAG200 will be given to human subjects who are not genetically related to the donor of the stem cells. Up to 40 volunteers aged between 18-65 years, will be enrolled. A maximum of four dose levels of MAG200 will be tested with 10 subjects in each dose level cohort; 8 subjects receiving MAG200 and 2 receiving placebo. The subjects and study team will not know which treatment a subject receives. Dosing will commence at the lowest dose level of MAG200 and a Safety Review Team will review the safety data of each dose level cohort before allowing progression to the next dose level to occur.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Submitted, not yet approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Charles Sturt University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Executive Officer
Human Research Ethics Committee
Charles Sturt University
Locked Bag 588
Wagga Wagga NSW 2678</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/07/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Julien Freitag</name>
      <address>Melbourne Stem Cell Centre
116-118 Thames St
Box Hill North
Vic 3128</address>
      <phone> +61 3 9270 8000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>info@mscc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Peter Hansen</name>
      <address>Magellan Biologicals Pty Ltd
c/- Minter Ellison
525 Collins Street
Melbourne  3000
Victoria</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9787 0102</phone>
      <fax> +61 3 8672 5928</fax>
      <email>trials@magellanstemcells.com.a</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Julien Freitag</name>
      <address>Melbourne Stem Cell Centre
116-118 Thames St
Box Hill North
Vic 3128</address>
      <phone> +61 3 9270 8000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>info@mscc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Penelope Amor</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+61 (0)409 195 270</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peneamor@mitchellcc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>