<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366477">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/06/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/09/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000969662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Phonological Treatment of Arabic-Speaking Children in Kuwait (Kuwaiti/ Gulf Area dialect)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In Arabic speaking children will phonological intervention improve speech intelligibility on treated sounds in comparison to untreated sounds?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Speech disorders/ Phonological disorders</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This single case experimental design study will provide phonological therapy which has been shown to be effective in English in Arabic. The therapy is a traditional faceto-face session with speech pathologist. Each child will have individually selected treatment targets addressed in a behavioural intervention as per standard speech pathology clinical practice. Treatment will be provided three times per week for 10 weeks for one hour per session- a maximum  total of 30 hours of therapy.</interventions>
    <comparator>The research is using a multiple baselines within participants design so 
some sounds will be treated and others will be held in reserve 
(untreated) but measured to show that they do not change. If the 
treated sounds change and the untreated ones do not then we will have 
demonstrated both experimental control and treatment efficacy. 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome measure: Percentage Consonant Correct Pre-Treatment and Post-Treatment. Assessment tool is standardized language assessment which will provide us with the child's speech repertoire.  
Test name: A 58-word picture naming Arabic articulation test will be used to evoke responses representing the initial, medial, and final consonants of Arabic (Amayreh, 2000).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>The child's speech will be assessed prior and post treatment to assess change. Since the study is a multiple baseline design, some children will have more baselines than others, and therefore, the post treatment assessment will be at least after 12 weeks and maximum after 14 weeks. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>The inclusion criteria will include monolingual Arabic-Kuwaiti speaking children who have identified/ or suspected to have a phonological/speech impairment without having any known concomitant difficulties such as hearing loss, cleft-lip/ or palate, stuttering, or neurological impairment.  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>7</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Non Arabic speaker children.
Bilingual children 
Other medical conditions that effect speech such as :hearing loss, cleft-lip/ or palate, stuttering, or neurological impairment. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed 
</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>This is a multiple baselines within participant design study. Each participant will start at different time while the others will continue to come to clinic to collect baseline from them. In this case we will have different baselines from each client to help us assess change due treatment. 
</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>It is difficult to determine what sample size is needed from previous research as studies on phonological contrast therapy available in the published research literature all have recruitment samples ranging between 1-6 participants. Only three cross-linguistic studies have used phonological contrast therapy with the following languages and number of participants; Cantonese with one participant only, Turkish with two participants only, and Portuguese with 14 participants. The research team has agreed on this particular size as the sample size depending on the availability of clients in Kuwait, and the ability to manage and control the study in the time frame given. Moreover, this sample size is adequate to provide statistical information regarding the effect size by using d statistic from Cohen (1988) as calculated by Busk and Serlin, 1992. 

According to Beeson &amp; Robey, 2006, any new treatment study is best to be examined in small number of clients to observe treatment effect. Therefore, this is a phase one study that we hope will answer if phonological contrast therapy applied in Arabic is effective or not. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>25/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/03/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>31/03/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>5</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Kuwait</country>
      <state>Kuwait</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Kuwait University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kuwait University 
Cultural Relations Office 
P.O Box 5969, Safat 13060, Kuwait</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Kuwait</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Kuwait University </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Kuwait University 
Cultural Relations Office 
P.O Box 5969, Safat 13060, Kuwait</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Kuwait</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim:
The primary concern of the proposed study is to investigate the efficacy and the ability to apply the phonological contrast therapy approach in Arabic, and to evaluate the effect of the phonological contrast therapy approach on speech accuracy and consistency of word production for children with consistent speech-sound disorder in Arabic. 
Hypothesis:
Arabic speaking children with speech disorders will benefit from contrast therapy approach delivered in Arabic Language.
Background information:
Treating consistent speech disorders in children with phonological contrast therapy has proven its efficacy in English (Baker &amp; McLeod, 2011). According to the literature, there are four major contrastive approaches for treating speech disorders: minimal pairs (Weiner, 1981), multiple oppositions (Williams, 2000 &amp; 2003), maximal oppositions (Gierut, 1990) and empty set (Gierut, 1991). The positive benefits of these treatments have been widely documented. Moreover, there are some studies that focused on comparing between these treatment types in an attempt to find out which method is the most effective one (Gierut, 2001) which reflected the complexity of the population. According to Crosbie et.al (2005), phonological contrast approaches target speech error patterns and help with recognizing a childs linguistic system in order to increase recognition of the similarities and differences of sounds and how these mark differences in meaning. Overall, most of the research that investigated the efficacy of the phonological contrast therapy approach resulted in children with consistent errors benefiting most from phonological contrast therapy. The pilot study on a single case study design has revealed some interesting results including a significant improvement with childs production accuracy following treatment presented in minimal pairs in Arabic. However, the data elicited from the pilot study is very preliminary as there is no available literature provides any information regarding speech treatment in Arabic. More sample size is required to validate the effectiveness of the treatment in monolingual Arabic speaking children.  
Method:
Recruitment
Participants will be recruited from the patients waiting list in Salem Al-Ali Centre for Speech and Hearing in Kuwait, and from Hospital of Natural Medicine. 
Participants
This study will involve 20 children of ages 3-7. The inclusion criteria will include monolingual Arabic-Kuwaiti speaking children who have identified/ or suspected to have a phonological/speech impairment without having any known concomitant difficulties such as hearing loss, cleft-lip/ or palate, stuttering, or neurological impairment.  
Procedures:
The participants will complete the following assessments test in order to fulfill the inclusion criteria: Receptive language assessment using an Arabic Standardized version of Peabody Picture Vocabulary Test  (Abu Alam &amp; Hadi, 1998); oral motor screening test from the Diagnostic Evaluation of Articulation and Phonology test (Dodd, Hua, Crosbie, Holm, &amp; Ozanne, 2002) ; and pure-tone hearing screening (ASHA, 1997). A 58-word picture naming Arabic articulation test will be used to evoke responses representing the initial, medial, and final consonants of Arabic Lebanese dialect (Amayreh, 2000).  These tests will be conducted in Salem Al-Ali centre and the at the Hospital of Natural Medicine. The tests will be conducted over 2 sessions. Parents will be encouraged to observe these sessions from the associated observation rooms.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Sydney Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Office
Margaret Telfer Building (K07)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/01/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013/921</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Manal Alsaad</name>
      <address>75 East St, Lidcombe NSW 2141, Australia
The University of sydney, Rm S153, Cumberland Campus, The University of Sydney, Lidcombe NSW , 1825</address>
      <phone>+61450048055</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mals1486@uni.sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Patricia McCabe</name>
      <address>Rm S153, Cumberland Campus , The University of Sydney  Lidcombe NSW . 1825

Faculty of Health Sciences
Cumberland Campus C42
75 East Street</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9747</phone>
      <fax> +61 2 9351 9173 </fax>
      <email>tricia.mccabe@sydney.edu.au  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Patricia McCabe</name>
      <address>Rm S153, Cumberland Campus, The University of Sydney  Lidcombe NSW  1825

Faculty of Health Sciences
Cumberland Campus C42
75 East Street</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 9747</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tricia.mccabe@sydney.edu.au  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>