<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373329">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001182381</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Treatment of alcohol dependent patients at-risk for subclinical Wernicke-Korsakoff syndrome</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Treatment of alcohol dependent patients at-risk for subclinical Wernicke-Korsakoff syndrome: effect of thiamine dosage on neurological and cognitive symptoms</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1199-4826</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>1011141 (NHMRC Grant ID)</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alcohol use disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Wernicke-Korsakoff syndrome (WKS)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Thiamine Hydrochloride

Day one of trial
Patient admitted for inpatient detoxification for alcohol withdrawal.
Eligible patients randomly allocated to one of two groups (see below for group descriptions).
Participant completes baseline neurological and cognitive assessment, as well as screening questionnaires regarding alcohol use and mental health.
On same day, but only after baseline assessment, participant receives first dose of thiamine treatment.

Day two
Participant receives second dose of thiamine.

Day three
Participant receives third dose of thiamine.
On same day, but only after third and final dose of thiamine, participant repeats neurological and cognitive assessment.

Two groups, randomly allocated.
Group 1 (Standard dose group): 300mg once daily for three days, intravenous infusion.
Group 2 (High dose group): 1,000mg once daily for three days, intravenous infusion.

For both groups, thiamine will be added to 100ml of normal saline and infused over 1 hour.  Thiamine hydrochloride provided by St Vincents Hospital as part of routine care.  Thiamine administered by nursing staff who are not members of the research team and who are blind to dose amount.</interventions>
    <comparator>Group 1 (Standard dose group  see above) serves as the control group.</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison between Standard and High dose groups on cognitive measures.
Cognitive measure (i): Working memory  Digit span task, which is a modified version of the Wechsler Adult Intelligence Scale Fourth Edition (WAIS-IV) Digit Span subtest.  Modified so that each item contains three, rather than two, trials.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 baseline (prior to treatment) and Day 3 (after all treatments)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison between Standard and High dose groups on neurological signs.
Neurological signs (i): Eye movement abnormalities total score  derived from a structured quantitative neurologic examination based on the Ataxia Staging and Scoring system (Pourcher &amp; Barbeau, 1980) and previously validated by members of the research team for the evaluation of neurological impairment in drug and alcohol-related cognitive impairment and encephalopathies (Cairney et al., 2004; Wood et al., 1986).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 baseline (prior to treatment) and Day 3 (after all treatments)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Comparison between Standard and High dose groups on neurological signs.
Neurological signs (ii): Ataxia total score  derived from same structured neurologic examination.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 baseline (prior to treatment) and Day 3 (after all treatments)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Additional primary outcome.
Comparison between Standard and High dose groups on cognitive measures.
Cognitive measure (ii): Anterograde memory  Wechsler Memory Scale Fourth Edition (WMS-IV) Logical Memory subtest.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 1 baseline (prior to treatment) and Day 3 (after all treatments)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Alcohol dependent patients presenting to Depaul House residential withdrawal unit.
Meet DSM-IV criteria for Alcohol dependence or alcohol abuse, as assessed with the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI) version 6.0.0 (Sheehan &amp; Lecrubier, 2009).
Consumption of at least six standard drinks daily for a period of at least three months.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Difficulties with language comprehension.
Significant pre-existing cognitive impairment due to a cause other than alcohol abuse or dependence.
Recent regular use of any non-prescription drug other than alcohol.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The order of allocation is determined by a randomisation chart.  This chart is kept in an opaque envelope and is not seen by those involved in assessing for eligibility or recruitment.  The holder of the allocation schedule, who is “on-site”, checks the schedule only after recruitment is made.</concealment>
    <sequence>Non-stratified, blocked randomisation  using large block sizes of either 10 or 20 in size and randomly varied to maximise unpredictability.  The allocation ratio per block was 1:1.  An online true random number generator was used to select order of block sizes and treatment allocation sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Power analysis sought to detect a minimal experimental effect that will lead to a clinically useful outcome.  Small but clinically useful effects have been described as corresponding to a difference between groups of about one-half of one standard deviation or a Cohens d of .5 (Cohen, 1988; Wolf &amp; Cornell, 1986).  This cautious estimate is also in line with the effect observed in our previous study (Ambrose, Bowden, &amp; Whelan, 2001).  Power calculations based on two treatment groups indicate n=70 per group and a univariate analysis of variance model with one response variable are required for adequate design power to have a high chance (.9 or greater) of rejecting the null hypothesis (at alpha = .05) of no difference between means (GPower: Faul et al., 2009).  Therefore we will aim to collect 140 participants in total.

Outcome measures to be analysed with univariate analysis of variance with dose as the independent variable.  Dependent variables include working memory, anterograde memory, eye movement abnormalities total score, and ataxia total score.  A number-needed-to-treat analysis will also be conducted with intention-to-treat corrections.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>19/02/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/11/2018</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>140</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>116</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>2/12/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Stephen Bowden</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Melbourne School of Psychological Sciences
Redmond Barry Building
UNIVERSITY OF MELBOURNE VIC 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>414 La Trobe St
Melbourne VIC 3000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of Melbourne</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Melbourne School of Psychological Sciences
Redmond Barry Building
UNIVERSITY OF MELBOURNE VIC 3010</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Wernicke-Korsakoff syndrome (WKS) is a neurological disorder caused by thiamine deficiency associated with alcohol dependence or other causes of malnutrition. Although WKS is a common condition, there are currently no universally accepted, national or international, evidence-based guidelines for thiamine dosing for the treatment of either acute symptomatic WKS or for prevention of subclinical WKS-related brain damage in at-risk people. WKS is most commonly seen in alcohol dependent people who therefore constitute a major at-risk population. In the absence of agreed treatment guidelines, different clinical groups or hospital settings tend to maintain their own protocols based on experience or tradition, and in general the dosage levels of thiamine prescribed in Australia for symptomatic WKS varies from lower doses (100-300mg daily) to higher doses (1000mg daily). Australian Department of Health and Aging treatment guidelines recommend 300mg per day for at risk patients (DoHA, 2009). The main aim of this study is to evaluate whether high dose (1000mg daily) thiamine is more effective than Australian standard dose (300mg daily) thiamine for treating subclinical WKS-related brain damage in at-risk alcohol dependent patients admitted for management of their alcohol dependence. The study has direct implications for how this common condition should be treated in the future.

In this study, patients will not have acute symptomatic WKS, rather, they will be alcohol dependent patients at risk of subclinical WKS-related brain damage. Patients will be treated as per usual hospital protocols, except that they will be randomly allocated to one of two treatment groups that differ only on dosage amount of thiamine (300mg or 1000mg per day for 3 days) administered via intravenous (IV) infusion. All patients admitted to Depaul House and receiving treatment as usual for alcohol withdrawal would routinely have received at least 3 days of thiamine (200mg x two times per day administered intramuscularly) as part of that treatment.

Baseline measures, to be obtained before treatment on day 1 and outcome measures obtained after treatment on day 3, include structured examinations of mental health and neurological symptoms, particularly signs associated with WKS such as lack of coordination and irregularity of muscle movement (ataxia) and abnormal eye movements (nystagmus, ophthalmoplegia). Cognitive function will be assessed via standardised tests of working memory and anterograde memory. All participants will receive full hospital care during and after data collection, as per usual hospital protocols for such patients.

It was hypothesised that higher doses of parenteral thiamine (1000 mg daily) will lead to greater improvements in specific aspects of cognition and neurological function than lower doses (300mg) in alcohol dependent patients undergoing alcohol withdrawal who are at risk for subclinical WKS-related brain damage.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St Vincent's Hospital Melbourne Human Research Ethics Committee D</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Governance Unit
Level 5
Mary Aikenhead Building
27 Victoria Parade
FITZROY VIC 3065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/11/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>117/11</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/10/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen Bowden</name>
      <address>Melbourne School of Psychological Sciences
Redmond Barry Building
UNIVERSITY OF MELBOURNE VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 6373</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6618</fax>
      <email>sbowden@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen Bowden</name>
      <address>Melbourne School of Psychological Sciences
Redmond Barry Building
UNIVERSITY OF MELBOURNE VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 6373</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6618</fax>
      <email>sbowden@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen Bowden</name>
      <address>Melbourne School of Psychological Sciences
Redmond Barry Building
UNIVERSITY OF MELBOURNE VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 6373</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6618</fax>
      <email>sbowden@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Stephen Bowden</name>
      <address>Melbourne School of Psychological Sciences
Redmond Barry Building
UNIVERSITY OF MELBOURNE VIC 3010</address>
      <phone>+61 3 8344 6373</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9347 6618</fax>
      <email>sbowden@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>