<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372612">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000544370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Embedding High Intensity Interval Training (HIIT) into the school day: The Burn 2 Learn pilot trial for senior school students</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A scalable intervention for increasing vigorous physical activity among older adolescents: The Burn 2 Learn pilot trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>B2L</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Mental health (i.e., psychological distress)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>cardiovascular disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the cardiovascular system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Burn 2 Learn intervention will involve the following intervention components and implementation strategies:

1) Accredited teacher professional learning workshop: 1 x full day (5 hours) workshop will be conducted for intervention group teachers identified and recruited as Burn 2 Learn 'school champions. The workshop will provide a rationale for the intervention, including up to date evidence of the benefits of vigorous physical activity for cognitive and mental health, as well as the roles and responsibilities of school champions.

2) Introductory seminar: will be delivered to Principals and teachers (20 min)  by the research team. The seminars will focus on the latest evidence regarding physical activity, fitness and academic achievement. The seminars will include video files with testimonies from experts in physical activity and cognition.

3) Peer leader training and student introduction session: We will recruit approximately 5-10 students from consenting schools to act as Burn 2 Learn peer leaders. Peer leaders and students will participate in an interactive/practical training workshop (2 hours) delivered at the study schools by members of the research team. The workshop will cover program familiarisation, peer leader roles and responsibilities, safety considerations and motivational leadership principles. Peer leaders will be responsible for scheduling, promoting, organizing, and leading the school-based physical activity sessions.

4) School-based activity sessions: Sessions will be run at schools by peer leaders (i.e., senior students) at lunch-time, recess, within free periods or before or after school (i.e., flexible delivery mode selected by schools). Schools will be encouraged to schedule 3 x sessions/week for 14 weeks. Each session will last 15-20 minutes (including warm-up and cool down). The sessions will involve students participating in High Intensity Interval Training (HIIT), that incorporates a combination of aerobic (e.g., shuttle runs, jumping jacks, boxing, dancing) and muscle strengthening exercises (e.g., push-ups, squat jumps and walking lunges), organized into between 8-16  intervals (30 seconds work, 30 seconds rest; 1:1 work to rest ratio). HIIT sessions will include variety and choice of activities within sessions to enhance motivation. Students will be able to select from pre-designed HIIT workouts including boxing, dance, running, resistance training and sport-based HIIT (e.g., soccer, touch football and basketball). It will not be mandatory for students to attend the sessions. Students' attendance at the activity sessions will be tracked using heart rate monitors, which will be synced to a smartphone/tablet using Bluetooth technology. The  OnBeat smartphone/tablet application (app) will be used to monitor students' heart rate during sessions.

5) Parents of intervention group students will receive 2 x e-newsletters containing information on the benefits of physical activity for academic performance and mental health and strategies to support their children, using the Skoolbag app and Facebook.

6) Equipment and resources: Schools will be provided with an equipment pack to assist in the delivery of the Burn 2 Learn program (~$2500 AUD) - 1 x iPad, 1 x heart rate monitor/student, Bluetooth speaker and B2L session cards (i.e., describing the various HIIT workouts).

</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual practice control - Students will participate in usual school activities and external sports and exercise. Students allocated to the control condition will receive the intervention following the final assessments.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardio-respiratory fitness: Assessed using the PACER 20m shuttle run test (laps)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 14 weeks post-baseline assessments</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time spent (i.e., minutes) in vigorous physical activity: Assessed using GT9X Link accelerometers and Evensen cut-points to determine activity intensity. Accelerometers will be worn on 7 consecutive days for 24 hours per day (even when bathing, swimming and sleeping).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 14 weeks post-baseline assessments</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Muscular fitness: Timed push-up test (upper body) and standing long jump test (lower body)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 14 weeks post-baseline assessments</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition: Waist circumference (central adiposity); height and weight for Body Mass Index (total adiposity)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 14 weeks post-baseline assessments</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive control: Computer administered tests - Eriksen Flanker task (inhibition) and serial n-back task (working memory).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 14 weeks post-baseline assessments</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Psychological distress: Assessed using the validated Strengths and Difficulties questionnaire (Goodman et al. 1997)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 14 weeks post-baseline assessments</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived stress: Assessed using the validated Perceived Stress Scale (Cohen et al. 1983)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 14 weeks post-baseline assessments</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Autonomous motivation for physical activity: Assessed using the validated Behavioural Regulations in Exercise Questionnaire - version 2 (BREQ-2) (Markland and Tobin, 2004)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 14 weeks post-baseline assessments</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health-related quality of life: Assessed using the validated KIDSCREEN10 questionnaire (Ravens-Sieberer et al. 2001)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 14-weeks post-baseline assessments</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Basic psychological needs satisfaction: Assessed using the validated Adolescent Psychological Need Support in Exercise Questionnaire (Emm-Collison et al. 2016)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 14-weeks post-baseline assessments</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Study participants must be in Grade 11 at consenting schools</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Students that have a health or medical condition that would preclude participation in vigorous physical activity will be excluded</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation to control or intervention groups will be conducted following baseline assessments. Therefore, group allocation is concealed from study team members determining participant eligibility and enrollment.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization will occur at the school-level by an independent researcher not involved in the present trial using a simple coin toss procedure.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Study will employ a wait-list control procedure, in which the control group will receive the intervention following the final assessment period.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculations have been based on estimated effect sizes for the primary outcome of cardio-respiratory fitness assessed using the PACER 20m shuttle run test (outcome = laps completed). Assuming an adjusted mean difference between groups of 5 laps with a standard deviation of change of 7 laps, and intervention:control participant ratio of 1:1, the required sample size to achieve 80% power with alpha level p &lt;.05 is 32 students per group (or 64 students total). To account for an expected drop-out rate of 10% at 14-weeks, the sample size was inflated to 40 students per group, or a total study sample of 80 students.

Analyses of the primary and secondary outcomes will be conducted using linear mixed models SAS V 9.1 (SAS Institute Inc, Cary, NC), with alpha levels set at p&lt;0.05. The models will be used to assess the impact of treatment (Burn to Learn or control), time (treated as categorical with levels baseline and 15 weeks) and the group-by-time interaction, using a random intercept to account for the repeated measures for each participant. Compared to complete case analyses, mixed models include available data for all participants in the analysis and are thus both more efficient and robust to bias. Mixed model analyses are consistent with the intention-to-treat principle, assuming the data are missing at random. The validity of this assumption will be explored by assessing relationships between missingness and observed values of covariates and previous outcomes.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>24/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>5/05/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>25/08/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>David R. Lubans</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Newcastle, Priority Research Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition, Level 3, ATC building, University Drive, Callaghan, NSW, 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>16 Marcus Clarke Street, Canberra City, ACT 2600</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NSW Department of Education</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 Oxford St
Darlinghurst
NSW 2010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this trial is to evaluate the impact of the Burn 2 Learn (B2L) intervention on students' cardio-respiratory fitness and secondary outcomes (muscular fitness, body composition, vigorous physical activity, cognitive control, motivation, basic needs satisfaction and psychological health). Our primary hypothesis is that students allocated to the intervention condition will experience improved cardio-respiratory fitness relative to students allocated to the control condition by the primary study end point (14 weeks post-baseline). We aim to recruit 80 grade 11 students from two schools (x40 per school) who will be randomly allocated (by school) to received the B2L intervention or participate in usual practice (control group to receive the intervention after the final assessments). The B2L intervention will involve students participating in 2-3 sessions per week of High Intensity Interval Training (HIIT) for 14 weeks, delivered at school by peer leaders (trained grade 11 students). To facilitate the intervention, 2 x teachers will be recruited as school champions and will attend a one-day professional learning workshop. Peer leaders (x 5-10 students) will be identified and recruited from the intervention school. Peer leaders and students will participate in a 2 hour workshop delivered by the research team. The HIIT sessions will involve a variety of engaging exercises and will occur for 15-20 minutes at a time. The intervention school will receive an equipment pack (heart-rate monitors, iPad, Bluetooth speaker, exercise cards) to facilitate session delivery. To gain support from the home environment, parents of study participants will receive 2 x eNewsletters via Facebook or the Skoolbag app during the study period. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle Human Research Ethics Comittee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University Drive, Callaghan, NSW, 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/03/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2016-0424</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/11/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>State Education Research Education Process (SERAP)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 53, Darlinghurst, NSW, 1300</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>13/03/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David R. Lubans</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle, Priority Research Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition, Level 3, ATC building, University Drive, Callaghan, NSW, 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 2049</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.lubans@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David R. Lubans</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle, Priority Research Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition, Level 3, ATC building, University Drive, Callaghan, NSW, 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 2049</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.lubans@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>David R. Lubans</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle, Priority Research Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition, Level 3, ATC building, University Drive, Callaghan, NSW, 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 2049</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.lubans@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Jordan J. Smith</name>
      <address>University of Newcastle, Priority Research Centre for Physical Activity and Nutrition, Level 3, ATC building, University Drive, Callaghan, NSW, 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4021 7704</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jordan.smith@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>