<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343294">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000843954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Investigating changes in hippocampal volume and regional cerebral perfusion and therapeutic and system related outcomes following the treatment of Post Traumatic Stress Disorder with Eye Movement Desensitization Reprocessing and exposure therapy: a pilot study.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Investigating changes in hippocampal volume and regional cerebral perfusion and therapeutic and system related outcomes (including symptom reduction and effects of participants experience of therapy on treatment efficacy, daily functioning and quality of life) following the treatment of Post Traumatic Stress Disorder with eye movement desensitization and reprocessing (EMDR) and prolonged exposure therapy: a pilot study.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nill</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Post Traumatic Stress Disorder - PTSD is an anxiety disorder that can develop after exposure to any distressing event, this event may involve the threat of death to oneself or to someone else, or to one's own or someone else's physical, sexual, or psychological integrity, overwhelming the individual's ability to cope.  Typical symptoms for PTSD include re-experiencing the original trauma (s) through flashbacks or nightmares, avoidance of stimuli associated with the trauma, and increased arousal - such as difficulty falling or staying asleep, anger and hyper vigilance.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>EMDR is a form of psychotherapy that was developed by Francine Shapiro to resolve the development of trauma-related disorders caused by exposure to distressing events.  The theory suggests when distressing experiences occur they may overwhelm usual cognitive and neurological coping mechanisms.  The memory and associated stimuli of the event are inadequately processed, and are dysfunction-ally stored in an isolated memory network.  The goal of EMDR therapy is to process these distressing memories, using dual attention stimuli (by way of bilateral stimulation (e.g. eye movements, tones or tapping) while triggering a physiological state that facilitates information processing, therefore reducing the distress and allowing the client to develop more adaptive coping mechanisms.  Following a 6 week period, after the individual assessment, where participants receive MRI and PET scans and act as their own control group; participants in the EMDR intervention group will receive 2 x 90 minute sessions per week for 6 weeks, administered in one-on-one individualized sessions by trained therapists.</interventions>
    <comparator>Exposure therapy is an internationally recognized treatment modality for PTSD.  This technique requires individuals to confront the distressing memory until its arousal-provoking properties are decreased through a process of habituation.  Following a 6 week period, after the individual assessment, where participants receive MRI and PET scans and act as their own control group; participants in the exposure therapy intervention group will receive 2 x 90 minute sessions per week for 6 weeks, administered in one-on-one individualized sessions by trained therapists.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean PTSD checklist - civilian: 17 item self-report measure of DSM IV symptoms of PTSD.  To be used as a screening tool and to monitor change following treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment - 6 weeks prior to treatment; Baseline - The beginning of treatment; post-treatment - at the conclusion of treatment; 6 week follow-up - 6 weeks following the conclusion of treatment; 6 month follow-up - 6 months following the conclusion of treatment and 12 month follow-up - 12 months following the conclusion of treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale scores (DASS) - 42 item self-report measure of depression, anxiety and stress symptoms often co-morbid with PTSD symptoms.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline - The beginning of treatment; post-treatment - at the conclusion of treatment; 6 week follow-up - 6 weeks following the conclusion of treatment; 6 month follow-up - 6 months following the conclusion of treatment and 12 month follow-up - 12 months following the conclusion of treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>PET and MRI results measuring hippocampal volumes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment - within the 6 week period prior to treatment beginning and Post-treatment - at the conclusion of treatment.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective Units of Distress - used as a monitoring tool throughout the treatment period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at the end of each EMDR treatment session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean scores on the Impact of Events Scale (IES) = 15 item self-report inventory which reflects DSM-IV criteria for PTSD and levels of distress.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Used at the beginning of each treatment session when a new distressing memory is being targeted; and at the end of each treatment session.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Qualitative individual interviews - questions specific to the participants experience of therapy, daily functioning and quality of life.  Themes will be extracted from the transcribed interviews and analyzed using content analysis.  Triangulation of data will include comparisons of experience of therapy and symptom reduction results and quality of life changes will be triangulated with the WHOQOL-BREF results.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Post-treatment; 6 week follow-up; 6 month follow-up and 12 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Currently diagnosable with PTSD (via assessment interview and CAPS form 2); willing to engage in psychological treatment; consenting to neuroimaging and audio-taped interviews.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Current drug or alcohol dependence; diabetes; currently pregnant or breast feeding; past history of psychotic illness; previously diagnosed organic brain disorder; evidence of diagnosable cluster B Personality Disorder (via SCID II); currently on Psychotropic based medications; unable to cope with confined spaces or needles; any metal implants.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be contacted off the wait-list of the Posttraumatic Stress Unit at Fremantle Hospital and the Murdoch University Psychology Clinic.  A screening telephone call will assess whether the participant meets criteria for the study and is willing to attend an assessment interview to assess possible admission.  The PTSD checklist, SCID II personality questionnaire and Dissociative Experience scale is completed to assess admissibility.  Following an assessment interview (using the CAPS form 2 to assess PTSD criteria) and signed consent, participants complete pre-treatment inventory and MRI / PET scans.  Following a six week wait, where participants act as their own control group, participants attend their initial intervention appointment; prior to entering the therapy room the therapist contacts the primary supervisor who informs them of the treatment type, randomly allocated through computer software.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer software will be used to randomly allocate participants to 1 of 2 treatment groups (EMDR or exposure therapy)</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>A comparative outcomes study; the between subjects design will compare 2 treatment groups; a within subjects design will compare each participant over 5 data collection points.  Each participant will act as their own control.

This study will be a mixed methods design using both quantitative and qualitative data.  Triangulation of quantitative and qualitative data will be used where possible.  Content analysis will be used to analyze the qualitative data.

The time frame will allow a longitudinal analysis to compare treatment efficacy, participants perceptions of the treatment experience, quality of life and daily functioning changes over time.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>20</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Murdoch University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Murdoch University
South Street
Murdoch WA 6164</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>School of Psychiatry and Clinical Neurosciences University of WA</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of WA
35 Stirling Highway
CRAWLEY  WA 6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of WA</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of WA
35 Stirling Highway
CRAWLEY  WA 6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Fremantle Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Alma Street
Fremantle  WA  6160</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
NEDLANDS  WA  6009</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Eye Movement Desensitisation and Reprogramming (EMDR) and exposure therapy are well established first line psychological treatments for Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD)(Boudewyns et al., 1993; Boudewyns &amp; Hyer, 1996; Edmond &amp; Rubin, 2004; Lee et al., 2002; Montgomery &amp; Ayllon, 1994; Power et al., 2002; Vaughan et al., 1994; Van Etten &amp; Taylor, 1998).  There have been few studies to date exploring changes in brain functioning following treatment in EMDR, which has left the underlying question of 'what is the mechanism by which the two therapies acheive their therapeutic effects' unresolved.   Evidence as to what neurological changes occur as a result of treatment may help vindicate the efficacy of treatment modalities and aid understanding of treatment function.  Positron Emission Tomography (PET) scanning enables research into changes in activation of different parts of the brain by measuring regional cerebral perfusion (blood flow), providing insight into this question by measuring brain activity.  Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) will enable accurate interpretation of the PET/CT scans and will aim to replicate or refute findings from a recent study that suggests effective treatment of PTSD is associated with an increase in hippocampal volume (Bossini et al., 2011).  This project aims to also explore the therapeutic efficacy of EMDR and exposure therapy (in terms of symptom reduction), and the significance of the participant's experience of therapy; the impact of this experience on therapeutic efficacy and on the participant's quality of life and levels of functioning.  Although there is an abundance of data evaluating the effectiveness of EMDR and prolonged exposure therapy in relation to symptom reduction (see refrences above), there are very few studies investigating participant's experience of therapy and the significance of this experience in their recovery both short and longer term; and only three major qualitative studies published on EMDR (Di Giorgio, Arnkoff, Glass, Lyhus &amp; Walter, 2004; Edmond, Sloan &amp; McCarty, 2004 and Ricci, Clayton and Shapiro, 2006). It was reported that due to the unusual nature of EMDR with the eye movements, exploration of participant's experiences of treatment was relevant, furthermore qualitative methods were felt to be the logical approach to gaining insight into these questions (Edmond, Sloan &amp; McCarty, 2004).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Murdoch University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Murdoch University 
South Street
MURDOCH  WA  6164</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/08/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Metropolitan Area Health Services Human Research Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Alma Street
Fremantle  WA  6160</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/07/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tracy McGuire</name>
      <address>Murdoch University
School of Psychology, Division of Health Sciences
South Street
MURDOCH  WA  6164</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93606000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.mcguire@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Chris Lee</name>
      <address>Murdoch University
School of Psychology, Division of Health Sciences
South Street
MURDOCH  WA  6164</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93606828</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chris.lee@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tracy McGuire</name>
      <address>Murdoch University
School of Psychology, Division of Health Sciences
South Street
MURDOCH  WA  6164</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93606000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>t.mcguire@murdoch.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>