<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308401">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/08/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>25/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000732280</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Analysis of two techniques for transcutaneous lower eyelid blepharoplasty: A prospective surgical trial by using random allocation.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patients with lower eyelid aging
are standard lower blepharoplasty and lower blepharoplasty with periorbital fat mobilization and arcus marginalis redrape effective in promoting the rejuvenation of the lower eyelid ?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>aging lower eyelid</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>lower eyelid laxity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Patients submitted to lower eyelid blepharoplasty by two different techniques. 
The Surgical Group 1 (SG1) consisted of standard fat-resection lower eyelid blepharoplasty.
The Surgical Group 2 (SG2) -  Subciliary incision was drawn 3 mm below entire lash line, from the punctum medially to the lateral canthal region. The lateral aspect was made 4 to 5mm from lateral canthal angle within an existing crows foot. A small incision through skin and muscle was made with a blade at the lateral end of the marking, measuring approximately 10 mm.  Straight iris scissors beveling away from the pretarsal orbicularis completed the subciliary skin incision, leaving the pretarsal orbicularis undisturbed. The preseptal orbicularis was opened from mid-pupil to the lateral orbital rim. The scissors were used to develop a plane between the septum and the preseptal orbicularis, then the skin muscle flap was raised, preserving approximately 6 mm of pretarsal orbicularis, exposing the retromuscular space. This flap was dissected to the level of the orbital rim using cutting eletrocautery, thereby the septum orbitale, the capsulopalpebral fascia, the inferior orbital rim, and arcus marginalis were exposed. The junction of the septum orbitale and the periosteum of the inferior orbital rim (arcus marginalis) was released using cutting eletrocautery.  After placing a traction stitch to hold the lower lid in extesion, the complex formed by septum orbitale and capsulopalpebral fascia was elevated and the orbital fat from each of the three compartments was released, and conservastively removed or preserved and then repositioned. Only the orbital fat from the medial and central compartments were transposed and sutured to the periosteum with 6-0 Vicryl (registered trademark). The tear trough was corrected by release of the muscular origin contributing to the deformity, addition of volume by fat transposition, and tightening of the skin muscle flap. Next, the junction of the septum orbitale and the periosteum of the inferior orbital rim was reset to its anatomical position (simply suture back to the orbital rim) with interrupted 6-0 Vicryl (registered trademark).

Duration of procedure: 
SG1- 1h 15m
SG2- 1h 25m</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients were assigned to interventions into two surgical groups by using random allocation. 
Surgical Group 1 (SG1) - patients submitted to conservatively standard fat-ressection lower blepharoplasty - Subciliary incision was drawn 3 mm below entire lash line, from the punctum medially to the lateral canthal region. The lateral aspect was made 4 to 5mm from lateral canthal angle within an existing crows foot. A small incision through skin and muscle was made with a blade at the lateral end of the marking, measuring approximately 10 mm.  Straight iris scissors beveling away from the pretarsal orbicularis completed the subciliary skin incision, leaving the pretarsal orbicularis undisturbed. The preseptal orbicularis was opened from mid-pupil to the lateral orbital rim. The scissors were used to develop a plane between the septum and the preseptal orbicularis, then the skin muscle flap was raised, preserving approximately 6 mm of pretarsal orbicularis, exposing the retromuscular space. This flap was dissected to the level of the orbital rim using cutting eletrocautery. Intraoperatively, the volume of fat from each of the three compartments was assessed. The maneuver of gently balloting the globe with gentle pressure on the upper-eyelid skin was not performed to expose the orbital fat. Fat removal was performed conservatively using eletrocautery without excision of the septum.   
Surgical Group 2 (SG2) - patients submitted to lower blepharoplasty with periorbital fat mobilization and arcus marginalis redrape.
In both techniques: elevation of the skin muscle flap was integral part of achieving the desired cosmetic result once the desired changes of the posterior lamella were performed. The anterior lamella was redraped in a superior lateral vector rather than a pure vertical vector. Excision of excess skin and muscle was done by removing a triangle of tissue lateral to the canthus, thereby minimizing the amount of tissue removed along the lid margin. The orbicularis muscle suspension was carried out by suturing the preseptal orbicularis muscle (attached to the lower skin flap) to the inferior aspect of the periosteum of the lateral orbital rim with a single stich of 6-0 Vicryl (registered trademark). A tension free closure was achieved with 6-0 nylon suture.
Duration of procedure: 
SG1- 1h 15m
SG2- 1h 25m</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To achieve some level of quantification of the results a graduated scale, as proposed by Barton et al, was used to grade the pre- and postoperative results, by having three independent observers examine pre- and postoperative standardized photographs, who had not been involved with the particular patients</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline (pre-operatively);
post-operatively-  between 6 months and 1 year after surgery.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>compare lower lid laxity before and after canthopexy

Lower lid laxity was evaluated in all 50 patients by intraoperative lid distraction. The anterior lid distraction test refers to how much the lower eyelid can be manually pulled or distracted from apposition with the globe. The measurement was made with Castroviejo's caliper during the surgery, registering the values gotten before and after the canthopexy. 
Lower lid redundancy (laxity) was also determined by grasping the lateral aspect of the lower lid, and tensing the lid in a horizontal direction while maintaining lid position just at the inferior limbus (lateral lid distraction test). The redundancy was defined as the distance from laterally displaced lateral commissure to the point where lower lid margin overlaps the lateral orbital rim edge.</outcome>
      <timepoint>before and immediately after surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>analyzing the complication's rate

Clinical charts were reviewed by the authors to identify postoperative complications, including orbital hematoma, blepharitis, chemosis, lid malposition, and surgical revisions. 
To achieve some level of quantification of the results a graduated scale, as proposed by Barton (Barton Jr FE, Ha R &amp; Awada M (2004): Fat extrusion and septal reset in patients with the tear trough triad: a critical appraisal. Plast Reconstr Surg 113: 2115-2121.), was used to grade the pre- and postoperative results, by having three independent observers examine pre- and postoperative standardized photographs, who had not been involved with the particular patients.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline (pre-operatively);
post-operatively-  between 6 months and 1 year after surgery.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Anyone between 30 to 65 years of age electing to undergo blepharoplasty, and who have passed the preoperative evaluation.
Preoperative evaluation included a thorough ophthalmologic history including previous ocular or periorbital surgery, history of dry eyes and/or visual disturbance, and any relevant medical conditions.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with history of previous injury or lower eyelid blepharoplasty were excluded from the present study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Determination of whether a patient would be treated in Surgical Group 1 or in Surgical Group 2 was based on random sampling numbers drawn up for each surgical group and were contained in a set of fifty sealed envelopes
(50 envelopes numbered consecutively from 1 through 50 were used as follows: 25 cards marked SG1 and other 25 cards marked SG2 were placed in each envelope by a physician not involved with this research and the researcher (surgeon) were blind as the type of surgery until moments before doing it. The envelopes were placed in an box and randomly taken before surgery.).
Any participant had an equal probability of assignment to the groups. After acceptance of a patient by the panel, and before admission to the operating room, the appropriate numbered envelope was opened by the surgeon; the card inside told if the patient was to be in Surgical Group 1 or in Surgical Group 2.</concealment>
    <sequence>Urn randomization</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state>Sao Paulo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Universidade Federal de Sao Paulo/Escola Paulista de Medicina (UNIFESP/EPM)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Rua Botucatu, 740 Sao Paulo/SP  Brazil 
ZIP 04023-900</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Universidade Federal de Sao Paulo/Escola Paulista de Medicina (UNIFESP/EPM)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Rua Botucatu, 740 Sao Paulo/SP  Brazil 
ZIP 04023-900</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study was to analyze prospectively fifty patients submitted to lower blepharoplasty, using a skin muscle flap, routine canthal support with lateral canthopexy at Federal University of Sao Paulo, between April 2005 and May 2007.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1) TRANSCUTANEOUS LOWER EYELID BLEPHAROPLASTY: ANALYSIS OF TWO TECHNIQUES, LATERAL CANTHAL SUPPORT AND OUTCOMES
XXVIII CONGRESSO BRASILEIRO DE CIRURGIA 
26 a 30/07/2009 Sao Paulo/SP Brazil

2) TRANSCUTANEOUS LOWER EYELID BLEPHAROPLASTY: ANALYSIS OF TWO TECHNIQUES, LATERAL CANTHAL SUPPORT AND OUTCOMES  
SIMPOSIO NACIONAL DA SOCIEDADE BRASILEIRA DE CIRURGIA PLASTICA OCULAR
15 e 16/05/2009, Botucatu/SP Brazil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite de Etica em Pesquisa (Human Subjects Review Board (Ethical Committee) at Federal University of Sao Paulo)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Rua Botucatu, 572
1 andar conj 14
tel + 55 (11) 5571-1062 / + 55 (11) 5539-7162
Sao Paulo/SP
ZIP 04023-061</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/01/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/04/1468</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/11/2004</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>giovanni andre pires viana</name>
      <address>al jauaperi 732
Sao Paulo/SP
zip 04523-013</address>
      <phone>+55 11 5055 3831</phone>
      <fax>+55 11 5055 3831</fax>
      <email>info@cliniplast.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>giovanni andre pires viana</name>
      <address>al jauaperi 732
Sao Paulo/SP
zip 04523-013</address>
      <phone>+55 11 5055 3831</phone>
      <fax>+55 11 5055 3831</fax>
      <email>info@cliniplast.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>giovanni andre pires viana</name>
      <address>al jauaperi 732
Sao Paulo/SP
zip 04523-013</address>
      <phone>+55 11 5055 3831</phone>
      <fax>+55 11 5055 3831</fax>
      <email>info@cliniplast.com</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>