<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367743">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/01/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/01/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000076572</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effects of One Month of Therapy with the Long-acting Bronchodilator Tiotropium on Small Airway Physiology in Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Effects of One Month of Therapy with the Long-acting Bronchodilator Tiotropium on Ventilation Heterogeneity in Patients with Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1166-0828</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will self-administer 18 micrograms tiotropium bromide via oral inhalation route once-daily for 28 +/- 2 days (the precise finish date determined by the availability of the PET scanner). Adherence to therapy will be monitored by drug return and counting</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the placebo arm will self-administer a placebo capsule via oral inhalation once daily for 28 +/- 2 days (the precise finish date determined by the availability of the PET scanner).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in ventilated lung volume, as measured by Galligas PET ventilation scan, following one month of therapy with tiotropium</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 +/- 2 days</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between change in ventilation heterogeneity, measured by Galligas PET ventilation scan, and change in forced oscillation technique (FOT) parameters (resistance and reactance)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 +/- 2 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between change in ventilation heterogeneity, measured by Galligas PET ventilation scan, and change in multiple breath nitrogen washout (MBNW) parameters (lung clearance index, Sacin, Scond)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 +/- 2 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between change in ventilation heterogeneity, measured by Galligas PET ventilation scan, and change in exercise capacity (endurance shuttle walk distance)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 +/-2 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between change in forced oscillation technique (FOT) parameters (resistance and reactance) and change in exercise capacity (endurance shuttle walk distance)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 +/- 2 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between change in MBNW parameters (lung clearance index, Sacin, Scond) and change in exercise capacity (endurance shuttle walk distance)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 +/- 2 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between change in PET ventilation heterogeneity and change in symptom score (St George's Respiratory Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 +/- 2 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between change in FOT parameters and change in symptom score (St George's Respiratory Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 +/- 2 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between change in MBNW parameters and change in symptom score (St George's Respiratory Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 +/- 2 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relationship between change in exercise capacity (endurance shuttle walk distance) and change in symptom score (St George's Respiratory Questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>28 +/- 2 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults with physician-diagnosed mild-moderate chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, with history of current or past smoking (total exposure &gt; 10 pack years)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>* Use of tiotropium or any other LAMA or LABA within the previous 4 weeks
* Musculoskeletal (for example, severe arthritis) or other conditions which limit the ability to walk at near-maximal pace
* Significant cardiac disease (ischaemic heart disease or arrhythmia) deemed by the investigators or the subjects treating cardiologist to make it unsafe for the subject to undertake a supervised near-maximal exercise test
* Documented hypersensitivity to, or intolerance of, anti-cholinergic therapies
* Significant respiratory infection or documented exacerbation of COPD within the previous 6 weeks
* Other active or chronic respiratory pathologies (for example, interstitial lung disease, asthma, chest wall pathology causing ventilatory restriction)
* Past history of lung surgery (including lobectomy or pneumonectomy, but not lung biopsy) or thoracic radiation therapy (excluding isolated mediastinal radiation therapy with no evidence of subsequent pulmonary fibrosis)
* Any major comorbidities deemed to impact on respiratory physiology or symptoms, including severe on uncontrolled heart failure, morbid obesity, muscular or neurological disorders causing respiratory muscle weakness or dysfunctional swallowing
* History of chronic kidney disease (moderate to severe, eGFR less than or equal to 45 mL/min/1.73m2) or severe hepatic impairment
* Unable to perform lung function testing at the enrollment visit
* Dependence on domiciliary supplemental oxygen, unable to go without for at least 1 hour
* Women who are breast feeding, pregnant, or unwilling to avoid pregnancy during the study period
* Unable to provide informed consent
* Current enrolment in other trials
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Eligibility determined by the lead investigator and informed consent obtained. Randomisation to the study arm performed by central administration unit who maintains the allocation schedule and dispenses medications according to the allocation schedule. </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using computer software, in a 2:1 active:placebo ratio</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>* Power calculations are based on previously obtained data from our research group, using SPECT ventilation scanning. This cohort of subjects with COPD had a mean ventilated volume of 61%. We anticipate a 20% increased in mean ventilated volume following therapy with tiotropium. Using a bimean power calculation (at a power of 80% and a significance of 0.05), for a 2:1 (active:placebo) group allocation, the numbers of subjects required to detect this increase are 30 in the active group and 15 in the placebo group.
* The changes in ventilated volume from baseline to end of the study will be measured from the PET/CT images.  Differences in mean changes between the active and placebo treated groups will be determined by an unpaired T-test.  
* Ventilation in the Galligas PET scans will be measuring using the method of Nagao et al which produces a parameter called the Fractal Dimension.  Differences in mean changes in mean fractal dimension between active and placebo treated groups will be determined by an unpaired T-test. 
* Relationships between changes in ventilated volume and ventilation heterogeneity in Galligas PET, and changes in FOT parameters, MBNW parameters, exercise capacity (endurance shuttle walk distance) and symptoms scores will be examined by Spearman or Pearson correlations, as appropriate. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/03/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>45</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <postcode>2065 - Royal North Shore Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>2137 - Concord</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>431 Glebe Point Road,
Glebe NSW 2037</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>431 Glebe Point Road, 
Glebe NSW 2037</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal North Shore Hospital Department of Respiratory and Sleep Medicine</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Pacific Highway,
St Leonards NSW 2065</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Inhaled bronchodilator medications (found in puffers/inhalers) are used for the treatment of COPD at all stages of the disease. Large clinical trials have proven the benefits of these medications in patients with COPD. However, we still do not fully understand the effects of these medications on lung function. Our research team has access to advanced methods of measuring lung function, and by using these techniques we hope to understand more about the lungs respond to bronchodilator treatment. By improving our understanding of the effects of these medications on lung function, we may be able to improve future treatments for patients with COPD.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Sydney Local Health District HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Office
Level 13, Kolling Building
Royal North Shore Hospital
Pacific Highway
St Leonards NSW 2065</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/HAWKE/388</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/12/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Greg King</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
431 Glebe Point Road,
Glebe NSW 2037</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ggk@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stephen Milne</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
431 Glebe Point Road,
Glebe NSW 2037</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stephen.milne@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stephen Milne</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
431 Glebe Point Road,
Glebe NSW 2037</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stephen.milne@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Stephen Milne</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
431 Glebe Point Road,
Glebe NSW 2037</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9114 0000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>stephen.milne@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>