<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335875">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/09/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000891022</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Influence of a stretching activity program on musculoskeletal function in workers with low back pain.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Controlled clinical trial to assess the effect of a stretching activity program on muscle pain and fuction in male workers with low back pain.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1116-6738</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Low back pain.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The stretching program is usually offered by the industry three times a week, 30 minutes a day, in group, with a physioterapist orientation. This was not an obligatory program. Workers mechanics that participated of this program for 32 weeks or more were included in the case group, and those that didn't participate of this program were included in the control group.</interventions>
    <comparator>This group of workers do not take part in the stretching program.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lower back pain was measured by using the visual analog scale (VAS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the baseline.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fatigue was measured using the questionnaire of perception of fatigue.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the baseline.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lumbar flexibility was assessed by measuring the flexion of the torso toward the floor using a simple universal goniometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the baseline.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood samples from fasting volunteers was collected through the brachial venipuncture.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional capacity was evaluated by the index of work ability (WAI), which iis composed of 60 questions. The answers are converted into numerical values and then weighted. The results can range from 7 (low work capacity) to 49 points (optimal capacity of the work).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Be a participant or not in the stretching program offered freely by the company (for a period greater or equal 32 weeks), ii) having at least one event of occupational low back pain (medical leave) prior to the study, iii) have obtained values equal to 5 the questionnaire Roland Morris (RM) by Nusbaum et al.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>As exclusion criteria were defined: i) event of low back pain in a period less or equal than 32 weeks or during the study, ii) a history of direct trauma and any type of surgery in the abdomen, chest, legs and spine, iii) a history of cardiopulmonary disorders, metabolic or neurological in the 32 weeks preceding the survey, iv) a history of infectious diseases in the 32 weeks preceding the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>19/11/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cintia Helena Santuzzi</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>R. Milthor de Oliveira Fernandes, n. 50, Jardim Camburi, Vitoria - ES. CEP:29090-760</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Brazil</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Brazil</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Technological advances and new market demands have subjected workers at a fast pace, with great physical strain, contributing to the increase in musculoskeletal injuries such as back pain.
Recent studies that concern the health of the worker seek ways to diagnose their risk factors and mechanisms that can mitigate them.
This study evaluated the effects of a stretching program for workers through an analysis of the parameters pain, perception of fatigue, lumbar flexibility, muscle damage marker creatine kinase (CK) and index of work ability (WAI).
The results showed that the group that participated in the stretching program showed a reduction of pain parameters and perception of fatigue, increased lumbar flexibility, and decrease of CK increase of WAI, suggesting that a stretching program provides an improvement of musculoskeletal conditions and may act by reducing the risk of occupational diseases. It is suggested further studies to confirm our findings.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee of the Federal University of Espirito Santo
/ UFES</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Av. Marechal Campos, 1468, Campos de Maruipe, predio da administracao, Vitoria - ES.
CEP: 29040090</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/10/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>(parecer n. 09/2006)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/07/2006</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Brazil</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Fernanda Mayrink Goncalves Zerbini</name>
      <address>Rua Doutor Moacir Goncalves, n 255, apt 302, Jardim da Penha, Vitoria, Espirito Santo. CEP: 29060-445</address>
      <phone>55 (27) 8135 8610</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nandamayrink@yahoo.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cintia Helena Santuzzi</name>
      <address>R. Milthor de Oliveira Fernandes, n. 50, apt. 404-A, Jardim Camburi - Vitoria, ES. CEP: 29090-760</address>
      <phone>55 (27) 9944 1177</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>csantuzzi@terra.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Fernanda Mayrink Goncalves Zerbini</name>
      <address>Rua Doutor Moacir Goncalves, n 255, apt 302, Jardim da Penha, Vitoria, Espirito Santo. CEP: 29060-445.</address>
      <phone>55 (27) 8135 8610</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>nandamayrink@yahoo.com.br</email>
      <country>Brazil</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>