<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368331">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/04/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/04/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000388516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A brief Ecological Momentary Intervention to reduce alcohol use and alcohol related harm in new college students.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A brief Ecological Momentary Intervention to reduce alcohol use and alcohol related harm in new college students.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1169-1378</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alcohol use</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Alcohol Related Consequences </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Other</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Research that is not of generic health relevance and not applicable to specific health categories listed above</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The participants will be assigned to one of 2 conditions outlined below:

Ecological momentary intervention and ecological momentary assessment (EMI-EMA): Participants in the EMI-EMA condition will be sent intervention text messages twice a day (at 7:30pm and 9pm) on the Tuesday, Thursday, Friday, and Saturday of Orientation Week. These messages will contain a social consequence of alcohol use. EMI-EMA participants will also receive messages asking them to report their weekend alcohol use fortnightly throughout the year (e.g., 'How many standard drinks did you consume Thurs, Fri, Sat? Please TB like this 5, 0, 1).

EMA only: Participants in the EMA condition will only receive messages asking them to report their alcohol use fortnightly throughout the year (e.g., 'How many standard drinks did you consume Thurs, Fri, Sat? Please TB like this 5, 0, 1).

All participants will also fill out a questionnaire at the start and end of the semester (baseline, 3 months, 6 months) asking them to report the number of alcohol related consequences they experienced over the past 3 months (B-YAACQ) as well as alcohol use over the last week and the AUDIT-C.</interventions>
    <comparator>No-intervention control (EMA only condition).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol use (number of drinks in the last week measured by timeline follow back).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Timeline follow back measured at baseline, 3 months, and 9 months. E.g., the Sunday before Orientation Week (baseline), and at the end of the academic semesters (3 months and 9 months).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>AUDIT-C questionnaire

</outcome>
      <timepoint>AUDIT-C measured at baseline, 3 months, and 9 months. E.g., the Sunday before Orientation Week (baseline), and at the end of the academic semesters (3 months and 9 months).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>EMA message - the number of weekend and Orientation Week drinks measured by text messages asking students to report their drinking from the past 3 days).  
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Academic year weekend alcohol use, measured by an EMA message asking participants to report their last 3 nights drinking. Messages sent fortnightly; weeks 3, 5, 7, 9, 11, and 13 of the first semester and second semester).
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol related consequences as measured by the Brief Young Adult Alcohol Consequences Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and after each semester (approximately 3 months and 9 months after baseline).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Must be a full time first year student residing at a residential college.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>25</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Students who do not live at a residential college. Returning students.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomization by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>NA</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Hierarchical Linear Modelling will be used to analyse all data. The model will examine drinking behaviour over time for
the EMA and EMA-EMI groups. The model will examine drinking behaviour as a repeated measure over time for the EMA and EMA-EMI groups and directly compare these groups. 

The total sample size [n = 350] should have sufficient power, even when taking potential drop-out into account. The design is well powered for detecting group differences of 6.5 standard drinks during OWeek and 2 standard drinks/week during the academic year.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/02/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/02/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/02/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>15/02/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>350</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Otago</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago Psychology Department</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Otago
362 Leith Street
Dunedin. 9016
New Zealand
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>University of Otago
362 Leith Street
Dunedin. 9016
New Zealand
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Young adults have the highest alcohol consumption of any age group. Within this high risk age group, university students stand out, consuming more alcohol than their non-university attending peers. As a result, university students not only have a higher incidence of alcohol use disorders, but also report a higher incidence of harm resulting from alcohol. A number of factors have been implicated in this increase in alcohol use at university, however, new research suggests that drinking during certain events (e.g., Orientation Week) may have a flow on effect and influence the number of drinks students consume throughout the year. 
The primary aim of the research project is to reduce overall alcohol consumption by university students (i.e., alcohol consumed during the academic year) by reducing the heavy drinking that characterises students drinking behaviour during OWeek. We hypothesize that an ecological momentary intervention (EMI) aimed at Orientation Week will reduce the amount of alcohol use throughout both Orientation Week and throughout the year.

Participants will be randomly assigned to either an Ecological Momentary Intervention (EMA) or EMA-EMI condition. Participants in the EMA condition will receive assessment text messages during OWeek to report their
alcohol consumption from the previous 3 days. Outside of these intensive periods, participants will receive a text message every second Sunday asking them to report their alcohol consumption for the previous 3 days. Participants in the EMA-EMI condition [i.e., assessment + intervention] will receive EMA text
messages and EMI text messages on four days during OWeek. The content of the EMI text messages will focus on the potential social implications of drinking too much.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Otago Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Otago
362 Leith Street
Dunedin. 9016
New Zealand
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/01/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/267</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>25/11/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tamlin Conner</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology, University of Otago, 275 Leith Walk, Dunedin, 9016 NZ</address>
      <phone>+64 (03) 479-7624</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tconner@psy.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tamlin Conner</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology, University of Otago, 275 Leith Walk, Dunedin 9016 NZ</address>
      <phone>+64 (03) 479-7624</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tconner@psy.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tamlin Conner</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology, University of Otago, 275 Leith Walk, Dunedin 9016 NZ</address>
      <phone>+64 (03) 479-7624</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tconner@psy.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Benjamin Riordan</name>
      <address>Department of Psychology, University of Otago, 275 Leith Walk, Dunedin 9016 NZ</address>
      <phone>+64 (03) 479-9472</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>riobe135@student.otago.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>