<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368322">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/05/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/06/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000603516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assessment of shoulder proprioception using the Microsoft Kinect sensor</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can the Microsoft Kinect sensor be used to assess the differences in shoulder proprioception between subjects with traumatic anterior shoulder instability and subjects with healthy, pain-free shoulders and between patients younger than 30 and older than 60 years of age?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>KSPS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Traumatic anterior instability of the shoulder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Age-related differences in shoulder proprioception</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>We will be using the Microsoft Kinect sensor and a Virtual Reality headset to measure proprioception at the shoulder. 

This will involve the subject being shown a video or image of a desired shoulder (and arm) position on the headset. They will be asked to try to copy this position themselves. The Kinect will record the subject's attempt and compare it to the desired position as shown on the headset.

Each participant will be tested only once in a single, one hour session. The testing session will be performed one on one by the student researcher in the team who is a medical student. As only one session is required per participant, strategies to monitor adherence do not apply.</interventions>
    <comparator>We will compare the new test with two tests already described in the literature. One is called the "laser-pointer assisted angle-reproduction test" which uses a small laser strapped to the subject's wrist. With their eyes open, the subject points the laser at the 3 targets on the board in turn and concentrates on their position. They are then blindfolded and the examiner asks them to point at one of the target points in random order. The test is performed 3 times per target point, per arm, in both flexion and abduction. The examiner does not move the participant's arm at any stage. Each time the participant points the laser they must hold their arm in position long enough for the coordinates of the laser spot to be recorded.

The second test uses a goniometer. The subject is blindfolded and their arm is moved by the examiner into a target position and held for 10 seconds. It is then returned to the starting position. The subject has to actively return their arm to the target position. The subject's attempt will be compared to the target position to assess how accurately they can reproduce the joint position.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean difference, in degrees, between the desired angle of the shoulder and the actual angle of the shoulder.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Healthy controls will be tested at baseline.

Patients with anterior shoulder instability will be tested after they have received a formal diagnosis from a surgeon or sports physician. There is no restriction on length of time after diagnosis that the tests can be performed.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean difference, in millimetres, between the desired position of the hand and the actual position of the hand.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Healthy controls will be tested at baseline.

Patients with anterior shoulder instability will be tested after they have received a formal diagnosis from a surgeon or sports physician. There is no restriction on length of time after diagnosis that the tests can be performed.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain and function measured by the Oxford Stability Score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After a diagnosis of traumatic anterior instability by a surgeon or sports physician.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stability, motion and function measured by the 1978 Rowe Score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>After a diagnosis of traumatic anterior instability by a surgeon or sports physician.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>For the instability group we require participants under the age of 40 years who have had at least one documented incident of anterior subluxation or dislocation followed by the development of symptoms of anterior instability.
The control group will consist of adult volunteers with healthy shoulder under 30 years of age and over 60 years of age. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Volunteers in the control group will be excluded if they are currently experiencing shoulder pain or if they have ever had shoulder surgery.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/03/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Professor Simon Bell</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Melbourne Shoulder and Elbow Centre. 31 Normanby St Brighton Victoria 3186 

Monash University. A/Professor of Orthopaedic Surgery</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Department of Surgery in the School of Clinical Sciences at Monash University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department of Surgery, Monash Medical Centre
Level 5, Block E
246 Clayton Road
Clayton, 3168
Victoria</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Susan White</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Olympic Park Sports Medicine Centre
Olympic Boulevard
AAMI Park
Melbourne, Victoria 3004</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Jennifer Coghlan</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Melbourne Shoulder and Elbow Centre. 
31 Normanby St 
Brighton, Victoria 3186 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to design a system, using the Microsoft Kinect sensor, to assess proprioception at the shoulder. Proprioception is the ability to tell where your arm is in space and what it is doing without looking at it. 

Several different methods to assess proprioception have been outlined in the literature. These largely require expensive, specialised equipment, trained operators, and a large time commitment.

We plan to make the Kinect System for Proprioception of the Shoulder (KSPS) portable, easy to use, accessible, and able to assess proprioception in the shoulder in a matter of minutes. 

Being able to accurately, easily, and quickly measure shoulder proprioception in a wide range of healthcare settings will help assess the treatment and rehabilitation of patients with injuries, assist with pre- and post-operative patient assessment, and evaluate the effectiveness of new shoulder treatments (surgical and non-surgical).

The KSPS will be compared to 2 different, non-invasive assessment methods.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Office
First Floor, Room 111
Chancellery Building E 
24 Sports Walk
Monash Research Office
Clayton Campus
Monash University VIC 3800</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/03/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CF15/821 - 2015000370</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368322-2015000370 Appr.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368322-PICF_KSPS_group 1_complete.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368322-PICF_KSPS_group 2_complete.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368322-questionnaire_KSPS.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Simon Bell</name>
      <address>Melbourne Shoulder and Elbow Centre. 31 Normanby St Brighton Victoria 3186 

Monash University. A/Professor of Orthopaedic surgery.</address>
      <phone>+61, 03, 95928028</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>snbell@bigpond.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Brooke Driessen</name>
      <address>Melbourne Shoulder and Elbow Centre. 31 Normanby St Brighton Victoria 3186 Monash University. 

Medical Student, Monash University.</address>
      <phone>+61, 400650198</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bmdri1@student.monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Brooke Driessen</name>
      <address>Melbourne Shoulder and Elbow Centre. 31 Normanby St Brighton Victoria 3186 Monash University. 

Medical Student Monash University.</address>
      <phone>+61, 400650198</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bmdri1@student.monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Brooke Driessen</name>
      <address>Melbourne Shoulder and Elbow Centre. 31 Normanby St Brighton Victoria 3186 Monash University. 

Medical Student, Monash University.</address>
      <phone>+61, 400650198</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>bmdri1@student.monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>