<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83623">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/02/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/04/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000165280</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Bacterial contamination of antibacterial contact lens cases during daily wear of marketed contact lenses</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective, single-group, open label, bilateral daily wear study to investigate bacterial contamination of antibacterial contact lens cases when used in conjunction with marketed contact lenses in healthy volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Antibacterial contact lens case contamination during daily wear</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>New secondary ID. Please modify.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bacterial contamination of antibacterial lens cases when used in conjunction with marketed contact lenses on a daily wear (ie. wearing contact lenses during the day and removing prior to sleep) schedule</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will be dispensed with commercially available Purevision (balafilcon A) lenses with antibacterial lens case. Participants will wear lenses on a daily wear (ie. not sleeping in the lenses) basis for 4 months. Lens performance will be assessed at the baseline visit, and after 2 weeks, 1 month, 3 months and 4 months. Lens cases will be collected for microbiological analysis at the monthly visits. All participants will use the same brand of lenses and antibacterial lens case</interventions>
    <comparator>Historical control. The study to which we will be comparing this study used the same lens type, solution and similar visit schedule (up to the 3 month visit) as the current study, the only difference is the type of lens case used. In the historical control a regular lens case was used.</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess bacterial contamination of antibacterial lens cases when used in conjunction with marketed contact lenses on a daily wear (ie. contact lenses worn during the day and removed prior to sleep) schedule. Used contact lens storage cases will be collected at the end of the clinical trial and transferred to the Institute for Eye Research (IER) microbiology laboratory. Swab samples will be taken from inner surfaces of lens cases for routine microbiology isolation and identification. Contamination rate of used cases will be then determined based on data from microbiological analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 1 month, 3 months and 4 months from the baseline visit</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>None</outcome>
      <timepoint>N/A</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Be able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent;
Be at least 18 years old;
Be willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the investigator;
Have ocular health findings considered to be 'normal' and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses 
Is correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses 
Be experienced or may be inexperienced at wearing contact lenses</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses;
Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health;	
any active ocular disease that would affect wearing of contact lenses;
A need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication up to 12 weeks prior to and during the trial;
Any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings/are known to affect a participants ocular health/physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse manner or beneficial manner;  
Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial;
Previous corneal refractive surgery;
Contraindications to contact lens wear;
Currently enrolled in another clinical trial;
Participation in a clinical trial within the previous 2 weeks for dispensing studies; 
Allergy or intolerance to silver;
Pregnant women are excluded from the trial - formal testing of pregnancy is not required. A participant's verbal report is sufficient.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/04/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Institute for Eye Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker St
University of New South Wales (UNSW),
Kensington NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Institute for Eye Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14, Barker St
University of New South Wales (UNSW),
Kensington NSW 2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>hypotheses for this study include:
Study hypothesis is that antibacterial lens cases will have less contamination inside the lens storage case than a regular lens case. Primary purpsoe of the study is to assess bacterial contamination of antibacterial contact lens cases when used in conjunction with marketed contact lenses worn on a daily wear and monthly replacement schedule and to compare the results to a historical control.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Vision Cooperative Research Ventre and Institute for Eye Research Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/03/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Mark Willcox</name>
      <address>Institute for Eye Research 
Level 4, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14 Barker St
University of New South Wales (UNSW),
Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>m.willcox@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Jerome Ozkan</name>
      <address>Institute for Eye Research 
Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14 Barker St
University of New South Wales (UNSW),
Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Mr Jerome Ozkan</name>
      <address>Institute for Eye Research 
Level 5, Rupert Myers Building
Gate 14 Barker St
University of New South Wales (UNSW),
Kensington NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93857516</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93857401</fax>
      <email>j.ozkan@ier.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>