<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308323">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/08/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000726257</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Randomised Control Trial of the Flinders Model of Self-Management support for older Australians with complex chronic diseases, and their carers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An efficacy trial testing whether older Australians (aged 60 years or more) with complex chronic disease (2 or more conditions) who receive the Flinders Model of Self-Management support program experience improved health status and reduced burden on carers (i.e. spouses) compared to those who receive a health education program.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular disease (including: ischaemic heart disease, cerebrovascular disease/stroke, peripheral vascular disease, congestive heart failure, hypertension).</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Respiratory (including: asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease).</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Musculoskeletal (including: osteoarthritis, rheumatoid arthritis, other arthritis, osteoporosis, chronic back pain).</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Psychological (including: depression, anxiety, insomnia).</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Digestive (including: gastro-oesophageal reflux disease).</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Kidney disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes (Type 1 or Type 2).</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Non-end stage cancers.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants in the intervention group will receive the Flinders Model of Self-Management (Flinders Model). The Flinders Model provides a generic set of tools that enable health professionals to undertake a structured assessment of self-management behaviours, collaborative identification of problems and goal setting leading to the development of individualised self-management care plans. The Flinders Model is generic and not disease specific. 

The intervention will comprise a total of three home visits and four follow-up phone calls conducted over a six month period by health professionals (e.g. nurses, occupational therapists, social workers, psychologists) trained in the Flinders Model.

Participants in the intervention group will also receive their usual medical care throughout the trial.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the attention control group (Health Education) will receive a package of educational materials targeted to their specific health conditions. This package will be designed by a chief investigator who has considerable experience in the development of educational health promotion and prevention resource materials. 

The health professionals who deliver this package will make three home visits and four follow-up phone calls over a six month period (the same as staff implementing the Flinders Model).  Health professionals delivering the attention control will provide support, encouragement and empathy to clients but will not address formal self-management skills. The integrity of this intervention will be monitored by a chief investigator. 

Participants in the attention control group will receive their usual medical care throughout the trial.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health Status.

This measure includes questions about self-rated health, health distress, illness intrusiveness, pain, energy, fatigue and depression.

These items are from evaluation tools developed at the Stanford Patient Education Research Centre.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and final measurement at completion of a 6 month intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health Behaviours.

This measure includes questions about exercise behaviours (using the Stanford evaluation tools) and medication adherence (using the Medication Adherence Report Scale or MARS-5 by Horne &amp; Weinman, 1999).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and final measurement at completion of a 6 month intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived self-efficacy. 

This measure is one of the Stanford evaluation tools.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and final measurement at completion of a 6 month intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health Services Utilisation.

This measure is one of the Stanford evaluation tools.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and final measurement at completion of a 6 month intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome measure for carers is the Caregiver Risk Screen (Guberman, Keefe, Fancey, Nahmiash &amp; Barylak, 2001).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and final measurement at completion of a 6 month intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Health Education Impact Questionnaire (heiQ) for both patients and carers (Osborne, Whitfield &amp; Elsworth, 2007).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and final measurement at completion of a 6 month intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be aged 60 years or older with two or more of the following types of chronic conditions: 
- Cardiovascular (including: ischaemic heart disease, cerebrovascular disease/stroke, peripheral vascular disease, congestive heart failure, hypertension);
- Respiratory (including: asthma, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease);
- Musculoskeletal (including: osteoarthritis, rheumatoid arthritis, other arthritis, osteoporosis, chronic back pain); 
- Psychological (including: depression, anxiety, insomnia);
- Digestive (including: gastro-oesophageal reflux disease);
- Kidney disease
- Diabetes (Type 1 or Type 2); and
- Cancer.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will not be eligible for the study if they:
- Have a clinically dominant disease likely to shorten life expectancy (e.g. late stage cancer)
- Are unable to comprehend English.
- Suffer from significant cognitive impairment.
- Are severely depressed.	
- Are currently actively involved in a Chronic Disease Self-Management (CDSM) program.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation by phone call to hospital pharmacy where allocation schedule is held.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple permuted block randomisation (randomly arranged to maintain allocation concealment) will be used with stratification by gender and carer availability. STATA statistical software will generate these blocks.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/09/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>254</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Flinders University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Discipline of General Practice
Level 3, Health Sciences Building
Registry Rd
Bedford Park SA 5042</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Government Department of Health and Ageing</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Integration and Self-Management Section
Chronic Disease Branch
GPO Box 9848
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the trial is to address the current lack of evidence for what is arguably Australia's most widely used chronic disease self-management program, the Flinders Model.

It is hypothesised that older Australians who receive the Flinders Model of Self-Management support program will experience improved health status compared to those who receive a health education package.

A secondary objective of the study is to ascertain the impact of the Flinders Model on spouses (carers) who care for those with complex chronic disease. It is unknown whether the Flinders Model will increase or decrease carer burden and stress.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Flinders Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research and Ethics Department
Southern Adelaide Health Service Room 2A 221
Flinders Medical Centre
Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/07/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00188</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Sara Howard</name>
      <address>Rm 3.08 Level 3
General Practice
Health Sciences Building
Registry Rd
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7221 8517</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7221 8544</fax>
      <email>sara.howard@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Sara Howard</name>
      <address>Rm 3.08 Level 3
General Practice
Health Sciences Building
Registry Rd
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7221 8517</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7221 8544</fax>
      <email>sara.howard@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Sara Howard</name>
      <address>Rm 3.08 Level 3
General Practice
Health Sciences Building
Registry Rd
Bedford Park SA 5042</address>
      <phone>+61 8 7221 8517</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 7221 8544</fax>
      <email>sara.howard@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>