<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365306">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/11/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/12/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001361796</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of a stakeholder-driven model of weekend allied health services</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does a new stakeholder-driven model of weekend allied health services improve efficiency and safety of patient care for acute medical / surgical patients compared to weekday only
services?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>adults who are acute medical and surgical inpatients</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>New allied health weekend service developed following focus group interviews with health professionals (medical, nursing and allied health) on each ward to identify the most appropriate distribution of funds to different allied health professions. Services will include physiotherapy, occupational therapy, social work, nutrition and speech pathology weekend allied health service delivery. Services delivered are the same as those done on weekdays, although the intensity of weekend services is lower (fewer hours per ward) than weekday services. Services may include mobilization, chest physiotherapy, discharge planning, assessment and prescription of aids and equipment, swallowing assessment, dietary analysis and prescription, and counselling.
The duration of this intervention is 6 months: the new model of
weekend allied health service delivery will be rolled-out across 6 acute medical and surgical units one-by-one on a monthly basis.</interventions>
    <comparator>No weekend allied health service delivery. The duration of this
intervention is 7 months, as it includes one month with no weekend services in any of the 6 trial wards, plus the 6 months of gradual roll-out of new services.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of hospital stay. This will be analysed as mean length of stay and the proportion of patients who stay longer than their Australian Refined Diagnosis Related Group average inlier length of stay according to data published from the previous year.</outcome>
      <timepoint>on patient discharge from acute hospital ward.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of unplanned hospital readmissions</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 28 days post patient discharge from hospital.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Rate of adverse events: In-hospital falls, Code Blue / Medical Emergency Team calls, pulmonary embolus, DVT, unexpected death and hospital acquired pressure area, or ICU admission from the ward. These will be analysed as any adverse event and also adverse events within each subcategory. Falls will be analysed as total falls, falls resulting in any injury, and falls resulting in fracture, brain injury, or death.</outcome>
      <timepoint>at point of patient discharge or transfer from the study ward.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of complaints emanating from targeted wards (total and allied health specific) as captured through the hospital RiskMan database</outcome>
      <timepoint>monthly data extraction over the 7 month trial period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of compliments emanating from targeted wards (total and allied health specific) are captured through the hospital RiskMan database</outcome>
      <timepoint>monthly data extraction over the 7 month trial period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient discharge destination</outcome>
      <timepoint>at patient discharge from the study ward</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction using Victorian Patient Satisfaction Survey - Overall satisfaction domain (on a randomly selected subset of participants)</outcome>
      <timepoint>on day of patient discharge from the study ward</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient functional independence using Modified Barthel Index (on a
randomly selected subset of participants)</outcome>
      <timepoint>on day of patient discharge from the study ward</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Staff absenteeism (medical, nursing, allied health)</outcome>
      <timepoint>monthly data extraction over 7 month trial period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient health related quality of life using EQ-5D-5L (on a randomly selected subset of participants)</outcome>
      <timepoint>on day of patient discharge from the study ward</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients admitted to participating acute medical / surgical wards at Dandenong Hospital, Western Hospital or Royal Melbourne Hospital during trial period</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Data from patients who are exposed to both control and intervention conditions will be excluded from the analyses.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>As this is a stepped-wedge cluster RCT, patients will not be individually randomised. Extensive consultation with the managers and clinicians at participating sites has resulted in a list of wards agreeing to participate in this trial. Placement of each ward into the ward number location will be determined at random by an investigator blinded to ward identity.</concealment>
    <sequence>One investigator will develop pseudonyms for each ward involved in the study. Another investigator, blinded to the true identity of each pseudonym, will use a random number generator in Microsoft Excel to allocate ward number locations to each pseudonym. The first investigator will then be able to reveal which pseudonym represented which ward.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>The design of this trial is a roll-out stepped wedge cluster randomised trial.

Qualitative outcomes:
A small, cross-disciplinary group of health professionals (4-6 per ward) will be sought to describe the impact that changing
the model of weekend allied health service has had on staff workload and patient care during the trial. This information will be collected at group-interviews. interviews will be conducted with staff members from each ward prior to the trial, and again at the  post-trial timepoint. The aim is to explore their satisfaction with and experiences of the different weekend allied health service delivery models. We will also explore differing workplace pressures both during the weekend and on working days experienced under the different models, and also
workers' perspectives on and response to being involved in a research program undertaken with a disinvestment focus.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Stepped-wedge cluster RCT: Linear mixed model analyses will be used to construct the 95% confidence intervals that compare effectiveness and safety outcomes between groups. These models will nest patients within wards, treating both as random factors, to account for the clustered nature of this data. Weekend allied health service delivery model provided will be treated as a fixed factor. Data distributions will be examined (+/- transformations as indicated) as a part of model building. Data from patients who are exposed to both control and intervention conditions within each phase will be excluded from the analyses. Superiority analyses will be conducted. Interim analyses will be conducted as monthly outcome data becomes available. Data will be analysed at a site-specific level (relevant to this specific trial registration) and in a pre-planned meta-analysis across 6 studies (including this one) being conducted as a part of this research program.
The economic analysis will be a cost-effectiveness analysis from the hospital perspective that examines the incremental cost per patient treated. These costs will include the total cost of patients during their admission plus additional costs from an unplanned admission within 28 days. The primary analysis will examine data from all patients, while a secondary analysis will focus on patients present on a weekend. Data from patients who are transferred between wards in different study periods (ie. one without access to allied health services, one with access to allied health services) will be excluded from the analyses as will data
from patients who remain within the same ward over two or more weekends if they are allowed to access weekend allied health services during one weekend, and not allowed to access allied health services on another.

A framework approach will be used for the analysis of qualitative data collected as a part of this study.

The sample size in this study is governed by the patient through-put of the participating wards over the trial period. Current data from study wards indicates there will be approximately 7308 patients in total. 

We used the approach for conducting power analyses for stepped
wedge trials advocated by Hussey and Hughes based upon the Wald statistic. Using this approach, this trial has 96% power, given a 0.03 absolute increase (10% relative increase) non-inferiority margin from 0.30 (40%) for the proportion of patients who exceed their diagnosis specific inlier average length of stay.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/09/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>3/04/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>30/04/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>7300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>8444</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Dandenong Hospital - Dandenong</hospital>
    <hospital>Western Hospital - Footscray</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Health, Victoria</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box 4057
Level 16, 50 Lonsdale Street
Melbourne VIC 3000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council - Partnership Project Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Provision of allied health services over 7 days per week as opposed to 5 days per week for medical and surgical hospital inpatients is a practice inconsistently applied across health services in Australia. Presently, no evidence from randomised trials is available to guide service delivery for this population. These services have developed incrementally and in an ad hoc process at Monash, Western and Melbourne Health, in a similar experience to other health services around the state. It is possible that this is wasting resources that could be used for other purposes within these organisations. This study aims to examine whether removal and provision of weekend allied health services on general medical and surgical wards has an impact on length of stay on those wards, other indicators of quality and safety of service provision, and staff satisfaction. A novel research methodology will be applied using a stepped wedge cluster randomised controlled trial design to both incrementally remove existing services, then reintroduce services in a structured, stakeholder driven process (the 1st phase has been registered as a separate trial ID: ACTRN12613001231730).  At Monash, Western and Melbourne Health, new, stakeholder driven weekend allied health services will be incrementally rolled out across 6 wards over a 7 month period. Outcomes will be collected predominantly through existing data collection processes, although additional data will be collected through staff group and key informant interviews, and random sampling of patients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Haines, T, O'Brien, L, McDermott, F, Markham, D, Mitchell, D, Watterson, D, and Skinner, E (2013) A novel research design can aid disinvestment/reallocation from existing health technologies with uncertain effectiveness, cost-effectiveness and/or safety. Journal of Clinical Epidemiology (in press)</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Monash Health Human Research Ethics Committee B</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Directorate
Monash Health
Monash Medical Centre
246 Clayton Road
CLAYTON VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/11/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC00383</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/08/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Terry Haines</name>
      <address>Allied Health Research Unit 
Monash Health 
Kingston Centre 
400 Warrigal Road 
Cheltenham VIC 3195</address>
      <phone>+61392651822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>terrence.haines@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Terry Haines</name>
      <address>Allied Health Research Unit 
Monash Health 
Kingston Centre 
400 Warrigal Road 
Cheltenham VIC 3195</address>
      <phone>+61392651822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>terrence.haines@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Terry Haines</name>
      <address>Allied Health Research Unit 
Monash Health 
Kingston Centre 
400 Warrigal Road 
Cheltenham VIC 3195</address>
      <phone>+61392651822</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>terrence.haines@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Lisa O'Brien</name>
      <address>Allied Health Research Unit 
Monash Health 
Kingston Centre 
400 Warrigal Road 
Cheltenham VIC 3195</address>
      <phone>61399044100</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lisa.obrien@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>