<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81998">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/05/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/05/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000249459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Inhaled corticosteroids in Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Inhaled corticosteroids (ICS) in subjects with mild to moderate Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD). Does Bronchodilator reversibility and an asthmatic airway phenotype predict for ICS response?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Smoking-related COPD</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A randomised, placebo-controlled trial of inhaled fluticasone propionate (500 Mmicrograms twice daily) over six months on airway inflammation in mild to moderate COPD. </interventions>
    <comparator>The placebo is delivered via an identical metered dose inhaler device delivering a dry powder and the number of puffs and frequency are the same as the active FP arm.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in cellular airway inflammation as assessed by sputum, bronchoalveolar lavage and endobronchial biopsy.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and after six months intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Clinical symptoms (daily diary card) and the St George's Respiratory Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and six months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvements in lung function.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured by spirometry at monthly intervals throughout the study.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>A physician diagnosis of COPD and evidence of airflow limitation on spirometry. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Potential participants were interviewed and examined by a respiratory physician and any history suggestive of asthma, i.e. symptoms present in childhood, related atopic disorders, eczema or hay fever, significant day-to-day variability or prominent nocturnal symptoms, or a history of wheeze rather than progressive breathlessness and any previous use of ICS excluded that subject from further participation. Other exclusion criteria included significant uncontrolled co-morbidities such as diabetes, angina or cardiac failure, and other co-existing respiratory disorders, i.e. pulmonary fibrosis, lung cancer and bronchiectasis.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects were recruited by advertisement in local newspapers and placement of posters in clinic waiting areas in the hospital as well as on the notice boards of social and Veterans Affairs clubs. Potential participants were screened by a research nurse and physician. If eligible, they were randomised in the Hospital Pharmacy to the two trail treatments; fluticasone or placebo. The inhaled medications were dispensed from Pharmacy in identical inhaler devices and the research nurse and physician were blinded to treatment allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computerised generated random number programme designed to randomise subjects to fluticasone or placebo.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Patients were blinded to treatment and the investigators and research nurse were blinded to treatment. Results were all analysed by researchers blinded to treatment, i.e. cell counts were undertaken on coded slides with no information whatsoevr on subject, date or treatment.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2004</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>35</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>GlaxoSmithKline</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>United Kingdom</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>GlaxoSmithKline</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>N/A</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The use of inhaled corticosteroids is well established in asthma, but whether they exert a beneficial effect in smoking related chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is less clear. There are suggestions that patients with COPD who have a disease with similarities to asthma, i.e. a good spirometric response to salbutamol and a pattern of airway inflammation with predominant eosinophils (a characteristic cell in asthma), will respond more favourably to ICS. In this study, we tested our hypothesis that COPD patients with features similar to asthma, i.e. bronchodilator reversibility and an airway eosinophilia would exhibit a better response to ICS. We assessed this using airway biopsies at the beginning and end of a six month ICS study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The Royal Hobart Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>H6532</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr David Reid</name>
      <address>Third Floor
School of Medicine
University of Tasmania
Collin Street
Hobart TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62227043</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 62264894</fax>
      <email>d.e.c.reid@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr David Reid</name>
      <address>Third Floor
School of Medicine
University of Tasmania
Collin Street
Hobart TAS 7001</address>
      <phone>+61 3 62227043</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 62264894</fax>
      <email>d.e.c.reid@utas.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>