<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="251">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/08/2005</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/08/2005</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12605000244606</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Open Label Extension of a Clinical Trial of Intravitreal  Triamcinolone for Diabetic Macular Oedema (TDMX study)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An open Label Extension of the phase II/III clinical trial of intravitreal triamcinolone on the effects and safety of clinically significant diabetic macular oedema that persists after laser treatment</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>TDMX study</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Diabetic Macular Oedema</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Results from our own randomised clinical trial, combined with anecdotal reports from other groups, suggests that intravitreal triamcinolone safely improves vision and reduces swelling for up to 2 years in most eyes with diabetic macular oedema which persists or recurs despite laser treatment. There are no data on longer term efficacy and safety. We will conduct an open-label extension of a prospective, single centre, double-masked, placebo-controlled clinical trial of IVTA for diabetic macular oedema that persists or recurs after laser treatment. Sixty four of the originally enrolled 69 (93%) eyes are available to be followed. Triamcinolone (0.1 ml Kenacort 40, 40mg/ml triamcinolone acetate, Bristol-Myers Squibb pharmaceuticals, Australia) will be injected into the vitreous in eyes which have persistent macular oedema (&gt;250 micron) AND visual acuity of 6/9 or worse. Treatment will be withheld at the investigators discretion if 2 previous injections have failed to significantly (50 micron) reduce macular oedema. The duration of the patient follow-up is 3 years and the duration of the entire study is 4 years.</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increase of &gt;=5 letters at the 5-year study visit on a LogMAR chart compared with (a) the initial baseline level and (b) the level at the 2-year study visit. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 2 years and 5 years.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of moderate or severe adverse events over the 3 years of the open-label extension</outcome>
      <timepoint>at baseline, 2 years and 5 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in macular thickness by OCT.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 5 years follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Any change in visual acuity.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 5 years follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of laser treatments required.</outcome>
      <timepoint>up to 5 years follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients at the conclusion of the TDMO study. Currently we are still following 64 of the 69 (93%) eyes that were initially entered into the TDMO study that had reduced vision from diabetic macular oedema at baseline. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Not stated</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Uncontrolled glaucoma; Loss of vision due to other causes (e.g. age related macular degeneration, myopic macular degeneration);known allergies to triamcinolone acetate; patient is already receiving systemic steroid treatment; intercurrent severe disease such as septicemia; any condition which would affect follow-up or photographic documentation (e.g. geographical, psycho-social, media opacities).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/04/2005</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>64</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Mark Gillies</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Save Sight Institute
Department of Clinical Ophthalmology and Eye Health</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Applied for NHMRC project grant 2006 (#402573)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NHMRC project grant 402573</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>No</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>We will conduct an open-label extension of a prospective, single centre, double-masked, placebo-controlled clinical trial of IVTA for diabetic macular oedema that persists or recurs after laser treatment. Sixty four of the originally enrolled 69 (93%) eyes are available to be followed. The primary outcome measures will be an increase of =5 letters at the 5-year study visit on a LogMAR chart compared with (a) the initial baseline level and (b) the level at the 2-year study visit. The incidence of moderate or severe adverse events over the 3 years of the open-label extension will also be a primary outcome. Secondary outcomes will include change in macular thickness by OCT, any change in visual acuity and number of laser treatments required. Standardised protocols have been developed for intravitreal injection, macular laser treatment, refraction and measurement of visual acuity. Treatment with triamcinolone will be offered to all patients, whether they previously received placebo or active treatment, on exit from the TDMO study. IVTA will be administered in the clinic under local anaesthesia. Treatments will be given at least 6 months apart according to prospectively identified criteria that take into account the previous and current visual acuity and macular thickness measured by OCT. The safety data will be monitored 6 monthly by an independent Safety Monitoring Committee.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1. Larsson J, Kifley A, ZhuM, Want JJ, Mitchell P, Sutter FKP, Gillies MC. Rapid reduction of 
hard exudates in eyes with diabetic retinopathy after intravitreal triamcinolone - Data from a 
randomized, placebo controlled clinical trial. Acta Ophthalmologica in press, acceptance date: 
Feb 4 2008 (IF:1.458) 
2.  Gillies MC, Islam FM, Zhu M, Larsson J, Wong TY. Efficacy and safety of multiple 
intravitreal triamcinolone injections for refractory diabetic macular oedema. Br J Ophthalmol. 
2007; 91:1323-6. (IF:2.524) 
3.  Gillies MC, Sutter FK, Simpson JM, Larsson J, Ali H, Zhu M. Intravitreal triamcinolone for 
refractory diabetic macular oedema: two-year results of a double-masked, placebo-controlled, 
randomized clinical trial. Ophthalmology. 2006;113:1533-8. (IF:4.031) 
4. Gillies MC, Simpson JM, Gaston C, Hunt G, Ali H, Zhu M, Sutter FKP. 5-year results of a randomized clinical trial with open label extension of intravitreal triamcinolone for refractory diabetic macular edema. Ophthalmology, In Press accepted 16.1.09.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SESIAHS Northern Network Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>NSW Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/10/2004</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>05/272</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Mark Gillies</name>
      <address>Save Sight Institute
Department of Clinical Ophthalmology and Eye Health
University of Sydney
Sydney/Sydney Eye Hospital Campus
GPO Box 4337
NSW 2001</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93827309</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93827318</fax>
      <email>mark@eye.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Christine Gaston</name>
      <address>Save Sight Institute
Department of Clinical Ophthalmology and Eye Health
University of Sydney
Sydney/Sydney Eye Hospital Campus
GPO Box 4337
NSW 2001</address>
      <phone>+61 2 93827309</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 93827318</fax>
      <email>cgaston@eye.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>