<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308231">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/08/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/08/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000696291</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial assessing the impact of footwear, heel raises and orthoses on pain relief in children with calcaneal aphophysitis ("Sever's")</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>For children in pain with Calcaneal Apophysitis, how do footwear, heel raises or pre-fabricated orthoses impact pain relief.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Calcaneal apophysitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Shoe and heel raises - Heel raise with new footwear - Heel raise with current footwear Heel raises are made from high density ethylene vinyl acetate (EVA). Heel raises are to be worn for the period of the trial/pain. Removal of the device at a point of pain free. The children are to continue with their every day activities whilst wearing the treatment device. The footwear prescription/replacement intervention involves a shoe with a firm heel counter, dual density EVA midsole, rear foot control and an arch support. The intervention period for thi interventions is  2 months with followup period of 12 months. </interventions>
    <comparator>Shoe and orthoses - Pre-fabricated orthoses and new footwear - Pre-fabricated orthoses and current footwear The prefabricated orthoses (intervention is a Firm prefabricated device. The orthotics is a high density EVA device that limits pronation.The orthoses will be covered in a 2mm blown EVA cover which is designed to increase shock absorption . The orthoses is to be worn for the period of the trial/pain. The children are to continue their everyday activity whilst wearing the treatment devices. Wearing in advice is to be provided to the participants. The footwear prescription/replacement intervention involves a shoe with a firm heel counter, dual density EVA midsole, rear foot control and an arch support. 	
The  intervention period for this intervention/comparator is 2 months with a followup period of 12 months</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Oxford Ankle Foot Questionnaire  is taken from parent and child perspectives.  This scale contains domains of: 
- physical, school and play</outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial randomisation, 1 month, 2 month and 6 and 12 month time points</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Faces Pain Scale  
 7 point verbal rating scale of pain severity at rest, on palpation, during activity and after activity (post 2 hours)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At initial randomization, 1 month and 2 month time points. 
The faces pain scale was not completed at the 6 and 12 month point. The 6 and 12 month followup is via the phone so the use of this tool was not appropriate and therefore not undertaken. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Children between the ages of eight to twelve years.
- Subjective report of pain located on the calcaneal apophysis (ie. posterior aspect of heel) with pain on palpation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>14</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Recently (last 12 months) diagnosed fracture or tumour of the foot or leg
- Diagnosed infective, reactive or rheumatoid arthritis</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The trial is to be conducted in a Community Health Service. Patients with the diagnosis of Calcaneal Apophysitis are invited to participate. Verbal and written consent will be contained.  After accepting the invitation, the patients will be evaluated and assigned to the treatment groups according to the randomization. Allocation will be concealed using opaque and sealed envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuated block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/05/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/01/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>124</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Terry Haines</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Allied Health Clinical Research Unit, Kingston Centre, Kingston Rd, Cheltenham, Victoria, 3192</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Alicia James</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Peninsula Health Service
12-32 Hastings Rd Frankston, 
Victoria 3199</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Cylie Williams</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Peninsula Health Service
12-32 Hastings Rd Frankston, 
Victoria 3199</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study seeks to establish a clinically evidenced base treatment options for the relief of pain associated with calcaneal apophysitis in children between the ages of eight and fourteen years of age.

The heel bone is located at the most posterior plantar aspect of the foot. The Achilles tendon attaches into the posterior, lower aspect of the calcaneus and near this attachment is the calcaneus secondary growth centre.  This is the site of pain experienced during Calcaneal apophysitsis.

Treatment within this study includes two levels of shoe orthoses. A heel raise or prefabricated orthoses. Both of these interventions are widely available, mutually exclusive treatment approaches that are relatively low in cost.  The footwear prescription/replacement intervention involves a shoe with a firm heel counter, dual density EVA midsole, and rear foot control. The alternate condition in this factor is no footwear prescription/replacement with the participant wearing their own footwear.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health Human Research Ethics Commitee (HREC) B</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support Unit
Research Directorate
Level 4, Main Block,
Monash Medical Centre 
246 Clayton Road 
CLAYTON VIC 3168</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/11/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/09/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Peninsula Health Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>2 Hastings Rd Frankston</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/09/PH/65</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Terry Haines</name>
      <address>Allied Health Research Unit
Kingston Centre
Cnr Warrigal and Kingston Rds
Cheltenham, Victoria, 3192</address>
      <phone>+ 61 3 9265 1774</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9265 1577</fax>
      <email>Terrence.haines@southernhealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alicia James</name>
      <address>Peninsula Health Service
12-32 Hastings Rd Frankston 3199 Vic </address>
      <phone>+61 3 97848361</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9784 7053</fax>
      <email>aliciajames@phcn.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alicia James</name>
      <address>Peninsula Health Service
12-32 Hastings Rd Frankston 3199 Vic  </address>
      <phone>+61 3 97848361</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9784 7053</fax>
      <email>aliciajames@phcn.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Alicia James</name>
      <address>Peninsula Health 12-32 Hastings Rd Frankston  3199 Vic </address>
      <phone>+61 3 97848361</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>aliciajames@phnc.vic.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>