<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370235">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000277448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A pilot study to assess the efficacy of Tai Chi for Type 1 Diabetes</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pilot study to assess the efficacy of Tai Chi for Type 1 Diabetes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Y16GLIUX</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 1 Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a quasi randomized controlled trial. Participants with type 1 diabetes will be randomly allocated to the Tai Chi, or the usual medical care alone control group using a computer-generated randomization schedulebased on recruitment date.  The recruitment of control group participants will be conducted after completion of recruitment of Tai Chi group participants. In addition to usual care, participants in the intervention groups (Group A) will have two supervised instructor-led group training sessions per week during the first three months of intervention; followed by self-led training during the remaining three months.  Tai Chi group participants will receive a DVD/video tape demonstrating the Tai Chi program and will be encouraged to practice at home on days when they do not attend group sessions.  Each Tai Chi session will last approximately 1 to 1.5 hours with 30 minutes warm up, 30 minutes practice, and 6 to 30 minutes cool down.  During the second three months of follow up, Tai Chi group participants will have free choice (self-led training) and are encouraged to organize their own group training, or practice at home. All participants will continue to receive medical usual care from their GPs throughout the study and receive a monthly phone call to encourage them to maintain their usual care and reduce drop-out from the study. The control group (Group B) will participate in the study during the first 3 months and attend baseline and 3 months assessments. The control group will be offered the Tai Chi program at the end of the study.  .</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group is now a wait-list control group who will be offered the intervention after the 3 month study period.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>*HbA1c (to give an indication of average blood glucose over the preceding 2 - 3
months).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assess at baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>*Depressive symptoms using CESD Depression Scale (CESD 10)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assess at baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Leg strength using a chair-stand test (number of stands completed in 30 seconds) modified from the US Senior Fitness Test. </outcome>
      <timepoint>For Tai Chi Group (Group A): Assess at baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks.
For Control Group (Group B): Assess at baseline and 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health related quality of life (using SF36).</outcome>
      <timepoint>For Tai Chi Group (Group A): Assess at baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks.
For Control Group (Group B): Assess at baseline and 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure: assessed by blood pressure monitor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For Tai Chi Group (Group A): Assess at baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks.
For Control Group (Group B): Assess at baseline and 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index: weight and height are assessed by weight and measurement tape.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For Tai Chi Group (Group A): Assess at baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks.
For Control Group (Group B): Assess at baseline and 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference: assessed by measurement tape.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For Tai Chi Group (Group A): Assess at baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks.
For Control Group (Group B): Assess at baseline and 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lipids: assessed by blood samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For Tai Chi Group (Group A): Assess at baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks.
For Control Group (Group B): Assess at baseline and 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in medication, in particular total daily dose of insulin, dose of BP lowering therapy, lipid lowering therapy and depression (using questionnaire). This is a composite secondary outcome using a questionnaire named "Changes in Medication" which is designed specifically for this study. </outcome>
      <timepoint>For Tai Chi Group (Group A): Assess at baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks.
For Control Group (Group B): Assess at baseline and 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Physical activity using a one week recall questionnaire adapted from the Active Australia Survey.  The items have demonstrated acceptable test-retest reliability.</outcome>
      <timepoint>For Tai Chi Group (Group A): Assess at baseline, 12 weeks and 24 weeks.
For Control Group (Group B): Assess at baseline and 12 weeks.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>type 1 diabetes with HbA1c of 7.5 - 10% on stable insulin therapy; aged 18 - 70 years; no health or injury problems that would prevent doing the exercises; able to attend intervention sessions 2 times per week for 12 weeks and 'self-led' training for a further 12 weeks; and living in Brisbane.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*Contraindications for physical activity. Medical condition which contraindicates participation in physical activity as suggested by the American College of Sports Medicine 2000 (eg unstable angina, uncontrolled blood pressure &gt; 200/110 mmHg, orthostatic hypotension &gt; 20 mmHg, critical aortic stenosis, uncontrolled atrial or ventricular
arrythmia, uncontrolled sinus tachycardia, acute systemic illness or fever, moderate to severe heart failure, 3 degrees AV block, active pericarditis or myocarditis, recent embolism, thrombophlebitis, resting ST segment displacement [&gt;2mm]);
*Mental illness such as diagnosed bipolar disorder, schizophrenia etc (except depression).
*Currently pregnant or intending to become pregnant during the program;
*Existing pregnancy (or is within 3 months postpartum, or planning pregnancy in the next 12 months)
*Serious back, neck or knee problems
*A diagnosis of dementia, malignancy or life threatening disease
*Previous stroke, neurological or orthopaedic condition inhibiting exercise training
*Inability to complete the data collection forms or follow the program instructions</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This was a quasi randomized controlled trial. Participants with type 1 diabetes were randomly allocated to the Tai Chi or the usual medical care alone control group based on recruitment date.  The recruitment of control group participants was conducted after completion of recruitment of Tai Chi group participants. </concealment>
    <sequence>Based on recruitment date, participants with type 1 diabetes were quasi randomized to the Tai Chi or the usual medical care alone control group: the recruitment of control group participants was conducted after completion of recruitment of Tai Chi group participants. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/05/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>2/05/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>28/05/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>18/08/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>46</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>13</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>13/11/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>Data collected is being analysed</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <postcode>4102 - Woolloongabba</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Queensland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>St Lucia, QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Diabetes Australia Research Trust</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5th Floor, 39 London Circuit
Canberra City ACT 2600</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Type 1 diabetes affects 10 - 15 per cent of all people with diabetes. Based on the promising findings from our preliminary studies on the efficacy of Tai Chi for type 2 diabetes, the overall aim of the proposed project is to assess the effects of Tai Chi on type 1 diabetes. The proposed project is a two-group quasi randomized controlled trial. Participants with type 1 diabetes will be randomly allocated to the Tai Chi, or the usual medical care alone control group based on recruitment date. Metabolic/biochemical, physical, psychological, general health and well-being, and behavioral measures will be assessed at baseline, 3 and 6 months for intervention group and at baseline and 3 months for the control group. The main hypothesis of the project is that study participants with type 1 diabetes who receive the Tai Chi program will demonstrate improvements in indicators of glycaemic control, mental health and quality of life after 3 months of participation relative to participants who receive usual care alone over the same period. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Metro South Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Metro South Health

TRI 37 Kent Street Woolloongabba QLD 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/01/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/QPAH/775</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry />
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Queensland Medical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St Lucia, Brisbane Queensland 4072 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016000093</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Xin Liu</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland School of Medicine
Level 7, Translational Research Institute
37 Kent Street, Woolloongabba, QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 34437483</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>xin.liu@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Xin Liu</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland School of Medicine
Level 7, Translational Research Institute
37 Kent Street, Woolloongabba, QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 34437483</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>xin.liu@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Xin Liu</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland School of Medicine
Level 7, Translational Research Institute
37 Kent Street, Woolloongabba, QLD 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 34437483</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>xin.liu@uqconnect.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>