<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343314">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/08/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000852954</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Randomised, double-blinded clinical trial comparing intranasal and intramuscular naloxone for suspected opioid overdose</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised, double-blinded clinical trial comparing intranasal and intramuscular naloxone for reversal of suspected opioid overdose in clients of the Sydney Medically Supervised Injecting Centre</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1123-3396</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Suspected acute opioid overdose</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>800mcg/mL active naloxone intranasally and intramuscular placebo, or 800mcg/mL active naloxone intramuscularly and intranasal placebo.  This will be a 'once off' intervention.  If a second dose is required, this will be by the standard procedure of 800mcg/2mL intramuscularly. 

Contents of the vial for IN administration will be drawn into one syringe.  Staff will attach the syringe to a MAD, and administer 0.5mL (400mcg) into each nostril, depressing the syringe rapidly to achieve adequate atomisation. In this way, each study participants will receive 0.5mL of fluid in each nostril. Supportive care/oxygenation will be administered simultaneously, in accordance with existing MSIC clinical protocols  
Administration of the IM injection will be by standard practice of drawing the full 1ml into a single 5ml syringe and administering to the deltoid muscle via a 21g needle.</interventions>
    <comparator>1 mL saline for both intramuscular and intranasal placebo</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>No requirement of second ("rescue") dose of naloxone.  A second dose of naloxone may be required where the participant has not satisfactorily recovered 15 minutes after initial presentation of overdose, ie: if the participant's Glasgow Coma Score is less than 13 and/or their respiratory rate is less than 10/minute.</outcome>
      <timepoint>15 minutes after first presentation of overdose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Glasgow Coma Score (GCS) greater than or equal to 13 as observed by trained clinician</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first administration of naloxone until 10 minutes post administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiration rate greater than or equal to 10 per minute as observed by trained clinician</outcome>
      <timepoint>From first administration of naloxone until 10 minutes post administration</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All clients with symptoms/signs of an opioid overdose requiring Naloxone administration will be eligible for entry. This is based on existing and approved MSIC protocols and clinical criteria for overdose (reduced level of consciousness as measured by the Glasgow Coma Score, pinpoint pupils, respiratory depression and/or reduced oxygen saturations as measured by pulse oximetry).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Less than 18 years of age
Pregnant or suspected of being pregnant</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The participants will be enrolled into the study after the informed consent process has been completed and the participant has met all inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion criteria.  The allocation schedule will be held off-site by the pharmacy packaging company who are also responsible for the randomisation of the study packs.  All clients are potentially participants.  They are allocated to either the active intranansal or active intramuscular groups by virture of the randomisation procedure undertaken by the pharmaceutical packaging company who are supplying the study packs.  Participants will be consecutively enrolled during all operating hours of the service.  All clients of the MSIC will be informed of the study at registration.  The participant will be informed of their enrollment once they have fully regained consciousness.  If they decline to participate, the data will be eliminated from the database.</concealment>
    <sequence>MSIC staff will manage drug overdoses using existing clinical protocols. These state that a client will receive airway management and oxygenation either via a Hudson mask or artificial ventilation (bagging) for five minutes before being assessed as to the need for naloxone. Where a client’s response after five minutes is inadequate, naloxone will be administered by a registered nurse in accordance with existing standing orders from the Medical Director.
Study participants will receive a random allocation of naloxone in one of 2 forms:
a.	Active intranasal naloxone and intramuscular placebo, or
b.	Intranasal placebo and active intramuscular naloxone
Study packs will be pre-prepared and contain two clearly labelled vials – 1) Intranasal - naloxone 800mcg/1mL or placebo (1mL) for IN administration and 2) Intramuscular - 800mcg/1ml or placebo for IM administration. The vials will be labelled as intranasal and intramuscular, therefore the person administering the drugs will be blinded to the treatment arms.  
Contents of the vial for IN administration will be drawn into one syringe.  Staff will attach the syringe to a MAD, and administer 0.5mL (400mcg) into each nostril, depressing the syringe rapidly to achieve adequate atomisation. In this way, each study participants will receive 0.5mL of fluid in each nostril. Supportive care/oxygenation will be administered simultaneously, in accordance with existing MSIC clinical protocols  
Administration of the IM injection will be by standard practice of drawing the full 1ml into a single 5ml syringe and administering to the deltoid muscle via a 21g needle.
The study packs will be randomised using computer sequence generation techniques by the pharmacy packaging company who are supplying the study packs.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>12/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sydney Medically Supervised Injecting Centre</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>66 Darlinghurst Road, Kings Cross, NSW, 2011</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>NSW Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>73 Miller Street, North Sydney, NSW 2060</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Victoria University</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Cnr Nicholson and Buckley Street, Footscray, Victoria, 3011</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Burnet Institute</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>85 Commercial Road, Melbourne, Victoria, 3004</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to determine whether naloxone, an opioid reversal agent, is as effective for the treatment of acute opioid overdose when administered via the intranasal (IN) route compared with the intramuscular route. The term 'opioid' refers to a class of drugs that includes heroin, and the prescription medications oxycontin and morphine. Injection of  naloxone into a muscle is currently the standard method of emergency treatment for an opioid overdose on site at the Sydney Medically Supervised Injecting Centre. However, Naloxone can be administered as an intranasal (IN) spray using a 'mucosal atomisation device.  Evidence suggests that  IN naloxone may be an effective and practical alternative. The significant benefits of IN administration include removing the risk of needlestick injury (and thus any blood borne virus transmission risk) to treating personnel. This is particularly relevant to ambulance officers and paramedics, as well as other emergency health care workers, such as in the hospital emergency department setting. 

Additionally, given the ease of administration and reduced issues regarding disposal of used needles, the availability of IN naloxone may potentially be extended. This may include non health care workers who regularly deal with opioid overdose in community settings, and drug users peers, who are likely to be present in the event of an overdose.  The Sydney Medically Supervised Injecting Centre (MSIC) provides the ideal setting for this study.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District HREC Northern Sector</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room G71, Edmund Blackett Building, Prince of Wales Hospital, Randwick, NSW, 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/07/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/10/0146</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marianne Jauncey</name>
      <address>PO Box 293, Kings Cross, NSW, 1340</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9360 1191</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9360 0707</fax>
      <email>mjauncey@sydneymsic.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ian Flaherty</name>
      <address>PO Box 293, Kings Cross, NSW, 1340</address>
      <phone>+61 421 513 800</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9360 0707</fax>
      <email>iflaherty@sydneymsic.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ian Flaherty</name>
      <address>PO Box 293, Kings Cross, NSW, 1340</address>
      <phone>+61 421 513 800</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9360 0707</fax>
      <email>iflaherty@sydneymsic.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>