<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82703">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/03/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>8/04/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000172303</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of supplemental oxygen in patients with chronic hypercapnic respiratory failure</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Ventilatory and haemodynamic responses to supplemental oxygen in patients with chronic hypercapnic respiratory failure</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic hypercapnic respiratory failure due to obesity hypoventilation syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other respiratory disorders / diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>During a testing session, participants will breathe supplemental oxygen at 2 concentrations (fraction of inspired oxygen 28% and 50%) for 20 minutes each. There will be a one-hour washout period between interventions. A group of healthy control participants will be tested on only one occasion to allow us to document the normal response to 28% and 50% oxygen. Participants with hypercapnic respiratory failure will perform testing on two occasions: once at initial presentation with untreated hypercapnic respiratory failure; and once after three months of treatment with nocturnal positive airway pressure therapy. Nocturnal positive airway pressure will be prescribed and implemented in accordance with usual clinical practice at our centre.  Some data collected as part of this study will also be used for two measurement validation studies.  The first study is investigating the validity of arterialised venous blood gases against gold standard acid-base measures obtained from arterial blood gases.  A single pair of simultaneously taken arterialised venous and arterial blood samples taken during each testing session will used for this validation.  The second study is investigating the validity of respiratory inductive plethysmography in people with obesity hypoventilation syndrome and healthy controls.  Simultaneous repeated measurements of tidal volume, minute ventilation, and respiratory rate measured by the air/oxygen breathing circuit and a non-invasive respiratory inductance vest will be compared for this validation study.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a crossover trial in which each participant will receive supplemental oxygen at 2 concentrations (fraction of inspired oxygen 28% and 50%). Each participant will therefore act as their own control in the comparison between 28% and 50% oxygen.  A group of healthy participants (age and gender matched to each participant with chronic hypercapnic respiratory failure) will also be recruited into the study to document the normal response to 28% and 50% oxygen.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Arterialised venous carbon dioxide</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, at 5 minute intervals during treatment time of 20 minutes, and 10 minutes after treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Minute ventilation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, at 5 minute intervals during 20 minute treatment and 10 minutes after treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Chronic hypercapnic respiratory failure due to obesity hypoventilation syndrome or neuromuscular disease</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>90</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Acute respiratory failure or recent respiratory illness,
Obstructive pulmonary disease,
Pregnancy,
Unstable cardiac condition,
Psychiatric illness,
Non-english speaking</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients referred to the department of sleep medicine, Royal Prince Alfred Hospital (RPAH) for the management of chronic hypercapnic respiratory failure will be screened for eligibility. Healthy control participants will be recruited from a sample of cenvenience on the basis of age and gender matching for each participant with chronic hypercapnic respiratory failure. Eligible people will be verbally approached by the investigators and will be provided with an information for participants handout. The study is a randomised crossover design, so the two concentrations of oxygen will be given to each subject in random order. Order of intervention for each subject will be generated randomly and placed in sealed opaque envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Order of treatment will be written in an opaque sealed envelope for each subject. This order will be generated via the website www.randomization.com</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/04/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>28</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sleep Unit 11West
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Sleep Unit 11West
Missenden Road
CAMPERDOWN 2050</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>75 East Street
P.O. Box 170
LIDCOMBE NSW 1825</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In medical practice and published research, it is well documented that in some patients with respiratory failure due to chronic lung disease, breathing high concentrations of oxygen can cause carbon dioxide levels to increase, sometimes to potentially harmful levels. The effect of oxygen on patients who have chronic respiratory failure from other causes such as obesity hypoventilation syndrome is less clear. We would like to test the effect of two concentrations of oxygen on breathing pattern and carbon dioxide levels in patients who have chronic respiratory failure due to obesity hypoventilation syndrome. We expect that breathing high concentration oxygen will cause an increase in carbon dioxide levels and alter breathing pattern in this group.  It has also been proposed that this group, treating (and reversing) hypercapnia through the use of nocturnal positive airway pressure therapy may improve responsiveness to carbon dioxide, thereby minimising the potentially harmful effects of supplemental oxygen. We hypothesised that three months of treatment with nocturnal positive airway pressure would lessen any adverse responses to supplemental oxygen observed during testing at initial presentation.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney South West Area Health Service Ethics Review Committee (RPA Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Level 8, Building 14
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/03/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/RPAH/53</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/01/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carly Hollier</name>
      <address>Sleep Unit 11west
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Rd.
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>(02) 9515 8708</phone>
      <fax>(02) 9515 7196</fax>
      <email>carly.hollier@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Ms. Carly Hollier</name>
      <address>Sleep Unit 11west
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Rd.
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>(02) 9515 8708</phone>
      <fax>(02) 9515 7196</fax>
      <email>carly.hollier@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Carly Hollier</name>
      <address>Sleep Unit 11west
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Rd.
CAMPERDOWN NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>(02) 9515 8708</phone>
      <fax>(02) 9515 7196</fax>
      <email>carly.hollier@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>