<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320896">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>3/12/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000478011</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effect of postoperative radiation therapy on time to local relapse in patients with neurotropic melanoma of the head and neck.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised trial to evaluate the effect of postoperative radiation therapy following wide excision of neurotropic melanoma of the head and neck on time to local relapse (ANZMTG 01.09 RTN2 Study).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RTN2</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Clinicaltrials.gov ID NCT00975520</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>Australian and New Zealand Melanoma Trials Group (ANZMTG) 01.09</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neurotropic Melanoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Malignant melanoma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm A: Initial Radiation Therapy. Treatment: Other - Radiation Therapy. Patients are randomised to receive initial Radiation Therapy following surgery. Radiation therapy must begin within 14 weeks of surgery. 48Gy is delivered in 20 fractions over 4 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm B: Initial Observation. Other Intervention - Observation. Patients randomised to initial observation following surgery. If local failure (defined as relapse of disease at any time following randomisation) occurs , patients will receive radiation therapy of 48Gy in 20 fractions over 4 weeks.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to Local relapse. Measured from date of randomisation to time of diagnosis of local relapse. Relapse should be confirmed through biopsy, imaging or photographs as defined in the protocol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 5 years from date of randomisation. From baseline, first day of radiotherapy, weekly during radiotherapy, 14 weeks post surgery, then every 3 months for two years and every 6 months until 5 years follow up has been reached.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relapse free survival. Measured from date of randomisation to the development of relapse at any site (inclduing regional and distant metastasis). Relapse should be confirmed through biopsy, imaging or photographs as defined in the protocol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 5 years from date of randomisation. From baseline, first day of radiotherapy, weekly during radiotherapy, 14 weeks post surgery, then every 3 months for two years and every 6 months until 5 years follow up has been reached.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to relapse. Measured from date of randomisation to the development of relapse at any site (inclduing regional and distant metastasis). Relapse should be confirmed through biopsy, imaging or photographs as defined in the protocol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 5 years from date of randomisation. From baseline, first day of radiotherapy, weekly during radiotherapy, 14 weeks post surgery, then every 3 months for two years and every 6 months until 5 years follow up has been reached.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall Survival. Measured from date of registration until death from any cause. Clinical assessment and follow-up.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 5 years from date of randomisation. From baseline, first day of radiotherapy, weekly during radiotherapy, 14 weeks post surgery, then every 3 months for two years and every 6 months until 5 years follow up has been reached.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cancer Specific Survival. Measured from date of registration until death from melanoma. Patients will be clinically assessed throughout the trial</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 5 years from date of randomisation. From baseline, first day of radiotherapy, weekly during radiotherapy, 14 weeks post surgery, then every 3 months for two years and every 6 months until 5 years follow up has been reached.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patterns of Relapse. Measured as the exact site (local, regional or distant) and timing of each relapse. Relapse should be confirmed through biopsy, imaging or photographs, where possile, as defined in the protocol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 5 years from date of randomisation. From baseline, first day of radiotherapy, weekly during radiotherapy, 14 weeks post surgery, then every 3 months for two years and every 6 months until 5 years follow up has been reached.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Late Toxicity. Measred using the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTC AE) v 4.0.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 5 years from date of randomisation, measured every 3 months for 2 years post radiotherapy (RT), then every 6 months for 3 years.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of Life. Measured by the European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Lofe Questionnaire(EORTC QLQ-C30) questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 14 weeks post surgery, then every 6 months until 5 year follow-up is complete.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients may be included in the trial only if they meet all of the following criteria: 1. Aged 18 years or older 2. Has provided written informed consent for participation in this trial 3. Histologically confirmed neurotropic primary melanoma 4. Tumour located above the clavicle and below the jaw or occiput (neck primary) or above the jaw/occiput (head primary) 5. Complete macroscopic resection of all known disease with or without microscopic positive margins 6. No previous surgery for melanoma (other than complete macroscopic resection as stated above) 7. No evidence of in-transit, nodal or distant metastases as determined by clinical examination, and any form of imaging. 8. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status score of 2 or less 9. Life expectancy greater than 6 months 10. Patients capable of childbearing are using adequate contraception 11. Available for follow up</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who fulfil any of the following criteria are not eligible for admission to trial: 1. Women who are pregnant or lactating. 2. Intercurrent illness that will interfere with the radiation therapy such as immunosuppression due to medication or medical condition. 3. Clinical and/or MRI evidence of a named cranial or cervical nerve involvement by tumour 3. Inability to localise surgical bed on any form of imaging and/or surgical margins (cm) not known 5. Previous radical radiation therapy to the head and neck, excluding superficial radiation therapy to cutaneous Squamous Cell Carcinoma (SCC) or basal cell carcinoma, which is not within or overlapping the tumour bed. 6. High risk for poor compliance with therapy or follow-up as assessed by investigator 7. Patients with prior cancers, except: those diagnosed &gt; or = 5 years ago with no evidence of disease relapse and clinical expectation of relapse of less than 5%; prior successfully treated Level 1 cutaneous melanomas &gt; or = 2 years ago; or non-melanoma skin cancer; or carcinoma in situ of the cervix. 7. Albinism. 8. Participation in other clinical trials with the same primary endpoint.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients are registered on trial by implementing the registration and eligibility case report forms (CRFs) and forwarding by fax to the Trial Coordinating Centre.
Prior to patient enrolment, the investigator should ensure that all of the following
requirements are met:
路 The patient meets all inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion criteria should
apply.
路 The patient and investigator have signed and dated all applicable consent forms.
路 All baseline assessments and investigations have been performed.
路 The eligibility checklist has been completed, signed and dated.

The randomisation will be performed from
the Trial Coordinating Centre with all trial staff blinded to the codes, and with the codes maintained in a locked secure environment. The randomisation process itself will be nonblinded to the trial staff involved.</concealment>
    <sequence>Eligible patients will be randomised in the ratio of 1:1 between the two arms, initial radiation therapy and initial observation. Allocation to treatment will be balanced by institution and site (head or neck) using the minimisation technique.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/09/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/09/2009</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,SA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Princess Alexandra Hospital - Woolloongabba</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Adult Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>The Townsville Hospital - Douglas</hospital>
    <hospital>Calvary Mater Newcastle - Waratah</hospital>
    <hospital>Westmead Hospital - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>Peter MacCallum Cancer Institute - East Melbourne</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>The Poche Centre, Melanoma Institute Australia - North Sydney</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>Wollongong Hospital - Wollongong</hospital>
    <hospital>Genesis Cancer Care - Tugun - Tugun</hospital>
    <hospital>Toowoomba Hospital - Toowoomba</hospital>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>4350 - Toowoomba</postcode>
    <postcode>4224 - Tugun</postcode>
    <postcode>3004 - Prahran </postcode>
    <postcode>2500 - Wollongong</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>New York, Texas</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United Kingdom</country>
      <state>Norfolk and Norwich University Hospital</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Australia and New Zealand Melanoma Trials Group (ANZMTG)</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Poche Centre
40 Rocklands Rd
North Sydney NSW 2060</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Central Operations Office
Calvary Mater Newcastle
Locked Bag 7 HRMC
NSW 2310
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Princess Alexandra Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba
QLD 4102</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Bryan Burmiester</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Princess Alexandra Hospital
Level 2
Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba
QLD 4102</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG)</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Central Operations Office
Calvary Mater Hospital
Locked Bag 7
HRMC NSW 2310
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study is comparing surgery alone with surgery plus post-operative radiation therapy for patients with completely resected primary melanoma showing histological features of neurotropism.

Who is it for?
You may be eligible to join this study if you aged 18 years or above and have been diagnosed with neurotropic primary melanoma in the head/neck area.

Study details
Participants in this study will be randomly allocated (by chance) to one of two groups. Participants in one group will undergo radiation therapy over 4 weeks, commencing within 3 months of surgery. Participants in the other group will undergo surgery followed by observation only.

Participants will be monitored for up to 5 years in order to evaluate treatment effect, survival rates, and quality of life.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.anzmtg.org</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Princess Alexandra Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Princess Alexandra Hospital
Level 2, Building 35 (TAFE 3)
Ipswich Road
Woolloongabba Qld 4102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/03/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2009/039 03/03/09</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Narelle Williams</name>
      <address>The Poche Centre
40 Rocklands Rd
North Sydney NSW 2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99117322</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 99549435</fax>
      <email>narelle.williams@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Narelle Williams</name>
      <address>The Poche Centre
40 Rocklands Rd
North Sydney NSW 2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 99117322</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 99549435</fax>
      <email>rtn2@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Narelle Williams</name>
      <address>The Poche Centre
40 Rocklands Rd
North Sydney NSW 2060</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9911 7322</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 99549435</fax>
      <email>rtn2@melanoma.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Matthew Foote</name>
      <address>Princess Alexandra Hospital
Level 2
Ipswitch rd
Woolloongabba Qld
4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3176 3067</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Matthew.Foote@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>