<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368275">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/12/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000002482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Phase 1 Investigator Initiated Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability and Preliminary Effectiveness of AB-SA01 in Patients with Chronic Rhinosinusitis Associated with Staphylococcus aureus Infection</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Phase 1 Investigator Initiated Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability and Preliminary Effectiveness of AB-SA01 in Patients with Chronic Rhinosinusitis Associated with Staphylococcus aureus Infection</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1174-7807</utrn>
    <trialacronym>nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic rhinosinusitis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Investigator initiated, single-centre, safety study to evaluate the safety and preliminary effectiveness of three dosage regimens of AB-SA01 in patients with chronic rhinosinusitis associated with Staphylococcus aureus Infection. This is a first in human (FIH) study.

A total of 9 participants will be enrolled in the study.  Three (3) cohorts of three (3) patients will be serially dosed with AB-SA01 by nasal douche in the following three (3) dosage regimens:
Cohort 1:  Twice daily for a period of 7 days with  phage at a concentration of 3x10^8 pfu prepared in 240 mL of a NeilMed sinus rinse

Cohort 2:  Twice daily for a period of 14 days with phage at a concentration of 3x10^8 pfu prepared in 240 mL of a NeilMed sinus rinse

Cohort 3:  Twice daily for a period of 14 days with phage at a concentration of 3x10^9 pfu 


The investigational product, AB-SA01, is a sterile solution containing three active lytic S. aureus bacteriophages: Sa87, Sa83 and J-Sa36.  The biological material subject of the Application to Import Biological Materials is a therapeutic bacteriophage (phage) mix consisting of three individual (Sa87, Sa83 and J-Sa36) naturally occurring, not genetically modified, Staphylococcus aureus phages.

To ensure adherence to the intervention, patients will be given detailed instructions of how to use the product and follow up calls during the treatment will be made to ensure there is no confusion.  Further to this patients will be asked to return all used and unused vials at the completion of the study, at which time they will also be asked questions specifically about compliance.

</interventions>
    <comparator>N/A</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To assess the safety and tolerability of three dosage regimens of AB-SA01 in patients with Chronic Rhinosinusitis associated with Staphylococcus aureus infection.

Specific assessments to evaluate treatment safety include the following: the frequency and type of adverse events, clinical laboratory testing and vital signs.

This is the first time that AB-SA01 has been used in man, therefore no information is available regarding side effects in humans, so this study may involve risks that are currently unforeseen.  No side effects have been seen in animal studies, including one study which involved the treatment of lung infections similar to those that occur in humans. Given that treatment is localised to the sinuses, any side effects that could arise would most likely be localised to the sinuses. Treatment with bacteriophages has been reported to result in a slight increase in body temperature perhaps due to the bacteria killing effect of bacteriophages. 

All treated participants in Cohort 1 will be observed during the dosing period and will undergo telephone follow-up evaluations to Day 14. All treated participants in Cohorts 2 and 3 will be observed during the dosing period and will undergo telephone follow-up evaluations to Day 21. For the first treatment of AB_SA01 patients will be observed for 2hrs with vitals.  At the completion of treatment, participants' sinus regions will undergo an endoscopic review to ensure no damage or irritation has occurred during AB_SA01 topical treatment

Patients will also be asked to record there temperatures twice daily in an effort to detect fevers that may be experienced by the patients.  An action plan has been devised when a significant fever is detected as described below.

If temperature is determined to be 37.5 - 38.5 degrees Celsius it will be recommended that the participant takes Panadol/ Paracetamol plus or minus Ibuprofen. If at any time temperature is more than 38.5 degrees Celsius, the participant will be asked to contact the clinical site as soon as possible to discuss and arrange a urine test, repeat blood tests and/or an onsite visit for a medical examination. If the fever does not subside after 24 hours, the laboratory results will be reviewed and a decision will be made by the SMC as to whether the participant should continue treatment</outcome>
      <timepoint>For the first dose of AB_SA01 patients will be observed for 2hrs with vitals tested pre-dose, immediately post dose, 30 minutes post-dose and 2 hours post-dose. 

During the dosing period, patient will be asked to report any adverse events they experience which will be monitored by the study doctors.  

Within 14 days pre-dose and 1 day post-final AB_SA01 dose the patient will have an endoscopic examination of there nose.

1 week post final AB_SA01 dose, all patients will be asked to fill in SNOT-22 and VAS questionnaires, and will be followed up over the phone to discuss the patients health and sinusitis condition. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The preliminary assessment of effectiveness of three dosage regimens of AB-SA01 by determining the presence of S. aureus.

This outcome will be tested by taking a swab at day 1 post-treatment.  The swab will be taken from the middle meatus which is the drainage point of all sinuses.  The swab will be sent to an external pathology company for isolation and assessment of the bacteria present in the patients sinuses.  


</outcome>
      <timepoint>one day post-treatment completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The preliminary assessment of effectiveness of three dosage regimens of AB-SA01 by endoscopic evaluation by the Investigator using the Lund-Kennedy scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>With 14 days pre-dose and one day post-treatment completion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The preliminary assessment of effectiveness of three dosage regimens of AB-SA01 by patient assessment of symptoms.

To assess this outcome the patients will be asked to fill out two types of symptom questionnaires both pre and post treatment.  These include the Sino-nasal outcome test (SNOT-22) and the visual analogue scale (VAS) test.  These values are then compared to see if there is any change in patient symptom score following AB_SA01 treatment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Within 14 days pre-dose, one day post-treatment completion and 7 days post-treatment completion.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	Participants must have had at least two of the following symptoms of chronic rhinosinusitis (nasal discharge, postnasal drip, nasal obstruction, facial pain and pressure or lack of sense of smell) that has been previously persistent for greater than 3 months.
2.	Participants must have had at least one operation for their chronic rhinosinusitis but should be at least 6 weeks post- operative.
3.	Participants must have a positive sinonasal swab that indicates infection of S. aureus in the sinuses that is sensitive to AB-SA01 within 14 days of enrolment.
4.	Participants must show evidence of chronic sinusitis by direct endoscopic examination.
5.	Participants must have the ability to administer nasal lavage twice daily for the duration of the treatment period. 
6.	Participants must have impaired quality of life as measured by RSDI.
7.	Participants must be male or female aged between 18 and 70 years.
8.	Participants must be able to give written informed consent.
9.	Participants must have the ability and willingness to attend several visits to the study centre.
10.	Participants must have the willingness and ability to comply with the requirements of the protocol as determined by the Investigator.
11.	Participants using highly effective, double barrier contraception (both male and female partners) during the study and for 1 month following the dose of AB-SA01.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.1.	Participants with a diagnosis of cystic fibrosis or ciliary dyskinesia.
2.	Female participants who are pregnant or breastfeeding.
3.	Participants who are immunocompromised.
4.	Participants who are actively taking oral steroids or antibiotics.
5.	Participants who have used antibiotics within 1 month prior to screening.
6.	Participants who have been on active trial therapy within one month of screening.
7.	Participants who have a positive sinonasal swab that indicates presence of P. aeruginosa in the sinuses.
8.	Any clinically significant laboratory abnormality.
9.	Participants who are unlikely to comply with the study protocol or, in the opinion of the investigator, would not be a suitable candidate for participation in the study.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be pre-identified prior to clinical appointment and will be sent an invitation to participate including the PICF.  During the initial clinical appointment, if the patient fits the inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion criteria, they will be asked to participate.  They will be tested for Staphylococcus aureus infection and subsequently the S. aureus is tested for AB-SA01 sensitivity. They will also have a blood test to identify any abnormal blood results that would exlude them from the trial.  If the S. aureus is sensitive to AB-SA01 infection and the blood results are normal the patients will receive treatment.  Cohort allocation will be determined by study stage, no random allocation will occur.</concealment>
    <sequence>N/A</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>In this study all patients will be treated with the same product AB_SA01, however there will be three distinct groups of patients:
Cohort 1:  Twice daily AB_SA01 treatment for a period of 7 days with  phage at a concentration of 3x10^8 plaque forming units (pfu) prepared in 240 mL of a NeilMed sinus rinse.

Cohort 2:  Twice daily AB_SA01 treatment for a period of 14 days with phage at a concentration of 3x10^8 pfu prepared in 240 mL of a NeilMed sinus rinse.

Cohort 3:  Twice daily AB_SA01 treatment for a period of 14 days with phage at a concentration of 3x10^9 pfu prepared in 240 mL of a NeilMed sinus rinse.
</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The sample size chosen for this study was selected without formal statistical power calculation.  Approximately 9 participants will be enrolled in the study, 3 in each cohort.  These sample sizes are based on what is reasonable in this patient population for preliminary evaluation of safety. It has been determined to be adequate to meet the study objectives.

The following data presentations and summaries will be performed. No formal inferential statistics will be p</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1 / Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>9/12/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>16/09/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>9</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>9</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>14/10/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital - Woodville</hospital>
    <postcode>5011 - Woodville South</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
28 Woodville rd,
Woodville South, 5011
South Australia, Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Adelaide, Department of Surgery</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Department Otorhinolaryngology 
3C Level 3 Main Building, The Queen Elizabeth Hospital, Woodville Road, Woodville 5011, South Australia, Australia
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ampliphi Biosciences Pty. Ltd.</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>AmpliPhi Australia Pty Ltd
Unit 7 27 Dale Street
Brookvale 2100 NSW
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>CRS is a debilitating inflammatory and infection based condition, affecting up to 9% of the Australian population (AIHW, 2010).  Currently available therapies to treat this condition include steroids, antibiotics and surgical intervention (Fokkens et al., 2012).  Unfortunately there remains a cohort of patients that are resistant to both medical and surgical interventions who experience persistent CRS symptoms, which is termed recalcitrant CRS (rCRS).  The presence of bacterial biofilms in the sinonasal tract is one aspect of the condition shown to contribute to this recalcitrance and symptom persistence.  Biofilms are 1000-fold more resistant to antibiotics compared to non-biofilm bacterial, making them resistant to the current place antibiotic therapies that are used to treat infections in CRS.  There is, therefore, a need to develop novel therapies that are effective against these biofilms if we are to succeed in treating these rCRS patients.  

Bacteriophage-based treatment, AB-SA01, could be the answer to the problem of biofilms in rCRS.  Bacteriophages or phages, identified almost 100 years ago, are bacterial viruses that specifically target bacterial cells, leading to cell death.  Given their specific mechanism of action, bacteriophages are not able to infect mammalian cells, and have thus far shown few adverse effects when applied to humans for use as antimicrobial treatments (Chanisvilli, 2012; Brussow, 2005). 
The Primary endpoint of the study is to:
1.	To assess the safety and tolerability of three dosage regimens of AB-SA01 in patients with Chronic Rhinosinusitis associated with Staphylococcus aureus infection.

The secondary objectives of the study are:
2.     The preliminary assessment of effectiveness of three dosage regimens of AB-SA01 by endoscopic evaluation by the Investigator using the Lund-Kennedy scale.
3.	The preliminary assessment of effectiveness of three dosage regimens of AB-SA01 by patient assessment of symptoms.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>We have just commenced data collation, statistical analysis and will be proceeding with manuscript  writing soon.
Abstract has been accepted for oral presentation at the ASOHNS ASM in March 2017 </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>HUMAN RESEARCH ETHICS COMMITTEE (TQEH/LMH/MH)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
Ethics: DX465101
Ground Floor, Basil Hetzel Institute
28 Woodville Road
WOODVILLE SOUTH  SA  5011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/12/TQEHLMH/43</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter-John Wormald</name>
      <address>Department of Otorhinolaryngology
The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
28 Woodville Rd,
Woodville South 5011
South Australia
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 7158</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peterj.wormald@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Peter-John Wormald</name>
      <address>Department of Otorhinolaryngology
The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
28 Woodville Rd,
Woodville South 5011
South Australia
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 7158</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peterj.wormald@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mian Ooi</name>
      <address>Basil Hetzel Institute
University of Adelaide
37 Woodville Rd
Woodville South, 5011
South Australia
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 7158</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mianli.ooi@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Mian Ooi</name>
      <address>Basil Hetzel Institute
University of Adelaide
37 Woodville Rd
Woodville South
5011
South Australia
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8222 7158</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mianli.ooi@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>