<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366415">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>28/05/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/06/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000593639</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving the engagement of patients suffering from wisdom tooth problems in shared clinical decision making using different formats of health information toward achieving better healthcare outcomes.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Impact of Guiding Patients Suffering from Wisdom Tooth Problems through Dental Open Educational Resources (DOER) on Enhancing Shared Clinical Decision-Making and Improving Health Care Outcomes: A Randomized Controlled Trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1157-3828 </utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Wisdom tooth problems</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention group (study group):  
Participants of this group will receive a list of recommended Dental Open Educational Resources as an additional resources for patient educational materials one month before consultation. Participants can access these information at any time as they are freely accessable online. Knowledge and anexiety will be assessed in pre-consultation survey. Patient participation in shared decision making,, satisfaction and quality of life will be evaluated post intervention pre-consultation and at  one month post consultation/ surgery. via a survey thatwill be posted to them. In the pre-consultation survey, participants will be asked if they reviewed the provided resources. A sample of 25 participants will be invited for structured interview that will take place face to face, online, over the phone depending on patient preference.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group: 
Participants will receive standard care patient education (verbal communication and information leaflets) at consultation. At consultation participants will be requested to fill in a pre-consultation survey to assess their knowledge and anxiety. Patient participation in shared decision making, satisfaction and quality of life will be evaluated through a one  month post consultation/ surgery survey that will be conducted either online or by post depending on patient preference.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.Engagement in shared clinical decision-making using dyadic SDM-Q-9 for patients and SDM--9-Doc for clinicians</outcome>
      <timepoint>At consultation:
1. For patient: using SDM-9Q for patients of consultation survey. 
2. For Clinicians: using SDM-Doc of clinicians survey.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2.Oral and general heath related QoL using OHIP-14 and EuroQol-5D-5L.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (one month before consultation) to get a baseline estimate and on follow-up servey (one month after consultation/ surgical removal). </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>1.Patient knowledge measured using wisdom tooth quiz which was designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (one month before consultation) and at Pre-consultation (in waiting room before consultation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>2.Anxiety levels using IDAF-4C.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (one month before consultation) and at Pre-consultation (in waiting room before consultation).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>3. Satisfaction using the satisfaction scale which was designed specifically for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (one month before consultation) and At follow-up (one month after consultation/ surgical removal)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>4. Gap between the preferred decisional role and actual decision experience using decisional role preference scale. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline (one month before consultation) and at consultation using consultation survey (after consultation section) that will be completed immediately after consultation and handed to the receptionest..</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>5. Decision outcomes: difference between number of teeth refered for extraction and teeth decided to be extracted, treatment pathway and anaesthetic option.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Clinican's  survey (at consultation). </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants who have been diagnosed  with wisdom teeth problems otherwise fit and healthy, aged 18-39 years, internet users, signed the informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>39</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>non internet user, have serious health problems, non English speakers.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The study subjects will be recruited from patients referred for  wisdom teeth removal at Adelaide Dental Hospital and East Adelaide Oral and Maxillofacial Clinic. Using patient referral information, participant will be approached by the unit secretary who is normally have an access to patients details providing the eligible participants with the study information sheet, consent form, baseline survey. One the reciept of the signed consent form and the baseline survey a decision will be made by the researcher either to include or exclude from the study. The  included participants then will be randomly allocated to either study or control group using a computerized variable block randomization by the researcher. Allocation is not concealed to the researcher.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Equal arm variable block randomization with random seed using radomization.com website. After participants were found to be eligible for inclusion in the study, each participant is provided with a sequential number that is continuous for the study. Depending on the flow of received baseline survey and the signed consent form, a randomization plan is generated from this website when an even number of participants was available: 2, 4, 6..... Each generated randomization plan is has the participant's continuous sequential number, the randomly allocated group, randomization date and time and seed number saved  This method allows for blindness the researcher to participants random allocation  and no need for an independent person to carry out the randomization.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Descriptives, correlations, t-test, linear regression, logit regression.

Sample size calculation
Each group will consist of 250 participants , This calculation was based on  the mean of OHIP scores of Australian population survey is 5.82 (SD=8.59). In a recent study carried out by Brennan (2013) and minimum important difference of OHIP 5-point scale (Locker et al., 2004) will generate a sample size of n=47 per group based on alpha 0.05 and power of 80%. However  Brennan et al. (2012) have reported that, 25% of  persons have reported worsening in their oral health mainly due to dental extractions. This will require multiplying the sample by four times resulting in a sample size of (n+188 per group).
As some of our study participants may not undergo surgical extraction because of a shared clinical decision-making, this will require inflation of sample size to compensate for this percentage or recruit until sample yield is achieved. In addition, this sample size is exceeds the required sample size for using EuroQoL-5D as treatment outcomes variable (Roset, 1999).

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/06/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>30/06/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>500</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Enrolling by invitation</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Adelaide Dental Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Frome Road, Adelaide, south Australia, 5000.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Research Centre for Population Oral Health, 
The University of Adelaide.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>122 frome Street, Adelaide, South Australia, Australia, 5005</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>East Adelaide Oral and Maxillofacial Clinic</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>1 Hutt Street
 Adelaide 5000
 South Australia
 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Kamal Hanna</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Australian Research Centre for Population Oral Health, 122 Frome Street, Adelaide, South Australia, 5005</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>A/ Prof David Brennan</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Australian Research Centre for Population Oral Health, 122 Frome Street, Adelaide, South Australia, 5005</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>A/ Prof Jason Armfield</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Australian Research Centre for Population Oral Health, 122 Frome Street, Adelaide, South Australia, 5005</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Paul Sambrook</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Adelaide Dental Hospital, frome road, Adelaide, South Australia, 5000.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Nowadays, many patients are surfing the internet for health information. However. patients surfing the internet without guidance may result in their requesting inappropriate care or complex treatments. Recently, it was found that, nearly half of Australian heath care professionals (not including dentists) are not recommending online health websites to their patients. This was due to lack of time and knowledge of reliable sources. Therefore, it is argued in this research that, guiding patients through patient centered open educational resources (based on website content analysis) will enhance the process of a shared clinical decision making and improve the healthcare outcome (oral and general health related quality of life). This research will contribute to patient education theory and fill the gap in knowledge regarding the applicability of using DOER in dental patient education. Moreover, this research will improve the clinical practice through enhancing the engagement of patients in the process of a shared clinical decision making leading to effective healthcare outcomes. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>2. Hanna, K., Brennan, D., Armfield, J., &amp; Sambrook, P. 2014, The Quality and Readability of Online Health Information Concerning Wisdom Teeth Problems, 54th Annual Scientific Meeting of the International Association for Dental Research Australian &amp; New Zealand Division. Brisbane, Australia.

3. Hanna, K., Brennan, D., Armfield, J., &amp; Sambrook, P. 2014, The Quality and Readability of Online Health Information Concerning Wisdom Teeth Problems, Oral presentation at IADR-ANZ Conference, Brisbane, Australia.

4. Hanna, K., Brennan, D., Armfield, J., &amp; Sambrook, P. 2014, The Quality and Readability of Online Health Information Concerning Wisdom Teeth Problems, poster presentation for Colgate competition at IADR-ANZ Conference, Brisbane, Australia.

5. Hanna K, Brennan D, Sambrook P, Armfield J. 2015, Why dentists need to provide patients with guidance in surfing the internet? School of Dentistry Research Day. Adelaide: The University of Adelaide.

6. Hanna K, Brennan D, Sambrook P, Armfield J. 2015. Third molars on the Internet: A guide for assessing information quality and readability. Interact J Med Res. 4 (4), PMID: 26443470.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Adelaide</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Branch
THE UNIVERSITY OF ADELAIDE 
SA 5005 </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/05/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HS-2013-023</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
Adelaide
SA
5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/14/RAH/160</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>22/05/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/366415-Dr Hanna RAH HREC approval letter.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>David Brennan</name>
      <address>Australian Research Centre for Population Oral Health, 122 Frome Street, adelaide, South Australia, 5005.</address>
      <phone>+61, 08, 83134046</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>david.brennan@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kamal Hanna</name>
      <address>Australian Research Centre for Population Oral Health, 122 Frome Street, Adelaide, South Australia, 5005. </address>
      <phone>+61, 08, 83135626</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kamal.hanna@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kamal Hanna</name>
      <address>Australian Research Centre for Population Oral HealthAustralian Research Centre for Population Oral Health, 122 Frome Street, Adelaide, South Australia, 5005.</address>
      <phone>+61, 08, 83135626</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kamal.hanna@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Kamal Hanna</name>
      <address>Australian Research Centre for Population Oral Health, 122 Frome Street, Adelaide, South Australia, 5005.</address>
      <phone>+61, 08, 83135626</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kamal.hanna@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>