<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369431">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/10/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/10/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001122549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Improving the treatment of depression and quality of life in Parkinsons disease: A randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of mindfulness based cognitive therapy for the treatment of depression in idiopathic Parkinson's disease.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1175-1631</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's disease </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Quality of life</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention is an 8-week Mindfulness based cognitive therapy (MBCT) program, which is designed to reduce depression, anxiety, and stress, with a particular focus on preventing relapse of depression. The MBCT program that will be used for the current study is an adapted version of Segal, Williams, and Teasdales's 2012 MBCT program which has been specialised for people with PD. This intervention program consists of 8 sessions (90 minutes each) which will run once per week across an 8-week period. The program targets skills such as concentration, awareness of thoughts, emotions, and bodily sensations, decentering, acceptance, letting go, and being in a state of being rather than doing. An additional session (lasting approximately one hour) for partners/carers of the participants with PD will be conducted early in the MBCT treatment (around session 2). This session will aim to help partners/carers of people with PD to understand psychological problems that occur in PD such as anxiety. It will also aim to teach them about mindfulness and encourage them to become actively involved in the mindfulness practice homework with their partner/carer. The MBCT group sessions will involve face to face sessions in small groups of participants (approximately 6-8). Trainee clinical psychologists will be running the sessions. There will be a register of attendance at sessions.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control treatment in this study is an 8-week Supportive Psychotherapy program. Sessions will run for 120 minutes, once weekly for an 8-week period. The researchers of this study will write a brief Supportive Psychotherapy treatment plan for the clinicians to follow. This will include standard non-specific common factors of psychotherapy including empathy, using the therapeutic relationship, group cohesion, active listening, group support, paraphrasing, genuineness, warmth and positive regard. The SP treatment plan is based on a detailed text on non-specific, common factors (Yalom, 1995). The participants will not be provided with any specific coping skills. Groups will include a small number of participants (6-8). Trainee clinical psychologists will run these sessions. A register of attendance will be completed each session to monitor adherence. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean score on Geriatric Depression Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 3 and 6 months following the intervention </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean score on the Geriatric Anxiety Inventory</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 3 and 6 months following intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean score on Parkinson's Disease Questionnaire (Quality of life measure)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 3 and 6 months following intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean score on the Caregiver Burden Inventory as completed by the partner/caregiver </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 3 and 6 months following the intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean score on the UPDRS (motor assessment)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post-intervention, and 3 and 6 months following the intervention </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Due to significant difficulties recruiting participants who met the DSM-5 criteria for Depressive Disorder the eligibility criteria was broadened to include people who did not meet this criteria and presented with mild to no symptoms of depression. The rest of the inclusion criteria remain the same. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Study criteria was changed to include participants on Deep Brain Stimulation. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Central randomisation </concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using procedures like coin-tossing and dice-rolling</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size calculations were performed for the primary outcome variable, which is on an intent-to-treat basis, using procedures for determining power for longitudinal designs with attrition. Power analyses assumed a two-tailed alpha of 0.01, 3 assessment points (with baseline serving as a covariate), and attrition rates of 25%. Based on a large effect size (0.8), with .80 power and 2 groups, a minimum sample of 50 participants is required (25 per group). Based on 6-8 participants per group 4 rounds of each group treatment (MBCT or SP) will be required. 

The data will be analysed using a GLMM. Participants will be allocated according to a computer-generated algorithm. Generalised linear mixed models (GLMMs) will be conducted in SPSS-V22 to test the hypotheses, which will use all data present at each assessment point thereby reducing subject attrition on power. In the primary and secondary outcomes, a Condition x Time interaction is predicted. Mediation will be tested via the Sobel test. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>15/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/06/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>19/09/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>16</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>22/05/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Fremantle Hospital and Health Service - Fremantle</hospital>
    <postcode>6102 - Bentley</postcode>
    <postcode>6959 - Fremantle</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kent St, Bentley WA 6102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Fremantle Hospital Medical Research Foundation </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Alma Street, Fremantle, WA, 6959</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Fremantle Hospital and Health Service</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Alma Street, Fremantle, WA, 6959</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this research is to see if a psychological treatment based on meditation principles called Mindfulness Based Cognitive Therapy (mindfulness) is an effective treatment for depression in Parkinsons disease. The study will compare an 8-week group MBCT treatment to a placebo-control group of Supportive Psychotherapy. The aim is to determine whether the MBCT program effectively reduces anxiety, depression, and caregiver burden and increases in quality of life and motor symptoms. This study will also introduce a session to the MBCT program which is specifically for partners/carers. This session will aim to help carers of people with PD to understand the principles of mindfulness to encourage them to become involved in the mindfulness practice with their partner/loved one. The aim of this is to help improve the person with Parkinsons disease use of mindfulness and also decrease stress for carers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kent St, Bentley, WA, 6102</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Metropolitan Health Service (SMHS) Human Research Ethics Committee (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Fiona Stanley Hospital
102-118 Murdoch Dr, Murdoch WA 6150</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/04/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/11/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Egan </name>
      <address>Curtin University
School of Psychology and Speech Pathology 
Kent Street, Bentley, WA, 6102</address>
      <phone>61 8 9266 2367</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Egan@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Caitlin Timms</name>
      <address>Curtin University
School of Psychology and Speech Pathology 
Kent Street, Bentley, WA, 6102</address>
      <phone>61410277969</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caitlin.timms@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sarah Egan </name>
      <address>Curtin University
School of Psychology and Speech Pathology 
Kent Street, Bentley, WA, 6102</address>
      <phone>61 8 9266 2367</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>S.Egan@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Caitlin Timms</name>
      <address>Curtin University School of Psychology and Speech Pathology Kent Street, Bentley, WA, 6102</address>
      <phone>61410277969</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>caitlin.timms@postgrad.curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>