<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363087">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/09/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/10/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001058864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Continuous versus intermittent noninvasive blood pressure measurement in patients undergoing surgery in the beach-chair position</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The influence of the continuous versus intermittent noninvasive blood pressure measurement on hemodynamic stability in patients undergoing surgery in the beach-chair position</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1135-1722</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>blood pressure measurement</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>hemodynamic stability</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>beach-chair position surgery</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Maintanace of the near-normal pressure values throughout the surgery in beach-chair position (using fluids and vasopressors) with continuous noninvasive measurement of blood pressure obtained by the CNAP device (volume clamp method).</interventions>
    <comparator>Maintanace of the near-normal pressure values throughout the surgery in beach-chair position (using fluids and vasopressors) with standard intermitent noninvasive measurement of blood pressure. The noninvasive pressure will be measured using upper arm cuff each 3-5min according to procedure and patient status, unlimited number of additional measurements is allowed in case of need.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time proportion (out of the anesthesia duration) with pressure outside the near-normal values (patients normal +/- 20%). 
Analysis per retrospective off-line analysis of continuous pressure readings: Time duration of periods with systolic pressure above the patients normal + 20% or below the pateints normal - 20% will be sumed up. Proportion of these times to total anesthesia duration will be assessed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Anesthesia duration</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time proportion (out of the anesthesia duration) with hypotension (patients normal - 20%).
Analysis per retrospective off-line analysis of continuous pressure readings: Time duration of periods with systolic pressure below the pateints normal - 20% will be sumed up. Proportion of these times to total anesthesia duration will be assessed.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Anesthesia duration</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number and rate of postoperative complications (infectious and organ complications - based on the list used in the POSSUM scoring system). Minor screened complications incl. postoperative nause and vomiting, anemia requiring transfusion, fever etc. Major complications incl. organ failure, reoperation, surgical site infection, sepsis, pneumonia etc.
Complications will be assessed per daily visits of treating physician (not member of the study team) and summarized before discharge by a blinded study team member.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Postoperatively until discharge.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in the Short Orientation Memory Concentration Test</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline (at preanesthesia visit), 20 + 60 minutes after waking from anesthesia</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients undergoing surgery in beach-chair position (throid gland surgery, shoulder surgery/arthroscopy)
General anesthesia
Given and signed informed consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>obvious perfusion abnormality on the side of measurement, vascular implants or known neuronal / neuromuscular disease on the side of measurement, peripheral edema</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All patients undergoing elective surgical procedures in beach-chair position will be deemed eligible for inclusion. During routine preanesthesia visit patients meeting inclusion and exclusion criteria will be informed about the possibility to participate in the study. After inclusion the informed consent will be obtained (and signed). Randomization in 1:1 proportion (stratified thyroid gland surgery / shoulder arthroscopy) will be performed on the OR by the treating anesthesiologist (member of the research team) - sealed envelopes technique. The randomization sheat will be marked by the patients ID and consealed till the data statistical analysis. All other members of the team as well as patient him/herself and other hospital staff will be unaware of the treatment group allocation.</concealment>
    <sequence>The sealed envelopes technique with the simple urn randomization method will be used to randomly allocate patients into the continuous and intermitent arm. Equal randomization in proportion 1:1 will be used. Startified in the thyroid gland surgery (20:20) and shoulder arthroscopy (20:20).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Treating anesthesiologist and study nurse will be aware of the treatment group allocation. Other staff as well as the patient will be blinded.</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dpt. of Anesthesia and Intensive Care of the Faculty of Medicine Plzen - Charles University Prague</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University hospital and The Faculty of Medicine in Plzen
Husova 3
Plzen
30605</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Czech Republic</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Charles University Research Fund (project number P36)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Faculty of Medicine in Plzen
Husova 3
Plzen
30605</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Czech Republic</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>CNSystems Medizintechnik AG</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Reininghausestrasse 13
Graz
8020</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Austria</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Jan Benes, MD</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Dpt. of Anesthesia and Intensive Care
The University hospital and The Faculty of Medicine in Plzen
Husova 3
Plzen
30605</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Czech Republic</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim of the study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of the use of a completly noninvasive device enabling the continuous measurement of blood pressure in patients with increased risk of cerebral malperfusion due to position changes (beach-chair position) under general anesthesia in compariosn to the standard anesthesia care. As a measure of safety/eficacy the proportion of time outside the near-normal ranges of blood pressures and hypotensive periods will be used in combination with assesment of mental abilities derrangements in the early postoperative course and potential postoperative morbidity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Local ethics committee of the Charles University hospital in Plzen</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Charles University hospital in Plzen
E.Benese 13
Plzen
305 99</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/05/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Czech Republic</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Assoc.Prof. Eduard Kasal MD, CSc</name>
      <address>Dpt. of Anesthesia and Intensive Care
The University hospital and The Faculty of Medicine in Plzen
Husova 3
Plzen
30605</address>
      <phone>+420377104380</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>kasal@fnplzen.cz</email>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jan Benes MD</name>
      <address>Dpt. of Anesthesia and Intensive Care
The University hospital and The Faculty of Medicine in Plzen
Husova 3
Plzen
30605</address>
      <phone>+420377104381</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>benesj@fnplzen.cz</email>
      <country>Czech Republic</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>