<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="320563">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/04/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/06/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000516088</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of Candesartan combined with steroid pulse therapy and tonsillectomy on clinical remission in Immunoglobulin A (IgA) nephropathy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Multicenter, Randomized, Parallel study of Angiotensin Receptor blockade (Candesartan) Combined with Steroid Pulse Therapy and Tonsillectomy in Immunoglobulin A (IgA) nephropathy Patients to assess remission rate and improvement rate of proteinuria and hematuria</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>Combination Therapy, Candesartan, Steroid pulse and Tonsillectomy in Ig A nephropathy (CAST IgA )</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Cochrane Renal Group 120700128</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>IgA nephropathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Candesartan, which is added on the control treatment (steroid pulse therapy, tonsillectomy and antiplatelets )
Candesartan and steroid pulse therapy administered simultaneously from baseline to 6 months, tonsilectomy done between 1-6 months, and candesartan restarted if necessary from 12-24 months.
1. Candesartan: it is started with the dose of 2-8mg oral tablet once daily and increased the dose up to 12 mg once daily if patients did not achieve remission of proteinuria for 6 months. The dose prescribed at discretion of treating clinician based on individual patient characteristics.
2. steroid pulse therapy: a) methyl prednisolone 500 mg/d b) intravenousy administered for serial 3 days followed by oral prednisolone (PSL) 30 mg/d for subsequent 4 days. c) three courses for initial serial 3 weeks followed by oral PSL 30 mg once alternative day for next 2 months. The dose of PSL was withdrawn by 10 mg alternative day every 2 months and finally discontinued at 6th month.
3. Tonsillectomy: it is done between 1-6 months by otorhinolaryngologist.
4. Antiplatelets (dilazep dihydrochloride):  it is administerd orally at a dose of 300 mg /day for 24 months.
5. At 12th month, candesartan is restarted if patients did not achieve remission of proteinuria.Candesartan is restarted with the dose of 2-8mg oral tablet once daily and increased the dose up to 12 mg once daily if patients did not achieve remission of proteinuria for next 12 months. The dose prescribed at discretion of treating clinician based on individual patient characteristics.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control treatment : steroid pulse therapy and tonsillectomy and antiplatelets
Description of each treatments are described in " Description of intervention(s) ".

At 12th month, candesartan is started, similarly to intervention group, if patients did not achieve remission of proteinuria.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Remission rate of proteinuria and hematuria
1) assess morning urine by urine analysis and chemistry
2) definition of remission 
  a) proteinuria: urinary protein less than 0.2 g/gCr 
  b) hemeturia : urinary renal blood cell counts less than 5/ high power field</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months, 12 months and 24 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduction rate of proteinuria and hematuria, which is assess morning urine by urine analysis and chemistry</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months, 12 months and 24 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in kidney function, which is assessed by estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months, 12 months and 24 months following randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.Histologically proven Ig A nephropathy patients 

2.Serum creatinine levels is &lt; 1.5 mg/dl

3.Urinary protein excretion is equal to and more than 0.5g/g creatinine and 

urinary red blood cell counts is equal to and more than 10/high power field

4.Histologically proven focal active lesion</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>15</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>69</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.Recent onset of cardiovascular disease 2.Severe hypertension (high systolic blood pressure &gt;200mmHg or high diastolic blood pressure &gt;100mmHg

3.Diabetes mellitus

4.Patient on angiotensin converting enzyme inhibitors (ACEI) or other angiotensin receptor blockades (ARB)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>sealed opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomization by using a permuted-block method with stratification according to proteinuria and years of disease onset</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <state>Okinawa</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Cardiovascular medicine, nephrology and neurology, University of the Ryukyus</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>207, uehara, Nishihara-cho, Okinawa 903-0215</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Japan</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of the Ryukyus</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>207, uehara, Nishihara-cho, Okinawa 903-0215</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Japan</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Remission of hematuria and proteinuria is a strong predictor of stable renal function in IgA nephropathy. Steroid pulse therapy combined with tonsilectomy can achieve relatively higher remission rate of hematuria and proteinuria in IgA nephropathy. Some of the patients can maintain the remission even after discontinuation of drug therapy.  Drug-free remission may be critical for patients, especially younger women. We conduct the study to evaluate the effectiveness of Candesartan combined with steroid pulse therapy and tonsillectomy on clinical remission in IgA nephropathy. Additionally, we evaluate the efficacy of Candesartan, the dose of which is increased regardless of blood pressure, on the remission rate in the patients, who do not achieve the remission by the combination steroid pulse therapy and tonsilectomy .</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>1 Hotta O, et al: Tonsillectomy and steroid pulse therapy significantly impact on clinical remission in patients with IgA nephropathy. Am J Kidney Dis 38: 736-743, 2001

2 Miyazaki M et al: A multicenter prospective cohort study of tonsillectomy and steroid therapy in Japanese patients with IgA nephropathy: A 5-year Report. Contrib Nephrol 157: 94-98, 2007</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The ethics review board of the University of the Ryukyus</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>207, uehara, Nishihara-cho, Okinawa 903-0215</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Japan</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Yusuke, Ohya</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiovascular Medicine, Nephrology, Neurology, University of Ryukyus, 207 Uehara, Nishihara-cho, Okinawa 903-0215, Japan</address>
      <phone>+81 98 895 1150</phone>
      <fax>+81 98 895 1416</fax>
      <email>ohaya@med.u-ryukyu.ac.jp</email>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr. Kentaro Kohagura</name>
      <address>Department of Cardiovascular Medicine, Nephrology and Neurology, University of The Ryukyus, 207 Uehara, Nishihara-cho, Okinawa 903-0215, Japan</address>
      <phone>+81 98 895 1150</phone>
      <fax>+81 98 895 1416</fax>
      <email>kohagura@med.u-ryukyu.ac.jp</email>
      <country>Japan</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>