<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335881">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>4/10/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>18/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000868088</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of venesection on insulin resistance and oxidative stress in people with non-alcoholic fatty liver disease.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Impact of therapeutic venesection on Insulin Resistance and oxidative stress in non-alcoholic fatty liver disease.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>IIRON study TWO</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Not applicable</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hepatic steatosis</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Iron overload</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Insulin resistance</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diseases of the mouth, teeth, oesophagus, digestive system including liver and colon</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Therapeutic venesection in NAFLD patients with hepatic steatosis and hyperferritinaemia. 
a) Participants will be randomised into either the intervention group and non-intervention group. 
b) For the intervention group, fortnightly venesection will be performed by the haematologist until serum ferritin level has reached 50 ug/L. Haemoglobin and iron studies will be checked  in between venesection sessions and all adverse events either related or not related to the venesection will be captured.  
c)  Removal of iron by venesection in patients with NAFLD has a number of parallel effects on iron metabolism, oxidative stress, insulin resistance and subsequent liver damage.  Specifically, venesection reduces circulating and intracellular iron.  This reduces serum free fatty acid (FFA) levels and oxidative stress thereby improving insulin sensitivity independent of changes in adiponectin or body fat mass.  This results in an improvement in hepatic steatosis, inflammation and fibrosis.     
Hepcidin and hepatocyte and adipocyte intracellular iron content modulates  insulin sensitivity. 
d) Duration of the study is 6 months. Frequency of venesection will depend on the participant's  haemoglobin and ferritin levels. It is likely that partcipants will need fortnightly venesection initially and taper towards longer intervals between sessions gradually.</interventions>
    <comparator>Controls will not undergo venesection but receive the same standard dietary and lifestyle counselling as the intervention group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in hepatic Steatosis and a reduction of  quantitative liver iron load by using Magnetic Resonance Imaging-Ferriscan  (MRI-Ferriscan ), in participants with non-alcoholic fatty liver disease.</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of treatment (6 months)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in insulin resistance by Homeostasis Model Assessment (HOMA).</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of treatmnent (6 months)

Measured with fasting blood test.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Biomarkers of oxidative stress</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of treatment (6 months)

Measured with Fasting blood test</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum hepcidin level</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of treatment (6 months)

Measured with Fasting blood test</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum adipocytokine level</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of treatment (6 months)

Measured with Fasting blood test</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Abdominal ultrasound demonstrated hepatic steatosis within three months of study entry.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Unable to provide informed consent, Ischaemic heart disease. Anaemia, pregnancy or lactation. Ferritin &lt;50ug/L. Venesection in the last 12 months prior to study entry. Other causes of liver disease: positive hepatitis B serology, positive hepatitis C serology, auto-antibodies, alpha-one anti-trypsin level and ceruloplasmin. Acute or chronic inflammatory conditions. Hereditary haemochromatosis (C282Y/C282Y or C282Y/H63D, HFE gene mutation). Alcohol consumption &gt;20 grams/day for males or &gt;10 grams/day for females. Secondary causes of NAFLD (corticostearoids, gastro-intestinal bypass). Use of anti-oxidants (vitamin E or C) or anti-Tumor Necrosis Factor (TNF) agents (pentocifylline). Poor glycaemic control diabetics-glycated haemoglobin &gt;8%  (HbA1c&gt;8%). Decompensated cirrhosis International Normalised Ratio (INR&gt;1.3, albumin &gt;35mg/dl or bilirubin &gt;20 mmol/L or ascites or hepatic encephalopathy. Malignancy (excluding basal cell or squamous cell skin cnacers)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Visit 1: Screening. Obtain informed consent, inclusion/exclusion criteria, record medical history including alcohol and smoking habits. Physical examination including blood pressure, height, weight, and waist circumference. Completion of Alcohol Quantification and Physical activity Questionaires. Fasting blood test and urine sample for storage. Appointment for Ferriscan. Ferriscan wil be performed in a major teaching hospital. 

Visit 2: Randomisation (within 2 weeks of screening). Inclusion/exclusion criteria, referral to see a dietician, dietary and lifestyle counselling, ECG for venesection group, appointment with haematologist for venesection. 

For the venesection (intervention group):- Fortnightly venesection until serum ferritin level is&lt;50 ug/L-skip one session of venesection if anaemia (Hb&lt;115g/L (female) &lt;135g/L (male), Further maintenance on a three monthly basis or as frequently as required to keep ferritin level &lt;50g/L. Iron studies will be performed prior to each venesection-vital signs and any adverse events will be recorded at each visit. 

Visit 3: Month 3 (for both groups). Check for any adverse events since last visit. Record any change in medications, alcohol and smoking habits. Brief physical examination including blood pressure, weight, and waist circumference. Completion of  Physical activity questionaire. Fasting blood test and  urine sample for storage. 

Visit 4: Month 6 (End of study for both groups) Check for any adverse events since last visit. Record any change in medications, alcohol and smoking habits. Brief physical examination including blood pressure, weight, and waist circumference. Completion of  Physical activity questionaire. Fasting blood test and collection of urine sample for storage. Appointment for Ferriscan.
Allocation codes will be sealed in thick brown envelopes and kept by the study coordinator.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation: Eighty participants will be recruited across two major teaching hospitals and be randomised into: 40 in venesection (group 3) and 40 in non-venesection (group 4). Numbers were divided equally between the 2 sites with study numbers from 01-80. Hospital 1: Numbers 01-40 (20 for group 3 and 20 for group 4). Hospital 2: Numbers 41-80 (20 for group 3 and 20 for group 4). Participants were then randomised to study numbers allocated for each site.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/04/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/05/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/04/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <hospital>Greenslopes Private Hospital - Greenslopes</hospital>
    <postcode>4120 - Greenslopes</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Raine Medical Research Foundation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Hollywood Specialist Centre
95 Monash Avenue
Nedlands WA  6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Raine Medical Research Foundation.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Hollywood Specialist Centre
95 Monash Avenue
Nedlands WA  6009</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Western Australia (WA) Department of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>189, Royal Street
East Perth
Western Australia  6004</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>WA Department of Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>189 Royal Street
East Peth
WA 6004</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This trial aims to examine the effect of removing iron in people with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (fatty liver). We hypothesize that removing iron will improve insulin resistance (how the body produces insulin in response to glucose), reduce oxidative stress in the body and reduce the amount of fat in the liver.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>na</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Poster presented at AASLD, 01Nov 2013-05 Nov 2013 Washington DC.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Group Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>A Block, 2nd Floor
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands WA  6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/03/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2008-008 (#2)</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>18/01/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Associate Professor Leon Adams</name>
      <address>Liver Transplant Unit
G Block, 6th Floor
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands   WA   6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93463228</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 93463098</fax>
      <email>leon.adams@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Leon Adams</name>
      <address>Liver Transplant Unit
G Blsok, 6th Floor
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands  WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93463983</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 93463098</fax>
      <email>helena.ching@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Helena Ching</name>
      <address>Liver Transplant Unit
G Blsok, 6th Floor
Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital
Hospital Avenue
Nedlands  WA 6009</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93463983</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 93463098</fax>
      <email>helena.ching@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Leon Adams</name>
      <address>Liver Transplant Unit G Blsok, 6th Floor Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital Hospital Avenue Nedlands WA 6009  
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 8 93463228</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>leon.adams@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>