<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362574">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>6/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000628842</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of oral nicotinamide (vitamin B3) on nonmelanoma skin cancer incidence and actinic keratoses in renal transplant recipients: a randomised controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Randomised double blinded placebo controlled trial to assess the effect of oral nicotinamide on numbers of new nonmelanoma skin cancers in immune suppressed adult renal transplant recipients with a history of at least two histologically confirmed nonmelanoma skin cancers within the previous 12 months</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1131-4130</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Nonmelanoma skin cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Actinic keratoses</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Basal cell carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cutaneous squamous cell carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Cognitive function</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Kidney function after transplant</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Non melanoma skin cancer</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Renal and Urogenital</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Kidney disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Oral nicotinamide 500mg orally or placebo twice daily for 6 months</interventions>
    <comparator>Placebo tablet containing calcium hydrogen phosphate anhydrous and cellulose- microcrystalline; taken orally twice daily for 6 months</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of nonmelanoma skin cancers (basal cell carcinomas + cutaneous squamous cell carcinomas + squamous cell carcinomas in situ + keratoacanthomas) as assessed by histological examination of lesions detected during dermatological follow up</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Numbers of actinic keratoses assessed by clinical counting</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 0, 2, 4 and 6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Numbers of nonmelanoma skin cancers confirmed by histology</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2 and 4 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Numbers of basal cell carcinomas confirmed by histology</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2, 4 and 6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Numbers of cutaneous squamous cell carcinomas (including squamous cell carcinomas in situ and keratoacanthomas) confirmed by histology</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 2, 4 and 6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skin cancer recurrences, occurring at sites of previously histologically confirmed skin cancer, assessed by histology</outcome>
      <timepoint>Skin cancers recurring at any timepoint during the 6 month study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skin tumour markers of skin cancer proliferation, differentiation, apoptosis, immune cell infiltration and DNA damage assessed with immunohistochemistry; SCC differentiation and BCC subtype assessed by histology</outcome>
      <timepoint>On skin cancers developing at any timepoint during the 6 month study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety profile of oral nicotinamide on patient and graft outcomes in renal transplant recipients, assessed by serum creatinine and eGFR, full blood count, electrolytes, liver function tests; urinary protein</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, 2 weeks, 4 weeks, 2, 4 and 6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in cognitive function assessed with standardised neuropsychological tests in the cognitive domains of memory, concentration, attention and executive function 
-Hopkins Verbal Learning Test  Revised (HVLT-R) (Brandt, 1991).

-Controlled Oral Word Association (COWA) (Spreen et al, 1998).

-Stroop Color and Word Test (Spreen and Strauss, 1998).

-Trail Making A &amp; B (Reitan, 1955).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in self-reported quality of life, assessed by: 

-EORTC QLQ-C30 Cognitive Function items, PROMIS cognitive abilities item pool, cognitive general concerns item pool
-PROMIS fatigue item pool
-PROMIS anxiety item pool
-PROMIS depression item pool
-PROMIS Global Health Short Form for global health perception</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and 6 months after randomisation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Prior renal transplant performed more than 12 months ago.
2. Current immune suppression.
3. Past history of at least two histologically confirmed nonmelanoma skin cancers within the past 12 months.

Equivalent to year 8 spoken and written English skills are required to participate in the cognitive component of the study. Patients with inadequate English skills may still participate in the other aspects of the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Recent transplant less than 12 months ago.
2. Unstable renal function.
3. Treatment for acute rejection in the past 3 months.
4. Significant liver disease (transaminases &gt;3x normal), severe cardiac disease
5. Internal malignancy, metastatic SCC or invasive melanoma within the past 5 years.
6. Need for ongoing carbamazepine use (possible interaction with nicotinamide).
7. Patients unavailable for follow up for the duration of the study because of general frailty, geographical or social reasons.
8. Gorlins syndrome or other genetic skin cancer syndrome.
9. Huge numbers of current skin cancers or large areas of confluent skin cancer at baseline preventing accurate assessment and counting of new skin cancers; field treatment for AKs within the past 4 weeks, preventing accurate assessment of AKs.
10. Pregnancy or lactation (any women of childbearing potential will be required to use contraception throughout the study).
11. Patients commenced on acitretin or other oral retinoids, or mTOR inhibitors within the past 6 months; 
12. Patients taking supplemental nicotinamide within the past 4 weeks.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All eligible patients enrolled in the study will be enetered into the central randomisation system. The patient number assigned at the time of randomisation will be the primary identifier for the patient. Randomisation will be performed by the NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre which will provide a centralised tele-randomisation service that will randomly allocate patients to nicotinamide or placebo groups in a 1:1 ratio stratified by gender, baseline skin cancer count and use of oral retinoids and/or mTOR inhibitors. The pharmacist will provide the drug kit allocated by the system for the patient, recording the kit number in the pharmacy log. The study number, patient name and MRN will then be written on the medication bottle.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomised to nicotinamide or placebo groups in a 1:1 ratio  using a permuted blocks method stratified by gender, baseline skin cancer count (6 or more versus 2-5 previous skin cancers), and whether or not they are taking oral retinoids, or mTOR inhibitors</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/06/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/08/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>21/03/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>22</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney Medical School,
University of Sydney NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australasian College of Dermatologists Scientific Research Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The Australasian College of Dermatologists
Suite 2A, Level 2
9 Blaxland Road
RHODES NSW 2138</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to assess the effect of nicotinamide (vitamin B3) on nonmelanoma skin cancer incidence in renal transplant recipients. Who is it for? You may be eligible to join this study if you are aged 18 years or more and have had a renal transplant more than 12 months ago. You should be experiencing current immune suppression and have a past history of at least two confirmed nonmelanoma skin cancers within the past 12 months. Trial details Participants in this trial will be randomly (by chance) allocated to one of two groups. Participants in one group will take two 500mg nicotinamide (vitamin B3) tablets daily for 6 months, whilst those in the other group will take two placebo (inactive) tablets daily instead. Participants will not know which group they are in until the end of the trial. Participants will be regularly assessed over the treatment period to determine the efficacy of nicotinamide in preventing nonmelanoma skin cancers and the safety of this treatment in renal transplant recipients.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital 
Missenden Rd
Camperdown NSW 2050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>13/02/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/RPAH/337</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Diona Damian</name>
      <address>Dermatology, GH3
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Rd
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+612 9515 8295</phone>
      <fax>+612 9565 1048</fax>
      <email>diona.damian@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Diona Damian</name>
      <address>Dermatology, GH3
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Rd
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+612 9515 8295</phone>
      <fax>+612 9565 1048</fax>
      <email>diona.damian@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Robyn Dalziell</name>
      <address>Dermatology, GH3
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Rd
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+612 9515 6788</phone>
      <fax>+612 9565 1048</fax>
      <email>robyn.dalziell@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Diona Damian</name>
      <address>Dermatology, GH3 Royal Prince Alfred Hospital Missenden Rd Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+612 9515 8295</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>diona.damian@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>