<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370055">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/11/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/11/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001606471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Do moderate protein, high carbohydrate predominantly plant-based diets assist in appetite control and improve short-term health outcomes in individuals aged 65-75 years?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Do moderate protein, high carbohydrate predominantly plant-based diets assist in appetite control and improve short-term health outcomes in individuals aged 65-75 years?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1189-6455</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>metabolic syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Metabolic disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Eligible participants will be invited to attend a baseline testing morning at the RPA-CPC Clinic. Male and female subjects aged 65-75 years will be randomly assigned to one of four diets for 4wks. Each of the dietary interventions will be manipulated to provide 15% of energy as protein but will differ in the ratio of plant to animal proteins and the proportion of carbohydrate and fat. 

The 4 dietary arms are as follows:
Arm 1: high plant to animal ratio (15% protein (38% plant, 62% animal), 61% carbohydrate, 24% fat)
Arm 2: high plant to animal ratio (15% protein (18% plant, 82% animal), 48% carbohydrate, 37% fat) 
Arm 3: low plant to animal ratio (15% protein (18% plant, 82% animal), 61% carbohydrate, 24% fat)
Arm 4: low plant to animal ratio (15% protein (38% plant, 62% animal), 48% carbohydrate, 37% fat)

Prepared meals, snacks and fruit will be delivered once per week for 4 weeks to participants homes. Participants will be asked to eat ad libitum, to only consume study foods delivered to them and to keep a weighed food diary. Participants will be provided with scales and a food diary and will be asked to keep a weighed record of their intake. Participants will be asked to provide their own drinks and to avoid soft drinks and alcoholic beverages during the study. Each participant will be contacted by phone to ensure the first food delivery has been received and for 4 x 48hr food recalls during the intervention. </interventions>
    <comparator>Comparisons will be as follows:
Arm 1 versus Arm 2
Arm 3 versus Arm 4
Arm 1 versus Arm 3
Arm 2 versus Arm 4


</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Study energy and macronutrient intake (MJ): Participants will be given ad libitum access to study food and will be asked to consume no other foods during the 4-wk intervention. This will allow participants to eat ad libitum from a diet of fixed macronutrient composition. Each participant will be supplied with kitchen scales and asked to keep a weighed food record throughout the study. Participants will record intake following each meal in the study food diary provided.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will record the weight of food consumed throughout the 4 week dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting plasma levels of fibroblast growth factor-21.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fasted plasma samples will be collected prior to the start of the 4wk dietary intervention and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting serum levels of glucose.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fasted serum samples will be collected prior to the start of the 4wk dietary intervention and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting serum levels of cholesterol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fasted serum samples will be collected prior to the start of the 4wk dietary intervention and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting serum levels of HDL cholesterol.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fasted serum samples will be collected prior to the start of the 4wk dietary intervention and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting plasma levels of high sensitivity C-reactive protein.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fasted serum samples will be collected prior to the start of the 4wk dietary intervention and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting serum levels of branched chain amino acids.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fasted serum samples will be collected prior to the start of the 4wk dietary intervention and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting serum levels of liver function enzymes.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fasted serum samples will be collected prior to the start of the 4wk dietary intervention and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting levels of cytokines will be measured in peripheral blood mononuclear (PBMC) cells by flow cytometry. PBMCs will be extracted from fasting plasma samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Fasted serum samples will be collected prior to the start of the 4wk dietary intervention and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Levels of short chain fatty acids (SCFA) in stool samples will be measured by NMR. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be asked to collect one stool sample prior to the start and end of the 4wk dietary intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gut microbiome will be measured from bacterial DNA extracted from the stool sample.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be asked to collect one stool sample prior to the start and end of the 4wk dietary intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>A timed chair stand test will be measured as an indicator of physical performance. Participants will be required to rise five times as fast as possible with their arms folded from a standard height (43cm) chair. Performance will be measured as time (seconds) from the initial seated position to the final seated position after completing five stands.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Physical performance will be measured prior to the start of the intervention and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gait/walk speed will be measured as an indicator of physical performance. Starting from a standing position, participants will be required to walk in their usual pace between two lines marked six metres (6-m) apart on the floor in the testing room; the time taken to walk the 6m will be timed with a stopwatch. Gait/walk speed (6m) is calculated as the average of two trial (metre/second).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Physical performance will be measured prior to the start of the intervention and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Grip strength will be measured as an indicator of physical performance. Grip strength (kg) of both hands will be determined using a Jamar dynamometer (Jamar, Bolingbrook, IL) and average of best result will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Physical performance will be measured prior to the start of the intervention and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>24 hour levels of urinary urea.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants will be asked to collect 24hr urine sample prior to the start and end of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood pressure will be measured by Omron Standard Blood Pressure Monitor.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made prior to and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Waist circumference using a tape measure</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made prior to and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body weight using a digital scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made prior to and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body height using a fixed stadiometer.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made prior to the 4wk dietary intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body composition will be measured using BodPod.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made prior to and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Appetite rating using visual analogue scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Appetite questionnaires will be completed on one day during each week of the 4wk dietary intervention. Questionnaires will be completed hourly from before breakfast until 10pm.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Food palatability ratings using visual analogue scales.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Palatability questionnaires will be completed on one day of each week during the 4wk dietary intervention. Questionnaires will be completed for each food the participant consumes. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lifestyle and general health will be assessed by questionnaire. This will include a collection of validated questionnaires including the CAGE questionnaire, physical activity scale for the elderly (PASE), geriatric depression scale (GDS), the 12-item short form health survey and Activities of Daily Living (ADL).
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Lifestyle and general health will be assessed prior to commencement of the 4wk dietary intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess tooth plaque using a Sillness and Loe Plaque Index.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made prior to and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assess periodontal status and dentition using a Florida Probe to chart periodontal pocket depths, recession, bleeding, suppuration, teeth present/missing, restorations and prosthodontics.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made prior to and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure gingival crevicular fluid volume using a Periotron 8010 to collect GCF fluid at 2 separate gingival crevice sites</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made prior to and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Measure salivary amylase 1 concentration in unstimulated saliva flow</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made prior to and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Collect stimulated saliva flow for analysis of protective potential.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made prior to and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Collect tooth plaque for measurement of bacterial composition.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measurements will be made prior to and on completion of the 4wk dietary intervention. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Females (post-menopausal) or males, 65-75 years, BMI 20-30kg/m2 will be recruited. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria will include diabetes mellitus (insulin dependent, Type 1 or 2), renal or liver disease, cancer or active neoplasms, hyperthyroidism (unless treated or under control), taking medications known to affect weight or energy expenditure, unintentional weight loss (&gt;10% body weight) over the past 5 years, smoking, alcohol intake &gt; 3 drinks/day, vegan and vegetarians, food allergies and/or intolerances, and when changes in diet are contraindicated by treating doctor.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be concealed. Concealment will be performed using sealed opaque numbered envelopes.</concealment>
    <sequence>Male and female groups will be randomized to each intervention using permuted block randomisation. The will be done using the R package “blockrand” for males and females separately.. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Linear mixed model regression with and without covariates to test for differences between the 4 dietary interventions. Linear regression and/or general additive models in R will be used to test the relationship between habitual dietary intakes and baseline measures.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>28/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>30/11/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Sydney
NSW, 2006
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>an individual, philanthropic donation to the University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>The University of Sydney
NSW, 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Not applicable</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Not applicable</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary aim of the current study is to determine the effect of a moderate protein, high carbohydrate predominantly plant-based diet on appetite control and short-term health outcomes in individuals 65-75 years of age using a meal delivery based dietary intervention. 220 subjects, comprising equal numbers of men and women will be recruited. Participants will attend the RPA-CPC Clinic on 3 occasions. The first will be to attend a screening interview where they will be asked to complete questionnaires on their medical history, medications, cognitive health and eating behaviour. Eligible participants will then be invited to attend a baseline testing morning at the RPA-CPC Clinic. At the baseline testing, participants will arrive after an overnight fast with un-brushed teeth, bringing with them a 7d food diary, completed questionnaires about their lifestyle and general health, a stool sample and a 24hr urine collection. A blood sample will be collected and then an oral health examination will be performed and saliva and bacterial samples from tooth-surfaces will be collected. Body weight, waist and hip circumference, blood pressure, body composition and physical performance will also be measured. Participants will be randomly assigned to one of four dietary interventions. On the week after baseline testing study diets will be provided via a meal delivery company. Participants will be asked to consume the foods ad libitum. Participants will be requested to consume only from study foods and to keep a weighed food diary. During the 4 wk intervention, a study co-ordinator will contact each participant by phone on 5 different occasions. The first will be to ensure food has been delivered on the day before the study is to start, and the remaining 4 calls will be for a 48hr food recall. At the end of the final week of the dietary intervention participants will attend the RPA-CPC Clinic for final testing. At final testing, participants will arrive after an overnight fast with un-brushed teeth and will bring with them their study diary and a 24hr urine collection. A blood sample will be collected and an oral health examination will be performed and saliva and bacterial samples from tooth-surfaces will be collected. Measurements of body weight, waist and hip circumference, blood pressure, body composition and physical performance will be repeated.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney Local Health District - RPAH</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Ethics Governance Office
RPAH Medical Centre
Suite 210A, 100 Carillion Avenue
NEWTOWN, NSW 2042
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/11/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X16-0285 &amp; HREC/16/RPAH/364</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>28/06/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Gosby</name>
      <address>Level 4
Charles Perkins Centre, Bldg D17
The University of Sydney
NSW, 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1689</phone>
      <fax>
      </fax>
      <email>alison.gosby@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Gosby</name>
      <address>Level 4
Charles Perkins Centre, Bldg D17
The University of Sydney
NSW, 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.gosby@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alison Gosby</name>
      <address>Level 4
Charles Perkins Centre
The University of Sydney
NSW, 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 2 8627 1689</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alison.gosby@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>