<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347895">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/02/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000168853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Assesment of New Radiation Oncology Technologies and Treatments</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The assessment of New Radiation Oncology Technologies and treatments (ANROTAT) in Post Prostatectomy, Anal Cancal, Nasopharynx and Intact Prostate (TRP11.A)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>ANROTAT (TRP 11.A)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>clincaltrials.gov identifier: NCT01379872</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Prostate Cancer (Post Prostatectomy)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anal Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Nasopharyngeal Cancer</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Intermediate Risk Prostate Cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other cancer types</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Anal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Prostate</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG) has been commissioned by the Department of Health and Ageing (DoHA) to undertake a project to assess new Radiation Oncology Technology and Treatments. This project is being undertaken in response to a recognised need for the Medicare Benefits Schedule (MBS) to support appropriate new radiation oncology technologies and treatments as they become available, to ensure optimal patient care.

The first phase of the project required TROG to develop a Generic Research Framework (the Framework) capable of collecting and generating information to substantiate the safety, clinical efficacy and cost effectiveness of new technologies and treatments.

The second phase of the project requires that the Framework be piloted to assess the safety, clinical efficacy and cost effectiveness of Intensity Modulated Radiation Therapy (IMRT) and Image Guided Radiation Therapy (IGRT) in four tumour sites. 

The two new radiation oncology technologies being assessed  are; 

1) Intensity-Modulated Radiation Therapy (IMRT); which is the method used to vary the fluence within a photon beam to achieve a highly conformal dose distribution to the target volume and minimise dose to surrounding organs at risk (OAR). The fluence modulations are inversely calculated using an optimisation process to produce a prescribed 3D dose distribution. Inverse treatment planning defines the desired dose to target and critical structures as a starting point, and intensity-modulated beam arrangements are derived to acceptably approach or meet these desired dose limits. At least single-point dose constraints, but more commonly a multipoint description of dosevolume limits, drive the process.1 The modulated beams are delivered using time variant apertures defined by multi-leaf collimators (MLC). The term IMRT for the purpose of the project refers to standard IMRT delivered by a fixed gantry. This definition excludes rotational IMRT delivered by single or multiple arcs (e.g. RapidArc) and Volumetric Arc Therapy (VMAT) (e.g.  Tomotherapy). 

2) Image Guided Radiation Therapy; is radiation therapy based on imaging acquired at the point of treatment delivery with the intent to ensure geometric accuracy of radiation delivery.  In this context, IGRT must be able to provide information of the target itself.
For the purpose of the ANROTAT project, IGRT is defined as daily imaging with on-line decision making that at a minimum allows for daily patient re-positioning based on imaging of the target volume or an appropriate surrogate marker. Two options exist:
a) Planar imaging using electronic portal imaging (EPI) or kilo-voltage (kV) on-board imaging. In this case, the implantation of fiducial markers into the prostate gland is required.
b) Volumetric imaging using one of various CT systems. kV and MV Cone Beam (CB) CT are allowed. Ultrasound methods are not permitted in the present protocol.
 IGRT for the ANROTAT project will focus on intact prostate imaging i.e. daily orthogonal planar imaging with fiducial markers or volumetric (e.g. CBCT) imaging.

The source data collected for this second stage of the project will be taken from patient medical records, reports, RT plans and QOL/Cost questionniares. As retrospective participants registered in this study have to have completed RT treatment with the last 60 months before registration, the year range the data will be collected is from 2006-2011.</interventions>
    <comparator>IMRT and IGRT will be compared against Three-Dimensional Conformal Radiation Therapy (3DCRT) and non-IGRT treatments. 

3DCRT is the use of three dimensional (3D) planning software and beam shaping devices such as multi-leaf collimators (MLC), to conform external photon beams to a target volume in three dimensions, whilst minimising dose to surrounding critical structures. 3DCRT is forward planned and based on a 3D dataset representing the patient, typically a computed tomography (CT) image set. Several types of algorithms are available to achieve the calculation of absorbed dose e.g. Pencil Beam, Superposition.
The forward planning process involves a set of conformal treatment fields, and the possible introduction of internal apertures, wedges, and/or additional beam directions to modify the dose distribution to avoid critical structures or boost certain regions of the target.


For the purpose of the ANROTAT project, non-IGRT is defined as any treatment approach that does not employ daily imaging of the target volume. Various imaging frequencies and off-line decision making models such as No Action Level (NAL) or the Newcastle model are acceptable. It is generally assumed that verification imaging is performed at least weekly and on-line action is typically restricted to gross misplacements.


The source data collected for this project will be taken from patient medical records, reports, RT plans and QOL/Cost questionniares. As retrospective participants registered in this study have to have completed RT treatment with the last 60 months before regisrtation, the year range the data will be collected is from 2006-2011.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare the dosimetry of treatment plans prepared using the new technologies against those prepared using the conventional standard approaches as a surrogate for effectiveness and safety</outcome>
      <timepoint>Prospective participants: Plans produced before comencement of treatment
Retrospective participants and datasets: Plans produced before comencement of treatment (reproduced after registration for the purpose of the study).
All radiotherapy plans are due for submission by mid February 2012.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Obtain data on the impact of disease and treatment on QoL</outcome>
      <timepoint>Propective participants: Baseline, during treatment (6 or 8 weeks) and post treatment (6weeks and/or 3 months) the exact timing depends on tumour type.
Retrospective participants: post treatment (more than or equal to 3 months post treatment)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare the resource usage associated with the planning and delivery of the new technologies compared to the conventional standard approaches</outcome>
      <timepoint>During data analysis</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Synthesise the data obtained for objectives 1-3 together with information from previous studies and expert opinion into a decision analytic model to estimate the safety, clinical efficacy and cost-effectiveness of the new technologies compared to the conventional standards</outcome>
      <timepoint>During data analysis</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All protocols: 
- Patient has provided written informed consent
- Sufficient knowledge of English and adequate cognitive function to be able to complete the QoL and other questionnaires 

Protocol A (Post Prostatectomy):
- Prior Radical Prostatectomy for adenocarcinoma of the prostate.
- Histological confirmation of adenocarcinoma of the prostate with the Gleason score reported (RP specimen).
- Patients must have at least one of the following risk factors: 
	- Positive margins 
	- Extraprostatic extension (EPE) with or without seminal vesicle involvement (pT3a or pT3b)PSA nadir less than or equal to 1.0 ng/ml following RP  
- ECOG performance status 0  1 
- Patients participating in the Toxicity and QoL evaluation QoL data must be scheduled to undergo RT or must have completed RT within the previous 12 months

Protocol B (Anal Canal):
- Histological confirmation of squamous cell carcinoma or basaloid carcinoma within the past 6 weeks
- T2-4N0, TanyN2 (ipsilateral groin nodes) and TanyN3 (bilateral groin nodes)
- Intention to elective irradiate all pelvic nodal groups up to L5-S1 interspace (including mesorectal, presacral, internal iliac, external iliac, ischiorectal fossa, obturator and inguinal groups)
- Planned for radical chemoradiation

Protocol C (Nasopharynx):
- Histologically confirmed carcinoma of the nasopharynx, types WHO1-111, Stage I-IVB within the past 6 weeks
- Adequate staging of local disease and exclusion of distant metastatic disease within the past 6 weeks.
- Disease must be considered potentially curable by chemoradiation
- Patients must be medically fit for cisplatin chemotherapy according to local practice 
- Performance status ECOG 0, 1 or 2.
- Patients participating in the cross sectional study of QoL must have completed radiation therapy treatment within 18-30 months prior to the date of informed consent (or 60 months in selected sites)

Protocol D (Intact Prostate):
- Histological diagnosis of carcinoma of the prostate less than or equal to 6 months of entry without evidence of metastatic disease to the lymph nodes, bone or lung
- Intermediate risk prostate cancer (that is, T1-2a, Gleason score less than or equal to 6, PSA 10.1-20.0 ng/ml; T2b-c, Gleason less than or equal to 6, PSA less than or equal to  20.0 ng/ml; T1-2, Gleason 7, PSA less than or equal to 20.0 ng/ ml)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Protocol A (Post Prostatectomy):
- Previous pelvic RT or surgery ie previous rectal or bladder resection
- Concurrent or previous malignancy within 5 years prior to registration (except non-melanomatous skin cancer) 
- Androgen deprivation (AD) prior to or following RP as this will affect QoL 
- Evidence of nodal or distant metastases
- Clinical or imaging evidence of local recurrence
- Planned adjuvant RT to cover pelvic lymph nodes
- PSA greater than 1.0 ng/ml 
- Co-morbidities that would interfere with the completion of treatment 
- Concurrent cytotoxic medication
- Hip prosthesis

Protocol B (Anal Canal):
- Evidence of metastatic disease
- Prior pelvic RT/ surgery (e.g. vaginal hysterectomy)
- Presence of hip prosthesis
- Acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS). HIV patients without AIDS eligible.
- Previous pelvic cancers 

Protocol C (Nasopharynx):
- Previous head and neck RT or major surgery
- Prior chemotherapy less than or equal to 6 months from study entry

Protocol D (Intact Prostate):
- Previous therapy for carcinoma of the prostate other than biopsy or transurethral resection.
- Previous pelvic RT or surgery (eg abdomino-perineal resection)  
- Hip prosthesis
- Inflammatory bowel disease</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/06/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>20/06/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/04/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>120</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>138</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <postcode>5000</postcode>
    <postcode>3081</postcode>
    <postcode>2605</postcode>
    <postcode>2310</postcode>
    <postcode>3220</postcode>
    <postcode>2521</postcode>
    <postcode>7250</postcode>
    <postcode>1871</postcode>
    <postcode>2450</postcode>
    <postcode>0820</postcode>
    <postcode>4102</postcode>
    <postcode>8006</postcode>
    <postcode>2031</postcode>
    <postcode>6014</postcode>
    <postcode>7001</postcode>
    <postcode>4350</postcode>
    <postcode>3002</postcode>
    <postcode>2050</postcode>
    <postcode>3181</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Trans Tasman Radiation Oncology Group Ltd</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Cantral Operations Office
Calvary Mater Newcastle
Locked bag 7
HRMC NSW 2310</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Health and Ageing</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 9848,
Canberra 
ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Department of Health and Ageing and the Radiation Oncology professions recognised that there was a need for the Medicare Benefits Schedule  (MBS) to support appropriate new radiation oncology technologies and treatments as they become available, to ensure optimal patient care. The ANROTAT projects aim is to develop and test a generic research framework able to collect and generate information to assess the safety, clinical efficacy and cost effectiveness of new radiation therapy technologies and treatments. This framework will then be used to assess the safety, clinical efficacy and cost effectiveness of;
  a) Intensity Modulated Radiation Therapy (IMRT) vs Three-Dimensional Conformal Radiation Therapy  (3DCRT) in prostate (post prostactomy), anal and nasopharyngeal cancer 
  b) Image Guided Radiation Therapy (IGRT) vs non-IGRT in  patient with intermediate risk prostate cancer 

Information will be collected on the participants treatment, individual experience and costs associated with their treatment, which will be used in comparing the existing and new types of radiation therapy treatment methods currently available in Australian Treatment Centres.

It is hypothesised that the new technologies;  
   - produce treatment plans with improved dosimetric properties shown through reduced toxicity without unacceptable loss of efficacy as compared to plans produced using conventional standards
   - have the potential to optimise tumour dose and improve tumour control without causing unacceptable levels of toxicity as compared to treatment using conventional standards.
   - are cost-effective compared to conventional standards

The ultimate aim of the ANROTAT study is to make the most effective radiation therapy treatment methods available to all cancer patients in Australia.

The ANROTAT project is a non-interventional prospective evaluation of clinical activity. It is therefore defined as a clinical audit rather than a clinical trial.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.trog.com.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Grand M, Amin R, Cornes DC, Duchesne G, Hall K, Kron T, Burmeister B The Assessment of New Radiation Oncology Technologies and Treatment (ANROTAT): The Design and Testing of a Generic Framework. ORAL Presentation RANZCR Perth 2010 ASM 14-17 October 2010. J Med Imaging &amp; Rad Onc.  Vol. 54, S1, A65, Oct 2010.

Grand M, Amin R, Cornes DC, Duchesne G, Haworth A, Hall K, Kron T, Burmeister B.The assessment of new radiation oncology technology and treatments (ANROTAT): What is the value in developing a framework? Oral Presentation. Presenter: Mel Grand. Elekta Useres Group Meeting, Kingscliff, 28th-30th May 2010.

Grand M, Amin R, Cornes DC, Duchesne G, Hall K, Kron T, Burmeister B.The evaluation of new radiation oncology technology and treatments (ANROTAT): The development of a generic research framework. Oral Presentation. Presenter: Mel Grand. ASMMIRT 2010, Gold Coast, 9-12th September 2010.

Grand M, Amin R, Cornes D.A, Duchesne G, Haworth A, Kron T, Burmeister B. The role of Medical Physicists in Developing a Generic Research Framework for the Assessment of New Radiation Oncology Technology and Treatments in Radiation Oncology. Oral presentation. Presenting Author: Mel Grand. EPSM ABEC Meeting 2010, Melbourne, 5-9 December 2010. 

S Babington, J Dixon, M Ebert, F Foroudi, J Frantzis, M Grand, P Greer, M Hall, A Haworth, B Hilder, T Kron, C Lin, A Rolfo, and P Vial. What is the Value of Image Guidance in External Beam Radiotherapy? Oral presentation. Presenter: Tomas Kron. EPSM ABEC Meeting 2010, Melbourne, 5-9 December 2010

Haworth A, Grand M, Corry J, Jackson M, Ng M, Kron T, Burmeister B, Duchesne G. Assessment of New Radiation Oncology Technology and Treatments in Radiation Oncology  the  ANROTAT project and collection of IMRT specific data. Oral presentation. Presenter: A Haworth. EPSM ABEC Meeting 2010, Melbourne, 5-9 December 2010

Grand M, OBrien P. Obstacles to Participation in Randomised Cancer Clinical Trials: a systematic review of the literature". Journal of Medical Imaging and Radiation Oncology. Oct 2011.

Ms Mel Grand - The Development and Implementation of a Generic Research Framework for the Assessment of New Radiation Oncology Technology and Treatments (ANROTAT): Providing the Evidence for Future Change. Annual Scientific Meeting of Medical Imaging and Radiation Therapists (ASMMIRT) 2011.  

Ms Haylea Cleaver - Quality Assurance (QA) and Phantom Dosimetry Credentialing within the collaborative research environment; A unique opportunity for the Radiation Therapist, ASMMIRT 2011.

Ms Haylea Cleaver - A system for review of diagnostic imaging in radiotherapy clinical trial quality assurance and the development of technical specifications, ASMMIRT 2011.

Mel Grand - RANZCR ASM 2011  Challenges in Bringing New Technology into Practice: The Development and Pilot of a Generic Research Framework for the Assessment of New Radiation Oncology Technology and Treatments (ANROTAT)  accepted for oral presentation

Tomas Kron - Engineering and Physical Sciences in Medicine and the Australian Biomedical Engineering Conference EPSM-ABEC 2011 (14-18/08/2011) - The TROG ANROTAT project  just another acronym?

Ms Mel Grand - The Development and Implementation of a Generic Research Framework for the Assessment of New Radiation Oncology Technology and Treatments (ANROTAT): Providing the Evidence for Future Change. Annual Scientific Meeting of Medical Imaging and Radiation Therapists (ASMMIRT) 2011.  

Grand M, OBrien P. Obstacles to Participation in Randomised Cancer Clinical Trials: a systematic review of the literature". Journal of Medical Imaging and Radiation Oncology. Oct 2011.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Locked Bag 1
New Lambton 
NSW
2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/05/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>11/04/20/4.07</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Bryan Burmeister</name>
      <address>Cancer Services
Princess Alexandra Hospital
Ipswich Rd
Wolloongabba
QLD, 4102</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3240 6581</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Bryan_Burmeister@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Rebecca Montgomery</name>
      <address>TROG Central Operations Office 
Department of Radiation Oncology  
Calvary Mater Newcastle  
Locked Bag 7 
Hunter Region Mail Centre 
NSW 2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 401 43910</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 40143618</fax>
      <email>trog@trog.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Rebecca Montgomery</name>
      <address>TROG Central Operations Office 
Department of Radiation Oncology  
Calvary Mater Newcastle  
Locked Bag 7 
Hunter Region Mail Centre 
NSW 2310</address>
      <phone>+61 2 40143917</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 40143618</fax>
      <email>rebecca.montgomery@trog.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Bryan Burmeister  </name>
      <address>Cancer Services Princess Alexandra Hospital Ipswich Rd Wolloongabba QLD, 4102  </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3240 6581  </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Bryan_Burmeister@health.qld.gov.au  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>