<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343224">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>21/07/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/07/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000765921</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of Methylphenidate Treatment in Children with Neurofibromatosis type 1 (NF1): A randomised, placebo controlled, cross over trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A placebo controlled trial of methylphenidate for treatment of cognitive and behavioural impairment in children and adolescents with neurofibromatosis type 1.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1123-0940</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>2011/0282 TGA CTN scheme</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neurofibromatosis type 1</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other human genetics and inherited disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Part 1
Methylphenidate will be the active substance in the first phase of this trial.  This part of the trial will be a randomised placebo controlled cross over trial with a duration of 12 weeks (6 weeks of active substance, 6 weeks of placebo). Methylphenidate dose level will be up to 1.5mg/kg a day. Dose level will not exceed 60mg/day.  The appropriate dose level for each subject will be determined during a 2 week titration phase. Methylphenidate powder will be presented as a crushed powder in opaque gelatin capsules containing either 5mg methylphendiate or 10mg methylphenidate. Treatment phase duration is 4 weeks. Capsules will need to be taken orally three times a day.  No washout period between the active arm and the placebo arm exists. 

Part 2 (open label)
Methylphenidate (Ritalin LA capsules) 10mg/20mg/30mg/40mg. 
If a participant demonstrates a significant reliable improvement in any of the primary outcome measures after they have completed Part 1 of the trial (i.e. completed both 6 weeks of methylphenidate and 6 weeks of placebo) he/she will be invited to immediately continue on methylphenidate (Ritalin long acting) for 13 weeks (or until 6 months after her/his baseline assessment). The dose level of Ritalin long acting will be different for each participant and will be equivalent to his/her dose level of active substance in Part 1 of the trial.  Participants will be required to take this dose level once in the morning on  daily basis.</interventions>
    <comparator>Part 1

The placebo will be presented in identical form as treatment as crushed powder in opaque gelatin capsules. The placebo capsules will contain a negligible amount of lactose. Participants on the placebo arm will undergo an identical 2 week mimic titration phase in which they will take placebo.   Participants must take the placebo 3 times a day for 4 weeks after the 2 week mimic titration phase.</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cambridge Neuropsychological Testing Automated Battery (CANTAB) Spatial Working Memory Task.  The number of between errors will be the outcome measure for this subtest.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Conners Continous Performance Test-II (CPT-II) Omission errors will be the outcome measure for this subtest</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Conners 3 parent questionnaire. The outcome measures will be inattentive and hyperactive/impulsivity scale (T scores).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Test of Everyday Attention for Children will be used in this study to assess selective attention (Sky Search), sustained attention (Score!) divided attention (Sky Search Dual Task) and attentional control/switching (Creature Counting). Raw scores will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Social Skills Improvement System Rating Scales (parent version) (SSIS: Gresham &amp; Elliott, 2008). Communication, cooperation, assertion, responsibility, empathy, engagement and self-control scales will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Conners 3 (teacher version) will be used to assess ADHD behavioural symptoms.   Outcome will be the inattentive and hyperactive/impulsivity scale  (T scores)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Planning/Problem solving will be assessed with the CANTAB Stockings of Cambridge Raw score: Problems solved in minimum moves.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Behavior Rating Inventory of Executive Function-Parent Report Forms (BRIEF; Gioia, Isquith, Guy &amp; Kenworthy, 2000; Guy, Isquith &amp; Gioia, 2004). The eight clinical scales including: initiate, inhibit, shift, plan, organize, self-monitor, emotional control, and working memory as well as Behavioural Regulation, Metacognition and a Global Executive Composite score will be outcome. T scores will be used.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tasks of Executive Control (TEC: Isquith, Roth,. and. Gioia, 2010)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Child Behaviour Checklist (CBCL 6-18: Achenbach, 2001). 
The following indexes will be outcome measure: Anxious/Depressed, Withdrawn/Depressed, Somatic Complaints, Social Problem, Thought Problems, Attention Problems, Rule-Breaking Behavior, Aggressive Behavior.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Paediatric Quality of Life Scale (PedsQL: Varni, Seid &amp; Kurtin, 2001)self-report and parent proxy-report scales.  Four core scales: physical, emotional, social, and school.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Visuospatial Skills will be assessed with the Judgment of Line Orientation (JLO: Benton, Varney &amp; Hamsher, 1976) Version V. Total correct.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fine Motor Skills will be assessed with The Grooved Pegboard (Lafayette Instrument Co, 2002). 
Measures recorderd will be the length of time required to perform each trial, the number of drops made during each trial and finally the number of pegs correctly placed in the holes for each trial.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Expressive language will be briefly assessed with The Formulated Sentences subtest- Australian version (CELF-4: Semel, Wiig, Secord 2003).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
After 6 weeks of treatment
After 6 weeks of placebo
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Academic Achievement will be assessed with the Wechsler Individual Achievement Test- Second Edition (WIAT-II: Wechsler, 2001) Single word reading, spelling and numerical operations.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
6 months from baseline</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children-version 4 Australian (WISC-IV; Wechsler, 2003;).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline (before treatment)
6 months from baseline.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>CANTAB Paired Associate learning (PAL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline line, Week 6 and week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Conners CPT-II commission errors </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, week 6 and week 12</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. All participants must fulfil the diagnosis of NF1 based on NIH criteria (NIH, 2000);

2. Participants must have a full scale IQ greater than or equal to 70 or if a significant discrepancy is present between PRI and VCI the higher will be used. This index used must be 70 or above; 

3. Participants behaviour must be rated as abnormal by their parent on the Conners 3. An abnormal score is defined as a T score equal to or greater than 65 on the following scales inattention, hyperactivity/impulsivity. 

4. Participants must have a cognitive impairment defined as having a score of at least one standard deviation or more below the population mean on at least one of the primary objective outcome measures: 
a) Conners Continuous Performance Test II (CPT II Omissions) 
b) CANTAB Spatial Working Memory (SWM) (between errors total). </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>7</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>16</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Participants who have intracranial pathology such as epilepsy, hydrocephalus, diagnosed traumatic brain injury, or progressive intracranial tumours (children with asymptomatic or static lesions will be eligible);

2. Children who have significant visual and/or hearing problems;

3. Children who have contraindications to stimulant medication. These include those with glaucoma, hypertension, previous insensitivity to stimulant medication or are on contraindicated medication such as monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors;

4. Children with Tourettes syndrome, tics, or other major psychiatric disorders;

5. Female participants of childbearing age should not be pregnant, must have a negative urine pregnancy test before initiation of treatment;

6. Children who have received any investigational drugs of any type within 30 days of initiation of study;

7. Children with a co-existing medical condition that is likely to interfere or who are taking any concomitant medication that is likely to interfere with safe administration of methylphenidate in the investigators opinion.

8. Children who are requiring any of the following medications: clonidine or other alpha2 adrenergic receptor agonists, tricyclic antidepressants, selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors, theophylline, coumarin, or anticonvulsants.

9. Children who have blood pressure measurements (systolic or diastolic) equal to or greater than 95th percentile for age, sex and height at screening.

10. Children who require drug therapy or hospitalisation for treatment of a mood disorder or anxiety disorder.

11. Children with ECG abnormalities that are deemed clinically significant

12. Children with drug or alcohol abuse or dependence within the prior six months

13. Children who are currently on stimulant medication for ADHD before the trial will be required to undergo a 3 week washout period prior to the screening assessment to minimise any potential carry over effects of the drug and allow the parents and teachers to complete the behavioural questionnaire based on the child's off medication behaviour. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>After informed assent has been obtained, a screening assessment will be performed. The screening assessment will include a medical history, a physical examination, ECG, and a urine sample test (to screen for pregnancy for females). Height, weight, blood pressure and pulse will be recorded. Participants will also be administered the MINI-KID &amp; the Disruptive Behavioural Disorders Structured Interview to identify child psychopathology or other excluding disorders such as oppositional defiant disorder, conduct disorder, major depressive disorder, dysthymic disorder and anxiety disorders. The site psychologist will administer the primary outcome measures and a test of general intelligence which are estimated to take around 1.5-2 hours to complete. Parents will be required to complete the Conner 3 questionnaire during this time. 

After a successful screening period, the participant will be randomised to one of two conditions: Treatment or placebo. Randomisation will be managed by the chief site biostatistician (who is independent to study). Allocation will be concealed to the person who determines eligibility.</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/07/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>30/07/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Children's Hospital at Westmead - Westmead</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>2145 - Westmead</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Children's Hospital at Westmead</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Corner of Hawkesbury Road and Hainsworth Street Westmead NSW 2145</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Children's Hospital at Westmead</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Corner of Hawkesbury Road and Hainsworth Street Westmead  NSW 2145</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Children's Tumor Foundation </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>20 Wall Street, 16th Floor
New York, NY 10005-3904</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The Royal Children's Hospital Melbourne</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>The Royal Childrens Hospital
Flemington Rd Parkville, Victoria 3052 AUS
</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The specific aim of this study is to determine whether methylphenidate  significantly reduces deficits in attention and/or executive function in children with NF1. This study also aims to establish whether MPH reduces ADHD related behaviours in neurofibromatosis.
It is hypothesised that methylphenidate will improve attention and executive function deficits in children with NF1 and reduce the ADHD like behavioural characteristics in children with NF1.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Children's Hospital at Westmead Human Research Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Corner of Hawkesbury Road and Hainsworth Street Westmead NSW 2145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>4/03/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>10/CHW/121</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/12/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Pride</name>
      <address>The Children's Hospital at Westmead 
Corner of Hawkesbury Road and Hainsworth Sreet
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>61 02 9845 3714</phone>
      <fax>61-2-9845-3389</fax>
      <email>natalie.pride@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Natalie Pride</name>
      <address>The Children's Hospital at Westmead 
Corner of Hawkesbury Road and Hainsworth Sreet
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>61 2 98453714</phone>
      <fax>61 02 9845 3945</fax>
      <email>natalie.pride@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Natalie Pride</name>
      <address>The Children's Hospital at Westmead 
Corner of Hawkesbury Road and Hainsworth Sreet
Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>+61 02 98453057</phone>
      <fax>61 02 9845 3945</fax>
      <email>natalie.pride@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Natalie Pride </name>
      <address>The Children's Hospital at Westmead Locked bag 4001 Westmead NSW 2145</address>
      <phone>61 2 9845 3714</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Natalie.Pride@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>