<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335170">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/02/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/03/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000189022</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of an instrument for the assessment and management of behavioural and psychological symptoms of dementia in aged care</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can aged care staff, and residents with behavioural and psychological symptoms of dementia (BPSD), benefit from staff training in the use of an assessment and management tool for challenging behaviours in residential care and/or education and clinical support  regarding BPSDs, by demonstrating reduced stress, improved attitudes towards working with people with dementia, and greater job satisfaction among staff and reductions in the frequency and severity of BPSDs among residents.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>behavioural and psychological symptoms of dementia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There will be three treatment conditions. CONDITION ONE: Aged care staff participants in condition one will receive training in the use of an assessment and management instrument for challenging behaviours in residential care. This training will involve a single two-hour session and will be conducted as a group session by one of the investigators. Condition one participants will also participate in a single session, two-hour educational workshop designed to teach aged care staff how to identify and manage the causes of challenging behaviours in aged care residents with dementia. Staff who participate in the educational workshop will also receive three months of fortnightly clinical support visits, carried out by an experienced clinician. 
CONDITION TWO: Aged care staff participants in condition two will receive the educational workshop and three months clinical support, but they will not receive the training session in the use of the assessment and management instrument.
CONDITION THREE: Aged care staff participants in condition three will receive the training session in the use of the assessment and management instrument, but they will not participate in the educational workshop or receive the three months of clinical support.</interventions>
    <comparator>Active control; 
Staff in the control condition will not receive the training session, the educational workshop or the clinical support. These participants will continue with their standard care routines and will be offered the training and educational workshop at the conclusion of the study</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced frequency and/or severity of behavioural and psychological symptoms of dementia in aged care residents. A research assistant who is blind to the treatment conditions will observe and record the frequency and/or severity of BPSDs in the participating residents on a behaviour monitoring sheet.  Frequently occurring behaviours will be observed and recorded over a three hour period and infrequent behaviours will be observed and recorded over a five day period.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and three months and six months after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced stress among staff associated with behavioural and psychological symptoms in residents, as assessed by a questionnaire containing the Carer Stress Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and three months and six months after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvements in job satisfaction and  attitudes towards working with people with dementia among aged care staff, as assessed through a questionnaire containing questions on satisfaction with work in aged care and the Approaches to Dementia scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, and three and six months after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvements in staff perceptions of self-efficacy in dealing with challenging behaviours, as assessed by a questionnaire containing the Self-efficacy in Working with Dementia scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and three and six months after intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Reduced frequency of general practitioner (GP) or other medical practitioner visits to treat BPSDs. This will be determined by viewing the resident's medical files and recording the number of visits in the previous three months</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and three months and six months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in psychotropic medications including reduced reliance on antipsychotics to treat behavioural symptoms. This information will be obtained from the medication records in the residents' file. The investigator will record the residents' current psychotropic medications as well as any changes in these medications in the previous three months</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and three months and six months after the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Residents: Aged care residents with dementia who present with behavioural and psychological symptoms that are identified by facility managers as challenging
Staff: Aged care staff who work with the resident population in this study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Residents: Aged care residents that do not have a dementia diagnosis or do not present with challenging behaviours and psychological symptoms, residents with a diagnosis of schizophrenia
Staff: Aged care staff that do not work with the resident population used in this study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Aged care facilities, and not the individual staff and residents, will be randomly allocated to each condition. Aged care agencies, that are collaborative partners in the study, will nominate facilities to participate in the study, and these facilities will then be randomly allocated to one of the four treatment conditions. The person who nominates the aged care facilities will be unaware, when the decision is made, to which condition each facility would be allocated. Allocation will be decided by central randomisation using computer software.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised random number generator</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>3/05/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>480</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deakin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>221 Burwood Highway
Burwood  Victoria  3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Greater Southern Area Health Service</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>34 Lowe St
Queanbeyan NSW 2620</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Other Collaborative groups</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Benetas</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Level 1, 789 Toorak Road, 
Hawthorn East, VIC 3123</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The study will evaluate the effectiveness of an instrument that has been developed to assist aged care staff in assessing and managing challenging behaviours in residents with dementia. The instrument is a systematic, step by step procedural tool that can be used by care staff to identify or eliminate the various physical, psychological and environmental causes of challenging behaviours in residents with dementia, and provides various strategies for managing these behaviours. It is anticipated that training staff to use the instrument will enable them to implement it within their care routines, and that effective use of the instrument will benefit staff by reducing the occurrence or impact of challenging behaviours in residents with dementia, and by alleviating the stress and strain on staff that care for these residents.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Ethics Office, Research Services Division, 
Deakin University, 
221 Burwood Hwy, 
Burwood VIC 3125</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/06/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HEAG-H 92/09</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Tanya Davison</name>
      <address>221 Burwood Hwy,
Burwood, VIC, 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 6505</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tanya.davison@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marita McCabe</name>
      <address>221 Burwood Hwy,
Burwood, VIC, 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 6856</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marita.mccabe@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Marita McCabe</name>
      <address>221 Burwood Hwy,
Burwood, VIC, 3125</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9244 6856</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>marita.mccabe@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>