<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363415">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/12/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000007730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Validating Cough Reflex Testing Against Instrumental Assessment Of Aspiration And Laryngeal Sensation.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Validating cough reflex testing in patients with dysphagia against instrumental assessment to identify those with silent aspiration</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1138-0135</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>dysphagia</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a prospective single blinded cross over correlational study. The aim of this stage is to validate the cough reflex test against previously validated instrumental measures of aspiration and penetration and laryngeal sensation (with the use of flexible naso-endoscopic assessment).

All participants will undergo 2 assessments; cough reflex testing and instrumental swallowing assessment. Both these tests are already in place at the research site for use with this patient group. Different independent researchers perform each test and will be blinded to the result of the alternate test. The tests were alternated in randomly.

Cough reflex testing takes 10 minutes approximately. Citric acid concentrations are administered for 15-seconds via facemask using PulmoMate Compressor/Nebuliser (Model 4650I, DeVilbiss Healthcare LLC, Pennsylvania, US) with a predetermined flow output of 8 litres per minute.  Patients are asked to breathe normally and cough if they feel the need to cough. Initially a placebo dose of 0.9% NaCl is presented to coach the patient on task completion. Citric acid concentrations are administered incrementally from low to high in 1-minute intervals. A placebo dose is interdispersed between each change in citric acid dose to prevent tachyphylaxis and blunting of lower doses. Presence or absence of cough during the 15-second delivery period is documented. 

VFSS assessment take place in the radiology suite. Patients are administered a standard protocol of volumes and consistencies of barium constrast agent and the procedures takes 10 minutes approximately. 

FEES was performed at the patients bedside using a 3.2 mm diameter flexible video rhino-laryngoscope (ENF- V2, Olympus Corporation, Tokyo, Japan), an integrated light source and video processor (Olympus, OTV-SI, Olympus Corporation) and LCD Monitor (Olympus OEV203, Olympus Corporation). No topical anaesthesia was used. The endoscope was passed through the nose and positioned in the pharynx. Again a protocol involving a variety of foods and drinks are given. Aspiration is noted.</interventions>
    <comparator>not applicable</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Validation of cough reflex testing against previously validated instrumental measures of aspiration. All assessments will be recorded and scored from the video recording by two researchers blinded to the result of the alternate test. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Same day- within 1 hour</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>not applicable</outcome>
      <timepoint>not applicable</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Consecutive inpatients referred to speech-language pathology for initial swallowing assessment. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients were excluded if they were too drowsy, medically unstable to participate, were tracheotomised or where evaluation was contraindicated (e.g nasal abnormalities including epistaxis and base of skull fractures for FEES). </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/10/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>17/01/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>New Zealand Speech-language Therapy Assocation</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO BOX 137 256, Parnell, Auckland 1151</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>New Zealand Speech-language Therapy Association</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO BOX 137 256, Parnell, Auckland 1151</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>North Shore Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>124 Shakesphere Rd, Takapuna, Auckland, 0622</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In many patients with swallowing problems the ability to cough when food enters the lungs will be impaired.  Currently there is no way to reliably identify patients who have no cough and therefore no way of protecting their airway if food/drink slips down the wrong way (aspiration).  The data from this study will be used to develop a method of identifying these at risk patients, and hence improving their management. The aim of this project is to validate a cough test against accepted measures of swallowing and sensation in the throat.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern Y Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health, No 1 The Terrace, PO BOX 5013, Wellington.6145</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>1/10/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTY/11/04/038</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/10/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Anna Miles</name>
      <address>Speech Sciences, Tamaki Campus, University of Auckland, 261 Morrin Rd, Tamaki, Auckland 1072</address>
      <phone>0064211371658</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.miles@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Anna Miles</name>
      <address>Speech Sciences, Tamaki Campus, University of Auckland, 261 Morrin Rd, Tamaki, Auckland 1072</address>
      <phone>0064211371658</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.miles@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Anna Miles</name>
      <address>Speech Sciences, Tamaki Campus, University of Auckland, 261 Morrin Rd, Tamaki, Auckland 1072</address>
      <phone>0064211371658</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.miles@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Anna Miles</name>
      <address>Speech Sciences, Tamaki Campus, University of Auckland, 261 Morrin Rd, Tamaki, Auckland 1072</address>
      <phone>0064211371658</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>a.miles@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>