<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370404">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/03/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>30/03/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000405415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Intravenous pentoxifylline as adjunct therapy to improve long-term disability in preterm infants</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Can Pentoxifylline improve long-term outcomes in preterm infants with late-onset sepsis or necrotising enterocolitis? A pragmatic, randomised, placebo-controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PROTECT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Preterm infants</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Late-onset sepsis (LOS)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Necrotising enterocolitis (NEC) </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Long-term disability</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of the normal brain and nervous system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Ideally within 6 hours (no later than 12 hours) of onset of suspected LOS or NEC patient will receive Pentoxifylline intravenous infusion 1ml/kg/h for 12h/day (60mg/kg/day) for 2 days. If the diagnosis of NEC or sepsis diagnosis is confirmed, this will be followed by 1ml/kg/h for 6hr/day (30mg/kg/day) on days 3-6. If the diagnosis of NEC or LOS is not confirmed the intervention will be discontinued at that time.</interventions>
    <comparator>Within 6hr of onset of suspected LOS or NEC patient will receive normal saline (NaCl 0.9%) intravenous infusion 1ml/kg/h for 12h/day for 2 days. If the diagnosis of NEC or sepsis diagnosis is confirmed, this will be followed by 1ml/kg/h for 6hr/day (30mg/kg/day) on days 3-6. If the diagnosis of NEC or LOS is not confirmed the intervention will be discontinued at that time</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary outcome is survival without any disability at 24 months (corrected for gestation) in infants treated with intravenous Pentoxifylline or placebo for LOS or NEC.

Presence/absence of disability at 24 months (+/- 6months) corrected for gestation will be assessed by way of a clinical follow-up visit, including administration of Bayley Scales of Infant Development, 3rd edition (BSID III). 

Disability is defined as: 
A)	mild (-1SD to -2SD), ambulant Cerebral Palsy (GMFCS I+II)  or unilateral deafness
B)	moderate (-2SD to -3SD), ambulant (with aids) Cerebral Palsy (GMFCS III), or has bilateral hearing impairment
C)	severe (&lt;-3SD), non-ambulant Cerebral Palsy (GMFCS IV+V), or blindness where vision is &lt;6/60.  
Scores on the BSID III will be assessed relative to a standardized mean (+/-SD) of 100+/-15, with higher scores indicating better performance for composite and individual components of cognitive, motor and language.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>At 24 months (+/- 6months) corrected for gestation. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Survival until discharge home and at 24 months (+/- 6 months).  This outcome will be assessed by hospital record review and regular phone/letter contact (every 6 months) with the family until the child reaches 24 months of age.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until 24 months (+/- 6 months).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Any disability at 24 months (+/- 6 months). Any disability will be assessed by the following assessments: A) BSID III and/or B) Ages and Stages Questionnaire III and/or C) Modified Short Health Status Questionnaire documenting either major developmental delay (including language or speech problems) or D) Cerebral Palsy with inability to walk unassisted or E) Severe visual loss (cannot fixate/legally blind or corrected acuity &lt;6/60 in both eyes) or F) Deafness (requiring a hearing aid or cochlear implants).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 24 months (+/- 6months) corrected for gestation.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disability by different grades and types will be assessed based on the BSID III and/or ASQ score and/or short health questionnaire administered to access cerebral palsy, deafness and blindness. All available information will be used to determine the absence/presence of disability.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 24 months (+/- 6months) corrected for gestation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Composite secondary outcome looking at i) surgery for proven NEC and ii) progression of NEC Stage II to Stage IIIA/B as per Modified Bell's Staging Criteria for NEC.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until discharged home.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of parenteral nutrition defined as the period of time (hours) during which any nutritional requirements are provided by parenteral nutrition (lipid emulsion and amino acid solutions).  Information will be extracted from medical records reveiw.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until discharged home.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Brain injury is defined as grade 3 and 4 intraventricular haemorrhage (IVH; on either side of the head) seen during ultrasound according to the system of grading defined by the Australian and New Zealand Neonatal Network (ANZNN) guidelines, or the presence by ultrasound any of the following: periventricular leukomalacia (PVL), porencephalic cysts or hydrocephalus requiring neurosurgical intervention.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until discharge home</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Duration of mechanical ventilation in days. Mechanical ventilation is defined as respiratory support provided either by endotracheal tube ventilation, continuous positive airway pressure or humidified high-flow oxygen. Information will be extracted from medical records reveiw.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until discharged home.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Chronic lung disease (also known as bronchopulmonary dysplasia) is defined as receiving supplemental oxygen or any form respiratory support (mechanical ventilation, continuous positive airway pressure, humidified high flow oxygen). Information will be extracted from medical records reveiw.</outcome>
      <timepoint>36 weeks corrected gestational age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severe retinopathy of prematurity (ROP) is defined as warranting treatment with laser surgery, cryotherapy or monoclonal antibody therapy (according to local site guidelines). Information will be extracted from medical records reveiw.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until discharged home.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of hospital stay is defined as the number of days from the Neonatal Intensive Care Unit admission to final discharge home.  Information will be extracted from medical records reveiw.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until discharged home.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma cytokine levels, before study treatment commencement and during treatment, will be measured by multiplex assay platform.  Plasma cytokine levels will only be measured in a subset of infants enrolled at the Perth, Western Australia, site.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Small blood samples will be taken at 1) time of blood draw for screening for LOS and/or NEC, and 2) 48 hours after commencment of study treatment.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Magnetic Resonance Image (MRI) will be used to define white matter injury. White matter injury, white matter integrity and development will be defined using the following methods: i) standardized qualitative scoring and diffusion measures of white matter integrity, which is define the extent of injury to white and gray matter and the cerebellum, these will be scored using a standard system and will be performed by two blinded assessors; ii) diffusion weighted images will be acquired by measuring apparent diffusion coefficient and anisotropy in eight template-based cerebral regions and in the corticospinal tract, corpus callosum, anterior limb of the internal capsule and optic radiation, and iii) tract-based spatial statistics will be applied to the diffusion data to identify regions of difference between randomised groups at term.  MRI will only be measured in a subset of infants enrolled at the Perth, Western Australia, site.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 38-42 weeks corrected gestational age.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to full enteral feeds, the time in days required for infant to achieve an enteral intake of 120ml/kg/day or more, for three consecutive days. Information will be extracted from medical records review.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Until discharge home</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Gestation &lt;29 weeks at birth.
&lt; 6 hours (no later than 12 hours) from blood culture taken for suspected late-onset sepsis or NEC.
Informed parental consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>72</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Hours</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>6</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Months</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Congenital malformations, chromosomal abnormalities or any other condition considered incompatible with disability-free survival at 24 months of age.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Upon consent, infants will be randomised using a web-based randomisation system. </concealment>
    <sequence>Treatment allocation will be balanced using minimisation for the following characteristics: study site and gestation (&lt;26 weeks gestation or &gt;/= 26 weeks gestation.  Multiple birth infants will be randomised individually.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Primary analysis population: 900 infants (approximately 50% of all infants randomised) are expected to show evidence of LOS or NEC within 48 hours of randomisation, yielding 80% power to detect a 25% reduction in risk of death or disability at 24 months (+/- 6 months) from 40%-30%, with two-tailed alpha of 0.05. Analysis allows for 5% loss to follow-up and 5% non-compliance.

Secondary analysis population: Full cohort of approximately 1,800 randomised babies will provide 80% power to detect a difference between event rates of 30% (control) versus 24% (intervention) at the two-sided 5% level of significance.

Sub-group analysis population (Perth, Western Australia only): For cytokine analysis the expected sample size of 80 infants will achieve at least 90% power at 2p=0.05 to detect a difference of 0.75 standard deviation between the mean cytokine concentrations of PTX and placebo groups. MRI o f80 infants will allow detection of a similar difference in MRI score between PTX and placebo groups with &gt;90% power.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/11/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2019</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1800</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize>45</currentsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,QLD,SA,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>King Edward Memorial Hospital - Subiaco</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Nepean Hospital - Kingswood</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <hospital>Mater Mother's Hospital - South Brisbane</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Womens and Childrens Hospital - North Adelaide</hospital>
    <hospital>Mercy Hospital for Women - Heidelberg</hospital>
    <hospital>Monash Medical Centre - Clayton campus - Clayton</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Childrens Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>The Canberra Hospital - Garran</hospital>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>John Hunter Children's Hospital - New Lambton</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Hospital for Women - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Flinders Medical Centre - Bedford Park</hospital>
    <postcode>6008 - Subiaco</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>2747 - Kingswood</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - St Leonards</postcode>
    <postcode>4101 - South Brisbane</postcode>
    <postcode>4029 - Royal Brisbane Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>5006 - North Adelaide</postcode>
    <postcode>3084 - Heidelberg</postcode>
    <postcode>3168 - Clayton</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Parkville</postcode>
    <postcode>2605 - Garran</postcode>
    <postcode>3052 - Melbourne University</postcode>
    <postcode>2305 - New Lambton Heights</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>5042 - Bedford Park</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Wellington</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Singapore</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>British Columbia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Alberta</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Manitoba</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Saskatchewan</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Ontario</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Quebec</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Canada</country>
      <state>Nova Scotia</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Switzerland</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Shenzhen, Guangdong Province</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <state>Taichung</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>c/o Dr Alpana Ghadge
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown, NSW 1450</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC) project grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 1421
Canberra, ACT, 2601
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>The University of Western Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>35 Stirling Highway, 
Perth, Western Australia, 6009</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Preterm infants are highly susceptible to bacterial late-onset sepsis (LOS) and necrotizing enterocolitis (NEC), both are major causes of systemic inflammation and contribute to brain injury and long-term disability in premature infants. Treating LOS and NEC are essential for survival, but suppressing systemic inflammation can also help reduce mortality, hospital stay and disability due to brain injury. The current treatments for NEC and LOS are limited to antibiotics, supportive care and surgery in some NEC cases, all of which do not aid in reducing systemic inflammation, therefore there is a need to reduce systemic inflammation. Pentoxifylline is a safe, low-cost, non-steroidal drug with potent immune-modulating activity with the potential of suppressing systemic inflammation induced by LOS or NEC. A recent Cochrane Review of 6 randomised controlled trials (RCT) suggests that PTX, given with antibiotics in neonatal sepsis, reduces mortality and length of hospital stay. 

We are conducting an international multicentre trial that will enrol and consent approximately 1,800 preterm infants (&lt;29 weeks gestational age). The primary aim is to evaluate the effect of treatment with intravenous Pentoxifylline versus placebo, starting within 6 hours from blood culture taken for suspected  LOS or NEC. After 48 hours treatment will cease if diagnosis is refuted or will continue for 4 days if diagnosis is proven. The primary outcome to measure effectiveness is survival without disability at 18-24 months of age (corrected for gestation).</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunter New England Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Hunter New England Local Health District 
Locked Bag 1
New Lambton, NSW, 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16/04/20/3.04</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>31/03/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern A Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/05/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>17/NTA/33</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/02/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Karen Simmer AO</name>
      <address>Neonatal Clinical Care Unit
A Block, First Floor
King Edward Memorial Hospital
374 Bagot Rd, Subiaco, Western Australia, 6008</address>
      <phone>+61893401260</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>karen.simmer@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Alpana Ghadge</name>
      <address>NHMRC Clinical Trials Centre
c/o Dr Alpana Ghadge
Locked Bag 77
Camperdown NSW 1450</address>
      <phone>+61295625341</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>PTX@ctc.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Tobias Strunk</name>
      <address>Neonatal Clinical Care Unit
A Block, First Floor
King Edward Memorial Hospital
374 Bagot Rd, Subiaco, Western Australia, 6008</address>
      <phone>+61893401260</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tobias.strunk@health.wa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Julie Hibbert</name>
      <address>Centre for Neonatal Research and Education
University of Western Australia
M551
35 Stirling Hwy
Perth, Western Australia, 6009</address>
      <phone>+61893401558</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>julie.hibbert@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>