<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372385">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/03/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000378325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does patella taping alter the degree of knee motion during functional tasks in individuals with anterior knee pain?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does patella taping influence knee kinematics in individuals with patellofemoral pain syndrome? A Crossover design study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1193-2452</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Ni known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Patellofemoral pain syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Kinematic analysis of the knee joint of individuals with Patellofemoral pain syndrome using 3D analysis software ( KneeKG infrared tracking device (Emovi Medical)  while performing 3 functional activities - walking, step down and single leg squat, at Baseline (untaped) with Dynamic Taping (Intervention A) and with Rigid tape (Intervention B). Each taping application will be specific to the individuals requirements. 
Baseline measure- following application of the exoskeleton harness, a habitulisation period of 2 minutes walking on the treadmill (to acclimitise to the harness placement and the treadmill walking action) and calibration of the knee KG system(which takes about 5 minutes maximum and requires the individual to move their leg in a variety of directions) the individual will be analysed performing the following 3 tasks.
1. walking at a comfortable speed on a treadmill for 45 seconds. 2 tests were completed
2. stepping down from a 20cm block with unharnessed leg to floor and returning repeatedly for 15 seconds and a slow and steady pace. 2 repeat tests carried out
3. Single leg squats for 15 seconds. 2 tests also.
The intervention order will predetermined by the participation number and was randomly generated using a computer program
That taping technique was then applied by the assessor.
Intervention A Involves the application of Dynamic tape(TM) which is a new concept sports tape composed of synthetic stretch nylon and lycra cloth with a choice of 4 techniques deemed appropriate for the individuals requirements depending on their biomechanics, neuromuscular deficiencies and patella alignment. Once the 1st Intervention (A or B) has completed the individual can either remove the tape immediately or keep it on and remove it 12 hrs prior to the 2nd testing session
Intervention B will be the application of rigid sports tape which has a Rayon construction with rubber zinc oxide adhesive material. This will be used in combination with hypoallergenic tape as an underlay, such as Fixomull.. The application is based on the McConnell Taping principle where the patella is repositioned and held by the tape. It will include medial glide, medial tilt and medial rotation as required for the participants presentation.
The 3 functional tasks as performed in the baseline measure were repeated immediately and then again on another day with a minumum of 12 hour washout period between the interventions
Testing occurs in the Physiotherapy Department at Prince of Wales Hospital and is carried out by the principal investigator who has 20 + yrs experience as a musculoskeletal physiotherapist.
Once the 1st Intervention (A or B) has been completed the individual can either remove the tape immediately or keep it on and remove it a minumum of 12 hrs prior to the 2nd testing session.


</interventions>
    <comparator>Baseline (Untaped) kinematic analysis of knee joint motion during 3 functional tasks of walking, stepping down and performing a single leg squat</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee Flexion/extension values during  the gait cycle while walking at a comfortable speed, stepping down and while performing a single leg squat using the Knee KG 3 D analysis unit and EMOVI software
This is a composite primary outcome</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following a 2 minute walk on the treadmill to get used to the harness and the walking conditions of the treadmill. Baseline assessment (untaped therefore control) will be completed. Then the 3 functional tests will be repeated immediately following application of either Intervention A and Intervention B tape and then again following at least 12 hours washout period prior to the application of the 2 nd taping material</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee Abduction/adduction values during  the gait cycle while walking at a comfortable speed, stepping down and while performing a single leg squat using the Knee KG 3 D analysis unit and EMOVI software
This is a composite primary outcome</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following a 2 minute walk on the treadmill to get used to the harness and the walking conditions of the treadmill. Baseline assessment (untaped therefore control) will be completed. Then the 3 functional tests will be repeated immediately following application of either Intervention A and Intervention B tape and then again following at least 12 hours washout period prior to the application of the 2 nd taping material</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Knee Rotation values during  the gait cycle while walking at a comfortable speed, stepping down and while performing a single leg squat using the Knee KG 3 D analysis unit and EMOVI software</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following a 2 minute walk on the treadmill to get used to the harness and the walking conditions of the treadmill. Baseline assessment (untaped therefore control) will be completed. Then the 3 functional tests will be repeated immediately following application of either Intervention A and Intervention B tape and then again following at least 12 hours washout period prior to the application of the 2 nd taping material</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>pain to be assessed during performance of functional task using a  Visual analogue scale (VAS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Following habitulisation of walking on the treadmill, and calibration of the Knee KG system the VAS scale will be verbally noted while the participant performs each of the 3 functional tasks at baseline (untaped-Control) then again with the inclusion of Intervention A (Dynamic tape) and Intervention B
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Any individual presenting with anterior knee pain exacerbated by 2 or more of the following activities  walking, running, jumping, ascending or descending stairs, static quads contraction, prolonged knee flexion</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Diagnosis of any other knee pathology including Knee OA, patella #, patella dislocation, ligamentous, soft tissue injury or previous knee surgery, recent physiotherapy intervention including taping application or previous skin reaction to adhesive tape</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation  of intervention order using a randomisation table created by computer software was included</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size: n=30 patients per treatment group. This number is based on the detection of a mean difference in the dependent variables of approximately 20%, a significance level of 5% and a power of 0.8. This number is a reflection also of the stated accuracy of the measurement systems employed in this study (lustig et al, 2012). </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>3/10/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/09/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>6/10/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Kerri Blyth</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Physiotherapy department
Prince of wales Hospital
High Street, Randwick, NSW, 2031</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of New South Wales</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Prince of Wales Clinical school
Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick, NSW 2031</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor William Walsh</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Surgical and Orthopaedic Research Lab
Prince Of Wales Hospital
Barker Street
Randwick, NSW, 2031</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patellofemoral Pain syndrome (PFPS) is a condition associated with anterior knee pain in the absence of other pathology. 
Kinematic variations have been identified in this condition. 
Physiotherapy management of this condition aims to correct neuromuscular imbalances and the use of patella taping is a common adjunct to manual therapy and exercise prescription.
With the advancement in taping materials and variation in application methods further investigation into the influence patella taping has on knee kinematics is justified.
Aim
To investigate if the application of patella tape influences the knee kinematics in three planes of motion compared to baseline untaped data.
Objectives
Analyse knee kinematics during three functional tasks of walking, step descent and single leg squat for each individual
Compare the effects of the two different taping materials (rigid and dynamic tape) on the repeated functional tasks versus the control data
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>SOUTH EASTERN SYDNEY LOCAL HEALTH DISTRICT - HUMAN RESEARCH ETHICS COMMITTEE (HREC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>G71, East Wing 
Edmund Blacket Building
Prince of Wales Hospital
Randwick NSW 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/11/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>14/261</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kerri Blyth</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Level 1 High Street
Prince of wales Hospital
Randwick
NSW, 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 5900</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9382 5903</fax>
      <email>Kerri.Blyth@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kerri Blyth</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Level 1 High Street
Prince of wales Hospital
Randwick
NSW, 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 5900</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9382 5903</fax>
      <email>Kerri.Blyth@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kerri Blyth</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Level 1 High Street
Prince of wales Hospital
Randwick
NSW, 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 5900</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9382 5903</fax>
      <email>Kerri.Blyth@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kerri Blyth</name>
      <address>Physiotherapy Department
Level 1 High Street
Prince of wales Hospital
Randwick
NSW, 2031</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 5900</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9382 5903</fax>
      <email>Kerri.Blyth@health.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>