<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="343411">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/09/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000948998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The efficacy and social validity of a group cognitive behavioural therapy for young migrants from war-affected countries</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A pretest posttest 3-month follow-up cluster randomised controlled trial of a group intervention "Teaching Recovery Techniques" to prevent worsening of early posttraumatic stress symptoms in young migrants.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>posttraumatic stress disorder</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The Teaching Recovery Techniques (Smith et al., 2000) is a group-based cognitive-behavioural therapy. It was developed for survivors of war or conflicts aged 8 years or older.  In brief, the Teaching Recovery Techniques is a psycho-social-education intervention, aimed at educating children about their symptoms and teaching adaptive coping strategies which include creating self-coping statements, relaxation, and exposure strategies. The program was designed to prevent worsening of early symptoms rather than to treat severe clinical diagnoses. The intervention manual and workbook can be found at Children and War website (www.childrenandwar.org). Participants in the intervention groups will receive the manualised intervention while those in the control groups will not receive any intervention until the end of the trial. The intervention will be run for one hour a week for a total of 8 weeks and facilitated by two trained facilitators.Control groups will be offered the same intervention at the end of trial for ethical reason.</interventions>
    <comparator>Control group will be assessed before and after the waiting period using the same measures as the intervention condition. Participants in control group will not receive any forms of intervention during the waiting period but will be offered the program immediately after the intervention ended in the intervention group, i.e., 8-9 weeks after pretest. Participants who become distressed during the waiting period will be withdrawn from the study for immediate intervention according to the project crisis protocol.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Revised Impact of Event Scale (RIES-13) mean score</outcome>
      <timepoint>pretest, posttest and 3-months after intervention ended</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Birleson Depression Self-Rating scale (DSRS) mean score</outcome>
      <timepoint>pretest, posttest and 3-months after intervention ended</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hopkins Symptom Checklist-37 for Adolescents (HSCL-37A) mean score</outcome>
      <timepoint>pretest, posttest and 3-months after intervention ended</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Parent Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ) mean score</outcome>
      <timepoint>pretest, posttest and 3-months after intervention ended</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Teacher Strengths and Difficulties Questionnaire (SDQ) mean score</outcome>
      <timepoint>pretest, posttest and 3-months after intervention ended</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To evaluate social validity of the intervention, we employed the Quantitative and Qualitive Student and Parent Evaluation Schedule adapted from Roberts, kane, Thomson and Bishop's (2003) study. In each intervention session, students rated on a 5-point Likert scale how much they have enjoyed and have learnt from the session. At the end of the intervention, students and parents were interviewed separately using a semi-structured interview about the usefulness and appropriateness of the program.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Weekly and at the end of the intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>exposure to war-related trauma before migrating to Australia, living in Australia for less than 7 years, and self-report symptoms of PTSD</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>11</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>17</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>diagnosis of PTSD, limited English proficiency, being a non-accompanied humanitarian entrant, and currently receiving psychological treatment for PTSD</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Cluster design was used to avoid contamination of intervention effect had individual design been used (Campbell, Elbourne &amp; Altman, 2004). To achieve this, eligible participants from the same schools will be grouped together and receive the same condition. Willing participants will be recruited from public and private schools in Perth with high density of refugee students. Participating schools will be asked to refer students for screening. This is done based on what the schools know about students' family background and current functioning.  In accordance with the specific ethical guidance regarding young people by the National Statement on Ethical Conduct in Human Research, we will contact the primary carers before approaching the students. Families referred by schools will be approached using several strategies, including parent information sessions, sending a brief information form to parents, and direct teacher-parents phone calls. Parents who express interest in the study will receive a Participant Information and consent form. The voluntary nature of the study will be emphasized and active consent, written or verbal, will be sought before screening. Students whose parents consented will be approached in schools during school hour. They will be given the Participant information letter and written consent will be collected before they are screened using the UCLA PTSD Index. Suitable participants will be grouped according to schools and then randomly allocated into intervention or control condition. Participants will be recruited before group allocation; therefore interviewers who screen the participants will be unaware of group allocation at assessment.</concealment>
    <sequence>In order to improve group equivalence, schools will be match-paired by school type (public vs private), school level (primary vs secondary school), and socioenomic status. Each school in the pairs will be randomly allocated into either intervention or WL control group by the statistical supervisor of this study who had no clinical involvement in the study using a computer generating random number.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>16/03/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/05/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>84</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Chew Sia Ooi</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Psychology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987, Perth, 
Western Australia 6845.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Curtin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Curtin University
School of Psychology
GPO Box U1987, Perth, 
Western Australia 6845.</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Healthway Research Starter Grant</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Western Australia Health Promotion Foundation
PO Box 1284
West Perth 
Western Australia 6872</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Rosie Rooney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987, Perth, 
Western Australia 6845.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>A/Prof Clare Roberts</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987, Perth, 
Western Australia 6845.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Bernadette Wright</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>West Australian Transcultural Mental Health Centre
50 Murray St, Perth, Western Australia 6000 
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Robert Kane</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychology, Curtin University
GPO Box U1987, Perth, Western Australia 6845.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study was designed to test the efficacy and social validity of a group program in helping war-exposed young people with posttraumatic stress symptoms. The content of the intervention includes, psychoeducation, techniques to manage intrusive memories, relaxation, and planning for the future. We expect that participants in the intervention condition will report a reduction in posttraumatic stress, depression and anxiety symptoms, as well as improvement in general functioning after receiving the intervention. We also expect the intervention to be socially aceptable to the participants and their parents.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth 
WA 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/07/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HR60/2008</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chew Ooi</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987,
Perth 
WA 6845.</address>
      <phone>+61(0)431649511</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chewsia@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chew Ooi</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987,
Perth 
WA 6845.</address>
      <phone>+61(0)431649511</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chewsia@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chew Ooi</name>
      <address>School of Psychology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987,
Perth 
WA 6845.</address>
      <phone>+61(0)431649511</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chewsia@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Chew Ooi</name>
      <address>School of Psychology Curtin University 
GPO Box U1987, Perth Western Australia 6845.</address>
      <phone>+61431649511</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>chewsia@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>