<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335523">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/05/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/11/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000997055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of Varying Body Weight on the Pharmacokinetics of Paracetamol in Children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Determining the Correct Paracetamol Dose for Children of Varying Body Weights</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Pharmacokinetics of paracetamol in obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Measuring blood (from IV or finger-prick sources) and saliva paracetamol concentration in children following a prescribed dose of paracetamol in overweight and obese children. A maximum of 7 IV blood, 9 saliva and 3 finger-prick blood samples may be taken. Children who present to the Emergency Medicine Department at the Womens and Childrens Hospital who have been given a dose of paracetamol will be approached about participating in the study. Paracetamol will be given at a dose, schedule and route which is at the discretion of the medical staff - this study will not influence the treatment that participants recieve in any way (including the use of intra-venous cannulas, which will only be used if they are inserted as part of normal medical care). Participants will be observed for no more than 6 hours after a dose of paracetamol. Patients will only be observed following a single dose.</interventions>
    <comparator>There will be 3 groups of children recruited - one with BMI at or under the 25th percentile for age (as per CDC growth charts), one who are overweight or obese (as per Cole et al 2000), and another with normal BMI for their age (ie those that do not fall into either of the above definitions). All children who are recruited will have recieved paracetamol at a dose, schedule and route which is at the discretion of the medical staff - this study will not influence the treatment that participants recieve in any way. Participants will be observed for no more than 6 hours after a dose of paracetamol. Patients will only be observed following a single dose.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine and compare the pharmacokinetics (half-life, volume of distribution, clearance) of paracetamol in obese, overweight and children with a normal body mass index.
The saliva paracetamol concentration will be determined in each patient at each time point, and pharmacokinetic parameters will be determined by non-compartmental modelling and population pharmacokinetic modelling</outcome>
      <timepoint>Saliva samples may be taken pre-dose, then 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 4 and 6 hours after a dose. IV blood samples are scheduled for 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 3, 4 and 6 hours after a dose, and finger-prick samples for 1, 2 and 4 hours after a dose. Alterations in this schedule are allowed, but the precise time samples were taken must be recorded accurately.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare the number of obese and overweight children whom achieve a therapeutically effective plasma paracetamol concentration (10-30mg/L) compared to the number of children with a normal body mass index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Using modelling techniques, we will be able to estimate what the drug concentration of any patient at any time (up to 6 hours after) a dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Determine the efficacy of paracetamol in achieving analgesia and/or antipyresis (ie reduction in pain as measured by routinely administered pain scores (eg visual analogue scales) or reduction in temperature (tympanic thermometry)) in obese, overweight and children with a normal body mass index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Using modelling techniques, we will be able to estimate what the pain scores and temperature of each patient at any time (up to 6 hours after) a dose</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Using pharmacokinetic modelling, develop simple dosage strategies to ensure optimal therapeutic benefits of paracetamol in children of varying body weight</outcome>
      <timepoint>Using modelling techniques, we will be able to estimate what the drug concentration of any patient at any time (up to 6 hours after) a dose</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Children who have been prescribed paracetamol by their treating doctor will be eligible for inclusion in the study.
Participants will have received one or more doses of paracetamol, the time of the last dose is precisely known.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>1</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>18</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Known abnormality in hepatic or renal function
Known chronic gastrointestinal dysfunction
Known mental health or intellectual disability</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>273</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of South Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of South Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>GPO Box 2471
Adelaide SA 5001</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Channel 7 Childrens Research Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 2438, REGENCY PARK, SA 5942</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Womens and Childrens Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>72 King William Road
North Adelaide SA 5000</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The most appropriate dosage of the commonly used analgesic and antipyretic medication paracetamol has not been studied in overweight and obese children. Following a dose of paracetamol, we will measure the saliva and blood concentration (obtained from finger-prick or IV cannula) of paracetamol in a group of overweight and obese children, and compare the calculated pharmacokinetic parameters in the overweight/obese population to the normal BMI population, and determine if there are any differences. In addition, we will measure the efficacy of paracetamol in relieving pain and/or fever in each of these patient groups. A subsequant population pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic modelling analysis will allow us to simulate what doses are required to maintain overweight and obese children within a target therapeutic range of 10-30mg/L for the longest period of time.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Womens and Childrens Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>72 King William Road
North Adelaide SA 5006</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/05/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RED2207/9/12</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/08/2009</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Michael Wiese</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
School of Pharmacy and Medical Sciences
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide 5001</address>
      <phone>08 8302 2312</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.wiese@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Michael Wiese</name>
      <address>University of South Australia
School of Pharmacy and Medical Sciences
GPO Box 2471
Adelaide 5001</address>
      <phone>61 8 8302 2312</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>michael.wiese@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>