<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368979">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/09/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000948594</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Does blocking intestinal sweet taste sensing decrease glucose absorption in patients with type 2 diabetes?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A blinded placebo-controlled trial to determine whether inhibiting intestinal detection of sweet taste reduces intestinal glucose uptake in healthy subjects and patients with type 2 diabetes</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Royal Adelaide Hospital Protocol Number: 150606</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Healthy subjects and patients with type 2 diabetes will be screened for eligibility then undergo 2 study day visits, separated by at least 2 weeks, in a randomised, double-blinded manner. 

All subjects will receive a standardised evening meal prior to the study day, then fast until the following morning, with water allowed after the meal until 10 pm. Patients treated by oral metformin will be instructed to withhold any dose due the evening for 2 days (48 hours) prior to the study visit, and to defer their morning dose until the meal at the end of the study.

On each study day, fasted unsedated subjects will have an intravenous cannula inserted into forearm veins for blood sampling and for infusion of glucose or insulin. Insulin (0.2 IU/mL) or 25% glucose will be infused intravenously at a rate adjusted to achieve hyperglycaemia (12 mmol/L) throughout the study period. Once stably clamped, a small diameter (5.3 mm) video endoscope will be placed in position in the second part of the duodenum via an anaesthetised nostril. Five mucosal biopsies will be collected via endoscope forceps, then the endoscope will be withdrawn. A thin intraduodenal catheter (3.5 mm) will be inserted via an anaesthetised nostril into the second part of the duodenum; positioning will be maintained by continuous measurement of the transmucosal potential difference between antrum and duodenum. An automated blood pressure cuff will be placed around the arm for measurement of blood pressure and heart rate throughout the study period. 

Subjects will be randomised to the order of infusions containing the sweetness inhibitor lactisole, or control (no lactisole), on alternative study days. 

On a control study day subjects will receive a preload infusion of 0.9% saline (2 mL/min) via the intraduodenal catheter over 30 min. At 30 min (T = 0) a glucose solution will be infused for 120 min (90 g glucose dissolved in water to a volume of 240 mL, 2 mL/min; 3 kcal/min). At T = 120 min a glucose solution containing the non-metabolisable glucose analogue 3-O-methyl glucose (3-OMG, to assess glucose absorption) will be infused via the intraduodenal catheter for 60 min (45 g glucose and 2.4 g of 3-OMG dissolved in water to a volume of 120 mL, 2 mL/min; 3 kcal/min).

On a lactisole study day subjects will receive a preload infusion of 450 ppm lactisole in 0.9% saline (27 mg dissolved in 60 mL; 2 mL/min) via the intraduodenal catheter over 30 min. At 30 min (T = 0) a glucose solution containing 450 ppm lactisole will be infused for 120 min (90 g glucose and 108 mg lactisole dissolved in water to a volume of 240 mL, 2 mL/min; 3 kcal/min). At T = 120 min a glucose solution containing 450 ppm lactisole and the non-metabolisable glucose analogue 3-O-methyl glucose (3-OMG, to assess glucose absorption) will be infused via the intraduodenal catheter for 60 min (45 g glucose, 54 mg lactisole and 2.4 g of 3-OMG dissolved in water to a volume of 120 mL, 2 mL/min; 3 kcal/min).

At the end of glucose infusions (T = 180 min), the intraduodenal catheter will be removed and the endoscope inserted again to collect 5 more duodenal biopsies; bloods will be collected regularly over the 5 hour study. A log of infusion administration will be kept to monitor protocol adherence.</interventions>
    <comparator>On a control study day subjects will receive a preload infusion of 0.9% saline (2 mL/min) via the intraduodenal catheter over 30 min. At 30 min (T = 0) a glucose solution will be infused for 120 min (90 g glucose dissolved in water to a volume of 240 mL, 2 mL/min; 3 kcal/min). At T = 120 min a glucose solution containing the non-metabolisable glucose analogue 3-O-methyl glucose (3-OMG, to assess glucose absorption) will be infused via the intraduodenal catheter for 60 min (45 g glucose and 2.4 g of 3-OMG dissolved in water to a volume of 120 mL, 2 mL/min; 3 kcal/min).</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportional differences in the incremental area under the curve, peak and/or time-to-peak for serum 3-OMG levels (absorption) for lactisole vs. placebo during intraduodenal glucose infusion; comparison between healthy subjects vs. type 2 patients (composite outcome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>T = -10, 0 (commencement of intraduodenal glucose infusion), 10, 20, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, 210, 240, 270 and 300 min</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportional differences in the incremental area under the curve, peak and/or time-to-peak for plasma incretin hormones for lactisole vs. placebo during intraduodenal glucose infusion; comparison between healthy subjects vs. type 2 patients (composite outcome)</outcome>
      <timepoint>T = -10, 0 (commencement of intraduodenal glucose infusion), 10, 20, 30, 45, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, 210, 240, 270 and 300 min</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in baseline or post-infusion expression of transcript (RNA) and/or protein for glucose sensing and transport/uptake pathway molecules in mucosal biopsies (composite outcome).

Targets assessed include sweet taste receptors (T1R2, T1R3), G-protein (alpha-gustducin), ion channels (Kir6.2, TRPM5) and glucose transporters (SGLT-1, GLUT2).</outcome>
      <timepoint>T = -2 (immediately prior to commencement of intraduodenal glucose infusion at T = 0) and 180 min</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Identification of glucose sensing, signalling and transport/uptake pathway molecules in functionally activated (glucose-responsive) cells within mucosal biopsies (composite outcome).

Targets assessed include sweet taste receptors (T1R2, T1R3), G-protein (alpha-gustducin), ion channels (Kir6.2, TRPM5), glucose transporters (SGLT-1, GLUT2) and cell markers (5-HT, GLP-1, GIP).</outcome>
      <timepoint>T = 180 min, where T=0 is the start of glucose infusion</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>(Healthy) Nondiabetic, healthy volunteers matched as closely as possible for sex and body mass index; body mass index 20-30 kg/m2; HbA1c less than or equal to 7.0%

(Type 2 Diabetic) Volunteers with type 2 diabetes (World Health Organisation criteria) managed by diet alone or metformin; body mass index &gt;20 kg/m2; HbA1c &gt;7.0%</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>75</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion
(Healthy) Significant illness including impairment to cardiovascular or respiratory function that limits a subjects activity and therefore would represent a risk to undertaking endoscopy safely (American Society of Anaesthesiologists Grade 3 or more); History of gastrointestinal disease, including significant upper gastrointestinal symptoms (assessed by a validated gastrointestinal symptom questionnaire), pancreatitis, or previous gastrointestinal surgery (other than uncomplicated appendectomy or cholecystectomy); Diffuse mucosal disease involving the upper gastrointestinal tract, including Crohns disease, coeliac disease, or ischaemic changes, evident either macroscopically or on histopathological examination of mucosal biopsies; Haemoglobin below the lower limit of the normal range (ie. &lt;135g/L for men and 115g/L for women), and ferritin below the lower limit of normal (below 20ng/mL for women and 30ng/mL for men); Significant history of migraine; Impaired renal or liver function (as assessed by calculated creatinine clearance &lt; 90 mL/min or abnormal liver function tests, &gt; 2 times upper limit of normal); Body mass index greater than 30 kg/m2 or less than 20 kg/m2; Donation of blood within the previous 3 months; Participation in any other research studies within the previous 3 months; Subjects requiring the use of anticoagulant drugs, antiplatelet agents or NSAIDS; Subjects with known coagulopathy; Presence of mucosal abnormalities at endoscopy; Subjects requiring medication that may influence gastrointestinal function; Evidence of drug abuse, consumption of more than 20 g alcohol or 10 cigarettes per day; Female patients not using appropriate contraceptive method (ie oral contraceptive pill, diaphragm, DepoProvera hormonal contraceptive injection, intrauterine device (IUD), Norplant method); Vegetarian, lactation or pregnancy (verified by urine testing in women of reproductive age; in these subjects, study will be completed during the follicular phase of the menstrual cycle)

(Type 2 Diabetics) Significant illness, other than type 2 diabetes, including impairment to cardiovascular or respiratory function that limits a subjects activity and therefore would represent a risk to undertaking endoscopy safely (American Society of Anesthesiologists Grade 3 or more); History of gastrointestinal disease, including significant upper gastrointestinal symptoms (assessed by a validated gastrointestinal symptom questionnaire), pancreatitis, or previous gastrointestinal surgery (other than uncomplicated appendectomy or cholecystectomy); Diffuse mucosal disease involving the upper gastrointestinal tract, including Crohns disease, coeliac disease, or ischaemic changes, evident either macroscopically or on histopathological examination of mucosal biopsies; Haemoglobin below the lower limit of the normal range (ie. &lt;135g/L for men and 115g/L for women), and ferritin below the lower limit of normal (below 20ng/mL for women and 30ng/mL for men); Significant history of migraine; Impaired renal or liver function (as assessed by calculated creatinine clearance &lt; 90 mL/min or abnormal liver function tests (&gt; 2 times upper limit of normal)); Subjects medicated with anti-diabetics other than metformin; Subjects unable to self-monitor blood glucose levels; Volunteers with body mass index less than 20 kg/m2; Donation of blood within the previous 3 months; Participation in any other research studies within the previous 3 months; Subjects requiring the use of anticoagulant drugs, anti-platelet agents or NSAIDS; Subjects with known coagulopathy; Presence of mucosal abnormalities at endoscopy; Subjects requiring medication that may influence gastrointestinal function; Evidence of drug abuse, consumption of more than 20 g alcohol or 10 cigarettes per day; Female patients not using appropriate contraceptive method (ie oral contraceptive pill, diaphragm, DepoProvera hormonal contraceptive injection, intrauterine device (IUD), Norplant method); Vegetarian, lactation, or pregnancy (verified by urine testing in women of reproductive age; in these subjects, the study will be completed during the follicular phase of the menstrual cycle)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential participants will be screened for medical and diet history, medications and lifestyle eligibility and assessed for blood haemoglobin, ferritin, HbA1c, renal and liver function. Study participants will provide written, informed consent and will be randomised and blinded to allocation of lactisole in the preload and main infusion on both study days.

Allocation to the order of infusion protocol will be concealed by schedule, which will be undertaken and held by pharmacy staff of the Royal Adelaide Hospital; allocation will be blind to staff and subjects involved in this project.</concealment>
    <sequence>computer-generated random number table</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample sizes are calculated for alpha=0.05 and beta=0.2 from a priori data on the primary outcome measures. The effect size for glucose absorption, the most variable outcome, is 1.052; subject dropouts are incorporated at 15%. All variables will be assessed using ANOVA, with treatment and time factors. Post hoc tests, adjusted for multiple comparisons, will be performed for significant effects. Relationships between transcript expression and other factors will be compared using Pearson correlation coefficient; area-under-the-curve data will be compared using 2-tailed paired Students t-tests.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/09/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>22/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>48</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Adelaide Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>A family of receptors in the gut recognises all known sweet tasting molecules, including glucose. We, and others, have shown that activation of these sweet taste receptors triggers a series of events, mediated by gut hormones, which coordinate the absorption and metabolism of glucose, increasing the capacity for both. These gut hormones increase insulin release in the presence of glucose, and increase levels and function of the major gut glucose transporter, sodium-glucose co-transporter 1 (SGLT-1). Accordingly, the activation status of gut sweet taste receptors has the potential for substantial influence on the control of blood glucose.

Patients with type 2 diabetes have increased capacity for glucose absorption from their gut, a trait which can worsen their blood glucose control, and increase disease progression. We recently published important data showing that sweet taste receptors in the duodenum were abnormal in patients with type 2 diabetes during high blood glucose, in association with increased glucose absorption. Blocking duodenal sweet taste receptors is known to reduce the release of gut hormones linked to increases in the glucose transporter SGLT-1 in both rodents and humans, however, it is unknown whether blocking sweet taste receptors in patients with type 2 diabetes can reduce glucose transporter function and, therein, glucose absorption, as a new approach to therapy. We now plan to test the effects of the sweet taste receptor blocker, lactisole, on blood glucose control in patients with type 2 diabetes following a glucose infusion.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide SA 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/07/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/15/RAH/224, RAH Protocol 150606</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard L Young</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine, University of Adelaide
Level 3, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital North Terrace, Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82222082</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82223870</fax>
      <email>richard.young@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard L Young</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine, University of Adelaide
Level 3, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital North Terrace, Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82222082</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82223870</fax>
      <email>richard.young@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard L Young</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine, University of Adelaide
Level 3, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital North Terrace, Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82222082</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82223870</fax>
      <email>richard.young@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard L Young</name>
      <address>Discipline of Medicine, University of Adelaide
Level 3, Eleanor Harrald Building
Royal Adelaide Hospital North Terrace, Adelaide SA 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82222082</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 82223870</fax>
      <email>richard.young@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>