<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370939">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000936426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Targeting maternal diet for better child outcomes: The Healthy Parents, Healthy Kids Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Targeting perinatal diet for better maternal and child outcomes: a randomised controlled trial</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1184-5171</utrn>
    <trialacronym>HPHK</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gut health in mothers and infants</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition> Immune system functioning in mothers and infants</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Dietary behaviours in women</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal oral and gastrointestinal development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the immune system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>In addition to receiving treatment as usual, pregnant women allocated to the intervention group will attend a half-day educational dietary workshop at the beginning of their third trimester (3 months before birth). Recommendations and dietary advice delivered in the workshop is designed to promote a healthy gut microbiota. Participants will attend a small-group session delivered by a nutritionist (Master of Human Nutrition qualification) at the Royal Childrens Hospital campus in Parkville, Victoria, Australia. The same workshop presentation and script will be used for each workshop that is delivered. The Australian Dietary Guidelines provide the framework for the intervention, plus the inclusion of prebiotic and probiotic foods. Participants will be provided with NHMRC Healthy Eating During Pregnancy flyers, the My pregnancy plate guide (developed by dieticians at Oregon Health and Science University), along with a list of prebiotic and probiotic foods developed for this study. The workshop adopts behaviour change techniques for participants to set their own dietary goals within the context of the material presented, and to assist with adherence to their personal dietary goals. To support participants with their individual dietary goals, each participant will receive two 15-minute (max) follow-up support phone calls occurring 1 and 2 months prior to birth. These calls will follow a support phone call script that was written by the nutritionist, which is centred around goals, barriers and enablers for healthy eating. Members of our study team receive training to make these calls use the same script. Intervention adherence will be monitored through a register of attendance at the session, and via the support phone calls. Dietary adherence will be measured through dietary questionnaires that are collected at different time points; first one is collected before the intervention (3 months before birth), then followup data collection takes place after the workshop 1 and 2 months before birth and 1 month after birth (follow-up). 
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants allocated to the comparison group will continue receiving treatment as usual from their current healthcare provider (obstetrician, doctor, midwife). At the end of the study once recruitment has closed and the last participant has completed their final follow-up home visit, the control group participants will receive the same information that the intervention group received in written form. Depending on when participants were recruited over the 9 month recruitment period, there may be a wait time of between 0 and 9 months.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Markers of gut health measured using stool samples:
Fecal microbial diversity (Shannon index);
fecal microbiota organisational taxonomic units;
fecal short chain fatty acid concentrations (microbiota metabolites) </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline: 
   Women: beginning of third trimester (3 months before expected due date)
Follow-up: 
   Infants at 4-weeks of age
   Mothers at 4-weeks post birth</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Between group differences in biomarkers of inflammation:
Women; 
  -  IL-6, IL1-beta, TNF-a, C-reactive protein (CRP) assessed by saliva assay
Infant: 
  - inflammatory panel assessed by a Proseek inflammatory panel using infant Guthrie spot (dry blood spot)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline: 
   Women: beginning of third trimester (3 months before expected due date)
Follow-up: 
   Infants: 4-weeks of age
   Mothers: 4-weeks post birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intervention efficacy in improving diet:
   - Between group differences in dietary intake will be determined comparing longterm dietary intake at baseline and follow-up. This will be measured through validated food frequency questionnaire (cancer council dietary questionnaire for epidemiological studies)
 
 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline measure: 
   Women: beginning of third trimester (3 months before expected due date)
Followup measure: 
   Women: 4-weeks after birth
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Intervention efficacy and feasibility
  - Trends in dietary intake over the 4 time points listed below using a separate simple dietary questionnaire (which has not been validated) representing dietary intake over the previous fortnight. This will also include analysis of the participant's level of participation (as measured by study records, attendance etc), and their motivation and readiness to improve their diet as measured by a questionnaire specifically designed for this study </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline measure: 
   Women: beginning of third trimester (3 months before expected due date)
Month 1 measure: 
   Women: 2-months before expected due date
Month 2 measure: 
   Women: 1-months before expected due date
Followup measure: 
   Women: 4-weeks after birth
</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Epigenetic markers will be assessed through buccal cell assays 
Between group differences in:
   - methylation of folate-sensitive gene ZFP57, (this is a protein coding gene, associated with diabetes mellitus);
  - methylation of glucocorticoid receptor gene (NR3C1), (this is associated with stress-related disorders);
  - methylation of acid receptor FFAR2/3, (this is a protein coding gene activated by short chain fatty acids, which are metabolites produced from fermentation of dietary fibre. FFAR2/3 is  assocated with glucose metabolism and immunity);
  - genome-wide methylation for differences in global methylation</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline: 
   Women: beginning of third trimester (3 months before expected due date)
Follow-up: 
   Infants: 4-weeks of age
   Mothers: 4-weeks post birth</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Participants will be included if they do not meet any of the exclusion criteria AND are: 
1.	Approaching week 26 of their pregnancy (third trimester) at the time of enrolment
2.	Available to attend a Saturday morning workshop on offer as close to the beginning of week 26 of their pregnancy as possible 

</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Under 18
2. No autonomy over own diet
3. Participant is uncomfortable communicating in English
4. Current diagnosis of a mental disorder (including: Major depression, Dysthymia, Anxiety disorder (generalised, social phobia, post traumatic stress disorder, Obsessive compulsive, Panic disorder), Eating disorder (Anorexia, Bulimia, Binge eating disorder), Psychotic disorder (Schizophrenia), Substance use disorder, Aspergers, Autism disorder, ADHD, ADD)
5. Obesity, pre-pregnancy body mass index of 30 or above
6. Diabetes Mellitus (type 1, 2 or gestational diabetes)
7. Diagnosis of bowel disorder (inflammatory bowel disease (Crohns disease, ulcerative colitis) or irritable bowel syndrome)
8. Medically advised to follow on an exclusion/ restriction diet (e.g. low FODMAP)
9. Current antibiotic, prebiotic or probiotic supplement use (in the past month)
10. Regular illicit drug use


</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Randomisation will be used with a 1:1 group allocation ratio with randomly permuted block sizes to ensure allocation to treatment concealment.</concealment>
    <sequence>A statistician not directly involved in the analysis of the study results will prepare the randomisation schedule using block randomisation to maintain balance between treatment arms. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome is based upon differences between the treatment and control groups for faecal microbial composition of mothers and their babies. The primary outcome will be measured by the Shannon index, a measure of bacterial diversity which is based on the number of bacterial taxa with 97% similarity present, and their abundance. It is expected that maternal microbiota will readily respond to the diet given the evidence from recent dietary experiments, it is expected that it will be more difficult to detect differences in infant microbiota. Therefore, the sample size is geared to detect changes in infant microbiota. Recruitment of 90 mothers will allow for 80% power to detect of a one directional difference in Shannon index of at least 0.224 or a two-way difference of 0.254, which is comparable to differences in microbial diversity at 4-weeks of age reported in other studies. The sample size includes a tolerance of 10% lost to followup.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/07/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>18/04/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Women's Hospital - Parkville</hospital>
    <postcode>3000 - Melbourne</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Deakin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Deakin University, School of Medicine, IMPACT SRC
PO Box 281
Geelong, VIC, 3220
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Deakin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>A/Prof Felice N Jacka
Deakin University, School of Medicine, IMPACT SRC
PO Box 281
Geelong, VIC, 3220
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Murdoch Children's Research Institute</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>MCRI, Royal Childrens Hospital
50 Flemington Road, 
Parkville, Vic, 3052
Australia</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Theres still so much we dont know about how diet might affect the health of pregnant women and their babies. A healthy diet during pregnancy is recommended for good health, but many women find it difficult to eat healthily during pregnancy. Weve developed an educational dietary program and would like to see how it compares to the support and dietary advice that women receive from their healthcare providers during pregnancy in influencing various health endpoints. 
This study is recruiting women in their second trimester (14 - 25 weeks) of pregnancy, so that they can participate in the study from the beginning of their third trimester (week 26), through to 4 weeks after their babies are born.

What will the research achieve?
The study will evaluate whether the program is helpful in supporting pregnant women to eat healthily during their pregnancy, and whether the procedures are practical and feasible. It also assesses the possible effect of the dietary program on certain biological aspects of health in pregnant women and their babies. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite>https://www.mcri.edu.au/research/projects/healthy-parents-healthy-kids-study</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Childrens Hosptial HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>50 Flemington Road 
Parkville, VIC, 3052
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>16/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>35200A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>7/09/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>221 Burwood Highway 
Burwood, VIC, 3125 
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/06/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2016-036</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>1/02/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Felice Jacka</name>
      <address>Deakin University, School of Medicine
IMPACT SRC, PO Box 281
Geelong, VIC, 3220
</address>
      <phone>+61 422194218</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.jacka@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Samantha Dawson</name>
      <address>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
50 Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9936 6291</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>samantha.dawson@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Felice N Jacka</name>
      <address>Deakin University, School of Medicine
IMPACT SRC, PO Box 281
Geelong, VIC, 3220
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61422194218</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.jacka@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Samantha Dawson</name>
      <address>Murdoch Childrens Research Institute
50 Flemington Road
Parkville VIC 3052
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9936 6291</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>samantha.dawson@mcri.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>