<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364308">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>28/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000607774</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The impact of point-of-care testing on cardiovascular risk assessment completion in primary care practice-EPOCH</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The impact of point-of-care testing on cardiovascular risk assessment completion in primary care practice-a prospective, cluster randomised trial of 20 GP practices in NZ.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>EPOCH-Evaluating a Point-Of-Care device in Heart Healthcare</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>N/A</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiovascular Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Point of care testing</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention study.  10 GP practices using the cobas b101 POC device to test HbA1c and Cholesterol levels in eligible patients in order to complete CVD risk assessment records. A GP or practice nurse at each center will administer the test using standard diagnostic cartridges and a  blood sample obtained by pin prick. The number of completed and non-completed cardiovascular risk profiles of primary health patients achieved using point of care testing over a 12 month period will be compared between the two groups.</interventions>
    <comparator>10 GP practices using standard  traditional lab-based tests results for HbA1c and Cholesterol, collected prospectively over the 12 month period will be used to complete the CVD risk assessments. The number of completed and non-completed cardiovascular risk profiles of primary health patients achieved using traditional lab -based test results, over a 12 month period will be compared to the POC testing and CVD risk assessments.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of Completed CVD risk assessments obtained from the anonymised GP medical records in both groups using the Predict software programme for collecting cardiovascular risk assessments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incomplete "parked" CVD risk assessments  obtained from the anonymised GP medical records in both groups using the Predict software programme for collecting cardiovascular risk assessments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Average time to complete CVD risk assessment  obtained from the anonymised GP medical records in both groups using the Predict software programme for collecting cardiovascular risk assessments.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost analysis of POC device use versus Lab based results for completing CVD risk assessments using cost information provided by PHO's and local laboratories.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Over 12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Male or female are aged at least 35 years and less than 80 years old, and meet New Zealand national age, gender and ethnicity guideline criteria for CVD risk assessment and repeat assessment 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>80</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-	are under 35 years old 
-	are 80 years old or older
-	are not eligible for CVD risk assessment
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>20 GP practices will be randomly allocated to the standard practice of lab-based HbA1c and cholesterol testing or using the POC cobas b 101 machine situated in the practice, to obtain HbA1c and Cholesterol test results. Eligible participants identified at each GP practice will be made aware of the method of obtaining the results in order to complete an nationally required CVD risk assessment.  GP practices will be allocated two one of the two groups via phoning the study statistician who will hold the allocation schedule at the administration site.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participating practices will be randomised by the study statistician into one of two groups. Randomisation using dynamic adaptive methods will be stratified by practice size (number of GPs) and the rurality of the location (urban or rural).</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The primary outcome is whether the eligible patients have had a completed CVD risk assessment during a one-year study period.  We assume a primary event rate of 70% in the laboratory group and a 10-15% increase to 85% in the POC group. This figure is based on a study set in community pharmacies where POC testing for cholesterol risk management led to a 10% increase a 5% two-sided level of significant test and study power of 90%, we estimate a minimum sample size of 1000 patients is needed</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/05/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/06/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>1000</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>13638</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Northland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Roche Diagnostics International Ltd

</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Roche Diagnostics International Ltd
Forrenstrasse 2
6343 Rotkreuz
Switzerland
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Switzerland</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>To measure the impact of point of care testing for lipids (TC/HDL) and diabetes (HbA1c) on the frequency of completed cardiovascular disease (CVD) risk assessments in the eligible population in primary care practices in Northland region, New Zealand</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Manuscript in draft only so not applicable at this time</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committees</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
1 the Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>24/06/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>13/NTB/79/AM02</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>3/06/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Susan Wells</name>
      <address>Epidemiology and Biostatistics
School of Population Health
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142, New Zealand



</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 2463</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 373 1710</fax>
      <email>s.wells@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sue Wells</name>
      <address>Epidemiology and Biostatistics School of Population Health University of Auckland Private Bag 92019 Auckland 1142, New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 2463</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 373 1710</fax>
      <email>s.wells@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sue Wells</name>
      <address>Epidemiology and Biostatistics School of Population Health University of Auckland Private Bag 92019 Auckland 1142, New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 2463</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 373 1710</fax>
      <email>s.wells@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Kate Hudson</name>
      <address>National Institute for Health Innovation
University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142, New Zealand
</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 4782</phone>
      <fax>+64 9 373 1710</fax>
      <email>regtrials@nihi.auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>