<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83172">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/09/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/09/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000464369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Training unsupported sitting in people with spinal cord injuries: a randomized controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Skill-based training of unsupported sitting in people with spinal cord injuries</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Spinal cord injury (SCI)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other neurological disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Subjects in the experimental group will receive an intensive training program specifically directed at improving their ability to sit unsupported. The training will be based on the principles of motor learning and administered three times a week for 30 minutes over a six-week period.</interventions>
    <comparator>Subjects in the control group will continue to receive usual care but will not receive more than three 5-minute sessions a week of therapy directed at improving their ability to sit unsupported. Usual care will include standard physiotherapy and occupational therapy as provided as part of inpatient rehabilitation in Sydney spinal injury units.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximal forward lean (cm) from a seated upright position.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post (1 day after last treatment)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maximal sideward reach (mm) from a seated upright position.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post (1 day after last treatment)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Canadian Outcome Performance Measure (performance outcome). This is a standardised assessment in which subjects rate self-selected goals with respect to their current ability to perform the goal. An 11-point visual analogue scale will be used where zero reflects a negative perception about their ability to perform the goal and ten reflects a positive perception. The change score from pre to post of each goal will be calculated.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post (1 day after last treatment)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceptions of change by subjects.
At the end of the trial all subjects will be required to rate the change in their ability to sit unsupported from the beginning of the trial to the end of the trial using the Clinical Global Impression of Change scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post (1 day after last treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Canadian Outcome Performance Measure (satisfaction outcome).
This assesses subjects perceptions about treatment effectiveness.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post (1 day after last treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceptions of change by therapists based on video footage. Blinded therapists will be required to view pre and post video footage and rate change using the Clinical Global Impression of Change Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post (1 day after last treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>T-shirt test (sec).
This test assesses subjects' ability to perform a functional task while sitting unsupported (i.e., put on a T-shirt).</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post (1 day after last treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>SCI Specific Falls Efficacy Scale
This is a 16-point scale which has been adopted from a similar scale for able-bodied individuals.</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre and post (1 day after last treatment)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1.	have sustained a spinal cord injury within the preceding 6 months
2.	have a complete or an incomplete spinal cord below the first thoracic level (as per the International Standards for the Neurological Assessment of people wiht SCI)
3.	attain a score of 5 or less on the sitting balance item of the COVS (i.e., have some potential to improve)
4.	are able to put a T-shirt either in short or long sitting (i.e., are likely to respond to the training)
5.	are receiving physiotherapy and occupational therapy as part of a comprehensive in-patient rehabilitation program</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1.	have a pressure area preventing them from getting out of bed
2.	are unlikely to remain in the spinal unit for sixweeks
3.	are unlikely to co-operate</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>All consecutive patients admitted to the Spinal Unit will be screened and invited to participate in the study. Participants will be randomly allocated to either an experimental or control group using the principles of concealed allocation.
An independent person will use a computer to generate a random number sequence. These will be placed in sealed opaque envelopes and kept off-site by a person no otherwise involved in the study.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer to generate a random number sequence.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>18/09/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/09/2008</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>26/10/2010</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>32</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>32</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Rehabilitation Hospital - Coorabel/Moorong - Ryde</hospital>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Bangladesh</country>
      <state>Dhaka</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Rehabilitation Studies Unit, Northen Clinical School, Faculty of Medicine, University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 6, Ryde, NSW, 1680</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Rehabilitation Centre Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 6, Ryde, NSW, 1680</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Rehabilitation Centre Sydney</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>PO Box 6, Ryde, NSW, 1680</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Spinal Unit, Prince of Wales Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>High St, Randwick, NSW, 2031</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Centre for Rehabilitation of the Paralysed</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>PO CRP-Chapain
Savar
Dhaka 1343
Bangladesh</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Bangladesh</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this single blind randomized controlled trial is to determine the effectiveness of an intensive training program directed at improving the ability of people with spinal cord injury to sit unsupported. Subjects from Sydney's two spinal injury units will be randomly allocated to an experimental or control condition. Experimental subjects will receive an intensive training program specifically directed at improving their ability to sit unsupported. Control subjects will receive usual care. Subjects ability to sit unsupported will be assessed by a blinded therapist at the beginning and end of the study with a standardized battery of tests. In addition, subjects and therapists impressions about the effectiveness of therapy will be assessed using rating scales designed for this purpose.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Harvey LA, Ristev D, Hossain MS, Hossain MA, Bowden JL, Boswell-Ruys CL, Hossain MM and Ben M. (2011) Training unsupported sitting does not improve ability to sit in people with recently-acquired paraplegia: a randomised controlled trial. Journal of Physiotherapy, 57, 83-90.

Hossain MS, Harvey LA, Ristev D, Bowden J, Hossain MM (2011) Training unsupported sitting in people with recently-acquired paraplegia: a randomized controlled trial. International Conference on Spinal Cord Medicine and Rehabilitation, Washington, USA.

Ben M, Harvey LA, Ristev D, Hossain MS, Hossain MA, Bowden JL, Boswell-Ruys CL, Hossain MM (2011). Training unsupported in people with recently acquired paraplegia: a randomized controlled trial. Australia and New Zealand Spinal Cord Society (ANZCoS), Brisbane, Australia.  

Hossain MS, Hossain MA Hossain MM, Momen KM, Ristev D, Bowden J and Harvey L (2011) Training unsupported sitting in people with recently-acquired paraplegia: a randomized controlled trial. ASCoN, Colombo, Sri Lanka.
</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Rehabilitation Centre Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>PO Box 6, Ryde, NSW, 1680</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/12/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>07/02</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lisa Harvey</name>
      <address>John Walsh Centre for Rehabilitation Research 
The University of Sydney, Kolling Institute 
Royal North Shore Hospital 
St Leonards, NSW, 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 4594 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 99264045</fax>
      <email>l.harvey@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lisa Harvey</name>
      <address>John Walsh Centre for Rehabilitation Research 
The University of Sydney, Kolling Institute 
Royal North Shore Hospital 
St Leonards, NSW, 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 4594 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9926 4045</fax>
      <email>l.harvey@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lisa Harvey</name>
      <address>John Walsh Centre for Rehabilitation Research 
The University of Sydney, Kolling Institute 
Royal North Shore Hospital 
St Leonards, NSW, 2065</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 4594 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 99264045</fax>
      <email>l.harvey@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Lisa Harvey</name>
      <address>John Walsh Centre for Rehabilitation Research 
The University of Sydney, Kolling Institute 
Royal North Shore Hospital 
St Leonards, NSW, 2065
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9926 4594 </phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9926 4045</fax>
      <email>l.harvey@usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>