<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362664">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>20/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>21/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000667819</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Treatment of Food Cravings: A Comparison of Emotional Freedom Techniques, Cognitive Behavioural Therapy and a Control Group</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In overweight and obese adults with severe food cravings, do Emotional Freedom Techniques or Cognitive Behavioural Therapy techniques result in more decreased food cravings?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1131-3568</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Food Cravings</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>overweight/obesity</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Eating disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>1. Emotional Freedom Techniques (EFT) - meridian-based procedure which combines cognitive strategies with somatic procedures adapted from acupuncture and related systems for altering the cognitive, behavioural, and neurochemical foundations of psychological problems. It is often referred to as psychological acupuncture and aims to incorporate this principle of acupuncture into psychotherapeutic settings. The premise behind Thought Field Therapy (TFT) and EFT suggests that negative emotions in the body are caused by a disturbance in the bodys energy field (or meridian system). The action of stimulating acupressure points on the body (through a tapping process) while focusing the mind on the negative emotion is thought to restore the balance in the body (Craig, 2008).  This act then eliminates negative emotions.  Feinstein (2008) has proposed the arousal of the amygdala and other brain structures in the stress response are desensitised using EFT, where other theories highlight connective tissue transmission of piezoelectric signals (Oschman, 2006), neurotransmitter ratio alterations (dopamine and serotonin, Feinstein et al., 2005), and increased HPA axis regulation and a reduction of the stress hormone cortisol (Church, 2008).
The EFT Intervention group will receive 8 x 2 hour sessions, which will be held over 8 weeks. Treatment will be delivered in groups of 15 participants and will be demonstrated by a qualified therapist, who will instruct participants to self administer the technique.</interventions>
    <comparator>Cognitive Behavioural Therapy - an action-oriented form of psychosocial therapy that assumes that maladaptive, or faulty, thinking patterns cause maladaptive behavior and "negative" emotions. (Maladaptive behavior is behavior that is counter-productive or interferes with everyday living.) The treatment focuses on changing an individual's thoughts (cognitive patterns) in order to change his or her behavior and emotional state.
The CBT intervention will receive 8 x 2 hour sessions, held over 8 weeks. Treatment will be delivered by a qualified psychologist in groups of 15 participants.

Control Waitlist - will wait for duration of treatment, then receive the most effective treatment after the 8-week treatment period.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decrease in food craving severity - measured through validated self report questionnaires (to assess frequency and severity). Questionnaire uses a likert scale of responses and is the Food Craving Inventory.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment, post treatment (8 weeks), 6-month followup, 12-month followup</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increase in power over food cravings -  measured through validated self report questionnaires (to assess frequency and severity). Questionnaire uses a likert scale of responses and is the Power of Food Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment, post treatment (8 weeks), 6-month followup, 12-month followup</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increase in restraint over food cravings -  measured through validated self report questionnaires (to assess frequency and severity). Questionnaire use a likert scale of responses and is the Revised Restraint Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment, post treatment (8 weeks), 6-month followup, 12-month followup</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decrease in body mass index</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment, post treatment (8 weeks), 6-month followup, 12-month followup</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Improvement in related constructs (e.g. anxiety and somatoform concerns) -  measured through validated self report questionnaires (to assess frequency and severity). Questionnaire use a likert scale of responses and is the Patient Health Questionnaire.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre treatment, post treatment (8 weeks), 6-month followup, 12-month followup</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Both genders, must be overweight (i.e. Body Mass Index; BMI; between 25-29) or obese (BMI greater than 30), between18 years old and 100 years, not suffering any severe psychological impairment, not currently receiving treatment (psychological or medical) for their food cravings</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants who are pregnant, and known sufferers of diabetes (Type I and II) and hypoglycemia which can impact cravings will be excluded; sufferers of Anorexia Nervosa not suitable</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited through local community announcements in print advertisements, radio, and television by the chief investigator (CI). The CI will be responsible for explaining the research purpose and process. A standard process will be used for informed consent, including a general information sheet for subjects and consent form indicating any areas of psychological risk, benefits of the study, self report questionnaire details and follow-up procedures.  After screening people who respond to call for participants (to determine eligibility), 120 will be randomly assigned to either an 8-week group EFT treatment condition, a comparison 8-week group CBT condition or a waitlist control group. Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomization table created by a computer software (i.e. computerised sequence generation)</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/05/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/05/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>19/08/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>150</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bond University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Robina Gold Coast Queensland Australia 4229</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Association of Comprehensive Energy Psychology</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>233 East Lancaster Ave, Suite 104
Ardmore, PA 19003</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Food cravings frequently lead to consumption of the craved food (Hill &amp; Heaton-Brown, 1994), are positively correlated with BMI (Delahanty, Meigs, Hayden, Williamson, &amp; Nathan, 2002; Franken &amp; Muris, 2005) and obese adults report preferences for high fat foods (Drewnowski et al., 1985), therefore addressing these cravings in treatment is paramount. This study will examine treatment of food cravings in overweight or obese adults. Food craving is hypothesised to be an important intervening causal variable in the development of obesity.  Research examining meridian-based procedures (e.g. Emotional Freedom Techniques, EFT) for food cravings has recently found significant improvements occurred in weight, body mass index, food cravings, subjective power of food, craving restraint and psychological coping for participants from pre- to 12-months after a 4-week treatment (p&lt;0.05). This randomised clinical trial intends to extend this work and compare EFT treatment for food cravings, with a gold standard treatment strategy, Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT), in addition to a control group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Stapleton, PB, Sheldon, T., &amp; Porter, B. (2012).  Clinical Benefits of Emotional Freedom Techniques on Food Cravings at 12-months follow-up: A randomised controlled trial. Energy Psychology: Theory, Research, and Treatment, in press

Stapleton, P.B., Sheldon, T., Porter, B., &amp; Whitty, J. 75% (2011). A Randomised Clinical Trial of a Meridian-Based Intervention for Food Cravings with Six Month Follow-up. Behaviour Change, 28 (1), 1-16.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bond University Research Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Bond University, Robina, Gold Coast Queensland 4229</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RO1465</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/02/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peta Stapleton</name>
      <address>Faculty of Humanities and Social Sciences
Bond University
Robina Gold Coast QLD 4229</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5595 2515</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 5595 2540</fax>
      <email>pstaplet@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peta Stapleton</name>
      <address>Faculty of Humanities and Social Sciences
Bond University
Robina Gold Coast QLD 4229</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5595 2515</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 5595 2540</fax>
      <email>pstaplet@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Peta Stapleton</name>
      <address>Faculty of Humanities and Social Sciences
Bond University
Robina Gold Coast QLD 4229</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5595 2515</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 5595 2540</fax>
      <email>pstaplet@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Peta Stapleton</name>
      <address>School Psychology, Bond University, University Dr, Robina QLD 4229</address>
      <phone>+61 7 5595 2515</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>pstaplet@bond.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>