<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371684">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>19/10/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001473459</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>An additional Saturday allied health service for Geriatric Evaluation and Management to reduce patient length of stay and increase functional independence</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>An additional Saturday allied health service for Geriatric Evaluation and Management to reduce patient length of stay and increase functional independence</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Geriatric Evaluation and Management</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>An allied health service for Geriatric Evaluation and Management will be provided on Saturdays in addition to the usual Monday to Friday service for a period of 6 months in the intervention Geriatric and Evaluation Management ward. The additional allied health service will be provided at levels that approximate Monday to Friday service levels for: occupational therapy, physiotherapy, social work, and allied health assistants. In addition on Saturdays speech pathology, psychology and dietetics in the intervention ward will be available to provide an on-call service. The additional allied health services on a Saturday will provide additional therapy for patients admitted the intervention ward for Geriatric Evaluation and Management. There are no minimal years of experience requirements for allied health clinicians providing the Saturday service but will be expected to have experience working in Geriatric Evaluation and Management. Occasions of service provided by the allied health clinicians will be monitored using the health service data base each month.</interventions>
    <comparator>The primary control treatment is Monday to Friday allied health services (occupational therapy, physiotherapy, social work, allied health assistants plus part-time speech pathology, psychology and dietetics provided in a second Geriatric Evaluation and Management ward at Eastern Health in the same 6 month period. Allied health services are not available on this ward to Geriatric and Evaluation management patients during the weekend. Occasions of service provided by the allied health clinicians will be monitored using the health service data base each month.

The secondary control period will include routinely collected data from the two participating wards during  the same 6 month period in the previous year (historical control) during which allied health services were offered from Monday to Friday only.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of stay in Geriatric Evaluation and Management</outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge from Geriatric Evaluation and Management</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functional Independence Measure (FIM) expressed as difference between discharge and admission, and FIM efficiency (change in FIM per day)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge from Geriatric Evaluation and Management</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incremental cost effectiveness ratio incorporating the FIM score</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post discharge from Geriatric Evaluation and Management</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Discharge destination categorised as a) home fully independent, b) home informal support, c) home professional support, d) residential care, e) transition care program, e) other</outcome>
      <timepoint>Discharge from Geriatric Evaluation and Management</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Readmission to Eastern Health hospital in the first 30 days after discharge describing length of stay and reason for readmission</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days post discharge from Geraitric Evaluation and Management</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All patients admitted for Geriatric Evaluation and Management in the two participating wards during the data collection phase</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Patients not admitted under Geriatric Evaluation and Management (e.g. for Transition Care Program).
2. Patients admitted prior to the data collection phase will be excluded. 
3. Patients readmitted to Geriatric Evaluation and Management after a previous Geriatric Evaluation and Management admission during the data collection phase will be considered to have been admitted during the initial admission. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based on average length of stay for the 2 participant wards (ward 1 = 25.8 days and ward 2 = 27.6 days) the total sample will be approximately 900 patients, approximately n = 436 in the pre-intervention and approximately n = 460 in the post-intervention phase. Based on an assumption that a 3-day reduction in length of stay (with a SD of 12 days) in the intervention ward will be clinically and economically significant, the sample will provide approximately 75% power at a 5% alpha level using 2-tailed tests.
Length of stay and functional independence will be compared using 2-way analysis of variance with the 2 independent factors of site (intervention versus control) and time (pre-intervention versus post-intervention). Significant interaction effects will be explored with simple main effects. Comparisons involving post-intervention data only will be analysed using either independent t tests or the Mann-Whitney U test as appropriate. Categorical outcomes will be compared using chi-square statistics. Sensitivity analyses will be completed excluding patients who have completed active treatment and waiting for placement. An interim analysis on length of stay data in the intervention ward will be conducted after 3 months. 
As part of the health economic analysis from a health service perspective, mean cost difference will be determined between the two groups using an independent t-test to report statistical significance. Incremental cost effectiveness ratios (ICERs) will be determined on the functional independence score and the mean difference between groups for cost. Confidence intervals around the individual ICERs for the functional independence score will be calculated using the bootstrap method. The ICERs will also be reported with confidence ellipses to represent a two-dimensional measure of variance, taking into account the variance of the cost and functional independence scores. In addition, the ICER will be reported as a cost effectiveness acceptability curve with a willingness to pay for the probability of achieving cost effectiveness.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>14/11/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>12/12/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>19/05/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>28/05/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>900</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>793</actualsamplesize>
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>18/06/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>10/06/2017</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Wantirna Health - Wantirna</hospital>
    <hospital>Box Hill Hospital - Box Hill</hospital>
    <postcode>3152 - Wantirna</postcode>
    <postcode>3128 - Box Hill</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eastern Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>5 Arnold Street, Box Hill, Victoria 3128</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Eastern Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>5 Arnold Street, Box Hill, Victoria 3128</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Geriatric Evaluation and Management (GEM), sometimes called slow stream rehabilitation,  manages patients with complex conditions associated with ageing, cognitive dysfunction, chronic illness and disability. A multidisciplinary team provides care that helps the person to return home with optimal levels of health. There is strong evidence that Geriatric Evaluation and Management works but hospital length of stay is long and the service is typically only provided from Monday to Friday. Providing Saturday allied health services in other areas of rehabilitation reduces length of stay. Using routinely collected patient data, this project will find out if the introduction by the health service of a Saturday multidisciplinary allied health service in Geriatric Evaluation and Management is a cost effective way of reducing length of stay and improving health outcomes.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Eastern Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>5 Arnold Street, Box Hill, Victoria, 3128</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>LR83/2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>16/09/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Taylor</name>
      <address>level 2/5 Arnold Street Box Hill, Victoria 3128
Eastern Health - La Trobe University</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90918874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Taylor@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Taylor</name>
      <address>level 2/5 Arnold Street Box Hill, Victoria 3128
Eastern Health - La Trobe University</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90918874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Taylor@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Taylor</name>
      <address>level 2/5 Arnold Street Box Hill, Victoria 3128
Eastern Health - La Trobe University</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90918874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Taylor@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Nicholas Taylor</name>
      <address>level 2/5 Arnold Street Box Hill, Victoria 3128
Eastern Health - La Trobe University</address>
      <phone>+61 3 90918874</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>N.Taylor@latrobe.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>