<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372393">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>30/03/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/04/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000503325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing models of physiotherapy service delivery in Parkinson's disease: A feasibility study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised trial of the feasibility of two different models of physiotherapy service delivery for people with Parkinson's disease; predominantly group-based and predominantly home-based .
</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Parkinson's disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Parkinson's disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>All participants will complete a predominantly group-based physiotherapy exercise program conducted in conjunction with an exercise self-management program for the first 5 weeks of the intervention. Participants will perform physiotherapy exercises three times per week, with two group sessions (1 hour per session) and one home-based session (1 hour) each week. Exercises will be prescribed by a physiotherapist and will be based on each individual participants initial assessment results.

The group will have 5-8 participants per class, under the supervision of a physiotherapist and two physiotherapy students. The exercise program will consist of task-specific training of activities while targeting key motor impairments  in PD (hypokinesia, bradykinesia, freezing of gait and postural instability). Examples of exercises  include balance exercises (anticipatory and reactive), sit to stand, stepping and walking incorporating cueing and  dual-task training strategies.

Participants home-based physiotherapy exercise programs will be prescribed by a physiotherapist and remotely monitored using internet and app resources available at PhysioTherapy eXercises. The home-based physiotherapy exercise program will be similar to the group-based program with adjustments made for safety and availability of equipment.

Participants will complete one weekly 15 minute self-management session, designed to increase self-efficacy for exercise and to promote the development of exercise self-management skills. The self-management program will be facilitated by a physiotherapist and consist of the following topics;
Why is exercise important (education session provided by the physiotherapist).
Goal setting (participants discuss how they like to exercise and set  appropriate goals).
Identifying barriers to exercise (participants identify their barriers to exercises).
Solutions for barriers to exercise (participants provide solutions for each barrier identified).
Developing a plan to continue exercising (participants develop a five week plan to continue exercising).
Participants will be provided with worksheets to complete during the self-management sessions.

At the end of week 5, participants will be randomised to the predominantly home-based (PHB) or predominantly group-based (PGB) model. 

Predominantly home-based physiotherapy 
The PHB group will be prescribed, by a physiotherapist, a home-based physiotherapy exercise program to complete independently three times per week (1 hour per session) for 5 weeks (weeks 6  10).  This program will be based on the group-based physiotherapy exercise program with adjustments made for safety and availability of equipment. Examples of exercises include balance exercises (anticipatory and reactive), sit to stand, stepping and walking incorporating cueing and dual-task training strategies.

These participants will receive two, five minute, phone calls (week 7 and week 9) from a physiotherapist. The purpose of the phone calls is to review participants performance, assist with any difficulties and progress the home exercise program (if indicated). The participants adherence and adverse events will be remotely monitored using internet and app resources available at PhysioTherapy eXercises. However, if participants prefer not to use the internet-based technology, adherence and adverse events will be monitored using paper-based log books.
</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants randomised to the PGB group will complete the same exercise and exercise self-management sessions as the PHB group for the first five weeks of intervention. Participants randomised to this group will continue to attend two group exercise classes per week (1 hour per session) and to perform the third exercise session independently at home (1 hour) for the remaining 5 weeks (weeks 6  10).  

The group will have 5-8 participants per class, under the supervision of a physiotherapist and two physiotherapy students. The exercise program will consist of task-specific training of activities while targeting key motor impairments in PD (hypokinesia, bradykinesia, freezing of gait and postural instability). Examples of exercises include balance exercises (anticipatory and reactive), sit to stand, stepping and walking incorporating cueing and dual-task training strategies.

Participants home-based physiotherapy exercise programs will be prescribed by a physiotherapist and remotely monitored using internet and app resources available at PhysioTherapy eXercises. The home-based physiotherapy exercise program will be similar to the group-based program with adjustments made for safety and availability of equipment.

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of Recruitment, assessed by the evaluation of :
      Number of participants screened
      Number eligible for inclusion 
      Number who consent to participate

</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of study</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasibility of the Intervention, assessed by the evaluation of:
    Time taken to develop physiotherapy programs using PhysioTherpay eXercises.
    Adherence of participants to the program including:  number of sessions completed and   number of exercises completed per session
     Adverse events e.g number of falls and injuries sustained when performing exercises


</outcome>
      <timepoint>After completion of the 10 week intervention</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Balance assessed using the MiniBEST test</outcome>
      <timepoint>At base line and on completion of the 10 week intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking speed - 10m walk test</outcome>
      <timepoint>At base line and on completion of the 10 week intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Freezing of gait as assessed using the New Freezing of Gait Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>At base line and on completion of the 10 week intervention</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participants satisfaction with the delivery of the exercise program. This will be evaluated using a participant questionnaire specifically designed for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of week 5 and on completion of the 10 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Idiopathic Parkinson's disease
Living in the community (Canberra and surrounding regions)
Stable medications for at least 2 weeks prior to baseline assessment
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Mini Mental State Examination of less than 24.
A medical condition which will prevent participants from completing a physiotherapy exercise program three times a week.
Are currently attending the PD exercise classes at the University of Canberra
Have attended the PD exercise classes at the University of Canberra in the last 12 weeks.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>People with PD who attend the University of Canberra clinic and people with PD who are members of Parkinson’s ACT will be informed about the study and if interested will be given a copy of the participant information sheet. Those who wish to participate will be screened and if eligible they will provide written informed consent prior to participation. Once enrolled in the trial a baseline assessment will be completed.  After the baseline assessment all participants will complete a predominantly group-based program for the initial 5 weeks (two group sessions and one home-based session) in conjunction with an exercise self-management. During week 5 participants will be allocated randomly to either the PGB group or PHB group. Randomisation will be computer-generated. Random permuted blocks will be used so that both groups contain equal numbers. Randomisation will be centralized off-site, thereby concealing the sequence of group allocation from the researcher recruiting the participants </concealment>
    <sequence>A random number table will be generated using Excel</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Feasibility will be determined using descriptive statistics. 
The effectiveness of the intervention on walking speed and balance will be determined using analysis of co-variance, adjusted for baseline scores.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>17/04/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>23/05/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Allyson Flynn</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University of Canberra
Faculty of Health Clinics
Building 28, Level C
Cnr Ginninderra Drive and Allawoona St
Bruce ACT 2617</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Discipline of Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney
PO BOX 170 Lidcombe 
NSW1825
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Canberrra</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Faculty of Health Clinics
Building 28, Level C
Cnr Ginninderra Drive and Allawoona St
Bruce ACT 2617
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Colleen Canning</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Discipline of Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney
PO BOX 170 Lidcombe 
NSW1825
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Natalie Allen</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Discpline of Physiotherapy
Faculty of Health Sciences
The University of Sydney
PO BOX 170 Lidcombe 
NSW1825

</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Elisabeth Preston</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Physiotherapy
University of Canberra 
Locked Bag 1
ACT 2601`</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>There is growing evidence that physiotherapy and exercise can improve mobility and balance in people with Parkinson's disease (PD). However, there is limited research on the method of service delivery to provide optimally effective and efficient physiotherapy to people with PD. The primary aim of this pilot randomised controlled trial is to investigate the feasibility of a predominantly home-based physiotherapy program compared to a predominantly group-based program. The secondary aim is to determine the effect of the programs on balance and mobility in people with PD. In addition participants will also provide feedback on their satisfaction of exercising in group environment and at home.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Canberra Human Research Ethics Commitee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of Canberra
Locked Bag 1
ACT 2601
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/09/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>16-153</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Allyson Flynn</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Clinics
University of Canberra
Building 28, Level C
Cnr Ginninderra Drive and Allawoona St
BRUCE ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+ 61 2 6206 8850</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Allyson.Flynn@Canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Allyson Flynn</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Clinics
University of Canberra
Building 28, Level C
Cnr Ginninderra Drive and Allawoona St
BRUCE ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6206 8850</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Allyson.Flynn@Canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Allyson Flynn</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Clinics
University of Canberra
Building 28, Level C
Cnr Ginninderra Drive and Allawoona St
BRUCE ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6206 8850</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Allyson.Flynn@Canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Allyson Flynn</name>
      <address>Faculty of Health Clinics
University of Canberra
Building 28, Level C
Cnr Ginninderra Drive and Allawoona St
BRUCE ACT 2617</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6206 8850</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Allyson.Flynn@Canberra.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>