<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370049">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/04/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000540415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Safety of Manuka honey CycloPower ophthalmic cream</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of Manuka honey CycloPower ophthalmic micro-emulsion cream on ocular parameters in healthy participants compared with no treatment</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Blepharitis  </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention involves external application of Manuka honey CycloPower ophthalmic cream (0.5-1ml) to the skin of the upper and lower eyelids of one eye only (randomised to the right or left eye), once daily for 2 weeks.  The fellow (untreated) eye serves as the control.  Compliance is monitored through follow-up telephone calls and the weighing of returned unused cream.</interventions>
    <comparator>No treatment </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Skin hyperaemia as measured by VAS grading by the researcher
  </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7 and Day 14 after treatment commencement </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Dry eye signs as measured by keratography</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7 and Day 14 after treatment commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Male or female healthy subjects aged 18-45 and in good health as determined by past medical history, physical examination, vital signs at screening.
2. Subjects must be able to communicate well with the investigator, to understand and comply with the requirements of the study and understand and sign the written informed consent.
3. Be willing not to wear contact lenses for 2 days prior to the start of the study and for the duration of the study</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>45</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Known allergy to any components of the microemulsion (bee products or Manuka honey Cyclopower)
2. Pregnancy or planned pregnancy during the course of the study
3. A past medical history or evidence of significant dermatological conditions e.g. eczema, dermatitis
4. A past medical history or evidence of ophthalmic disease that could affect study outcomes
5. A past history or evidence of systemic disease that could affect the study outcomes
6. Dosing of a study drug in any clinical investigation within 30 days prior to initial treatment in this study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Treated eye and control eye allocation will be randomised and concealed from the investigator via opaque sealed envelopes given to the subjects.  </concealment>
    <sequence>A computer-generated randomisation schedule allocates the left/right eye to treatment/control  </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Other</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Paired eye study</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>8/12/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>24/04/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>25</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Auckland</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Auckland</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>85 Park Road, Grafton, Auckland, 1023</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Manuka Health New Zealand Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>34 Hannigan Dr, St Johns, Auckland 1072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Manuka Health New Zealand Ltd.</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>34 Hannigan Dr, St Johns, Auckland 1072</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Blepharitis, or inflammation of the eyelid, is a common, debilitating and chronic condition. This disease manifests clinically as either anterior blepharitis affecting the front portion of the eyelid and the eyelashes, or posterior blepharitis which involves the inner eyelid. Posterior blepharitis is usually caused by dysfunction of the lipid-producing meibomian glands in the eyelid and both types of blepharitis increase the susceptibility of the eyelids to over-colonisation by bacteria.

Existing treatments for eyelid disease are costly and ineffective, and no readily and commercially available ophthalmic product targets both the bacterial and inflammatory disease processes.  Both the anti-bacterial and anti-inflammatory effects of New Zealand native Manuka honey have been proven, and it has been shown in research conducted in collaboration with Medihoney Antibacterial Honey (Medihoney Pty Ltd., Australia) that a honey-based ophthalmic formation may have a therapeutic effect in blepharitis and meibomian gland dysfunction (MGD).  Therefore, there is a clear rationale for developing a novel ophthalmic product based on New Zealand native Manuka honey for reducing the bacterial load, and the level of inflammation in blepharitis and MGD. 

We identified the species of bacteria present on the eyelids of people affected by eyelid disease and demonstrated that Manuka Honey with CycloPower has an anti-bacterial effect on these specific microorganisms.  Subsequently, we developed a formulation of Manuka Honey with CycloPower suitable for use externally around the eye and the safety and lack of toxicity of this product was demonstrated first in a corneal epithelial cell line in vitro, and then in vivo in an animal study.  Thus, we hypothesise that the use of Manuka Honey with CycloPower may be safe and well tolerated in healthy human volunteers in this present trial. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>013084</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/09/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer P Craig</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142</address>
      <phone>+6499238173</phone>
      <fax>+6493677173</fax>
      <email>jp.craig@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer P Craig</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland
85 Park Rd, Grafton
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+6499238173</phone>
      <fax>+6493677173</fax>
      <email>jp.craig@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer P Craig</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland
85 Park Rd, Grafton
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+6499238173</phone>
      <fax>+6493677173</fax>
      <email>jp.craig@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Jennifer P Craig</name>
      <address>Department of Ophthalmology
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland
85 Park Rd, Grafton
Auckland 1142
</address>
      <phone>+6499238173</phone>
      <fax>+6493677173</fax>
      <email>jp.craig@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>