<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368793">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/07/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/11/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615001198516</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>General anesthesia for bronchial thermoplasty in patients with severe, persistent asthma - description of a protocol</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>General  anesthesia for bronchial thermoplasty in patients suffering  from severe, persistent asthma- impact on perioperative respiratory stability and operator comfort.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>General Anesthesia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Asthma</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Bronchial thermoplasty</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Asthma</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Bronchial thermoplasty consists of controlled delivery of radiofrequency electrical energy to the bronchial wall which heats up the tissue thus reducing the amount of smooth muscle present in the airway. The result is a diminished potential for bronchoconstriction and long-lasting improvement of asthma symptoms.
The treatment is divided into 3 sessions lasting approximately 1 hour, 3 weeks apart.  In our centre bronchial thermoplasty  is performed in the operating theatre by the pneumologist , with the patient   under general anaesthesia irrespective of enrolement  in this trial.
Patients are premedicated with 0.5 mg of Alprazolam orally one hour before the procedure. Non-invasive monitoring consisting of pulse oxymetry, ECG , blood pressure and  neuromuscular monitoring is placed and peripheral venous access is obtained on arrival in the operating room.
General anaesthesia is induced with Remifentanyl 0.5 micrograms /kg/min for 5 min then 0.15-0.25 micrograms/kg/min,  Lidocaine 1 mg/kg,  Propofol TCI( Marsh model)  for a target concentration above 2 micrograms/ml and Rocuronium 0.6 mg/kg.  A laryngeal mask airway(LMA  Ambu Registered Trademark AuraGain Trademark) is inserted under deep anaesthesia ,the gastric content is aspirated via the dedicated  port and pressure controlled mechanical ventilation is initiated. A radial artery catheter is placed and a blood gas analysis is performed before the beginning of the procedure and then every 15 min during the thermoplasty session. Adjuncts to the anaesthesia are used in order to minimise bronchospasm and/or oedema related to the airway instrumentation: Magnesium sulphate 2g iv in 30 min, Methylprednisolone  125 mg iv and Adrenaline 0.5 mg subcutaneously after the induction of general anaesthesia. Once the area to treat is identified by fiberoptic bronchoscopy the thermoplasty electrode is guided into place via the LMA and the procedure begins.
Curarisation is maintained by supplementary boluses of Rocuronium 0.15 mg/kg. Paracetamol iv 15 mg/kg, Tramadol 1 mg/kg and Alizapride 1 mg/kg are administered 30 min before the end of the procedure. 
Neuromuscular blockade is reversed with Sugammadex once the session is over ,Remifentanyl and Propofol infusions are stopped and the LMA is removed  once spontaneous breathing is restored. The patient is monitored in the Post Anaesthesia Care Unit(PACU) for two hours before discharge to the ward. Bronchodilator aerosols are administered to control bronchospasm if present and Piritramide is titrated to control pain. Blood gas samples are analysed on arrival and at the end of the PACU stay.
</interventions>
    <comparator>NIL</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Respiratory stability as assessed by  tidal volume, peak inspiratory pressure, peripheral capillary  oxygen saturation(SpO2),  fraction of inspired  oxygen(FiO2), partial pressure of oxygen in the arterial blood(PaO2), partial pressure of carbon dioxide in the arterial blood and end tidal carbon dioxide concentration(EtCO2)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and every 2 minutes intraoperatively for SpO2, FiO2, tidal volume, peak  inspiratory pressure and EtCO2. At baseline and every 15 minutes intraoperatively for PaO2 et PaCO2</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Operator satisfaction as assesed by the total duration of the thermoplasty session and the cumulated pause time needed for optimisation of patients respiratory status if  desaturation, cough or air leaks occur.</outcome>
      <timepoint>From start of thermoplasty session as defined by the first delivery of the radiofrequency current to the  first bronchus to treat to the end of the session defined by the last activation of the thermoplasty device.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hemodynamic stability as assessed by heart rate and  blood pressure measured invasively via a radial artery catheter.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline and every 2 minutes intraoperatively. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The need for bronchodilators as assessed by the total dose of Duovent and adrenaline aerosols</outcome>
      <timepoint>From arrival until 2 hours after arrival in the post anesthesia care unit.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thoracic pain as assessed by Visual Analogue Scale</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 5 minutes during the 2 hour stay in the Post Anesthesia Care Unit</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults suffering from severe persistent asthma scheduled for bronchial thermoplasty under general anesthesia</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Suspicion of pregnancy confirmed by beta HCG dosage</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Defined population</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>16/12/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>1/09/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>4</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>4</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>CHU Dinant-Godinne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Avenue Gaston Therasse 1
5530 Yvoir
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Belgium</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Bronchial thermoplasty is a new treatment modality for severe, persistent asthma that delivers thermal energy to the airway wall resulting in a prolonged reduction in airway smooth muscle mass. Its a procedure performed during bronchoscopy, usually under light sedation . General anesthesia and mechanical ventilation of the patient might improve the overall safety of the procedure. The aim of this study is to evaluate respiratory and hemodynamic stability of asthmatic patients who undergo bronchial thermoplasty under general anesthesia as well as operator and patient comfort.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>The first patient benefiting from bronchial thermoplasty in our hospital was scheduled for december 2014 and for safety reasons the procedure was performed under general anesthesia, with an anesthesia protocole adapted for asthmatic patients undergoing interventional bronchoscopy procedures. That protocole was submitted to the ethics commitee, but the approval came after the first patient was treated. However the protocole remained the same throughout the recruitment period and informed consent was obtained for all the patients.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comite d’Ethique Medicale du CHU Dinant-Godinne</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Avenue Gaston Therasse 1
5530 Yvoir</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Belgium</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vornicu Ovidiu Ionut</name>
      <address>Avenue Gaston Therasse 1
5530 Yvoir</address>
      <phone>+3281423947</phone>
      <fax>+3281423920</fax>
      <email>ovidiu.vornicu@uclouvain.be</email>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vornicu Ovidiu Ionut</name>
      <address>Avenue Gaston Therasse 1
5530 Yvoir</address>
      <phone>+3281423947</phone>
      <fax>+3281423920</fax>
      <email>ovidiu.vornicu@uclouvain.be</email>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Mayne Alain</name>
      <address>Avenue Gaston Therasse 1
5530 Yvoir</address>
      <phone>+3281423915</phone>
      <fax>+3281423920</fax>
      <email>alain.mayne@uclouvain.be</email>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vornicu Ovidiu Ionut</name>
      <address>Avenue Gaston Therasse 1
5530 Yvoir</address>
      <phone>+3281423947</phone>
      <fax>+3281423920</fax>
      <email>ovidiu.vornicu@uclouvain.be</email>
      <country>Belgium</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>