<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364551">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/07/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000776707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Very Early Rehabilitation in Speech in patients with aphasia following stroke.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A three armed, prospective multicentre randomised controlled speech therapy trial comparing usual care, usual care plus and Very Early Rehabilitation in Speech (VERSE) with blinded outcome assessment of the Aphasia Quotient score  in patients with aphasia following acute stroke. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111 - 1145 - 4130</utrn>
    <trialacronym>VERSE</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Aphasia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Speech therapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Arm Two Usual care Plus  -  Increased intensity of speech therapy sessions (uncontrolled) The therapy provided is at the discretion of the speech therapist based on usual care speech therapy provided in the stroke unit.  It involves a combination of non standardised aphasia therapy, counselling and patient/family education however the intensity or the number of treamtent sessions will be specified and equivalent to 20 sessions of 45 - 60 minutes. There will be a minimum of 3 and a maximum of 5 sessions per week. Intevention must be completed within a maximum 25 working days after baseline assessment.
Arm 3 VERSE intervention - Increased intensity of speech therapy sessions (prescribed) The number of sessions will be equal to arm 2 (20 sessions of 45 - 60 minutes of 1:1 speech therapy, but the intervention will be standardised and prescribed by an expert advisory committee for the therapist to follow. The intervention will be specifically tailored to meet specific set goals based on patients needs and include predominantly direct 1:1 therapy.
All sessions in all arms of treatment will be recorded. Documentation will include the date, duration and content of each session. A random sample of sessions will be recorded and submitted to the study monitor to ensure adherence to the protocol.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 1- Usual Care. The therapy provided is at the discretion of the speech therapist based on usual care speech therapy provided in the stroke unit.  It involves a combination of non standardised aphasia therapy, counselling and patient/family education. Audited results indicate that usual care consists of 14 minutes per week but therapists report 1- 3 sessions of 30 minutes a week. In this trial we anticipate that usual care speech therapy will be less than 6 hours in total during the trial intervention period. (up to 25 days)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Aphasia Quotient (AQ)score</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 weeks post stroke</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Aphasia Quotient (AQ) score</outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks post stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Discourse Analysis (Correct Information Units) </outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 26 weeks post stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety Depression Rating Score (ADRS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 26 weeks post stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stroke and Aphasia Quality of Life (SAQoL)</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 and 26 weeks post stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resource Utilisation Questionnaire </outcome>
      <timepoint>26 weeks post stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Acute stroke with resultant acute aphasia of any type and score &lt; 93.7 of the Aphasia Quotient (no TIA, SAH or SDH)
Medical stability at recruitment 
Ability to maintain a wakeful alert state for 30 consecutive minutes within 14 days of stroke onset 
Normal or corrected hearing and vision. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Pre existing aphasia
Patients who have suffered a head injury, have had or require neurosurgery,
Pre existing  or current clinical diagnosis of dementia or major depression
Concurrent progressive neurological disorders
Patients unable to participate in English based therapy due to English being a second language.
Concurrent participation in another interventional trial  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be assigned to group via a web based centralized automated allocation system. </concealment>
    <sequence>A computer-generated blocked and stratified randomisation procedure will allocate participants to one of three treatment arms. Participants will be stratified based on aphasia severity, determined by the Aphasia Quotient and the acute care hospital site. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Baseline patient characteristics will be described using means and standard deviations. One-way ANOVA or the Kruskal-Wallis test and chi-square tests will examine differences in characteristics between groups. Generalised estimating equations (GEE) will be used to analyse differences in communication outcomes. The GEE models will control for AQ and mRS at baseline. GEE is a sophisticated regression-type approach. It is preferred to naive methods due to its robustness against violations of normality and in handling missing data.  
Analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) will be used to analyse the differences between group quality of life. The ANCOVA model will control for baseline stroke and aphasia severity together with other identified baseline group differences. 
The cost-effectiveness (resource utilisation) will be determined  by the incremental cost per AQ improvement (e.g. net costs/AQ score gained is below the threshold of &lt; $50,000 or is cost saving). The cost per fewer occurrences of depression at twelve weeks post stroke will also be described. Probabilistic multivariable analysis will be used to account for variability in point estimates and reported as medians (95% uncertainty intervals) using @RISK software (Palisade Corporation) for these sensitivity and uncertainty analyses. The sample size estimation was performed using GPower 3.1 with power set at 80% and significance level at 0.05. A balanced repeated measures design was assumed. A conservative power analysis was performed to determine the sample size required to detect the smallest effect of VERSE compared to UC-plus. The results showed that a total sample size of 195 was required. Assuming a 20% attrition rate this would ultimately require the recruitment of 244 participants (81.3 per group). The trial will therefore recruit 82 patients per group requiring a total number of 246 participants.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>23/09/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>5/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>246</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW,QLD,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Joondalup Health Campus - Joondalup</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Melbourne Hospital - City campus - Parkville</hospital>
    <hospital>Cairns Base Hospital - Cairns</hospital>
    <hospital>St George Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital - Camperdown</hospital>
    <hospital>Fremantle Hospital and Health Service - Fremantle</hospital>
    <hospital>Albury Wodonga Health - Albury campus - Albury</hospital>
    <hospital>Gold Coast Hospital - Southport</hospital>
    <hospital>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital - Nedlands</hospital>
    <hospital>The Alfred - Prahran </hospital>
    <hospital>St Vincent's Hospital (Melbourne) Ltd - Fitzroy</hospital>
    <hospital>Concord Repatriation Hospital - Concord</hospital>
    <hospital>Prince of Wales Hospital - Randwick</hospital>
    <hospital>Royal North Shore Hospital - St Leonards</hospital>
    <postcode>6027 - Joondalup</postcode>
    <postcode>3050 - Royal Melbourne Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>4870 - Cairns</postcode>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
    <postcode>2050 - Camperdown</postcode>
    <postcode>6160 - Fremantle</postcode>
    <postcode>2640 - Albury</postcode>
    <postcode>3065 - Fitzroy</postcode>
    <postcode>3181 - Prahran</postcode>
    <postcode>6009 - Nedlands</postcode>
    <postcode>2139 - Concord Repatriation Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2065 - Royal North Shore Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>4215 - Southport</postcode>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Tauranga and Christchurch</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Edith Cowan University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>270 Joondalup Dr  Joondalup WA 6027
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Trial objectives 
To demonstrate that a standardised and prescribed speech therapy regimen for aphasia is more effective and cost saving than non-standardised usual care training methods in the very early post-stroke recovery period.
Primary Hypothesis
Compared to usual care, providing very early daily aphasia therapy (UC-plus and VERSE) will result in improved communication ability determined by at least a 20% greater score on the Aphasia Quotient (AQ) at twelve weeks post stroke. 

Secondary hypotheses are:
VERSE (standardised, daily very early) aphasia therapy will result in a 4.4% greater score on the Aphasia Quotient when compared to UC-plus (non-standardised daily
very early) aphasia therapy at twelve weeks post stroke 
(4% improvement on the AQ score represents a significant communication improvement).

Very early aphasia therapy (UC-plus and VERSE) will result in better quality of life at twelve weeks post stroke than Usual Care control.
 
Very early aphasia therapy (UC-plus and VERSE) will be more cost-effective than UC at twelve weeks post stroke. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Melbourne Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Grattan St Parkville Victoria 3050</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/05/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/07/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Erin Godecke</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Social Sciences 
Edith Cowan University
270 Joondalup Dve 
JOONDALUP WA  6027 </address>
      <phone> +61 8 6304 5901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.godecke@ecu.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Erin Godecke</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Social Sciences 
Edith Cowan University
270 Joondalup Dve 
JOONDALUP WA  6027 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 6304 5901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.godecke@ecu.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Erin Godecke</name>
      <address>School of Psychology and Social Sciences 
Edith Cowan University
270 Joondalup Dve 
JOONDALUP WA  6027 </address>
      <phone>+61 8 6304 5901</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.godecke@ecu.edu.au </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Fiona Ellery</name>
      <address>The Florey Institute of Neuroscience and Mental Health
245 Burgundy St
Heidelberg
Victoria 3084</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9035 7042</phone>
      <fax>+61 3 9496 2251</fax>
      <email>fellery@unimelb.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>