<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81955">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/04/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>13/04/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000206426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Community Care and Hospital Based collaborative Falls Prevention Project</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Hospital based falls prevention programs for the elderly combined with follow up community based falls prevention programs to enhance reduction of subsequent falls compared to hospital only intervention</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Falls in the elderly living in the community</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other injuries and accidents</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Community based falls prevention follow up of people discharged from a hospital emergency department following a fall and people discharged from a hospital out patient falls prevention clinic. 
The intervention group will receive up to 8 hours of support worker contact time over 2 to 4 weeks to review risk factors in the home, strategies to reduce risk factors, assistance to implement a falls action plan. This includes practical assistance e.g. visits to GP, Optometrist, Podiatrist, reinforcing awareness and reduction of risk factors.

All patients discharged from either the hospital Emergency Department or Falls Clinic have a standard Falls Action Plan to implement following the standard hospital falls intervention process. This can include a home exercise plan, organising an optometrist or podiatrist review, removing loose rugs or obtaining a non slip mat for the bathroom.

A face to face interview 4 weeks post discharge will review actions taken with the original falls action Plan of the intervention group and the control group.

At this time both groups will be provided with a falls callender to record informatin on falls. At three months all will have a phone reminder to regarding filling in the falls calendar and at 6 months a questionairre for both groups will measure qualitative and quantitative outcomes for both groups. The number of falls in the six month period from discharge to the initial 4 week post discharge will be ascertained at interview and from the initial interview at the end of a six month period of recording falls on the calendar.

Patients attending the hospital's emergency department (100) and Falls Clinic (100) who meet inclusion criteria and who consent to participate will be randomised into 
control group (no community follow up) and intervention group (post discharge community follow up)</interventions>
    <comparator>control group (no community follow up) </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increased implementation of actions to reduce risk factors.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured by comparing the Falls Action Plan developed during the hospital intervention at 4 weeks post discharge via a face to face interview and after a further 6 months via a final questionnaire.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decreased falls over a six month post intervention period. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured by a participant record on a Falls Calendar and reported admissions to hospital as a result of a fall during the six months.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The number of falls participants in the intervention and control groups will be compared as will implementation of a Falls Action Plan to reduce risk factors. The area a fall occurs such as bathroom or footpath will also be recorded.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The extent to which the Falls Action Plan is actioned will be measured during the interview at 4 weeks post discharge and at the 6 months post intervention questionnaire. This will also provide an indication of 'carry over' awareness and action on reducing falls post intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increased awareness of falls prevention and confidence falls are not inevitable and perception they can take action to reduce risks.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be measured at the initial interview and and the end of six months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Presenting to the Emergency Department or Falls Clinic. live in the Perth north metropolitan hospital catchment area. live in the community.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People with functinal cognitive impaiment unable to participate in the intervention e.g. dementia. People living in nursing home ineligible for community support services by Perth Home Care, HACC, VA etc.. People unable to speak or read english - study requires interview and reading /fillling in form.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Subjects meeting the inclusion criteria admitted to the hospital Emergency Department or Falls Clinic who consent to participate from the time of commencement of the trial until 100 are enrolled from each Department. Details are forwarded by the hospital staff providing the standards falls intervention in either Department to an of site Project Manager who randomly allocates them to either the control group or trial intervention group. Each person is assigned a number. The research staff conducting the initial interview and phone follow up have a number for each participant but is not made aware of which group they are assigned to. Details of those in the intervention group are provided the Perth Home Care Services for Support Worker interventin by the Project Manager. Research staff collating data are provided with the numerical codes for each group at the end of the trial.</concealment>
    <sequence>Sequence generated using SPSS (statistical software) randomisation function</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Therapists providing in hospital programs are blinded as are the research staff doing interviews and phone follow up (research assistants aiding researchers in collecting and assessing the data). Participants are blinded in that that the patient information they get in hospital states they may be contacted by a staff member of Perth Home Care Services. Other than that they are advised they will be contacted for an interview and will be asked to fill in a falls calendar (all participants).</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/04/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>200</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Perth Home Care Services Inc.</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The Australian Commonwealth Department of Health &amp; Ageing</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital &amp; Silver Chain Research Department</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study seeks to identify if community based individual falls prevention intervention improves outcomes in individuals who have received current hospital based intervention either from the Emergency Department or the out patient Falls Clinic. Improved outcomes are in areas of understanding falls can be prevented and measures they can take to reduce risks. This includes implementing changes in behaviour or environment. It also will determine if the extent of awareness and implementatin of reducing risk factors reduces the incidence of subsequent falls.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname> Silver Chain research Department</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>EC app 039 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sir Charles Gairdner Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>2007 - 046</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jaye Johnson</name>
      <address>Perth Home Care Services
30 Hasler Road
PO Box 1597
Osborne Park WA 6017</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92047863</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jayej@phcs.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jaye Johnson</name>
      <address>Perth Home Care Services
30 Hasler Road
PO Box 1597
Osborne Park WA 6017</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92047863</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jayej@phcs.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>