<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364023">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/04/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000486729</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Acceptance and commitment therapy: Evaluation of a novel approach to enhance the quality of life of aged care residents</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Acceptance and commitment therapy: Evaluation of a novel approach to enhance the quality of life of aged care residents</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1141-7451</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Poor quality of life
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>12 sessions of Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT). The aim of ACT is to maximise a persons potential for a rich, full and meaningful life. ACT does this by: a) teaching mindfulness skills, b) helping the client to clarify their values - then using that knowledge to guide, inspire and motivate the client to change their life for the better. 

ACT will be administered in individual sessions (2 x 60 minute sessions per week for 6 weeks) by Doctor of Psychology (Clinical) candidates, under supervision from the research team. Attendence record will be kept and treatment adherence will be monitored in weekly supervision sessions.</interventions>
    <comparator>No treatment (wait list control). This group will be offered the intervention after 2 months. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Increase in Lancaster Quality of Life Profile-Residential</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 7 weeks and 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decrease in Geriatric Depression Scale-15 score</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and 7 weeks and 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Decrease in total score on Geriatric Anxiety Inventory</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and 7 weeks and 3 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Permanent resident in aged care facility.
Facility staff reports of mental health concern or adjustment difficulty or poor quality of life.
Fluency in English.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Substantial cognitive impairment (MMSE &lt; 19). 
Severe medical illness that would compromise participation in psychtherapy.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Wait list control</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>A Multiple Analysis of Covariance (MANCOVA) will be used to compare outcome measures at baseline and post-intervention. This method allows for comparison of multiple outcomes simultaneously, and also controls for any differences between groups in baseline scores. 
Changes in outcome measures from post-intervention (i.e., follow-up data) will be recorded for the intervention group only (due to the difficulty of following two waves for 5 months within a 12 month study period). Repeated-measures t-tests will be employed. 

A power analysis was performed using G*Power (version 3.1.4; Faul et al., 2007). For the scales chosen, a sample size of 26 can detect pre-post differences of an effect size of 0.5, with power exceeding 0.8, at alpha = 0.05 (two-sided). Our previous systematic review of psychotherapy in aged care settings reported a mean attrition rate of 19% (Davison et al., 2012). We will recruit 36 participants, to allow for a conservative estimate of 28% attrition. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/04/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>10/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>19/07/2013</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>36</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Tanya Davison</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Aged Mental Health Research Unit, Monash University
Kingston Centre, Warrigal Road, Cheltenham, VIC 3192.</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Lions John Cockayne Memorial Grant Trust Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Professor Barbara Workman
Chair, Lions John Cockayne Memorial Fellowship Trust Fund Committee

Monash Ageing Research Centre
c/o Medical Administration
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Road
Cheltenham VIC 3192 AUSTRALIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Daniel O'Connor</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Aged Mental Health Research Unit, Monash University
Kingston Centre, Warrigal Road, Cheltenham, VIC 3192.</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project aims to evaluate the effectiveness of acceptance and commitment therapy (ACT) in improving the quality of life and mental health of older adults living in aged care facilities. We also aim to determine the feasibility of this approach when implemented as part of a psychology student placement program and its acceptance to older adults and their professional carers.

Older adults living in residential care facilities often report poor quality of life and are at a high risk depression and
anxiety. Despite this, this population has very limited access to nonpharmacological interventions and support. Our team is currently establishing a placement program for Doctor of Psychology (Clinical) candidates, who will deliver a
structured program of ACT to residents across three aged care facilities, under supervision, in 2013. This therapy
has proven effective and popular for use with younger adults, but has not yet been evaluated in aged care settings.

The placement program offers an opportunity for future clinical psychologists to gain experience in working with
older adults, and helps address the shortage of trained mental health clinicians in aged care settings. This study will use a randomized controlled design to evaluate the effectiveness of this student-led intervention in
improving quality of life, as well as reducing symptoms of depression and anxiety, compared to a control group. The
results of this study will be used to inform our future training program, as well as contribute to the literature on the effectiveness of psychological interventions with older adults residing in residential care settings.

Participants will include 36 aged care residents who will be randomly allocated to the intervention or control group,
with control participants offered the intervention at the end of the study. The intervention consists of 12 individual 60minute sessions delivered by a student psychologist twice weekly. The intervention will be evaluated using
measures related to quality of life, symptoms of depression and anxiety, with satisfaction and feasibility determined
in postintervention interviews with the participants and facility staff.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Southern Health HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Monash Medical Centre
Clayton Road
Clayton VIC 3168
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>9/04/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tanya Davison</name>
      <address>Aged Mental Health Research Unit
Monash University
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Road
Cheltenham
VIC 3192</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9265 1700</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tanya.davison@monash.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tanya Davison</name>
      <address>Aged Mental Health Research Unit
Monash University
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Road
Cheltenham
VIC 3192</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9265 1700</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tanya.davison@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tanya Davison</name>
      <address>Aged Mental Health Research Unit
Monash University
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Road
Cheltenham
VIC 3192</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9265 1700</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>tanya.davison@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tanya Davison</name>
      <address>Aged Mental Health Research Unit
Monash University
Kingston Centre
Warrigal Road
Cheltenham
VIC 3192</address>
      <phone>+61 3 9265 1700</phone>
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>