<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="373482">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/08/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/09/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001327370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effectiveness of pharmacist based educational program on glycaemic control, self-care activities and disease knowledge in type 2 diabetes patients in Pakistan.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled study to evaluate the effect of pharmacist led educational intervention on glycaemic control, self-care activities and disease knowledge among type 2 diabetes patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>NIL</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>NIL</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type 2 diabetes mellitus</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This randomized controlled trail (RCT) will be conducted at diabetes clinic of Capital Development Authority (CDA) hospital, located in Islamabad, Pakistan. Overall eighty (80) T2DM patients, with poorly controlled diabetes (HbA1c&gt; 7%) will be randomized into intervention (N=40) and control groups (N=40). A baseline assessment for patients of both groups will be done for their self-care activities and disease knowledge by using validated Urdu versions of Diabetes Self-management Questionnaire (DSMQ) and Diabetes Knowledge Questionnaire (DKQ), respectively. After the baseline evaluation, interventional group patients will be supplemented with a face to face pharmacist-led educational intervention (60 min duration). The educational intervention and patient informatory material has been designed according to American diabetes Association (ADA) guidelines and validated after detailed conversation with the field experts. A qualified pharmacist (researcher) will educate the patients in the interventional group about disease (diabetes), its symptoms, clinical goals, self-care activities (self-monitoring of blood glucose, physical activity, importance of regular medication in-take and healthy diet), and, reducing risks. Patients in the intervention group will be educated by pharmacist with the help of presentation, informatory brochures and pictograms. During 24 weeks of study, interventional group participants will be required to improve their self-care activities and in order to keep track of self-monitoring blood glucose they will also be provided log books to keep the record of their self-monitored blood glucose levels during this intervention period. Intervention group patients will be educated again at their first follow visit (12th week) for their self-care activities and any barrier (s) / problem (s) towards their self-care will be discussed (30 min duration). Additionally a brief telephonic follow-up by the pharmacist will be carried out for each patient four times during these 6 months intervention (at week 4,8,16 and 20). Whereas the control group patients (N=40) will receive the usual medical care. The researcher will use the interactive discussion strategy to enhance intervention group patients motivation to improve diabetes self-care behaviours. Final assessments for glycaemic control (HbA1c), self-care activities and disease knowledge, will be conducted at the end of trail (24th week) for both intervention and control groups. A brief educational programs satisfaction survey will be carried out at the end of the intervention (24th week) from the intervention arm participants. </interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will receive the usual care, which include a combination of medical treatment, physician monitoring and an optional counselling session about diabetes. The control group will be in waiting list to get the intervention which will be provided at the end of the study after post test data collection. That is, they will receive the intervention 6 months after enrolment.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the HbA1c</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the diabetes self-care activities. 
The Diabetes Self-management Questionnaire (DSMQ) will be used to measure the patients self-care activities (validated Urdu version).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patients knowledge about diabetes. 
Diabetes Knowledge Questionnaire (DKQ), developed for the Starr County Diabetes Education Study, has been translated and validated in Urdu language in Pakistan.
Reference: Bukhsh A, Lee SWH, Pusparajah P, Khan AH and Khan TM (2017) Psychometric Properties of the Urdu Version of Diabetes Knowledge Questionnaire. Front. Public Health 5:139.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Body mass index </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 months after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Includes poorly controlled (HbA1c&gt;7%) T2DM, adult patients (age more than or equal to 30 years) regardless of gender; speak and understand Urdu and / or English language (s) ; having no significant co-morbidity; not being involved in any trial / study related to diabetes during last 3 months and able to attend regular visits</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>30</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if they are of other types of diabetes (gestational diabetes, T1DM); age less than 30 years; unable to answer the questionnaire independently or having hearing, vision or cognitive impairments.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients handpick a numbered envelope from the basket</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple random technique will be used form a list of random numbers of eligible patients which will be compiled by using the patients’ hospital identification numbers. After recruitment, the patients will be requested to handpick an envelope from the basket indicating allocation to either control or intervention group with 1:1 randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>NIL</designfeatures>
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>The analyses will performed using SPSS 22.0.0 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). Frequencies and descriptive statistics will be used for patients demographic presentation, while means and standard deviations will be calculated for the continuous variables and group differences will be analysed by using Pearson chi-square test for categorical variables, independent t test for continuous variables, and Mann-Whitney U-test for ordinal variables or non-normal distributions. Primary outcome of the educational intervention on HbA1C levels, self-care activities scores (DSMQ) and disease knowledge scores (DKQ) will be analysed by using analysis of variance (ANOVA). Paired t test will be used to analyze within group effects. The effects of the intervention will be examined in multivariate general linear models. P values &lt;.05 will be considered as significant for all analysis.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>2/10/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>30/10/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>80</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <currentsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/05/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Pakistan</country>
      <state>PUNJAB</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Monash University Malaysia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Jalan Lagoon Selatan, 47500 Bandar Sunway, Selangor Darul Ehsan</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Malaysia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Monash University Malaysia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>?Jalan Lagoon Selatan, 47500 Bandar Sunway, Selangor Darul Ehsan,
MALAYSIA</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Malaysia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Capital Development Authority Hospital, Islamabad</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>CDA Hospital, St# 31, G-6/2, Islamabad</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Pakistan</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study aims to examine the impact of a face to face short term (6 months) pharmacist-led educational intervention model in poorly controlled T2DM patient (HbA1c &gt;7%) in Pakistan.  In this study we will investigate the mean change in HbA1C at 6 months after the baseline, and a comparison will be made with a similar comparator group of T2DM patients who will not be provided education intervention. In addition comparison between self-care activities and disease knowledge between the groups will also be studied.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>NIL</trialwebsite>
    <publication>NIl</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>NIL</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Research and Ethics Committee, CDA, Hospital, Islamabad</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>CDA Hospital, St# 31, G-6/2, Islamabad </ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>8/08/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>CDA-077-2017</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/07/2017</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Pakistan</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tahir Mehmood Khan</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy, MONASH University, Jalan Lagoon Selatan, 47500 Bandar Sunway, Selangor Darul Ehsan, MALAYSIA</address>
      <phone>+603 5514 6364</phone>
      <fax>+603 5514 6364</fax>
      <email>tahir.mehmood@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Allah Bukhsh</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy, MONASH University, Jalan Lagoon Selatan, 47500 Bandar Sunway, Selangor Darul Ehsan, MALAYSIA</address>
      <phone>+601133623703</phone>
      <fax>+603 5514 6364</fax>
      <email>allah.bukhsh@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Tahir Mehmood Khan</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy, MONASH University, Jalan Lagoon Selatan, 47500 Bandar Sunway, Selangor Darul Ehsan, MALAYSIA</address>
      <phone>+601127640646</phone>
      <fax>+603 5514 6364</fax>
      <email>tahir.mehmood@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Allah Bukhsh</name>
      <address>School of Pharmacy, MONASH University, Jalan Lagoon Selatan, 47500 Bandar Sunway, Selangor Darul Ehsan, MALAYSIA</address>
      <phone>+601133623703</phone>
      <fax>+603 5514 6364</fax>
      <email>allah.bukhsh@monash.edu</email>
      <country>Malaysia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>