<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371259">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001080415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of tart cherry juice on recovery and next day performance in well-trained Water Polo players</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of tart cherry juice on recovery and next day performance in well-trained Water Polo players</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1186-1386</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Oxidative Stress</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Inflammation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Recovery and Next-Day Performance in Well-Trained Water Polo Athletes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal musculoskeletal and cartilage development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A randomised repeated measures, cross-over design was utilised. All participants (n=9) were recruited from the Western Australian Institute of Sport (WAIS) Waterpolo (Men) Squad using the attached participant information sheets. A meeting was held with the head coach of WAIS Water Polo to discuss opportunities to disseminate the information sheet to potential participants. The information sheet was handed out at a training session. This information contained the lead investigators contact details, allowing potential participants to register their interest should they feel inclined. 

Each experimental trial occured over 7 days. From day 1 to day 6, participants were supplemented with tart cherry juice or a placebo equivalent. During experimental weeks, all training (technical skills, weights, swimming) and recovery activities (cold water immersion) will be identical (between the cherry juice and placebo groups) and undertaken in a controlled environment. All testing sessions will also be performed in the morning to minimise any diurnal influence. Water-based performance testing included numerous tests (10 m sprint, water polo multi stage shuttle test, in water vertical jump and repeat sprint test) performed at the start (day 1) and at the end of each experimental trial (day 7). Finally, a 5-week washout period was adopted between the two experimental trials to preclude any follow-on effects,

On day 6, participants performed a simulated fatiguing team game activity, which has previously been reported to mimic the demands of a waterpolo match (Tan et al., 2010). The following morning (day 7), performance tests were repeated.  Additionally, throughout the investigation various biological markers will also be measured (via venepuncture) to assess the efficacy of the cherry juice. Inflammatory markers (HS IL-6 and CRP) were measured on day 6 (pre- &amp; post-exercise) and on day 7 (12 h post-exercise).  Additionally, markers of oxidative stress (Uric Acid and F2-isoprostanes) were measured on day 1 and 6 (pre- &amp; post-exercise), and again on day 7 (pre-exercise).

Participants consumed 90 mL daily of tart Montmorency CJ (Prunus Cerasus) concentrate (Cherry Active, Sunbury, UK) or a placebo equivalent for a total of 6 days. The cherry concentrate was diluted with water, such that each 30 mL serving was made up into a 200 mL beverage. Both the cherry juice and placebo were consumed in two doses each day; 200 mL before morning training, and 400 mL in the evening post-training. According to the manufacturer, a 30 mL dose of Cherry Active concentrate is equivalent to approximately 90 whole Montmorency tart cherries (Cherry Active, Sunbury, UK) containing 9.117 mg/mL of anthocyanins, which can have positive health and performance outcomes (Bell et al., 2014, Bowtell et al., 2011, Howatson at el., 2012).Daily adherence to supplement consumption was made by the investigators being present at every training session and obtaining empty bottle containers.

Bell, P.G., McHugh, M., Stevenson, E., &amp; Howatson, G. (2014). The role of cherries in exercise and health. Scandinavian Journal of Medicine &amp; Science in Sports, 24, 477-490.
Bowtell, J., Sumners, D., Dyer, A., Fox, P., &amp; Mileva, K. (2011). Montmorency cherry juice reduces muscle damage caused by intensive strength exercise. Medicine &amp; Science in Sports &amp; Exercise, 43, 1544-1551.
Howatson, G., Bell, P.G., Tallent, J., Middleton, B., McHugh, M.P., &amp; Ellis, J. (2012). Effect of tart cherry juice (prunus cerasus) on melatonin levels and enhanced sleep quality. European Journal of Nutrition, 51, 909-916.
Tan, F., Polglaze, T., Cox, G., Dawson, B., Mujika, I., &amp; Clark, S. (2010). Effects of induced alkalosis on simulated match performance in elite female water polo players. International Journal of Sport Nutrition, 20, 198.

</interventions>
    <comparator>This study adopted a randomised repeated measures, cross-over design. As such, participants performed both the cherry juice and placebo trial. The placebo was made by combining 40 mL of three different off the shelf cordials. Lime (Woolworths select lime cordial, Australia), cranberry (Bickfords cranberry juice cordial, Australia) and raspberry (Cottees raspberry flavoured cordial, Australia) cordials were mixed with food colouring and 480 mL of water in order to closely imitate the taste, colour and carbohydrate content (10 g/100 mL, maltodextrin powder, Nutricia Poly-Joule, Australia) without any of the anthocyanin content of the cherry juice. 


</comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with a reduction in performance tests* decline when comparing the tart cherry juice and placebo trials

*Swimming-based tests comprised the 10 m sprint test, the repeat sprint test (RST), in-water vertical jump test (VJ), and the Water Polo Intermittent Shuttle Test (WIST) (Tan et al., 2009). All test protocols were conducted in accordance with the Australian National Water Polo Test Protocols (Tanner &amp; Gore, 2013)

Tan F, Polglaze T, &amp; Dawson B. Activity profiles and physical demands of elite women's water polo match play. J Sport Sci 2009; 27: 1095-1104.
Tanner RK, Gore CJ, &amp; Australian Institute of Sport. Physiological tests for elite athletes. 2nd ed. Champaign, IL: Human Kinetics;  2013.

</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7 Performance tests

*Swimming-based tests comprised the 10 m sprint test, the repeat sprint test (RST), in-water vertical jump test (VJ), and the Water Polo Intermittent Shuttle Test (WIST) (Tan et al., 2009). All test protocols were conducted in accordance with the Australian National Water </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with reduced oxidative stress (F2-IsoP and uric acid)  when comparing the tart cherry juice and placebo trials

Sample Analysis
The UA and F2-IsoP were assessed from blood samples. UA was measured using an Architect analyzer (ci8200), and determined using a UA Reagent (Abbott Diagnostics, Abbott Laboratories, Abbott Park, IL 60064, USA).  F2-IsoP was analysed using an Agilent 6890 gas chromatograph coupled to an Agilent 5973 mass selective detector. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 6 post-exercise and Day 7 (12 h post-exercise)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Proportion of participants with reduced inflammation (IL-6 and CRP) when comparing the tart cherry supplement and placebo trials

Sample Analysis
The IL-6 and CRP were assessed from blood samples. IL-6 was measured via immunoassay technique (Quantikine HS ELISA, R&amp;D Systems, Inc. Minneapolis, USA). The CRP was measured using an Architect analyser (ci8200), and determined using a CRP Vario Reagent (SENTINEL CH. SpA, Via Robert Koch, 2, Milan 20152, Italy). </outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 6 post-exercise and Day 7 (12 h post-exercise)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-perceived delayed onset of muscle soreness (DOMS) ratings between the cherry juice and placebo trials.

DOMS was assessed using a numerical rating scale to measure how sore athletes felt, encompassing the anchor points of 0 (normal; without pain or stiffness) to 10 (very painful) (Hill &amp; Richardson, 1989).

Hill DW, &amp; Richardson JD. Effectiveness of 10% trolamine salicylate cream on muscular soreness induced by a reproducible program of weight training. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther 1989; 11: 19-23.



</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-perceived quality of recovery, assessed using the total quality of recovery (TQR) scale between the cherry juice and placebo trials.

TQR was quantified using a numerical rating scale to determine how well athletes felt they had recovered, and encompassed the anchor points 6 (very, very poor recovery) to 20 (very, very good recovery) (Kentta &amp; Hassmen, 1998).

Kentta G, &amp; Hassmen P. Overtraining and recovery. Sports Med 1998; 26: 1-16.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Day 7 </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Well-trained Water Polo male athlete that are currently part of the Western Australian 
Institute of sport daily training environment. All participants &lt;18 years of age required parent/legal guardian consent prior to participating.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Injury and/or sickness</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation was concealed to participants and the principal researcher via numbered containers to which trial (cherry juice or placebo) the participant was allocated to during the experimental weeks.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a randomisation table from a statistic book was adopted for this process.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Ten elite male waterpolo players will be recruited from the Western Australian Institute of Sport Waterpolo Squad. This sample size (n=10; F=2.14; expected power=0.85; a=p&lt;0.05) was determined using a power analysis (G*power Version 3.1.9.2, Bonn University, Bonn, Germany) based on inflammatory responses under the influence of tart cherry juice (Howatson et al., 2009). Howatson et al., (2009) Scan J Med Sci Sports. 20(6), 843-852.

Results are expressed at mean (+/-SD) and were analysed using a repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) to determine time, condition and interaction effects of tart cherry juice on measures of perceptual recovery (TQR and DOMS), blood variables (UA, F2-IsoP, IL-6 and CRP)  and performance. A post-hoc paired samples t-test was used to determine any differences between trials. The alpha level was accepted at p&lt;0.05. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>8/05/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>30/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>9</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>23/08/2015</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>30/08/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>6010 - Mount Claremont</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Western Australian Institute of Sport</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>WAIS High Performance Service Centre
McGillivray Road
Mt Claremont, WA 6010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Institute of Sport, Australian Sports Comission</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Leverrier St, Bruce ACT 2617</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>The University of Western australia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>35 Stirling Hwy, Crawley WA 6009</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Federation University Australia</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University Dr, Mount Helen VIC 3350</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The specific aim of this study is to assess if recovery measures and next day performance can be enhanced in well-trained Water Polo athletes through exposure to the phytochemicals found in tart cherry juice. Results will be applicable to elite waterpolo players and team sport athletes. It is hypothesised that cherry jucie would improve recovery and limit any decline in performance at the end of 7 days of hard Water Polo training.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>The University of Western Australia Human Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>35 Stirling Hwy, Crawley WA 6009</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/04/2015</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RA/4/1/7380</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>2/03/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371259-Application Approval.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371259-Research Study Info and Consent Form C4.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marc Sim</name>
      <address>Federation University Australia
University Dr, Mount Helen VIC 3350</address>
      <phone>+61353279004</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.sim@federation.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marc Sim</name>
      <address>Federation University Australia
University Dr, Mount Helen VIC 3350</address>
      <phone>+61353279004</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.sim@federation.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marc Sim</name>
      <address>Federation University Australia
University Dr, Mount Helen VIC 3350</address>
      <phone>+61353279004</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.sim@federation.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Marc Sim</name>
      <address>Federation University Australia
University Dr, Mount Helen VIC 3350</address>
      <phone>+61353279004</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>m.sim@federation.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>