<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336323">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/12/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>10/12/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610001086055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of Stenotrophomonas maltophilia case contamination and corneal infiltrative event rates in both experienced and new contact lens wearers.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Prospective, open-label, daily wear study of NIGHT &amp; DAY[Registered trade mark] contact lenses in conjunction with OPTI-FREE[Registered trade mark] RepleniSH[Registered trade mark] lens care product to evaluate Stenotrophomonas maltophilia case contamination and corneal infiltrative event rates in both experienced and new contact lens wearers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Contact lens wear</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal eye development and function</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a prospective, single group, daily wear (DW) study where 90 participants will wear NIGHT &amp; DAY [Registered trade mark] lenses bilaterally on a daily wear (DW) basis in conjunction with OPT-FREE [Trade mark] RepleniSH [Trade mark] solution for 4 months. There will be a minimum of 5 scheduled visits: baseline, 1 month visit, 2 month visit, 3 month visit and 4 month visit. These visits will involve assessment of visual acuity and examination with a slit-lamp biomicroscope (a specialised microscope for viewing the eye). Lenses will be worn a minimum of 5 days per week, and 6 hours on the day lenses are worn.</interventions>
    <comparator>Correlation between contamination of contact lens cases with Stenotrophomonas maltophilia and corneal infiltrative events (CIEs)</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To determine whether a correlation exists between contamination of contact lens cases with Stenotrophomonas maltophilia and CIEs, when contact lenses and worn on a daily wear basis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 2, 3 and 4 months</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>-Able to read and comprehend English and give informed consent as demonstrated by signing a record of informed consent
-Be at least 18 years old, male or female;
-Willing to comply with the wearing and clinical trial visit schedule as directed by the investigator;
-Have ocular health findings considered to be normal and which would not prevent the participant from safely wearing contact lenses;
-Is correctable to at least 6/12 (20/40) or better in each eye with contact lenses; 
-May be experienced or inexperienced at wearing contact lenses.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>-Any pre-existing ocular irritation, injury or condition (including infection or disease) of the cornea, conjunctiva or eyelids that would preclude contact lens fitting and safe wearing of contact lenses;
-Any systemic disease that adversely affects ocular health e.g. diabetes, Graves disease, and auto-immune diseases such as ankylosing spondylitis, multiple sclerosis, Sjögrens syndrome and systemic lupus erythematosus. Conditions such as systemic hypertension and arthritis do not automatically exclude prospective participants;
-Use of or a need for concurrent category S3 and above ocular medication at enrolment and/or during the study;
-Use of or a need for any systemic medication or topical medications which may alter normal ocular findings/are known to affect a participants ocular health/physiology or contact lens performance either in an adverse or beneficial manner at enrolment and/or during the study;
N.B.: Systemic antihistamines are allowed on an as needed basis, provided they are not used prophylactically during the trial and at least 24 hours before study product is used;
-Eye surgery within 12 weeks immediately prior to enrolment for this trial;
-Previous corneal refractive surgery;
-Contraindications to contact lens wear;
-Known allergy or intolerance to ingredients in any of the study products;
-Currently enrolled in another clinical trial.
-Pregnancy: Formal testing of pregnancy is not required. A participants verbal report is sufficient

-The Investigator may, at his/her discretion, exclude anyone who they believe may not be able to fulfil the study requirements, or if it is believed to be in the participants best interests.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Particicpant needs to satisfy inclusion/exclusion criteria. All participants are allocated the same treatment</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>31/01/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>4/02/2011</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>19/08/2011</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>19/08/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Abbott Medical Optics, Inc</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1700 East St. Andrew Place
PO Box 25162
Santa Ana, CA 92799-5162, USA</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>United States of America</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Brien Holden Vision Institute</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 5, Rupert Myers Building Gate 14, Barker Street University of New South Wales, NSW 2052</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary> This study will examine whether a correlation exists between contamination of contact lens cases with Stenotrophomonas maltophilia and CIEs, when contact lenses and worn on a daily wear basis. The hypothesis is case contamination with Stenotrophomonas maltophilia does not correlate with CIEs.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>VIHEC Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, North Wing, Rupert Myers Building (RMB), Gate 14, Barker Street, The University of New South Wales SYDNEY NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>28/01/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/12/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker Street, The University of New South Wales SYDNEY NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 6165</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker Street, The University of New South Wales SYDNEY NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 6165</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker Street, The University of New South Wales SYDNEY NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 6165</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Daniel Tilia</name>
      <address>Level 5, North Wing, RMB, Gate 14, Barker Street, The University of New South Wales SYDNEY NSW 2052  </address>
      <phone>+61293857516</phone>
      <fax />
      <email> d.tilia@brienholdenvision.org  </email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>