<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371283">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001174471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy of nasogastric and endotracheal tube securement devices, preventative dressings and topical skin applications for reducing device-related pressure injuries in intensive care patients; a pilot study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy of nasogastric and endotracheal tube securement devices, preventative dressings and topical skin applications for reducing device-related pressure injuries in intensive care patients; a pilot study</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1186-2392</utrn>
    <trialacronym>REMEDy</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Critical illness</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Pressure injuries</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Skin</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other skin conditions</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There are two arms of the study described below; Arm 1 - Nasogastric (NGT) securement devices with two interventions and a control; and Arm 2 - Endotracheal tube (ETT) securement devices with two interventions and a control. 

ARM 1 (Wide bore NGT are left in situ for 3-5 days and then replaced with a fine bore NGT which can remain in situ indefinitely). 
Subgroup 1A - NGT secured with tapes; Subgroup 1B NGT secured to ETT with TubeSAFE (Registered Trademark) clip. 
Subgroup 1A participants NGT will be secured using self-adhesive tape (Hypafix [Registered Trademark], BSN Medical) attaching one end of the cotton tape to the nose over an anchoring dressing (DuoDERM [Registered Trademark] Extra Thin Dressing, ConvaTec), and attaching the other end to the nasogastric tube according to specific instructions. 
Subgroup 1B participants NGT will be secured using a TubeSAFE [Registered Trademark] clip which attaches the NGT to the ETT. 
All participants in subgroup 1A and 1B will receive the following intervention: 
1) 12-hourly (i.e. each shift) application of 3M [Trademark] Cavilon No Sting Barrier film [Trademark] wipes, pre-packaged barrier wipes, on the nare surface around the device 
2) Daily application of Mepilex [Registered Trademark] Lite (Molnlycke Health Care), a thin dressing, to pad the nare surface surrounding the device 
3) Application of foam padding (3M), cut to wrap around the portion of the device in contact with the nare 
4) 3-hourly assessment of the skin surrounding the device 
5) 3-hourly repositioning of the device 
6) Shift by shift documentation of all assessment, device positions, prevention strategies.

ARM 2 (ETTs can remain in situ for 2-3 weeks depending on the patients projected clinical trajectory)
Subgroup 2A - ETT secured with AnchorFast [Trademark] (Hollister [Registered Trademark] Inc.) ETT attachment device. 
All participants in this subgroup will receive the following intervention: 
1)	The participants cheek skin is clean, dry with no oily residue and no barrier wipe is applied 
2)	Tube attachment device applied and to remain in situ up to 5 days (as per manufacturers instructions)
3)	Daily application of Mepilex [Registered Trademark] Lite (Molnlycke Health Care), a thin dressing, to pad the skin surface in the corners of the mouth 
4)	3-hourly assessment of the skin surrounding the device 
5)	3-hourly repositioning of ETT (right, centre or left) 
6)	Shift by shift documentation of all assessment, device position, prevention strategies. 

Subgroup 2B - ETT secured with tape and foam roll
Subgroup 2B participants ETT will be secured using cotton tape secured around the ETT and tied around participants neck using foam to protect the skin at the nape of the neck and the cheeks. 
All participants in this subgroup will receive the following intervention: 
1)	12-hourly application of a barrier wipe on the skin surface surrounding the device 
2)	12-hourly repositioning of the device by resecuring the device (i.e. application of new tape and foam roll)
3)	Daily application of Mepilex [Registered Trademark] Lite (Molnlycke Health Care), a thin padded dressing, on the skin/mucosal surface (corners of the mouth) surrounding the device 
4)	3-hourly assessment of the skin underneath the device 
5)	Shift by shift documentation of all assessment, device position, prevention strategies. 

If the participant is eligible for both the NGT and ETT arms of the study they will be randomised to a subgroup in both arms. If a participant has both a NGT and ETT they will be first randomised to one of the three Arm 1 NGT subgroups (intervention [Subgroup 1A or Subgroup 1B] or the control group [Subgroup 1C]). Then the participant will be randomised to one of the three subgroups in Arm 2 ETT (intervention [Subgroup 2A or Subgroup 2B] or the control [Subgroup 2C]). 

The devices (NGTs and and ETTs) will be inserted respectively by appropriately trained nursing or medical personnel. Following intensive onsite training by the study investigators, bedside registered nurses in the intensive care units will administer the interventions. Adherence to the intervention delivery will be monitored by research nurses through completion of a checklist as part of the daily data collection. Feedback will be provided to the bedside registered nurses delivering the intervention.</interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 1 
Subgroup 1C - Control - Participants' NGT will be secured using Naso-fix (ConvaTec Inc.), a 'mushroom' shaped adhesive tape configuration. All participants in the control group will receive standard care, i.e. the current standard of care in the ICU:
 1) shift by shift assessment of the device 
2) ad hoc repositioning of the device
3) ad hoc documentation of the device position (left or right).

Arm 2
Subgroup 2C - Control - Participants' ETT will be secured with either an AnchorFast (Trademark) (Hollister [Registered Trademark] Inc.) ETT attachment device or cotton tape and foam. Choice of ETT securement in the control group will be according to standard care guidelines at each site. Participants in the control group will also receive:
1) shift by shift assessment of the device
2) ad hoc repositioning of the device
3) ad hoc documentation of the device position (left, middle or right). </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome: development of any stage medical device-related pressure injuries (MDR PI). The primary outcome will be assessed by direct clinical examination of the skin surrounding the device. Diagnosis of a mucosal or stage 2 MDR PI will be made using current international staging guidelines for classification of pressure injuries i.e.. National Pressure Ulcer Advisory Panel, European Pressure Ulcer Advisory Panel and Pan Pacific Pressure Injury Alliance. Prevention and Treatment of Pressure Ulcers: Quick Reference Guide. Emily Haesler (Ed.). Cambridge Media: Osborne Park, Australia; 2014 </outcome>
      <timepoint>The primary outcome measure will be assessed daily for the duration of device use and follow-up will occur for up to 72 hours in the following circumstances:
1) If the participant is in the ICU and the device is removed 
2) If the participant is discharged to the ward with the device insitu (i.e. NGTs only) </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of time to any stage MDR PI occurrence.

The secondary outcome will be assessed by direct clinical examination of the skin surrounding the device and documentation of time to PI occurrence. Diagnosis of a mucosal or stage 2 MDR PI will be made using current international staging guidelines for classification of pressure injuries i.e.i.e..	National Pressure Ulcer Advisory Panel, European Pressure Ulcer Advisory Panel and Pan Pacific Pressure Injury Alliance. Prevention and Treatment of Pressure Ulcers: Quick Reference Guide. Emily Haesler (Ed.). Cambridge Media: Osborne Park, Australia; 2014  .</outcome>
      <timepoint>The measure will be assessed daily for the duration of device use until 72 hours post discharge from ICU.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Severity of staging of MDR PI.

The secondary outcome will be assessed by direct clinical examination of the skin surrounding the device. Diagnosis of a mucosal or stage 2 MDR PI will be made using current international staging guidelines for classification of pressure injuries i.e..	National Pressure Ulcer Advisory Panel, European Pressure Ulcer Advisory Panel and Pan Pacific Pressure Injury Alliance. Prevention and Treatment of Pressure Ulcers: Quick Reference Guide. Emily Haesler (Ed.). Cambridge Media: Osborne Park, Australia; 2014 .</outcome>
      <timepoint>The measure will be assessed daily for the duration of device use until 72 hours post discharge from ICU.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All ICU patients = or &gt;18 years who have a NGT and/or ETT in situ
Patients who are expected to remain in ICU &gt; 24 hours 
NGT or ETT inserted a maximum of 12 hours prior to ICU admission
Patients readmitted to ICU with no oral or nasal skin injury present
NGT arm only - must have wide bore NGT and an ETT in situ.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Burn patients with an ETT wired in place (ETT arm only)
Patients with NGT sutured in place or nasal bridle (NGT arm only)
Patients with facial trauma
Traumatic brain injured patients requiring intracranial pressure monitoring and/or ventricular drainage of cerebrospinal fluid
Cervical spine injured patients who have a hard collar in situ
Hirsute patients with beards where patient permission to shave is not possible
Patients who are receiving non-invasive ventilation
Patients with a device (NGT or ETT) predicted to be in situ &lt; 48 hours.
Patients with a community or hospital-acquired NGT or ETT PI diagnosed within 24 hours of admission to the ICU.
Patients on whom treatment is withdrawn or who are being palliated.
Patients currently enrolled on three studies in the ICU.
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation is not concealed. Although patients will be masked to group allocation, it is not practicable to mask bedside ICU RNs (who will provide the interventions) and research nurses (who will monitor processes of care). </concealment>
    <sequence>Eligible participants in each arm (NGT or ETT) will be randomised into one of three subgroups. Study groups will be assigned using a computer generated random number generation for both arms. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample Size
75-100 participants meeting the inclusion criteria will be enrolled with 12-17 participants per group.
Statistical Analysis Plan
Data for both clinical and feasibility outcomes will be analysed descriptively using frequencies, and means as percentages, as appropriate for continuous and categorical variables. Kaplan-Meier survival analysis will be used to compare time to new MDR PI events between subgroups in each arm. Study data will be used to undertake a sample size calculation for the larger follow on study. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>12/01/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Herston</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Queensland University of Technology</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>GPO Box 2434; 
Brisbane, 
QLD 4001. </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Wound Management Innovation CRC</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Office
Oxley House
Level 2, 25 Donkin St
West End QLD 4101

Postal Address:
PO BOX 2375
Toowong DC QLD 4066 </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Intensive Care Services
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Level 3 Ned Hanlon Building
Butterfield Street
Herston, QLD, 4029</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Nicola Barker-Gregory</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Intensive Care Unit
Level 2 
Redcliffe Hospital Metro North Hospital and Health Service Locked Bag 1, Redcliffe QLD 4020</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients in the intensive care unit (ICU) are known to be at higher risk of developing pressure injuries than other patient populations due to their illnesses and the types of therapies (medications, devices and technologies) used to treat their life-threatening event. More medical devices are used in critically ill patients because of the life-saving treatments needed and, thus, there are often high rates of medical device-related pressure injuries.  Medical device-related pressure injuries are suspected when an injury has the same shape or outline as the device. Stomach tubes for feeding patients, and breathing tubes for mechanically assisted breathing, are the two most common devices used in ICUs. Together they cause the most medical device-related pressure injuries in the intensive care. Critically ill patients in the ICU with medical devices are nearly four times more likely to develop a pressure injury of any kind. There has been some research into ways to reduce medical device-related pressure injuries but none of these suggested methods have been tested in large patient groups.  Hence, the aim of this project is to test the effectiveness of different ways of securing these devices, the use of a thin dressing under the device, regular assessment of your skin beneath the device, and regular repositioning of the device. The combination of these preventative methods in an intensive care environment has not been tested.  
This study will examine whether ICU patients with NGT or ETT who receive the intervention demonstrate less medical device related PI compared with patients who receive standard care practices.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>Nil</trialwebsite>
    <publication>Nil to date</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>Nil</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 7, Block 7
Butterfield St
Herston
QLD 4029.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/10/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/08/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/371283-REMEDy Study RBWH HREC 16-428 signed approval.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Fiona Coyer</name>
      <address>School of Nursing, Queensland University of Technology and the Intensive Care Services Department, Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital.
Level 2, Centre for Clinical Nursing, Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital, Butterfield St., Herston, QLD 4029.</address>
      <phone>+61 4380 49714</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.coyer@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Fiona Coyer</name>
      <address>School of Nursing, Queensland University of Technology and the Intensive Care Services Department, Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital.
Level 2, Centre for Clinical Nursing, Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital, Butterfield St., Herston, QLD 4029.</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 2140</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.coyer@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Fiona Coyer</name>
      <address>School of Nursing, Queensland University of Technology and the Intensive Care Services Department, Royal Brisbane &amp; Women's Hospital.
Level 2, Centre for Clinical Nursing, Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital, Butterfield St., Herston, QLD 4029.</address>
      <phone>+61 4380 49714</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>f.coyer@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jane-Louise Cook</name>
      <address>Level 2, Centre for Clinical Nursing, Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital, Butterfield St., Herston, QLD 4029.</address>
      <phone>=61 4380 71463</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>janelouise.cook@qut.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>