<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="366127">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/04/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/04/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000409673</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>MoodSwings: An Online Self Help Program for Bipolar Disorder</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>MoodSwings 2.0: A Randomised Controlled Trial Assessing the Effectiveness of an Internet-Based Intervention for Bipolar Disorder on Mood Symptom Severity</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1155-4445</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Bipolar Disorder</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other mental health disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly allocated to one of three groups, which will have varying levels of access to the MoodSwings Internet-Based Intervention for Bipolar Disorder. The first group is the control group (see below), while the second and third groups allow partial and full access to the MoodSwings program content. Program content includes a series of nine learning modules, which cover a number of topics related to bipolar disorder. The first five learning modules are made available fortnightly, and the last 4 modules are released at 3, 6, 9 and 12 months after program commencement. Program content also includes a series of interactive tools, which allow users to monitor their moods, and work on strategies to better manage their bipolar disorder. These tools are also made available fortnightly. Once released, tools and modules remain available for the remainder of the 12 month study period. In addition to the MoodSwings program content, all groups will also have access to an online discussion board. There are three separate boards, with one for each group. 

The two treatment groups are:
Level 2: Access to a moderated discussion board and a series of learning modules.
Level 3: Access to a moderated discussion board, a series of learning modules and a number of interactive tools.

All posts submitted to the discussion boards will be moderated by research staff members, who will be supervised by trained clinicians. The discussion board moderators will post new topics for discussion at least once per month; however they will not otherwise engage in discussion.

Participants will have access to the program for a total of 12 months. They will be assessed both online and over the phone at baseline then followed up at 3, 6, 9 and 12 months from program commencement.

To encourage adherence, participants will receive automated reminder messages if they do not log in to the program for 2 weeks. The research team are also able to track log in records to monitor adherence, however there are no other strategies in place to encourage adherence as we plan to observe natural usage patterns. 
</interventions>
    <comparator>The first group in this study is the control group:
Level 1: Access to a moderated discussion board

There are a total of three discussion boards involved in the MoodSwings program, with one board allocated to each group.

All posts submitted to the discussion boards will be moderated by research staff members, who will be supervised by trained clinicians. The discussion board moderators will post new topics for discussion at least once per month; however they will not otherwise engage in discussion.

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression symptom severity (measured by Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS))
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Changes assessed quarterly over 12 month study period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mania symptom severity (measured by Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Changes assessed quarterly over 12 month study period</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health service utilization (measured by Cornell Service Index)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Changes assessed quarterly over 12 month study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Relapse (measured by Time to Intervention for Mood Episode (TIME))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Changes assessed quarterly over 12 month study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Functioning (measured by SF-12)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Changes assessed quarterly over 12 month study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Social support (measured by Medical Outcomes Study - Social Support Survey (MOS-SSS))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Changes assessed quarterly over 12 month study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life (measured by Quality of Life Enjoyment and Satisfaction Questionnaire (Q-LES-Q))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Changes assessed quarterly over 12 month study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medication adherence (measured by Medication Adherence Rating Scale (MARS))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Changes assessed quarterly over 12 month study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Treatment satisfaction (measured by Patient Satisfaction Questionnaire 18 item (PSQ-18))</outcome>
      <timepoint>Changes assessed quarterly over 12 month study period</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Current diagnosis of bipolar I disorder, bipolar II disorder or bipolar disorder not otherwise specified (confirmed by Structured Clinical Interview for DSM (SCID))
- Aged 21 to 65 years
- Access to a computer with an internet connection
- Able to speak and read English proficiently
- Sees a health care professional at least twice per year to discuss bipolar disorder symptoms and treatment needs
- Local access to emergency care
- Willing to provide emergency contact details</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>21</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Current psychosis (confirmed by Structured Clinical Interview for DSM (SCID))
- Current mania (confirmed by Structured Clinical Interview for DSM (SCID))
- Acutely suicidal (confirmed by Hamilton  Rating Scale for Depression (HAM-D) item 3)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participant screening is completed by a blinded interviewer. Once deemed eligible, participants are randomised automatically by the MoodSwings online program.</concealment>
    <sequence>Block randomisation, created by computer software</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Based upon definitions of the minimal meaningful clinical difference observed in most clinical trials of persons with bipolar disorder, we have defined a reduction of 3.5 points on the Montgomery-Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) as a meaningful clinical outcome.  An estimate of 300 patients (100 per group) will be more than adequate to detect, with 80% power, a time-averaged difference of 3.5 points on the MADRS scale.  This calculation assumes a significance level alpha of 0.05, four post assessments, serial correlation equal to 0.4, standard deviation of 10 points and 20% attrition (Liu &amp; Wu, 2005). </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>27/03/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>27/03/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>27/03/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>300</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Barwon Health - Geelong Hospital campus - Geelong</hospital>
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>United States of America</country>
      <state>California, Palo Alto</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Melbourne</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>1-100 Grattan Street, Parkville VIC 3010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Institutes of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>31 Center Dr, Bethesda, MD 20892, United States</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Hospital</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>VA Palo Alto</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>3801 Miranda Ave, Palo Alto, CA 94304, United States</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United States of America</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This study will examine if there is a benefit of an online intervention for persons with bipolar diagnoses, and what components appear to be useful. Specifically, the study will examine (1) whether exposure to the MoodSwings 2.0 intervention results in decreased depression and manic symptoms, as measured by the Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) and Young Mania Rating Scale (YMRS) respectively; and (2) whether there is an association between graduated levels of involvement (Level 1, 2, or 3) and resulting improvement. We expect that those assigned to the control condition (Level 1) will have fewer positive outcomes than those in Level 2 or 3. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.moodswings.net.au</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes>This trial is recruiting internationally, with coordinating centres located in Geelong, Australia and Palo Alto, United States. There are no geographical restrictions for participants.</publicnotes>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Barwon Health Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Kitchener House
Ryrie Street
Geelong, VIC, 3220</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/10/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/11/VICBH/47</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/09/2011</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Michael Berk</name>
      <address>IMPACT SRC - Kitchener House
Ryrie Street, Geelong, VIC, 3220</address>
      <phone>+613 4215 3330</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>MIKEBE@BarwonHealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Emma Gliddon</name>
      <address>IMPACT SRC - Kitchener House
Ryrie Street, Geelong, VIC, 3220</address>
      <phone>+613 4215 3311</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>info@moodswings.net.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Emma Gliddon</name>
      <address>IMPACT SRC - Kitchener House
Ryrie Street, Geelong, VIC, 3220</address>
      <phone>+613 4215 3311</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>EGLIDD@BarwonHealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Emma Gliddon</name>
      <address>IMPACT SRC - Kitchener House
Ryrie Street, Geelong, VIC, 3220</address>
      <phone>+613 4215 3311</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>EGLIDD@BarwonHealth.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>