<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362958">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/08/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/08/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000922875</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Computerised psychoeductional intervention for inflammatory bowel disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Effect of a computerised psychoeducational intervention on quality of life in people with inflammatory bowel disease.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1133-9642</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CCBT4IBD</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Inflammatory Bowel Disease</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Oral and Gastrointestinal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Inflammatory bowel disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The computerised psychoeducation will cover a number of topics: goal setting; thoughts feelings and behaviours; avoiding avoidance; coping styles; diet; effective communication; pain management; and relapse prevention. Patients will be given up to 12 weeks to complete the 8 one hour sessions; this is to allow for the effects of holidays, busy schedules, etc. to be nullified by people being given opportunities to catch up. Cognitive behavioural therapy techniques are used as part of the intervention.</interventions>
    <comparator>Treatment as usual. Those allocated to the treatment as usual group will receive usual care (i.e. not have any treatment withheld aside from the computerised psychoeducation).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Inflammatory Bowel Disease Quality of Life will be measured using the Inflammatory Bowel Disease Questionnaire (IBDQ).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention (12 weeks), 6 months post intervention, and 12 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety will be measured using the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention (12 weeks), 6 months post intervention, and 12 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression will be measured using the Hospital Anxiety and Depression (HADS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention (12 weeks), 6 months post intervention, and 12 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medical Costs will be measured at 12 months by examining patient notes and allocating amounts to outpatient clinic visits, hospital stays, number of procedures, medication use, and so forth.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Coping will be measured using the Brief COPE and the IBD Cope.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention (12 weeks), 6 months post intervention, and 12 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generic quality of life will be measured using the SF-12.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, post intervention (12 weeks), 6 months post intervention, and 12 months post intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients will be prescreened to see whether they meet the inclusion criteria of the study, which includes age 18-65, IBD diagnosis, willingness to participate, adequate computer literacy.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Severe disease, significant cognitive deficit, previous exposure to Cognitive Behavioural Therapy, and severe physical or psychiatric comorbidity.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients will be approached in person and asked whether they are interested in participating in the study. They will also be screened to ensure they meet inclusion/exclusion criteria. If they show interest and meet the criteria, then they will be presented with an information sheet and consent form and have the study explained to them in lay terms. The consent form will give them an option to either opt in or opt out of the study. They will have the option of consenting at that time or deciding later.
Patients will be screened before they are randomized which means that when the decision is made regarding their inclusion/exclusion, the person making this decision will be  unaware of which group the subject will be allocated to.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer program provided by John Pearson (biostatistian) will be used to randomise the subjects</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/11/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Otago, Christchurch</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Otago, Christchurch</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 4345
Christchurch 8140</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Todd Foundation</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Postal Address: PO Box 3142

Street Address: L14, Todd Building, 95 Customhouse Quay

Wellington 6011

New Zealand</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In this study, we will be randomizing 238 inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) patients to either an 8 session course of a computerised psychoeducational intervention or treatment as usual (TAU). The psychoeducation will cover a number of topics: goal setting; thoughts feelings and behaviours; avoiding avoidance; coping styles; diet; effective communication; pain management; and relapse prevention. Patients will be given up to 12 weeks to complete the 8 sessions; this is to allow for the effects of holidays, busy schedules, etc. to be nullified by people being given opportunities to catch up. We will be recruiting more patients into psychoeducation (n=126) than TAU (n=112) because we have been told by researchers who have done a similar study in Adelaide that we can expect more people to drop out of the computerised psychoeducation group. We will be measuring anxiety, depression, quality of life (QOL), coping styles, and IBD symptoms at baseline and obtaining demographic information (with patients consent) from the Concierto Patient Management System. We will also be measuring anxiety, depression, QOL, coping styles, and IBD symptoms post intervention in the psychoeducation group and at the 12-week equivalent in the TAU group. In addition, we will measure patient perceptions of the computerised psychoeducation program by asking such questions as whether they found the computerised psychoeducation relevant, valid, and effective. Perhaps our most important measure will come at 12 months post-intervention, when we will be asking patients about the abovementioned variables and also measuring whether direct medical costs have been reduced through less outpatient visits and hospitalizations in the psychoeducation group.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Health and Disability Ethics Committee (HDEC)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/08/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andrew McCombie</name>
      <address>PO Box 4345
Department of Medicine
University of Otago
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3786305</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mccombieandrew@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andrew McCombie</name>
      <address>PO Box 4345
Department of Medicine
University of Otago
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3786305</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mccombieandrew@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Andrew McCombie</name>
      <address>PO Box 4345
Department of Medicine
University of Otago
Christchurch 8140</address>
      <phone>+64 3 3786305</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 3640935</fax>
      <email>mccombieandrew@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>