<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335077">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>22/01/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/02/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000096055</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Circuit class therapy for rehabilitation after stroke. A pragmatic randomised controlled trial (CIRCIT).</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Is circuit class therapy more effective than usual care over 5 days or usual care over 7 days a week in improving six minute walk test performance in stroke survivors receiving inpatient rehabilitation after stroke?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1113-4627</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CIRCIT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Stroke</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ischaemic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Stroke</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Haemorrhagic</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This is a 3-armed randomised controlled trial (RCT) to compare two methods of providing an increased amount of physical therapy during stroke rehabilitation to usual care.
Intervention 1 = Circuit class therapy. Participants will receive a target of 3 hours per day (5 days a week) of group circuit class therapy aimed at improving mobility and upper limb function. Circuit class therapy groups will be run with a staff to participant ratio of between 1:4 and 1:6. Participants in this arm of the trial will not receive individual (one-to-one) treatment sessions. 
Intervention 2 = 7-day per week therapy. Participants in this arm of the trial will receive usual care physical therapy over 7-days per week. Active therapy time will be capped at 90 minutes per day.

Control arm - usual care (see further description below)

As the trial aims to compare different models of service delivery, the interventions will be provided for the duration of the participants' inpatient stay (average 6 weeks).</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care physical therapy. Participants in this arm of the trial will receive usual care physical therapy, 5-days a week, capped at 90 minutes of active therapy time per day. Participants will receive usual care therapy for the duration of their inpatient stay (average 6 weeks).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking ability (Six minute walk test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 4 weeks after admission to rehabilitation and at 3 and 6 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Walking ability (timed 10 metre walk and Functional Ambulation Classification)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 4 weeks from start of rehabilitation and 3 and 6 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Ability to perform Activities of Daily Living (Functional Independence Measure)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 4 weeks from start of rehabilitation and 3 and 6 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Upper limb function (Wolf Motor Function Test)</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 and 4 weeks from start of rehabilitation and 3 and 6 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stroke Impact Scale (mobility section)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks from start of rehabilitation and 3 and 6 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life (Assessment of quality of life instrument)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks from start of rehabilitation and 3 and 6 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Participant satisfaction (Hopsat questionnaire)</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks from start of rehabilitation and 3 and 6 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Complications (including adverse events). Medical records will be audited to determine the number and nature of all adverse events and new medical conditions experienced while in hospital. These will include (but are not limited to) worsening of stroke symtoms, falls (inlcuding those that do not result in injury), angina, myocardial infarction or chest infections.</outcome>
      <timepoint>4 weeks from start of rehabilitation and 3 and 6 months post-stroke</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Length of hospital stay. This will be taken as the number of days between admission to rehabilitation and discharge from rehabilitation (as documented in the medical records).</outcome>
      <timepoint>at discharge from inpatient rehabilitation</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Resource utilisation. Prospective data will be collected on the amount of therapist time provided to all participants as well as any other related costs such as equipment purchases etc.</outcome>
      <timepoint>During inpatient rehabilitation data will be prospectively collected regarding costs associated with providing the interventions.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>People admitted to an inpatient rehabilitation facility with a diagnosis of stroke.
A motor Functional Independence Measure (FIM) score of between 38 and 62 points at admission to rehabilitation</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>People who required physical assistance from another person to walk prior to their hospital admission.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be allocated to groups via a phone-in centralised system off-site to the data collection sites.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated sequence generation, stratified by site.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Nil applicable</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/07/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>25/06/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>282</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Susan Hillier</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471 
Adelaide, SA 5001</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Dr Coralie English</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471 
Adelaide, SA 5001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Professor Maria Crotty</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Head of Department, Rehabilitation and Aged Care
Flinders University
PO Box 2100
Adelaide SA 5001</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Leonie Segal</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471 
Adelaide, SA 5001</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Professor Julie Bernhardt</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>National Stroke Research Institute
Neurosciences Building Level 1 Austin Health
300 Waterdale Rd
Heidelberg Heights 
VIC 3081</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Adrian Esterman</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471 
Adelaide, SA 5001</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Loss of independence is common following stroke, and may lead to reduced quality of life. We will investigate if an increased amount of physical rehabilitation following stroke leads to improvements in walking ability, arm function and independence. Two ways of providing an increased amount of physical rehabilitation will be compared to usual care to find out which leads to improved physical mobility and how they compare economically. 
The key hypotheses are:
1. Compared to usual care therapy (5 days a week), group circuit class therapy (provided 5 days a week for 3 hours per day) will lead to improvements in walking function and mobility.
2. Compared to usual care therapy (5 days a week) providing physical therapy over 7 days a week will lead to improvements in walking function and mobility.
3. Compared to 7-day a week therapy, group circuit class therapy (5 days a week) will lead to improvements in walking function and mobility.
4. Group circuit class therapy will be more cost-effective than 7-day week therapy.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Hillier S, English C, Crotty M, Segal L, Bernhardt J and Esterman A. (2011) "Circuit class or seven day therapy for increasing intensity of rehabilitation after stroke. Protocol of the CIRCIT trial." International Journal of Stroke 6:560-565 doi: 10.1111/j.1747-4949.2011.00686.x. 

Kaur G, English C, Hillier S (2013) Physiotherapists systematically overestimate the amount of time stroke survivors spend engaged in active therapy during inpatient rehabilitation: an observational study. Journal of Physiotherapy 59: 45-51 

English C, Hillier S, Kaur G and Hundertmark L Stroke survivors spend more time in active task practice, but similar time in walking practice when physiotherapy is provided in circuit classes versus individual therapy sessions. Journal of Physiotherapy 60:50-54 http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jphys.2013.12.006 

Circles within CIRCIT South Australian Rehabilitation Research Forum, Adelaide March 15th 2013 (sponsored by the South Australian Department of Health Statewide Rehabilitation Network)

Circuit class therapy and 7-day a week therapy. Are they effective?  Australian Physiotherapy Association National Neurology Conference, Melbourne October 17-19th 2013

English C, Hillier S, Bernhardt J, Crotty M, Esterman A and Segal L Circuit Class Therapy and 7-Day Week Therapy for Increasing Rehabilitation Intensity of Therapy (CIRCIT). World Congress of NeuroRehabilitation, April 9-12 Istanbul

English C, Hillier S, Kaur G and Hundertmark L Do stroke survivors spend more time in active task practice in circuit class therapy session versus individual physiotherapy sessions? Australian Physiotherapy Association National Neurology Conference, Melbourne October 17-19th 2013 

English C, Hillier S Bernhardt J, Crotty, M, Esterman A, and Segal L Circuit class therapy and 7-day a week physiotherapy services both increase dosage of physiotherapy and patient activity levels in rehabilitation settings - Early lessons from the CIRCIT trial. Australasian Faculty of Rehabilitation Medicine Conference Sept 17-19 2013

Bennett L, Hillier S, Luker J, English C Stroke survivors perspectives on 2 novel models of inpatient rehabilitation:  7 day a week usual care therapy or 5 day a week circuit class therapy South Australian Rehabilitation Research Forum, Adelaide March 15th 2013

Harling R, Kaur G, English C, Hillier S, Dempsey R Circuit Class therapy in real world clinical practice. Is it as intensive as we think? South Australian Rehabilitation Research Forum, Adelaide March 15th 2013

English C, Hillier S, Crotty M, Segal L, Bernhardt J and Esterman A. Circuit class therapy for rehabilitation after stroke. Protocol of the CIRCIT trial. International Journal of Stroke 5(1) September 2010 p 15</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of South Australia Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research and Innovation Services
University of South Australia
Mawson Lakes Campus
Mawson Lakes Boulevard
Mawson Lakes SA 5095</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>11/01/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>P379/09</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Flinders Clinical Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Room 2A221 
Flinders Medical Centre 
Bedford Park SA 5042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/12/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>1/09/0377</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Susan Hillier</name>
      <address>School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471
Adelaide 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83022544</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83022766</fax>
      <email>susan.hillier@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Susan Hillier</name>
      <address>School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471
Adelaide 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83022544</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83022766</fax>
      <email>susan.hillier@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Susan Hillier</name>
      <address>School of Health Sciences
University of South Australia
PO Box 2471
Adelaide 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83022544</phone>
      <fax>+61 8 83022766</fax>
      <email>susan.hillier@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Susan Hillier</name>
      <address>School of Health Sciences, University of South Australia
PO Box 2471
Adelaide, SA 5001</address>
      <phone>+61 8 83022544</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>susan.hillier@unisa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>