<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="335718">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>14/07/2010</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/10/2010</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12610000880044</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Efficacy and safety of artemether-lumefantrine and dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria, and chloroquine for P.vivax in Myit Kyi Nar Township, Kachin State, Myanmar</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Efficacy and safety of artemether-lumefantrine and dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of falciparum malaria, and chloroquine for P.vivax  in Kachin State, Myanmar</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>malaria</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>One arm propective evaluation with: (i) artemether-lumefantrine and (ii) dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated  P. falciparum malaria; and (iii) with chloroquine for the treatment of  Plasmodium vivax malaria. 

Dose regimen: 
Artemether-lumefantrine tablets (Tablet containing artemether 20 mg/lumefantrine 120 mg): 6-dose regimen of artemether-lumefantrince twice a day for 3 days according to the following weight bands:5-14 kg body weight (bw): 1 tablet; 15-24 kg body weight (bw): 2 tablets; 25-34 kg body weight (bw): 3 tablets, and greater than or equal to 35 kg body weight (bw): 4 tablets. All treatment will be orally taken tablets.

Dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine tablets (tablet containing dihydroartemisinin 40 mg/piperaquine phophate 320 mg):  2-2.4/16-19.2 mg/kg once a day for 3 days according to the following weight bands:11-18 kg body weight (bw): 1 tablet; 19-29 kg body weight (bw): 1 1/2 tablets; 30-39 kg body weight (bw): 2 tablets and greater than or equal to 40 kg body weight (bw): 3 tablets. All treatment will be orally taken tablets.

Chloroquine phophate tablets (tablet contains 150 mg base): 25 mg/kg body weight ober 3 consecutive days (10 mg/kg body weight on day 0, 10 mg/kg body weight (bw) on day 1 and 5 mg/kg body weight (bw) on day 2). All treatment will be orally taken tablets.</interventions>
    <comparator>One arms prospective evaluation of clinical and parasitological responses to directly observed treatment for uncomplicated falciparum malaria and vivax malaria</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of artemether-lumefantrine and of dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine  treatment failures (early treatment failure+late clinical failure+late parasitological failure).  

Enrolled patients will be assessed for parasitological (using microscopy) and clinical responses during the 28 days follow-up and treatmnt outcomes will be classified according to the latest WHO protocol (http://www.who.int/malaria/publications/atoz/9789241597531/en/index.html).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 28 day following treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of chloroquine treatment failure (early treatment failure+late clinical failure+late parasitological failure).  Enrolled patients will be assessed for parasitological (using microscopy) and clinical responses during the 28 days follow-up and treatmnt outcomes will be classified according to the latest WHO protocol (http://www.who.int/malaria/publications/atoz/9789241597531/en/index.html).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 28 day following treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>% of adverse events in the artesunate+sulfadoxine/ pyrimethamine, artemether-lumefantrine and chloroquine treated groups. All patients will be asked routinely about previous symptoms and about symptoms that have emerged since the previous follow-up visit. All adverse events will be recorded on the case report form.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At 28 day following treatment</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>*age between 6 years inclusive and above except females aged 12-17 year old inclusive;
*mono-infection with P. falciparum detected by microscopy (parasitaemia of 500-100,000/microliter asexual forms) or P. vivax detected by microscopy (parasitaemia &gt; 250/µl asexual forms)
*presence of axillary temperature equal to or more than 37.5 degrees centigrade or history of fever during the past 24 hours;
*ability to swallow oral medication;
*ability and willingness to comply with the study protocol for the duration of the study and to comply with the study visit schedule; and
*informed consent from the patient or from a parent or guardian in the case of children.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>6</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>60</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>*presence signs of severe falciparum malaria according to the definitions of World Health Organization (WHO);
*mixed or mono-infection with another Plasmodium species detected by microscopy;
*presence of severe malnutrition (defined as a child whose growth standard below 3 z-score, has symmetrical oedema involving at least the feet or has a mid-upper arm circumference less than 110 mm);
*presence of febrile conditions due to diseases other than malaria (e.g. measles, acute lower respiratory tract infection, severe diarrhoea with dehydration) or other known underlying chronic or severe diseases (e.g. cardiac, renal and hepatic diseases, Human Immuno Deficiency Virus /Auto Immune Deficiency Syndrome(HIV/AIDS);
*regular medication, which may interfere with antimalarial pharmacokinetics;
*history of hypersensitivity reactions or contraindications to any of the medicine(s) being tested or used as alternative treatment(s); and
*a positive pregnancy test or breastfeeding;
*unable to or unwilling to take a pregnancy test or contraceptives.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Potential patients will be screened for inclusion/exclusion criteria. Once the patient meets all the enrolment criteria and he/she or a parent/guardian (in case of children) consented to participate in the study, the patient will be recruited in to the study. All antimalarial treatment will be given by a study team member under supervision. Thereafter, patients are required to undergo regular clinical reassessment. Blood films for parasite counts will be made on days 2, 3 and 7 and then weekly for the remainder of the follow-up period, i.e. on days 14, 21, and 28.
As it is a nonrandomised trial the first treatment regime ( coartem) will be given up to the required sample number(80 patients) followed by administering dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine phosphate regime to another group of (80 patients).</concealment>
    <sequence>This is a one arm prospective study in which all eligible patients are given test drug.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>3/09/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>12/11/2011</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>240</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Myanmar</country>
      <state>Kachin State</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Department of Medical Research (Upper Myanmar), Ministry of Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sithar village, 
Ward Number(16)
East of Ani Sa Khan Airport 
Pyin Oo Lwin township (Postal code 05061)
Mandalay Division, 
Myanmar</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Myanmar</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Medical Research (Upper Myanmar), Ministry of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Sithar village, 
Ward Number(16)
East of Ani Sa Khan Airport 
Pyin Oo Lwin township( Postal code 05061)
Mandalay Division, 
Myanmar</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Myanmar</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Mekong Malaria Project ( through World Health) Organization)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>World Health Organization (WHO) Country Office
12A Floor, Traders Hotel,
223 Sule Pagoda Road, KyauktadaTownship,
Postal code 11182, Yangon, Myanmar</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Myanmar</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other Collaborative groups</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Department of Medical Research (Upper Myanmar), Ministry of Health</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Sithar village, 
Ward Number(16)
East of Ani Sa Khan Airport 
Pyin Oo Lwin township( Postal code 05061)
Mandalay Division, 
Myanmar</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Myanmar</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Title: Efficacy and safety of artemether-lumefantrine and dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria, and chloroquine for P.vivax in  Myit Kyi Nar Township, Kachin State.
Background: Therapeutic efficacy studies will be done in in  Myit Kyi Nar Township, Kachin State in Myanmar to assess the efficacy and safety of artemether-lumefantrine and dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria, and chloroquine for the treatment of  Plasmodium vivax.  

Objective: to evaluate the efficacy and safety of artemether-lumefantrine and dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine for the treatment of uncomplicated falciparum malaria, and chloroquine for Plasmodium vivax in Myit Kyi Nar Township, Kachin State.

Methods: The participants will be febrile people above 6 years with confirmed uncomplicated P. falciparum or P. vivax infection. Patients will be treated with artemether-lumefantrine twice a day over 3 days or dihydroartemisinin-piperaquine over 3 days, or chloroquine daily for 3 days. Clinical and parasitological parameters will be monitored over a 28-day follow-up period to evaluate drug efficacy. 

The results of this study will be used to assist the Ministry of Health of Myanmar in assessing the current national treatment guidelines for uncomplicated P. falciparum and vivax malaria.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>No trial related presentations/publications are done</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethical Review Committee , World Health Organization (ERC, WHO)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>20, Avenue Appia, 1211 geneva, 27.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>2/07/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>RPC405</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>9/06/2010</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Switzerland</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Etical Committee of Department of Medical Research (Upper Myanmar), Ministry of Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Sithar village, 
Ward Number(16)
East of Ani Sa Khan Airport 
Pyin Oo Lwin township( Postal code 05061)
Mandalay Division, 
Myanmar

( Division is similar to state/province)</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/05/2010</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>7/Ethics/DMRUM/2010</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Myanmar</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Khin Lin</name>
      <address>Director/Head
Parasitology Research Division
Department of Medical Research (Upper Myanmar)
Sithar village, 
Ward Number(16)
East of Ani Sa Khan Airport 
Pyin Oo Lwin township( Postal code 05061)
Mandalay Division
Myanmar</address>
      <phone>+95-085-50438</phone>
      <fax>+95-085-90435</fax>
      <email>lin.khin@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Myanmar</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Khin Lin</name>
      <address>Director/Head
Parasitology Research Division
Department of Medical Research (Upper Myanmar)
Sithar village, 
Ward Number(16)
East of Ani Sa Khan Airport 
Pyin Oo Lwin township( Postal code 05061)
Mandalay Division
Myanmar</address>
      <phone>+95-085-50438</phone>
      <fax>+95-085-90435</fax>
      <email>lin.khin@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Myanmar</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Khin Lin</name>
      <address>Director/Head
Parasitology Research Division
Department of Medical Research (Upper Myanmar)
Sithar village, 
Ward Number(16)
East of Ani Sa Khan Airport 
Pyin Oo Lwin township( Postal code 05061)
Mandalay Division
Myanmar</address>
      <phone>+95-085-50438</phone>
      <fax>+95-085-50435</fax>
      <email>lin.khin@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Myanmar</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Khin Lin</name>
      <address>Director/Head Parasitology Research Division Department of Medical Research (Upper Myanmar) Sithar village, Ward Number(16) East of Ani Sa Khan Airport Pyin Oo Lwin township( Postal code 05061) Mandalay Division Myanmar
</address>
      <phone>+95-085-50438</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>lin.khin@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Myanmar</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>