<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="368163">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/03/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/03/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000295549</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of a companion robot for people with dementia and their carers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of the companion robot Paro on behavioural and psychological outcomes in people with dementia and their carers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1168-1996</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dementia</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Caregiver burden and quality of life </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Neurological</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Dementias</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Paro is a Japanese robot designed to have the positive effects of a pet without the demands. Paro is an advanced interactive robot developed by the Intelligent Systems Research Institute (ISRI), a leading Japanese industrial automation pioneer. Paro is modelled after a baby Canadian harp seal and is covered in white artificial fur. It weighs approximately 2.5 kg. Paro has four senses; sight, sound, balance, and touch meaning that Paro responds to contact, as well as to other stimuli in its environment by moving or imitating the noises of a baby harp seal.  Paro operates by using the three elements; its internal states, sensory information from its sensors and its own diurnal rhythm to carry out various activities during its interaction with people. 
Companion robots such as Paro draw on the principles of animal therapy and research conducted predominantly in Japan has found that Paro improves patients moods, facilitates social interactions and in general leads to higher quality of life for people in retirement care, particularly those with dementia.

We propose to conduct a randomized controlled trial with 30 participants and their caregivers at an aged-care facility with eleven Paro robots to investigate effects on behavioural, neuroendocrine, social and psychological outcomes. Participants will be randomly assigned to the control group  or to the Paro group using a random list generator. Participants in the intervention group will interact with the robots over 3 months, in small groups at the care facility and individually, at home. Paro group sessions will consist of a maximum of four residents to one Paro robot, which has been found to be the optimum group size.

Two researchers will run 1 hour daily sessions with Paro at the daycare centre, as participants attend the daycare on various days of the week, it is expected that participants will interact with Paro between 1-3 hours per week. In addition, participants will be given the option of taking Paro home, where Paro will be available to participants 24/7, to use when needed.
The interaction sessions will involve verbal communication, patting and playing with Paro. The researchers will monitor sessions with Paro and also provide instruction to caregivers concerning how to use Paro.  Adherence to sessions will be monitored by researchers taking a register of participant attendance. 


</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants in the control group will partake in normal activities as scheduled by the aged care facility. Normal activities typically involve school children visits, games and crafts sessions.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Agitation as measured by the Neuropsychiatric Inventory, Cohen-Mansfield Agitation Index, observations of behaviour during sessions</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver burden as measured by the Zarit Burden Interview</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver quality of life as measure by the World Health Organisation Quality of Life Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cortisol from both patients and their caregivers as measured by salivary and hair cortisol samples, respectively. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Hair cortisol will be taken from caregivers at baseline, 6 weeks and at 12 weeks after intervention commencement. Salivary cortisol will be taken before and after control and intervention sessions for individuals with dementia. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient's cognitive functioning as measured by Addenbrooke's Cognitive Examination-III (ACE-III)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient's level of depression as measured by the Cornell Scale of Depression in Dementia (CSDD)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient and caregiver blood pressure measurements as measured using a digitial blood pressure monitor </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement. Also before and after control and intervention sessions for individuals with dementia. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Caregiver perceived stress as measured by the Perceived Stress Scale </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceived respect (Question designed specifically for this study: How much do you feel the care recipient treats you with respect)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, and at 6 and 12 weeks after intervention commencement </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alpha amylase from saliva samples</outcome>
      <timepoint>Before and after control and intervention sessions for individuals with dementia. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Individuals who have attended the Selwyn Foundation dementia daycare Anchorage unit for at least 3 months and their caregivers 
Fluent in English
Informed consent must be obtained  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>physically unable to interact with Paro 
Non-English speaker</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Selwyn Foundation have a list of all the people who attend dementia daycare. Letters will be sent to the caregivers by Selwyn Foundation to invite them and their relative with dementia to participate in the study. They will also be contacted either face to face or by telephone to ask if they and their relative would be interested in taking part. 
If they are interested in participating researchers will obtain written informed consent. As people with dementia are unable to give informed consent, consent will be obtained from the caregiver as their enduring power of attorney.

Participants will be randomly assigned to the control group or to the Paro group using a random list generator. On an average day at the centre there will be about 4 people in the control group and 4 in the intervention group.

Allocation concealment will be ensured through delivery of randomisation using sealed, opaque envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation using a random list generator created by computer software </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We previously found an effect size d=1.15 of Paro on social behaviour in rest home and hospital residents. Using a two-tailed t-test, choosing d=1.15, alpha = .05 and power of .80, we would need 13 participants in each group.

ANCOVAs will be performed to compare changes between baseline and follow-up measures of each of the outcome measures with corresponding baseline scores entered as covariates.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>25/03/2015</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>25/03/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>30</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Elizabeth Broadbent</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>AUCKLAND HOSPITAL
Level 12, Room 599-12005
PARK ROAD
Auckland 1023
GRAFTON</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Auckland Faculty Research Development Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Physical address:
FMHS Research Office
Administration
Level 1, Building 505
85 Park Road
Grafton

Postal Address:
Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences
The University of Auckland
Private Bag 92019
Auckland 1142
New Zealand </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Chih-Hsin Liang</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>AUCKLAND HOSPITAL
Level 12, Room 599-12004
PARK ROAD
Auckland 1023
GRAFTON</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Bruce MacDonald</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>UNIVERSITY OF AUCKLAND
903
Level 3, Room 903-342
368 KHYBER PASS
Auckland 1023
NEWMARKET</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr. Mark Fisher </othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Clinical Head / Consultant Psychiatrist
Koropiko  Mental Health Services for Older People Memory Team
ECT Service
Middlemore Hospital, Otahuhu
Private Bag 93311, Auckland 1640</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Isabell Piroth</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>AUCKLAND HOSPITAL
Level 12, Room 599-12004
PARK ROAD
Auckland 1023
GRAFTON</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of the study is to further investigate the benefits of the companion robot, Paro,  for people with dementia.

The specific objectives are:
-To investigate whether interacting with companion robots can reduce cognitive, functional, depressive, and behavioural problems in people with dementia.
-To investigate whether companion robots can reduce caregiver stress.
-To investigate whether interacting with companion robots can reduce stress hormones in people with dementia and their caregivers.
-To investigate whether companion robots can reduce the need for medication in people with dementia. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Auckland Human Participants Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Post Award Services

Research Office
Level 10, Building 620
49 Symonds Street
Grafton
Auckland 1010</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>18/11/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>013067</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>24/09/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/368163-Ethics Approval Letter.pdf</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Elizabeth Broadbent</name>
      <address>AUCKLAND HOSPITAL
Level 12, Room 599-12005
PARK ROAD
Auckland 1023
GRAFTON
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+64 9 923 6756</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>e.broadbent@auckland.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Chih-Hsin (Amy) Liang</name>
      <address>AUCKLAND HOSPITAL
Level 12, Room 599-12004
PARK ROAD
Auckland 1023
GRAFTON
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+642102298861</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>clia679@aucklanduni.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Miss</title>
      <name>Chih-Hsin (Amy Liang)</name>
      <address>AUCKLAND HOSPITAL
Level 12, Room 599-12004
PARK ROAD
Auckland 1023
GRAFTON
New Zealand</address>
      <phone>+642102298861</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>clia679@aucklanduni.ac.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>