<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365599">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>10/01/2014</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/01/2014</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12614000059662</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Teriparatide for Pelvic Fracture Healing</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Single-blinded, pilot randomised controlled trial examining the efficacy of teriparatide in fracture after minimal trauma pelvic fracture</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoporotic pelvic fracture</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoporosis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Injuries and Accidents</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Fractures</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Teriparatide (recombinant human 1-34 parathyroid hormone) - 20 micrograms subcutaneously daily for 8 weeks in addition to standard care

Adherence will be monitored by having the patient return any the injection device after each four week period (one device has sufficient teripartide for 4 weeks' treatment)</interventions>
    <comparator>Standard care (analgesia, physiotherapy)</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in the rates of fracture healing on computer tomorgraph (CT) scan.
Fracture healing will be defined as: any evidence of bony callous bridging (either disorganised, cloud-like or mature, remodelled bony callous) at the fracture line (at any pelvic fracture site) as judged by two independent, blinded radiologists.  Where there is an initial inconsistency between the two radiologists, discussion will be held between them, until a consensus can be reached.</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The degree of immature bony callous bridging at the fracture line on CT scan, according to the following criteria:
1. No evidence of disorganised, cloud-like bony callous (woven bone) bridging
2. Bridging across less than 25% of the fracture line with disorganised, cloud-like bony callous
3. Bridging across 25  50% of the fracture line with disorganised, cloud-like bony callous
4. Bridging across 50% - 75% of the fracture line with disorganised, cloud-like bony callous
5. Bridging across 75% - 100% of the fracture line with disorganised, cloud-like bony callus
</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The degree of mature, remodelled bony callous bridging at the fracture line on CT scan according to the following criteria:
1. Mature, remodelled bony callous (lamellar bone) bridging across less than 25% of the fracture line
2. Mature, remodelled bony callous bridging across 25  50% of the fracture line
3. Mature, remodelled bony callous bridging across 50-75% of the fracture line
4. Bridging across 75% - 100% of the fracture line with mature, remodelled bony callus
</outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in functional outcomes using Short Physical Performance Battery</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8 and 16 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in pain scores on a numeric graphic scale (0-10)
</outcome>
      <timepoint>4, 8 and 16 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in patient Quality of Life using the (AQOL-6) instrument </outcome>
      <timepoint>8 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total duration of hospital admission</outcome>
      <timepoint>16 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital resource utilisation as measured by diagnostic related group (DRG) categories</outcome>
      <timepoint>16 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in proportion of patients with an increase in level of care (i.e. home to residential care, or low level to high level care)</outcome>
      <timepoint>16 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Difference in proportion in patients requiring time in inpatient rehabilitation facility</outcome>
      <timepoint>16 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Differences in mortality rates</outcome>
      <timepoint> 16 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effective of teriparatide over standard care

This will be assessed with the use of a Markov model to calculate an incremental cost-effectiveness ratio for teriparatide over standard care.  The cost will be determined from the perspective of hospital utilisation (as outlined above, using DRG data) with quality adjusted life years (QALYs) saved calculated using quality of life data from the AQOL-6 instrument.</outcome>
      <timepoint>16 weeks</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Pelvic fracture confirmed on plain x-ray 
Minimal trauma fracture
Postmenopausal women or men age greater than or equal to 65 years
Non-operative management 
Ability to self-administer teripartide injection, or have a carer able and willing to do so
Pre-morbidly able to mobilise without human assistance (i.e. not bed or wheel chair bound)
Capacity to provide informed consent
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>65</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Potential contraindication to teriparatide therapy - diagnosed hyperparathyroidism or hypercalcaemia, patients who are at increased baseline risk for osteosarcoma, such as those with Pagets disease of bone, history of prior radiation therapy, or unexplained elevation of alkaline phosphatase, patients with pre-existing malignancies, renal stones, gout, or renal insufficiency (glomerular filration rate less than 30mL/min, as determined by Cockroft-Gault), previous treatment with teriparatide
Participant who is terminally ill
A fracture other than a pelvic fracture
Active malignancy
Pathological fracture
Significant impairment of liver synthetic dysfunction (prolonged prothrombin time, elevated bilirubin) or marked derangements of liver enzymes (aspartate aminotransferase [AST], alanine aminotransferase [ALT], gamma-glutaryl transferase [GGT] or alkaline phosphatise [ALP] greater than twice the upper limit of normal)
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Investigators involved in the assessment of outcomes will be blinded to the group allocation.  Only a research nurse and a single investigator (the investigator that will perform the education of teripartide injection and follow up) will be aware of the patient’s treatment allocation.

Allocation concealment will be performed by an unblinded investigator or the unblinded research nurse using sealed opaque envelopes.  These investigators will not be involved in any of the outcome assessments.  </concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation will occur using a random number generator within Microsoft Excel, producing 40 random numbers.  Patients assigned an even number will be allocated to group 1 (treatment group) and odd numbers to group 2 (standard care).  Randomisation will occur on a 1:1 basis.  </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Statistical analysis will be performed on an intention-to-treat basis.  
Patient characteristics will be summarised and compared between the intervention and control group. The primary outcome will be analysed using Pearsons Chi-squared (or Fishers exact tests, if required) as will other categorical variables.  Continuous variables will be compared using t-tests (for normally distributed data) and Wilcoxon rank sum or Kruskal-Wallis (for non-parametric data). 
Pre-specified subgroup analysis will occur, with each group divided into those that had had any anti-resportive osteoporotic treatment in the preceding twelve months and those with no previously anti-resportive osteoporotic treatment, or treatment greater than twelve months prior.
AQOL-6 data will be used to calculate differences in participant group utility (mean), which, along with health care cost data, will be used in Markov modelling to calculate an incremental cost-effectiveness ratio for teriparatide over standard care.  Sensitivity analysis will be used to assess for the amount of uncertainy in the model.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>10/02/2014</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>19/09/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>26/11/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>5</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Stopped early</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>11/04/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis>No data analysis planned</dataanalysis>
    <withdrawnreason>Lack of funding/staff/facilities,Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Brisbane &amp; Womens Hospital - Herston</hospital>
    <hospital>Greenslopes Private Hospital - Greenslopes</hospital>
    <hospital>Toowoomba Hospital - Toowoomba</hospital>
    <postcode>4029 - Royal Brisbane Hospital</postcode>
    <postcode>4120 - Greenslopes</postcode>
    <postcode>4350 - Toowoomba</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Butterfield Street
Herston, Qld, 4029</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Foundation</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Butterfield Street
Herston, Qld, 4029</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Teripartide is a medication that works on cells within the bone (called osteoblasts) to help form new bone which is
approved in Australia to treat osteoporosis. A previous, but flawed study has shown some promising results with the
use of parathyroid hormone (a medication very similar to teriparatide). There is also some inconsistent evidence of
improved fracture healing after wrist fractures. Preclinical
studies in rats have also shown some evidence of faster
fracture healing.
We will perform a small, pilot, randomised trial assessing the effect of 8 weeks of teriparatide on fracture healing.
We will recruit up to 40 participants who have had a minimal trauma pelvic fracture, who would otherwise undergo conservative management, who can either selfadminister or have a carer able and willing to administer daily subcutaneous injections for 8 weeks. Each participant will be randomised to either the treatment (20 micrograms
per day of teriparatide via subcutaneous injection) or standard care (pain relief, physiotherapy).
Our primary aim is to demonstrate (assessed on computer tomography scan) that a larger proportion of participants
will have demonstrable cortical bridging (fracture healing) at the fracture site after 8 weeks of treatment. Secondary
aims will be to demonstrate improvements in pain, functional status and quality of life after 4, 8 and 16 weeks.
This study will guide us in the design of a larger, multicentre
trial, if the initial results show promise.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Butterfield Street
Herston, Qld, 4029</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/QRBW/200</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Donovan</name>
      <address>Internal Medicine and Aged Care
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston, Qld, 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter_donovan@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Donovan</name>
      <address>Internal Medicine and Aged Care
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston, Qld, 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter_donovan@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Peter Donovan</name>
      <address>Internal Medicine and Aged Care
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston, Qld, 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter_donovan@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Peter Donovan</name>
      <address>Internal Medicine and Aged Care
Royal Brisbane and Women's Hospital
Butterfield Street
Herston, Q, 4029</address>
      <phone>+61 7 3646 8111</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>peter_donovan@health.qld.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>