<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370542">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/04/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>3/06/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000737437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Regression of resilient neovessels with monthly anti-Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor (VEGF) treatment in laser treated proliferative diabetic retinopathy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Regression of resilient neovessels with monthly anti-VEGF treatment in laser treated proliferative diabetic retinopathy</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>none</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>diabetic retinopathy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>proliferative diabetic retinopathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>monthly intravitreal injection of 0.05 cc or 1.25 mg of Bevacizumab by a retina specialist, the intravitreal injection is done in a minor operating room.  After scrubbing the eyelids with betadine, and application of a sterile speculum, one drop of Cebesine 0.4% is instilled to ensure anesthesia.  at 3.5 mm from limbus in the inferotemporal quadrant 0.05 cc of 125 mg of Bevacizumab are injected into the vitreous pointing the 30 gauge needle towards the macula..  This, in addition to stereo fundus photography are top be repeated on a monthly basis until either quiescence of neo-vascular activity happens  or traction starts to develop or the period of study has finished., Both quiescence or traction are assessed the stereo photography and a Berzin viewer,</interventions>
    <comparator>no control group</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>quiescence of neo-vascular activity based on stereo fundus photography.</outcome>
      <timepoint>12 months after the first injection, patients will be followed on a monthly basis</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>visual acuity using the ETDRS chart</outcome>
      <timepoint>Each "session" is the brief evaluation during each visit, which comprises a visual acuity testing followed by dilatation then stereo fundus photography.  This is done 12 times on a monthly basis after the first injection is given.  </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>neovessel caliber, to be measured from digital fundus images using  the onscreen calipers.  </outcome>
      <timepoint>15 minutes each visit,.  These are monthly visits for 12 times after the first injection.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Complete pan retinal photocoagulation laser treated proliferative diabetic retinopathy 6 months prior to presentation, with evidence of residual neovascular activity documented by stereo fundus photography.  Willingness to sign consent form.  Willingness to get an intravitreal injection (or multiple ones scheduled on a monthly basis);  Willingness to come every month for evaluation.  </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>diagnosis of glaucoma, history of cerebrovascular accidents, evidence of retinal traction and the presence of media opacity hindering proper fundus photo imaging.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>There are no previous studies looking at resilient NV (only case reports).  No sample size has been calculated.  This however prompted us to aim at recruiting around 100 eyes to look into the efficacy and to look at possible 2 or 3 risk factors for such a response.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>11/06/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>6/10/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Lebanon</country>
      <state>Beirut</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Haytham Salti</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>American University of Beirut Medical Center
Maamari Street
Beirut, LEBANON Riad El Solh
110236</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Lebanon</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Haytham Salti</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>American University of Beirut Medical Center
Maamari Street 
Beirut, LEBANON- Riad El Solh
110236</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Lebanon</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>American University of Beirut Medical Center </sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Maamari Street
Beirut Lebanon- Riad El Solh
 110236</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Lebanon</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Hypothesis:  Injection of Bevacizumab into the eye can help in patients who did not respond completely to the laser treatment.  
Methods: 
Patient Recruitment: Patients with proliferative diabetic retinopathy who had undergone PRP therapy at least 6 months prior to study recruitment with documented residual NV activity are invited to participate in the study. 
Patients evaluation:  The initial visit comprises a complete medical history and a comprehensive eye examination including posterior biomicroscopy and indirect ophthalmoscopy. Stereo fundus imaging to evaluate the neovascular activity.  Intravitreal injection: standardized intravitreal injection is done _published protocols available online_ briefly, after wearing sterile gloves, scrubbing the eyelids with betadine, a sterile lid speculum is applied. Anesthesia is achieved with procaine eye drops (Cebesine 0.4% ).  Bevacizumab, at a dose of 1.25mg in 0.05 cc is injected into the vitreous cavity 3.5 mm from the limbus in the superotemporal area using a 30 gauge needle.  This procedure is repeated on a monthly basis aiming at NV regression, which is evaluated using stereo fundus photography.  When the NVs become smaller in size and caliber and inactive or if a tractional component starts to develop, the injections would be withheld and the fundus would be observed with serial monthly photography until study closure.  If NV activity is re-documented, then injections would resume on a monthly basis as long as traction is not present.

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>IRB-Military Hospital Badaro street</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>1 Badaro Street, Beirut LEBANON 11-7070</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/03/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>10/04/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Lebanon</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Haytham Salti</name>
      <address>American University of Beirut Medical Center
Maamari Street Riad El Solh
110236
Beirut</address>
      <phone>+9613776683</phone>
      <fax>+9611370837</fax>
      <email>hs06@aub.edu.lb</email>
      <country>Lebanon</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Maamoun Abdul Fattah</name>
      <address>American University of Beirut
Bliss street Riad El Solh
 110236</address>
      <phone>+96178845330</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ma318@aub.edu.lb</email>
      <country>Lebanon</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Haytham Salti</name>
      <address>American University of Beirut Medical Center
Maamari Street,
Beirut Lebanon Riad El Solh
 110236</address>
      <phone>+9613776683</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>hs06@aub.edu.lb</email>
      <country>Lebanon</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>