<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364212">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/05/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/05/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000537752</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A randomised controlled trial of cognitive remediation therapy for the obese - a preliminary investigation</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The efficacy of behavioural weight loss programme plus cognitive remediation therapy compared to behavioural weight loss programme alone on cognitive functioning, weight loss, mood, emotion regulation, habitual cluster behaviours and health literacy in obese individuals from the community</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1142-7870</utrn>
    <trialacronym>NIL</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>depression</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>emotion regulation</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>habitual cluster behaviours</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>health literacy</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>executive function</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>There is one intervention group that will undergo both the Behaviour Weight Loss Programme (BWL) and Cognitive Remediation Therapy (CRT). For this group, the Cognitive Remediation Therapy will run immediately after completion of BWL. The Behavioural Weight Loss Programme will be run in a group format (small group sessions of 6 to 8 people) by a Clinical Psychologist, once weekly, 90 minutes for 3 consecutive weeks. The BWL program in this study targets diet and exercise through behavioural modification techniques. Participants receive comprehensive education about nutrition. Problem solving techniques are taught so that participants can effectively deal with difficult situations that threaten their weight control efforts. Toward the end of treatment, attention is given to motivation enhancement and relapse prevention to help individuals maintain their weight loss. A record of attendance will be kept to monitor adherence.

CRTwill be run on a individual basis by a Clinical Psychologist who has had special training in CRT. The CRT sessions will be conducted twice weekly for four weeks (a total of 8 sessions) each session lasting for approximately an hour. A record of attendance will be kept to monitor attendance. Cognitive exercises in the form of puzzles, games, memory tasks will form the content of CRT, where the focus is not on performance per se but learning and reflection. Homework tasks will be provided in between sessions to facilitate generalization of skills gained in therapy.



</interventions>
    <comparator>Behavioural Weight Loss (BWL) Program:Three 90 minutes weekly sessions of a group Behavioural Weight Loss (BWL) program, administered to small groups of 6 to 8 people by a Clinical Psychologist.  At the end of the third session, half the group will be randomized to enter CRT. Those participants who do not enter CRT will be the control group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cognitive Functioning. Outcome assessed through a neuro-psychological test battery comprising of (a) Rey Complex Figure Test (b) Trail Making Task (c) Wisconsin Card Sorting Task (d) National Adult Reading Test (e) Reward Loss Task (f) BRIEF A and (g) Digit Span subtest of WAIS III</outcome>
      <timepoint>Immediately post completion of all CRT sessions (8 sessions in total)  </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>weight loss- assessed by digital scales</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post CRT</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression assessed by the psychometric inventory DASS 21</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post CRT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Emotion regulation- assessed by the psychometric inventory DERS</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post CRT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health Literacy- assessed by- Modified version of the Bulimia Mental Health Literacy Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post CRT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Habitual Cluster Behaviours- assessed by the  (modified) Self-Report Habit Index (SRHI);</outcome>
      <timepoint>90 days post CRT</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria for this group are: having a BMI &gt; 30, age 18- 55 years, current weight under 180 kgs, ability to consent and having completed 10 years of education in English. Participants who are depressed and wish to take part of the trial will be included. Patients with hypertension (medicated or not medicated), type 2 diabetes, or high cholesterol will be included. Those with binge eating disorder will not be excluded. We aim for equal number of females and males, but based on past weight loss studies, ~60% will be females.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>55</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Participants will be excluded if they have a history of  psychosis, head injury, neurological disorder including degenerative or inflammatory conditions or stroke, ADHD, epilepsy, developmental or intellectual disability, are unable to complete the testing (e.g. due to hearing, vision or language impediment), are on regular sedative or stimulant medication, and/or if they report substance (alcohol or other) regular use/abuse (more than 2 standard drinks 5 times a week). Individuals will also be excluded if they have regular use of sedatives, hypnotics, antipsychotics, anti-cholinergic or cholinergic medications.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants: 90 obese individuals (BMI: kg/m2 &gt;= 30) will be recruited from the community. Participants will be recruited via direct advertisement to the community. After establishing that a person meets all eligibility criteria (via a phone interview), a clinical assessment will be conducted to exclude co-morbidities and to collect baseline measures. The participant will then be allocated to three 90 minutes weekly sessions of a group Behavioural Weight Loss (BWL) program. Participants in this group will be referred to their G.P., community health centre or a local psychologist if emotional duress or a mental illness is evident. At the end of the BWL programme, half the participants will be randomized to a CRT individual programme conducted twice weekly for 4 weeks. The other half will not receive further treatment. Allocation concealment was achieved by using the web randomization programme called Sealedenvelope.com. </concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomly allocated to a treatment condition following a blind randomisation procedure (according to CONSORT- Moher et al., 2011). The treatment condition for each individual will be predetermined by the use of an external web-based randomization program, called Sealed Envelope (www.sealedenvelope.com). </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Analytic Strategies: Data will be inspected for normality and non-parametric statistic applied where appropriate. Sample of 90 or 45 per group is based on power estimates using Cohens tables for an effect size of 0.6, power of 0.8, 2-tailed test p&lt;0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>9/03/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>90</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>2077 - Hornsby</postcode>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
    <postcode>2200 - Bankstown</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Medicine
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>University of Western Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>School of Medicine
University of Western Sydney
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of New South Wales</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Psychiatry
34 Botany Street,
University of New South Wales,
Randwick NSW 2031 </sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obese individuals are known to suffer from significant cognitive deficits, especially in the area of executive function, leading to poor planning, impulse control and decision making deficits. Research in this field has identified a point at which an intervention could interrupt this vicious cycle. This project aims to examine the relationship between cognition and obesity through a randomized controlled trial (RCT) testing the efficacy of a novel cognitive remediation therapy (CRT) in obese individuals to reduce these deficits and aid weight loss maintenance  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Jayanthi Raman, Evelyn Smith, and Phillipa Hay, The Clinical Obesity Maintenance Model: An Integration of Psychological Constructs including Mood, Emotional Regulation, Disordered Overeating, Habitual Cluster Behaviours, Health Literacy and Cognitive Function, Journal of Obesity, vol. 2013, Article ID 240128, 9 pages, 2013. doi:10.1155/2013/240128</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of WEstern Sydney Human Ethics</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Jill Shute
Office of Research Services
Kingswood Campus, Building K
Locked Bag 1797
Penrith NSW 2751
Australia</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>23/10/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H9787</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jayanthi Raman</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney, School of Medicine, Locked Bag 1797, Penrith, NSW 2751.</address>
      <phone>+61408422850</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>js2009au@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jayanthi Raman</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney, School of Medicine, Locked Bag 1797, Penrith, NSW 2751.</address>
      <phone>+61408422850</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>js2009au@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jayanthi Raman</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney, School of Medicine, Locked Bag 1797, Penrith, NSW 2751.</address>
      <phone>+61408422850</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>js2009au@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Jayanthi Raman</name>
      <address>University of Western Sydney, School of Medicine, Locked Bag 1797, Penrith, NSW 2751.</address>
      <phone>+61408422850</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>js2009au@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>