<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363309">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/11/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>29/11/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612001257853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Red light (670nm) treatment to prevent retinopathy of prematurity (ROP)</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Red light (670nm) treatment to prevent retinopathy of prematurity (ROP)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RED ROP study</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Retinopathy of prematurity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Lung Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Eye</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diseases / disorders of the eye</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the respiratory system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Premature neonates less than 30 weeks gestation or less than 1150 grams birthweight will be exposed to 670nm red light treatment daily for 15 minutes (9 Joules/cm2) from the first 24-48 hours of life until 34 weeks corrected age. The 670nm red light used will be the WARP 75 (Registered trademark light) (Food and Drug Administration (FDA) cleared for market medical devices (US Patent # 6,796,994 issued Sept. 2004)) which is placed on top of the neonates isolette 25cm above the baby in a similar fashion to that of phototherapy for hyperbilirubinaemia. Routine ophthalmological follow-up as inpatients will occur along with neurodevelopmental follow-up and ophthalomological follow-up at 2-3 years of age.</interventions>
    <comparator>This is a small phase 2 study looking at feasibility and efficacy. All neonates enrolled in the study will receive the treatment - there will be no control group.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>670nm red light will reduce the incidence of all stages of retinopathy of prematurity. Eye examinations will be performed by Ophthalmologists and the internationally accepted staging of ROP will be utilised according to standard examination guidelines commencing at 32 weeks corrected age until the retina is vascularised at term corrected age. The worst stage of ROP in either eye at term corrected age will be collected.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The above final outcome will be assessed at term corrected age (this is a standard term for neonates born extremely premature and is designated as 40 weeks).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>670nm red ight will reduce the incidence of retinopathy of prematurity requiring laser surgery. Eye examinations will be performed by Ophthalmologists and the internationally accepted staging of ROP will be utilised according to standard examination guidelines commencing at 32 weeks corrected age until the retina is vascularised at term corrected age. If laser surgery is required to treat stage 3 ROP this data will be collected.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The above final outcome will be assessed at term corrected age (this is a standard term for neonates born extremely premature and is designated as 40 weeks).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>670nm red light will reduce the incidence of chronic lung disease of prematurity. This outcome is determined by the universally standard definition of a neonate requiring oxygen or any respiratory support at 36 weeks corrected age.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The above final outcome will be assessed at 36 weeks corrected age the universally accepted definition for chronic lung disease of prematurity</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Premature neonates less than 30 weeks gestation or less than 1150 grams birthweight
Informed consent obtained in the first 24-48 hours of life</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>24</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Weeks</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Significant chromosomal or congenital anomalies</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Parents of premature neonates will be approached within the first 24-48 hours to consider participation in the study. All enrolled neonates will receive the treatment.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>25</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Canberra Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Canberra Hospital
PO Box 11
Woden, 2606
ACT</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Canberra Hospital Private Practice Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Canberra Hospital
PO Box 11
Woden, 2606
ACT</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>John Curtin School of Medical Research</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Australian National University
Canberra, 2601
ACT</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>John Curtin School of Medical Research</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Australian National University
Canberra, 2601
ACT</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Retinopathy of prematurity is a common complication of very premature delivery (less than 30 weeks gestation) and without appropriate screening and treatment can lead to retinal detachment and blindness. It is the leading cause of blindness in children. While in the uterus the fetus and the retina is developing in an environment where the partial pressure of oxygen is only 25-35 mmHg. Following premature delivery the retina is then exposed to partial pressures of oxygen of 60 mmHg and above. ROP has been shown to occur as a result of this hyperoxic exposure, and despite tight control on oxygen saturations which has led to a significant reduction in the disease, ROP still occurs in some part due to the fact that the retina is not meant to develop in this hyperoxic environment. Exacerbating this situation is that many of the neonates at most risk of ROP have significant lung disease of prematurity and as a consequence have recurrent episodes of hyper and hypoxia which occur despite attempts at tight control of oxygen delivery. 670nm red light is thought to act on the cytochrome c oxidative pathway (within cells of the body), which reduces the presence and production of oxygen free radicals. 670nm red light has been shown to reduce ROP in a mice and rat animal model. It has been used safely in the treatment of soft tissue injuries and mouth ulcers following radiation treatment and studies are ongoing with its use in diabetic retinopathy and age-related macular degeneration. This study aims to look at whether 670nm red light reduces the incidence of any stage of ROP and the incidence of ROP requiring laser surgery.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Not yet submitted</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>ACT HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>ACT Health Directorate Research Office
Building 10 Level 6 
Canberra Hospital
PO Box 11
Woden, 2606
ACT</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate />
      <hrec>ETH 9.12.211</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/11/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Alison Kent</name>
      <address>Dept of Neonatology
Canberra Hospital
Centenary Hospital for Women and Children
PO Box 11
Woden, 2606
ACT</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6174 7565</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6174 5747</fax>
      <email>alison.kent@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Alison Kent</name>
      <address>Dept of Neonatology
Canberra Hospital
Centenary Hospital for Women and Children
PO Box 11
Woden, 2606
ACT</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6174 7565</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6174 5747</fax>
      <email>alison.kent@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Alison Kent</name>
      <address>Dept of Neonatology
Canberra Hospital
Centenary Hospital for Women and Children
PO Box 11
Woden, 2606
ACT</address>
      <phone>+61 2 6174 7565</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 6174 5747</fax>
      <email>alison.kent@act.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>