<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362979">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>27/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/07/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000745741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Can a new "Emergency Department Assessment of Chest-pain Score (EDACS)" reduce hospital admissions and observation for patients presenting with possible heart attack?</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In people presenting to the Emergency Department (ED) at Christchurch Hospital with chest pain, can a the use of a new "Emergency Department Assessment of Chest-pain Score (EDACS)" compared to the TIMI score increase the proportion of patients successfully discharged home within 6 hours of ED arrival with no Major Adverse Cardiac Event (MACE) during the following 30 days?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U111111339936</utrn>
    <trialacronym>EDACS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cardiac Chest Pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health service research</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomised to an initial assessment using either the control or experimental Accelerated Diagnostic Pathways (ADPs). The difference between the ADP's is risk assessment score that is used. This is the modified TIMI score in the control arm and the EDACS score in the experimental arm

Control ADP: is described below.

Experimental ADP uses EDACS score and ECG and troponin:

EDACS score

Age          Score
18-45	=+2
46-50	=+4
51-55	=+6
56-60	=+8
61-65	=+10
66-70	=+12
71-75	=+14
76-80	=+16
81-85	=+18
86+	        =+20

3 Risk factors and 18-50	        =+4
3 Risk factors and 51+	        =+0

Diaphoresis	                                             =+3
Radiates to arm or shoulder	                     =+5
Occurred with inspiration (pleuritic)	             =-4
Reproduced by palpation	                             =-6

Male sex	                                                     =+6

1) EDACS score &lt;16
2) normal cardiac troponin (cTn)  at 0 and 2 hours after arrival, and 

3) no new ischaemic changes on ECGs. 

If ALL three parameters above are met then the patient is classified as low-risk. Low risk patients will be eligible for early discharge to outpatient investigations after the 2-hour troponin result is available. Non low-risk patients will require further cTn testing after at least 6 hours following first or worst symptoms

 </interventions>
    <comparator>Control ADP Pathway: 
Modified TIMI score and ECG and troponin as below:

(A) MODIFIED TIMI SCORE=0
(A modified TIMI score is used without the Biomarker/ECG components. This is because these components are already incorporated in the pathway in a more comprehensive form.)
Clinical Characteristics: 
Score ONE for every positive response	
Score ZERO for any negative or unknown response
a) Age 65 years or over
b) 3 of the following 5 CAD risk factors  

The risk factors are:
(i) Family history: i.e.,  at age less than 55 years of age:        
(1) Angina,     (2) MI,     (3) Sudden cardiac death without obvious cause
(ii)	Hypertension
(iii)	Hyperlipidemia
(iv)	Diabetes
(v)	Active smoker

c)	Known CAD (stenosis 50% or higher):  
e.g. a positive investigation or procedure for CAD including:
 PCI, stent, positive angiogram, positive exercise tolerance test

d)	ASA (i.e., Acetylsalicylic Acid / Aspirin) use in past          7 days 
	(Single GP or ambulance dose not included)

e) 	Recent severe angina (e.g. 2 or more events in last 24 hrs)



(B) normal cardiac troponin (cTn) concentrations at 0 and 2 hours after arrival, and 

(C) no new ischaemic changes on ECGs. 

If ALL three parameter above are met then the patient is classified as low-risk. Low risk patients will be eligible for early discharge to outpatient investigations after the 2-hour troponin result is available. Non low-risk patients will require cTn testing on hospital arrival and again after at least 6 hours following first or worst symptoms</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary objective: Compare the effectiveness, when applied to clinical practice, of an accelerated diagnostic protocol within a clinical pathway that uses the EDACS score against the standard accelerated diagnostic process at Christchurch Hospital which incorporates the Thrombolysis In Myocardial Infarction (TIMI) score.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The proportion of patients successfully discharged home after ED assessment within 6 hours of ED arrival with no Major Adverse Cardiac Event (MACE) during the following 30 days. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Major Adverse Cardiac Event (MACE) including:

(i) death  (unless clearly non-cardiac), 
(ii) cardiac arrest, 
(iii) emergency revascularization procedure, 
(iv) cardiogenic shock, 
(v) ventricular arrhythmia needing intervention, 
(vi) high-degree atrioventricular block needing intervention,
(vii) acute myocardial infarction. 

AMI classified using the global taskforce recommendations requiring evidence of myocardial necrosis together with clinical evidence of myocardial ischemia (ischemic symptoms, ECG changes, or imaging evidence).  </outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acute coronary syndrome related hospital re-attendance, (including unstable angina and urgent revascularization)</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 30 days post admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>All cause hospital re-attendance</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 30 days post admission</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>cost effectiveness (a health economist is being contracted by the Canterbury District Health Board (CDHB)</outcome>
      <timepoint>30 days</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>health utility measured using the EQ-5D self-complete questionnaire at three months after attendance</outcome>
      <timepoint>at 90 days post attendance</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>satisfaction with care measured at three months after attendance using a modified Group Health Association questionnaire that has been used successfully in previous studies of diagnostic strategies for acute chest pain</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post attendance</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>ethnicity and socio-economic representation.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months post attendance</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Adults (age 18 years or older) presenting acutely from the community to the Emergency Department (ED) with chest pain suggestive of acute coronary syndrome for whom, the attending clinician(s) intend(s) to perform serial troponin analysis (cTns), to investigate for possible acute myocardial infarction. 

In accordance with American Heart Association guidelines, possible cardiac symptoms include: the presence of acute chest, epigastric, neck, jaw or arm pain or discomfort or pressure without apparent non-cardiac source.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>ST Segment Elevation Myocardial Infarction (STEMI) present on any electrocardiograph (ECG). (These patients are at very high risk and guidelines mandate immediate transfer to cardiology facilities for treatment and/ monitoring) 

Patients with proven or suspected non-coronary pathology as the cause of chest pain

Patients who will require admission regardless of a negative cTn, due to other medical conditions, or need for other investigations 

Transfers from other departments or hospitals and patients attending with an acute troponin result already known to be raised before arrival.

Subjects previously enrolled in this study 

Anticipated problem with follow-up e.g. resident outside New Zealand 
Patient (or Legal Representative) unable or unwilling to provide informed consent

Patients for whom the researcher does not think that recruitment is appropriate for non-medical reasons (e.g. poor mental status, emotionally vulnerable)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The research nurses will monitor the Emergency Department queue screen to identify patients attending with possible chest pain and screen these patients. Only a limited numbers of characters from the triage nurse assessment are visible on the ED queue screen meaning that a presentation of “Chest pain and shortness of breath after being kicked in chest by cow, possible rib fracture and pneumothorax” will appear as “Chest pain”. The research nurses will not know until they approach and screen the patient for eligibility if there is suspected cardiac chest pain due to a possible AMI. For this reason, it will immediately be obvious that many screened patients are not suitable for enrolment. The attending clinician will be allowed time to decide if the patient requires investigation for possible AMI and for liaison with the research nurse about trial eligibility. The nurses will record demographic details and reason for exclusion, allowing completion of a Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) flowchart.

Patient consent to participate in trial randomisation will be obtained in writing by the study nurses after the patient has been provided with an information sheet and a verbal explanation of the trial. Patients will always have the opportunity to withdraw from the study at any time and for any reason. 

Research Nurses will randomise patients using a sequential sealed envelope process. Study packs will be kept in a locked filing cabinet. They numbered opaque envelope containing the randomisation allocation will be contained within an opaque folder with a matching number within the study packs.</concealment>
    <sequence>The randomisation sequence will be generated by a biostatistician and the allocation envelopes will be prepared by a member of the study group that is not involved with patient recruitment or outcomes adjudication. The method used to create the random order for the allocation of subjects into different groups will be permuted block randomisation.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Blinding of clinical staff will not be possible, however the primary objectives will be determined by adjudicators blind to the study group assignment and the analyses will be performed by investigators blind to the study group assignment</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>RCT analysis plan: 

Study participants baseline characteristics will be summarized using standard descriptive statistics. Successful discharge and occurrence of MACE will be compared between study groups using the chi squared test or Fishers exact test, and the odds ratio with 95% confidence intervals. The time from attendance to hospital discharge will be displayed using Kaplan-Meier curves. The primary analysis will be undertaken on an intention-to-treat basis. 

Current research predicts an 18% discharge rate at 6 hours in the control arm (experimental arm of the current RCT). Even if the experimental arm achieved early discharge in 30% of patients (rather than the 40+% as predicted) this would be an important difference. This study will be powered to detect a 13% difference between the early discharge rates with a Beta=0.10 (90% power) and a 2-tailed Alpha=0.05. This will require recruitment of 265 patients in each arm and 530 patients in total. Based on recruitment in our current study this will take approximately 18 months.

</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/07/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/07/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/01/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>530</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Canterbury</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Government body</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>New Zealand Health Research Council</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 3 - ProCARE Building, Grafton Mews, at 110 Stanley Street, Auckland 1010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>New Zealand Health Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 3 - ProCARE Building, Grafton Mews, at 110 Stanley Street, Auckland 1010</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Canterbury District Health Board</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Riccarton Avenue
Private Bag 4710
Christchurch</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>New Zealand</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This research investigates an innovative and worklable change to the medical decision making process for patients presenting the Emergency Departments with chest pain that is possibly due to a heart attack. This randomised trial aims to prove the effectiveness of a new "fast-track" (2-hour) pathway compared with the existing "fast-track" pathway that is used in current standard care. It uses a specially purpose developed Emergency Department Assessment of Chest-pain Score (EDACS) to identify low-risk patients rather than the risk score currently used in clinical practice that was not designed for this purpose. This should double the number of patients that can have a heart attack rules out earlier (up to 10 hours earlier) than is usually possible. The EDACS score (and the safety of it's use) has already been observationally validated in a two centre cohort of &gt;600 patients separate from the patient group in which it was developed. If successful this new pathweay would make a tangible contribution to health care by preventing unnecessary hospital admission and facilitating early discharge home in a large group of patients. This outcome is beneficial to both patients and the health service, by reassuring patients earlier that heart attack has been ruled out and by avoiding unnecessary admission, duplication of staff activities, and reducing pressure upon urgent care services.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Central Regional Health and Disability Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
No 1 The Terrace
PO Box 5013
6145
Wellington
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/12/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/CEN/23</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/08/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Martin Than</name>
      <address>Emergency Department
Christchurch Hospital
Private bag 4710
Christchurch</address>
      <phone>+643 364 0640</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martin.than@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Dr Martin Than</name>
      <address>Emergency Department
Christchurch Hospital
Private bag 4710
Christchurch</address>
      <phone>+643 364 0270</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martinthan@cdhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Lorraine Skelton</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
University of Otago, Christchurch
PO Box 4345
Christchurch</address>
      <phone>+643 364 1-63</phone>
      <fax>+643 364 0935</fax>
      <email>lorraine.skelton@cdhb.health.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Martin Than</name>
      <address>Emergency Department
Christchurch Hospital
Private Bag 4710
Christchurch</address>
      <phone>+6421450685</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>martinthan@xtra.co.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>