<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="308183">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/07/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>14/07/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000574246</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Postoperative adjuvant treatment with Capecitabine postpones recurrence of hepatocellular carcinoma after curative resection: a randomized controlled trial</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective randomized controlled trial comparing recurrence outcome of adjuvant capecitabine therapy versus no adjuvant therapy for patients with hepatocellular carcinoma after curative resection</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>ChiCTR-TRC-00000160
Chinese Clinical Trial Register</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Hepatocellular carcinoma</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Liver</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Beginning 3 to 4 weeks post operation, the capecitabine group received two weeks of capecitabine oral tablet at 1000 mg/m2, twice a day, 30 min after breakfast and dinner (Xeloda, 500 mg/tablet, Roche, Shanghai, China) followed by one week of rest. This three week regimen was repeated for a total of 4 to 6 cycles.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group received  no adjuvant therapy for 18 weeks</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Time to recurrence (TTR)

Recurrence was confirmed by dynamic contrast-enhanced Computerised Tomography scanning or selective hepatic arteriography in subjects with an elevated alpha-fetoprotein  level or with a newly identified mass.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Time from curative hepatectomy to the first diagnosis of tumor recurrence.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival (OS)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every year after randomization for 5 years</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Disease-free survival (DFS)
Disease-free survival:Time from randomization to either recurrence or death. Patients alive and free of recurrence at the end of follow-up are surveyed via patient census.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every year after randomization for 5 years</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients whose age ranged from 18 to 70 years, with histologically proven hepatocellular carcinoma, and who underwent curative hepatectomy with less than 50% of the liver and with a tumor-free resection margin greater than 1 cm ;a postoperative decline of alpha-fetoprotein (AFP) level to less than 20 micro g/L; Child-Pugh class A; normalized hepatic function (glutamic pyruvic transaminase/glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (GPT/GOT) equal to 2 times the upper normal limit; total serum bilirubin less than 34.2 micro mol/L); normal renal function and hematological parameters (serum creatinine less than 132 micro mol/L; white blood cell (WBC) count equal to 2500×109/L; platelet count (PTL) equal to 40×109/L); life expectancy longer than 6 months; Karnofsky Performance Scale (KPS) score egual to 70.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Prior therapy with capecitabine, concomitant chemotherapy, allergy or history of severe adverse reactions to 5-fluoro-2,4(1H,3H)pyrimidinedione, bone or cerebral metastases, and malignant tumors in other regions of the body over the previous five years; peripheral neuropathy, history of central nervous system diseases, abnormal electrocardiogram findings, psychiatric disorders; severe cardiac, metabolic and/or infectious diseases; active peptic ulcer disease requiring treatment, absorption disorders, or upper digestive tract disorders; Pregnant or lactating females and pre-menopausal women without using contraception.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Drawing consecutively numbered sealed envelopes and implementation was ensured by a research assistant.</concealment>
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 2 / Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/08/2003</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>China</country>
      <state>Shanghai</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>No.225 Changhai Road, Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital, Second Military Medical University, Shanghai 200438, China</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>No.225 Changhai Road, Shanghai 200438, China</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>China</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Second Military Medical University</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>No.800 Xiangyin Road, Shanghai 200433, China</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>China</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Postoperative recurrence of hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is a major problem that hampers the efficacy of surgical resection. To date, adjuvant chemotherapy or other adjuvant modalities have not been proven effective for HCC. We conducted a randomized controlled trial to investigate whether postoperative adjuvant therapy with capecitabine could inhibit the recurrence of HCC after radical resection.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Institutional Review Board of Shanghai Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital, Second Military Medical University, Shanghai 200438, China</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/07/2003</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EHBH-RCT-2003-12</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>8/07/2003</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>China</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>XIA Yong</name>
      <address>No.225 Changhai Road, Eastern Hepatobiliary Surgery Hospital, Second Military Medical University,Shanghai  200438,China</address>
      <phone>+86-21-81875056</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shenfengdfgd@yahoo.cn</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>XIA Yong</name>
      <address>No.225 Changhai Road, Shanghai  200438,China</address>
      <phone>+86-0-13601608920</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>shenfengdfgd@yahoo.cn</email>
      <country>China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>