<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="372511">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/06/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000959370</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Active Minds, Happy Families: healthy lifestyles for preschoolers and their mums  - a program targeting healthy levels of physical activity and sedentary behaviours in preschool children and their mums, and improvements in social skills and cognitive development in children</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Active Minds, Happy Families: a family- and preschool-based intervention targeting physical activity and sedentary behaviours in preschool children and their mothers, children's social skills and cognitive functioning, and mothers' well-being</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>AMHF</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Physical activity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Sedentary behaviour</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Screen time </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Emotional wellbeing </healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Studies of normal psychology, cognitive function and behaviour</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Active minds, happy families targets improvements in physical activity and sedentary behaviours in preschoolers' and their mothers. The program directly engages mothers, targets early childhood settings and utilises a stealth approach. The study is a pilot group randomised trial with a wait-list control group, involving a 10 week intervention and pre- and post-intervention assessments. Preschools and mothers with a child aged 3-5 years will be targeted. One hundred families across ten groups will be recruited and randomised to either a wait-list control or intervention group. 

The intervention consists of face-to-face training for teachers, provision of equipment to preschools and online activities for mothers and preschool teachers. The program draws on constructs from the social cognitive and family systems theories and the ecological model. All strategies implemented are aimed at changing preschool social (e.g. practices, interactions with children) and physical (e.g. removal of chairs, provision of equipment) environments. Teachers will be provided with a 60 minute, in-house training session by experienced research staff (all teachers at each centre will be trained at the same time if available; training will be tailored to meet teacher and centre needs). Teachers will also receive access to a teacher-specific website which includes information addressing the individual (e.g. knowledge), social and physical environment levels of the ecological model through six modules. 

These modules are: 1. outline of the program aims; 2. summary of program actions; 3. detailed information on each of the strategies of the program such as when it might be applicable to use each strategy and how they link with the Early Years Learning Framework; 4. an overview of the Early Years Learning Framework; 5. information on the background, need and rationale for the program; and 6. additional resources.

Teachers will be provided with on-going support by researchers throughout implementation, by request through phone call, email and/or speaking to teachers in person if required. Research staff will contact centre staff at least fortnightly throughout implementation of the program to provide an opportunity for questions and support. Centres will also be provided with equipment to support physical activity to the value of $200. The comprehensive website also targets mothers and consists of 5-10 minute modules which mothers will work through each week to develop skills and knowledge to support their behaviour change. Strategies will focus on activities aimed to support children's psychosocial wellbeing while encouraging behaviour change in both children and their mothers. Mothers will also receive targeted SMS messages to provide further information and support. Mothers will receive 2 SMS each week targeting awareness raising (e.g. impact of too much screen time) and strategies for behaviour change (e.g. activities to use to replace screen time). 

</interventions>
    <comparator>The study is a pilot group randomised trial with a wait-list control group, involving a ten week intervention and pre- and post-intervention assessments. Those in the control group will have the opportunity to participate in the intervention once follow-up data is collected. </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in time spent in physical activity measured using ActiGraph accelerometer (internationally recognised and used activity monitors). Children will be wearing the monitor for a week at each timepoint to measure activity levels. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed immediately following the 10 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in time spent in sedentary behaviour measured using ActivPAL (internationally recognised and used activity monitors). Children will be wearing the monitor for a week at each timepoint to measure activity levels. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed immediately following the 10 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in child screen time pre- to post-intervention. Outcome assessed by parent questionnaire. The questionnaire will capture the child's time in a number of types of screen time including TV viewing, computer use, smart phones and digital tablets.  The questionnaire is based on the previously published HAPPY survey (Hinkley et al, 2012).</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed immediately following the 10 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in child's social skills pre- to post-intervention. Outcome assessed by parent report of child social skills using the "Social Skills Rating System". </outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed immediately following the 10 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in child cognitive functioning pre- to post-intervention. Childrens cognitive functioning, such as language skills and executive functioning, will be assessed using the NIH toolbox. The test is suitable for children aged 3-years and older. 

</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed immediately following the 10 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Centre environments: Trained research assistants will audit centre environment characteristics (e.g. availability and placement of equipment, use of chairs) and changes in preschool practices. This will be assessed using an observation instrument specifically designed for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed immediately following the 10 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in mother's screen time pre- to post-intervention. Outcome assessed by self-report. The questionnaire will capture the mother's time in a number of types of screen time including TV viewing, computer use, smart phones and digital tablets.  Items are taken from the Active Australia Survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed immediately following the 10 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in mother's physical activity pre- to post-intervention. Outcome assessed by self-report. The questionnaire will capture the mother's time in a number of types of physical activity, including leisure time PA and various intensities.  Items are taken from the Active Australia Survey.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed immediately following the 10 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Maternal mood will be assessed using the  Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This outcome will be assessed immediately following the 10 week intervention.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>In 2017, eligible participating families will have one child aged between 3-5 years who attends preschool at one of the participating preschools. The only inclusion criteria for families is having a child aged between 3 to 5 years old enrolled at one of the participating centres. Key inclusion criteria for centres is participation of ten families and willingness to undertake intervention activities and implementation of strategies. This is our ONLY key inclusion criteria. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>3</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>We do not have any exclusion criteria </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence>One hundred families across 10 groups will be recruited and randomised to either a wait-list control (n=50) or intervention (n=50) group. A random number generator will be used grouping participants into category 1 or category 2 which will correspond to the wait-list control or intervention groups. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>4/03/2017</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>14/06/2017</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>93</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/07/2017</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Trina Hinkley</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Deakin University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this project is to test the efficacy of a low-cost, stealth intervention utilising novel approaches to improve health behaviours in preschoolers (3-5yrs) and their mothers.

This project targets improvements in physical activity and sedentary behaviours in preschoolers and their mothers. The proposed program directly engages mothers, targets early childhood settings and utilises a stealth approach. Mothers identify little need and multiple barriers to changing their and their childrens behaviours but programs targeting inter-generational behaviour change may be effective. A stealth approach, focusing on outcomes or characteristics valued by participants without appearing to be directly related to the targeted behaviour itself, is a novel and necessary approach to take in addressing physical activity and sedentary behaviours in preschoolers and their mothers. 

This project includes a focus on children's social skills and cognitive development as previous research has identified that these are outcomes of particular relevance to mothers of preschool children. The researchers hypothesise that by targeting improvements in children's physical activity and sedentary behaviours, particularly screen time, children's social skills and cognitive functioning will also improve.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Deakin University Human Ethics Advisory Group - Health</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>31/01/2017</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HEAG-H 207_2016</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/12/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Trina Hinkley</name>
      <address>Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</address>
      <phone>+61392445480</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trina.hinkley@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Trina Hinkley</name>
      <address>Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</address>
      <phone>+61392445480</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trina.hinkley@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Trina Hinkley</name>
      <address>Deakin University
221 Burwood Hwy
Burwood  Vic  3125</address>
      <phone>+61392445480</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trina.hinkley@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Trina Hinkley</name>
      <address />
      <phone>61392445480</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>trina.hinkley@deakin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>