<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362640">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/06/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/06/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000654853</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dietary Fats and Biomarkers of Human Health: Excess Saturated Fat or Lack of Omega 3 Fatty Acids</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Would it be an excess of saturated fat in the diet or a deficiency of omega-3 fatty acids the responsible for increased blood lipid levels? And what would be the effect of the background diet on omega-3 supplementation in healthy adults in an acute study?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>nil</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>lipid levels and systemic inflammation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other inflammatory or immune system disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A dietary intervention trial will be conducted in healthy subjects, in randomised controlled cross-over design. The trial will involve intervention with a single dose of dietary regimen followed by collection of 5 blood samples at 0, 3, 4, 5 and 6 hours following meal consumption. The meal will consist in 3 fish oil capsules (3 x 0.5g) and a portion (186g) of mashed potatoes containing 36g butter. Subjects will be asked to fill a medical and a physical activity questionnaire and will have their anthropometric measurements taken. In addition, subjects will complete a 24 hour food record. After a week period the participants will return and repeat the procedure for the alternative diet.</interventions>
    <comparator>A dietary intervention trial will be conducted in healthy subjects, in randomised controlled cross-over design. The trial will involve intervention with a single dose of dietary regimen followed by collection of 5 blood samples at 0, 3, 4, 5 and 6 hours following meal consumption. The meal will consist in 3 fish oil capsules (3x 0.5g) and a portion (180g) of mashed potatoes containing 30g of sunflower oil. Subjects will be asked to fill a medical and a physical activity questionnaire and will have their anthropometric measurements taken. In addition, subjects will complete a 24 hour food record. After a week period the participants will return and repeat the procedure for the alternative diet.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incorporation of fatty acids into plasma</outcome>
      <timepoint>At both visits in each blood samples collected  (0, 3, 4, 5 and 6 hours following meal consumption).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Lipid profile (Trigycerides and total, LDL and HDL cholesterol)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At both visits in each blood samples collected  (0, 3, 4, 5 and 6 hours following meal consumption).
.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Analisys of inflammation markers (IL-6, TNF-alpha and hsCRP) in blood samples.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At both visits in each blood samples collected  (0, 3, 4, 5 and 6 hours following meal consumption).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nil</outcome>
      <timepoint>Nil</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy male or female aged between 18 and 65 years at initial assessment</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Are current using lipid-lowering drugs (eg statins) or fish oil supplements;
Have a current regular consumption of 2 or more fish meals a week;
Have history of congestive heart failure, stroke, myocardial infarction, coronary artery
bypass graft, or atherosclerotic CVD;
Have history of diabetes, triglycerides higher than 10 mmol/L; LDL cholesterol higher
than 5 mmol/L;
Have history of gastrointestinal/liver disease;
Are current a smoker;
Are pregnant or breast feeding women.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants will be recruited from the general public through media advertising, advertisements placed on noticeboards at the University of Newcastle and distributed via departmental and faculty email lists. Participants will also be recruited from the Hunter Medical Research Institute (HMRI) Volunteer Register. Participants  will complete a health questionnaire to ensure that inclusion criteria are met. Randomisation of participants to one of group diet will be performed by one of the researchers in the researsh group. Allocation is not concealed.</concealment>
    <sequence>Randomisation of participants to one of group diet will be performed by one of the researchers in the researsh group using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures>nil</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>4/07/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>54</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Newcastle</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Professor Manohar Garg</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Room 305C, Medical Sciences Building
The University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Consumption of foods rich in saturated fats have been associated with elevated blood lipid levels and adverse health effects. However studies using animal models have demonstrated that dietary saturated fats raise blood lipid (cholesterol and triglyceride) levels only when the diet is low/deficient in omega-3 fatty acids. If the same is true for humans, this research will have important implications for the prevention of cardiovascular and other chronic diseases. Therefore we hypothesise that saturated fat consumption does not raise blood lipid levels if the diet is sufficient in omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids. We also hypothesise that the benefits of n-3 PUFA can be optimised when consumed in combination with saturated fats. This is a randomized controlled trial in cross-over design. It involves intervention with a single dose of dietary regimen, after an overnight fast, followed by collection of 5 blood samples at 0, 3, 4, 5 and 6 hours following meal consumption. Participants will be randomised to one of two diets, high saturated fat or high omega-6 polyunsaturated fatty acids. They will be given a portion of mashed potatoes containing either butter (saturated fat) or vegetable oil (omega-6) and 3 capsules of fish oil. After a week period the participants will come back and repeat the procedure receiving the alternative diets. They will also be asked to fill a medical and physical activity questionnaire and a 24 hour food diary in each visit.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Newcastle Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Researsh Office
The Chancellery of University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/05/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>H-2012-0117</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Professor Manohar Garg</name>
      <address>School of Biomedical Sciences and Pharmacy
Medical Sciences Building
The University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 5647</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 2028</fax>
      <email>manohar.garg@newcastle.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cintia Dias</name>
      <address>School of Biomedical Sciences and Pharmacy
Medical Sciences Building
The University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 5638</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 2028</fax>
      <email>cintia.dias@uon.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Cintia Dias</name>
      <address>School of Biomedical Sciences and Pharmacy
Medical Sciences Building
The University of Newcastle
University Drive
Callaghan NSW 2308</address>
      <phone>+61 2 4921 5638</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 4921 2028</fax>
      <email>cintia.dias@uon.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>