<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83278">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>12/11/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/03/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000137291</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>CPAP- Is Pressure Important? A randomised, double blinded, crossover, pilot trial on Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP), and it's effects upon apnoea, bradycardia and desaturation episodes, and oxygen requirement in preterm infants with respiratory distress syndrome.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) Affect Apnoea, Bradycardia and Desaturation Episodes, and Oxygen Requirement in Preterm Infants on CPAP for Respiratory Distress Syndrome?  A Randomised, Double-Blinded Crossover Pilot Trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Respiratory Distress Syndrome</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Reproductive Health and Childbirth</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Complications of newborn</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) at 8cmH2O supplied via Hudson CPAP to an infant who is already using Hudson CPAP for respiratory support.  During two seperate five-hour periods on consecutive days, the infant receiving the CPAP pressure of 8cmH2O will have the oxygen requirement, blood oxygen saturation and heart rate recorded by the Neonatal Unit's electronic bedside monitoring system.  The hypothesis is that there is no difference in the number of apnoeas, bradycardias, desaturation episodes and oxygen requirement between the two CPAP pressures of 8cmH2O and 6cmH2O.   As this is a pilot study, there will be no defined washout period as we do not yet have enough data to predict how long it would need to be.  The length of the washout period would be one of the things we want to discover from the trial.</interventions>
    <comparator>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure (CPAP) at 6cmH2O supplied via Hudson CPAP to infants who are already using Hudson CPAP for respiratory distress. Infants will receive CPAP at 6cmH2O for 2 five hour periods on consecutive days, either before or after they receive 8cmH2O.  Once again their observations will be recorded by the electronic bedmaster monitoring system.  There will be no formal follow up after the intervention periods have finished as both these CPAP pressures are routinely used in our neonatal unit and can both be regarded as standared treatment for respiratory distress syndrome in the preterm infant.  Neonatal intensive care will, of courese, be ongoing.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Number of clinically significant episodes of apnoea, bradycardia and desaturation episodes requiring intervention by the bedside nurse (stimulation, change in inspired oxygen concentration, bag and mask ventilation) .  This will be collected and recorded on the infant's usual nursing chart by the bedside nurse.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Information will be collected continuously throughout the trial period by the bedside nurse, as it would be collected as usual in the intensive-care environment.  As a minimum, all stable observations will be recorded hourly and all interventions will be recordd as they occur.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Episodes of apnoea, bradycardia and desaturation as recorded on the bedside cardiorespiratory and saturation monitor (Apnoea defined as cessation of breathing for longer than 20 seconds, or shorter if associated with bradycardia or desaturation.)  This will be assessed by examination of the data collected by the bedside electronic monitoring and comparison of the number, duration and severity of events.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Information will be collected by the bedside monitor continuously throughout the trial period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean inspired oxygen concentration to maintain saturations as per current unit guidelines (oxygen saturation levels maintained between 86% and 94% in premature infants on supplemental oxygen.)  Assessment by comparion of data readouts from the electronic monitoring system.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Every 6 seconds throughout the trial period.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Possible need for and duration of a washout period will be assessed by examination of all the data collected to look for an increase in instability after a change in CPAP pressure and at what point this instability resolves.</outcome>
      <timepoint>End of trial</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Feasability of using 6cmH2O and 8cmH2O as CPAP pressure settings in a larger trial of CPAP pressures.  This will be assessed by the finding of any statistical trend towards a difference in between the two pressures from the electronic and bedside data which is collected.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be assessed when all the data from all 10 infants enetered into the trial has been collected and compared.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Premature infant of less than 30 weeks corrected gestational age, diagnosis of respiratory distress syndrome, ongoing respiratory distress or apnoea of prematurity requiring treatment with CPAP, stable on CPAP for the past 48 hours, no changes to caffeine dose (if used) for 48 hours.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>24</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Weeks</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>30</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Major congenital of chromosomal abnormality, treatment with doxapram for troublesome apnoea, current post-natal corticosteroid treatment, any contraindication to the use of CPAP</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed, opaque envelope method</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation method:  There will be 5 opaque envelopes containing an allocation to each pathway (10 participants).  These identical envelopes will be shuffled and one chosen at random for each participant.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>26/02/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>10</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Anna Tottman</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Paediatric Registrar
Newborn Services
National Women's Hospital
Auckland City Hospital
2, Park Road
Grafton
Auckland  1010</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname />
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Mariam Buksh</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Neonatologist
Newborn Services
National Women's Hospital
Auckland City Hospital
2, Park Road
Grafton
Auckland 1010</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>New Zealand</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This pilot study intends to compare the effect of two different levels of positive end-expiratory pressure (PEEP) on the respiratory status of premature infants who require continuous positive airway support (CPAP) for the treatment of respiratory distress syndrome.  Our hypothesis that there is no difference in the number of apnoea, bradycardia and desaturation episodes, and oxygen requirement when using PEEP 6cmH2O as compared to 8cmH2O.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern X Regional Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
3rd Floor, Unisys Building
650 Great South Rd, Penrose
Private Bag 92 522
Wellesley Street 
Auckland</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/01/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>NTX/08/10/097</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>14/10/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Anna Tottman</name>
      <address>Newborn Services
National Women's Hospital
Auckland City Hospital
2, Park Road
Grafton
Auckland 1010</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3074949</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ATottman@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Anna Tottman</name>
      <address>Newborn Services
National Women's Hospital
Auckland City Hospital
2, Park Road
Grafton
Auckland 1010</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3074949</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ATottman@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Anna Tottman</name>
      <address>Newborn Services
National Women's Hospital
Auckland City Hospital
2, Park Road
Grafton
Auckland 1010</address>
      <phone>+64 9 3074949</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ATottman@adhb.govt.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>