<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370738">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/02/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>17/02/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617000251325</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Comparing home infusion devices for antibiotic treatment - CHID Study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised crossover trial evaluating patient and nurse satisfaction of the electronic portable infusion device (Ambit) versus elastomeric delivery (Baxter) for the continuous administration of antibiotic in the home in patients with infectious disease.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>CHID</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Any infectious disease requiring intravenous antibiotic therapy and suitable for treatment via a continuous infusion in the home setting</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Intervention arm: Patients will be administered antibiotics with an AmbIT Continuous electronic infusion pump, in the home for 4 - 7 days.  This duration is variable due to the need to align with standard outpatient appointment times and will be determined by the time between discharge and appointment, or from one appointment to the next.  A separate cassette with attached tubing and connector is provided for each day with a single pump used for the intervention period. The medication type, dose, rate and home care are as per normal clinical practice. Education on the use of the electronic pump will be via written information sheets provided by the pump manufacturers and verbal information from the study nurse. Education and delivery of the pump will occur prior to leaving hospital or during a clinic visit by the study nurse. 
A home care nurse (Royal District Nursing Service, RDNS) will visit each patient daily in their home as per normal practice and change the infusion cassette for the pump. As these nurses may not have previous experience using the AmbIT pump, all nurses who provide home care to patients on this trial will receive training via a 4 minute custom-made video, available on-line, prior to first enrolment. They will also receive a written information sheet about the trial, and a 24-hour technical support telephone number has been provided should any pump-related issues occur (e.g. alarm of the AmbIT pump).
Due to the need to maintain continuous administration of antibiotics, a wash out period between devices is not part of this study.
Patient intervention adherence will be checked by the study nurse at each clinic visit. Nurses will be contacted via email and phone by the study nurse to confirm training has been undertaken and remind them of the survey. </interventions>
    <comparator>Control arm: Patients will be administered antibiotics with a Baxter elastomeric infusion pump, in the home for 4 - 7 days. This duration is variable due to the need to align with standard outpatient appointment times and will be determined by the time between discharge and appointment, or from one appointment to the next. A separate infusion pump is provided for each of the days. The medication type, dose, rate and home care are as per normal clinical practice. Education on the use of the elastomeric pump will be via written information sheets provided by the pump manufacturers and verbal information from the study nurse. Education and delivery of the pump will occur prior to leaving hospital or during a clinic visit by the study nurse. 
A home care nurse (Royal District Nursing Service, RDNS) will visit each patient daily in their home and change the elastomeric pump as per normal practice 
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction of infusion pumps in the home assessed by surveys specifically designed for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of 4 - 7 days with each infusion pump.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Nurse satisfaction with infusion pumps in the home assessed by a survey specifically designed for this study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Completion of survey after providing a home visit to at least one patient on this trial.  To be completed at the convenience of each nurse, but prior to the conclusion of the trial.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total number of infusion system related complications including occlusions, disconnections, leaks, infections, repairs or replacements of the line and/or device itself.  These will be evaluated from a case record form and patient log book.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the completion of each 4 - 7 day period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Through RAH pharmacy and CPIE Pharmacy Services, the data on purchase cost of pumps, disposables (including batteries) and medication will be recorded and calculated on a per patient basis.  Service and cleaning cost of the reusable electronic pump will be obtained from CPIE records.  Weight of the returned pumps will be used to calculate unused drug quantities, extra costs of medication not administered due to prescription changes will also be included.
The outcome is a comparison of the operating costs associated with each type of pump.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the  completion of both arms.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The dose of antibiotic received by the patient over a 24-hour period will be estimated based on the volume of initial infusion solution minus the quantity remaining in each returned infusion pump. The estimated dose received will be compared to the total daily dose prescribed by the physician, and an approximate flow rate calculated based on the connection and disconnection times recorded in the patient log book. 
The outcome is an estimated average flow rate and dose of the antibiotic administered with each type of pump.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Calculated per day, at the end of each arm.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Temperature data recorded from the patients skin will be compared to calibration conditions for peripheral skin temperature utilised by manufacturers of elastomeric pumps. This data will be recorded every 10 minutes with an iButton temperature sensor attached to the patient's skin proximal to the infusion site.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each day for the period of both arms.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The average and peak ambient temperatures surrounding the infusion pump will be determined during (i) storage prior to patient connection and (ii) while connected to the patient. This data will be recorded every 10 minutes with an iButton temperature sensor attached to the surface of each elastomeric pump or medication cassette.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At the end of each day for the period of both arms.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>18 years of age or older
Inpatient of the Royal Adelaide Hospital
Patient can provide voluntary informed consent 
Has been given Infectious Diseases approval for home antibiotic therapy
To receive a minimum of 8 days of intravenous therapy post discharge from Hospital
Patient must have the capacity to provide formal feedback on device satisfaction by using a questionnaire and log book.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Not referred to the Infectious Diseases unit for home intravenous antibiotic therapy.
Patient is unable or unwilling to fill out the patient questionnaire survey and or log book.
Skin allergy or contact dermatitis to stainless steel.
Patients primary clinician is unwilling to enrol patient.
Pregnancy.
Patient is totally dependent upon care for all daily needs and/or is immobile.
The following antibiotics are excluded due to restricted shelf life: Ceftazadime, Ticarcillin/Clavulanate.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>20/02/2017</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/07/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>SA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>The Royal Adelaide Hospital - Adelaide</hospital>
    <postcode>5000 - Adelaide</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Flinders university </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sturt Road, Bedford Park 5042, South Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Government of South Australia, Department of Further Education, Employment, Science and Techonology (now Department of State Development)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 4, 11 Waymouth Street, Adelaide, South Australia 5000</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>CPIE Pharmacy Services</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2 Crittenden Road
Findon
SA 5023</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Commercial sector/Industry</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>CPIE Pharmacy Services</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>2 Crittenden Road
FINDON   SA   5024</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study is to compare and contrast patient and nurse satisfaction with the Baxter(Registered Trademark) device and the Ambit(Registered Trademark) device for delivery of intravenous antibiotics in the home setting. The secondary aims are to examine any complications that occur with this these infusion pumps, the quantity of medication they deliver and the temperature during storage and use of these devices.
The proposed research design is to allocate patients to receive home antibiotic infusion with one of two infusion devices for one week, then continue that treatment with the other device for one week. At the end of both periods the patients will be asked to fill in a questionnaire regarding their satisfaction with the device and any problems that arose. A survey will also be conducted of RDNS nursing staff that have provided home care to these patients to assess nurse satisfaction.
In addition to the surveys, all infusion devices/bags will be weighed after their use to determine the quantity of any drug remaining. Each pump/bag will be equipped with a temperature sensor to determine the storage temperature of the drugs when kept in patients homes, as well as the ambient temperature during pump use. A temperature sensor will be placed on each patients arm to measure skin temperature during pump use, as this has an impact on elastomeric infusion pump accuracy. Patient case note data will also be monitored to collect statistics on infusion related complications, such as occlusions, disconnections, infections or repairs required.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Adelaide Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 4, Womens Health Centre
Royal Adelaide Hospital
North Terrace
Adelaide, South Australia, 5000</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/05/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>R20160420</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/04/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brett Ritchie</name>
      <address>Infectious Diseases Unit,
Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 1 IMVS Building
North Terrace
Adelaide
SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82225340</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brett.ritchie@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brett Ritchie</name>
      <address>Infectious Diseases Unit
Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 1 IMVS Building
North Terrace
Adelaide
SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82225340</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brett.ritchie@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Brett Ritchie</name>
      <address>Infectious Diseases Unit,
Royal Adelaide Hospital
Level 1 IMVS Building
North Terrace
Adelaide
SA, 5000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82225340</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>brett.ritchie@sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mrs</title>
      <name>Jodie Hobbs</name>
      <address>Medical Device Research Institute
School of Computer Science, Engineering and Mathematics
Flinders University
Tonsley Building 1, Level 5 
1284 South Road, Clovelly Park, SA, 5042 
</address>
      <phone>+61 8 8201 5489 </phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jodie.hobbs@flinders.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>