<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371185">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/07/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>9/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001069448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Bioavailability of bovine lactoferrin after a novel microencapsulation process and its effect on inflammatory markers and the gut microbiome in healthy males</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Bioavailability of bovine lactoferrin after a novel microencapsulation process and its effect on inflammatory markers and the gut microbiome.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>General health promotion
</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Inflammatory and Immune System</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Normal development and function of the immune system</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A randomised, double-blind, cross-over trial. Each arm of the trial will last for 4 weeks, with a 2-week washout period in between. The total trial period is 10 weeks.
- Two doses of Bovine Lactoferrin (BLf) will be tested, with and without modification
- Participants will receive modified Bovine Lactoferrin, or non-modified BLf in a capsule. These capsules will be equivalent for BLf content. Those on the higher dose will simply take more of the capsules as a dose. Participants will be asked to take their required dose of capsules after breakfast each morning.
- Intervention will be delivered by an Advanced Accredited Practising Dieititian (AdvAPD).
- All participants will have fasting blood tests taken at baseline, 2 and 4 weeks after intervention commencement.
- Participants will attend face to face appointments at the School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences, University of Queensland at baseline, 2 weeks and 4 weeks after intervention commencement. This will be repeated on week 6 (after washout) and week 8 and 10. Note: week 6 pertains to baseline of the second arm; week 8 and week 10 pertains to week 2 and week 4 respectively.
- Intervention adherence will be assessed by collecting used lactoferrin supplement containers and supplement record forms from participants.</interventions>
    <comparator>Participants may be allocated to one of two dosing orders, and to modified or non-modified lactoferrin capsules</comparator>
    <control>Dose comparison</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum lactoferrin levels   measured using a serum lactoferrin ELISA (abcam) 
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fecal lactoferrin levels - measured using IBD-scan kit (Techlab, inc.)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Incidence of common viral infections (i.e. the common cold, influenza, gastroenteritis) - measured by initial screening using total white cell counts, followed by self-report of illness throughout the study.</outcome>
      <timepoint>White cell counts: baseline, 2 and 4 weeks after intervention commencement
Self report of illness: baseline, 2 and 4 weeks after intervention commencement</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum CD4+ and CD8+ counts - using flow cytometric analysis</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2 and 4 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Gut microbiome profile  analysis of fecal sample - amplicon production, sequencing and community profiling </outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and at 4 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life scores  using the SF-36 questionnaire
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline and 4 weeks after intervention commencement.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Healthy body weight (body mass index [BMI] 18.5-24.9 kg/m2), not overweight or obese 
- Available to participate for the required timeframe of the study (10 weeks)
- Not anaemic (i.e. Haemoglobin greater than or equal to 150 plus or minus 20g/L; Haematocrit greater than or equal to 0.45 plus or minus 0.05; red blood cell count greater than or equal to 5.0 plus or minus 0.5 x 1012/L)
- Non smoker
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Any allergy or intolerance to dairy products
- BMI &lt;18.5 or &gt;24.9 kg/m2
- Current consumption of lactoferrin-fortified products or lactoferrin supplements
- Inability to provide informed consent due to diminished understanding or comprehension, or a language other than English spoken and an interpreter unavailable
-Anaemic (i.e. Haemoglobin greater than or equal to 150 plus or minus 20g/L; Haematocrit greater than or equal to 0.45 plus or minus 0.05; red blood cell count greater than or equal to 5.0 plus or minus 0.5 x 1012/L)
-Taking any form of recreational drug
-Taking immunosuppressives (i.e. corticosteroids such as prednisone; monoclonal antibodies including basiliximab, daclizumab and muromonab; cyclosporine or azathioprine; tacrolimus; sirolimus; mycophenolate mofetil; other cytotoxic drugs, e.g. methotrexate, chlorambucil) or any other immunomodulating drugs or analogues (i.e.  levamisole, immune globulin, thymic factors, cytokines, thalidomide, lenalidomide, Revlimid, Actimid, pomalidomide and apremilast).
-Current viral infection (without reference to serology)
-Consuming &gt;2 standard drinks on any day (i.e. alcohol consumption beyond the national guidelines)
-Smokers, including those in the process of quitting  i.e. using e-cigs and nicotine patches
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Third party (A PhD scholar at the School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences, The University of Queensland, who is external to this research team) will perform the randomisation of treatment allocation and coding of products. Participants will be randomised to receive a particular dose (known to the randomiser but not the principal investigator through packaging differences), then randomised to the order of product presentation.</concealment>
    <sequence>Subjects will be randomly allocated to dose using a permuted block randomisation design by an external party. Subjects will then be randomised to receive either the modified lactoferrin, or the non-modified lactoferrin for the first arm of the trial. They will then be given the other product for the crossover.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Bio-availability</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/08/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>11/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>12/08/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>19/08/2016</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>12</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>12</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>20/10/2016</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate>20/10/2016</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>QLD</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Dr Olivia Wright</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences, 
The University of Queensland
St Lucia QLD 4072</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>UniQuest Pty Ltd</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>UniQuest Pty Ltd
Level 7, General Purpose South
Staff House Road
The University of Queensland
Brisbane Qld 4072</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>None</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>None</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Lactoferrin is a protein involved in protection against microbial infections and the prevention of systemic inflammation, and is found in milk, saliva and other secretions. 

The study is designed to measure how well the lactoferrin absorbs into the digestive system, compared to a modified lactoferrin product. We will also be looking at how well the immune system is functioning before and after taking the lactoferrin/modified lactoferrin product.

The purpose of the study is to improve understanding of the absorption and efficacy of bovine lactoferrin with a view to the creation of new functional food products in the future. 

</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Bellberry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>129 Glen Osmond Road, Eastwood SA 5063</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2015-11-747</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>21/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Olivia Wright</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland
School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences
Connell Building (26)
St Lucia QLD 4072 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 6669</phone>
      <fax>(+61) 7 3365 6877</fax>
      <email>o.wright@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Paul Stockwell</name>
      <address>Level 7, General Purpose South
Staff House Road
The University of Queensland
Brisbane Qld 4072</address>
      <phone>+61 (7) 3365 7476</phone>
      <fax>+61 (7) 3365-4433</fax>
      <email>p.stockwell@uniquest.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Gary Wilson</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland
School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences
Connell Building (26)
St Lucia QLD 4072 </address>
      <phone>(+61) 7 3365 6445</phone>
      <fax>(+61) 7 3365 6877 </fax>
      <email>g.wilson2@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Olivia Wright</name>
      <address>The University of Queensland
School of Human Movement and Nutrition Sciences
Connell Building (26)
St Lucia QLD 4072 </address>
      <phone>+61 7 3365 6669</phone>
      <fax>(+61) 7 3365 6877</fax>
      <email>o.wright@uq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>