<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="1526">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/08/2006</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/01/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000039482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Novel treatments for alcohol dependence: A randomized controlled trial of structured stepped-care intervention for psychiatric comorbidity</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Novel treatments for alcohol dependence: A randomized controlled trial of structured stepped-care intervention for psychiatric comorbidity to improve drinking outcomes and reduce comorbid mood or anxiety symptoms.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Alcohol Dependence</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>12-week intervention: Reduction and stabilisation of alcohol intake using pharmacotherapy (naltrexone, acamprosate or a combination of the two)followed by formal psychiatric assessment.                                                                        Participants meeting criteria for psychiatric comorbidity will be randomised to receive manualised psychological therapy for comorbid psychiatric and alcohol problems.</interventions>
    <comparator>To receive usual counselling care (control group).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(i) time to relapse (&gt;5 drinks on any one day)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at week 12 (post-treatment) and week 26 (follow-up)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(ii) clinician rated severity from Anxiety Disorders Interview Schedule for DSM-IV (ADIS-IV) and Hamilton DepressionRating Scale (HDRS) on anxiety and depressive diagnoses.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at week 12 (post-treatment) and week 26 (follow-up)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(i) time to consumption of any alcohol (lapse) identified by self-reported alcohol consumption.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at week 12 (post-treatment) and week 26 (follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(ii) self-reported amount of alcohol consumed, expressed as the average consumption per drinking day.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at week 12 (post-treatment) and week 26 (follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(iii) improvement in depressive or anxiety symptoms (Depression Anxiety and Stress Scale; DASS-21).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at week 12 (post-treatment) and week 26 (follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(iv) biological markers of alcohol consumption at 6, 12 and 26 weeks (carbohydrate-deficient transferrin (CDT), Liver Function Tests (LFTs) and Mean Cell Volume (MCV)).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at week 12 (post-treatment) and week 26 (follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>(v) episodes of alcohol related harm (psychosocial, occupational, forensic, medical).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Measured at week 12 (post-treatment) and week 26 (follow-up).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria for step 1: (i) alcohol dependence according to DSM-IV criteria (Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders 4th edition), with alcohol as the subjects drug of choice, (ii) adequate cognition and English language skills to give valid consent and complete research interviews (as assessed by the mini mental state examination), (iii) willingness to give written consent, (iv) abstinence from alcohol for between 3 and 21 days (standard clinical criteria for use of acamprosate or naltrexone), (v) resolution of any clinically evident alcohol withdrawal (score 0-1 on RPA hospital alcohol withdrawal scale), and a positive score on the initial comorbidity suspicion checklist (CSC).
Entry criteria to step 2: (i) Completion of 3 weeks on acamprosate and/or natlrexone, (ii) resolution of any clinically evident alcohol withdrawal (score 0-1 on RPA hospital alcohol withdrawal scale), (iii) case formulation and diagnosis for anxiety or depression (see below).</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria for step 1: (i) sensitivity to study medications or therapy with these drugs within 6 months, (ii) active major psychiatric disorder associated with significant suicide risk, (iii) pregnancy or lactation, (iv) advanced liver disease (hepatocellular failure, variceal bleeding, ascites or encephalopathy), (v) other serious medical illness that would interfere with adherence to the study protocol. 
Exclusion criteria 2: (i) Non-compliance on acamprosate and/or naltrexone, (ii) alcohol consumption at baseline levels, (iii) resolution of clinically evident anxiety or depression as assessed by the case formulation (see below). These patients will be offered further treatment as appropriate within the service and continue to be monitored.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Consecutively numbered sealed envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Stratfied for concomitant selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SSRI) use and randomised by an independent party using shuffled allocation cards</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>subjects will be blind to treatment allocation</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/04/2006</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Alcohol Education and Rehabilitation Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Hospital</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Co-morbid depression and anxiety are becoming a critical issue in the management of alcohol dependence due to the high prevalence, debilitating effects and lack of effective treatment options. This proposal seeks to generate and evaluate a novel, integrated treatment for comorbid anxiety or depressive disorder. Participants will all receive anti-craving medication (naltrexone and/or acamprosate) and formal assessment of clinically relevant anxiety or depression. They will then be randomized to receive either a usual counselling care or a CBT stepped-care intervention including a manual-based psychotherapy appropriate for their psychiatric profile. Participants will be followed up at 3 and 6 months to determine the benefits of integrated treatment on alcohol consumption, comorbid symptoms and health. It is hypothesised that stepped care for alcohol dependence with comorbid mood or anxiety disorders will result in less relapse and lower alcohol consumption compared to usual care, and result in a greater improvement in comorbid symptoms and quality of life compared to usual care.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>19/07/2005</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>07-2005/3/8420</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Royal Prince Alfred Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>30/03/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>X05-0279</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of NSW</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>20/06/2006</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC06140</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paul Haber</name>
      <address>Drug Health Services
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95156419</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 95158970</fax>
      <email>phaber@mail.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Paul Haber</name>
      <address>Drug Health Services
Royal Prince Alfred Hospital
Missenden Road
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95156419</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 95158970</fax>
      <email>phaber@mail.usyd.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>