<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370087">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/02/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>23/02/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000247471</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A double-blinded randomised controlled trial of daily use mouthwash to reduce the detection of pharyngeal gonorrhoea among men who have sex with men</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Will daily use of mouthwash reduce the detection of pharyngeal gonorrhoea among men who have sex with men?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>OMEGA (Oral Mouthwash use to Eradicate GonorrhoeA)</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Gonorrhoea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sexually transmitted infections</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Men will receive four 500mL bottles of study mouthwash (Mouthwash A) in a plain, clean and opaque bottle labelled with participants study ID. Mouthwash A contains 0% alcohol and is available in the supermarkets or chemists. All participants will be asked to rinse and garage 20 mL of the given mouthwash for 60 seconds at least once every day during the 12-week study period but no more than 5 times per day as per the product recommendation.

Adherence will be monitored by the self-admitted questionnaires and returning the mouthwash bottles at clinic visits week 6 and 12. </interventions>
    <comparator>Men will receive four 500mL bottles of study mouthwash (Mouthwash B) in a plain, clean and opaque bottle labelled with participants study ID. Mouthwash B contains 0% alcohol and is available in the supermarkets or chemists. All participants will be asked to rinse and garage 20 mL of the given mouthwash for 60 seconds at least once every day during the 12-week study period but no more than 5 times per day as per the product recommendation.

Adherence will be monitored by the self-admitted questionnaires and returning the mouthwash bottles at clinic visits week 6 and 12. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of MSM who test positive for pharyngeal gonorrhoea within 12 weeks.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At week 6 and 12. 
Participants will be required to attend the clinic at week 6 and 12. Pharyngeal swabs will be taken by the clinicians at week 6 and 12, and participants will be required to post their self-collected saliva sample at week 3 and 9. The proportion of pharyngeal gonorrhoea positive is defined as any positive in any specimens within 12 weeks.  Interim cases of pharyngeal gonorrhoea diagnosed outside of these four time points will also be included if they occur between 3 and 12 weeks.  An example might include an individual who presents with acute symptomatic urethral gonorrhoea and who is also tested for pharyngeal gonorrhoea at this presentation.   </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adherence to mouthwash over 12 weeks. This will be assessed using questionnaire. This questionnaire is designed by the principal investigator and has been reviewed and revised by several associate investigators.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At week 12. 
Participants will be asked to complete a total of 5 paper-based questionnaires at week 0, 3, 6, 9, and 12, respectively. A long questionnaire will be provided to participants at week 0, 6, and 12, and a short version at week 3 and 9. The questionnaire includes basic demographic details, general information on use of mouthwash, sexual experiences, use of antibiotics, adherence and feedback of the study mouthwash, and diagnosis of gonorrhoea.  The one-page short version of questionnaire will take approximately 1-2 minutes to complete; while the long version of questionnaire will take approximately 5-10 minutes to complete. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The proportion of MSM with other sexually transmitted infections (HIV, syphilis, rectal gonorrhoea, rectal chlamydia, urethral gonorrhoea, urethral chlamydia, pharyngeal chlamydia) within 12 weeks.</outcome>
      <timepoint>At week 12. 
Participants will be required to attend the clinic at week 12. Urine, throat swabs and anal swabs will be taken by the clinicians for gonorrhoea and chlamydia screening. Blood will be taken for HIV and syphilis serology. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Acceptability of using mouthwash daily as an intervention to prevent pharyngeal gonorrhoea. This will be assessed using questionnaire. This questionnaire is designed by the principal investigator and has been reviewed and revised by several associate investigators. </outcome>
      <timepoint>At week 12. 
Participants will be required to complete a questionnaire. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Men who self-report having sex with another man and aged 16 years or above.
2. Men who fulfil one of the following criteria:
(a) Aged 16-24 years old, tested positive or negative for pharyngeal gonorrhoea by nucleic acid amplification test (NAAT) detection or treated 30 days prior to the enrolment ; OR
(b) Aged 25 years or above, tested positive for pharyngeal gonorrhoea by nucleic acid amplification test (NAAT) detection or treated 30 days prior to the enrolment. 
3. Men who provide consent to contact their GP to clarify the use and name of antibiotics over the 12-week study period  .
4. Men who have sufficient English language proficiency to understand the requirements of the study and complete the questionnaire.
5. Men who are willing and able to complete the study procedures. 
6. Men who are able to provide written informed consent to the study. 
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>16</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Males</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Men who will be away for more than 3 weeks within the next 12 weeks.
2. Men who report known contraindications to use mouthwash or food dye such as allergy.
3. Men who report use of long-term use of antibiotics for more than 4 weeks.
4. Men who use mouthwash regularly and are not willing to only use the study mouthwash within the next 12 weeks.
5. Transgender individuals.
6. Men who have previously enrolled in the OMEGA study. 
7. Men who are not able to provide consent to contact their GP to clarify the use and name of antibiotics over the 12-week study period. 
8. Men who have a member living in the household is on the OMEGA study. </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>This is a double-blind, controlled RCT study. A trial biostatistician, who has no clinical input into the trial, will generate and hold the random number sequence. The randomisation sequence will be computer generated using a small block size.</concealment>
    <sequence>A randomisation ratio of 1:1 will be used, with no stratification. The randomisation list will be used to label the two trial mouthwash with a study identification number (SIN). Eligible participants who consent will be allocated to their randomised arm and will be given the next available SIN which will then define their study treatment. If any participants withdraw from the trial before receiving any study treatment, their SIN will not be reused. Only the trial biostatistician will be aware of which mouthwashes are interventions and which are controls, and only the trial biostatistician will have access to whether individual participants are on the intervention or control arm. Participants, clinicians, research nurses, and other trial staff will not know which mouthwash the participant is randomised to. The sequence will be generated by computer software (i.e. Stata).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>No</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Data will be analysed in Stata. The primary analysis will be an intention to treat analysis for all those with at least once follow up swab. 

Primary analysis: The primary end point will be the proportion of men who have gonorrhoea detected in the pharynx or saliva by any method at 3, 6, 9 or 12 weeks or at any time between 3 and 12 weeks outside of these 4 tests. The proportion of men with pharyngeal gonorrhoea detected will be summarised using exact binomial confidence internals. The two study arms will be compared using logistic regression. While randomisation should ensure balance of baseline characteristics, if there are any differences in baseline characteristics, including age, follow-up time and sexual behaviours throughout trial, a logistic regression will be performed to adjust for these factors.

Secondary analysis: A sensitivity analysis will also be performed comparing treatment arms in terms of gonorrhoea detection at 3, 6, 9 or 12 weeks using repeated measures logistic regression methods. A secondary analysis will also be undertaken for those who have adhered to high levels of mouthwash use. The number of days using mouthwash will be calculated for each participant, and summarised by treatment arm as median and interquartile range. A high level adherence to mouthwash will be defined as men who use a mouthwash more than 50% of the time over the 12-week period (i.e. use a mouthwash for at least 42 days). Although our pilot data showed that the adherence of mouthwash was more than 90% but it was over a 14-day period, we hypothesized that this proportion may drop to 50% over a 12-week period. 

We have therefore powered the trial to detect a 50% reduction in the gonorrhoea detection rate from 20% in the 'control' arm to 10% in the 'treatment' arm. To detect this reduction with 80% power would require 438 men to be randomised (219 to each arm), with continuity corrections. To allow for up to 15% loss of follow up, we will recruit a total of 504 men, 252 in each group. 
 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/03/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>31/03/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>29/12/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>504</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>VIC</recruitmentstate>
    <postcode>3053 - Carlton</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Alfred Health</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>55 Commercial Rd, Melbourne VIC 3004</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1, 16 Marcus Clarke Street, Canberra, ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Men who have sex with men tested positive for pharyngeal gonorrhoea at Melbourne Sexual Health Centre (MSHC) who volunteer will be randomised to rinse and gargle the study mouthwash every day within the next 12 weeks. The primary outcome is the proportion of MSM with diagnosed with pharyngeal gonorrhoea within 12 weeks.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.mshc.org.au/omega</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Alfred Hospital Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>The Alfred, PO Box 315, Prahran Victoria 3181</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>29/16</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>19/01/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eric Chow</name>
      <address>Melbourne Sexual Health Centre, 
580 Swanston Street, Carlton, VIC 3053, Australia</address>
      <phone>+613-9341-6233</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>echow@mshc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Sandra Walker</name>
      <address>Melbourne Sexual Health Centre, 
580 Swanston Street, Carlton, VIC 3053, Australia</address>
      <phone>+613-9341-6247</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>SWalker@mshc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eric Chow</name>
      <address>Melbourne Sexual Health Centre, 
580 Swanston Street, Carlton, VIC 3053, Australia</address>
      <phone>+613-9341-6233</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>echow@mshc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Eric Chow</name>
      <address>Melbourne Sexual Health Centre, 
580 Swanston Street, Carlton, VIC 3053, Australia</address>
      <phone>+613-9341-6233</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>echow@mshc.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>