<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="362717">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/07/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/07/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000725864</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Financial Intervention for Smoking Cessation Among Low-Income Smokers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised controlled trial examining the effectiveness of a smoking cessation intervention (financial counselling, free Nicotine Replacement Therapy (NRT) and Quitline support) versus free NRT and Quitline support only on reducing smoking in socioeconomically disadvantaged groups</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>Nil</utrn>
    <trialacronym>FISCALS</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Tobacco Addiction/Smoking Cessation</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Epidemiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The intervention group will receive four telephone-based financial counselling sessions with a qualified financial counsellor who has been trained to be sensitive to smoking cessation issues. Each financial counselling session will be 1 hour in duration and will be conducted on an approximately weekly basis over 4-weeks following baseline. The sessions will focus on three key areas: budgeting, money management and financial goal setting. This will include personalised expense assessments; education on the relationship between financial strain and smoking; advice on bill tracking and how to deal with debts; discussion of financial goals and targeted advice on how to achieve identified goals; and education on frugal living strategies. All intervention participants will also be provided with a personalised budget, including a if you didnt smoke scenario following their initial session, which will be reviewed and discussed at subsequent sessions. In addition, the intervention group will concurently receive the usual gold practice standard intervention including 10-weeks free Nicotine Replacement Therapy (NRT) and call-back support from Quitline commencing following baseline. Participants will nominate their preferred form of NRT, which will be mailed to them by the research team. Dosage will be determined based on the level of nicotine dependence at baseline as measured using the Heaviness of Smoking Index. In addition, participants will receive one on one telephone-based call-back support from Quitline advisors who will provide advice, support and information on smoking cessation. Standard elements of telephone-based cessation counselling include: negotiating a quit date, monitoring and motivating use of NRT, arranging social support and self-reward for abstinence. The number of Quitline counselling sessions each participant engages in and the duration of contact with Quitline will be recorded for each participant.</interventions>
    <comparator>The control group will be given only the usual gold practice standard intervention comprising 10-weeks free Nicotine Replacement Therapy and call-back support from Quitline (as described above).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported sustained abstinence from smoking, reported as having quit at each follow-up with no reported smoking at all in the last week. This will be assessed via telephone-based interviews with researchers.</outcome>
      <timepoint>2-months post-baseline and 6-months post-quit date</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in self-reported financial stress measured using the Index of Financial Stress (Siahpush &amp; Carlin, 2003)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2-months post-baseline and 6-months post-quit date</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Quality of Adjusted Life Years (QALYs) as measured by the EQ-5D</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2-months post-baseline and 6-months post-quit date</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in psychological stress using the Depression Anxiety Stress Scale - 21 (DASS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Baseline, 2-months post-baseline and 6-months post-quit date</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Current daily smokers (at least 10 cigarettes/day); ability to read and understand English; currently in receipt of government benefits; motivated to quit smoking; agree to receive help to quit; willing to make an attempt to quit; willing to consent to and complete research tasks, not currently taking smoking medication (e.g. Champix)</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Currently enrolled in a smoking cessation trial; unable to read/understand English language study materials; no home or mobile telephone; not willing to make an attempt to quit smoking; currently taking smoking medication (e.g. Champix)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruitment advertisements will invite smokers who are interested in participation to call a dedicated study phone number for more information. During the initial call, each prospective participant will be screened for eligibility. Eligible participants will then be provided with information about the project over the telephone and will be asked if they are interested in participating. If so, all eligible and willing participants will be asked to provide informed verbal consent to participate. Those consenting to participate will be asked to provide their current contact details to make an appointment for the research team to call them approximately one week later for their first interview. All participants will be randomised at their first interview, one week following recruitment. Allocation concealment will be achieved via central computer-based randomisation.</concealment>
    <sequence>A computer generated block randomisation strategy will be employed.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>N/A</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/10/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>8/04/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>19/12/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1046</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Professor Richard Mattick</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of New South Wales
Sydney, NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Kristy Martire</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychology
University of New South Wales
Sydney, NSW 2052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Billie Bonevski</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Medicine and Public Health
University of Newcastle
Callaghan, NSW 2308</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Ron Borland</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Cancer Council Victoria 
1 Rathdowne St
Carlton Vic 3053</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Christopher Doran</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Medicine and Public Health
University of Newcastle
Callaghan, NSW 2308</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Wayne Hall</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>University of Queensland Centre for Clinical Research
University of Queensland 
Herston, QLD, 4029</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Michael Farrell</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of New South Wales
Sydney, NSW 2052</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In recent years there has been a national decline in smoking rates however, this reduction is least evident among the most disadvantaged sector of the Australian population. This is mainly attributable to lower levels of quit success among disadvantaged groups rather than differences in quit intentions or attempts. Recent research has shown that financial stress is a major barrier to sustained smoking cessation among socioeconomically disadvantaged smokers, even after controlling for nicotine addiction, psychological stress, and use of cessation counselling and pharmacotherapies.  The aim of this project is to test an innovative approach to improving smoking cessation outcomes among low socioeconomic status (SES) smokers by providing financial counselling to reduce the financial stress experienced by disadvantaged smokers making quit attempts. This will be achieved by conducting a randomised controlled trial comparing cessation rates between low SES smokers who receive subsidised nicotine replacement therapy (NRT) with a Quitline call-back with those who receive subsidised NRT and Quitline call-back plus financial counselling. Smoking outcomes will be assessed at 2 and 6 months post-intervention. The results from this project will provide valuable information on the efficacy of targeted interventions for socioeconomically disadvantaged smokers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>University of New South Wales Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Level 3, Rupert Myers Building South Wing
UNSW Kensington Campus NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/07/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HC12318</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/06/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Professor Richard Mattick</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of New South Wales
Sydney, NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 9385 0333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.mattick@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ryan Courtney</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of New South Wales
Sydney, NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 8936 1004</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.courtney@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Philip Clare</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of New South Wales
Sydney, NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 8936 1247</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>p.clare@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Richard Mattick</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre University of New South Wales Sydney, NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+61 (02) 9385 0333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>r.mattick@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>