<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369166">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/09/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/01/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000075482</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Effects of Positive End-Expiratory Pressure on Cross-Sectional Area of  Internal Jugular Vein in Obese Patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The effect of the positive end expiratory pressure on the change in size of the right internal jugular vein to exhibit optimal position for internal jugular vein catheterization in preoperative, mechanically ventilated obese patients.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obese patients undergoing elective surgery under endotracheal intubation will be included in this random, prospective, clinical study</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>72 obese adult patients (BMI&gt;30 kg/m2) with ASA status II-III between 18 and 65 years age old  who were scheduled for elective surgery under general anesthesia were enrolled in the study.  In the operating room all patients recevied a balanced hydroxyethyl starch solution, (HES 130/0.4/6%; Voluven, Fresenius Kabi),6 ml/kg of the calculated ideal body weight (IBW), over 15 minute before induction of anesthesia. All anaesthetics administered were given as part of standard care. Anesthesia was induced with propofol 1.5-2.5 mg/kg of lean body weight(LBW) and fentanil 2-3 mcg/kg of LBW and rocuronium 0.6-1.2 mg/kg of IBW. Anesthesia was maintained with sevoflurane in air:oxygen mixture (50: 50) to keep a target MAC of 0.8 during the image recordings and data collection to reduce possible hypotension due to anesthesia without surgical stimulation. Lungs were ventilated in a volume-controlled mode with tidal volume of 7 ml/kg IBW. All of the measurements were performed in &lt;20degree contralateral neck rotation. The cross-sectional area  (CSA) of right internal jugular vein (IJV) measured at the level of the cricoid cartilage using a two-dimensional ultrasound machine with a 10-MHz linear probe (Mindray M5 'Registered Trademark, Shenzhen). Probe was placed perpendicular to the skin with minimal pressure to ensure that the examined vein was not compressed. While the probe was held in the proper position an investigator manipulated the ventilator 3 different conditions according to the order of the randomly assigned sequence:
1-a baseline condition without Positive end-expiratory pressure (PEEP) (P0), 
2-a PEEP of 5 cm H2O(P5), 
3-a PEEP of 12 cm H2O(P12).
Randomization was achieved using the Orthoganol Latin Square Design method.  Each PEEP condition is administered for one minutes and the ultrasound images were obtained at least 3 seconds after instituting each maneuver for 10 seconds. Images capture timing of the study was considered as a washout time.  The same practitioner performed all ultrasound examinations. Following measurements were calculated at each condition using preloaded software installed in the ultrasound machine by an independent observer who was blinded to the study protocol; 
1-CSA of the right IJV,
2-Transvers diamater(TD) and anteroposterior diameter(APD) of the IJV, 
3-Margin of safety(MOS)(defined as the distance from the lateral most border of the IJV and the lateral-most border of the carotid artery(CA) at which the IJV could be punctured without touching the CA).
4-Depth of the IJV from the skin(measured by drawing a line between the skin and the closest margin of the vein to the skins surface), 
5-Degree of overlap(categorized on the basis of the percentage of overlap; 
      1- 0%(no overlap); 
      2- IJV overlapped&lt;25% of the diameter of the CA; 
      3- IJV overlapped 2550% of the diameter of the CA; 
      4- IJV overlapped&gt;50% of the diameter of the CA.

</interventions>
    <comparator>Different PEEP values; 0, 5 and 12 cm H2O PEEP levels. PEEP 0 will act as the control arm.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary aim of this  study was to investigate changes in CSA of the right IJV during different PEEP levels in anesthetized obese patients using ultrasound.. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Image records were obtained after induction of anesthesia and before surgical start. CSA measurements were performed later from recorded images</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome measure was the transverse  diameter of the right IJV at 0 cm H2O PEEP, 5 cm H2O and 12 cm H2O PEEP levels. Transverse  diameter assessed using ultrasound.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Image records were obtained after induction of anesthesia and before the surgical start. Transverse  diameter  measurements were performed later from recorded images</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome measure was the anteroposterior diameter of the right IJV at 0 cm H2O PEEP, 5 cm H2O and 12 cm H2O PEEP levels. Anteroposterior diameter assessed using ultrasound.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>Image records were obtained after induction of anesthesia and before the surgical start. Anteroposterior diameter measurements were performed later from recorded images</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome measure was the overlap between the right IJV and carotid artery at 0 cm H2O PEEP, 5 cm H2O and 12 cm H2O PEEP levels which assessed using ultrasound.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Image records were obtained after induction of anesthesia and before the surgical start. The overlap between the right IJV and carotid artery measurements were performed later from recorded images</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome measure was the margin of the safety at 0 cm H2O PEEP, 5 cm H2O and 12 cm H2O PEEP levels which assessed using ultrasound.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Image records were obtained after induction of anesthesia and before the surgical start. The margin of the safety measurements were performed later from recorded images</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Obese adult patients (body mass index &gt;30 kg/m2) with American Society of Anesthesiologists(ASA) status II-III between 18 and 65 years age old  who were scheduled for elective surgery under general anesthesia were enrolled in the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria were as follows, previous IJV cannulation, thrombosis of IJV, anatomical neck abnormalities, uncontrolled hypertension and diabetes, congestive heart failure, valvular heart disease, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, pulmonary hypertension. Patients who experienced  severe hypotension (mean arterial blood pressure (MAP) of 30% below the baseline value) and bradycardia (heart rate (HR) below 45 beats per min) after induction of anesthesia and/or during the ultrasound measurements were excluded from the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Computer-generated randomization codes were prepared and provided to investigators in sequentially numbered sealed opaque envelopes before induction of general anaesthesia. </concealment>
    <sequence>Computer-generated randomization codes were prepared and provided to investigators in sequentially numbered sealed opaque envelopes before induction of general anaesthesia. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>29/01/2015</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>7/05/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>72</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>72</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Konya Training and Research Hospital   </primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Konya Training and Research Hospital,Clinic of Anesthesiology and Reanimation, 42090, Meram, Konya   </primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Konya Training and Research Hospital   </fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Konya Training and Research Hospital,Clinic of Anesthesiology and Reanimation, 42090, Meram, Konya   </fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Obesity is one of the most important risk factors for complications of internal jugular vein(IJV) cannulation. The efficacy and safety of the positive end-expiratory pressure (PEEP) maneuvers to increase cross-sectional area (CSA) of IJV are still being debate in obese patients. The aim of this prospective randomized ultrasound study was to investigate changes in CSA of the right IJV during different PEEP levels in anesthetized obese patients. 
Seventy two obese patients undergoing various elective surgeries under general endotracheal anesthesia were enrolled. The CSA of the right IJV was measured at PEEP 0 (P0), 5 (P5), and 12 (P12) cm H2O. We defined a greater than or equal 20% increase in the CSA as clinically relevant
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>no</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Selcuk University Institutional Review Board  </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ardicli Quarter, 42250, Selcuklu, Konya,Turkey</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>22/12/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>B.30.2.SEL.0.28.00.00/130 </hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/11/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Turkey</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Betul Kozanhan</name>
      <address>Konya Training and Research Hospital, Clinic of Anesthesiology and Reanimation, Meram, Konya Postcode:42090</address>
      <phone>+90 332 221 00 00</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>betulkozanhan@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Seza Apiliogullari</name>
      <address>Selcuk University Faculty of Medicine Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation Postalcode:42250
Selcuklu/Konya/TURKEY</address>
      <phone>+90 332 223 6000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drsezaapili@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Seza Apiliogullari</name>
      <address>Selcuk University Faculty of Medicine Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation Postalcode:42250
Selcuklu/Konya/TURKEY</address>
      <phone>+90 332 223 6000</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drsezaapili@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>