<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82480">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/12/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>20/12/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000649415</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Evaluation of Dysfunctional Patellar Misalignment at the passage from the supine to the sitting position and vice versa in patients with a negative anamnesis for muscular or bone-relevant trauma.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Evaluation of Dysfunctional Patellar Misalignment at the passage from the supine to the sitting position and vice versa in patients with a negative anamnesis for muscular or bone-relevant trauma.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PFD</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Dysfunctional patellar misalignment</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other muscular and skeletal disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Slight somatic differences, when not due to specific causes, prove the existence of Fluctuating Asymmetry (FA). FAs are defined as a casual loss of perfect symmetry, highlighted at level of symmetrical body segments and caused by environmental stressors. They are inversely related with the general psycho-physical condition of the subject. In this study that has involved in eight years 3700 subjects, we have highlighted and described the presence of asymmetry both in tonic and phasic activation of symmetrical muscular groups. We named this asymmetrical activation as Functional Dysmetria (FD). We might assume that FD is determined by a neuropsychomotor attitude deriving from the adaptation at environmental stress, as observed for FAs. We could also suppose that the asymmetrical tonic and phasic activation of symmetrical muscular groups may determine those alterations of structural charge, this causing those modifications in skeleton morphology typical of FAs. The observation has been carried out with subject in supine position, in sitting position, during the passage from supine to sitting position and vice versa. So as to quantify misalignment and then FD, we employed a not invasive calibre that we have specifically devised, with 1-mm-resolution. The measurements, were taken with the subject in supine position, in sitting position. After each check the subject was asked to descend the bed and walk a dozen steps; afterwards they laid down again on the bed for a new survey. All this was repeated three consecutive times for each subject.</interventions>
    <comparator>No treatment. Between each consecutive observation and measurement we took five minutes and we took fifteen minutes after the first and second session.</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The observation of the presence of asymmetrical both in tonic and phasic activation of symmetrical muscular groups and patellar misalignment at the passage from the supine to the sitting position and vice versa and the quantification of this misalignment with a non invasive calibre that we have specifically devised, with 1-mm-resolution.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The observational and measurement trial consisted of two following sessions.  In every session we have take three observations and measurements: immediately, after five minutes the second and after other five minutes the third session. The second session like the first one was carried out after fifteen minutes.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Detect  the presence  of patellar misalignment at the passage from the supine to the sitting position and vice versa and the quantification of this misalignment with a non invasive calibre that we have specifically devised, with 1-mm-resolution.</outcome>
      <timepoint>The observational and measurement trial consisted of two following sessions.  In every session we have take three observations and measurements: immediately, after five minutes the second and after other five minutes the third session. The second session like the first one was carried out after fifteen minutes.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy subjects, with a negative anamnesis for muscular or bone-relevant trauma and patologies during the last 2 years</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>2</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>97</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Subjects, with positive anamnesis for muscular or bone-relevant trauma in the last 2 years. Congenital malformation and other musculoskeletal or neurologically-known pathologies</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Screening</purposeobs>
    <duration>Cross-sectional</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Prospective</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/09/1997</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>3700</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Istituto Rinaldi Fontani</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Via Nazionale 23 50123 Firenze</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Italy</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Istituto Rinaldi Fontani</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Via Nazionale 23 50123 Firenze</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Italy</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Societa di Ottimizzazione Neuro Psico Fisica e CRM Terapia</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Via Nazionale 23 50123 Firenze</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Italy</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>It is generally agreed that, in absence of orthopaedic pathologies, a misalignment of certain body segments may be highlighted in a certain group of examined subjects. These misalignments are especially evident at level of  pelvis and Lower Limbs (LLs). This observation lead us to believe that this was an ordinary phenomenon of  postural neuropsychomotor attitude, consequence of a dysfunctional adaptation to environmental stress, exactly as for Fluctuating Asymmetry. Through the observation of a wide sample of 3700 subjects, we could detect the presence of an asymmetry in tonic and phasic activation of  symmetrical muscular groups in LLs. This activation will show through a misalignment of upper and lower right and left patellar margins, misalignment which will invert by moving from supine to sitting position while the subject is lying on the visiting bed . We named this phenomenon as Functional Dysmetria (FD), which we believe to be upheld by postural neuropsychomotor mechanisms, as expression of a dysfunctional adaptive attitude in response to the interaction between subject and environment. FD may be compared to an actual difference in length of LLs, but not necessarily is to be associated  with a real heterometry, from which it must therefore be kept aside. We chose the definition of Dysmetria to underline both the dysfunctional (from the Greek d?? = difficulty to perform, and µ?t??? = measurement) and functional components, as the phenomenon is apparently not the consequence of organic injuries. In conclusion, the analysis of the results shows that  every examined subject had both the misalignment of the considered reperes and a FD of LLs, highlighted at the passage from the supine to the sitting position and vice versa. The average value of misalignment is 6.21 mm (StDev = 0.38). The values of misalignment vary among subjects and are not related to age or sex. Furthermore, the examined values do not modify upon repositioning of the subject and are stable in time.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Salvatore Rinaldi M.D.</name>
      <address>Via Nazionale 23 50123 Firenze</address>
      <phone>+39 055 290307</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>srinaldi@irf.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Vania Fontani M.D.</name>
      <address>Via Nazionale 23 50123 Firenze</address>
      <phone>+39 055 290307</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vfontani@irf.it</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>