<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="83809">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/04/2009</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>22/05/2009</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12609000336280</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Basal-bolus insulin versus sliding scale insulin for managing blood sugar levels in hospitalized diabetic patients</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Hospitalized diabetic patients undergoing basal-bolus insulin versus sliding scale management for control of blood glucose levels</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Inpatient blood glucose management</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Basal-bolus insulin management via subcuteous injection is now recommended for inpatient glycaemic control. This replaces the old subcutaneous injection sliding scale insulin management approach. This study will prospectively collect performance data around a basal-bolus insulin approach developed at this hospital and compare it to retrospective data around the use of sliding scale insulin management at the hospital. Four times daily capillary blood glucose will be recorded in each group.
Subcutaneous sliding scale insulin is initiated at the doctors discretion and the quantitative adjustment within the sliding scale is empirical, depending on what insulin doses the doctor feels are appropriate for that particular patient. Frequency of insuin administration is generally four times daily but may vary. This is continued until either discharge or the treating doctor feels the patient will maintain satisfactory glycaemic control without sliding scale insulin intervention, with a maximum data collection of 1 week. This data will be collected retrospectively as the hospital has now switched over to a basal-bolus insulin management approach.
The basal-bolus insulin management (via subcutaneous injection) is  intiated at the discretion of the treating doctor. An initial daily insulin dose is calculated according to set criteria, and 50% of this is then divided into a basal (glargine) dose administered once daily and 50% to rapid-acting insulin split into bolus doses three times daily prior to each meal +/- a small dose of correctional insulin depending on the blood glucose level at the time. This is continued until either discharge or the treating doctor feels the patient will maintain satisfactory glycaemic control without basal-bolus insulin intervention, with a maximum data collection of 1 week.</interventions>
    <comparator>Patients previously admitted to the hospital who had glycaemic control managed using sliding scale insulin. Data will be collected from the period January 06 to August 07</comparator>
    <control>Historical</control>
    <interventioncode>Not applicable</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mean daily blood glucose. This is taken by using the mean of the routine four times daily capillary blood glucose readings taken by nursing staff for each patient, using a standardized point-of-care glucometer. The study is powered to detect a mean daily difference of 2mmol/L.Comparison will be via Student t-test</outcome>
      <timepoint>Capillary blood glucose performed four times daily. Patients maintained on either basal-bolus or sliding scale at doctors discretion, usually 3-14 days.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Daily proportion of blood glucose readings in desirable range (4-10mmol/L).This is calculated by utilising the routine four times daily capillary blood glucose readings taken by nursing staff for each patient, using a standardized point-of-care glucometer. Comparison will be via Chi-square.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Capillary blood glucose performed four times daily. Patients maintained on either basal-bolus or sliding scale at doctors discretion, usually 3-14 days.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Any diabetic patient admitted to the hospital requiring either basal-bolus insulin or sliding scale insulin for intensification of glycaemic control.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>None</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Observational</studytype>
    <purpose />
    <allocation />
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs>Natural history</purposeobs>
    <duration>Longitudinal</duration>
    <selection>Convenience sample</selection>
    <timing>Both</timing>
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2009</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>158</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Repatriation General Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Daws Road
Daw Park, SA 5041</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Sanofi-Aventis</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>12-24 Talavera Road 
Macquarie Park
NSW 2113</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Government body</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>South Australian Department of Health</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Grenfell St
Adelaide SA 5000</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>While basal-bolus insulin management is preferred over sliding scale for glycaemic control of hospitalised diabetics requiring intensified glycaemic control, there are no recommended basal-bolus approaches, and little data comparing the 2 approaches. The development of our basal-bolus approach requires testing to ensure its clinical efficacy, and that it is actually a better practice than sliding scale insulin. The main comparator will be the mean daily glucose readings taken from the routine four times daily capillary blood glucose measurements.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Repatriation General Hospital Research and Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Road
Daw Park, SA 5041</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/12/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>AUD020/07GR</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Greg Roberts</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Dept
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Rd, Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751632</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>greg.roberts2@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Greg Roberts</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Dept
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Rd, Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751632</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>greg.roberts2@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Greg Roberts</name>
      <address>Pharmacy Dept
Repatriation General Hospital
Daws Rd, Daw Park SA 5041</address>
      <phone>+61 8 82751632</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>greg.roberts2@health.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>