<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363799">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>1/03/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>4/03/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000252718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Pain Course: A Randomised Controlled Trial assessing the efficacy and acceptability of an Internet Delivered-Treatment Program for Managing Chronic Pain provided with different levels of clinical support.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Pain Course: A Randomised Controlled Trial assessing an Internet Delivered-Treatment Program for Managing Chronic Pain provided with different levels of clinical support. </scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Chronic Pain
</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Anxiety</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of four groups: (1) a clinician-initiated contact group, (2) a participant-initiated contact group, (3) a self-guided group, and a (4) waitlist control group, who begin the program as soon as the treatments group finish the program. All participants will meet diagnostic criteria for chronic pain (i.e. pain lasting longer than 6 months). All participants will complete 5 lessons of Internet based treatment about management of symptoms of chronic pain and anxiety, depression and disability associated with pain. One lesson will be completed every 7 to 10 days. Each lesson will take about 15 minutes to complete. Participants will also have access to summaries of each lesson, and will read anonymous stories about other people with chronic pain, taking a further 20 minutes per summary. 

Participants in the clinician-initiated contact group group will receive weekly telephone calls or emails from a trained and supervised Psychologist at the eCentreClinic to provide support, encouragement and to answer questions about the content of the Course. Participants in the participant-initiated contact group will receive exactly the same materials and content except, instead of being contact by a clinican, they will have the option to contact or request contact with the eCentreClinic Psychologist themselves.  In contrast, those in the Self-Guided Group will not receive contact with the Psychologist during the Course. In all other respects the Courses are identical. Participants in the waitlist control group will receive access to the Course after the treatment groups finish and will be provided with participant-initiated contact.

The duration of the program is 8 weeks. Study questionnaires will be administered at application, pre-treatment, post-treatment, and at 3, 12 and 24 month follow-up. Some questionnaires will be administered weekly during the Course. The major sets of questionnaires will take about 10 to 15 minutes to complete. The treatment materials are based on previous internet-based programs, which apply cognitive behavioural techniques.</interventions>
    <comparator>A waitlist control group who begin the treatment immediately after the treatment groups complete the Course.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Roland Morris Disability Questionnaire (RMDQ), which measures disability associated with pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Application, pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3, 12 and 24 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient Health Questionnaire 9-Item (PHQ9), which is a measure of depression.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Application, pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3, 12 and 24 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-Item (GAD7), which is a measure of anxiety.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Application, pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3, 12 and 24 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Wisconsin Brief Pain Questionnaire (WBPQ), which is a general measure of the nature of participants pain including location, severity and duration.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Application, pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3, 12 and 24 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain Things You Do Questionnaire (PTYDQ), which is a measure of helpful cognitive and behavioural skill use.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment, post-treatment and 3, 12 and 24 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Employment and health service use will be measured by the Employment and Health Service Use Questionnaire</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment and 3, 12 and 24 month follow-up.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Pain Self-Efficacy Questionnaire (PSEQ), which is a measure of peoples' beliefs about their ability to do daily activities despite pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment and post-treatment. That is, immediately prior to participants starting the Course and 9 weeks later, immediately after the Course finishes.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Tampa Scale of Kinesiophobia (TAMPA), which measures fear of movement because of pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment and post-treatment. That is, immediately prior to participants starting the Course and 9 weeks later, immediately after the Course finishes.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Chronic Pain Acceptance Questionnaire 8-item (CPAQ8), which measures acceptance of chronic pain.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-treatment and post-treatment. That is, immediately prior to participants starting the Course and 9 weeks later, immediately after the Course finishes.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>- Has experienced Chronic Pain (i.e. Pain &gt; 6 months)
- Internet access + Printer access
- Australian resident
- Has had their pain assessed by their GP or medical specialist.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>100</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Active psychosis
- Pain not assessed by GP
- Severe depression, suicidal intent or plan (PHQ-9 total score &gt; 22)</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Participants apply online via the clinic's website (www.ecentreclinic.org.au). Successful applications are followed by a telephone interview to confirm suitability for the trial. Randomisation will occur prior to application and concealment occurs through the use of  locked and concealed cells in a spreadsheet, which recruitment staff are required to open serially.</concealment>
    <sequence>Participants will be randomized using a list generated prior to the study via a software program (www.random.org) using permuted block randomisation. </sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>False</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>5/03/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>14/03/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>10/04/2014</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>450</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up continuing</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>ACT,NSW,NT,QLD,SA,TAS,WA,VIC</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Macquarie University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>eCentreClinic, The Centre For Emotional Health (CEH), Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109, Australia.
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Motor Accidents Authority of New South Wales</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Motor Accidents Authority of NSW
Address:	Motor Accidents Authority
Level 25, 580 George Street
Sydney NSW 2000, Australia
DX: DX 1517 SYDNEY
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 1
16 Marcus Clarke Street
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Associate Professor Nick Titov</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109, Australia.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Dr Kathryn Nicholson Perry</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychology, University of Western Sydney, locked bag 1797, Penrith South DC, NSW 2751, Australia</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Ms Milena Gandy</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109, Australia.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Louise Sharpe</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>School of Psychology, Sydney University, Brennan MacCallum Building, NSW, 2006.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>Individual</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Professor Michael Nicholas</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Anaesthesia, Northern Clinical School, Kolling Institute of Medical Research, Royal North Shore Hospital, The University of Sydney, NSW 2006.</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>Australia</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>This project builds on an earlier project and seeks to examine the efficacy and acceptability of the Pain Course when provided with different levels of clinical support. We expect that people in the treatment groups will report similar levels of clinical benefit and acceptability.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>www.ecentreclinic.org</trialwebsite>
    <publication>- Dear, B. F., Titov, N., Nicholson Perry, K., Johnston, L., Wootton, B. M., Terides, M. D., Rapee, R. M., &amp; Hudson, J. L. (submitted). The Pain Course: A randomised controlled trial of clinician-guided internet-delivered cognitive behaviour therapy program for managing chronic pain and emotional wellbeing. 
- Johnston, L., Titov, N., Andrews, G., Dear, B. F., &amp; Spence, J. (submitted). Comorbidity and internet-delivered transdiagnostic cognitive behavioural therapy for anxiety disorders. Cognitive Behaviour Therapy. 
- Dear, B. F., Titov, N., Schwencke, G., Andews, G., Johnston, L., Craske, M. G., &amp; McEvoy, P. (2011). An open trial of a brief transdiagnostic treatment for anxiety and depression. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 49, 830-837. 
- Johnston, L., Titov, N., Andrews, G., Spence, J., &amp; Dear, B.F. (2011). A RCT of a transdiagnostic internet-delivered treatment for three anxiety disorders: Examination of support roles and disorder-specific outcomes. PLoS ONE 6(11): e28079. 
- Titov N., Dear B.F., Schwencke G., Andrews G., Johnston L., Craske M., &amp; McEvoy, P. (2011). Transdiagnostic Internet treatment of anxiety and depression: A randomised controlled trial. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 49, 441-452.
- Titov, N., Andrews, G., Johnston, L., Robinson, E., &amp; Spence, J. (2010). Transdiagnostic Internet treatment for anxiety disorders: A randomized controlled trial. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 48, 890-899. </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Macquarie University, HUman Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Human Research Ethics Committee
Level 3, Research Hub, Building C5C, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109.</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/02/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>5201200872</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blake F. Dear</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic, The Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109.</address>
      <phone>61 2 9850 9979</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9850 8062</fax>
      <email>blake.dear@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blake F. Dear</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic, The Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109.</address>
      <phone>61 2 9850 9979</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9850 8062</fax>
      <email>blake.dear@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blake F. Dear</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic, The Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109.</address>
      <phone>61 2 9850 9979</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9850 8062</fax>
      <email>blake.dear@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Blake F. Dear</name>
      <address>eCentreClinic, The Centre for Emotional Health, Department of Psychology, Macquarie University, NSW, 2109.</address>
      <phone>61 2 9850 9979</phone>
      <fax>61 2 9850 8062</fax>
      <email>blake.dear@mq.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>