<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82819">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>15/05/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/05/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000252314</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cancer care after surgery  the CONNECT study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A randomised trial to assess the effectiveness of a centralised telephone-based remote access care coordination service to improve care processes and patient outcomes for people who have had surgery for colorectal cancer</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Colorectal cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Bowel - Back passage (rectum) or large bowel (colon)</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>A centralised telephone-based remote access cancer care coordination intervention, administered by a cancer nurse. After submitting a self-complete questionnaire at baseline (just prior to, or in the days following, surgery for colorectal cancer), participants will be randomised into the intervention or control group.  Patients in the intervention group will receive the nursing care coordination and support service telephone calls from the cancer nurse at 3 days, 10 days, 1 month, 3 months, and 6 months after their discharge from hospital.</interventions>
    <comparator>Usual care (regular standard follow-up appointments with the patients surgeon, general practitioner [GP], oncologist (if applicable), radiologist (if applicable).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Care coordination (as measured by a self-complete multiple-choice questionnaire we developed in the pilot study for this project)</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, then 1, 3 and 6 months after discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Quality of life (as measured by the self-complete FACT-C questionnaire).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, then 1, 3 and 6 months after discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Health service utilisation (as measured by a self-complete questionnaire about frequency of visits to a range of health professionals including the surgeon, general practitioner, oncologist, radiologist. Also measured by determining number of attendances at GP, hospital admissions, and emergency department attendances from medical records).</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, then 1, 3 and 6 months after discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost effectiveness of the telephone intervention. A cost consequence analysis will be conducted whereby the net difference in costs associated with the intervention and health service utilisation between the intervention and control groups will be compared to the net difference in the primary outcome measures. The cost data will be collected via self completed questionnaires about health service utilisation (and other outcomes described above).</outcome>
      <timepoint>1, 3 and 6 months after discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Satisfaction with health services (as measured by the self-complete FACIT-TS-PS questionnaire).</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months after discharge from hospital</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients who:
* Are aged 18 years or more
* Are having surgery for a newly diagnosed primary colorectal cancer (Dukes stage A-D)
* Are aware of cancer diagnosis
* Are able to understand the study and give consent</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients who:
* Are diagnosed with recurrent colorectal cancer
* Die during the admission
* Are cognitively impaired or cannot give informed consent
* Do not have access to a telephone at their primary residence
* Do not plan to reside in Australia for the next 6 months
* Are hearing impaired to a level that they are unable to participate in a telephone conversation
* Do not speak and read English to a level that would allow them to participate in the telephone discussions and follow-up interviews (unless a family member or friend is able to translate for them).</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Educational / counselling / training</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Surgeons from the participating hospitals will recruit patients for this study. During a pre-surgery consultation (which is usually 1 - 2 weeks prior to surgery), the surgeon will invite the patient to participate in the study. If the patient is an emergency admission, the surgeon will invite them to participate in the study at a suitable time during the patient's post-operative hospital stay. The surgeon will provide the patient with written and verbal information about the study. At baseline (just prior to, or during their hospital stay for colorectal cancer surgery) patients will be asked by their surgeon to complete a questionnaire. The patients will return the questionnaire signed consent forms via reply paid post to the central research office. Once these forms have been received, patients will be randomly allocated to the intervention or control group by the project manager (located in the central research office) who holds the allocation schedule.</concealment>
    <sequence>Simple randomisation by using a randomisation table created by computer software.</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/06/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>720</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>A/Prof Jane Young</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Surgical Outcomes Research Centre
PO Box M157
Missenden Rd
NSW 2050</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Cancer Institute NSW</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 41 
Alexandria
NSW 1435</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Phyllis Butow</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Medical Psychology Research Unit
Brennan MacCallum Building (A19)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Michael Solomon</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Surgical Outcomes Research Centre
PO Box M157
Missenden Rd
NSW 2050</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Glenn Salkeld</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Public Health
Edward Ford Building (A27)
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Prof Kate White</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Faculty of Nursing and Midwifery
Mallet Street Campus
University of Sydney
NSW 2006</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Patients with colorectal cancer are often required to navigate a complex system involving a diverse range of medical, nursing and allied health practitioners in both hospital and community settings. Improving care coordination, patients experience of care and patient outcomes are widely recognised as priorities for the improvement of cancer services.  

A simple strategy that could have wide application for patients in regional and rual Australia as well as those in metropolitan centres is a centralised telephone-based remote access cancer care coordination intervention, administered by a cancer nurse. This strategy will be implemented and evaluated in this study to determine whether it improves care coordination and patient outcomes in the six months following cancer surgery.

Over a period of 2 years, 720 patients who undergo surgery for a newly diagnosed colorectal cancer will be recruited. Participants will be randomised to the intervention or control (usual care) group. Those in the intervention group will receive the nursing care coordination and support service telephone calls from the cancer nurse at 3 days, 10 days, 1 month, 3 months and 6 months after discharge from hospital. Those in the control group will receive courtesy calls only from the research team in the first week following discharge from hospital, and then again at 1 month, 3 months and 6 months following discharge. 

All participants will be asked to complete questionnaires relating to quality of life and psychological distress at baseline (just prior to, or in the days following, surgery for colorectal cancer). They will then complete these questionnaires, as well as additional questions relating to satisfaction with treatment, health service utilisation and care coordination at 1, 3 and 6 months after discharge.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney South West Area Health Service Ethics Review Committee (RPAH Zone)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Development Office, RPAH Medical Centre, 100 Carillon Avenue, Newtown, NSW 2042</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>15/04/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>08/RPAH/138</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>26/03/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>A/Prof Jane Young</name>
      <address>PO Box M157
Missenden Rd
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>02 9515 3200</phone>
      <fax>02 95153222</fax>
      <email>jane.young@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>James Harrison</name>
      <address>Surgical Outcomes Research Centre
PO Box M157
Missenden Rd
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>02 9515 3200</phone>
      <fax>02 95153222</fax>
      <email>james.harrison@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>James Harrison</name>
      <address>PO Box M157
Missenden Rd
NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>02 9515 3200</phone>
      <fax>02 95153222</fax>
      <email>james.harrison@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>