<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82960">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/07/2008</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>1/08/2008</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12608000386336</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Ruling-out Coronary Artery Disease utilising non-invasive investigations in place of Invasive Coronary Angiography: a comparison between Computer Tomography Angiography and Myocardial Perfusion Imaging in patients with an intermediate probability of coronary artery disease</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>In patient groups with an intermediate probability of coronary artery disease is there a difference between computer tomography coronary angiography and myocardial perfusion imaging in ruling out significant coronary artery disease</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RoCAD</trialacronym>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Coronary Artery Disease</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Coronary heart disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Computer Tomography Coronary Angiography (CTCA) or Coronary CT is a new technique which involves injecting dye into an arm vein and performing a specialised x-ray of the heart called a CT scan. While CT scans have been extensively used to image many organs, it is only recently that the technology has evolved to be fast enough to scan a beating heart. It is important for test accuracy that the heart is beating in a regular rhythm so that the scan can give the best results. This means that you will be given a medication (called a beta-blocker) to slow your heart down before the test. These same tablets are regularly used to treat coronary heart disease, and your specialist is very familiar with their use. Like the Nuclear Medicine study, the Coronary CT does not have the coronary angiography hazards associated with the placement of catheters but appears to have similar accuracy to angiography. Patients randomised to the CTCA test will undergo one CTCA.</interventions>
    <comparator>Myocardial Perfusion Imaging involves injecting a radioactive material into the blood via a small needle in the arm or hand after stimulating the heart either by an exercise test or injecting a drug. The heart is then scanned with a specialised camera to see how much of the radioactive material has gone into the heart muscle. If there is a reduced amount of radioactivity in the heart muscle then this implies that there are blockages within the coronary arteries we can then determine approximately how many of the coronary arteries are blocked. This test does not involve the hazards of placing catheters into the coronary arteries and thus is considerably safer than coronary angiography but is also less accurate. Patients randomised to the Myocardial Perfusion Imaging test will undergo just one scan.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The primary endpoint of this study is the number of Invasive Selective Coronary Angiography (ISCA) undertaken in each group within 6 months of the randomised diagnostic test</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post imaging</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total number of additional invasive/non-invasive Coronary Artery Disease (CAD) imaging studies in the 6 months following the randomised diagnostic test.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post imaging</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cardiologist satisfaction as determined by Cardiologist Feedback Form scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 month post imaging</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient satisfaction as determined by Patient Post-test Feedback Form scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>1 and 6 months post imaging</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient 6 month progress as determined by; (a) Patient 6 month Follow-up Form scores, (b) SF-36 physical and mental health summary scores, and (c) Seattle Angina Questionnaire domain scores.</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline and 6 months post imaging</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Cost-effectiveness Evaluation. This will be measured by the number of ISCA studies avoided by undergoing less invasive and costly CTCA scans.</outcome>
      <timepoint>end of study - 6 months after the patients scan (either CTCA of Myocardial Perfusion Imaging)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patient fulfilling all of the following criteria (a, b &amp; c) will be considered: a) Intermediate pre-test probability of CAD (10-70%), ie Men = 40 years without typical angina Women = 60 years without typical angina; b) One of the following clinical presentation: 1) Chest pain with Left Bundle Branch Block (LBBB), or 2) Equivocal exercise test (ie Duke Treadmill Score -10 to 4), or 3) Suspected Dilated Cardiomyopathy (ie Unexplained global left ventricular systolic dysfunction) and c) Treating-cardiologist would undertake ISCA if these non-invasive tests were not available.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with following features will be excluded from the study: 1) Patients with high pre-test probability of CAD ( &gt; 70%), ie those with typical angina, 2) Patients with low pre-test probability of CAD ( &lt; 10%) including those with normal coronary angiography within the past 2 years, 3) Previously Documented CAD, ie. Previous myocardial infarction, Previous revascularisation therapy (Percutanious Coronary Intervention or Coronary Artery Bypass Graft) Previous coronary angiography demonstrating &gt; 50% stenosis or Regional wall motion abnormality 4) Contra-indications to undertaking CTCA or MPI such as: Contrast allergy, Pregnancy, suspected pregnancy, Contra-indications to beta-blockers (asthma), Absence of sinus rhythm, Renal Impairment (Creatinine = 180 umol/L or eGFR &lt; 50ml/min) or Thyroid Stimulating Hormone (TSH) &lt; 0.36 mU/L</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Recruiting Cardiologists identify appropriate patients fulfilling the above criteria
Informed patient consent obtained
Cardiologist contacts QE Imaging Receptionist and notify them of the patient’s participation in the study
The Pre-randomisation Checklist will be completed. Items 1-4 will be completed by the QE Imaging Staff and assign the Patient Identification Code.
Randomisation by QE Imaging Staff using the sealed envelope system. This system utilises a 6 patient block design stratified per referring cardiologist. 
The cardiologist will be informed of the study randomisation and a booking will be made by the QE Imaging Reception for CTCA or Stress MPI as required. The CTCA studies will be booked in for a Friday.
The QE Imaging Reception will notify the Study Co-ordinator as to the patient’s recruitment into the study and forward the Pre-randomisation Checklist.
The Study Co-ordinator will arrange to meet with the patient prior to the diagnostic test to ensure the Pre-randomisation Checklist is completed, including providing the patient with the Patient Information Sheet  and obtaining a signed patient informed consent. Also during this meeting, clinical details for the Case Report Form  will obtained and the patient will complete the quality of life surveys (SF-36 &amp; Seattle Angina Questionnaire).
(PLEASE NOT 'QE' is a correct name, as is SF-36)</concealment>
    <sequence>A total of 50 Computer Tomography Coronary Angiogram (CTCA) and 50 Myocardial Perfusion Imaging (MPI) slips were written and placed into envelops. 5 CTCA and 5 MPI envelops were then labelled with consultant number 1. 3 of each of these two groups were then taken and shuffled and labelled consultant 1, envelop number 1 through 6 and placed in the front of a devided box. The remaining 4 envelops were also shuffled and then labelled consultant 1 number 7 through 10 and placed with the first 6 envelopes. This process was repeated until there were 10 groups of 10 envelops</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/07/2008</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>100</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Woodville Road
Woddville 5011</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>BUPA Australia</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>600 Glenferrie Road
Hawthorn Victoria 3122</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of this study is to assess the clinical applications of the proven diagnostic abilities of Computer Tomography Coronary Angiography (CTCA). Specifically, in patient groups with an intermediate probability of coronary artery disease is there a difference between computer tomography coronary angiography and myocardial perfusion imaging in ruling out significant coronary artery disease.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics of Human Research Committee (TQEH &amp; LMH)</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Woodville Road
Woddville 5011</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/02/2008</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2007154</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>17/01/2008</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>John Beltrame</name>
      <address>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
Cardiology Department
Level 3
Woodville Road
Woodville 5011</address>
      <phone>08 8222 7632</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>john.beltrame@adelaide.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Jennifer Cranefield</name>
      <address>The Queen Elizabeth Hospital
Radiolgy Department
Ground Floor 
Woodville Rad
Woddville 5011</address>
      <phone>08 8222 6894</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>jennifer.cranefield@nwahs.sa.gov.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>