<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81985">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>26/04/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>27/04/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000223437</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A SINGLE CENTER OPEN-LABEL PILOT STUDY TO EVALUATE THE TOLERABILITY AND SAFETY OF A SYNTHETIC SOFT TISSUE IMPLANT MATERIAL IN THE SKIN OF NORMAL VOLUNTEERS</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A single centre open-label pilot study to evaluate the tolerability and safety of the Family C synthetic thermoplastic block copolymer implant as a clinically acceptable dermal filler material in healthy volunteers.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>nil known </secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Tolerability and safety of a new synthetic soft tissue implant material for soft tissue augmentation in healthy volunteers.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other surgery</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Each participant will receive two (diameter - 4.4 mm, thickness ~1 to 2 mm) Test Article implants, placed at the mid-to-deep dermal layer and/or superficial fat junction of their skin.  The implant sites will be selected by the investigator within the anatomic region of the torso (superior pelvic rim to the apex of the shoulders) of each participant.  The skin implant material will be placed by making a small single incision, up to 1.5 cm in length to the level of the mid-to-deep dermis or superficial fat junction, as appropriate.  The implant will then be placed into the incision pocket and sutured closed.  The implants will remain in place for 90 days with follow up visits at days 7, 14, 30, 60 for evaluation and grading of site per protocol.  At day 90 the implants will be excised. All specimens will be submitted for histologic examination. A final visit will occur 30 days post excision for evaluation of the test sites.</interventions>
    <comparator>No control</comparator>
    <control>Uncontrolled</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Other interventions</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety Endpoints:
The number and percentage of participants who develop a positive response to the implant(s).</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants are intructed to observe the test sites daily for any positive response as per protocol.  Participants return for evaluation and grading of the sites on days 7, 14, 30 &amp; 60 and then on day 90 following grading of the implant site, for excision of the implants. A final follow up visit occurs on day 120 for post excision evaluation of the implant sites.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Safety Endpoints: Histologic findings and adverse events will be summarized.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Participants are intructed to observe the test sites daily for any positive response as per protocol.  Participants return for evaluation and grading of the sites on days 7, 14, 30 &amp; 60 and then on day 90 following grading of the implant site, for excision of the implants. A final follow up visit occurs on day 120 for post excision evaluation of the implant sites.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>NIL</outcome>
      <timepoint>NIL</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. In generally good health2. Participants willing and able to comply with the requirements of the study3. Participants willing and able to comply with the follow-up requirements4. Participants willing and able to give informed consent5. Females must be post-menopausal, surgically sterile or willing to use a medically acceptable form of birth control during the study.  Males must be willing to use a medically acceptable form of birth control during the study.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Participants who are pregnant, nursing or intend to become pregnant during the study period2. Participants who were or are currently being treated with any systemic immunosuppressive therapy including but not limited to chemotherapy agents or corticosteroids within the past 3 months. The use of stable doses of inhaled corticosteroids is acceptable.3. Participants who were or are currently being treated with any topical Over The Counter (OTC) drug or prescription therapy on their torso within the past 3 months.4. Participants with skin findings or disease in the proposed implant area that could confound the interpretation of the reactivity of the implant sites.5. Participants with a history indicative of abnormal immune function (e.g. auto-immune diseases, HIV, cancer [other than non-melanoma skin cancer], etc.)6. Participants with known sensitivity to any of the Test Article materials.7. Participants with severe allergies manifested by a history of anaphylaxis.8. Participant is currently enrolled in an investigational drug or device study. 9. Participant has received an investigational drug or treatment with an investigational device within 30 days prior to entering this study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Single group</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/06/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>8</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>COSMETREND PTY LTD</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Po Box 5056,
Greenwich   NSW   2065</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AESTHETIC SCIENCES CORPORATION</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>2995 Woodside Road, Suite 400
Woodside, California 94062</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>United States of America</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>NIL</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary purpose of this pilot study is to assess the clinical tolerability and safety of a new synthetic soft tissue implant material in the skin of healthy volunteers.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>BellBerry Limited</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>12/06/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>Dr Darrell Perkins</name>
      <address>AESTHETIC DAY SURGERY
14 Kensington Street
Kogarah NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95870871</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 95258400</fax>
      <email>info@aestheticdaysurgery.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Brenley Milsom</name>
      <address>ADVANTAGE Medical Products Consulting Pty Ltd 
5 Yatama Place (PO Box 339)
Currumbin Waters QLD 4223</address>
      <phone>+61 7 55224880</phone>
      <fax>+61 7 55224128</fax>
      <email>bmilsom@advantagempc.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Mr</title>
      <name>na</name>
      <address>na</address>
      <phone>na</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>na</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>