<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="369309">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/07/2017</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/07/2017</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12617001003369</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Probenecid and food effects on flucloxacillin pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics in healthy volunteers</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Probenecid and food effects on flucloxacillin pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics in healthy volunteers</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Skin infection</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Infection</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other infectious diseases</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Volunteers were administered flucloxacillin 1000 mg orally on three study days separated by a 7-day washout period.
Arm 1:  Flucloxacillin 1000 mg orally, single dose while fasting
Arm 2:  Flucloxacillin 1000 mg orally plus probenecid 500 mg orally, both single dose while fasting
Arm 3:  Flucloxacillin 1000 mg orally plus probenecid 500 mg orally, both single dose with food
On each study day, participants fasted for eight hours (overnight) but had free access to water.  On fasting days only water could be consumed until two hours after receiving the study medication.  On the fed day, each participant ingested two scrambled eggs made with two tablespoons of milk (full cream), two slices of mixed grain and toasted sesame bread with margarine and 250 mL of orange juice.  Each meal contained 492 kcal of energy, 21.8 g of protein, 22 g of fat and 52.6 g of carbohydrate.  Caffeine was permitted only after the 4-hour blood sample, and alcohol was forbidden until completion of the study.  Adherence to fasting was assessed verbally.  </interventions>
    <comparator>Arm 1:  Flucloxacillin 1000 mg orally, single dose while fasting</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Total flucloxacillin plasma concentrations were measured using an LC-MS/MS method </outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples were taken at baseline then 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 4, 6, 8 and 12 hours after administration of flucloxacillin</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Free flucloxacillin plasma concentrations were measured using an LC-MS/MS method </outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood samples were taken at baseline then 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 2.5, 3, 4, 6, 8 and 12 hours after administration of flucloxacillin</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Adverse events, such as nausea, anorexia, diarrhoea, skin itch or rash were assessed by verbal questioning at the end of each study day</outcome>
      <timepoint>0 to 12 hours after administration of study drugs</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Healthy volunteer</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>40</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Food intolerance, pregnancy, chronic illness, renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt; 80 mL/min by Cockcroft-Gault formula), liver dysfunction, malabsorption or known intolerance of flucloxacillin or probenecid.  Volunteers were excluded from the study if they took any regular medications (other than a hormonal oral contraceptive pill) or were intolerant of fasting for up to 10 hours.  </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Pharmacokinetics</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The number of volunteers chosen was pretty standard for a PK/PD study of this type.  Treatment arms were compared for common PK parameters and for the concentrations achieved for 30%, 50% and 70% of the usual dose intervals.  Statistics evaluated included repeated measures one-way ANOVA, ratios of each regimen over the others, post-hoc analysis using Bonferronis multiple comparison test, and if no differences were demonstrated, 90% confidence intervals for bioequivalence testing (mean ± 90% CI within 0.8 to 1.25). The probability of target attainment (PTAs) for each arm were plotted against a range of MICs  of common skin-infecting bacteria</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 1</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>7/01/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>11/02/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>11</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>11</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>11/02/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <state>Nelson/Tasman</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Richard Everts</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Department of Medicine
Nelson Hospital
Private Bag 18
Nelson 7042</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>New Zealand</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Nelson Research and Education Trust Fund</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>c/o Dr Bruce King
Nelson Hospital
Private Bag 18
Nelson 7042</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>New Zealand</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Introduction and methods
Flucloxacillin is the first-line antibiotic agent in many parts of the world, including NZ and Australia, for treating Staphylococcus aureus and skin infections.  It is often given by 24-hour intravenous (IV) infusion to outpatients with moderately severe infections, but this costs NZ$150-200/day and sometimes causes problems with the IV catheter.  It is often given by mouth to patients with mild infections, but this requires four-times-daily dosing and is recommended to be taken 1 hour before or 2 hours after a meal.  It would be very useful if there was a more effective and convenient oral flucloxacillin regimen that could be taken with or without food. 
In the early 1950s, probenecid was developed as a penicillin booster.  In this study, we evaluated the effect of low dose probenecid (500 mg), with or without a small meal, on oral flucloxacillin pharmacokinetics in 11 healthy volunteers.  We used modern testing methods, measured free flucloxacillin concentrations, and evaluated the results in terms of modern PK/PD targets for the likely bacteria involved.

Results
Probenecid delayed clearance of flucloxacillin from the body, approximately doubling the time the flucloxacillin was above the target minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC90 = 0.5 mg/L for Staphylococcus aureus.  Food delayed the absorption of flucloxacillin but did not reduce it.. For a target of time above 0.5 mg/L for more than 50% of the day (e.g. for a deep S. aureus bone or joint infection), modeling at steady state showed that flucloxacillin 1 g with probenecid 500 mg taken 6- or 8-hourly with or without food would achieve this in almost all cases.  For a target of time above 0.5 mg/L for more than 30% of the day (e.g. for a mild skin infection), modeling at steady state showed that flucloxacillin 1 g with probenecid 500 mg taken twice daily with or without food would achieve this in almost all cases.  

Conclusion
These results show that probenecid is a powerful booster of flucloxacillin and that food did not negatively affect the relevant results.  Taking probenecid and flucloxacillin together could enable patients with mild infections to have a more convenient twice daily regimen and could enable patients with moderate deep serious gram-positive infections to avoid home intravenous infusions.  </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>A report of this work was presented verbally at the Australasian Society of Clinical and Experimental Pharmacologists and Toxicologists (ASCEPT) annual scientific meeting in Melbourne, Australia, in December 2013 and at the Australasian Society for Infectious Diseases (ASID) annual scientific meeting in Adelaide, Australia, in March 2014.  Abstracts were not published for non-attendees.  </publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Northern B Health and Disability Ethics Committee </ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ministry of Health
Health and Disability Ethics Committees
PO Box 5013
Wellington 6140</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>27/11/2012</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>12/NTB/56</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>5/11/2012</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>New Zealand</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369309-12-NTB-56_Approved_Letter.pdf</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369309-probenecid flucloxacillin PK in volunteers study - protocol.doc</filepath>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/369309-Abstract ASID March 2014 - Everts et al - Flucloxacillin and Probenecid.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Everts</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
Nelson Hospital
Private Bag 18
Nelson 7042</address>
      <phone>+64 3 539-1170</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 539-4958</fax>
      <email>richard.everts@nbph.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Everts</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
Nelson Hospital
Private Bag 18
Nelson 7042</address>
      <phone>+64 3 539-1170</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 539-4958</fax>
      <email>richard.everts@nbph.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Everts</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
Nelson Hospital
Private Bag 18
Nelson 7042</address>
      <phone>+64 3 539-1170</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 539-4958</fax>
      <email>richard.everts@nbph.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Richard Everts</name>
      <address>Department of Medicine
Nelson Hospital
Private Bag 18
Nelson 7042</address>
      <phone>+64 3 539-1170</phone>
      <fax>+64 3 539-4958</fax>
      <email>richard.everts@nbph.org.nz</email>
      <country>New Zealand</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>