<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="347906">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>5/01/2012</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>6/01/2012</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12612000026820</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The CAP Study: Evaluating a comprehensive universal and targeted intervention designed to prevent substance use and related harms in Australian adolescents</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The CAP intervention: A comprehensive universal and targeted intervention to prevent substance use and related harms in Australian adolescents aged 13 to 15</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1121-8314</utrn>
    <trialacronym>CAP</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Substance use prevention</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Prevention of substance use-related harms</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Addiction</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other public health</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Participating secondary schools will be randomly allocated to one of four groups. One group will serve as the control group and receive their usual drug education in school while the remaining three groups will receive either of the following interventions:

Arm 1- Climate Schools Intervention (CL): The Climate Schools program aims to reduce the use of Australias most commonly used licit and illicit drugs: alcohol and cannabis, and related harms. The Program consists of twelve 40-minute lessons delivered as part of the Year 8 PDHPE syllabus. The lessons are delivered weekly for 6 weeks (Climate Schools Alcohol module) and then approximately a 6 month break before the delivery of another 6 weekly lessons (Climate Schools Alcohol and Cannabis module). The first part of each lesson is completed individually over the internet where students are engaged through cartoon storylines which impart information about the short- and long-term effects of alcohol and cannabis, normative alcohol and cannabis use, refusal skills, and first aid. The second part of each lesson is a group or class activity delivered by the teacher which reinforces the information in the cartoons and allows interactive communication between students. Teachers are provided with a manual containing the activities, implementation guidelines, links to the education syllabus and summaries for each lesson. The first six lessons focus specifically on alcohol and are delivered approximately six month prior to the remaining six lessons which focus on cannabis. The overall duration of Arm 1 is approximately 6 months.

Arm 2- Preventure Intervention (PR): The Preventure program is a brief personality-targeted substance use preventive intervention for high-risk adolescents aged 14-15 years. Unlike universal programs, this selected personality-targeted approach addresses personality risk-factors for early-onset substance misuse and other risky behaviours. Participating students will be screened at baseline using the 24-item Substance Use Risk Profile (SURPS) questionnaire which assesses variation in personality risk for substance abuse along four dimensions: Sensation Seeking, Impulsivity, Anxiety Sensitivity and Hopelessness (Woicik et al., 2009). The Preventure program is also consistent with new models which conceptualise substance use as being driven by personality traits such as impulsivity and disinhibition (Dick et al., 2008).

This program involves two 90-minute group sessions (6-8 students per group) delivered one week apart by a trained clinical psychologist and co-facilitator. The interventions are conducted using manuals which incorporate psycho-educational and cognitive behavioural components, and include real life scenarios shared by high-risk youth in specifically-organised focus groups. In the first session, participants are guided in a goal setting exercise, designed to enhance motivation to change behaviour. Psycho-educational strategies are used to teach participants about their target personality variable and associated problematic coping behaviours like avoidance, interpersonal dependence, aggression, risky behaviours and substance misuse. They are then introduced to the cognitive behavioural model and guided in breaking down personal experience according to the physical, cognitive and behavioural components of an emotional response. A novel component to this intervention approach is the fact that all exercises discuss thoughts, emotions and behaviours in a personality-specific way, e.g. identifying situational triggers and cognitive distortions related to Sensation Seeking specifically. In the second session, participants are encouraged to identify and challenge personality-specific cognitive distortions that lead to problematic behaviours. The overall duration of Arm 2 is approximately 3 months.

Arm 3- Climate Schools and Preventure Intervention (CAP): The CAP intervention will deliver the Climate Schools and Preventure programs, described above, simultaneously with the aim of providing a comprehensive universal and targeted model to prevent substance use and related harms in Australian adolescents. The overall duration of Arm 3 is approximately 9 months.</interventions>
    <comparator>The combined Climate Schools and Preventure (CAP) Intervention will be compared to:

a) A "standard treatment" control group - Students will not receive the Climate Schools or the Preventure Interventions. Participants will complete their standard Year 8 PDHPE classes, delivered by their teacher

b) Climate Schools only intervention - Students will receive 12 x 40minute lessons delivered as part of the Year 8 PDHPE syllabus. Each lesson consists of computer lessons and activities from the program manual, to be administered by the teacher

c) Preventure only intervention - Students will attend their standard PDHPE lessons, delivered by their teacher. Students who are identified as being 'high-risk' based on their personality profile will be invited to participate in 2 x 90minute sessions carried out by a registered Clinical Psychologist and co-facilitator. These sessions incorporate psycho-educational and cognitive behavioural components.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Uptake and harmful use of alcohol and illicit substance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 6, 12, 24 and 36 months after intervention commencement. Uptake and harmful use will be assessed by an adapted version of the School Health Alcohol Harm Reduction Project (SHAHRP) Patterns of Alcohol and Cannabis Use instrument, the Diagnostic Interview Schedule for Children (DISC-IV), the Alcohol and Lifestyle Questionnaire and nine items relating to student's current and intended future use of alcohol and illicit drugs.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Substance use related harms</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 6, 12, 24 and 36 months after intervention commencement, using the Bullying Questionnaire and Reactive-Proactive Aggression Questionnaire. Harms caused by cannabis will be assessed using 12 items adapted from the SHAHRP survey instrument and a set of questions adapted from the Adolescent Cannabis Problems Questionnaire.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Alcohol and cannabis knowledge and attitudes</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 6, 12, 24 and 36 months after intervention commencement, assessed by questions adapted from the SHAHRP questionnaire.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Mental health comorbidity</outcome>
      <timepoint>Assessed at baseline and at 6, 12, 24 and 36 months after intervention commencement. Psychological distress will be assessed using the Kessler 6 Scale, depression and anxiety symptoms will be assessed using the Brief Symptom Inventory (BSI) and Psychotic symptoms will be measured using the Thoughts and Feelings Questionnaire</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>All students (male and female) between the ages of 12 and 15 yrs.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>12</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>15</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Those younger than 12 or older than 15 years of age</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Schools will be randomised to one of the four study groups using the online program Research Randomizer. Allocation will be concealed via central randomisation using computer software.</concealment>
    <sequence>Schools will be randomised to one of the four study groups using the online program Research Randomizer (simple randomisation using computer software).</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Factorial</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>16/09/2011</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>1920</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Prof Maree Teesson</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of NSW
Sydney NSW 2052</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>National Health and Medical Research Council</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>National Health and Medical Research Council
GPO Box 1421
Canberra ACT 2601</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>University</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>University of NSW</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>University of NSW
Sydney NSW 2052</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
    <othercollaborator>
      <othercollaboratortype>University</othercollaboratortype>
      <othercollaboratorname>Kings College</othercollaboratorname>
      <othercollaboratoraddress>Addictions Department
Institute of Psychiatry
Kings College London WC2R 2LS</othercollaboratoraddress>
      <othercollaboratorcountry>United Kingdom</othercollaboratorcountry>
    </othercollaborator>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The aim of the current proposal is to combine the effective universal Climate Schools and targeted Preventure programs into a comprehensive model to prevent substance use and related harms in adolescents. This model will be known as the CAP intervention. Delivering prevention using the proposed comprehensive approach offers a way of preventing substance use at a whole population level and has the potential to maximize outcomes for both high- and low-risk youth. This study will be the first time such intervention has been trailed, and will also be the first trial of a targeted substance use prevention program in Australia.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>http://www.capstudy.org.au/</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>UNSW Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>University of NSW
Sydney NSW 2052</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>29/08/2011</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC 11274</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Prof Maree Teesson</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of NSW
Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 0333</phone>
      <fax>+612 9385 0222</fax>
      <email>m.teesson@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Nicola Newton</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of NSW
Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 0204</phone>
      <fax>+612 9385 0222</fax>
      <email>nickien@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Emma Barrett</name>
      <address>National Drug and Alcohol Research Centre
University of NSW
Sydney NSW 2052</address>
      <phone>+612 9385 0164</phone>
      <fax>+612 9385 0222</fax>
      <email>e.barrett@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>