<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371502">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>23/09/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>24/10/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001479493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Dynamic response to fluid challenge administration in operating room: a pilot trial.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Dynamic response to fluid challenge administration in operating room: a pilot trial.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nihil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Surgical Patients</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hemodynamic instability</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Hypotension</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other anaesthesiology</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Fluid challenge consisting in 500 ml of intravenous crystalloids (both saline 0,9% or Ringer Acetate or Lactate were allowed), administered in 10 minutes.
The Fluid challenge is administered by the attending physician to correct hemodynamic instability during the surgical procedure (see also eligibility).
All the patients received hemodynamic monitoring with the MostCare system which provides all the hemodynamic variables evaluated in the study before and after fluid challenge administration (cardiac output, stroke volume, arterial elastance, cardiac cycle efficiency) 
All patients will receive an echocardiographic assessment before and after the FC including, tissue doppler waveforms (both right and left ventricle), mitral pattern assessment (includine E/e'; E/A waves analysis), Velocity time integral of aortic flow pattern (VTI) and VTI variations</interventions>
    <comparator>The pulse pressure variation, a dynamic index of fluid responsiveness, has been considered as the gold standard. Pulse pressure variation was recorded during in operating room during the surgical procedure. Off line evaluation of PPV before and after the fluid challenge was the used as control treatment</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Aim of the present study is assessing whether a model including pulse pressure variation, cardiac cycle efficiency, arterial elastane and dicrotic pressure assessed by MostCare system, changes during a fluid challenge infusion anticipate its outcome, compared to the standard assessment.</outcome>
      <timepoint>single time point: the end of fluid challenge (duration 10 minutes)</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The assessment of the area under the curve (AUC) of the predefined variables included in the model (pulse pressure variation, cardiac cycle efficiency, arterial elastane and dicrotic pressure)</outcome>
      <timepoint>single time point: the end of fluid challenge (duration 10 minutes)</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1) to have &gt; or = 18 years
2) to be scheduled for elective open abdominal surgery under general anesthesia with mechanical ventilation with a volume controlled mode (with a tidal volume (VT) &lt; 8 ml/kg), 
3) to require an invasive blood pressure monitoring. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1) the American Society of Anesthesiologists' physical status classification (ASA) equal to 4, 
2) presence of a previous history of arrhythmia, or left ventricular ejection fraction &lt; 30%, or right ventricular dysfunction (assessed by a &lt; 0.16 m/s of systolic peak velocity of tricuspid annular motion), or a moderate to severe valvular heart disease , or intra-cardiac shunt, 3) chronic medication with beta-blockers.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Non-randomised trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Normal distribution was evaluated by means of the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. All the considered variables were averaged over one minute and average values were used for all comparisons. ROC curves (95% confidence interval, [CI]) were constructed for percent changes of PPV between baseline mean value vs. the response to the FC. 
The variations of CCE and MAP- Pdic, Ea and SAP  Pdic were compared using analysis of variance (ANOVA); for nonparametric data the Friedman test followed by Dunn multiple comparisons and for parametric data ANOVA with Bonferroni post hoc tests adjusting for multiple comparisons were used. The Greenhouse-Geisser correction was used when sphericity could not be assumed. 
We performed bivariate analyses using the t-test for quantitative variables and the chi-square test (or Fishers exact test, if indicated) for qualitative variables and constructed a bivariate logistic regression model. The model include, baseline PPV, the variation of CCE, Ea, MAP- Pdic, Ea and SAP  Pdic between baseline and the first minute measuring a variation statistically significant for DELTA_CCE, DELTA_MAP- Pdic, DELTA_Ea and DELTA_SAP  Pdic. A Hosmer &amp; Lemeshow test was calculated to evaluate the model fit. 
Statistical analyses were conducted using SPPS version 30.0 (SPSS, Inc., Chicago, IL). For all comparisons, we considered significant p values &lt; 0.05. 
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>1/12/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate>31/12/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>50</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>50</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>31/12/2015</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <state>Novara, Florence</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Antonio Messina</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>AOU Maggiore della Carita'
Corso Mazzini, 18
28100 Novara (NO)
Intensive care unit
</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Italy</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>AOU Maggiore della Carita'</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Corso Mazzini, 18
28100 Novara (NO)</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Italy</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>nihil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>nihil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Background: Assessing preload dependence by means of static and dynamic indexes of fluid responsiveness is limited to a minority of critically ill and surgical patients. The lack in the sensitivity and specificity of these indexes in revealing fluid responsiveness before fluid challenge (FC) administration increases the risk of fluid overloading. Since, in responders and non-responders, the FC causes different hemodynamic effects in cardiac function and peripheral tone the outcome could be predicted before the entire infusion by dynamically assessing these variables. 
Methods: 50 patients scheduled for elective abdominal surgery. The FC was administered to improve an episode of hemodynamic instability, and consisted in 500 ml of crystalloids in 10 minutes. A bivariate logistic regression mode was constructed to predict the outcome of the FC including baseline pulse pressure variation (PPV), and four different cardiovascular indexes provided by the MostCare.
Design: prospective multicentric study</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Preliminary data of the present trial have been presented to the 29 ESICM congress 2016 (1-5 October, Milan- Italy): "EARLY VARIATIONS OF PULSE PRESSURE VARIATION, CARDIAC CYCLE EFFICIENCY AND DICROTIC PRESSURE TO PREDICT FLUID CHALLENGE SUCCESS
Abstract Presenter: Antonio Messina, MD, AOU Maggiore della Carita' (Novara, Italy). Poster Corner presentation; 3 October.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Comitato etico Interaziendale AOU Maggiore della Carita'</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Corso Mazzini, 18
28100 Novara (NO)</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>26/09/2014</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>Protocol 838/CE, CE 118/14</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>23/08/2014</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Italy</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Antonio Messina</name>
      <address>AOU Maggiore della Carita'
Corso Mazzini, 18
28100 Novara (NO)</address>
      <phone>+3903213733380</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mess81rc@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Antonio Messina</name>
      <address>AOU Maggiore della Carita'
Corso Mazzini, 18
28100 Novara (NO)</address>
      <phone>+3903213733380</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mess81rc@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>antonio messina</name>
      <address>AOU Maggiore della Carita'
Corso Mazzini, 18
28100 Novara (NO)</address>
      <phone>+3903213733380</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mess81rc@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Italy</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>antonio messina</name>
      <address />
      <phone>+3903213733380</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>mess81rc@gmail.com</email>
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>