<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="367877">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>2/02/2015</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/02/2015</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12615000133538</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The effects of alcohol consumption on cardiovascular risk in patients with type II diabetes mellitus</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A controlled trial of the effect of alcohol on cardiovascular risk in type II diabetic patients</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Type II diabetes mellitus</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Blood pressure</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Serum lipids</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cardiovascular </conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Hypertension</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other diet and nutrition disorders</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>During an initial 4-week run-in period, patients continue their usual regular alcohol intake and complete baseline assessment of their usual dietary and drinking patterns. They are then be randomized into a 3 period cross-over study of Latin square design, during which they consume during sequential 4-week study periods:-

	(1)	alcohol as red wine (a shiraz cabernet blend of known composition and alcohol content - alcohol 13% v/v, sourced from Orlando Wyndham, Rowland Flat, South Australia) 
	(a)	in women: 20-30 g/day  approx. 140-210 g/week. (2-3 bottles/week with a minimum consumption of 20 g/day every day and maximum consumption of 30 g/day every day).
(b)	in men: 30-40 g/day  approx. 210-280 g/week (3-4 bottles/week with a minimum consumption of 30 g/day every day and maximum consumption of 40 g/day every day).

or	(2)	an identical red wine but which has been de-alcoholised (again sourced from Orlando Wyndham, Rowland Flat, South Australia), consumed in equivalent volumes daily to the regular alcohol period. During this 4-week period they otherwise remain abstinent from all alcohol.

or	(3)	water. During this 4-week period they will otherwise remain abstinent from all alcohol.


The precise amount of red wine and de-alcoholised red wine within the above ranges is dictated by subject's usual alcohol intake at entry to the study.

There was no washout period between each 4-week study period.

All measurements are performed at the conclusion of the initial 4-week run-in period and at the conclusion of each 4-week study period. BP and heart rate are measured using 24-hour ambulatory BP measurements; glucose, insulin, lipids and lipoproteins are measured in fasting blood samples.

Compliance with the designated changes in alcohol intake are recorded by 7-day retrospective weekly diaries, completed at weekly visits to the clinical trials unit. In addition serum is sampled at the end of the 4-week run-in period and the end of each subsequent study period for both gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase and carbohydrate deficient transferrin as biomarkers of alcohol intake. Twenty-four hour urinary 4-O-methylgallic acid is determined as a biomarker of red wine intake.</interventions>
    <comparator>During a 4-week period subjects consume an equal volume of water with their meals but remain abstinent from all alcohol.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>24 hr, daytime and night time ambulatory blood pressure.

24-hour ambulatory BP measurement is performed using a SpaceLabs Monitor (Model 90217, SpaceLabs Medical Inc) while subjects continue their normal routine. The recorder is preset to take BP and heart rate (HR) recordings every 30 min and is fitted at the conclusion of the initial 4-week run-in period and at the conclusion of each 4-week study period. BP records are not visible to the subjects. Subjects are instructed to complete an activity diary which describes the posture and activity of the subject at the time of the BP reading. While the BP measurements are being made, subjects are instructed to keep their arm motionless by their side to avoid artefactual readings caused by vibration. In cases when the SpaceLabs Monitor detects an error in BP measurement subjects are instructed to rectify the error or return to the department to have the recorder corrected. Readings associated with a test code and those with a difference of &lt; 20 mmHg between SBP and DBP are excluded from analysis. Mean BP and HR are calculated for each of the 24 hours and then mean 24 hour, awake and asleep BP and HR are computed. Waking and sleeping times are determined from subjects activity diaries.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measurements are performed at the conclusion of the initial 4-week run-in period and at the conclusion of each 4-week study period. </timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fasting serum glucose and insulin levels</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measurements are performed at the conclusion of the initial 4-week run-in period and at the conclusion of each 4-week study period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Serum lipids and lipoproteins</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measurements are performed at the conclusion of the initial 4-week run-in period and at the conclusion of each 4-week study period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Plasma levels of specialized pro-resolving lipid mediators (SPM's) assessed by liquid chromatographytandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS).</outcome>
      <timepoint>All measurements are performed at the conclusion of the initial 4-week run-in period and at the conclusion of each 4-week study period.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Type II diabetic non-smoking men aged 40-70 years and postmenopausal women, recruited from the diabetic clinic at Royal Perth Hospital and by advertisement from the general population. Patients will have previous evidence of diabetes by either being on hypoglycaemic medication, or having had a diabetic glucose tolerance test, or at least 2 fasting plasma glucose concentrations &gt; 7.1 mmol/l. They will be drinking an average of 2-3 standard drinks/day (20-30 g/day ethanol) for women or 3-4 standard drinks/day (30-40 g/day ethanol) for men. All patients will have HbA1c &lt; 8.5%.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>40</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Type 1 diabetes
Recent (&lt; 3 months) symptomatic heart disease
Angina pectoris
History of myocardial infarction or stroke
Peripheral vascular disease
Major surgery &lt; 3 months
BP &gt;170/100 mmHg
Liver or renal disease (plasma creatinine &gt;120 mmol/L)
HbA1c &gt; 8.5%
Smokers &amp; ex-smokers &lt; 2 years
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Concealment by central randomisation</concealment>
    <sequence>Permuted block randomisation</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The 24 hr ambulatory BP records are analysed utilising pooled time series regression with random effects models adjusted for serial correlation.Using data from our previous study of the effects of alcohol consumption on ambulatory BP in men, we estimate that with change in 24 hr ambulatory systolic BP as the major endpoint there will be at least 80% power to demonstrate a 5 mmHg change (SD of difference in paired values in SBP=7.5 mmHg). We estimate that with an adjusted alpha level of 0.015 (assuming the potential for 3 paired comparisons), that 27 subjects will be required.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>13/08/2003</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>13/08/2003</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>12/02/2004</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>12/02/2004</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>27</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>28</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Perth Hospital - Perth</hospital>
    <postcode>6000 - Perth</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>University of Western Australia</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>The University of Western Australia
35 Stirling Hwy
Crawley WA 6009</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Charities/Societies/Foundations</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Australian Health Management Group</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>23-27 Macquarie St (Cnr O'Donnell St)
PO Box 1436 Parramatta NSW 2124</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Ian B Puddey</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>School of Medicine and Pharmacology
Faculty of Medicine, Dentistry and Health Sciences
University of Western Australia
RPH MRF Building
Rear 50 Murray St, Perth, WA 6000
</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The current epidemiological literature suggests that regular higher consumption of alcohol raises blood pressure (BP). In view of the well-known association between BP and cardiovascular disease (CVD), and the fact that patients with diabetes have increased risk of CVD, this trial tests the hypothesis that a reduction in alcohol intake in Type II diabetic patients who are regular drinkers, will reduce cardiovascular risk.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Puddey IB, Mori TA, Burke V, Zilkens RR, Hodgson JM, Beilin LJ. The effects of alcohol on blood pressure, HDL-C and glycaemic control in Type 2 diabetic subjects: a controlled intervention study. J Hypertension 2005, 23 (Supplement 2):S99.</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Ethics Committee, Royal Perth Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Ethics Committee
Royal Perth Hospital
Wellington St Campus
Box X2213
GPO Perth WA 6001</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>7/08/2002</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>EC 2003/004</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ian B Puddey</name>
      <address>School of Medicine and Pharmacology Faculty of Medicine, Dentistry and
Health Sciences University of Western Australia RPH MRF Building Rear 50
Murray St, Perth, WA 6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92240232 or +61 8 92240258</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ian.Puddey@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ian B Puddey</name>
      <address>School of Medicine and Pharmacology Faculty of Medicine, Dentistry and
Health Sciences University of Western Australia RPH MRF Building Rear 50
Murray St, Perth, WA 6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92240232 or +61 8 92240258</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ian.Puddey@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ian B Puddey</name>
      <address>School of Medicine and Pharmacology Faculty of Medicine, Dentistry and
Health Sciences University of Western Australia RPH MRF Building Rear 50
Murray St, Perth, WA 6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92240232 or +61 8 92240258</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ian.Puddey@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Ian B Puddey</name>
      <address>School of Medicine and Pharmacology Faculty of Medicine, Dentistry and
Health Sciences University of Western Australia RPH MRF Building Rear 50
Murray St, Perth, WA 6000</address>
      <phone>+61 8 92240232 or +61 8 92240258</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>Ian.Puddey@uwa.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>