<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="81899">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>8/03/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>31/05/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000288426</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>OSA screening in COPD</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The utility of a clinical algorithm for diagnosing Obstructive Sleep Apnoea (OSA) in symptomatic patients with Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>COPD</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Obstructive Sleep Apnoea</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Respiratory</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Sleep apnoea</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Questionnaires, biometric data, upper airway function (using the Forced Oscillation Technique) and lung function (using standard pre and post bronchodilator spirometry) will be administered over 30 minutes by research staff upon enrolment. Subjects will then be allocated to receive both the single channel home based sleep apnoea monitoring device (Flow Wizard, DiagnoseIT, Australia) for three nights at home and in hospital polysomnography for one night in random order. Subjects will receive both the in hospital polysomnography and home testing within a four week period. The wash out period is 24hours.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Diagnosis / Prognosis</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To establish the utility of a clinical algorithm based on questionnaires, upper airway assessment, biometrics, upper airway function (Forced Oscillation Technique), lung function and home monitoring (via a single channel device measuring nasal flow) in diagnosing for OSA in symptomatic patients with COPD.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Determined at the conclusion of the trial.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To establish the utility of a clinical algorithm based on questionnaires, upper airway assessment, biometrics, upper airway function (Forced Oscillation Technique), lung function and home monitoring (via a single channel device measuring nasal flow in diagnosing Obstructive Sleep Apnoea (OSA) in those with varying degrees of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) severity according to the Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) criteria.</outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be determined at the conclusion of the trial.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>To compare the utility of a clinical algorithm based on questionnaires, upper airway assessment, biometrics, upper airway function (Forced Oscillation Technique), lung function and home monitoring (via a single channel device measuring nasal flow in diagnosing OSA in COPD in different patient subgroups for example according to sex, ethnicity, different disease groups such as cardiac etc. </outcome>
      <timepoint>This will be determined at the conclusion of the trial.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Group 1 (Control group): symptoms of sleep apnoea (including snoring, choking, witnessed apneas and daytime sleepiness) and/or co morbidities including obesity, hypertension and the metabolic syndrome that are non smokers with &lt; 5 pack year history.                                                                                                                                                                                    Group 2 COPD patients who are smokers or ex smokers with &gt; 10 pack year history of smoking and symptoms of OSA, and/or co morbidities including obesity, hypertension and the metabolic syndrome, are able to give informed consent.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype />
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype />
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Inability to comply with procedures, previous diagnosis of other respiratory and/or sleep disorders, and current treatment with continuous positive airways pressure, a tracheostomy or home oxygen as well as poorly controlled other medical conditions.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Diagnosis</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Sealed envelopes</concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Crossover</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>15/03/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>360</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Other</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Other</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>At enrolment eligibility will be confirmed. Subjects will answer questionnaires; have anthropometric measures taken and upper airway function and lung function assessed. All patients will undergo home testing with a diagnostic device for three nights and have an in laboratory sleep study in random order. All tests will be performed within a 4 week period. The results will not be communicated to the participant or the treating physicians until all components have been performed. The participants will then be referred to a sleep specialist to have the results of the polysomnogram discussed, and appropriate management instituted outside of the study, as dictated by usual clinical practice.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Sydney South West Area Health Service- Royal Prince Alfred Hospital (RPAH) Zone</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/03/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec> X07-0003,</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Dr Lydia Makarie Rofail</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
PO Box M77 Missenden Rd
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95157590</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 95575059</fax>
      <email>lydiamr@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Sarah Newton-John</name>
      <address>Woolcock Institute of Medical Research
PO Box M77 Missenden Rd
Camperdown NSW 2050</address>
      <phone>+61 2 95156578</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 95505865</fax>
      <email>sarahnj@woolcock.org.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>