<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="82096">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>16/06/2007</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>19/06/2007</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12607000329460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Phase III Randomized Trial of Maintenance Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (PLD)/ Carboplatin versus without in Patients with Advanced Ovarian Cancer</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Patients with Advanced Ovarian Cancer with complete remission after first-line chemotherapy-Maintenance Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (PLD) / Carboplatin versus observation-time to progression, quality of life and toxicity of treatment-progression free survival</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>AGOG06-001</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Advanced ovarian cancer</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Cancer</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Ovarian and primary peritoneal</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Maintenance Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (PLD) 30mg/m2/ Carboplatin Area Under the Curve = 4 in 28-day cycles for 6 courses versus observation (no treatment) after complete remission of first-line chemotherapy.</interventions>
    <comparator />
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Progression-free survival</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, by history and Physical Exam/Pelvic exam on every visit, and abdominal pelvic CT scan at baseline and every year from the start of treatment until progression during the study (including clinical suspicion).</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Overall survival, Quality-of-Life, safety profile</outcome>
      <timepoint>At baseline, by history and PE/PV on every visit and abdominal pelvic CT scan at baseline and every year from the start of treatment until progression during the study (including clinical suspicion).</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>To be eligible for inclusion, each patient must fulfill all of the following criteria:a. histologically proven ovarian cancer of International Federation of Gynecology and Obstetrics stage III/IVb. treatment with five to six cycles of Paclitaxol / Platinum regimenc. attainment of a clinical defined complete response (ie, no cancer-related symptom ; normal physical examination, CT scan of the abdominal/pelvis and chest x-ray ; CA-125 level &lt; 35 U/mL) d. performance status of Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group 0, 1, 2 e. adequate hematopoietic function is defined as below:- Absolute Neutrophil Count &gt; 1,500/uL- Platelets &gt; 100,000/uLf. adequate organ function is defined as below:- Total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 X Upper Limit of Normal (ULN)- Alanine aminotranferase / Aspartate aminotransferase &lt; 1.5 X ULN (&lt;5.0 x ULN if hepatic metastasis) - Serum creatinine &lt; 1.5 × ULNg. age 20-75 years oldh. life expectancy equal or longer than 3 monthsi. ability to understand and willingness to sign a written informed consent document</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>0</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Not stated</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>0</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Not stated</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>a. presence of CNS metastases (including clinical suspicion)b. other malignancy with exception of curative treated non-melanoma skin cancer or cervical carcinoma in situ within 5 years prior to entering the studyc. presence of other serious concomitant illness which can affect or elevate the value of CA-125, e.g.;- Autoimmune disease- Sarcoidosis- Chronic active hepatitis- Pericarditis- Cirrhosis of liver- Abdominal tuberculosis- Pancratitisd. presence of other serious concomitant illness which might be aggravated by study medication:- Uncontrolled infection (active serious infections that are not controlled by antibiotics)- Active cardiac disease e.g. decompensate myocardial infarction within the 6-month period preceding entry into the study.- History of ventricular arrhythmia or congestive heart failure.e. surgery within 2 weeks prior to entering the studyf. radiotherapy within 4 weeks prior to entering the studyg. concurrent chemotherapy, radiotherapy, or other investigational drug except non-disease related conditions (e.g. insulin for diabetes) during study periodh. mental status is not fit for clinical triali. pregnant or breast feeding womenj. potential child-bearing women unless using a reliable and appropriate contraceptive method.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation concealment will be applied. A central randomisation by phone/fax/computerpermuted block randomization will be employed to generate the randomization scheme for an approximate equal number of patients between two treatment groups.</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation will be used. Each randomization number will be assigned to individual patient according to the sequence for screened patient becomes eligible.Stratification : (1) residual tumor after primary surgery (&gt; 1cm or = 1cm)  (2) baseline CA125 &lt;10, 10-25 , &gt;25-35 u/mL</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 3</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>21/06/2007</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>290</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress />
    <primarysponsorcountry>Taiwan, Province Of China</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>TTY BIOPHARM COMPANY LIMITED</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress />
      <fundingcountry />
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Asian Gynecologic Oncology Group</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>In the current study, we will use Lipo-Dox® in combination with carboplatin as maintenance chemotherapy in advanced epithelial ovarian patients who have achieved clinical complete remission after 5-6 courses of taxane/platinum based first-line chemotherapy. 
All eligible subjects will randomize to arm A or arm B.
Arm A: 
Subjects will receive PLD(Lipo-Dox) 30 mg/m2 intravenously (iv) over 1 hour on day 1 and follow by Carboplatin 4 AUC intravenous infusion for 30 minutes in a 28-day cycle for maximum six cycles.
Arm B: 
Subjects will not receive any treatment.
Therapeutic Assessment includes progression free survival, quality-of-life, overall survival, and safety profiles.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>IRB of Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress />
      <ethicapprovaldate>5/01/2007</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>95-0761A</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Taiwan</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chyong-Huey Lai, MD</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology
Chang Gung Memorial Hospital Linkou Medical Center
5 Fu-Shin St
Kueishan
Taoyuan 333</address>
      <phone>886-3-3281200</phone>
      <fax>886-3-3288252</fax>
      <email>laich46@cgmh.org.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Province Of China</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Chyong-Huey Lai, MD</name>
      <address>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology
Chang Gung Memorial Hospital Linkou Medical Center
5 Fu-Shin St.
Kueishan Taoyuan 333</address>
      <phone>886-3-3281200</phone>
      <fax>886-3-3288252</fax>
      <email>laich46@cgmh.org.tw</email>
      <country>Taiwan, Republic Of China</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>