<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370898">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>13/06/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/09/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001229460</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Magnific Study- A randomised controlled trial of magnetic non-invasive acupuncture for infant comfort for heel prick tests. </studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The Magnific Study - Magnetic Non-Invasive acupuncture for Infant Comfort during heel prick test in Neonatal Intensive Care Unit (NICU)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1184-2568</utrn>
    <trialacronym>Magnific</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Neonatal Intensive Care</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Procedural pain</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Alternative and Complementary Medicine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other alternative and complementary medicine</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Magnets or placebos will be placed at five ear points (both ears) at least 2 hours before a heel prick. The magnets or placebos will be left for three days during which the infant will be assessed for his/her response to the heel prick with the PIPP (Premature Infant Pain Profile) score. After three days, the magnets will be removed and the infant will be discharged from the study.  The magnets are embedded in a sticker. The placebos are stickers with the magnets removed. A "bump" is created on the surface of the sticker with liquid paper to mask the magnet. The magnet will be placed either by an acupuncturist or by a research officer who is trained by the acupuncturist. The stickers will be checked every day by the site research officer and replaced if they have fallen off before the end of the three day period. </interventions>
    <comparator>Babies in the placebo group will have stickers without magnets placed on their ears. </comparator>
    <control>Placebo</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary outcome is the PIPP score during and 1 hour after the heel prick. </outcome>
      <timepoint>Before (baseline), during (at heel prick) and 1 hour after the heel prick</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Medical record review of whether sucrose was provided at any time before, during or after the heel prick. </outcome>
      <timepoint>After completion of each heel prick</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Infants who require a heel prick for blood collection in the NICU. Babies will be matched by gender, gestation and age. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage />
    <inclusiveminagetype>No limit</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>4</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Weeks</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Babies who need sedation and analgesia for other reasons e.g. post-operative analgesia or who cannot express pain (e.g. muscle relaxed, intubated and ventilated). </exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The attending clinician will be approached by the site investigator to determine if the infant is eligible for the study. If eligible, the site investigator will determine randomisation to either magnet or placebo in a code that is concealed within sealed opaque envelopes and generated by random computerised sequence. </concealment>
    <sequence>Computer generated</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Safety/efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Sample size is calculated on PIPP scores as this dictates how the pain of an infant is managed in an NICU. 40 infants are required to achieve a 20% decrease in mean PIPP score in response to a painful procedure will require, with 80% power and 5% alpha.

Statistical analysis for the primary endpoints of this study will be conducted by the intention to treat principle. Analyses will be based on the GEE extension to the generalized linear model with each measure treated as a binary outcome using a logit link to evaluate the effect of treatment controlling for gestational age stratum. Comparison between the two treatment arms (magnet and no magnet) will be assessed using analysis of variance (ANOVA) models and comparable non-parametric tests for continuous variables and generalized linear models and contingency table procedures (Chi square tests) for categorical variables, controlling for gestational age strata. Linear and generalized regression models will adjust for potential confounders (i.e., demographic and clinical data, site) and evaluate the independent association between the use of magnets or no magnet on pain scores. For each outcome measure, model-based approaches will examine whether treatment effects differ across the two gestational age strata, and if so will evaluate treatment effect within strata, although the power to detect such differences is limited. </statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>22/08/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/12/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>40</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>Royal Hospital for Women - Randwick</hospital>
    <postcode>2031 - Randwick</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Hospital</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Royal Hospital for Women</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Royal Hospital for Women
Barker Street
Randwick
NSW
2031
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Royal Hospital for Women</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Royal Hospital for Women
Barker Street
Randwick
NSW
2031
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The Magnific Study aims to determine if the use of magnetic acupuncture will reduce the stress and pain experienced by infants in newborn intensive care units in response to a very common painful stimulus, heel pricks for blood collection. Babies will be randomised to having 5 magnetic stickers or placebos placed on each ear for 3 days. During this time, the baby's response to a heel prick will be measured using a widely used pain scale, the PIPP score. After three days, the stickers (with and without magnets) will be removed and the PIPP scores will be examined.</summary>
    <trialwebsite>To be arranged</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>South Eastern Sydney Local Health District</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Prince of Wales Hospital
High Street
Randwick NSW 2031</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>21/07/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>29/10/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ju Lee Oei</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Care
The Royal Hospital for Women
Barker Street
Randwick NSW 2031
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 6111</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9382 6191</fax>
      <email>j.oei@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ju Lee Oei</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Care
The Royal Hospital for Women
Barker Street
Randwick NSW 2031
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 6111</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9382 6191</fax>
      <email>j.oei@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ju Lee Oei</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Care
The Royal Hospital for Women
Barker Street
Randwick NSW 2031
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 6111</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9382 6191</fax>
      <email>j.oei@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Ju Lee Oei</name>
      <address>Department of Newborn Care
The Royal Hospital for Women
Barker Street
Randwick NSW 2031
</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9382 6111</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9382 6191</fax>
      <email>j.oei@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>