<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363657">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>7/02/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>12/02/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000169741</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Cervical radiculopathy: A new traction method versus ventroflexion traction :A randomized controlled 1-year follow-up study</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>the efficacy of two different traction methods in addition to conventional treatment on  nerve root function, pain, and disability in patients with discogenic cervical radiculopathy </scientifictitle>
    <utrn>U1111-1139-3107</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Cervical radiculopathy</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Physiotherapy</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The other two groups (A&amp;B)  received conventional treatment in addition to intermittent mechanical cervical traction; the group (A) received the traditional ventroflexion tractionfor 20 minutes, three times per week for four weeks. During the ventroflexion traction the patient was lying supine on a softly padded table with a pillow under the knees for relaxation. The position of the head during traction was adjusted by using a goniometer at 24 degree flexion without rotation or side flexion. the traction force was started at 9.1 kg (20 Ib) or 10% of the patient's body weight (whichever was less) and increased approximately 0.91 to 2.27 kg (2-5 Ib) every visit, depending on centralization or reduction of symptoms. The maximum force used was 15.91 kg (35 Ib). The on/off cycle was set at 50/10.
The group (B), which received the  flexor carpi radialis H- reflex based traction method for 20 minutes,
three times per week for four weeks, followed the same procedures of traditional traction with only exception that the optimal head posture was selected according to findings of H reflex. flexor carpi radialis H- reflex amplitude was recorded after the patient maintained the end range of 24 degree head flexion, mid position, 15 degree backward extension and 5 degree backward extension for 20 minutes. The electrophysiological findings represented in peak to peak amplitudes were compared with the findings recorded during comfortable neutral positions. The idea behind this technique is that postural modification can cause amplitude inhibition, indicating more compression of the impinged nerve root, or recovery, indicating decompression of the root. The peak to peak amplitudes was selected as compression decompression indicator as it is a more sensitive predictor of normal physiologic changes than is latency, which need more long time to be changed .</interventions>
    <comparator>The treatment regimens for control group consisted of physical pain relief methods (infrared, interferential therapy, and massage), muscle strengthening via isometric contraction of flexor and extensor muscles, and thoracic spine manipulation

IR application 
The patient was assumed the forward lean sitting position where the area to be treated (the paraspinal muscles of the neck and  trapizus muscle)  was adequately exposed, supported and relaxed. The lamp was positioned at distance ranged from (50-75cm) .the radiation strikes the surface at or near right angle to achieve maximum penetration. The duration of application was fifteen minutes per session
Interferential  application
During interferential application, patients were asked to adopt prone position. Interferential treatment was introduced using electrotherapy device ( Phyaction 787 , Netherlands). The interferential therapy was delivered at an amplitude-modulated constant frequency of 100 Hz and a pulse duration of 125 micro s due to its analgesic effect. A 20-min interferential session has been widely accepted within physiotherapy practitioners. 
Soft tissue mobilization
Soft tissue mobilization was performed to the muscles of the upper quarter with the involved upper extremity positioned in abduction and external rotation to preload the neural structures of the upper limb.Manual pressure was applied to the soft tissues of the upper quadrant in a deep, stroking manner with the intention to decrease pain and improve the mobility of the soft tissues surrounding the pathway of the neural structures of the upper limb. The therapist concentrated on any tissues on the cervical and scapular region and upper extremity that were graded as tight or tender in the evaluation. 


Thoracic Spine Manipulation
Initial treatment included high-velocity, low-amplitude thrust manipulation procedures directed at the upper- and mid-thoracic spines of spinal segments identified as hypomobile during segmental mobility testing34. Although we were unable to locate evidence for the use of thoracic spine manipulation in a patient population with cervical radiculopathy, several studies has demonstrated that an association exists between mobility in the thoracic spine and neck/shoulder pain. Based on these findings, it seems reasonable that a clinician would at least consider utilization of manual therapies to the thoracic spine for patients with cervical radiculopathy. 
Strengthening Exercises
Strengthening Exercises Following the thoracic spine manipulation, patients were instructed in and performed exercises focusing on strengthening of the deep neck flexors and scapulothoracic muscles regardless of their strength levels. The patients performed
deep neck flexor strengthening exercises , without the use of a biofeedback unit. The patient was supine, with the cervical spine in neutral, and instructed to flatten the curve of the neck by nodding the head. This position was held for 10 seconds and repeated 10 times. 
This conventional treatment was to be repeated three times per week for four weeks. Those in the control group received this conventional treatment only.  </comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Rehabilitation</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Neck Disability Index: The NDI is a 10-item questionnaire that measures a patients self-reported neck pain related disability. Questions include activities of daily living, such as: personal care, lifting, reading, work, driving, sleeping, recreational activities, pain intensity, concentration and headache. The questions are measured on a six-point scale from 0 (no disability) to 5 (full disability). The numeric response for each item is summed for a total score ranging from 0 to 50.  A higher NDI score indicates a greater patients perceived disability . </outcome>
      <timepoint>pre treatment,after 4 weeks of treatment,and at1-year follow up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The secondary outcome measures included symptoms (neck and arm pain), and neurophysiogical findings (latency and peak to peak amplitude of FCR H- reflex).</outcome>
      <timepoint>pre treatment,after 4 weeks of treatment,at 1-year follow up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients were included if they had unilateral C6 or C7 radiculopathy following herniated disc confirmed by imaging (computed tomography [CT] and/or magnetic resonance imaging [MRI]), C6  or C7 dermatomal numbness, and duration of symptoms more than 3 months to avoid acute stage of inflammation. Further, Inclusion criteria for these patients included a test item cluster identified by Wainner et al, which included the presence of 4 positive examination findings (Spurling test, upper limb tension test, cervical distraction test, and less than 60° cervical rotation towards the symptomatic side</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>35</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>48</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Exclusion criteria included the  presence of any medical "red flags" (eg, tumor, fracture, rheumatoid arthritis, osteoporosis, prolonged steroid use), History of previous cervical or thoracic spine surgery , Signs or symptoms of upper motor neuron disease, vestibulobasilar insufficiency, osteoporosis, , amyotrophic lateral sclerosis and inability to tolerate cervical flexion or extension position</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Patients were randomly assigned to one of  three groups after initial evaluation. They were randomly assigned by an independent person who picked one of the sealed envelopes, which contained numbers chosen by random number generator. Randomization was restricted to permuted blocks of different sizes to ensure equal numbers being allocated to each group. Each random permuted block was transferred to a sequence of consecutively numbered, sealed, opaque envelopes and these were stored in a locked drawer until required. As each participant formally entered the trial, the researcher opened the next envelope in the sequence in the presence of the patient.</concealment>
    <sequence> Randomization was restricted to permuted blocks of different sizes to ensure equal numbers being allocated to each group</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>mixed model analysis with repeated measures</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2010</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>1/03/2010</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>1/09/2011</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>1/07/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>216</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state>cairo</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Ibrahim Moustafa Moustafa</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress> Faculty of Physical Therapy, cairo university, Egypt 7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt. Postal Code: 12612</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Self funded/Unfunded</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Ibrahim Moustafa Moustafa</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Faculty of Physical Therapy, cairo university, Egypt 7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt. Postal Code: 12612</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Individual</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Aliaa Attiah Diab</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Faculty of Physical Therapy, cairo university, Egypt

7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt.

Postal Code: 12612</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Egypt</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The purpose of this study was to compare the nerve root function, pain, and disability in patients with discogenic cervical radiculopathy after two different  multimodal programs in both the short- and long-term; One of them involves manual therapy, exercise and the traditional ventroflexion traction in which an angle of 24 degree of flexion is considered as an optimal traction angle . The another one involves manual therapy, exercise and  new method of traction  in which we identify the optimal traction angle based on the maximum recovery of the peak to peak amplitude of flexor carpi radilais H- reflex .in this study ,we hypothesized that the addition of new method of traction to a multimodal program will yield a significant additional benefit to pain, function or disability in patients with cervical radiculopathy. </summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>faculty counsel for post graduated study and researcher</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Faculty of Physical Therapy - Cairo University 7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt. Postal Code: 12612
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>3/05/2009</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate />
      <ethiccountry>Egypt</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ibrahim Moustafa Moustafa</name>
      <address>faculty of physical therapy- Cairo university 7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt. Postal Code: 12612
</address>
      <phone>0020127022334</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ibrahiem.mostafa@pt.cu.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ibrahim Moustafa Moustafa</name>
      <address>faculty of physical therapy- Cairo university 7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt. Postal Code: 12612
</address>
      <phone>0020127022334</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ibrahiem.mostafa@pt.cu.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ibrahim Moustafa Moustafa</name>
      <address>faculty of physical therapy- Cairo university 7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt. Postal Code: 12612
</address>
      <phone>0020127022334</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ibrahiem.mostafa@pt.cu.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ibrahim Moustafa Moustafa</name>
      <address>faculty of physical therapy- Cairo university 7 Ahmed Elzaiat St. Ben Elsaryat - EI Dokki-Giza - Egypt. Postal Code: 12612
</address>
      <phone>0020127022334</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>ibrahiem.mostafa@pt.cu.edu.eg</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>