<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="336730">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>29/03/2011</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>5/04/2011</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12611000353998</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Validity of protective tube cecostomy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective randomized clinical trial of tube cecostomy versus loop colostomy for fecal diversion after left hemicolectomy due to obstructing disease regarding mean operative time, hospital stay,  mortality rate, stoma care and patient satisfaction,</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>no</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>left hemicolectomy due to obstructing disease.</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Group A: 44 patients undergoing tube cecostomy for fecal diversion after left hemicolectomy due to obstructing cancer. Tube cecostomy was performed as described by Clark and Hubay in 1972.Two concentric purse-string sutures are  placed over the anterior portion of the cecum leaving 3 cm. distance between them . A serosal incision is made central to the sutures and a suction trochar passed into the cecum to deflate it. Following this, the mucosa of the cecum is grasped with fine hemostats and elevated. A number 28 Foley catheter with a 30 cc. balloon is passed through the mucosal opening and a ligature is tied snugly around the everted mucosal edge to insure hemostasis. Then, 4 seromuscular stitches are applied to fix the cecum to the parietal peritoneum. The cecal tube is connected to the collecting tube. The cecal tubes were removed within 8 weeks.
Group B: 44 patients undergoing loop colostomy by exeriorization of the transverse colon in the form of loop  as diverting stoma for fecal diversion after left hemicolectomy.
The colostomies were closed within 8 weeks.</interventions>
    <comparator>Intervention: tube cecostomy Comparator/Control: loop colostomy .
The colostomies were closed within 8 weeks
Regarding the demographic data and the cause of bowel obstruction, we found no significant differences in both groups . Operative time, in group B, the duration of the primary  operation was considerably longer and statistically significant compared with that of group A as long time was needed to mobilize the colon and fashioning the stoma. Stoma care and patient satisfaction were better in patients with cecostomy group. 
The hospital stay for primary operation (admission, resuscitation, resection with colostomy) in patients of group B was 18-22 days and 7-9 days for colostomy closure . The total hospital stay in group B was 25-31 days  .  While the stay for primary operation in patients of group A ( admission , resuscitation, resection with cecostomy)  was 14-16 days and 2-3 days for cecostomy tube removal . The total hospital stay in group A was 16-19 days [ P&lt; 0.0003] .</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: surgery</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Primary  operation mortality rate.
Primary  operation means the left hemicolectomy with the stoma construction.
operation mortality rate is assessed  by clinical means</outcome>
      <timepoint>2 weeks postoperative</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Operative time.
Operative time is assessed  clinically</outcome>
      <timepoint>intraoperative</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Stoma care and patient satisfaction, both are assessed by clinical data and patient's report.</outcome>
      <timepoint>3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Re-operations for stoma closure, is assessed  clinically</outcome>
      <timepoint>after these 3 months</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Hospital stay, is assessed according medical recrods data and registration unit</outcome>
      <timepoint>within one month</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Inclusion criteria:
	The following inclusion criteria were defined:  (1) gross large bowel obstruction on plain films of the abdomen with compatible history and physical findings; (2) barium enema showing complete colorectal obstruction; (3) surgical finding of complete large bowel obstruction</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>22</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with perforation in addition to obstruction, and those with uncertain diagnosis or insufficient clinical data were also excluded from the study</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/01/1998</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate />
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>44</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Closed: follow-up complete</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry />
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <state />
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Individual</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Aly Saber</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Port-Fouad general Hospital. Port-Fouad, Egypt</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Egypt</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Port-Fouad general Hospital.</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Port-Fouad general Hospital, Port-Fouad, Egypt</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Egypt</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Historically, cecostomy has been advocated to protect a left sided anastomosis, used as a treatment for large bowel obstruction, cecal perforation.

Hypothesis:
  For temporary fecal diversion after left hemicolectomy due to obstructing cancer or sigmoid  volvulus  , tube cecostomy may help to reduce the rate of anastomotic leakage and also to avoid the second operation for stoma closure.

Methods:
	Over eleven years between  January 1998 and November 2009, all patients fulfilling the inclusion criteria with large bowel obstruction due to cancer or sigmoid volvulus only, were randomly divided into two   groups: A and B. Group A: 44 patients undergoing tube cecostomy as diverting stomas after left hemicolectomy due to obstructing cancer. Tube cecostomy was performed as described by Clark and Hubay in 1972 . Group B: 44 patients undergoing loop colostomy as diverting stomas after left hemicolectomy due to obstructing cancer.

Conclusion:

	Tube cecostomy is of therapeutic value in select situations. Proper patient selection, careful tube placement, and vigilant postoperative tube care should provide adequate function with minimal morbidity.</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication>Not published yet</publication>
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Aly Saber</name>
      <address>Port-Fouad general Hospital, Port-Fouad, Egypt.</address>
      <phone>+2/066/3406474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alysaber54@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Aly Saber</name>
      <address>Port-Fouad general Hospital, Port-Fouad, Egypt.</address>
      <phone>+2/066/ 3406474</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>alysaber54@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name>Aly Saber</name>
      <address>Port-Fouad general Hospital, Port-Fouad, Egypt.</address>
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email>alysaber54@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Egypt</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>