<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="365140">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>11/10/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>15/10/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613001150730</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>How to be Brave; Program to treat specific phobia in children and Prevent anxiety and depression in adolescence and adulthood.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A Randomised Controlled Trial comparing one-session therapy (Active version) for childhood specific phobia vs. waitlist control (Control version).</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Specific Phobia in children (phobia of falling from high places and phobia of small enclosed spaces)</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Anxiety</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This One Session Treatment is conducted over one 3-hour session and involves the child gradually facing their fears of falling from heights or small enclosed spaces (graded exposure). The child and therapist build a step ladder of activities/events ranging from the least anxiety provoking to the most. The therapist models how to face the feared object or situation step by step, and then supports the child to replicate the exposure. Research suggests this treatment is effective. OST is carried out by a trained and qualified clinical psychologist.

Only phobias of falling from heights and enclosed spaces will be addressed in this trial. 

OST will be carried out at the end of the current school term in which the participant consents to participate. The treatment will be run in a small group of other children and parents. Participants with a fear of heights will be treated as one group and participants with a fear of enclosed spaces will be treated as a separate group. Research suggests that group CBT for children is effective as they are familiar with learning in a group environment (school) and are able to support and celebrate each other's achievements.</interventions>
    <comparator>One-session treatment (OST) of graded exposure to feared stimuli (heights or small enclosed space) lasting up to three hours will be carried out at the end of the following school term in which the participant consents to participate. This group will receive  the same treatment as the intervention group at the end of the following school term, after the intervention group have received treatment. This is a waitlist control group.

OST is carried out by a trained and qualified clinical psychologist.

</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Other</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in Behavioural Avoidance Test (BAT) scores</outcome>
      <timepoint>Administered at base-line; T1 (before start of intervention), post intervention; T2 (immediately after intervention) and 6-month follow up; T3.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Fears Survey Schedule for Children- Revised (FSSC-R)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre intervention; T1.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>OST participant attendance</outcome>
      <timepoint>Attendance numbers collected immediately after treatment</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Must have completed the THIS WAY UP Schools online stress management course at school.

Must be in years 5 or 6 of primary school,

Must score highly on the questions taken from the Fears Survey Schedule in Children- Revised (FSSC-R) 

Must state that their fear identified by the FSSC-R stops them from doing what they would like to do</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>8</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>11</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Nil</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>The Stress Management course is currently being used by primary and secondary schools across Australia as part of the Personal Development Health and Physical Education curriculum. Details of the course can be accessed at www.thiswayup.org.au/schools. 

Students who meet eligibility criteria will receive a letter (as well as their parents) inviting them to participate in the trial. Students and parents who consent will be enrolled in the trial.



</concealment>
    <sequence>The schools will be randomised as opposed to the individual participants to avoid contamination. Participating schools will be randomised using a list generated prior to the study.

Allocation concealment will occur in the following way: A staff member not involved in the clinical trial will generate the sequence using computer software and place each choice in a sequentially numbered, opaque sealed and stapled envelope.</sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>We expect pre-post improvement of of effect size (ES) 1.0 for the OST group on the Behavioural Avoidance Test scores. It is also expected that the OST group will improve more than the waitlist control group  by an ES of &gt;0.8, power at 80% and alpha set at 0.5.

Analyses will be undertaken using mixed-model repeated measures (MMRM) ANOVA with measurement time point as a within-groups factor and intervention as a between-groups factor.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase />
    <anticipatedstartdate>11/11/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>18/11/2013</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>2/02/2015</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>18/11/2013</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>0</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Withdrawn</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate>18/11/2013</actuallastvisitdate>
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason>Participant recruitment difficulties</withdrawnreason>
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Bupa</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Bupa
GPO Box 9809
Brisbane, QLD 4001
Australia</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Commercial sector/Industry</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>BUPA (The British United Provident Association Limited; a company which provides private medical insurance)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Bupa
GPO Box 9809
Brisbane, QLD 4001
Australia</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>Nil</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>Nil</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>After completing the online managing stress course and OST children will be skilled in mastering irrational fears and will have improved mental health and wellbeing. They will be better equipped to confront difficult situations in school and in play.

Evidence strongly points to the prevention of the onset of anxiety and depressive disorders in adults through the treatment of fears in children (Kessler et al., 2011).

The rationale for this study is to demonstrate the efficacy of identifying children in primary school with specific phobia and using early intervention (OST) to reduce the risk of anxiety and depressive disorders later in adolescence and adulthood.

The main hypothesis is:
Participants who were randomised and attended the OST will have reduced fears (lower BAT scores) after treatment compared to the waitlist control group.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>St. Vincent's Hospital HREC</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>St. Vincent's Hospital
394-404 Victoria St
Darlinghurst, 2010
NSW</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>6/08/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HREC/13/SVH/147</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>12/07/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Gavin Andrews</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression, St Vincents Hospital, Victoria St, Darlinghurst, 2010. NSW</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1405</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gavina@unsw.ed.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Louise Brownhill</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression, St Vincents Hospital, Victoria St, Darlinghurst, 2010. NSW</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1541</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.brownhill@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Louise Brownhill</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression, St Vincents Hospital, Victoria St, Darlinghurst, 2010. NSW</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1541</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>l.brownhill@unsw.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Ms</title>
      <name>Louise Brownhill</name>
      <address>Clinical Research Unit for Anxiety and Depression, St Vincents Hospital, Victoria St, Darlinghurst, 2010. NSW</address>
      <phone>+612 8382 1541</phone>
      <fax>l.brownhill@unsw.edu.au</fax>
      <email />
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>