<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="364451">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>18/06/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>2/08/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000857707</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>The Preview Study Australia: prevention of diabetes through lifestyle intervention and population studies in Europe and around the world.

</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The preview study is a randomised, controlled, multi-centre, international clinical trial of 2 types of diet and 2 exercise strategies (4 arms in total) for the prevention of type 2 diabetes in overweight or obese volunteers at high risk of diabetes.</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>PREVIEW- PREVention of diabetes In Europe and Worldwide</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>Project no. 312057
Seventh Framework Programme</secondaryid>
    <secondaryid>NTOCO177-7893 WHOrganisation Trial No.</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Obesity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Diabetes</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Metabolic and Endocrine</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Diabetes</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Diet and Nutrition</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Obesity</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>The study consists of two distinct parts, i.e an 8 week weight reduction period followed by a 148 week randomized weight maintenance, diet and exercise intervention. 
All participants are put on an energy restricted low calorie diet (LCD) consisting of 800-1000kcal/d with a target macronutrient composition of 15-20% of total energy from fat, 35-40% from protein and 45-50% from carbohydrate. The participants will be provided with nutritionally complete meal replacement LCD products  (4 sachets per day) supplied by Cambridge Weight Plan U.K. for 8 weeks, aiming for a minimum 8% reduction in weight. 
The post-LCD phase aims to prevent Type 2 Diabetes by modifying lifestyle factors such as diet and physical activity to promote healthy weight maintenance. The participants are randomized into two different diet interventions and two exercise interventions for a total of 148 weeks. The 2 diet interventions are:
1.  Moderate Protein (MP) Diet: protein 15% of total energy intake (E%), carbohydrates 55 E%, and a dietary glycaemic index (GI) greater than 56;
2. High protein (HP) Diet: protein 25 E%, carbohydrates 45 E%, GI less than 55.
Both diet interventions focus on healthy food items to be consumed ad libitum with respect to energy. A dietitian will educate participants on portion sizes, healthy eating habits to achieve the macronutrient and GI prescription and self-monitoring in order to maintain weight loss. 
The two exercise interventions are:
1.	Moderate Intensity (MI): 60-75% of maximal heart rate (HRmax) 150mins total/week (frequency 3-5 times) e.g. brisk walking.
2.	High intensity (HI): 76-90% HRmax for 75 mins total/week (frequency 2-3 times) e.g. running. 
In the first weeks of the weight maintenance phase the participants will work with an exercise physiologist to plan their physical activity program including a 4week period where exercise levels are slowly introduced to reach the intended prescribed program.

</interventions>
    <comparator>All participants are randomised into one diet and one exercise group, therefore there will be four intervention groups (MP-MI, MP-HI, HP-MI and HP-HI).</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Early detection / Screening</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>The incidence of type-2 diabetes in the high protein versus medium protein diet will be measured 3 years after the baseline and based on the WHO/IDF criteria:
1. Fasting plasma glucose greater than 7.0mmol/l
2. 75g oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT) with FBG greater than 7.0 mmol/l and/or 2 hour plasma glucose greater than 11.1 mmol/l or,
3. Glycated haemoglobin (HbA1c) greater than 6.5%, or
4. random plasma glucose greater than 11.1 mmol/l in the presence of classical diabetes symptoms.
</outcome>
      <timepoint>OGTTs and blood tests will be conducted at baseline, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months to test for type-2 diabetes. Patients will also be requested to report any adverse events or change in medical status. Participants will be asked about any adverse events at group meetings at 2, 4,  6 weeks and 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 8, 10, 12, 15, 16, 18, 24, 30 and 36 months and informal phone/email contact in the last 2 years between visits.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Thee secondary outcomes will be tested against the four intervention groups based on WHO/IDF criteria (adjusted for diet). The following parameter will be examined: change in HbA1c as a measure of average glucose levels.</outcome>
      <timepoint>HbA1c will be measured at baseline, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in insulin sensitivity will be examined in the four intervention groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Change in HbA1c, as a measure of average blood glucose levels and OGTTS will be conducted at baseline, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months to test for insulin sensitivity. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in anthropometry i.e. change in body weight (scales), body fat mass (DEXA scan), and measured waist, hip and thigh circumference. The proportion of subjects maintaining at least 0, 5, or 10% weight loss relative to initial body weight will be compared in the four intervention groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Anthropometry will be measured at baseline, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months .</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Change in the risk factors for cardiovascular disease such as blood pressure, lipid profile, c-reactive protein and liver enzymes, will be compared in the four intervention groups.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Blood tests and blood pressure measurements will be conducted at baseline, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months to test for type-2 diabetes.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Changes in perceived quality of life  and workability will be compared in the four intervention groups using questionnaires,(WHOQOL-BREF (The WHOQOL Group 1998) and  (Work Ability Index (WAI:Tuomi et al 1998), respectively .</outcome>
      <timepoint>Questionnaires will be conducted at baseline, 6, 12, 24 and 36 months and compared in the four intervention groups.. </timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Assessment sleep and chronic stress in the four intervention groups, using the Epworth Sleepiness Scale (ESS) and Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) questionnaires.










</outcome>
      <timepoint>The questionnaires will be conducted at baseline, 6 12, 24 and 36 months.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>1. Body Mass Index greater than 25kg/m2
2. WHO/IDF (International Diabetes Foundation) definition of pre-diabetes: Impaired fasting glucose (IFG) 5.6-6.9mmol/l or Impaired glucose tolerance (IGT) Venous plasma glucose concentration of 7.8-11.0 mmol/l at 2 hrs after oral administration of 75g glucose (oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT)), with fasting plasma glucose less than 7.0 mmol/l.
</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>25</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>70</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>1. Diabetes (other than gestational diabetes).
2. Systolic blood pressure  above 160 mmHg and/or diastolic blood pressure above 100mmHg
3. Previous bariatric surgery
4. Significant health problems
</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>Allocation will be concealed. Potential participants will be recruited using a variety of ways i.e. newspaper advertisements, written and electronic media (website questionnaire), local obesity and diabetes associations and direct contact with primary and occupational health care providers. Individuals will be invited to contact the site-centre by email, telephone or SMS. Individuals will be contacted by phone or email for a short pre-screening interview where most inclusion and exclusion criteria will be queried. Based on the interview potential participants will be sent a written description of the study and when written consent is obtained invited to a laboratory-screening day. All potential participants will sign a consent form before laboratory screening begins.  Measurements of height, weight, resting blood pressure, an ECG (people over 55 years) and a simplified OGTT consisting of a fasting blood glucose and a 2 hour blood glucose (after 75g glucose) will be used to assess subjects eligibility. Subjects will be informed of their eligibility. The participant will be randomized into one of the four intervention groups by a central computer generated randomization system at the central administration site in Denmark. Randomization of all the participants is done by stratifying the participants according to age-group and sex (men, women). The randomization is done in blocks to ensure an equal number of participants in each group. The randomization will not be revealed to the group until week 9 of the study (after their LCD phase).</concealment>
    <sequence>Subject numbers will be generated at the central study site at the University of Helsinki. All data will be collected using an electronic case record form (eCRF) based on the electronic data capture system OpenClinica. A screening number and the date of birth identify the subjects on the eCRF. The randomization number/code is via a web application linked to OpenClinica. Randomization is done by stratifying the subjects according to age group and sex. It will be done in blocks in order to ensure an equal number of participants in each group. </sequence>
    <masking>Open (masking not used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>Published data has demonstrated among patients who completed the study the 3 year incidence of type 2 diabetes in adults aged over 40 with a diabetes risk score AUSDIAB OVER 6 is 21%. Our main power calculations are based on two intervention arms (i.e. HP vs MP diet). We hypothesize a risk reduction of 25% in the MP group and will reduce the diabetes incidence to 15.8%. In the HP group the risk reduction, we hypothesize, will achieve a 50% risk reduction to 10.5% at 3 years.
Using these assumptions a conservative estimate of the sample size required to detect this difference in incidence (15.8% vs 10.5%) is at least 649 per arm or 1298 participants in total (for a two-sided comparison with a power of 80% and alpha of 0.05). We estimate a 30% drop-out rate (similar to DIOGenes) during the 148 week intervention period.
Thus, we need at least 1860 subjects (across all study centres) starting the intervention. To further allow for a drop-out after inclusion and for subjects not losing 8% weight during the 8 week weight loss period (estimated 25%), a total of about 2472 subjects will be recruited.
The consortium will therefore recruit a total of 2,500 participants at high risk of diabetes, from the 8 centres ( a total of 310-315 in each centre) to initiate the weight reduction period.
</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1 />
    <masking2 />
    <masking3 />
    <masking4 />
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>30/08/2013</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>21/01/2014</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2014</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>27/02/2015</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>310</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize>195</actualsamplesize>
    <recruitmentstatus>Active, not recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>1/06/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>The University of Sydney</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Level 6 Charles Perkins Centre D 17
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>The University of Sydney</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Level 6 Charles Perkins Centre D17 The uNiversity of Sydney, NSW 2006</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>Other Collaborative groups</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council - European Union (NHMRC-EU) Collaborative Project.</sponsorname>
      <sponsoraddress>NHMRC  European Union Collaborative Research Grants
Research Programs
GPO Box 1421
CANBERRA  ACT  2601</sponsoraddress>
      <sponsorcountry>Australia</sponsorcountry>
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>The primary goal of the Preview intervention study is to identify the most efficient lifestyle pattern for the prevention of type-2 diabetes in a population of pre-diabetic overweight or obese individuals (i.e those at high risk of diabetes). This will be done by conducting a  clinical randomized intervention trial of 3 years duration in a total 310 pre-diabetic adults in Australia. </summary>
    <trialwebsite>preview.ning.com/sydney</trialwebsite>
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Office of Research Integrity/Research Portfolio The University of Sydney</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Office of Research Integrity/Research Portfolio,
Level 6 Jane Foss Russell Building G02
The University of Sydney
NSW 2006
</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>14/07/2013</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>2013/535</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>27/06/2013</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Prof</title>
      <name>Jennie Brand Miller</name>
      <address>School of life and Environmental Sciences Level 6 Charles Perkins Centre, D17, University of Sydney, NSW 2006.</address>
      <phone>+61 2 9351 3759</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 9036 3024</fax>
      <email>jennie.brandmiller@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Roslyn Muirhead</name>
      <address>PREVIEW Study, Level 6 Charles Perkins Centre D17 The University of Sydney, Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+ 61 478 472 170</phone>
      <fax>+61 2 90363176</fax>
      <email>roslyn.muirhead@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ros Muirhead</name>
      <address>PREVIEW Study, Level 6 Charles Perkins Centre D17 The University of Sydney, Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 478 472 170</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>roslyn.muirhead@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Ros Muirhead</name>
      <address>PREVIEW Study, Level 6 Charles Perkins Centre D17 The University of Sydney, Sydney NSW 2006</address>
      <phone>+61 478 472 170</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>roslyn.muirhead@sydney.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>