<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="370165">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>17/05/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>11/07/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616000920493</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>A Comparison of Different Patellar Implant Designs in Total Knee Replacement.</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>A prospective randomized comparative trial (pilot study) to compare intra-operative and post-operative outcome measures between inset, onlay round and onlay oval designs of patellar implants in patients undergoing unilateral total knee arthroplasty for degenerative osteoarthritis</scientifictitle>
    <utrn> U1111-1179-9194</utrn>
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>Nil Known</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>Osteoarthritis</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Musculoskeletal</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Osteoarthritis</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Surgery</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Surgical techniques</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>This research will study the outcomes of using different patellar implants in Total Knee Arthroplasty (TKA). Patients with knee osteoarthritis undergoing TKA will be randomized into three groups allocated to one of the three patellar implants' designs. The different patellar designs to be evaluated in this study are:
-  Onlay oval: asymmetrical oval patella designs with three projections cemented on the resurfaced patella.
- Onlay round: symmetrical round patella designs with three projections cemented on the resurfaced patella.
 - Inset: a round biconvex design with one projection cemented on reamed under-surface of patella.

Intervention will be performed by a fellowship trained surgeons with minimum 10 years experience. The approximate duration of the TKA procedure is around 90 minutes. The duration of performing the selected patellar implants is 5-10 minutes. Adherence to the assigned randomization will be monitored by the assisting fellow. any misconduct or fidelity will be documented and reported in the monthly research meeting. </interventions>
    <comparator>The Inset design group will be the comparator group.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Surgery</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Devices</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patellar surface coverage: A photograph will be taken to the patella after implanting the trial design with a ruler to the side. Photoshop CS program will be used to calculate the percentage of surface coverage by the implant.</outcome>
      <timepoint>Intra-operative: This will be done after implanting the trial patellar design.</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patellar tilt on weight bearing merchant view (x-ray)</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Blood supply to patella using bone scan; to asses for patellar osteonecrosis.</outcome>
      <timepoint>6 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Patient's pain and functional scores (Composite secondary outcome): using validated Kujala scores. (Patient self reported outcome score using validated questionnaire. Kujala questionnaire reports on patient's pain, daily activities and functional level)</outcome>
      <timepoint>Pre-operative
6 months post surgery</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Patients undergoing unilateral total knee arthroplasty for degenerative osteoarthritis</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>50</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>85</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>- Revision TKA surgery
- Bilateral simultaneous TKA
- Prior osteotomies around the knee or extra-articular deformities
- Systemic inflammatory disease (e.g. rheumatoid arthritis, Systemic lupus erythematosus, etc)
- Medial and lateral knee ligamentous instability on knee examination.
- TKA for acute trauma and need for allograft
- Prior patellar fracture, ruptured extensor mechanism
- Constrained implants, stemmed components or metal augmentation during surgery.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Treatment</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment>A computer software will be used for randomization of patients into the three designs options.  The study will be patient blinded. and the operating surgeon will be informed about the randomization at surgery time.(Allocation is not concealed)</concealment>
    <sequence>Computerised sequence generation</sequence>
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods>Based on power analysis, a sample size of 20 patients in each cohort would provide appropriate power (beta level = 0.80, alpha level = 0.05) to detect an 80% improvement in percentage of patellar surface coverage (as oval onlay design proposed to provide nearly full coverage) and in risk of osteonecrosis by preserving the lateral facet with the oval onlay design. There will be a midterm analysis when 30 patients are recruited to assess whether significance has been reached and whether or not, further patient enrolment is necessary. Means, ranges, and standard deviations will be recorded for percentage of patellar surface coverage, pre-operative and postoperative scores in all groups. ANOVA will be used to compare differences in means between continuous variables. ANOVA will be used to statistically assess pre-operative demographic factors.  Fisher's exact test will be used to test for significance in osteonecrosis difference (proportions) between the groups. Statistical significance set at p = 0.05.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate />
    <actualstartdate>15/06/2016</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>31/08/2016</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>60</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate />
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>NSW</recruitmentstate>
    <hospital>St George Private Hospital - Kogarah</hospital>
    <postcode>2217 - Kogarah</postcode>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>Commercial sector/Industry</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Sydney Knee Specialist</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Sydney Knee Specialists, Suite 8
19, Kensington St
Kogarah, NSW 2217</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Hospital</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>St George Private Hospital</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>1 South St, Kogarah NSW 2217</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Aim:
To compare the intra-operative and post-operative outcome measures between three different patellar implant designs in patients undergoing total knee arthroplasty (TKA) surgery with regards to patellar bone coverage and tracking, patient-reported outcomes and post-operative radiological and scintigraphic  analysis. 

Background:
Controversy remains regarding whether the patella should be resurfaced in total knee arthroplasty. However, at present the scientific literature supports patellar resurfacing with regards to reduced re-operation risk and improved long term patient satisfaction.
Two basic techniques present for resurfacing the patella; either onlay or inset. In the inset design, a round domed implant is reamed in the patella and fixed with a single central projection (peg). On the other hand, the onlay design has either round (symmetrical) or oval (asymmetrical) shaped patellae with three small peripheral pegs fixed on the cut surface of the patella. When using a round patellar implant, either onlay or inset, some surgeons perform a lateral facetectomy to avoid lateral compression syndrome and enhance patellar tracking. However, neither method has proved to be superior.

A wide range of complications are associated with patellar resurfacing. These include patellar fracture, osteonecrosis related to devascularisation, patellar polyethylene (PE) wear, aseptic loosening, instability, dislocation, overstuffing and rupture of the extensor mechanism. Many of these can be catastrophic. One should always consider the peculiar blood supply to the patella during TKA and patellar resurfacing as iatrogenic disruption of supplying vessels has been identified as a major contributing factor in post-operative patellofemoral complications. The hypothesis of this study is that onlay oval design provides optimal bone coverage, better tracking, better patient reported outcome scores and carries the lowest risk of osteonecrosis in comparison with the other two designs.

Trial Objectives:
To prospectively compare intra-operative observed measures, patient-reported outcome measures and radiological results between inset, onlay round and onlay oval designs of patellar implants in patients undergoing total knee arthroplasty surgery. Specifically, we will compare patellar surface bone coverage, pain and functional scores together with patellar tracking and vascular status of the patella postoperatively. 
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Hunters New England research ethics and governance unit</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Research Support and Development Office
Locked bag 1, New Lambton, NSW, 2305</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>25/02/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec />
      <ethicsubmitdate>15/12/2015</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment>
    <filepath>http://www.anzctr.org.au/AnzctrAttachments/370165-Patella trial protocol ED edit.docx</filepath>
  </attachment>
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Samuel Macdessi</name>
      <address>Sydney Knee Specialists, Suite 8, 19, Kensington St, Kogarah NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+61283070333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>samuelmacdessi@sydneyknee.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Samuel Macdessi</name>
      <address>Sydney Knee Specialists, Suite 8, 19, Kensington St, Kogarah NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+61283070333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>samuelmacdessi@sydneyknee.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Samuel Macdess</name>
      <address>Sydney Knee Specialists, Suite 8, 19, Kensington St, Kogarah NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+61283070333</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>samuelmacdessi@sydneyknee.com.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Monther Gharaibeh</name>
      <address>Sydney Knee Specialists, Suite 8, 19, Kensington St, Kogarah NSW 2217</address>
      <phone>+61410056080</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>gharaibeh82@yahoo.com</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>