<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="371356">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>24/08/2016</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>26/08/2016</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12616001177448</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Promoting walking, less sitting and better mental health in older adults</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>The feasibility and efficacy of an motivationally embellished intervention to increase walking, reduce sitting and improve mental health in older adults in retirement villages: The Residents in Action Trial (RiAT)</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym>RiAT</trialacronym>
    <secondaryid>None</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition>sedentary</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>physical inactivity</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>poor mental health</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Public Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Health promotion/education</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Physical Medicine / Rehabilitation</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Other physical medicine / rehabilitation</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Seven retirement villages will be assigned to the experimental condition with another seven retirement villages serving as the control condition. Resident ambassadors are residents in the retirement villages who are healthy and already physically active themselves and who are willing and demonstrate commitment to take on this role. 
All resident ambassadors (ie in both conditions) will be asked to take part in a one-day face-to-face safe walk leader workshop led by members of the research team. This workshop will consist of training in how to lead group walks in a safe manner, what to do in case of emergencies and specify the tasks needed to coordinate and lead the group walks. The workshop will consist of practical exercises and participants will receive printed hand-outs of leaflets to support learning.
Resident ambassadors in the experimental villages will also be trained by members of the research team via two face to face 2-hour workshops in applying motivational techniques to empower their physically inactive peers to increase walking, reduce sitting and improve mental health through a combination of group-led walks, group educational sessions, and booklets incorporating key behaviour change techniques. Specifically, In these workshops, the ambassadors will be briefly introduced to the basic principles of the motivational framework underpinning the intervention (i.e., SDT), and will be engaged in practical exercises that will aim to show how to support other residents' autonomous motivation for walking and for reducing sitting behaviours. Specifically, the different motivations underpinning engagement in these behaviours will be described and illustrated. The resident ambassadors will then be introduced to ways in which autonomous motivation can be supported, for example via promoting participants' feelings of competence, personal volition and choice, and feelings of connectedness with other members of the walking group. Such activities have been shown in the SDT literature to support key psychological needs and hence boost autonomous motivation. The resident ambassadors will be encouraged to discuss concrete examples of how they can put these principles into practice. They will also be provided with relevant examples. Resident ambassadors will be trained to be supportive, encourage participants' involvement and opinions in making choices (e.g., walking routes, ways to break up sitting time), use open-ended questions, be empathetic, avoid judgemental or controlling language, provide rationales for activities, and encourage personal responsibility and initiative. Such behaviours have been associated with an "autonomy-supportive" interpersonal communication style and sustained changes in individuals' motivation and well-being. 
All resident ambassadors will lead 3 weekly group walks for 10 weeks, each lasting 20-30 minutes. Resident participants will be encouraged to engage in 2 further independently organised walks per week of similar duration for 10 weeks. After 10 weeks, the resident participants will be encouraged to independently organise 5 weekly 20-30 minute walks for a further 6 weeks. Resident participants will receive one group-taught 2-hour session delivered face to face by the research team, at the beginning of the intervention, on the benefits of walking and reducing sitting time for health, and will be provided with outdoor walk route maps, and information on step counts for specific walks to destinations inside and outside the villages. The participants will also receive a tips sheet on ways to break up sitting time which will be based on the strategies. Further, all participants will be provided with log-books for the documentation of step counts on a daily basis. They will also be encouraged to use a tick sheet to indicate a) how many times per day they take a break from sitting (when sitting more than 30 minutes), and, b) on each occasion, which of the selected strategies they have used to break up sitting time. The resident participants in the experimental condition will also be offered another 2-hour face to face group session on motivation and self-regulation strategies delivered by members of the research team, and will receive printed materials and activity sheets to support their learning.



</interventions>
    <comparator>Resident ambassadors will receive one day safe walk leader workshop but will not be motivationally trained (in contrast to the resident ambassadors in the intervention group). The resident ambassadors will lead 3 weekly group walks for 10 weeks, each lasting 20-30 minutes. Resident participants will be encouraged to engage in 2 further independently organised walks per week of similar duration for 10 weeks. After 10 weeks, the resident participants will be encouraged to independently organise 5 weekly 20-30 minute walks for another 6 weeks. Resident participants will receive one group-taught 2-hour session delivered by the research team, at the beginning of the intervention, on the benefits of walking and reducing sitting time for health, and will be provided with outdoor walk route maps, and information on step counts for specific walks to destinations inside and outside the villages. The participants will also receive a tips sheet on ways to break up sitting time which will be based on the strategies. Further, all participants will be provided with log-books for the documentation of step counts on a daily basis. They will also be encouraged to use a tick sheet to indicate a) how many times per day they take a break from sitting (when sitting more than 30 minutes), and, b) on each occasion, which of the selected strategies they have used to break up sitting time. The resident participants in this condition will not receive any training in specific motivational and self-regulation strategies.
</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Lifestyle</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Behaviour</interventioncode>
    <interventioncode>Prevention</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Step counts will be retrieved from participants' log books</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 16 weeks (end of the intervention), 6 month follow-up</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Self-reported physical activity will be assessed via the Physical Activity Scale for the Elderly (PASE; Washburn et al., 1993; Journal of Clinical Epidemiology, 46, 153-162)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 16 weeks (end of the intervention), 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Perceptions of health will be measured via one item from the SF-12 (Gandek et al., 1998, Journal of Clinical Epidemiology, 51, 1171-1178)</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 16 weeks (end of the intervention), 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>General functioning and quality of life will be assessed suing the Dartmouth COOP Functional Assessment Charts (Nelson et al., 1987; Journal of Chronic Disease, 40, 55S-63S).</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 16 weeks (end of the intervention), 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Depression measured by the relevant sub-scale of the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS; Zigmond &amp; Snaith, 1983; Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavia, 67, 361-370).</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 16 weeks (end of the intervention), 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Subjective vitality as assessed via the Subjective Vitality Scale (Rubio &amp; Hood, 2000; Social Indicators Research, 52, 313-324).</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 16 weeks (end of the intervention), 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Loneliness will be measured using the loneliness scale developed by Hawkley et al. (2005; Psychological Science, 16, 798-804).</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 16 weeks (end of the intervention), 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Anxiety as assessed by the relevant sub-scale of the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS; Zigmond &amp; Snaith, 1983; Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavia, 67, 361-370).</outcome>
      <timepoint>baseline, 16 weeks (end of intervention), 6-month follow-up</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>Eligible participants will be permanent village residents, aged 65 years or over, who are able to communicate well in English, provide consent, participate in baseline assessments, have no terminal illness or health problems that prevent them from walking (we will include those who use walking sticks and walking frames), do not have a known dementia diagnosis, can walk continuously on a flat surface at a light/moderate pace for fifteen minutes, have not had two or more falls in the past 3 months, and do not currently meet the physical activity recommendations for health (150 minutes moderate intensity
physical activity per week in bouts of 10 minutes or more). Participants will also be asked to complete the Physical Activity Readiness Questionnaire to ensure that there are no contraindications for walking.</inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>60</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage />
    <inclusivemaxagetype>No limit</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>Yes</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Sufficiently physically active (currently meets recommendation of 150 minutes of at least moderate physical activity per week), health problems preventing walking, contraindications for walking as specified by the Physical Activity Readiness Questionnaire, dementia diagnosis</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking>Blinded (masking used)</masking>
    <assignment>Parallel</assignment>
    <designfeatures>Cluster</designfeatures>
    <endpoint>Efficacy</endpoint>
    <statisticalmethods>The main purpose of the analyses is to develop reliable power estimates for a subsequent definitive trial. Specifically, descriptive statistics on variable means and adherence to, and drop-out from, the intervention will be calculated. Further, internal reliability coefficients for questionnaire data will be estimated. The main analyses will be conducted using multilevel modelling (also called mixed-effects modelling) on an intention-to-treat basis for missing values. This type of analysis is superior to standard regression analyses and repeated measures ANOVAs as it adjusts standard errors to take into account village clustering effects. We will compare mean scores and rates of change across arms for walking and sitting behaviours, and all mental health outcomes; we will also examine individual
variation from mean trends. Perceived environmental and village characteristics (lease for life, resident funded, and subsidised tenancy) will be analysed as moderators of the effects of arm allocation on the outcomes. Confidence intervals of outcome variability and effect sizes will be calculated. An upper 90% confidence limit of the ICC of the primary outcome will be estimated to inform the sample size calculation for a future definitive clustered RCT.</statisticalmethods>
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>False</masking2>
    <masking3>False</masking3>
    <masking4>False</masking4>
    <patientregistry>False</patientregistry>
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Not Applicable</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>9/09/2016</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate />
    <anticipatedenddate>31/01/2017</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate />
    <samplesize>210</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Not yet recruiting</recruitmentstatus>
    <anticipatedlastvisitdate>28/02/2018</anticipatedlastvisitdate>
    <actuallastvisitdate />
    <dataanalysis />
    <withdrawnreason />
    <withdrawnreasonother />
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate>WA</recruitmentstate>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Curtin University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Kent Street
Bentley
Perth
WA 6102</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Australia</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>Government body</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Western Australian Health Promotion Foundation (Healthway)</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>PO Box 1284 
West Perth 
WA 6872</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Australia</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Ageing Australians represent a growing proportion of the total population and retirement villages are becoming an increasingly popular residential option for older adults. Although initiatives designed to increase activity among residents are widely available in these settings, their uptake is limited and their sustainability unknown. There is an urgent need to identify effective, sustainable strategies that can serve to increase physical activity, reduce sitting, and improve mental health. We will examine whether a 16-week programme using well-established motivational techniques, will result in sustainable increases in walking, reduced sitting time and improved mental health in older adults (minimum 60 years old) residing in retirement villages in Western Australia. The program will use motivational strategies for which the research team is particularly expert and has successfully used in previously funded research. To make the intervention relevant to the target population, we have also conducted extensive interviews with residents and managers in retirement villages in preparation for this proposal. The results of these interviews have been used to adapt the program to the needs of the target group. It is expected that participants who are allocated to the treatment with trained walk ambassadors and who have received motivation training will show greater (sustained) increases in walking, reductions in sitting and larger improvements in mental health. Participants will be divided into two groups, each consisting of 105 residents. Residents from 7 villages allocated to one group will take part in a combination of 16 weeks of group-led and individual walks facilitated by motivationally trained resident ambassadors. Residents will also be taught motivation skills they can use to help them change and sustain a physically active lifestyle in the longer-term without the help of the resident ambassadors. The comparison group (n=105), consisting of residents from 7 different villages, will also be encouraged to engage in group and individual walks, but their resident ambassadors will not be trained in motivational techniques. Changes in walking and sitting behaviour, and as a consequence, changes in mental health, will be examined. The effects of the surrounding physical environment (e.g., perceived safety, safety from traffic and proximity to amenities) will also be explored. This is a motivation-enhancing programme which has the potential to eventually be rolled out across various types of accommodation for older adults.
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
    <ethicscommitee>
      <ethicname>Curtin University Human Research Ethics Committee</ethicname>
      <ethicaddress>Curtin University
Office of Research and Development
GPO Box U1987
Perth 
Western Australia 6845</ethicaddress>
      <ethicapprovaldate>10/08/2016</ethicapprovaldate>
      <hrec>HRE2016-0187</hrec>
      <ethicsubmitdate>30/05/2016</ethicsubmitdate>
      <ethiccountry>Australia</ethiccountry>
    </ethicscommitee>
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Cecilie Thogersen-Ntoumani</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
Western Australia 6845
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 8 92 66 5171</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>C.Thogersen@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Cecilie Thogersen-Ntoumani</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
Western Australia 6845
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 8 92 66 5171</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>C.Thogersen@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Cecilie Thogersen-Ntoumani</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
Western Australia 6845
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 8 92 66 5171</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>C.Thogersen@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Cecilie Thogersen-Ntoumani</name>
      <address>School of Psychology &amp; Speech Pathology
Curtin University
GPO Box U1987
Perth
Western Australia 6845
Australia</address>
      <phone>+61 (0) 8 92 66 5171</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>C.Thogersen@curtin.edu.au</email>
      <country>Australia</country>
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>