<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='anzctrTransform.xsl'?>
<ANZCTR_Trial requestNumber="363459">
  <stage>Registered</stage>
  <submitdate>9/01/2013</submitdate>
  <approvaldate>16/01/2013</approvaldate>
  <actrnumber>ACTRN12613000054718</actrnumber>
  <trial_identification>
    <studytitle>Effect of Rocuronium and Sugammadex on Myalgia and Headache After Electro-Convulsive Therapy</studytitle>
    <scientifictitle>Does Rocuronium-sugammadex reduce Myalgia and headache after ECT in patients with major depression?</scientifictitle>
    <utrn />
    <trialacronym />
    <secondaryid>no</secondaryid>
  </trial_identification>
  <conditions>
    <healthcondition> Myalgia after electroconvulsive therapy (ECT) 
 </healthcondition>
    <healthcondition> Headache after electroconvulsive therapy (ECT)</healthcondition>
    <healthcondition>Major depression</healthcondition>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Anaesthesiology</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Pain management</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
    <conditioncode>
      <conditioncode1>Mental Health</conditioncode1>
      <conditioncode2>Depression</conditioncode2>
    </conditioncode>
  </conditions>
  <interventions>
    <interventions>Twenty one patients for group R undergoing ECT were included in the study. Anesthesia induction was provided with  propofol 1 mg/kg IV and rocuronium 0,3 mg/kg IV in the Group R (n=21). Electroshock was applied after obtaining full muscular relaxation. Sugammadex 4 mg/kg IV was administered to  after the motor seizure. Receiving ECT three times a week to complete an average of 6 to 12 treatments. The first three ECT sessions were included in the study. The patients were evaluated as regards the time of start of spontaneous respiration following the induction, time of opening the eyes in response to verbal stimuli, and VAS scores for myalgia and headache at hours 2, 6, 12 and 24 following the ECT.</interventions>
    <comparator>Twenty Four for group S patients undergoing ECT were included in the study. Anesthesia induction was provided with propofol 1 mg/kg intravenously (IV) and succinylcholine 1 mg/kg IV in the Group S (n=24), Electroshock was applied after obtaining full muscular relaxation. Receiving ECT three times a week to complete an average of 6 to 12 treatments. The first three ECT sessions were included in the study. The patients were evaluated as regards the time of start of spontaneous respiration following the induction, time of opening the eyes in response to verbal stimuli, and VAS scores for myalgia and headache at hours 2, 6, 12 and 24 following the ECT.</comparator>
    <control>Active</control>
    <interventioncode>Treatment: Drugs</interventioncode>
  </interventions>
  <outcomes>
    <primaryOutcome>
      <outcome>Compare the effects of succinylcholine and rocuronium-sugammadex on visual analogue scale (VAS) myalgia and headache after ECT</outcome>
      <timepoint>Visual analogue scale (VAS) myalgia and headache was measured after 2, 6, 12 and 24 hours following each ECT session.
</timepoint>
    </primaryOutcome>
    <secondaryOutcome>
      <outcome>the awakening time (spontaneous respiration and opening the eyes in response to verbal stimuli) in group R and group S.</outcome>
      <timepoint> Measured from the time of anaesthesia induction until awakening time.</timepoint>
    </secondaryOutcome>
  </outcomes>
  <eligibility>
    <inclusivecriteria>who would receive ECT three times a week due to major depression, without a history of ECT in the past, between 18-65 years of age, and had a physical status of ASA I and II. Of the 6-12 sessions of ECT, the first three were included in the study. </inclusivecriteria>
    <inclusiveminage>18</inclusiveminage>
    <inclusiveminagetype>Years</inclusiveminagetype>
    <inclusivemaxage>65</inclusivemaxage>
    <inclusivemaxagetype>Years</inclusivemaxagetype>
    <inclusivegender>Both males and females</inclusivegender>
    <healthyvolunteer>No</healthyvolunteer>
    <exclusivecriteria>Patients with neuromuscular, cardio-vascular and renal disease, and those who were pregnant and patients with pre-existing chronic pain were excluded from the study.</exclusivecriteria>
  </eligibility>
  <trial_design>
    <studytype>Interventional</studytype>
    <purpose>Prevention</purpose>
    <allocation>Randomised controlled trial</allocation>
    <concealment />
    <sequence />
    <masking />
    <assignment />
    <designfeatures />
    <endpoint />
    <statisticalmethods />
    <masking1>True</masking1>
    <masking2>True</masking2>
    <masking3>True</masking3>
    <masking4>True</masking4>
    <patientregistry />
    <followup />
    <followuptype />
    <purposeobs />
    <duration />
    <selection />
    <timing />
  </trial_design>
  <recruitment>
    <phase>Phase 4</phase>
    <anticipatedstartdate>1/02/2012</anticipatedstartdate>
    <actualstartdate>6/02/2012</actualstartdate>
    <anticipatedenddate>15/06/2012</anticipatedenddate>
    <actualenddate>20/07/2012</actualenddate>
    <samplesize>48</samplesize>
    <actualsamplesize />
    <recruitmentstatus>Completed</recruitmentstatus>
    <recruitmentcountry>Australia,Outside</recruitmentcountry>
    <recruitmentstate />
    <countryoutsideaustralia>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <state>Gazizantep</state>
    </countryoutsideaustralia>
  </recruitment>
  <sponsorship>
    <primarysponsortype>University</primarysponsortype>
    <primarysponsorname>Gaziantep University</primarysponsorname>
    <primarysponsoraddress>Gaziantep University Medical Faculty,
Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation ,
27310 Sahinbey,</primarysponsoraddress>
    <primarysponsorcountry>Turkey</primarysponsorcountry>
    <fundingsource>
      <fundingtype>University</fundingtype>
      <fundingname>Gaziantep University</fundingname>
      <fundingaddress>Gaziantep University Medical Faculty,
Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation ,
27310 Sahinbey,
</fundingaddress>
      <fundingcountry>Turkey</fundingcountry>
    </fundingsource>
    <secondarysponsor>
      <sponsortype>None</sponsortype>
      <sponsorname />
      <sponsoraddress />
      <sponsorcountry />
    </secondarysponsor>
  </sponsorship>
  <ethicsAndSummary>
    <summary>Abstract 
Introduction: Myalgia and headache are frequently observed conditions after electroconvulsive therapy (ECT). In this study, we aimed to compare the effects of succinylcholine and rocuronium-sugammadex on myalgia and headache after ECT. 
Material and Method: Forty five patients undergoing ECT were included in the study. Anesthesia induction was provided with propofol 1 mg/kg and succinylcholine 1 mg/kg in the Group S (n=24), and with propofol 1 mg/kg and rocuronium 0,3 mg/kg in the Group R (n=21). Electroshock was applied after obtaining full muscular relaxation. Sugammadex 4 mg/kg was administered to the group R after the motor seizure. The first three ECT sessions of all the patients were evaluated as regards the time of start of spontaneous respiration following the induction, time of opening the eyes in response to verbal stimuli, and VAS scores for myalgia and headache at hours 2, 6, 12 and 24 following the ECT.
Results: There were no significant differences as regards demographic data and hemodynamic data upon comparison of the two groups. The times for the start of the spontaneous respiration and opening the eyes in response to verbal stimuli were found significantly shorter in all the three sessions in the Group R as compared to the Group S (p&lt;0,002). MyalgiaVAS scores at hours 2, 6 and 12 and the headache VAS scores at hours 2 and 6 were significantly higher in the Group S as compared to the Group R (p&lt;0,015).
Conclusion: We concluded that the rate of myalgia and headache after ECT was significantly lower in group R than in group S and also the awakening time (spontaneous respiration and opening the eyes in response to verbal stimuli) in group R was significantly shorter than in group S.
Key Words: Electroconvulsive therapy, succinylcholine, sugammadex, myalgia, headache
</summary>
    <trialwebsite />
    <publication />
    <ethicsreview>Approved</ethicsreview>
    <publicnotes />
  </ethicsAndSummary>
  <attachment />
  <contacts>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vahap Saricicek</name>
      <address>Gaziantep University Medical Faculty,
Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation ,
27310 Sahinbey,
Gaziantep,  TURKEY
</address>
      <phone>+90 5335491664</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vahapsaricicek@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Principal Investigator</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>Dr</title>
      <name>Vahap saricicek</name>
      <address>Gaziantep University Medical Faculty,
Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation ,
27310 Sahinbey,
Gaziantep,  TURKE</address>
      <phone>+90 5335491664</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>vahapsaricicek@hotmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Public Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title>A/Prof</title>
      <name>Levent Sahin</name>
      <address>Gaziantep University Medical Faculty,
Department of Anesthesiology and Reanimation ,
27310 Sahinbey,
Gaziantep,  TURKE</address>
      <phone>+90 3423606060-77804</phone>
      <fax />
      <email>drlsahin@gmail.com</email>
      <country>Turkey</country>
      <type>Scientific Queries</type>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <title />
      <name />
      <address />
      <phone />
      <fax />
      <email />
      <country />
      <type>Updating Information</type>
    </contact>
  </contacts>
</ANZCTR_Trial>